<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spoto</journal-id>
<journal-title>Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0194-5998</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-6817</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599811431663</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0194599811431663</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Rhinoscleroma in an Urban Nonendemic Setting</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Suchanova</surname><given-names>Pavlina P.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599811431663">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mohyuddin</surname><given-names>Nadia G.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599811431663">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Waitkus</surname><given-names>Paul M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599811431663">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>Susan A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599811431663">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0194599811431663"><label>1</label>Baylor College of Medicine, Bobby R. Alford Department of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0194599811431663"><label>2</label>Baylor College of Medicine, Department of Pathology &amp; Immunology, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0194599811431663">Pavlina P. Suchanova, MD, Baylor College of Medicine, Bobby R. Alford Department of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, One Baylor Plaza, NA-102, Houston, TX 77054 Email: <email>suchanov@bcm.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>147</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>173</fpage>
<lpage>174</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>25</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>7</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery Foundation 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Official journal of the American Academy of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>rhinoscleroma</kwd>
<kwd>case reports</kwd>
<kwd>nasal cavity</kwd>
<kwd>larynx</kwd>
<kwd>antibiotics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Rhinoscleroma is a chronic, slowly progressive, infectious disease of the respiratory tract that is endemic to Central America, Egypt, tropical Africa, Indonesia, Eastern Europe, and India.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0194599811431663">1</xref></sup> It is caused by a gram-negative aerobic coccobacillus <italic>Klebsiella rhiscleromatis</italic>, and if left untreated, it can lead to disfiguring nasal deformity and laryngeal stenosis. Increased travel from endemic areas is increasing its incidence in a nonendemic setting, and there is a need for an increased awareness of its clinical presentation, diagnosis, and treatment options among practicing otolaryngologists.</p>
<sec id="section1-0194599811431663" sec-type="cases">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>We obtained approval from the Institutional Review Board at Baylor College of Medicine. We report here 2 cases of nasal and 1 case of laryngeal rhinoscleroma in an urban nonendemic setting at Ben Taub General Hospital in Houston, Texas. Geographically, all patients were originally from endemic areas and presented in the spring of 2010. They were treated medically and/or surgically with an established follow-up of more than 12 months.</p>
<sec id="section2-0194599811431663">
<title>Case 1</title>
<p>A 56-year-old woman from Honduras, otherwise healthy, presented to the ENT clinic in spring 2010 for an evaluation of a right-sided thyroid nodule. A left fleshy nasal mass filling most of the inferior meatus was incidentally found on examination. The patient denied any nasal symptoms, except for decreased nasal flow on the left. A biopsy taken in the clinic was consistent with rhinoscleroma on histopathology, and the patient was started on Bactrim DS twice daily for 6 months with a complete resolution of the lesion. She is currently scheduled for a right thyroid lobectomy with a possible total thyroidectomy for her multinodular goiter.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0194599811431663">
<title>Case 2</title>
<p>A 35-year-old man from Mexico, otherwise healthy, presented to the ENT clinic in the spring of 2010 with a 4-month history of right-sided nasal obstruction with intermittent epistaxis. He was previously treated for allergic rhinitis. A large fleshy and friable nasal mass was seen on examination, and a biopsy taken in the clinic was consistent with rhinoscleroma. Computed tomography sinus without contrast showed a 4.3 × 2 × 3-cm right nasal soft-tissue mass without bony erosion. Patient was started on ciprofloxacin 500 mg twice daily and had an interval improvement in size of the mass after 3 months of treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0194599811431663"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>). Limited surgical debridement followed by a total of 6 months of antibiotic therapy achieved a complete resolution of the lesion.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0194599811431663" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Fleshy and friable left nasal mass emanating from the septum below the middle turbinate.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599811431663-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0194599811431663">
<title>Case 3</title>
<p>A 46-year-old woman from El Salvador with a history of metastatic papillary thyroid carcinoma and laryngeal papillomas with several debridements in the past presented with a history of worsening hoarseness for several years. Direct laryngoscopy in the operating room revealed multiple polypoid-like lesions in the supraglottis and glottis with biopsy results consistent with rhinoscleroma. The patient was treated with a total of 6 months of antibiotic therapy with sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim and then ciprofloxacin (changed because of right arm dysesthesias) with a complete resolution of all lesions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0194599811431663" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Although respiratory scleroma is a rare diagnosis in the United States, with increasing travel and an influx of immigrant populations from endemic areas, there is an increase in its incidence in nonendemic areas. Lack of awareness when disease presents in developed countries often leads to delay in diagnosis and can cause nasal deformities, airway obstruction, and symptoms mimicking allergic rhinitis and prolonged sinusitis. The disease process usually involves the nasal cavity and nasopharynx, but it can also infect the larynx, trachea, middle ear, or the orbit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599811431663">2</xref></sup> The first catarrhal stage of disease progression causes nonspecific rhinitis symptoms that usually evolve into crusting and nasal obstruction with intermittent epistaxis as the disease enters the second granulomatous stage. Extensive scarring and nasal/laryngeal stenosis characterize the third sclerotic stage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0194599811431663">3</xref></sup> Histopathology examination confirms the diagnosis with the pathognomonic Mikulitz cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0194599811431663"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>) that represent large foamy macrophages with intracellular rods of <italic>Klebsiella rhinoscleromatis.</italic> Management with long-term antibiotics (3-6 months) with the fewest side effects (Ciprofloxacin, Bactrim) plus or minus surgical debridement is the mainstay of therapy, even though no randomized controlled trials exist to compare various treatment choices and their efficacy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0194599811431663">4</xref></sup> Long-term follow-up is vital because of high relapse rates (as high as 41%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0194599811431663">5</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig2-0194599811431663" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Hematoxylin-eosin sections of the laryngeal biopsies (100×) contain numerous vacuolated macrophages (referred to as Mikulicz cells), some of which contain bacillary microorganisms identifiable on routinely stained slides.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599811431663-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0194599811431663">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p><bold>Pavlina P. Suchanova</bold>, conception of the case report about rhinoscleroma and acquisition of the data for all 3 patients with rhinoscleroma, drafting of the article and its final approval. <bold>Nadia G. Mohyuddin</bold>, conception of the case report about rhinoscleroma; analysis, revision of the article, and its final approval. <bold>Paul M. Rodriguez-Waitkus</bold>, acquisition of pathology data for all 3 patients, creation of pathology slides, drafting of the article and its final approval. <bold>Susan A. Eicher</bold>, analysis, revision, and final approval of the article.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0194599811431663">
<title>Disclosures</title>
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Sponsorships:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Funding source:</bold> None.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>No sponsorships or competing interests have been disclosed for this article.</p>
<p>This case report was presented as a poster during the 2011 AAO-HNSF Annual Meeting; September 11-14, 2011; San Francisco, California.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0194599811431663">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canalis</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title><italic>Klebsiella rhinoscleromatis</italic>: a clinical and pathogenic enigma</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>-<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0194599811431663">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhowate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Degwekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rawlani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dangore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rhinoscleroma with involvement of the maxillary sinus, orbital floor, and temporomandibular joint: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>. <comment>In press</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0194599811431663">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rhinoscleroma: a retrospective study of pathologic and clinical features</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0194599811431663">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>N’gattia</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kacouchia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koffi-N’guessan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective study of the rhinoscleroma about 14 cases in ENT departments of university hospitals</article-title>. <source>Eur Ann Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Dis</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0194599811431663">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fawaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Clinical, radiological and pathological study of 88 of typical and complicated scleroma</article-title>. <source>Clin Respir J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>