<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppic</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part C: Journal of Mechanical Engineering Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4062</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2983</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954406211418588</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954406211418588</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Fluid Mechanics</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A study on the effect of the rake angle on the performance of marine propellers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayati</surname><given-names>A N</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>S M</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Shams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954406211418588">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954406211418588">Department of Mechanical Engineering, K.N. Toosi University of Technology, Tehran, Iran</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954406211418588"><label>*</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, K.N. Toosi University of Technology, Tehran, Iran. email: <email>shams@kntu.ac.ir</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>940</fpage>
<lpage>955</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Authors 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In this study, the open water performance of three propellers with diverse rake angles was investigated by computational fluid dynamics method. The objective of this study was to find out the influence of the rake angle on the performance of conventional screw propellers. For this purpose, first, the obtained results for three B-series propellers were validated against the empirical results and then by modifying the rake angle, different models were investigated by the same method. Flow characteristics were examined for the models and the evolvement of vortices on different planes around the propeller were compared. The results suggest that in case of conventional screw propellers with linear rake distribution, while the effect of the rake angle on the propeller efficiency is not significant, the augmentation of this parameter improves the propeller thrust, especially at high propeller loads, but at the same time, the required torque increases, which is not desirable for the propeller design process.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>rake angle</kwd>
<kwd>marine propellers</kwd>
<kwd>computational fluid dynamics methods</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954406211418588"><title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>Computational fluid dynamics (CFD) methods have been developed remarkably on the basis of Reynolds averaged Navier–Stokes equations in the analysis of marine propellers in recent decades. Although the numerical modelling of flow around various solids is possible, in case of propellers, it is difficult due to several factors such as geometry complexity, turbulent flow occurrence, flow separation, boundary layer effects, wake field, and cavitation incidence.</p>
<p>Uto and Kodama [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406211418588">1</xref></bold>] used the CFD method for modelling the flow around a propeller behind a submerged body. By employing a structured mesh, their obtained results were restricted to open water condition. In addition, due to the complexity of the blade geometry, they were not capable of accurate prediction of the flow near the tip of the blades. Funeno [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954406211418588">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406211418588">3</xref></bold>] studied the flow around high-skewed propellers usingan unstructured mesh. Despite the good compatibility of the obtained results with empirical results, the approach of mesh generation was very complicated and time consuming due to the division of the numerical domain into several regions and individual mesh generation for each of them. Martínez-Calle <italic>et al.</italic> [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954406211418588">4</xref></bold>] modelled a propeller in open water condition by employing standard <italic>k</italic>–<italic>ε</italic> turbulence model. Although the results of this that study were generally acceptable, the average amount of error in the prediction of propeller torque was 30 per cent. Watanabe <italic>et al.</italic> [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406211418588">5</xref></bold>] modelled a propeller in both steady and unsteady conditions using the standard <italic>k</italic>–<italic>ω</italic> turbulence model. The obtained results had good compatibility with experimental results and the average amount of error in thrust prediction was 15per cent. Rhee and Evangelos [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954406211418588">6</xref></bold>] modelled the flow around a propeller by two-dimensional simulation with the standard <italic>k</italic>–<italic>ω</italic> turbulence model and the error percentage in their final results was 13 per cent. Many other works were carried out on the performance prediction of conventional and high-skewed propellers by CFD method [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954406211418588">7</xref></bold>–<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954406211418588">10</xref></bold>].</p>
<p>In spite of several studies done on the performance prediction of marine propellers, the effect of a specific geometrical parameter on the performance has rarely been investigated. The geometry complexity and the effect of several geometrical parameters on it are the main troubles in such studies. Skew angle is a typical parameter which was taken into consideration in some literatures such as Abdel-Maksoud <italic>et al.</italic> [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954406211418588">7</xref></bold>] and Ghasemi [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954406211418588">11</xref></bold>] to compare its effect on the propeller performance. The results of such studies indicated that the use of high-skewed propellers leads to morereduction in propeller-excited vibrations on the full-body and better-performance characteristics simultaneously.</p>
<p>Rake angle is another important parameter in propeller technology that influences the propeller performance; however, no numerical studies on this parameter have been carried out, especially, to find out the performance improvement of a propeller by the modification of the rake angle. The objective of this study was to examine the effect of the rake angle alteration on the performance of a typical screw propeller by CFD method. It was supposed that the results were trustworthy for other screw propellers with linear rake distribution.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954406211418588"><title>2 RAKE ANGLE</title>
<p>As it was defined by Carlton [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954406211418588">12</xref></bold>], the propeller rake on any arbitrary section of a propeller (<italic>i</italic><sub>T</sub>(<italic>r</italic>)) includes two separate components: the generator rake (<italic>i</italic><sub>G</sub>) and the skew induced rake (<italic>i</italic><sub>S</sub>). Therefore, the total rake at each section can be written as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0954406211418588"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>As a physical definition, rake angle is a parameter which determines the blades position against the flow direction. If the blades are mounted perpendicular to the hub, then the propeller would have zero rake angle, but as the blades incline towards or backwards the flow direction, negative or positive rake appears, respectively. In standard conventional propeller series, in which the rake distribution on each propeller section is a linear function of its radial distance from the propeller centre, the rake angle is defined as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0954406211418588"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The general range for the rake angle of conventional standard propellers is between −5° (forward) and +20° (backward). Among various standard series of propellers, Wageningen B-screw, which was first developed by Troost [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954406211418588">13</xref></bold>], is the most well-known series and its conventional rake angle is equal to 15°.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0954406211418588"><title>3 PROPELLER MODELS</title>
<p>Three B3-50 propellers with different pitch ratios (0.6, 0.8, and 1) were studied. The models were generated by the application of GAMBIT 2.3. The principal geometrical parameters of each propeller are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954406211418588">Table 1</xref>. The conventional propeller with a pitch ratio of 0.6 and a rake angle of 15° is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406211418588">Fig. 1(a)</xref>. By modifying the rake angle of this propeller, other models with diverse rake angles were reproduced and are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406211418588">Fig. 1(b)</xref> to (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406211418588">d</xref>). The only geometrical distinction between these models is the amount of the rake angle which was set to −5°, 15°, and 20° for examining the influence of this parameter on the performance of screw propellers. Same procedure was carried out for modelling the two other models with different pitch ratios.
<table-wrap id="table1-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Main geometrical parameters of the propellers</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954406211418588" xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Diameter (m)</td>
<td>0.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of blades</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Expanded area ratio</td>
<td>0.5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Pitch ratio</td>
<td>0.6, 0.8, and 1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Hub ratio</td>
<td>0.169</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Chord length (0.7<italic>R</italic>) (m)</td>
<td>0.0723</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Thickness ratio (0.7<italic>R</italic>)</td>
<td>0.0473</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Skew angle (°)</td>
<td>5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Handedness</td>
<td>Right handed</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Section type</td>
<td>Inner sections: airfoil</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Outer sections: segmental</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>B3-50 models with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6: (a) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 15°; (b) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = −5°; (c) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°; and (d) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954406211418588"><title>4 NUMERICAL SOLUTION</title>
<sec id="sec5-0954406211418588"><title>4.1 Governing equations</title>
<p>The computations were executed by the application of FLUENT 6.3, which is established on the basis of CFD codes and is well known as a robust commercial software package in diverse problems in the analysis of marine propellers according to several literatures published in this field of study [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954406211418588">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406211418588">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406211418588">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954406211418588">15</xref></bold>]</p>
<p>The governing equation for mass conservation in each principal direction can be written as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0954406211418588"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>ρ</italic> is the fluid density and <italic>u<sub>i</sub></italic> the velocity in each of the principal directions (<italic>x, y, z</italic>). In addition, momentum conservation equation in principal directions can be written as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0954406211418588"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>τ<sub>ij</sub></italic> is the Reynolds stress tensor defined as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0954406211418588"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>δ<sub>ij</sub></italic> is the Kronecker delta which is unity when <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic> are the same and zero in other cases. Considering equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0954406211418588">3</xref>) to (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954406211418588">5</xref>), the Reynolds averaged momentum equations are derived as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0954406211418588"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>For turbulence description, the standard <italic>k</italic>–<italic>ω</italic> model which was developed by Wilcox [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954406211418588">16</xref></bold>] was employed, where <italic>k</italic> and <italic>ω</italic> represent turbulence kinetic energy and turbulence dissipation rate, respectively, and are obtained from the following equations
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0954406211418588"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0954406211418588"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>σ<sub>k</sub></italic> and <italic>σ<sub>ω</sub></italic> indicate turbulent Prandtl numbers for <italic>k</italic> and <italic>ω</italic>, respectively, and <italic>β</italic> and <italic>β</italic><sup>*</sup> obtained from experimental formulations by Wilcox [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954406211418588">16</xref></bold>]. Furthermore, turbulent viscousity, <italic>μ</italic><italic><sub>t</sub></italic>, is obtained from the combination of <italic>k</italic> and <italic>ω</italic> according to the following equation
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0954406211418588"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The selected solver for the equations was 3D Segregated. The employed algorithm for pressure–velocity coupling was SIMPLE with standard discretization for pressure and second-order upwind discretization for momentum, <italic>k</italic> and <italic>ω</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954406211418588"><title>4.2 Grid generation</title>
<p>An unstructured hybrid mesh was employed for grid generation. Blades surfaces were meshed with triangular cells. Smaller triangles with sides of approximately 0.001<italic>D</italic> (where <italic>D</italic> is the propeller diameter) were used for regions near the root, blade edges, and tip for better monitoring the flow in these regions. Other surfaces were meshed with larger triangles with sides of approximately 0.1<italic>D</italic>. In addition, for better prediction of the flow between the propeller blades, a moving mesh zone was generated around the propeller (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406211418588">Fig. 2</xref>). Finally, the remaining regions in the domain were meshed with appropriate growing rate of 1.1 with tetrahedral cells.
<fig id="fig2-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Generated grid for computational domain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954406211418588"><title>4.3. Boundary conditions</title>
<p>In order to investigate the propeller performance in uniform flow and simulating open water condition, a cylindrical control volume was assumed around each propeller with velocity inlet and outflow boundary conditions for the entry of the flow in front of the propeller and the flow exit astern the propeller, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406211418588">Fig. 3</xref>). The domain dimensions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0954406211418588">Table 2</xref>) were considered large enough to avoid external effects on the performance prediction of the propellers. In order to avoid the occurrence of the stagnation point at the propeller hub, the blades were attained to a long shaft along the control volume. The rotating speed of the propeller shaft was set to 25 r/s (1500 r/min) throughout this study and the flow velocity through the inlet boundary was varied for different values of advance ratio.
<table-wrap id="table2-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Domain dimensions for the computational solution</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0954406211418588" xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="center">
<tr><th align="center" colspan="4">Distance from the centre of the propeller to<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Inlet boundary</th>
<th>Outlet boundary</th>
<th>Radial boundary</th>
<th>Moving zone</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="center">
<tr>
<td>1.5<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>3.5<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>1.5<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>0.525<italic>D</italic></td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig3-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Arranged control volume for computational solution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0954406211418588"><title>5 VALIDATION</title>
<p>For the validation of the obtained results, first, the study of mesh independency was carried out for the conventional propeller with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6 (<italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 15°) and the results are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0954406211418588">Table 3</xref>. It was indicated that the third pattern of mesh generation offered the least error in the prediction of the thrust coefficient and as mesh sizes decreased in the last pattern, no better results were obtained. Therefore, the selected pattern was executed for the mesh generation of all the models throughout the study. Second, the open water performance diagrams for three conventional models with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> equal to 0.6, 0.8, and 1 were compared to the numerical results and are represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406211418588">Fig. 4(a)</xref> to (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406211418588">c</xref>), respectively. The definitions of the principle performance parameters of the propellers are defined as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0954406211418588"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-0954406211418588"><label>(11)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0954406211418588"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0954406211418588"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>J</italic> is the advance ratio and is varied by increasing the advance velocity at the propeller inlet, <italic>K</italic><sub>T</sub> the thrust coefficient which indicates the thrust generated at a determined advance ratio, <italic>K</italic><sub>Q</sub> the torque coefficient which indicates the torque needed for the propeller rotation at a determined advance ratio, and finally <italic>η</italic><sub>O</sub> the propeller efficiency that indicates the ratio of the generated thrust to the required torque at a determined advance ratio.
<table-wrap id="table3-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mesh independency for conventional B3-50 with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6 at <italic>J</italic> = 0.4</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0954406211418588" xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="center">
<tr><th>Row</th>
<th>Mesh size at blade surface</th>
<th>Mesh size far from blade</th>
<th>Total number of cells</th>
<th>Thrust coefficient</th>
<th>Error (%)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="center">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.02<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>0.1<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>1 269 273</td>
<td>0.1031</td>
<td>6.1874</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.01<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>0.1<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>1 436 899</td>
<td>0.1037</td>
<td>5.6415</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>0.001<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>0.1<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>1 582 128</td>
<td>0.1078</td>
<td>1.9108</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>0.0001<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>0.05<italic>D</italic></td>
<td>3 006 478</td>
<td>0.1055</td>
<td>4.0036</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig4-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Comparison between the numerical and the empirical results for B3-50: (a) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6; (b) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8; and (c) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>There is a good agreement between the numerical and the experimental results. The average amount of error in the prediction of the thrust and torque coefficients with the current numerical method are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406211418588">Fig. 5</xref>. In all models, the average percentage of error in the performance prediction is below 16 per cent, which is acceptable with respect to similar literatures. Furthermore, the predicted results for models with higher pitch ratios (<italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 1) have less discrepancy with respect to empirical results, which implies the capability of standard <italic>k</italic>–<italic>ω</italic> turbulence model in simulating the performance of higher twisted propellers very well.
<fig id="fig5-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Average error in the performance prediction of B3-50 with different pitch ratios</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>By increasing the propeller load, more thrust and torque are generated, which is confirmed by numerical solution. At heavy loads (low advance ratios), as the flow velocity at the propeller inlet decreases, the difference between static pressure on both sides of the propeller augments remarkably. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406211418588">Figure 6</xref> indicates that the range of the static pressure on both sides of the propeller is much higher at heavy loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406211418588">Fig. 6(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406211418588">b</xref>)) compared to normal loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406211418588">Fig. 6(c)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406211418588">d</xref>)). The static pressure distribution on the blade surface at the suction side indicates high-pressure region at the leading edge. This incidence is due to the position of the leading edge of the blades on the hub and the direction of the propeller rotation. As seen from the propeller astern, clockwise rotation leads to the existence of minimum fluid velocity at the leading edge (the flow inlet to the blade sections) and so highest static pressure at this location.
<fig id="fig6-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Static pressure distribution for conventional B3-50 with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8: (a) pressure side, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) suction side, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) pressure side, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) suction side, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>For a better comparison between the static pressure distribution on the blade surface at heavy and normal loads, the non-dimensional pressure coefficient is shown on two inner and outer sections in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406211418588">Fig. 7</xref>. The pressure coefficient is defined as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0954406211418588"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>P</italic><sub>s</sub> is the static pressure at the propeller surface, <italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub> the pressure remote from the propeller, <italic>v</italic> the local velocity at the propeller inlet, and <italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub> the pressure coefficient which indicates the static pressure with respect to the free stream pressure. The fluctuations in the pressure coefficient as the flow proceeds from the leading edge (<italic>x</italic>/<italic>c</italic> = 0) to the trailing edge (<italic>x</italic>/<italic>c</italic> = 1) is mainly due to the variations in the flow regime, turbulent transition occurrence, and boundary layer effects along the section. By comparing <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406211418588">Fig. 7(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406211418588">b</xref>), it is inferred that the difference between the static pressure on both sides of the propeller is much greater on outer sections and for inner sections, a great decline occurs in its range. In addition, according to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406211418588">Fig. 7(a)</xref> to (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406211418588">d</xref>), at high propeller loads, the range of the static pressure on both sides is much greater than that at normal loads, which indicates more thrust generation at low advance ratios.
<fig id="fig7-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Chordwise distribution of pressure coefficient for conventional B3-50 with P/D = 0.8: (a) <italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.3, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.7, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) <italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.3, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.7, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Furthermore, the axial velocity distribution on the pressure side of the propeller blades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406211418588">Fig. 8</xref>) indicates that maximum fluid velocity occurs at the blade tip which is obvious due to the furthest distance from the propeller centre of rotation. Furthermore, the region with minimum velocity occurs at the blade root and there is a remarkable increase in the velocity from the root to the tip of the blades. Comparing two cases of the propeller loads, at heavy loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406211418588">Fig. 8(a)</xref>), a small region with reverse flow is observed around the blade root near the propeller hub at the pressure side, which is due to the low flow velocity at the propeller inlet at low advance ratio.
<fig id="fig8-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Axial velocity distribution for conventional B3-50 with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8 on pressure side: (a) <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In order to examine the vortex distribution around the propeller at different loads, first, the strength of the vortices are illustrated on two planes parallel to the propeller plane which are located beside the suction and the pressure side of the propeller with distances <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = −0.3 and 0.3 from the propeller centre, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406211418588">Fig. 9</xref>). The vorticity magnitude is defined as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-0954406211418588"><label>(15)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>u, v</italic>, and <italic>w</italic> are the terms of the velocity vector in principal directions (<italic>x, y</italic> and <italic>z</italic>), respectively and <italic>ω</italic> the vorticity magnitude of the induced vortices in the rotational flow.
<fig id="fig9-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Vortex evolvement around B3-50 with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8: (a) <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = −0.3, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.3, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = −0.3, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.3, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig9.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406211418588">Figure 9(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406211418588">c</xref>) indicate that the evolvement of vortices originates from the region close to the propeller shaft while the vortices at heavy loads are developed more than those at normal loads. In the planes behind the propeller (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406211418588">Fig. 9(b)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406211418588">d</xref>)) the vortices are well developed throughout the planes and the regions with maximum strength are developed through farther distances from the propeller shaft, while for heavy loads, the overall vorticity strength is greater than normal propeller loads.</p>
<p>Second, the vorticity on the propeller plane with <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0 is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406211418588">Fig. 10</xref>. At heavy loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406211418588">Fig. 10(a)</xref>), the region with high vorticity strength is fully developed from the root to the tip of the blades, whichindicates more energy loss and consequently poor efficiency, as shown previously in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406211418588">Fig. 4(b)</xref>. For higher advance ratios, the region with maximum vorticity strength declines gradually and conveys tothe root and inner sections of the blades, which implies less energy loss. Thus, the increase in the efficiency is expected, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406211418588">Fig. 4(b)</xref>. For low propeller loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406211418588">Fig. 10(d)</xref>), the region with maximum vorticity is distributed close to the blade surface and the overall vorticity strength is less than the other cases. Consequently, the energy loss in this load is minimum and the propeller has maximum efficiency at this advance ratio, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406211418588">Fig. 4(b)</xref>.
<fig id="fig10-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Vorticity distribution at the propeller plane for B3-50 with <italic>P/D</italic> = 0.8: (a) <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>J</italic> = 0.245; (c) <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>J</italic> = 0.676</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954406211418588"><title>6 RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
<p>The effect of the rake angle on the thrust and torque coefficients and the efficiency of the propellers for a range of advance ratios are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406211418588">Figs 11</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954406211418588">13</xref>. The overall thrust and torque coefficients for propellers with higher backward rake angles (<italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 15° and 20°) are greater than those with forward rake angles (<italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = −5°) and lower backward rake angles (<italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°). While an overall increase is shown for different advance ratios, by increasing the rake angle, the augmentation is more significant at heavy propeller loads (<italic>J</italic> = 0.1). In spite of the improvement in the propeller generated thrust for higher rake angles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406211418588">Fig. 11</xref>), more torque and consequently more power is required for the propeller rotation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954406211418588">Fig. 12</xref>), while the efficiency alteration for different rake angles is not significant for the range of propeller loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954406211418588">Fig. 13</xref>); However, for low propeller loads, a slight augmentation is observed in the propeller efficiency for models with higher backward rake angles. This increase is more significant for models with higher pitch ratios, as observed by comparing <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954406211418588">Fig. 13(a)</xref> to (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954406211418588">c</xref>). The overall improvement in the performance of the propellers by comparing models with forward and high backward rake angles (−5° and 20°) is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0954406211418588">Fig. 14</xref>. For propellers with <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8, the performance improvement was monitored more remarkably than other models. Therefore, this model was selected for the rest of the study.
<fig id="fig11-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Effect of the rake angle on the propeller thrust coefficient: (a) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6; (b) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8; and (c) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig11.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig12-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Effect of the rake angle on the propeller torque coefficient: (a) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6; (b) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8; and (c) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig12.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig13-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Effect of the rake angle on the propeller efficiency: (a) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.6; (b) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 0.8; and (c) <italic>P</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig14-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Overall improvement in the performance of propellers by the rake angle augmentation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig14.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p>The improvement in the performance of propellers with high backward rake angles is mainly due to the arrangement of the propeller sections in different rake angles which changes the flow characteristics on each propeller section and especially influences the static pressure distribution on both sides of the propellers. The static pressure distribution on the pressure side of two propellers with low and high backward rake angles (5° and 20°, respectively) are presented for heavy and normal loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0954406211418588">Fig. 15</xref>). Overall increase in the static pressure on the blade surface is observed for propeller with high backward rake angle with respect to that with low backward rake angle at both advance ratios. The region with high static pressure is developed towards the trailing edge and inner sections, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0954406211418588">Fig. 15(b)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0954406211418588">d</xref>). For better comparison, the chordwise distribution of the pressure coefficient on a determined propeller section (<italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.7) is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-0954406211418588">Fig. 16</xref> for heavy and normal propeller loads. As the advance ratio increases, the range of the pressure coefficient on both sides of the section decreases significantly, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406211418588">Fig. 7</xref>, previously. The location of zero pressure coefficient is considerable in the analysis of flow characteristics on the section, which shows the equality of the local pressure at a point to that of the free stream pressure. By comparing the pressure chordwise distribution on the pressure side of the section at both advance ratios (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-0954406211418588">Fig. 16(a)</xref> to (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-0954406211418588">d</xref>)), it is inferred that for propellers with high backward rake angles, the minimum pressure coefficient is greater than those with low backward rake angles and in the case of high backward rake angle (<italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°), there is no point on the section with zero pressure coefficient throughout the pressure side. By averaging the pressure coefficient from the leading to the trailing edge on the suction and the pressure side of the determined section, the average <italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub> difference between the two sides was obtained and is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-0954406211418588">Fig. 17</xref> for heavy and normal propeller loads. The augmentation in the average <italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub> difference indicates more thrust and torque generation for propellers with higher backward rake angles.
<fig id="fig15-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Static pressure distribution for the selected propeller with: (a) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig15.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig16-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>Chordwise distribution of pressure coefficient on section <italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.7: (a) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig16.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig17-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 17</label><caption><p>Effect of the rake angle on the average <italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub> difference on section <italic>r</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0.7: (a) <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig17.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The axial velocity distribution on the suction side of the propellers with high and low backward rake angles is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0954406211418588">Fig. 18</xref>. The overall range of the axial velocity on the blade surfaces for the propeller with high rake angle is lower than those with low values. At heavy propeller loads, this distinction is better monitored, comparing <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0954406211418588">Fig. 18(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0954406211418588">b</xref>). The region with maximum velocity declines from the blade tip to inner sections, which is mainly due to the arrangement of the blades as the flow enters the propeller suction side.
<fig id="fig18-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 18</label><caption><p>Axial velocity distribution on the suction side: (a) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig18.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The vorticity distribution on the propeller plane (<italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic> = 0) which is perpendicular to the propeller axis is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19-0954406211418588">Fig. 19</xref> for heavy and normal propeller loads. The overall strength of the vortices around the propeller with high backward rake angle is less than that around the propeller with low value. Comparing the induced vortices at the tip of the blades for both models, it is observed that the region with maximum vorticity declines significantly, which is well monitored for normal propeller loads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19-0954406211418588">Fig. 19(c)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19-0954406211418588">d</xref>)). Therefore, the energy loss for propellers with high backward rake angles is less than that for models with low backward rake angles, which implies better performance.
<fig id="fig19-0954406211418588" position="float"><label>Fig. 19</label><caption><p>Vorticity distribution at the propeller plane: (a) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (b) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.1; (c) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 5°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5; and (d) <italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub> = 20°, <italic>J</italic> = 0.5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406211418588-fig19.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0954406211418588"><title>7 CONCLUSION</title>
<p>In this study, the effect of the rake angle on the performance of three typical screw propellers was investigated by CFD method. It was indicated that increasing the rake angle improves the performance and especially the generated thrust of conventional propellers. The improvement was well monitored at heavy propeller loads and indicated the remarkable effect of the rake angle on the propeller performance at heavy loads; however, the variation of the propeller efficiency for different rake angles was not noticeable in the case of propellers with linear rake distribution. Furthermore, improvements were shown in the flow characteristics around the propellers with higher backward rake angles. As a further study, it would be interesting to investigate the effect of the propeller rake modification and progressive rakes on the improvements of the performance of screw propellers and specifically enhancing the efficiency of conventional propellers.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954406211418588"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Application of CFD to the flow computation around a marine propeller: Grid generation and inviscid flow computation using Euler equations</article-title>. <source>J. Kansai Soc. Naval Archit.</source>, <year>1992</year>, <volume>218</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954406211418588"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funeno</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Analysis of steady viscous flow around a highly skewed propeller</article-title>. <source>J. Kansai Soc. Naval Archit.</source>, <year>1999</year>, <volume>231</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954406211418588"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Funeno, I. On viscous flow around marine propellers, hub vortex and scale effect. In Proceedings of <italic>New S-Tech, Third Conference for New Ship and Marine Technology</italic>, Kobe, Japan, 21–23 May 2002, pp. 17–26</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954406211418588"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Martínez-Calle, J., Balbona-Calvo, L., Gonzalez-Perez, J., and Blanco-Marigorta, E. An open water numerical model for a marine propeller: a comparison with experimental data. In Proceedings of the <italic>ASME FEDSM'02, 2002 Joint US-European Fluids Engineering Summer Conference</italic>, Montreal, Canada, 14–18 July 2002</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954406211418588"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Watanabe, T,. Kawamura, T., Takekoshi, Y., Maeda, M., and Rhee, S. H. Simulation of steady and unsteady cavitation on a marine propeller using a RANS CFD code. In <italic>Fifth International Symposium on Cavitation (CAV2003)</italic>, Osaka, Japan, 1–4 November 2002</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954406211418588"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Rhee, S. H. and Evangelos, K. Two-dimensional simulation of unsteady marine propulsor blade flow using dynamic meshing techniques, Fluent Inc., 10 Cavendish Ct., Lebanon, NH 03766, USA, 2004</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954406211418588"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Maksoud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menter</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuttke</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Viscous flow simulation for conventional and high-skew marine propellers</article-title>. <source>J. Ship Technol. Res.</source>, <year>1998</year>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954406211418588"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Computational fluid dynamics of four-quadrant marine-propulsor flow</article-title>. <source>J. Ship Res.</source>, <year>1999</year>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954406211418588"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Kawamura, T., Takekoshi, Y., Yamaguchi, H., Minowa, T., Maeda, M., Fujii, A., Kimura, K., and Taketani, T. Simulation of unsteady cavitating flow around marine propeller using a RANS CFD code. In <italic>Sixth International Symposium on Cavitation (CAV2006)</italic>, Wageningen, The Netherlands, 11–15 September 2006</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954406211418588"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Computational validation for flow around marine propeller using unstructured mesh based Navier-Stokes solver</article-title>. <source>JSME Int. J., Ser. B</source>, <year>2005</year>, <volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954406211418588"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The effect of wake flow and skew angle on the ship propeller performance</article-title>. <source>Scientia Iranica</source>, <year>2005</year>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954406211418588"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Carlton, J. S. <italic>Marine propellers and propulsion</italic>, 2edn, 2007 (Elsevier, Oxford)</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954406211418588"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troost</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Open-water test series with modern propeller forms</article-title>. <source>Trans. NECIES</source>, <year>1938</year>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954406211418588"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Da-Qing, L. Validations of RANS predictions of open water performance of a highly skewed propeller with experiments. In Proceedings of the <italic>Conference of Global Chinese Scholars on Hydrodynamics</italic>, Shanghai, China, 11–14 July 2006</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954406211418588"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benini</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Significance of blade element theory in performance prediction of marine propellers</article-title>. <source>J. Ocean Eng.</source>, <year>2004</year>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>957</fpage>–<lpage>974</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954406211418588"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Wilcox, D. C. <italic>Turbulence modeling for CFD</italic>, 2 edn, 1998 (DCW Industries, Inc., La Canada, California)</comment></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0954406211418588">
<title/>
<sec id="sec11-0954406211418588"><title>APPENDIX</title>
<sec id="sec12-0954406211418588">
<title>Notation</title>
<p><def-list id="duolist1-0954406211418588">
<def-item><term><italic>D</italic></term><def><p>propeller diameter (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>F</italic></term><def><p>external body forces (N)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>g</italic></term><def><p>gravitational acceleration (m/s<sup>2</sup>)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>i</italic><sub>G</sub></term><def><p>generator rake (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>i</italic><sub>S</sub></term><def><p>skew-induced rake (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>i</italic><sub>T</sub></term><def><p>total rake (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>J</italic></term><def><p>advance ratio</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>K</italic><sub>T</sub></term><def><p>thrust coefficient</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>K</italic><sub>Q</sub></term><def><p>torque coefficient</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>n</italic></term><def><p>rotational speed of the propeller shaft (r/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P</italic><sub>s</sub></term><def><p>local static pressure (KPa)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub></term><def><p>free stream pressure (KPa)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>Q</italic></term><def><p>propeller torque (N.m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>R</italic></term><def><p>propeller radius (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>T</italic></term><def><p>propeller thrust (N)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>u</italic></term><def><p><italic>x</italic> velocity (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>v</italic></term><def><p><italic>y</italic> velocity (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>v</italic><sub>a</sub></term><def><p>advance velocity (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>w</italic></term><def><p><italic>z</italic> velocity (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>η</italic><sub>O</sub></term><def><p>open water efficiency</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>θ</italic><sub>r</sub></term><def><p>rake angle (deg)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>µ</italic></term><def><p>fluid viscosity (kg/(m.s))</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ρ</italic></term><def><p>fluid density (kg/m<sup>3</sup>)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ω</italic></term><def><p>vorticity magnitude (1/s)</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>