<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Health Management</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0972-0634</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">0973-0729</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0972063413489065</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0972063413489065</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Abstracts</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Abstract: <bold>Singh Arvind Kumar, Mani Kalaivani, Krishnan Anand, Aggarwal Praveen and Gupta Sanjeev Kumar</bold>. Prevalence, Awareness, Treatment and Control of Diabetes among Elderly Persons in an Urban Slum of Delhi. <italic>Indian Journal of Community Medicine</italic>, 2012; <italic>37</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Kalpa</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0972063413489065">Research Officer, IHMR, Jaipur</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>310</fpage>
<lpage>310</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Singh Arvind</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalaivani</surname><given-names>Mani</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>Krishnan</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Praveen</surname><given-names>Aggarwal</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Gupta Sanjeev</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Prevalence, Awareness, Treatment and Control of Diabetes among Elderly Persons in an Urban Slum of Delhi</article-title>. <source>Indian Journal of Community Medicine</source>, <year>2012</year>; <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.
</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Indian Institute of Health Management Research</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Diabetes is a non-communicable disease contributing 5 per cent of the total mortality. India has witnessed demographic transition with a reduction in crude birth rate and increase in life expectancy which ultimately leads to increase in aged population. The article has made an attempt to estimate the prevalence of diabetes in elderly persons (aged 60 years and above) in an urban slum and to assess their awareness, treatment and control of this condition. The cross-sectional community based study was conducted in an urban slum of Delhi. Awareness and treatment of diabetes was recorded. Fasting blood glucose was estimated by using Eukare automated glucometer. Diabetes was diagnosed if fasting blood glucose was &gt;=126 mg/dL, or if the participant was taking treatment for diabetes. Impaired fasting blood glucose was diagnosed if fasting blood glucose was 110–125 mg/dL. Fasting blood glucose testing was done on 474 elderly people, out of which 52 per cent were male. Most of them were in the age group of 60–64 years. The prevalence of diabetes was estimated to be 18.8 per cent whereas prevalence of impaired fasting blood glucose was 19.8 per cent and both were found higher among women. One-third of the diabetes participants were aware of their condition; two-thirds of these were on treatment, and three-fourths of those on treatment had controlled fasting blood sugar level. Awareness, treatment and control were better in women than men. Only one slum was selected for the study, which was identified as one of the limitations. Policies on non-communicable diseases should be strengthened and special emphasis should be given to elderly people. Despite of that, health staff should get the training on Non-cimmunicable diseases (NCDs) and especially on its management.</p>
<sig-block><sig>
Kalpa Sharma<break/>
<italic>Research Officer, IHMR, Jaipur</italic>
</sig></sig-block>
</body>
</article>