<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RAJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spraj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Race and Justics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2153-3687</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2153368712468861</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2153368712468861</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Racial Disproportionality in the Criminal Justice System for Drug Offenses</article-title>
<subtitle>A State Legislative Response to the Problem</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Lyons</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2153368712468861">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2153368712468861"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lurigio</surname>
<given-names>Arthur J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2153368712468861">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roque</surname>
<given-names>Lorena</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2153368712468861">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>Pamela</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2153368712468861">3</xref>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p>
<bold>Thomas Lyons</bold> is assistant professor and director of the HIV/AIDS Research and Policy Institute at Chicago State University. A medical anthropologist, he obtained his doctorate from University of Chicago and did postdoctoral work at the George Washington University. His interests are in HIV and AIDS among substance users and in incarcerated populations; qualitative methodology; drug policy; and intervention research. He previously served as a research associate at Treatment Alternatives for Safe Communities (TASC).</p>
<p>
<bold>Arthur J. Lurigio</bold>, a psychologist, is Associate Dean for Faculty in the College of Arts and Sciences, and a Professor of Criminal Justice and Psychology at Loyola University Chicago. He is also a member of the Graduate Faculty and Director of the Center for the Advancement of Research, Training, and Education (CARTE) at Loyola University Chicago. In 2003, Dr. Lurigio was named a faculty scholar, the highest honor bestowed on senior faculty at Loyola University Chicago.</p>
<p>
<bold>Lorena Roque</bold> is a research associate for Loyola University's Center for Advancement of Research, Training and Education. She holds dual Bachelor's degrees in Social Ecology and Social Sciences (with a specialization in research and analytic methods) from the University of California at Irvine, and a Master's of Arts degree (M.A.) in Criminal Justice (with a specialization in research and evaluation) from Loyola University Chicago. Ms. Roque has worked on multiple federally funded projects, and regularly presents findings from her work with community-based agencies at local and national conferences.</p>
<p>
<bold>Pamela F. Rodriguez</bold> is president of TASC, Inc. of Illinois, a statewide, nonprofit case management agency that serves adults and youth with substance use and mental health disorders. Ms. Rodriguez oversees TASC's service delivery to approximagely 17,000 individuals each year who are referred to TASC by Illinois courts, corrections, and child welfare systems. Ms. Rodriguez earned her master's degree from the University of Chicago.</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-2153368712468861">
<label>1</label>Chicago State University, Chicago, IL, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-2153368712468861">
<label>2</label>Loyola University Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-2153368712468861">
<label>3</label>TASC, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2153368712468861">Thomas Lyons, HIV/AIDS Research and Policy Institute, Chicago State University, 9501S. King Dr., Chicago IL 60628, USA. Email: <email>tlyons20@csu.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Sage Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article describes the work of the Illinois Disproportionate Justice Impact Study Commission, a nonpartisan, multidisciplinary group of policy makers, government leaders, and justice professionals that focused on understanding and alleviating the disproportionate incarceration of African Americans and Latinos in Illinois for drug law violations. The study data were obtained from arrest records statewide and court cases in Cook County (Chicago), which were both drawn from calendar year 2005. Results showed that racial disproportionality in arrests for drug crimes is found in urban, suburban, and rural counties of the state and is more pronounced among arrestees with arrest records than among first-time arrestees. Analyses of Cook County court data showed that controlling for other variables, including criminal history, African Americans were approximately 2.2 times more likely than Whites, and Latinos were approximately 1.6 times more likely than Whites, to be prosecuted for drug offenses. Unequal outcomes in court processing compound the disparities at arrest, perpetuating a vicious cycle. The article concludes with the Commission’s proposed remedies for racial disproportionality.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>drug laws</kwd>
<kwd>drugs</kwd>
<kwd>race and sentencing</kwd>
<kwd>race and courts</kwd>
<kwd>racial profiling</kwd>
<kwd>race and policing</kwd>
<kwd>African/Black Americans</kwd>
<kwd>race/ethnicity</kwd>
<kwd>Latino/Hispanic Americans</kwd>
<kwd>community corrections</kwd>
<kwd>race and corrections</kwd>
<kwd>pretrial process</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The mass incarceration of minorities in the war on drugs is one of the most pressing social problems in the United States, and to a large extent must be remedied through policy and legislative changes at the state level, where drug laws are made and enforced. This article describes the work of the Illinois Disproportionate Justice Impact Study (DJIS) Commission, a nonpartisan, multidisciplinary group of policy makers, government leaders, and justice professionals, appointed by the Illinois legislature in 2009. The Commission’s research advisory group analyzed arrest and criminal processing data in order to guide the Commission in recommending systemic changes that could mitigate or eliminate racial disproportionality in sentencing for drug crimes. These data were gathered from samples of statewide criminal records and from court cases in Cook County (Chicago), both of which were drawn from calendar year 2005 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-2153368712468861">Lurigio, Lyons, Brookes, &amp; Whitney, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>The research advisory group determined that four research questions were of primary importance in guiding the Commission’s recommendations:</p>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Which specific laws account for the disproportionality in incarceration for drug-related offenses?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To what extent is this racial disproportionality a statewide phenomenon?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Are racial disparities fully explained by disparities at arrest, or do disparities in criminal justice processing also contribute to disproportionality in incarceration?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To what extent does criminal history account for racial disparities at arrest and sentencing?</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<sec id="section1-2153368712468861">
<title>Background</title>
<sec id="section2-2153368712468861">
<title>The War on Drugs</title>
<p>The war on drugs has played a well-documented role in the disproportionate incarceration of African Americans and Latinos in state prison systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-2153368712468861">Mauer, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-2153368712468861">Western, 2006</xref>). In 1980, 19,000 (6%) state prison inmates had been convicted of drug offenses; by 1999, that number had risen to more than 250,000 (20%), increasing 10-fold the nation’s incarceration rate, from 15 to 150 inmates per 100,000 Americans. African Americans are disproportionately arrested, charged, and sentenced to prison for drug offenses. Although African Americans constituted only 13% of the general population in 2005, they represented 34% of those arrested and 45% of those incarcerated in state prison for a drug offense in that year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-2153368712468861">Sentencing Project, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>In 2005, Illinois ranked 14th among the states in the ratio of incarcerated African Americans to Whites, which was 9 times higher among the former (2,020 per 100,000) than the latter (223 per 100,000; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-2153368712468861">Mauer &amp; King, 2007</xref>). Beginning in the 1980s, arrests and admissions to prison for drug law violations in Illinois rose dramatically. By far, the most common drug crime leading to arrest is Class 4 possession of a controlled substance, the lowest (least serious) felony drug charge. The overall number of admissions to prison for drug offenses has declined since 2005. Nonetheless, racial disproportionality persists. In 2009, 61% of the people admitted to Illinois prisons for drug crimes were African American, 23% were White, 15% were Latino, and 1% was of another racial designation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-2153368712468861">Olson, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Racial differences in patterns of drug use and sales have been posited to account for this disproportionality. The most recent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-2153368712468861">Illinois Household Survey (2003</xref>) found that past-month use of illicit drugs, which suggests problematic use that could bring people in contact with the criminal justice system, was reported by 3.7% of Whites, 3.5% of African Americans, and 1.6% of Latinos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-2153368712468861">Illinois Household Survey, 2003</xref>). However, other data from the survey, such treatment admission data and diagnoses of drug dependence among those surveyed, as well as national research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2153368712468861">Galea et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-2153368712468861">Ramchand, Pacula, &amp; Iguchi, 2006</xref>) suggest that within the minority of each population who are substance users, the problem might be more serious among African Americans and Latinos than among Whites. Furthermore, if African Americans and Latinos are more likely than Whites to sell illicit drugs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2153368712468861">Goode, 2002</xref>), greater racial disproportionality would be expected among defendants charged with drug distribution as opposed to lesser possession charges. In Illinois, possession of any amount of cocaine, opiates, and other substances is a felony under the Controlled Substances Act. Hence, in theory, although certainly not in criminal justice practice, each of the individuals who used illicit drugs other than marijuana as estimated from the 2003 Illinois survey—some 120,000 Whites, 10,000 African Americans, and 14,000 Latinos—committed a possession offense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-2153368712468861">Illinois Household Survey, 2003</xref>, p. 18).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-2153368712468861">
<title>Disproportionality and Arrests</title>
<p>In sheer numbers, most of the overrepresentation of people of color in the criminal justice system can be attributed to disparities at the point of arrest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-2153368712468861">Heaps, Lurigio, Rodriguez, Lyons, &amp; Brookes, 2009</xref>). Racial profiling and other policing strategies could account for these disparities in arrest, irrespective of underlying rates of offending. Racially selective drug searches of both drivers and pedestrians have been documented throughout the United States in both large and small communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2153368712468861">Amnesty International, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2153368712468861">Beckett, Nyrop, &amp; Pfingst, 2006</xref>). Numerous studies of racial profiling have been performed in the fields of criminology, sociology, and law (see, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-2153368712468861">Roh &amp; Robinson, 2009</xref>, for a review). In Illinois, for example, a study conducted in 2007 found that Latino drivers were 2.4 times more likely and African American drivers were 3 times more likely than White drivers to have their vehicles searched during a traffic stop. The same study showed that minority drivers who were stopped were half as likely as White drivers to have contraband in their vehicles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-2153368712468861">Illinois Department of Transportation, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Racial profiling can exert a “ratchet effect” that ultimately leads to higher rates of crime in minority communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-2153368712468861">Harcourt, 2008</xref>). Police target the group that has the highest real or perceived offending rate. This group is more likely to be stopped, searched, and discovered in possession of illicit drugs than their counterparts in other racial groups. Each year, the disproportionality is exacerbated, as the higher “hit rate” among the targeted group is used to guide policing strategies for the following year. “The resulting ratchet effect [of such strategies has] significant detrimental consequences on the employment, educational, familial, and social outcomes of the profiled populations—including, in the case of racial profiling, the devastating effects associated with the notion of black criminality that pervades the public imagination” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-2153368712468861">Harcourt, 2008</xref>, p. 271). As part of its mandate, the Illinois DJIS Commission examined racial disproportionality in drug arrests throughout Illinois’s 102 counties, most of which are rural. Among the many studies of racial profiling, few have examined racial disproportionality in arrests in suburban or rural communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-2153368712468861">Puhrmann, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-2153368712468861">Southern Poverty Law Center, 2009</xref>); however, one study found that urban residents had a stronger perception of racial profiling than rural residents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-2153368712468861">Weitzer &amp; Tuch, 2002</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section4-2153368712468861">
<title>Criminal history effects</title>
<p>More than 20% of all adults nationwide have a criminal arrest record on file with the state—mostly for serious misdemeanors and felonies (Rodriguez and Ensellem, 2011). In stark contrast, estimates suggest that 80% of working-age African American men in Chicago have criminal records (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2153368712468861">Alexander, 2010</xref>). Beyond the profound and devastating effects of a criminal record on employment, citizenship, and receipt of social services, especially for non-Whites, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2153368712468861">Alexander, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-2153368712468861">Pager, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-2153368712468861">Western, 2006</xref>), an individual with a criminal record is more likely to be arrested for a given crime than an individual without a record, especially if the suspect is known to the police or the police are able to access criminal histories (rap sheets) electronically at the time of arrest. Thus, racial differences in criminal histories—themselves reflecting past arrests—can contribute to racial disproportionality.</p>
<p>In practice, the effect of criminal history on the probability of arrest is difficult to distinguish from the individual’s propensity to commit further criminal acts. The only obvious point at which criminal history plays no role is the first time in life that each individual is arrested. As part of the DJIS Commission’s research, we identified first-time arrestees—that is, those with no felony or misdemeanor arrests in Illinois state police records—in 2005. The identification of first arrests from state police data on adults is methodologically challenging, given that someone with an arrest history can move into the state, or can have been arrested as a juvenile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2153368712468861">Geerken, 1994</xref>). Nonetheless, a cross-sectional analysis of first arrests presents a rough snapshot of people at the same stage in their official criminal careers. These data can provide a unique view into drug offending before the “ratcheting” effect of an accumulated criminal history.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-2153368712468861">
<title>Disparities in criminal justice processing</title>
<p>As we noted above, the overrepresentation of non-Whites in the criminal justice system has been attributed to their overrepresentation at the point of arrest. However, research has also shown that once arrested, African Americans are more likely than Whites to be prosecuted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-2153368712468861">Stemen, 2010</xref>) and sentenced to prison (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2153368712468861">Spohn &amp; Holleran, 2000</xref>). Criminological interest in possible racial bias in the prosecution and adjudication of cases in the criminal courts has a long history. Before the 1980s, these studies seldom focused on sentences for drug offenses, which had not yet constituted a large percentage of cases heard in the criminal courts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-2153368712468861">Hagan, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-2153368712468861">Lizotte, 1978</xref>). For example, an analysis of Cook County court data from the mid-1990s found that young African American men were more likely to be sentenced to prison (on all charges) than other defendants convicted on similar charges, after controlling for criminal history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2153368712468861">Spohn &amp; Holleran, 2000</xref>). The current study replicates Spohn and Holleran’s analysis of sentencing decisions, using 2005 data and focusing on drug charges. In addition, this study examines an earlier stage in the court process, namely, the decision to prosecute those arrested on drug charges, and includes a variable representing the selection effect from that stage in the model for the sentencing stage. The present data do not include employment status or occupation, which have been found to be strong and theoretically important independent predictors in previous sentencing models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-2153368712468861">Lizotte, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2153368712468861">Spohn &amp; Holleran, 2000</xref>). However, the appointment of a public defender (a variable available only for some analyses, as described below) likely serves as a proxy for socioeconomic status. Unequal outcomes in court processing could compound the disparities at arrest, creating a vicious cycle.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-2153368712468861" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section7-2153368712468861">
<title>Statewide Data</title>
<p>The DJIS Commission obtained two de-identified data sets for analyses. The first data set consisted of statewide records from the Illinois Criminal Justice Information Authority (ICJIA), which annually compiles Illinois state police records. Individuals are identified with a unique identification number corresponding to fingerprint. We requested felony drug arrests in 2005 in order to have prospective data to 2009 on the outcomes of the arrests. Specifically, we examined felony drug law violations under the Controlled Substances Act; the Cannabis Control Act; and the Methamphetamine Control and Community Protection Act, which was passed in 2005. Although persons arrested on only misdemeanor charges in 2005 constituted the majority of all drug arrestees, the mandate of the Commission was to focus only on felony drug charges. For felony drug arrestees in 2005, we obtained data on demographic characteristics, including age, gender, and geographic location of arrest (Chicago and suburban Cook County); arrest and court charges; and dispositions and sentences. More than 99% of the records were coded “B” or “W” (i.e., Black or White) at the time of arrest; less than 1% had other codes. This designation is standard in Illinois state police records, which lack detailed information on ethnicity or race. Therefore, in the present analysis, we categorized arrestees in the statewide data as “White” or “non-White.” Presumably, both the White and non-White categories each consisted of unknowable percentages of people of Latino or other ethnic origin.</p>
<p>We obtained data on all prior and subsequent (up to 2009) arrests in Illinois, both felony and misdemeanor, for this set of individuals arrested on felony drug charges in 2005. These data were provided in separate de-identified files, linked by code numbers, and merged into an Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) file in order to create two linked data files: a file of characteristics of the 2005 arrestees, including criminal history, and a file with the 2005 arrest charges, dispositions, and sentencing history, if any, subsequent to that arrest.</p>
<p>With these arrest data, we created a separate file of individuals whose felony drug arrest in 2005 was, according to ICJIA data, their first arrest of any kind in Illinois for a felony or misdemeanor. We further restricted this sample of first-time arrestees to those whose first arrest was for the lowest level of felony drug possession (Class 4) under the Controlled Substances and Cannabis Control Acts. These first-time Class 4 felony possession arrestees constituted 11% of all Class 4 felony possession arrestees in 2005.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-2153368712468861">
<title>Cook County Data</title>
<p>The second data set, from the clerk of the Circuit Court of Cook County, consisted of a randomly selected sample of 5,000 felony drug and nondrug criminal cases adjudicated in 2005. Cook County (including Chicago) accounted for more than two thirds of the state’s drug arrestees in that year. Of the original 5,000 cases, 86% (<italic>n</italic> = 4,322) had race/ethnicity and complete adjudication data and were used for the analyses. For each defendant, we collected data on demographic characteristics, including age, gender, and race/ethnicity. The Cook County court data classify defendants as African American, Hispanic, White, or another race/ethnicity. Each record contained felony charge class and type (drug, property, violent, or other charge) as originally charged; final felony charge class and type; disposition; and sentence; as well as a complete record of court proceedings for each of these charges and the date of each proceeding.</p>
<p>For only those defendants whose cases were brought to felony court (described below), the court proceedings records contained information about whether the defendant was held in custody or released on bond and whether a public defender was appointed to the case. From these charge files, we created an SPSS file with a single record for each defendant. In addition, we requested criminal history information from ICJIA (from state police records) for each of the randomly selected defendants, matched by his or her state ID (corresponding to fingerprint). We obtained a successful match for 93% of the 4,322 cases.</p>
<p>Descriptive statistics were calculated in SPSS for both the Illinois State Police and the Cook County data. In addition, for the Cook County data, multivariate logistic regressions explored the effects of race on two key decision points, prosecution and prison sentences, controlling for other factors. For the sentencing model, we controlled for the class and type of charge on which the defendant was convicted (i.e., the postplea bargaining charges). These analyses were conducted both for defendants with drug charges and for the whole sample. The inclusion of all charges, not merely drug charges, in selected analyses of the Cook County data allowed us to closely replicate a study that was conducted in the same jurisdiction in the mid-1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2153368712468861">Spohn &amp; Holleran, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Selection bias in these multivariate analyses can occur between the stages of criminal justice processing. Simply put, defendants who move from arrest, to prosecution, to conviction and sentencing are different cohorts of people because of the winnowing effects of criminal justice processing. The cohort at the sentencing stage is a subset of the cohort at the preliminary hearing stage, with a different set of characteristics (e.g., race). These characteristics are associated with outcomes (e.g., sentencing to prison); therefore, estimations of effects must take into account the absence of some observations, which would otherwise contribute to the estimation. This bias was accounted for in multivariate analyses of the sentencing stage by including a predicted value for each individual from the model of the preliminary hearing stage—in effect, weighting the analysis to account for the missing cohort members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-2153368712468861">Roncek, 1991</xref>). (The presumably much greater selection effect at the arrest stage could not be directly estimated with these data.)</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-2153368712468861">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section10-2153368712468861">
<title>Statewide Data</title>
<p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-2153368712468861">Table 1</xref> shows the demographic characteristics of 41,674 unduplicated individuals who were arrested in Illinois on felony drug charges in 2005 and who were coded either “B” or “W” in the state police records. Overall, 66% of these arrestees were coded as non-White (“B”). The distributions for age, gender, and type of drug arrest were similar for White and non-White arrestees. The majority (79%) of non-Whites were arrested in the city of Chicago. However, non-Whites were arrested at a higher rate than Whites relative to their representation in the general population throughout Illinois, including urban, suburban, and rural counties. Racial disparities for drug arrests varied widely by county but tended to be greater in counties with smaller populations of non-White residents (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-2153368712468861">Table 2</xref> for examples). Home to more than half of Illinois’s population, Cook County has a non-White disproportionality ratio in arrests of nearly 2:1 relative to its population, but is by no means the county with the highest racial disproportionality in arrests.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-2153368712468861" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Illinois Statewide Drug-Charge Arrestee Characteristics, 2005, by Race (<italic>N</italic> = 41,674)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-2153368712468861" xlink:href="10.1177_2153368712468861-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="2">Characteristics</th>
<th>Non-Whites (<italic>n</italic> = 27,867)</th>
<th>Whites (<italic>n</italic> = 13,807)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td>Male</td>
<td>85%</td>
<td>80%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Female</td>
<td>15%</td>
<td>20%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at arrest</td>
<td>Mean age</td>
<td>33.1</td>
<td>31.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>19 and under</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td>&lt;1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>20–29</td>
<td>32%</td>
<td>33%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>30–39</td>
<td>22%</td>
<td>32%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>40–49</td>
<td>24%</td>
<td>22%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>50 and older</td>
<td>21%</td>
<td>12%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type of drug arrest</td>
<td>Class 4 possession only</td>
<td>58%</td>
<td>60%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Other than possession</td>
<td>42%</td>
<td>40%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Location of arrest</td>
<td>Chicago</td>
<td>79%</td>
<td>43%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Suburban Cook</td>
<td>8%</td>
<td>13%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Non-Cook urban</td>
<td>9%</td>
<td>26%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Non-Cook rural</td>
<td>3%</td>
<td>18%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-2153368712468861" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>County Population and Drug Arrests, Selected Illinois Counties</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-2153368712468861" xlink:href="10.1177_2153368712468861-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>County</th>
<th colspan="2">County population 2008</th>
<th colspan="3">Arrestees on drug charges, 2005</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Total population 2008</th>
<th>Percent non-White</th>
<th>Arrests, total</th>
<th>Percent non-White</th>
<th>Ratio of proportions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Rural</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Iroquois</td>
<td>30,017</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Stephenson</td>
<td>46,821</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Adams</td>
<td>66,892</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>167</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Livingston</td>
<td>37,965</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Suburban</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> McHenry</td>
<td>312,946</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>402</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Will</td>
<td>664,361</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>438</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lake</td>
<td>702,558</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>613</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> DuPage</td>
<td>925,530</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>656</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Urban</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tazewell</td>
<td>130,789</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>127</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Madison</td>
<td>266,886</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>602</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Winnebago</td>
<td>295,803</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>769</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cook</td>
<td>5,257,001</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>32,489</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>With respect to the number of people affected, most of the racial disproportionality in Illinois drug laws was related to drug possession charges, which accounted for nearly three fourths of felony drug arrests across the state. Class 4 possession of a controlled substance (up to 15 g) accounted for 68% of felony drug arrests in Illinois. Of those arrested for a Class 4 drug offense, 66% were non-White. The second most common arrest charge (6% of all arrestees) was for the manufacture or delivery of a controlled substance; 90% of these arrestees were non-White. Other types of charges, ranging from felony cannabis possession to possession of drug paraphernalia to criminal drug conspiracy, were highly infrequent. Other charges with the highest percentage of non-White arrestees included cannabis sales on or near school property; 90% of these arrestees were non-White. The only category of charge in which arrestees were predominantly White were charges under methamphetamine laws, which were substantially revised in Illinois in 2005 and constituted less than 1% of cases.</p>
<p>Of the individuals arrested in 2005 on felony drug charges for which the most serious charge was Class 4 possession, 3,096 (11%) had no record of a prior arrest, either felony or misdemeanor, in Illinois state police records. Of these first-time arrestees, 62% (<italic>n</italic> = 1,936) were White. In contrast, only 27% of the remaining Class 4 possession arrestees (i.e., those with criminal records) were White and 72% were non-White. Since approximately 25% of Illinois’s population in the 2000 census were non-White, these percentages would correspond to an approximate non-White disproportionality ratio of 1.2:1 among first-time arrestees and 2.8:1 among arrestees with criminal histories, relative to the population. Among the first-time arrestees, the mean age was similar for Whites and non-Whites (about 28 years old), but 4% of the non-White sample were under 20 years old versus 0.9% of the White sample, suggesting a greater degree of truncation of the non-White sample due to missing juvenile data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-2153368712468861">
<title>Cook County Data</title>
<p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-2153368712468861">Table 3</xref> presents the characteristics of the randomly selected sample of all Cook County defendants (drug and nondrug) in 2005. According to this sample, almost 80% of those entering the Cook County court system were African American, 13% were Latino, and 8% were White. The vast majority (84%) were men, and nearly half (45%) were 30 years old or younger. As evidence that the Cook County court system was inundated with low-level drug cases, 72% of the sample had a drug charge (among others), and 70% were charged with Class 4 possession. More than 60% of the overall sample had one or more Class 4 possession charges and no other charges.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-2153368712468861" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Cook County Drug and Non-Drug Felony Cases, 2005 (n = 4,322)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-2153368712468861" xlink:href="10.1177_2153368712468861-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
<th>Number</th>
<th>Percent (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Race</td>
<td>African American</td>
<td>3,388</td>
<td>78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Hispanic</td>
<td>579</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>White</td>
<td>355</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td>Male</td>
<td>3,630</td>
<td>84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Female</td>
<td>692</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>30 and under</td>
<td>1,942</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>31–39 years of age</td>
<td>1,018</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>40 and older</td>
<td>1,358</td>
<td>31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Highest felony charge</td>
<td>Class 4</td>
<td>2,551</td>
<td>59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Class 3</td>
<td>263</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Class 2</td>
<td>551</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Class 1</td>
<td>303</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Class X</td>
<td>196</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Unlawful use of a weapon by a felon</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Unspecified class</td>
<td>388</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drug charge</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>3,106</td>
<td>72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>1,213</td>
<td>28</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The possible outcomes of the preliminary hearing stage of the adjudication process were examined; these included the dismissal of charges by the judge, the decision by the state’s attorney to drop charges (i.e., nolle prosequi), or the transfer of the case to criminal court for prosecution. In the Cook County sample, 40% of the defendants charged with Class 4 drug possession were transferred to criminal court, whereas 60% had all charges either dropped by the state’s attorney or dismissed by the judge. Even though most cases were eventually dropped or dismissed, defendants spent an average of 3 weeks after their arrest awaiting a preliminary hearing. An unknown but large number of them were detained in jail before being processed and released.</p>
<p>Although most cases involving drug charges were dismissed or charges were dropped in all racial/ethnic groups, African American defendants (39%) were more likely than White (31%) and Latino (23%) defendants to be transferred to criminal court. The multivariate model for the decision to prosecute in felony court for defendants <italic>with drug charges</italic>, or to drop or dismiss charges is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-2153368712468861">Table 4</xref>. This analysis showed that, controlling for other variables, including charge class, number of non-drug charges, and criminal history, African Americans were approximately twice as likely as Whites, and Latinos were approximately 1.6 times more likely than Whites, to be prosecuted.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-2153368712468861" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Conditional Logistic Regression Model for Decision to Prosecute in Felony Court, Cook County Drug Defendants 2005 (<italic>N</italic> = 2,955)<sup>a</sup>Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-2153368712468861" xlink:href="10.1177_2153368712468861-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="2">Characteristics</th>
<th>
<italic>p</italic> value</th>
<th>OR</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>29 and under</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>30–39 years of age</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>40 and older</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td>Male</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Female</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>0.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Race</td>
<td>White</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>1.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>African American</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>2.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Hispanic</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>1.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prior Convictions</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>1.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>1–3</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>4–6</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>7+</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.70</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-2153368712468861">
<p>
<italic>Note. R</italic>
<sup>2</sup> of model = .26.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-2153368712468861">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Model also includes felony charge class (Class 4-1 and Class X) and whether defendant has nondrug charges.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The high volume of drug cases in the county contributes to most cases being dismissed or dropped—an outcome that could be perceived as preferable to a conviction. However, in Cook County, drug-crime defendants spent an average of 21 days awaiting the disposition of their cases in this sample; during this time, many are in custody. Moreover, many are likely to return to the criminal justice system after their initial cases are dropped. As reported above, previous arrests can increase the likelihood of future arrests, especially among non-Whites.</p>
<p>To examine prison sentences, we were able to include in the model two important additional variables from felony court records, namely, detention status and whether a public defender was appointed to the case. Overall, 45% of African Americans, 20% of Whites, and 32% of Latinos in felony court were detained prior to trial; 74%, 53%, and 53%, respectively, were appointed a public defender. The model with all defendants, drug and nondrug, partially replicated the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2153368712468861">Spohn and Holleran (2000</xref>). After controlling for the type and class of charge for which the defendant was convicted and the number of previous convictions, defendants who were most likely to be sentenced to prison were African American, held in custody, and represented by a public defender. In contrast to Spohn and Holleran’s findings, younger age and male gender were unrelated to prison sentence; data were unavailable on employment status, which was a significant variable in the earlier study.</p>
<p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-2153368712468861">Table 5</xref> presents data on the sentencing of individuals with at least one drug charge (72% of the sample). As with the model for the decision to prosecute, this model controlled for charge class and the number of non-drug charges; it also included an indicator variable for whether charges were amended during felony court proceedings (evidence of plea bargaining). In addition, it included prior convictions, detention status, and the appointment of a public defender, and it was weighted for the selection effect stemming from the preliminary hearing stage. In this expanded model, the effect of race (African American vs. White) on a prison sentence was marginally significant (odds ratio [OR] = 1.93 <italic>p</italic> = .068) and Latino ethnicity was nonsignificant (OR = 0.88). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-2153368712468861">Table 5</xref> shows that apart from prior convictions, detention prior to trial was the most significant predictor of a prison sentence. (We did not analyze how many of these sentences were for “time served.”)</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-2153368712468861" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Conditional Logistic Regression Model for Decision to Sentence to Prison, Cook County Drug Defendants 2005 (<italic>N</italic> = 1,342)<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-2153368712468861" xlink:href="10.1177_2153368712468861-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="2">Characteristics</th>
<th>
<italic>p</italic> value</th>
<th>OR</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>29 and under</td>
<td>––</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>30–39 years of age</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>1.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>40 and older</td>
<td>.80</td>
<td>1.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td>Male</td>
<td>––</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Female</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>0.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Race</td>
<td>White</td>
<td>––</td>
<td>1.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>African American</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>1.93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>Hispanic</td>
<td>.88</td>
<td>0.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Detained prior to trial</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>2.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Public defender appointed</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amended charges (plea)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>2.15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prior convictions</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>1.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>1–3</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>4–6</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>7<sup>+</sup>
</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>1.70</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-2153368712468861">
<p>
<italic>Note. R</italic>
<sup>2 </sup>of model = .36.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-2153368712468861">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Model also includes felony charge class (Class 4-1 and Class X), whether defendant has nondrug charges and predicted probability from first stage regression.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Although the multivariate models demonstrate the effect of race after controlling for other factors, the cumulative effect of these disparities can also be seen in the simple proportion of cases initially charged with Class 4 possession that penetrate further into the criminal justice system. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2153368712468861">Figure 1</xref> illustrates that among the initial pool of those arrested for a Class 4 possession charges (with no other charges), African Americans were eventually sentenced to prison at an (unadjusted) rate almost 5 times greater than Whites: (19% vs. 4%). When the sample is restricted to defendants with fewer than two previous convictions, African Americans were sentenced to prison at a rate 3 times that of Whites (10% vs. 3%).</p>
<fig id="fig1-2153368712468861" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Criminal justice system process penetration among Class 4 drug possession defendants, Cook County sample 2005, by race.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2153368712468861-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-2153368712468861">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="section13-2153368712468861">
<title>Arrests and Charges</title>
<p>The Illinois DJIS Commission analyzed both statewide arrest data and detailed court processing data from Cook County in order to gain a comprehensive understanding of racial disparities in the criminal justice system among drug offenders. The results presented here are consistent with both national studies and studies in Illinois that show that non-Whites are arrested for drug offenses at a higher proportion than their representation in the general population. Our analyses of county arrest data show that this disproportionality is found in urban, suburban, and rural counties of the state. In nonurban areas, racial differences in drug arrests are less attributable to the operation of open-air drug markets than they are in inner-city neighborhoods. Instead, the data are suggestive of police-initiated racial profiling in nonurban areas, a phenomenon that has been documented throughout the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2153368712468861">Amnesty International, 2004</xref>) and might in fact be more common in mostly White areas. In a few very small rural counties, the number of non-Whites arrested on drug charges approached the non-White population in the census. Further research is needed focusing on whether non-Whites living in, or driving through, rural areas are being profiled.</p>
<p>Statewide, two thirds of possession arrestees were non-White, whereas up to 90% of arrestees on more serious drug charges were non-White, lending support to the contention that patterns of underlying drug offending differ between Whites and non-Whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2153368712468861">Goode 2002</xref>). However, low-level possession arrests significantly contribute to the overall disproportionality in incarceration rates. Any attempt to address the disproportionate incarceration of minorities in Illinois must focus on how Class 4 possession laws are enforced. For example, 19% of African Americans in our Cook County sample charged with possession alone, with no other charge, were sentenced to prison. The prevailing assumption is that a possession charge indicates that the defendant has committed a more serious offense (i.e., drug sales) for which the police or the prosecution had insufficient evidence. Apart from the question of whether such informal practices are just, it is likely that a large proportion of possession offenders have substance use disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-2153368712468861">Heaps et al., 2009</xref>). For people who are addicted to illicit drugs, arrest, prosecution, and a brief term in jail or prison without treatment are unlikely to encourage future abstinence and can exacerbate abuse and dependence problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-2153368712468861">Western, 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-2153368712468861">
<title>Criminal History</title>
<p>Police might be more likely to select people with arrest histories when deciding whether to search a vehicle (based on license plate) or a pedestrian (based on whether the suspect is known to police). Criminal history is a logical heuristic for police to employ in choosing whether to arrest a suspect, but it further contributes to racial disproportionality in arrests. After stratifying the arrest data by whether individuals had previous arrests, we found that most first-time arrestees on possession charges in Illinois were White. This result supports survey findings showing that the vast majority of illicit drug users in Illinois are White, as well as research findings showing that the searches of vehicles owned or operated by Whites were more likely to uncover contraband than vehicle searches among non-Whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-2153368712468861">Illinois Department of Transportation, 2007</xref>). This result also suggests that the outcome of a first arrest might be different for Whites than non-Whites. Whites might have more access to sentencing alternatives or first-offender programs that decrease the probability of further involvement in the criminal justice system. Because court disposition data were incomplete in the state police data set, we were unable to test this hypothesis. However, such a result would be expected if first-offender programs were less available to arrestees in Cook County where the majority of the non-Whites in Illinois reside.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-2153368712468861">
<title>Disparities in Court Processing</title>
<p>At the court processing stage, our study documents further racial disparities. First, although the majority of low-level drug charges are dropped by prosecutors or dismissed in Cook County, African Americans and Latinos are more likely than Whites to be prosecuted, controlling for criminal history and other factors. Even charges that are dropped could have consequences for an individual’s future involvement in the criminal justice system. Such individuals now have an arrest record. Furthermore, time spent in jail (length between arrest and disposition in 2005 averaged 21 days among cases eventually dropped) can be profoundly disruptive to people’s lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-2153368712468861">Rabinowitz, 2010</xref>). At the sentencing stage, African American race, in itself, was only marginally statistically significant, and Latino ethnicity was nonsignificant, in an expanded model of the decision to sentence to prison. The “imprisonment penalty” paid by non-White defendants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2153368712468861">Spohn &amp; Holleran, 2000</xref>) seems to be accounted for in these data by the criminal justice processing factors of representation by a public defender, plea bargaining, and detention in custody—all of which are associated with race/ethnicity.</p>
<p>Early contact with the criminal justice system provides an opportunity for diversion and rehabilitative programming. Research on sentencing among first-time arrestees should investigate whether Whites and non-Whites have the same access to drug treatment and other interventions in lieu of incarceration. In a study of Cook County Drug Court for probation violators charged with drug offenses, nearly half of the offenders (most of whom were African American) chose prison instead of probation with mandatory treatment, urinalysis, and other conditions of release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-2153368712468861">Olson, 2001</xref>). The study also found that African American probationers were less likely than White probationers to be ordered to drug treatment. However, the question of racial barriers to diversion is difficult to answer with state police data alone, because charge and sentencing information is often missing. In a significant number of drug arrests, either the arrestees were not charged or their charges were not logged into the record—a distinction that was impossible to discern from the data. Given the importance of the first point of contact with the criminal justice system, more detailed research is needed on first arrests (it was difficult to ascertain whether the 8% of our Cook County sample without matching state police records contained any such individuals).</p>
<p>Every point of contact with the criminal justice system could be a point of intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-2153368712468861">Heaps et al., 2009</xref>). Increased access to diversion programs or alternatives to incarceration coupled with simple and timely processes for record expungement and sealing can mitigate future involvement of minorities in the criminal justice system. Without such mechanisms, criminal histories begin to accrue. Taken together, the state data and Cook County court data suggest that unequal outcomes in the court system compound racial disparities at arrest.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-2153368712468861">
<title>Study Limitations</title>
<p>The data presented here are limited. Many individuals involved in the criminal justice system were first arrested as juveniles—information that is missing from our data set for first arrestees. The Illinois State Police data set contained no arrest information from other states. In a study of criminal histories in Louisiana, African Americans were much less likely than Whites to have been born out of state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2153368712468861">Geerken, 1994</xref>), suggesting that a greater proportion of 2005 arrests might have been mistakenly counted as first arrests among Whites than those mistakenly counted as first arrests among African Americans. Furthermore, the analysis of multi-charge arrests is problematic; in this study, we focused on arrests for which the most serious charge was a Class 4 drug possession.</p>
<p>A still more serious limitation in the state police data is the poor quality of the racial/ethnic identification. It is impossible to know whether most Latinos were counted as “W” or as “B” in the cards filled out by the state and local police. Nearly 5% of our state sample was classified as both “W” and “B” at different points in their arrest histories; we excluded these from our analyses. For these reasons, we lacked the confidence in the data to perform more than simple descriptive statistics. Although the Cook County Courts collect more detailed data on race and ethnicity, we excluded 14% of the original 5,000 randomly selected cases because they lacked either race/ethnicity or disposition data. We had no basis to determine whether those cases differed systematically from the ones included in the study.</p>
<p>The Cook County court data set lacked information on detention status and use of a private attorney or public defender, unless the defendant was prosecuted in felony court. These variables are likely to be important in identifying whether a case is prosecuted and should be collected systematically in order to improve the efficiency of case processing and reduce racial disproportionality. Nor did we create a path model to distinguish the interactive effects of race, socioeconomic status, and criminal justice processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-2153368712468861">Lizotte, 1978</xref>). Our analyses for the Commission were not intended to settle decades-long debates in criminology about racial bias in the courtroom. However, the finding of disproportionality at the prosecution stage calls for future research at this stage of case processing and for improvements in data collection in the courts. A final limitation is that our data were from 2005, the year in which admissions to prison for drug offenses peaked. Although admissions to prison have declined, the proportion of admissions for African Americans and Latinos has remained stable and disparate through 2009.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-2153368712468861">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The DJIS Commission presented its findings to the Illinois legislature in 2010 with recommendations for remedying racial disproportionality. Among the recommendations were the following:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>A Racial and Ethnic Impact Research Task Force should be established to ensure the standardized collection and analyses of data on the racial and ethnic identity of arrestees. The task force convened in October 2011.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>State legislators should be able to request a Racial and Ethnic Impact Statement on bills or appropriation measures that impact criminal offenses, penalties, sentencing, probation, or parole policies.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>For criminal background checks that are conducted for employers, the state should prohibit the inclusion of drug-related arrests that do not result in convictions. HB0298, approved in 2011 by the General Assembly and the Governor, allows court-ordered sealing of arrest records when the charges do not result in convictions.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Jurisdictions should define a fixed portion of drug asset forfeiture funds to support drug treatment and diversion programs. HB2048, approved in 2011 by the General Assembly and the Governor, allows county prosecutors to use money collected from drug dealers to fund drug treatment and halfway houses.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>The purpose of the Commission’s research was to obtain Illinois data in order to guide Illinois policy. However, key findings of the Commission, though largely preliminary, support recent research on race and the criminal justice system in the United States (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-2153368712468861">Western, 2006</xref>). Owing to the statewide scope of the study and analyses of two distinct data sets, these findings make a contribution toward our understanding of case processing at multiple stages of the criminal justice system. Racial profiling has mostly been analyzed in urban areas. The Commission was mandated to examine the entire state and discovered that racial disproportionality was rife—a finding that could potentially draw into the conversation, and make accountable, suburban and rural politicians and policy makers. In addition, the Commission focused on the effects of the accumulation of a criminal history among arrestees on low-level drug charges, which makes an important contribution to the literature. The racial composition of first-time arrestees was not substantially different from that of the population as a whole, calling into question the assumption that underlying patterns of drug use differ by race (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2153368712468861">Goode 2002</xref>). Although these data were imperfect, the analysis was possible only because the entire 2005 cohort of drug arrestees in Illinois were analyzed. Data on first-time arrestees support the notion of “cumulative disadvantage” and a perspective across the life course of individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-2153368712468861">Sampson &amp; Lauritsen, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>Most previous analysis of racial bias in court processing has focused on violent offenders and index crimes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-2153368712468861">Lizotte, 1978</xref>). The fact that the overwhelming majority of offenders in a random sample of cases in a large urban jurisdiction were low-level drug offenders suggests that criminologists should examine these cases more closely. It is in low-level cases, and in the earliest stages of court processing, where discretion may be greatest, and a version of the “liberation hypothesis” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2153368712468861">Farrell &amp; Givelber, 2010</xref>) would predict that extralegal factors such as the race of the defendant would play a greater role. These low-level decisions have a cumulative effect on incarceration rates that is far from negligible. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-2153368712468861">Murakawa and Beckett (2010</xref>) have stated, “seemingly small infractions and racial disparities accrete into lasting criminal justice entanglement characterized by large and often growing racial inequalities.”</p>
<p>Finally, if “all politics is local,” then so, at least in part, should be the research into the causes and remedies for mass incarceration. States are under immense fiscal pressure to reduce their prison populations as well as the size of their criminal justice systems. Policy makers, as well as voters, are likely to be more attentive to facts about their own jurisdiction than to national statistics. The Illinois DJIS Commission, then, offers a strategy for other states in their efforts for reducing racial disparities in the criminal justice system.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>This research was conducted under the auspices of the Disproportionate Justice Impact Study Commission of the Illinois Legislature (Honorable Mattie Hunter and Honorable Arthur L. Turner, cochairs). We are grateful to the members of the DJIS Research Advisory Group, chaired by Creasie Finney Hairston, University of Illinois at Chicago. Special thanks are extended to Laura Brookes at TASC and Christine Devitt Westley at the Illinois Criminal Justice Information Authority. All opinions in this article are those of the authors only.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-2153368712468861">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-2153368712468861">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship and/or publication of this article: The project was supported by a grant from the U.S. Department of Justice, Bureau of Justice Assistance (Grant No. 2008-DD-BX-0200) to the Center for Health and Justice at TASC, Chicago, IL.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>The new Jim Crow: Mass incarceration in the age of colorblindness</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The New Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Amnesty International</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Threat and humiliation: Racial profiling, domestic security, and human rights in the United States</article-title>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.amnestyusa.org/pdfs/rp_report.pdf">http://www.amnestyusa.org/pdfs/rp_report.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beckett</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nyrop</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pfingst</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Race, drugs and policing: Understanding disparities in drug delivery arrests</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Farrell</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Givelber</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Liberation reconsidered: Understanding why judges and juries disagree about guilt</article-title>. <source>Journal of Law and Criminology</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>1549</fpage>–<lpage>1586</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Galea</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahern</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tardiff</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leon</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coffin</surname>
<given-names>P. O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Derr</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vlahov</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Racial/ethnic disparities in overdose mortality trends in New York City, 1990–1998</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Health</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geerken</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Rap sheets in criminological research: Considerations and caveats</article-title>. <source>Journal of Quantitative Criminology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goode</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Drug arrests at the millennium</article-title>. <source>Social Science and Public Policy</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hagan</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>Extra-legal attributes and criminal sentencing: An assessment of sociological viewpoint</article-title>. <source>Law and</source> Society, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harcourt</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A reader’s companion to “Against Prediction”: A reply to Ariela Gross, Yoram Margalioth, and Yoav Sapir on economic modeling, selective incapacitation, governmentality, and race</article-title>. <source>Law &amp; Social Inquiry</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heaps</surname>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lurigio</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyons</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brookes</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Recovery-oriented care for drug abusing offenders</article-title>. <source>Addiction Science and Criminal Practice: Journal of the National Institute on Drug Abuse</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Illinois Department of Transportation</collab>. (<year>2007</year>). <source>Illinois traffic stops statistics study. Annual Report</source>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dot.il.gov/travelstats/2007%20Illinois%20Traffic%20Stops%20Statistics%20Study%20Final%20Report.pdf">http://www.dot.il.gov/travelstats/2007%20Illinois%20Traffic%20Stops%20Statistics%20Study%20Final%20Report.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Illinois Household Survey</collab>. (<year>2003</year>). <source>Alcohol, tobacco, and other drug use in Illinois: Prevalence and treatment need, 2003</source>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.srl.uic.edu/Publist/DASA/IL_Household_Survey.pdf">http://www.srl.uic.edu/Publist/DASA/IL_Household_Survey.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lizotte</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Extra-legal factors in Chicago’s criminal courts: Testing the conflict model of criminal justice</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lurigio</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyons</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brookes</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitney</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010, December</year>). <source>Illinois disproportionate justice impact study commission: Final report</source> <comment>(Submitted to the Illinois General Assembly, Springfield, Illinois)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Criminal Justice, Loyola University Chicago and TASC</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mauer</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Race to incarcerate</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The New Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mauer</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Uneven justice: State rates of incarceration by race and ethnicity</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Sentencing Project</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murakawa</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beckett</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The penology of racial innocence: The erasure of racism in the study and practice of punishment</article-title>. <source>Law &amp; Society Review</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>D. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Racial disparities in drug sentencing</source>. <comment>Testimony presented to the Illinois House Judiciary: Criminal Justice Committee</comment>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Olive-Harvey College</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>D. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Unpublished analyses of State Fiscal Year 2009 Illinois Department of Corrections’ Court Admissions Data</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Loyola University</publisher-name>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pager</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Marked: Race, crime, and finding work in an era of mass incarceration</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puhrmann</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Public support for racial profiling: Exploring urban and rural residence</source>. <comment>Conference paper abstract, American Society for Criminology, 2009 Annual Meeting</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rabinowitz</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Holding cells: Understanding the collateral consequences of pretrial detentions</source>. <comment>(Unpublished doctoral dissertation)</comment>. <publisher-name>Northwestern University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Evanston, IL</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ramchand</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pacula</surname>
<given-names>R. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Iguchi</surname>
<given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in marijuana-users’ risk of arrest in the United States</article-title>. <source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23a-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emsellem</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>65 Million need not apply: The case for reforming criminal background checks for employment. The National Employment Law Project</article-title>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nelp.3cdn.net/c1696a4161be2c85dd_t0m62vj76.pdf">http://nelp.3cdn.net/c1696a4161be2c85dd_t0m62vj76.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roh</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A geographic approach to racial profiling: The microanalysis and macroanalysis of racial disparity in traffic stops</article-title>. <source>Police Quarterly</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roncek</surname>
<given-names>D. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Using logit coefficients to obtain the effects of independent variables on changes in probabilities</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sampson</surname>
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lauritsen</surname>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in crime and criminal justice in the United States</article-title>. <source>Crime and Justice</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Sentencing Project</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>The changing racial dynamics of the war on drugs</source>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sentencingproject.org/doc/dp_raceanddrugs.pdf">http://www.sentencingproject.org/doc/dp_raceanddrugs.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Southern Poverty Law Center</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Under siege: Life for low-income Latinos in the south</source>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/publications/under-siege-life-for-low-income-latinos-in-the-south">http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/publications/under-siege-life-for-low-income-latinos-in-the-south</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spohn</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holleran</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The imprisonment penalty paid by young unemployed black and Hispanic male offenders</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stemen</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010, June</year>). <source>Prosecution and racial justice: Using prosecution case management data to examine disparity</source>. <publisher-name>Conference abstract, National Institute of Justice Annual Conference</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weitzer</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuch</surname>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Perceptions of racial profiling: Race, class, and personal experience</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source> <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-2153368712468861">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Western</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Punishment and inequality in America</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>