<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spoto</journal-id>
<journal-title>Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0194-5998</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-6817</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599812458087</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0194599812458087</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pneumolabyrinth following Eustachian Tube Insufflation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Magliulo</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812458087">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ciniglio Appiani</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812458087">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Porcaro</surname><given-names>Matilde</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812458087">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Iannella</surname><given-names>Giannicola</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812458087">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0194599812458087"><label>1</label>Sapienza University, Rome, Italy</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0194599812458087">Giuseppe Magliulo, MD, Viale dell’Università, Via Gregorio VII n. 80, 00165 Rome, Italy Email: <email>giuseppemagliuloorl@yahoo.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>147</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>980</fpage>
<lpage>981</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>10</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>27</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>24</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery Foundation 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Official journal of the American Academy of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>pneumolabyrinth</kwd>
<kwd>subtotal petrosectomy</kwd>
<kwd>Eustachian tube insufflations</kwd>
<kwd>stapedotomy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Pneumolabyrinth is a condition in which the vestibule and/or cochlea is filled with air.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0194599812458087">1</xref></sup> Eustachian tube insufflation (ETI) is a type of treatment for recurrent serous otitis media that is still popular in Europe. It exploits the anti-inflammatory and mucolytic effects of thermal waters containing sulfur and bromo-iodine gas.</p>
<p>To our knowledge, no case of a pneumolabyrinth due to barotrauma provoked by ETI has been described previously. The aim of this article is to present a patient who developed a pneumolabyrinth following ETI.</p>
<sec id="section1-0194599812458087">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 55-year-old woman was referred to our hospital complaining of vertigo and profound hearing loss in the left ear. One month before, she had undergone ETI because she had recurrent otitis media with effusion (OME). Immediately after the first insufflation, she developed vertigo, hearing loss, and tinnitus. Ten years earlier, she had a successful operation for left stapedotomy. Since then, she has denied symptoms or signs of perilymph fistula (PLF) as attacks of vertigo or hearing impairment.</p>
<p>Otoscopy was normal bilaterally. Pure-tone audiometry revealed profound hearing loss in the left ear, and type A tympanograms were bilaterally observed. No spontaneous nystagmus was detected. Caloric test, vestibular-evoked myogenic potentials (ocular-VEMPs; cervical-VEMPs), and video head impulse test (vHIT) revealed a complete left areflexia. High-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) of the temporal bone revealed pneumolabyrinth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0194599812458087"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>). An exploratory tympanotomy showed fibrous tissue around the prosthesis with a small hole creating a communication between the middle ear and the scala vestibule. The oval window was sealed with fat and reinforced with perichondrium. Notwithstanding this, the symptoms did not improve and, 3 weeks postoperatively, HRCT showed the persistence of air in the inner ear. Another exploratory tympanotomy failed to heal the pneumolabyrinth. Thus, it was decided to perform a subtotal petrosectomy with blind sac closure of the external auditory canal (EAC) and obliteration of the eustachian tube. Finally, the middle ear and mastoid were obliterated with abdominal fat.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0194599812458087" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Preoperative high-resolution computed tomography scan: air inside the cochlea (black arrow) and in the vestibule (white arrow).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812458087-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Vestibular symptoms improved the day after this surgical procedure and had disappeared at 1 month. At this time, profound hearing loss persisted, and vHIT and VEMPs still revealed left areflexia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599812458087">2</xref></sup> The HRCT scan performed postoperatively at 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0194599812458087"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>) and 6 months showed no signs of pneumolabyrinth. The institutional review board of Sapienza University approved the study.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0194599812458087" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Postoperative high-resolution computed tomography scan: no air into the anterior (black arrow) and posterior (white arrow) labyrinth.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812458087-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0194599812458087">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Pneumolabyrinth is a rare clinical manifestation of PLF resulting from temporal bone fractures, traumatic stapes dislocation, stapedectomy, cochlear implantation, barotrauma, chronic ear disease, and neoplasms of the middle ear.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0194599812458087">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0194599812458087"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0194599812458087">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>In our case, the pathogenesis of pneumolabyrinth may be reasonably linked to the PLF resulting from ETI in the presence of a poststapedotomy fistula with air trapped through a one-way valve mechanism. Eustachian tube insufflation is a type of treatment for recurrent OME that uses the anti-inflammatory and mucolytic effects of thermal waters containing sulfur and bromo-iodine gas. It consists of conveying the gas with a pressure of 0.5 atm for 2 minutes with a gas temperature of 37.5°C into the middle ear by introducing a small probe, the “Itard catheter,” into the patient’s nose until reaching the pharyngeal ostium of the eustachian tube. Although this procedure is considered safe, some cases of pneumocephalus caused by ETI have been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0194599812458087">4</xref></sup> To our knowledge, this is the first report of a pneumolabyrinth following this procedure.</p>
<p>There is no definite management strategy for pneumolabyrinth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0194599812458087">5</xref></sup> The surgical option should not be postponed to increase the chances of successful hearing. In our case, because of the persistence of the pneumolabyrinth after 2 subsequent procedures, we preferred performing a subtotal petrosectomy instead of plugging the eustachian tube with insertion of a pressure equalization tube to increase the chance of successful outcome.</p>
<p>A thorough history and physical examination are necessary prior to considering ETI for recurrent OME. Because of the risk of perilymph leakage and pneumolabyrinth, providers should exercise caution when recommending this treatment option or other particular processes of cannulation of the eustachian tube for patients with a history of stapes surgery. Although Mandalà et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0194599812458087">3</xref></sup> also reported a poststapedectomy pneumolabyrinth from barotrauma secondary to rapid altitude changes in the ear, our one case report obviously does not justify advising every single stapes patient not to “pop their ears” on a plane or in the mountains. This dramatic pronouncement would unnecessarily label stapes surgery as potentially unsafe.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0194599812458087">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p><bold>Giuseppe Magliulo</bold>, substantial contributions to conception and design, analysis and interpretation of data, revising the article critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Mario Ciniglio Appiani</bold>, acquisition of data, drafting the article, final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Matilde Porcaro</bold>, acquisition of data, drafting the article; <bold>Giannicola Iannella</bold>, acquisition of data, drafting the article.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0194599812458087">
<title>Disclosures</title>
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Sponsorships:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Funding source:</bold> None.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>No sponsorships or competing interests have been disclosed for this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0194599812458087">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mafee</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valvassori</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yannias</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pneumolabyrinth: a new radiologic sign for fracture of the stapes footplate</article-title>. <source>Am J Otol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>-<lpage>375</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0194599812458087">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schmid-Priscoveanu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obzim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Straumann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Caloric and search-coil head-impulse testing in patients after vestibular neuritis</article-title>. <source>J Assoc Res Otolaryngol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0194599812458087">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandalà</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colletti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pneumolabyrinth and positional vertigo after stapedectomy</article-title>. <source>Auris Nasus Larynx</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>-<lpage>550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0194599812458087">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moritake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Otogenic tension pneumocephalus complicated by eustachian tube insufflation in a patient with a ventriculoperitoneal shunt</article-title>. <source>J Neurosurg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1098</fpage>-<lpage>1101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0194599812458087">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pneumolabyrinth without temporal bone fracture: different outcomes for hearing recovery</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>1464</fpage>-<lpage>1466</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>