<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Industrial Relations</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1856</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1472-9296</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022185611433004</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022185611433004</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Georgina Murray and David Peetz, <italic>Women of the Coal Rushes</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>Laurie</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0022185611433004">Washington State University, Vancouver, USA</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>54</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>92</fpage>
<lpage>94</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Australian Labour and Employment Relations Association (ALERA), SAGE Publications Ltd, Los Angeles, London, New Delhi, Singapore and Washington DC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">ALERA</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0022185611433009"><title><bold>Georgina Murray and David Peetz, <italic>Women of the Coal Rushes</italic>.</bold> Sydney: University of New South Wales Press, 2010. 320 pp., $49.95 (pbk).</title>
<p>Mining has long been assumed to be the occupational domain of men. But as Georgina Murray, David Peetz, and the 100 women interviewed for their study of Queensland mining towns reveal, women have been the backbone of the coal industry. As wives and mothers they maintained male miners and formed women’s auxiliaries to provide aid to unions and communities; in more recent decades, they have operated the trucks and equipment to mine coal alongside men. <italic>Women of the Coal Rushes</italic> examines the worlds that women made in home, town, and pit from the late 19th century to the present, and how their mining world changed with the economic restructuring that began in the 1990s.</p>
<p>The book’s main strength is the rich oral history excerpts from women who describe mining and women’s support for miners both past and present. From their participation in the 1952 ‘stay down’ strike in Collinsville to the Dysart Miners Support Group formed in 2001 to protest against the company’s use of contract workers, women’s auxiliaries have played a key role in addressing both miners’ and their families’ concerns. The auxiliaries received some funds deducted from miners’ pay and were most active in assisting strikes and families after accidents, ‘when the women really came together’ (p. 142), as one woman recalled. Yet women also organized themselves to demand adequate housing, run cooperative stores, start libraries and scholarship funds, and support each other and community institutions. Despite their critical role maintaining pickets, women were often relegated to gender-specific tasks, such as cooking and delivering meals for strikers, and were denied decision-making authority within the union. The authors note that auxiliary women may not have explicitly expressed feminist ideals but ‘they were motivated by class struggle, fighting beside their men, for their men, for their families and for themselves’ (p. 146). Mining town life could also be bleak for women who suffered from abusive or alcoholic husbands and who were haunted by the ever-pending consequences of dangerous work. Some of the most compelling stories describe the aftermath of mining disasters like the Box Flat explosion in 1972 that killed 17, and disasters in 1986 and 1994 that overwhelmed Moura residents with the losses of three-dozen men.</p>
<p>The coal rushes of the past few decades have generated much wealth for Australia as they have extracted the hard physical labor of many men and women. Despite male resistance, demand for labor actually increased opportunities for women, who recently made up 8% of the production workforce in Queensland mines. At the same time as they received praise for being ‘more careful’ workers, they were directed into part-time and unskilled jobs, which reduced their job security, pay, and opportunities. Despite their gaining access to some mining jobs since the 1970s, gender norms remained, both in terms of navigating discrimination and in continuing to bear the burden of domestic chores. As one woman miner recalled, ‘They didn’t want women out there … there’s still that thing … this mining culture’ (p. 242). Yet the authors find that women were generally enthusiastic about the financial rewards and the confidence gained from doing ‘men’s’ work.</p>
<p>As the authors note, women’s more recent access to coalfield jobs at the same time that structural changes diminished the former solidarity of the coal towns represented a shift in power relations – improvements in some areas ‘but deteriorations in power in others’ (p. 292). The book examines the range of factors that have led to deteriorating working conditions and the decline of unions since the mid-1980s: the expansion of open-cut rather than underground mines, which reduced camaraderie on the job; restructuring that allowed companies to create 12-hour shifts with flexible work weeks to expand production; companies’ halt in construction of or support of mining towns to favor ‘fly-in, fly-out’ or ‘drive-in, drive-out’ methods of transporting workers to job sites; and new industrial relations laws that made it easier for companies to hire contract and part-time workers and open non-union mines. The authors note that these changes have had a disproportionate impact on women, who must try to maintain families with absent miner spouses or work in the industry with demanding shift schedules. Women miners have been especially damaged by the decline of union influence, since despite their initial resistance, unions protected their female members.</p>
<p>Community life has changed with these new developments. Unlike the decline of mining communities in North America that accompanied a declining industry, many booming Queensland mining towns have seen populations double – which has made living in the towns expensive, sending many women not working in the industry to coastal cities, raising the proportion of men to women in mining communities, and unraveling the social bonds that had held towns together for decades.</p>
<p>At times the book’s chronology is confusing, more careful organization would have eliminated some repetition, and one often longs for more of the authors’ analysis of the interviews. But this case study of Queensland illuminates the hidden histories of women in mining and makes a significant contribution to mining studies worldwide.</p>
<p>LAURIE MERCIER</p>
<p><italic>Washington State University, Vancouver, USA</italic></p></sec>
</body>
</article>