<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ASR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spasr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am Sociol Rev</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Sociological Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0003-1224</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-8271</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003122412466283</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0003122412466283</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Acknowledgments and Index</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Index</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>77</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1077</fpage>
<lpage>1079</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>American Sociological Review</italic>, 2012 Volume 77, Numbers 1–6</p>
<p>Published Bimonthly by the American Sociological Association</p>
<array id="array1-0003122412466283">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Adamczyk, Amy and Brittany E. Hayes.</bold> Religion and Sexual Behaviors: Understanding the Influence of Islamic Cultures and Religious Affiliation for Explaining Sex Outside of Marriage.</td>
<td>723</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Armstrong, Elizabeth A., Paula England, and Alison C. K. Fogarty.</bold> Accounting for Women’s Orgasm and Sexual Enjoyment in College Hookups and Relationships.</td>
<td>435</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Axinn, William G.</bold> See Elyse A. Jennings.</td>
<td>923</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Baba, Yasunori.</bold> See Sotaro Shibayama.</td>
<td>804</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Bail, Christopher A.</bold> The Fringe Effect: Civil Society Organizations and the Evolution of Media Discourse about Islam since the September 11th Attacks.</td>
<td>855</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Bearman, Peter S.</bold> See Uri Shwed.</td>
<td>1064</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Best, Rachel Kahn.</bold> Disease Politics and Medical Research Funding: Three Ways Advocacy Shapes Policy.</td>
<td>780</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Blackstone, Amy.</bold> See Heather McLaughlin.</td>
<td>625</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Bruggeman, Jeroen, V. A. Traag, and Justus Uitermark.</bold> Detecting Communities through Network Data.</td>
<td>1050</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Burt, Callie Harbin, Ronald L. Simons, and Frederick X. Gibbons.</bold> Racial Discrimination, Ethnic-Racial Socialization, and Crime: A Micro-sociological Model of Risk and Resilience.</td>
<td>648</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Carter, Michael J.</bold> See Jan E. Stets.</td>
<td>120</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Chenoweth, Erica.</bold> See Laura Dugan.</td>
<td>597</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Childress, C. Clayton and Noah E. Friedkin.</bold> Cultural Reception and Production: The Social Construction of Meaning in Book Clubs</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Chorev, Nitsan.</bold> Changing Global Norms through Reactive Diffusion: The Case of Intellectual Property Protection of AIDS Drugs.</td>
<td>831</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Collins, Randall.</bold> C-Escalation and D-Escalation: A Theory of the Time-Dynamics of Conflict</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Crowder, Kyle, Jeremy Pais, and Scott J. South.</bold> Neighborhood Diversity, Metropolitan Constraints, and Household Migration</td>
<td>325</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>DiPrete, Thomas A.</bold> See Joscha Legewie.</td>
<td>463</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Dixon, Marc and Andrew W. Martin.</bold> We Can’t Win This on Our Own: Unions, Firms, and Mobilization of External Allies in Labor Disputes.</td>
<td>946</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Dugan, Laura and Erica Chenoweth.</bold> Moving Beyond Deterrence: The Effectiveness of Raising the Expected Utility of Abstaining from Terrorism in Israel.</td>
<td>597</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>England, Paula.</bold> See Elizabeth A. Armstrong.</td>
<td>435</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Fallon, Kathleen M., Liam Swiss, and Jocelyn Viterna.</bold> Resolving the Democracy Paradox: Democratization and Women’s Legislative Representation in Developing Nations, 1975 to 2009</td>
<td>380</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Flores, René and Edward Telles.</bold> Social Stratification in Mexico: Disentangling Color, Ethnicity, and Class.</td>
<td>486</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Fogarty, Alison C. K.</bold> See Elizabeth A. Armstrong.</td>
<td>435</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Friedkin, Noah E.</bold> See C. Clayton Childress.</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Gauchat, Gordon.</bold> Politicization of Science in the Public Sphere: A Study of Public Trust in the United States, 1974 to 2010</td>
<td>167</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Ghimire, Dirgha J.</bold> See Elyse A. Jennings.</td>
<td>923</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Gibbons, Frederick X.</bold> See Callie Harbin Burt.</td>
<td>648</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Gibson, Christopher.</bold> Making Redistributive Direct Democracy Matter: Development and Women’s Participation in the Gram Sabhas of Kerala, India</td>
<td>409</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Goldstein, Adam.</bold> Revenge of the Managers: Labor Cost-Cutting and the Paradoxical Resurgence of Managerialism in the Shareholder Value Era, 1984 to 2001</td>
<td>268</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Gornick, Janet C.</bold> See Karen S. Lyness.</td>
<td>1023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Grotto, Angela R.</bold> See Karen S. Lyness.</td>
<td>1023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Hackett, Edward J.</bold> See John N. Parker.</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Hamm, Patrick, Lawrence P. King, and David Stuckler.</bold> Mass Privatization, State Capacity, and Economic Growth in Post-Communist Countries</td>
<td>295</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Hayes, Brittany E.</bold> See Amy Adamczyk.</td>
<td>723</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Hummer, Robert A.</bold> See Ryan K. Masters.</td>
<td>548</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Jæger, Mads Meier.</bold> The Extended Family and Children’s Educational Success.</td>
<td>903</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Jennings, Elyse A., William G. Axinn, and Dirgha J. Ghimire.</bold> The Effect of Parents’ Attitudes on Sons’ Marriage Timing.</td>
<td>923</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Kelly, Nathan J.</bold> See Thomas W. Volscho.</td>
<td>679</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Kim, Hyojoung and Steven Pfaff.</bold> Structure and Dynamics of Religious Insurgency: Students and the Spread of the Reformation.</td>
<td>188</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>King, Brayden G.</bold> See Ion Bogdan Vasi.</td>
<td>573</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>King, Lawrence P.</bold> See Patrick Hamm.</td>
<td>295</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Legewie, Joscha and Thomas A. DiPrete.</bold> School Context and the Gender Gap in Educational Achievement.</td>
<td>463</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Lim, Alwyn and Kiyoteru Tsutsui.</bold> Globalization and Commitment in Corporate Social Responsibility: Cross-National Analyses of Institutional and Political-Economy Effects</td>
<td>69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Lim, Chaeyoon and Carol Ann MacGregor.</bold> Religion and Volunteering in Context: Disentangling the Contextual Effects of Religion on Voluntary Behavior.</td>
<td>747</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Lyness, Karen S., Janet C. Gornick, Pamela Stone, and Angela R. Grotto.</bold> It’s All about Control: Worker Control over Schedule and Hours in Cross-National Context.</td>
<td>1023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>MacGregor, Carol Ann.</bold> See Chaeyoon Lim.</td>
<td>747</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Martin, Andrew W.</bold> See Marc Dixon.</td>
<td>946</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Masters, Ryan K., Robert A. Hummer, and Daniel A. Powers.</bold> Educational Differences in U.S. Adult Mortality: A Cohort Perspective.</td>
<td>548</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>McLaughlin, Heather, Christopher Uggen, and Amy Blackstone.</bold> Sexual Harassment, Workplace Authority, and the Paradox of Power.</td>
<td>625</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Melamed, David.</bold> See Linda D. Molm.</td>
<td>141</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Molm, Linda D., Monica M. Whitham, and David Melamed.</bold> Forms of Exchange and Integrative Bonds: Effects of History and Embeddedness</td>
<td>141</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Noonan, Mary C.</bold> See Phyllis L. F. Rippeyoung</td>
<td>244</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Pais, Jeremy.</bold> See Kyle Crowder.</td>
<td>325</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Parker, John N. and Edward J. Hackett.</bold> Hot Spots and Hot Moments in Scientific Collaborations and Social Movements</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Pfaff, Steven.</bold> See Hyojoung Kim.</td>
<td>188</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Powers, Daniel A.</bold> See Ryan K. Masters.</td>
<td>548</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Quillian, Lincoln.</bold> Segregation and Poverty Concentration: The Role of Three Segregations</td>
<td>354</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Rippeyoung, Phyllis L. F. and Mary C. Noonan.</bold> Is Breastfeeding Truly Cost Free? Income Consequences of Breastfeeding for Women</td>
<td>244</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Rivera, Lauren A.</bold> Hiring as Cultural Matching: The Case of Elite Professional Service Firms.</td>
<td>999</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Rosenfeld, Michael J. and Reuben J. Thomas.</bold> Searching for a Mate: The Rise of the Internet as a Social Intermediary.</td>
<td>523</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Ruef, Martin.</bold> Constructing Labor Markets: The Valuation of Black Labor in the U.S. South, 1831 to 1867.</td>
<td>970</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Sallaz, Jeffrey J.</bold> Politics of Organizational Adornment: Lessons from Las Vegas and Beyond</td>
<td>99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Schnittker, Jason.</bold> See Christopher Wildeman.</td>
<td>216</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Shibayama, Sotaro, John P. Walsh, and Yasunori Baba.</bold> Academic Entrepreneurship and Exchange of Scientific Resources: Material Transfer in Life and Materials Sciences in Japanese Universities.</td>
<td>804</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Shwed, Uri and Peter S. Bearman.</bold> Symmetry Is Beautiful.</td>
<td>1064</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Silva, Jennifer M.</bold> Constructing Adulthood in an Age of Uncertainty.</td>
<td>505</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Simko, Christina.</bold> Rhetorics of Suffering: September 11 Commemorations as Theodicy.</td>
<td>880</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Simons, Ronald L.</bold> See Callie Harbin Burt.</td>
<td>648</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>South, Scott J.</bold> See Kyle Crowder.</td>
<td>325</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Stark, David and Balazs Vedres.</bold> Political Holes in the Economy: The Business Network of Partisan Firms in Hungary.</td>
<td>700</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Stets, Jan E. and Michael J. Carter.</bold> A Theory of the Self for the Sociology of Morality</td>
<td>120</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Stone, Pamela.</bold> See Karen S. Lyness.</td>
<td>1023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Stuckler, David.</bold> See Patrick Hamm</td>
<td>295</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Swiss, Liam.</bold> See Kathleen M. Fallon.</td>
<td>380</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Telles, Edward.</bold> See René Flores.</td>
<td>486</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Thomas, Reuben J.</bold> See Michael J. Rosenfeld.</td>
<td>523</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Traag, V. A.</bold> See Jeroen Bruggeman.</td>
<td>1050</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Tsutsui, Kiyoteru.</bold> See Alwyn Lim.</td>
<td>69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Turney, Kristin.</bold> See Christopher Wildeman.</td>
<td>216</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Uggen, Christopher.</bold> See Heather McLaughlin.</td>
<td>625</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Uitermark, Justus.</bold> See Jeroen Bruggeman.</td>
<td>1050</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Vasi, Ion Bogdan and Brayden G. King.</bold> Social Movements, Risk Perceptions, and Economic Outcomes: The Effect of Primary and Secondary Stakeholder Activism on Firms’ Perceived Environmental Risk and Financial Performance.</td>
<td>573</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Vedres, Balazs.</bold> See David Stark.</td>
<td>700</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Villarreal, Andrés.</bold> Flawed Statistical Reasoning and Misconceptions about Race and Ethnicity.</td>
<td>495</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Viterna, Jocelyn.</bold> See Kathleen M. Fallon.</td>
<td>380</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Volscho, Thomas W. and Nathan J. Kelly.</bold> The Rise of the Super-Rich: Power Resources, Taxes, Financial Markets, and the Dynamics of the Top 1 Percent, 1949 to 2008.</td>
<td>679</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Walsh, John P.</bold> See Sotaro Shibayama.</td>
<td>804</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Whitham, Monica M.</bold> See Linda D. Molm.</td>
<td>141</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Wildeman, Christopher, Jason Schnittker, and Kristin Turney.</bold> Despair by Association? The Mental Health of Mothers with Children by Recently Incarcerated Fathers</td>
<td>216</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</array>
</body>
</article>