<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LRT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splrt</journal-id>
<journal-title>Lighting Research &amp; Technology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1477-1535</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0938</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1477153512443062</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1477153512443062</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and ocular safety of bright light therapy lamps</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Baczynska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1477153512443062"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>LLA</given-names></name><degrees>MSci</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1477153512443062">Laser and Optical Radiation Dosimetry Group, Health Protection Agency, Didcot, Oxfordshire, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1477153512443062">K Baczynska, Laser and Optical Radiation Dosimetry Group, Health Protection Agency, Didcot, Oxfordshire, OX11 0RQ, UK E-mail: <email>katarzyna.baczynska@hpa.org.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>45</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>40</fpage>
<lpage>51</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Chartered Institution of Building Services Engineers 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The optical radiation safety of various seasonal affective disorder (SAD) treatment lamps, sunrise simulators and daylight bulbs available on the UK market have been assessed using recognised guidelines. An analysis is included of the photometry of circadian entrainment by bright light therapy, with a justification for a melanopsin-based action spectrum for treatment efficacy. Parameters relating to both efficacy and phototoxicity risk, which are potentially relevant to bright light therapy treatment regimes, are considered. Unpredictable variations are highlighted which lead to the conclusion that several relevant photometric variables of treatment lamps need to be characterised to predict efficacy and potential hazards.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1477153512443062" sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title>
<p>Reduced light exposure in winter, due to shortening day lengths, leads to seasonal affective disorder (SAD) in sufferers and may cause related symptoms in others.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1477153512443062">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1477153512443062"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1477153512443062">3</xref></sup> Essentially, bright light therapy lamps for SAD treatment (SAD lamps), sunrise simulators and daylight bulbs are designed to mimic the brightness, morning light pattern and spectrum of natural daylight, respectively. Manufacturers promote the lamps for treatments to mitigate SAD, difficulty getting up in the mornings and/or low energy levels.</p>
<p>Assessing the treatment efficacy of the lamps is less intuitive but of greater clinical importance than their ability to mimic daylight visually. Factors that determine the appropriateness of a lamp include a number of optical characteristics of the lamp:
<list id="list1-1477153512443062" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>the light emitted in the spectral region which produces the desired biological effects;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the irradiance and distribution of the light on the retina;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>visual discomfort due to flicker, brightness or unnatural colour and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the potential to cause harm to the skin or the eye.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The term light as used in this paper refers to optical radiation penetrating within the ocular media, in the range of 380 nm to 1 mm.</p>
<p>Most bright light therapy lamps consist of fluorescent tubes, incandescent lamps or arrays of white light emitting diodes (LEDs). Lamp sizes vary and some have a diffusing screen or clear window which acts as a physical barrier, changes the directional distribution of emitted light and may also block ultraviolet radiation (UVR).</p>
<p>Where provided, users are usually encouraged not to stare at the lamps directly but to concentrate on another task on a nearby surface. Manufacturers recommend placing the lamp at a variety of distances, most often around 500 mm. Under these conditions, much of the light reaching the eyes is indirect and direct illumination is off-axis, and both are affected by the directional distribution of the emitted light.</p>
<p>Studies carried out using bright white light confirm that it can be used as an effective treatments for SAD and to mitigate related symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1477153512443062">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1477153512443062">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1477153512443062">4</xref></sup> Regular exposure to artificial light in the morning can compete with natural light for entrainment of the circadian cycle in healthy individuals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1477153512443062">5</xref></sup> Prolonged exposures to light in the evening and at night can delay melatonin production, sleep onset, reduce subsequent sleep quality and shift the circadian clock to a later phase.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1477153512443062">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1477153512443062">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1477153512443062">7</xref></sup> Circadian responses to light have been shown to be mediated by intrinsically photosensitive retinal ganglion cells, a sub-class of retinal ganglion cells that express the photopigment melanopsin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1477153512443062">8</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1477153512443062"><title>2. Methods</title>
<p>Guidelines issued by the International Commission on Non-Ionizing Radiation Protection (ICNIRP) set out a range of mechanisms for ocular tissue damage arising from non-laser optical radiation:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1477153512443062">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1477153512443062">10</xref></sup>
<list id="list2-1477153512443062" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>cataracts and corneal damage similar to sun burn caused by UVR;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>retinal damage initiated through photochemical reactions due to UVR and visible light;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>retinal burns due to heating from absorbed visible and infrared (IR) radiation and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>corneal and lens burns from IR radiation.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The lamps were assessed against the exposure limits from the guidelines for UVR and photochemical hazards based on direct spectral irradiance measurements. Over long durations, greater than 10 seconds, the blue light hazard (BLH) is the most restrictive retinal hazard for blue-rich white light sources,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1477153512443062">11</xref></sup> so the thermal damage thresholds (for retinal burns from heating alone) can be discounted. It would also be very unusual for a bright light therapy lamp to emit sufficient quantities of IR radiation to cause burns to the cornea, lens or skin.</p>
<p>The basic BLH exposure limit value (ELV) in the guidelines is calculated as the product of radiance and exposure duration, the radiance dose. However, in this study, a simplified effective irradiance limit was used instead. For long durations of exposure to the small sources (&lt;110 mrad), effective radiance for comparison with the BLH exposure limit is averaged over a solid angle of 0.01 sr to account for the increase of the retinal image size due to the eye’s movement. Such spatial averaging results in an effective irradiance limit of 1 Wċm<sup>−2</sup> for small sources. Use of this 1 Wċm<sup>−2</sup> effective irradiance limit for sources larger than 110 mrad overestimates BLH but can be used as a first step in simplified analysis: If the limit of 1 W · m<sup>−2</sup> is not exceeded, no detailed assessment is required.</p>
<p>Measurements were taken at a worst case scenario position directly opposite the lamp face. A distance of 200 mm was selected as the closest distance for which a prolonged focused retinal exposure is conceivable.</p>
<p>Spectral irradiance was measured with an open field of view. Without taking the source geometry into account, the 1 Wċm<sup>−2</sup> irradiance threshold could be unnecessarily restrictive for extended sources. For this reason, the angular subtense of each source, α<sub>s</sub>, was determined using photographs taken in the measurement plane at 500 mm. The side of each pixel subtended 0.28 mrad, corresponding to 0.14 mm. A reference photograph established distortions to be negligible, even for large sources, and demonstrated that the image resolution was equal to the theoretical pixel resolution.</p>
<p>The sources were classified as ‘small’ or ‘large’ relative to the angle, <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub>, defined in the ICNIRP guidelines, where <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub> represents the radiance averaging angle. For fixation (staring), this angle increases from a lower limit of 11 mrad to 110 mrad, depending on the exposure duration due to eye and head movements. All measured sources were large but some had individual elements that would appear as small sources, i.e. individual LEDs.</p>
<p>For small sources, <italic>α</italic><sub>s</sub> ≤ <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub>, the 1 Wċm<sup>−2</sup> threshold applies directly to the irradiance measured with an open field of view. In isolation, a single LED would be such a small source. The contribution of a single LED to the irradiance from an array could be calculated by dividing by the total number of LEDs.</p>
<p>For large sources, <italic>α</italic><sub>s</sub> &gt; <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub>, the 1 Wċm<sup>−2</sup> threshold applies to the ‘adjusted irradiance’, i.e. the irradiance estimated to be due only to light arriving from a restricted field of view with angular subtense <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub> at the eye. As <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub> depends on exposure duration, it was necessary to assume the most restrictive plausible value, corresponding to a shorter exposure of 30 minutes. Note that this results in an overestimate for <italic>γ</italic><sub>ph</sub> by a factor of two when varying exposure durations between 30 minutes and 2 hours. An upper limit for ‘adjusted irradiance’, <inline-formula id="ilm1-1477153512443062"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-1477153512443062"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, was calculated as follows:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1477153512443062"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-1477153512443062"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Adjusted irradiance</mml:mtext><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ph</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1477153512443062" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>E</italic><sub>B</sub> is the irradiance measured with an open field of view and weighted with the BLH action spectrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1477153512443062">Figure 1</xref>). A source of uniform radiance is assumed and inequality arises from off-axis angles where the cosine is &lt;1 for all extended sources.
<fig id="fig1-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Action spectra for illuminance <italic>V</italic>(<italic>λ</italic>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1477153512443062">12</xref></sup> circadian entrainment <italic>C</italic><sub>M</sub>(<italic>λ</italic>) and acute retinal photochemical hazard <italic>B</italic>(<italic>λ</italic>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1477153512443062">13</xref></sup> with normalised maximal sensitivity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The exact action spectrum for melatonin suppression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1477153512443062">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1477153512443062">7</xref></sup> and bright light therapy are occasionally considered different action spectra to melanopsin sensitivity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1477153512443062">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1477153512443062"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1477153512443062"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1477153512443062">17</xref></sup> In this study, instead, it is presumed that melanopsin sensitivity alone is responsible for circadian entrainment. This simplification is based partly on evidence that data from one of the original papers on melatonin suppression refitted with non-linear regression are consistent with a melanopsin template,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1477153512443062">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1477153512443062">19</xref></sup> with maximum irradiance sensitivity in vivo of 488 nm (Full width half maximum: FWHM = 84 nm).</p>
<p>There is currently no universally accepted standard for circadian-weighted irradiance; there is a lack of consensus about the action spectrum and two known competing definitions are different to the action spectrum, labelled as <italic>C</italic><sub>M</sub>(λ), illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1477153512443062">Figure 1</xref> (the M refers to melanopsin).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1477153512443062">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1477153512443062">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>Circadian irradiance in Wċm<sup>−2</sup> is defined for this paper as:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1477153512443062"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-1477153512443062"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Circadian irradiance</mml:mtext><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CM</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>390</mml:mn><mml:mtext>nm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>660</mml:mn><mml:mtext>nm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>M</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1477153512443062" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>f</italic>(<italic>λ</italic>) is the spectral irradiance of the source measured in Wċm<sup>−2</sup>ċnm<sup>−1</sup>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1477153512443062">Figure 1</xref> also shows the action spectra which are used to determine illuminance and BLH-weighted irradiance, <italic>V</italic>(<italic>λ</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1477153512443062">12</xref></sup> and <italic>B</italic>(<italic>λ</italic>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1477153512443062">13</xref></sup> respectively.</p>
<p>Spectral irradiance was also measured at a realistic and commonly recommended treatment distance, 500 mm, to assess efficacy and augment photochemical-hazard assessments which requires a comparison of relative levels of the photometric quantities given by the action spectra illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1477153512443062">Figure 1</xref>. Similar measurements were also made at angles of 30 and 60 degrees, i.e. with the lamp rotated around the vertical axis through the centre of the lamp face, to capture directional distribution characteristics.</p>
<p>All spectral irradiance measurements were carried out in a controlled laboratory environment using a portable spectroradiometer (Ocean Optics USB2000, working range 250 nm to 870 nm), coupled to an integrating sphere (Ocean Optics FOIS-1: Ocean Optics Inc., Dunedin, FL, USA). Calibration was performed with a 1 kW quartz tungsten halogen lamp, which was itself calibrated for spectral irradiance to the National Institute of Science and Technology traceable reference standard.</p>
<p>Stray light is a known limitation for CCD array spectrometers, particularly for UVR and, potentially, for short-wavelength visible light.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1477153512443062">21</xref></sup> To assess the impact of stray light on illuminance, circadian and BLH irradiance calculations, the irradiance data were compared with measurements made with a Bentham DMC150 scanning double-grating spectroradiometer (Bentham instruments, Reading, Berks, UK), also calibrated as detailed above, for a representative sample of lamps. Scans with 1 nm step confirmed that stray light effects were negligible in these calculations. Lamps appearing to have significant UVR were also measured with the double grating instrument, from 250 nm to 400 nm, for confirmation of the UVR hazard assessments.</p>
<p>Temporal modulation of the optical output, or flicker, was measured using a ThorLab high-speed silicon-based detector DET36A (Thorlabs Ltd, Ely, Cambs, UK) with a rise time of 20 ns, a National Instruments USB-6211 DAQ (National Instruments Corp., Austen, TX, USA) with a 100 kHz sampling rate and analysed using the standard definition for percent flicker (or modulation).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1477153512443062">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1477153512443062">23</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1477153512443062"><title>3. Selection, specifications and spectral characteristics of the lamps tested</title>
<p>The lamps were purchased via UK retailers, to include a range of design features lighting technologies as well as SAD treatment light boxes and systems, sunrise simulators and daylight bulbs. Details are set out in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1477153512443062">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table1-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Lamp manufacturers’ specifications and instructions relating to direct viewing of the lamps during therapy sessions when provided</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1477153512443062" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="6"><hr/><bold>LEDs and Incandescent (INC) lamps:</bold> LED4 resembles a sports cap, with 3 LEDs behind a diffuser mounted in front of each eye. All other LED and INC luminaires are small relative to typical treatment distance. LEDs 1-3 are LED arrays behind fairly clear screens and individual LEDs are visible. LED4 and INC 1 have contoured diffusers.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Details</td>
<td>View directly?</td>
<td>Maximum lux (at mm)</td>
<td>Duration, min (at mm)</td>
<td>Treatment distance, mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED1</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>2500 (500)</td>
<td>45<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1477153512443062">†</xref></sup> (500)</td>
<td>500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED2</td>
<td>Sunrise simulator alarm</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>6000 (n/a)</td>
<td>15-60 (n/a)</td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED3</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>1041 (500)</td>
<td>15-60<sup>‡</sup> (500)</td>
<td>300-600</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED4</td>
<td>SAD treatment visor</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>1000 (40)</td>
<td>60 (40)</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED5</td>
<td>Sunrise simulator alarm</td>
<td colspan="4" rowspan="2">These lamps provide too little light for SAD treatment. Distributors suggest INC1 is used as a complement to SAD therapy and LED5 as being helpful for SAD sufferers. We have not assessed these lesser claims.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>INC1</td>
<td>Sunrise simulator alarm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6"><bold>Fluorescent lamps (FLR):</bold> FLR4 and 5 are desk lamps with customised small diameter fluorescent tubes, in front of a reflector. Other FLR lamps are SAD treatment light boxes with diffusers. FLR2 is a smaller panel design.<hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><hr/></td>
<td><hr/>Details</td>
<td><hr/>View directly?</td>
<td><hr/>Maximum lux (at mm)</td>
<td><hr/>Duration, min (at mm)</td>
<td><hr/>Treatment distance, mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR1</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>OK to, but no need</td>
<td>10 000 (500)</td>
<td>60-120 (500)</td>
<td>500-1300</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR2</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>5500 (76)</td>
<td>20-45 (500)</td>
<td>500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR3</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>OK to, but no need</td>
<td>10 000 (200)</td>
<td>60-120 (500)</td>
<td>500-800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR4</td>
<td>SAD treatment desk lamp</td>
<td colspan="4">No details provided</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR5</td>
<td>SAD treatment desk lamp</td>
<td>OK to, but no need</td>
<td>10 000 (200)</td>
<td>60-120 (500)</td>
<td>500-800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR6</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>Occasional glances</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>30 (600) to 120 (at 200)</td>
<td>200-600</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR7</td>
<td>SAD treatment</td>
<td>Occasional glances</td>
<td>10 000 (380)</td>
<td>30 (550) or 60 (at 380)</td>
<td>380 or 550</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB1<sup>∼</sup></td>
<td>Fluorescent daylight bulb</td>
<td colspan="4" rowspan="5"><bold>Daylight bulbs (BULB):</bold> Bulbs 1 to 3 are compact fluorescent daylight lamps. 4 a and b differ only in tube length (both large diameter). These lamps not sold specifically for SAD treatment.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB2</td>
<td>Fluorescent daylight bulb</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB3</td>
<td>Fluorescent daylight bulb</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB4a</td>
<td>Fluor’t blue-enriched tube</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB4b</td>
<td>Fluor’t blue-enriched tube</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1477153512443062"><p><sup>†</sup>online information implies 30 minutes. <sup>‡</sup>information provided implies no upper limit to treatment frequency or duration. <sup>∼</sup>No evidence was found that BULB1 was sold based on health effects.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The spectra of white LEDs, fluorescent and incandescent lamps each have distinct characteristics as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1477153512443062">Figure 2</xref>. White LEDs typically combine a relatively narrow blue peak with broader emission from a phosphor across the green to red spectra. Fluorescent lamp spectra are dominated by narrow peaks from UVA through to red with a broad underlying phosphor. Incandescent lamp spectra are smooth and dominated by longer (red) wavelength emissions for a typical 2700 K lamp.
<fig id="fig2-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Typical spectra of seasonal affective disorder (SAD) lamps, sunrise simulators and daylight bulbs for light emitting diodes (LED3), fluorescent (FLR2), incandescent (INC1) lamps and the CIE standard illuminant D65,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1477153512443062">24</xref></sup> representing natural daylight. The spectra are normalised for equal illuminance, and plotted in 10-nm steps</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The CIE standard illuminant D65,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1477153512443062">24</xref></sup> based on the spectrum of daylight, is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1477153512443062">Figure 2</xref> for comparison. D65 is not a real illuminant, but <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1477153512443062">Figure 2</xref> shows that daylight is a more balanced spectrum than the artificial lighting from the lamps tested, although true daylight incorporates many narrow dips due to atmospheric absorption, absent from D65.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1477153512443062"><title>4. Results</title>
<p>Assessments based on ICNIRP guidelines confirmed that none of the lamps exceed UVR or BLH ocular exposure limits for a single prolonged exposure of up to 2 hours at 200 mm or further. However, the guidelines do not include limits to preclude the possibility of a risk due to chronic or repeated exposures, so a complete hazard assessment is not possible.</p>
<p>The 500 mm treatment distance, circadian irradiance and illuminance are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1477153512443062">Table 2</xref>. The variation in the circadian irradiance of the SAD treatment lamps was approximately a factor of 30. The variation of the illuminance of all the lamps was greater than a factor of 2000, reducing to a still significant factor of 50 when only the SAD treatment lamps were considered.
<table-wrap id="table2-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Biologically weighted irradiances at 500 mm and the adjusted efficacy and protection ratios of circadian irradiance to illuminance and BLH irradiances, respectively</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1477153512443062" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Lamp</th>
<th>Illuminance, <italic>E</italic><sub>V</sub> at 500 mm (lx)</th>
<th>Circadian irradiance, <italic>E</italic><sub>C</sub><sub>M</sub> at 500 mm (Wċm<sup>−2</sup>)</th>
<th>Efficacy ratio = a<sub>1</sub>ċ(<italic>E</italic><sub>C</sub><sub>M</sub> / <italic>E</italic><sub>V</sub>)</th>
<th>Protection ratio = a<sub>2</sub>ċ(<italic>E</italic><sub>C</sub><sub>M</sub>/<italic>E</italic><sub>B</sub>)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>LED1</td>
<td>1678</td>
<td>2.96</td>
<td>1.48</td>
<td>1.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED2</td>
<td>1598</td>
<td>2.26</td>
<td>1.19</td>
<td>0.86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED3</td>
<td>2448</td>
<td>2.73</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>1.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED4</td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>1.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LED5</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>n/a<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1477153512443062">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>n/a<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1477153512443062">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>INC1</td>
<td>228</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>1.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR1</td>
<td>10 585</td>
<td>5.91</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR2</td>
<td>225</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR3</td>
<td>2339</td>
<td>2.21</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>1.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR4</td>
<td>1080</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>1.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR5</td>
<td>2120</td>
<td>2.02</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>1.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR6</td>
<td>3543</td>
<td>3.15</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>1.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLR7</td>
<td>7419</td>
<td>7.36</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>1.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB1</td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>1.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB2</td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>1.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB3</td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>1.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BULB4a,b</td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>n/a<sup>a</sup></td>
<td>1.30</td>
<td>0.80</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1477153512443062"><label>a</label><p>Not comparable without further assumptions.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1477153512443062"><label>b</label><p>Other light sources would dominate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1477153512443062">Table 2</xref> also shows the calculated values of the efficacy and protection ratios and their mathematical definitions. The efficacy and protection ratios quantify how much circadian irradiance spectra of equal illuminance or BLH (phototoxic) irradiance contain, respectively. These ratios are adjusted by constant factors a<sub>1</sub> and a<sub>2</sub> to equal unity for a source of uniform spectral irradiance (a<sub>1</sub> = 840 lxċW<sup>−1</sup>ċm<sup>2</sup> and a<sub>2</sub> = 0.793 which is dimensionless). Higher efficacy and protection ratios relate to higher proportions of circadian irradiance and lower proportions of illuminance and BLH irradiance, respectively, which are all desirable features for an effective and safe therapy lamp. Note that BLH irradiance, <italic>E</italic><sub>B</sub>, is not shown, as without geometrical adjustment it could be misinterpreted.</p>
<p>The efficacy and protection ratios assess only the relative spectral characteristics of each lamp; complex interactions via source and retinal geometry are deliberately not included. This separation of geometry and spectra greatly simplifies the analysis and the use of normalisation constants a<sub>1</sub> and a<sub>2</sub> provides an intuitive meaning to the efficacy and protection ratio values. The efficacy ratio shows that most of the SAD lamps are richer in central photopic wavelength region, leading to higher illuminance, than the wavelengths required to achieve high circadian irradiance.</p>
<p>Due to the recommended exposure position, much of the light from the SAD lamps reaching the eyes is expected to be indirect or off-axis. Consequently, lamps with a broad directional distribution should provide a better source for therapy. To some extent, incorporating LEDs into a visor (fixed treatment position) gets around the need for a broad directional output, but otherwise, the LED lamps provide little off-axis illumination, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1477153512443062">Figure 3</xref>. Lamps with complex geometries were excluded from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1477153512443062">Figure 3</xref>.
<fig id="fig3-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Directional output at 0, 30 and 60 degrees around the vertical axis at 500 mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Some lamps incorporated diffusers through which the light source could not be clearly seen, whereas others had screens which were visually clear. The incandescent and fluorescent treatment lamps and sunrise simulators invariably incorporated a diffuser. The LED lamps, with the exception of the visor, did not feature a diffuser, leading to restricted directional output characteristics.</p>
<p>The directional distribution data show a partially unexpected result for FLR2, with axial (i.e. at 0°) irradiance levels not being the peak directional output. It appears that the grooved and wavy texture of the diffuser provides greater intensity at 30 degrees than normal to the diffuser surface.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1477153512443062">Figure 4</xref> shows the modulation, or percent flicker, of the optical emissions at 100 Hz. No lamp had appreciable modulation at other frequencies below 300 Hz. Although all the fluorescent lights contained modulation at frequencies above 1 kHz, this is not considered to be biologically relevant.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1477153512443062">25</xref></sup> Whilst there were LED and fluorescent lamps with modulation of less than 10% at 100 Hz, this was not achieved in the majority of cases. Note that the incandescent lamp modulation was &gt; 10% at 100 Hz.
<fig id="fig4-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Histogram of lamps with modulation at 100 Hz (flicker), split between LED, fluorescent and incandescent lamps</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1477153512443062"><title>5. Discussion</title>
<p>For bright light therapy there is a case to extend the scope of the BLH assessments beyond the single exposure scenario assumed by the ICNIRP guidelines. The guidelines use the simplifying assumption that dose is proportional to exposure duration, but this approximation must necessarily be less correct for doses accumulated over longer periods.</p>
<p>Time-dependency data on the Rhesus monkey<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1477153512443062">26</xref></sup> provides strong evidence of the likely form of time-dependency in humans, but the extent to which repeated daily exposures accumulate in humans has not been quantified. It would be extremely useful, clearly, to understand the human time-dependence of acute, and possibly chronic, photochemical damage and associated repair mechanisms. However, the spectral characteristics of the sources provide some relevant information which at least enables comparisons relating to lamp safety for repeated daily exposures to be drawn; the protection ratio indicates how efficiently spectra stimulate melanopsin relative to the accumulation of photochemical damage.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1477153512443062">Figure 5</xref> shows the distribution of the lamps in the two-dimensional space defined by the efficacy and protection ratios. Plotting the ‘efficacy-protection space’ is helpful to compare which lamps have higher efficacy per lux, as well as lower potential hazard, and to understand what can and cannot be achieved by real lamps.
<fig id="fig5-1477153512443062" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The ‘efficacy-protection space’ plots the efficacy ratio on the vertical axis against the protection ratio. Log scale ranges: protection ratio = 0.5 to 5; efficacy ratio = 0.3 to 3. D65 (1.06, 1.11).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153512443062-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The differences in the efficacy ratios imply that a range of stimuli, i.e. <italic>E</italic><sub>C</sub><sub>M</sub>, is possible with lamps of equal illuminance, <italic>E</italic><sub>V</sub>. The differences in the protection ratios show a range of stimuli is possible with equal values of BLH-weighted irradiance, <italic>E</italic><sub>B</sub>. Theoretically, reduced treatment times may be possible with lamps higher up the chart without increasing potential phototoxicity. Reduced potential phototoxicity lies on the right side for equal levels of illuminance.</p>
<p>In general, blue-enriched lamps have a greater efficacy ratio, e.g. LED1, BULB4a and b. In contrast, blue-enrichment does not lead predictably to a higher or lower protection ratio. For example, LED1 emits relatively long wavelength blue light, whereas BULB4a and b emissions are enriched with shorter wavelength blue light, and this noticeably affects their protection ratios. BULB4a and b produce the lowest value of this ratio for any lamp and LED1 the highest, with the exception of INC1.</p>
<p>The spectra of lamps LED2, BULB4a and b give low protection ratios, indicating that potentially harmful wavelengths of blue light are over-represented. These outlying points can be easily identified towards the left of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1477153512443062">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
<p>For blackbody radiation, there is a pronounced relationship, where higher efficacy ratios are achieved at the cost of lower protection ratio values. The clustered fluorescent sources (diamonds) appear to loosely follow a similar pattern and are below or on the blackbody locus. For white LEDs (triangles), a larger sample would be needed to infer a relationship. Incandescent sources and daylight conditions lie close to the blackbody locus, and single colour LEDs would lie close to the narrowband locus.</p>
<p>One factor for both fluorescent lamps and LEDs which affects their position in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1477153512443062">Figure 5</xref> is the proportion of emissions coming from excitory wavelengths (short wavelengths) to phosphor emissions (longer wavelengths). The exact position of the LEDs mainly depends on the wavelength of the blue peak and the proportion of emissions from the phosphor.</p>
<p>The shaded ‘trade-off area relates to spectra that theoretically perform better (towards the top right) than blackbody radiation, including daylight, but less well, inevitably, than monochromatic light. Between the limits D65 (<italic>circa</italic> 6500 K) and the incandescent lamp (<italic>circa</italic> 2700 K), illuminants close to the blackbody locus provide white light. Conversely, illuminants close to the monochromatic limits between 488 nm and 520 nm have the highest combinations of efficacy and protection ratios but provide strongly coloured light. For an ‘ideal’ lamp spectrum, there may be a trade-off between the unnatural appearance and the improved performance of narrow band spectra.</p>
<p>Relatively few of the lamps lie within the area of ‘trade-off’ between incandescent (blackbody) and narrowband sources. Although LED technology potentially provides preferable emission spectra, the directional emission distributions of arrays were shown to be narrow in the absence of a diffuser. Consequently, a diffuser is considered to be an important feature and reduces the direct glare and hotspots from the lamps.</p>
<p>Modulation below 160 Hz, or flicker, was observed only at 100 Hz. Flicker is particularly relevant in peripheral vision,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1477153512443062">27</xref></sup> and users are recommended not to stare directly at the lamp but by implication keep it in their peripheral vision. Despite this and as noted in our results, not all fluorescent and LED sources are flicker-free.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1477153512443062" sec-type="Conclusion"><title>6. Conclusion</title>
<p>Although it has been demonstrated that the lamp emissions did not exceed the ELVs from the ICNIRP guidelines, the ocular safety of these lamps for repeated daily exposures could not be confirmed. In all likelihood, the safety margins from the guidelines together with the simplifying assumptions used in the assessments may be sufficient to ensure these lamps can safely be used as intended. However, due to the existing limits of knowledge of photochemical ocular hazards, the effect of repeated exposures as well as the potential for chronic damage cannot be quantified, so the possibility that the use of bright light therapy lamps may contribute to retinal damage cannot be entirely ruled out.</p>
<p>The ‘efficacy-protection space’ provides a hazard assessment tool for repeated exposures, but it cannot be considered as a comprehensive safety assessment. There are uncertainties relating to the action spectra of circadian entrainment and chronic photochemical hazard mechanisms, and revised versions of the ‘efficacy-protection space’ would apply for any departures from the action spectra used in this paper.</p>
<p>Many of the differences in spectra between the lamps, and in particular the efficacy and protection ratios, were unpredictable from the information supplied by the manufacturers, and often limited information was available prior to purchase. No lamp specifications contained information about the potential for bright blue light to cause phototoxicity.</p>
<p>Medical advice about bright light treatment therapy based on evidence of effectiveness and ocular safety of the specific lamp or device can only be achieved efficiently if the spectral, flicker and directional outputs of a lamp are characterised. As full information is not currently available, medical advice will have limitations; it could not be reasonably expected to allow for the unknowns of human time-dependence of acute, and possibly chronic, photochemical damage and associated repair mechanisms.</p>
<p>Summarising the key results:
<list id="list3-1477153512443062" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>No lamp presents a risk of over-exposure to optical radiation, at a distance of 200 mm or greater, when assessed according to ICNIRP guidelines for a 2-hour exposure or shorter.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The ‘efficacy-protection space’ diagram can be used to asses the spectra emitted by lamps for the purpose of bright light therapy. Using the assumed action spectra for circadian effects and potential phototoxicity:
<list id="list4-1477153512443062" list-type="roman-lower">
<list-item><p>There are significant unpredictable variations in the performance of the lamps.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The performance difference between the LED lamps (n = 5) is significant and the directional distribution of light at 30 degrees is much lower than 10% for the LED panel arrays (n = 4). However, luminaires containing suitably chosen white LEDs have the potential to provide good efficacy and protection ratios.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fluorescent lamps provide a good directional distribution but poor efficacy and/or poor protection ratios. None of the fluorescent lamps (n = 11) out-perform the blackbody locus for efficacy and protection ratios.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The sole incandescent lamp has by far the best protection ratio of all the lamps, but a low efficacy ratio.</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>One LED had 100% flicker at 100 Hz and the majority of lamps had 100 Hz flicker greater than 10%, regardless of the lamp type, design or purpose.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>It would be useful to have further data on the additivity of the acute BLH mechanism in humans, and that of possible chronic damage mechanisms. It would also be useful to understand the additivity of bright light exposures for circadian entrainment and a more complete understanding of the role of rods and cones in humans.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec7-1477153512443062"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This paper is work commissioned by the National Institute for Health Research. The views expressed in this paper are those of the authors and not necessarily the NHS, the National Institute for Health Research or the Department of Health.</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors thank Marina Khazova at the Health Protection Agency (Chilton, Oxon, UK) for many enlightening discussions and valuable contributions to this paper and Dr Kudret Yelden at the Royal Hospital of Neurodisability (Putney, London, UK) for kind permission to use our measurement data for their ten lamps (represented by lamp FLR5) in this paper.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1477153512443062"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefler</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Emens</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The circadian basis of winter depression</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Science USA</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>103</volume>(<issue>19</issue>): <fpage>7414</fpage>–<lpage>7419</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1477153512443062"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Newsome</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehr</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Seasonal affective disorder. A description of the syndrome and preliminary findings with light therapy</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1477153512443062"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Baczynska K, O’Hagan J, Khazova M. <italic>Assessment of the optical radiation safety of seasonal affective disorder lamps</italic>: <italic>Proceedings of the Health Protection Conference 2009</italic></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1477153512443062"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bright artificial light treatment of a manic-depressive patient with a seasonal mood cycle</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Psychiatry</source> <year>1982</year>; <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1496</fpage>–<lpage>1498</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1477153512443062"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Vetter C, Juda M, Lang D, Wojtysiak A, Roenneberg T. Blue-enriched office light competes with natural light as a zeitgeber. <italic>Scandinavian Journal of Work Environment and Health</italic> 2011; 37(5): 437–445</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1477153512443062"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanifin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Greeson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollag</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Action spectrum for melatonin regulation in humans: evidence for a novel circadian photoreceptor</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>6405</fpage>–<lpage>6412</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1477153512443062"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thapan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Arendt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skene</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An action spectrum for melatonin suppression: evidence for a novel non-rod, non-cone photoreceptor system in humans</article-title>. <source>Journal of Physiology</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>535</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1477153512443062"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phototransduction by retinal ganglion cells that set the circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>295</volume>(<issue>5557</issue>): <fpage>1070</fpage>–<lpage>1073</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1477153512443062"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>International Commission on Non-Ionizing Radiation Protection (ICNIRP)</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines on limits of exposure to broad-band incoherent optical radiation (0.38 to 3 mm)</article-title>. <source>Health Physics</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1477153512443062"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>International Commission on Non-Ionizing Radiation Protection (ICNIRP)</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines on limits of exposure to ultraviolet radiation of wavelengths between 180 nm and 400 nm (incoherent optical radiation)</article-title>. <source>Health Physics</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>87</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1477153512443062"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sliney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolbarsht</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Safety with Lasers and Other Optical Sources</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1477153512443062"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Commission International de l’Eclairage (CIE). <italic>The Basis of Physical Photometry</italic>. CIE Publication 18.2. Paris: CIE, 1983</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1477153512443062"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Commission International de l’Eclairage. <italic>CIE Collection in Photobiology and Photochemistry 2000 Blue-light Photochemical Retinal Hazard</italic>. CIE Publication 138/1. Vienna: CIE, 2000</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1477153512443062"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revell</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Skene</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Light-induced melatonin suppression in humans with polychromatic and monochromatic light</article-title>. <source>Chronobiology International</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1125</fpage>–<lpage>1137</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1477153512443062"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mainster</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Blue-blocking IOLs decrease photoreception without providing significant photoprotection</article-title>. <source>Survey of Ophthalmology</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>55</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1477153512443062"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DIN. <italic>Optical Radiation Physics and Illuminating Engineering – Part 100: Non-visual Effects of Ocular Light on Human Beings – Quantities, Symbols and Action Spectra</italic>. Berlin: Lighting Technology Standards Committee (FNL) in the DIN, 2009: 16</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1477153512443062"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lall</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Revell</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Momiji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Enezi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Altimus</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guler</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allender</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hankins</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distinct contributions of rod, cone, and melanopsin photoreceptors to encoding irradiance</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1477153512443062"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Peirson S. Personal communication. <italic>Relating that Original Data on the Melatonin-Suppression Action Spectrum (from Reference 6) had been Refitted and Shown to be Consistent with a Melanopsin Action Spectrum with Maximal Sensitivity to 476 nm at the Retina</italic>. 2011</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1477153512443062"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hankins</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The primary visual pathway in humans is regulated according to long-term light exposure through the action of a non-classical photopigment</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1477153512443062"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiro</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bierman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullough</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Circadian light</article-title>. <source>Journal of Circadian Rhythms</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1477153512443062"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumthaler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stray light correction for solar measurements using array spectrometers</article-title>. <source>Review of Scientific Instruments</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>80</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>096108</fpage>–<lpage>096108</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1477153512443062"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poplawski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Proposing measures of flicker in the low frequencies for lighting applications</article-title>. <source>Leukos</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1477153512443062"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khazova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Hagan</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Optical radiation emissions from compact fluorescent lamps</article-title>. <source>Radiation Protection Dosimetry</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>131</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1477153512443062"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Commission Internationale de l’Eclairage (CIE). <italic>Colorimetry – Part 2: Standard Illuminants for Colorimetry</italic>. CIE Standard S014-2/E. Vienna: CIE, 2006</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1477153512443062"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimmo-Smith</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedocs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fluorescent lighting, headaches and eyestrain</article-title>. <source>Lighting Research and Technology</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1477153512443062"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griess</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blankenstein</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Additivity and repair of actinic retinal lesions</article-title>. <source>Investigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1477153512443062"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachenmayr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brettel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The peripheral critical flicker frequency</article-title>. <source>Vision Research</source> <year>1979</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1019</fpage>–<lpage>1023</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>