<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwmr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Waste Manag Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Waste Management &amp; Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-242X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-3669</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734242X10387012</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734242X10387012</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Investigating factors influencing construction waste management efforts in developing countries: an experience from Thailand</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Manowong</surname><given-names>Ektewan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0734242X10387012">Department of Civil Engineering, Bremen University of Applied Sciences, Bremen, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0734242X10387012">Ektewan Manowong, Department of Civil Engineering, Bremen University of Applied Sciences, Bremen, Germany Email: <email>emanowong@ext.hs-bremen.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>56</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>7</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>19</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© International Solid Waste Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Solid Waste Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Rapid economic growth and urbanization in developing countries lead to extensive construction activities that generate a large amount of waste. A challenge is how to manage construction waste in the most sustainable way. In the developing world, research on construction waste management is scarce and such academic knowledge needs to be responsive to actual practices in the industry in order to be implemented. As construction projects involve a number of participants and stakeholders, their participation and commitment can have a major influence on the goals of green and sustainable construction for urban development. This study provides a significant step in conducting a very first research of this kind in Thailand by aiming to investigate the level of construction stakeholders’ commitment as well as the achievement of construction waste management in order to improve short-term practices and to establish a long-term strategic construction waste management plan. In this study, a structural equation model was employed to investigate the influence of factors that are related to environmental aspects, social aspects, and economic aspect of construction waste management. Concern about health and safety was found to be the most significant and dominant influence on the achievement of sustainable construction waste management. Other factors affecting the successful management of construction waste in Thai construction projects were also identified. It is perceived that this study has potential to contribute useful guidelines for practitioners both in Thailand and other developing countries with similar contexts.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Construction waste management</kwd>
<kwd>developing countries</kwd>
<kwd>structural equation modelling</kwd>
<kwd>sustainable construction</kwd>
<kwd>Thailand</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0734242X10387012" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Construction industry has been found to be a major generator of waste and pollution. Waste from construction activities significantly pollutes the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X10387012">Shen et al. 2004</xref>). In developed countries, construction waste management (CWM) has already been an important aspect that is included in a project management plan. However, in developing countries such as Thailand, CWM practices are still found to be insufficient and inappropriate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD 2007</xref>). Construction waste has been largely disposed of at both public and private landfills. When the dumping sites become inadequate to accommodate a higher volume of construction waste, heavy and bulky waste from construction and demolition sites becomes a waste stream requiring further attention. As a consequence of a lack of landfill space, the amount of construction waste illegally dumped in public places has increased, causing social and environmental problems to the local communities.</p>
<p>In developing countries, research on the social, environmental, and economic impacts of construction waste management has not been widely conducted. Meanwhile, in developed countries, extensive research on construction waste has mainly focused on the types of construction waste and work practices, processes and technologies that contribute to the generation of waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0734242X10387012">Yost &amp; Lund 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X10387012">Shen et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X10387012">Haggar 2007</xref>). However, the importance of people’s willingness to change their attitudes and behaviour pertaining to waste generation, collection and disposal has not been researched to the same extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0734242X10387012">Teo &amp; Loosemore 2001</xref>). Hence, in the present study, the participation and commitment of construction stakeholders are regarded as important drivers for construction management. The challenges in managing construction waste are therefore to actively identify what, where, when, and how to do/deal with the generated waste. Furthermore, it is necessary to specify who needs to be engaged in the CWM process.</p>
<p>As there has been very little research on construction waste management in Thailand, this study aimed to take an important step to initiate this kind of research in order to raise awareness on waste management among construction stakeholders within the country. The results and findings of this research are targeted to reflect useful information and direct perspectives from construction operatives, which can be adapted and adopted for further improvement of construction waste management. It is also expected that this paper will contribute and integrate knowledge from academic research to practical implementations in the construction industry with specific interest in the achievement of green and sustainable construction. The influences of three sustainability aspects on the project stakeholders’ efforts on construction waste management were investigated by using the structural equation modelling (SEM) technique. The finding of influential factors and their inter-relationships provide useful insights for establishing effective CWM strategies in Thailand and other developing countries with similar contexts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0734242X10387012">
<title>Construction waste management and sustainable development</title>
<p>The construction industry can contribute to society by considering the needs of sustainable development from the planning to construction and finally dismantling of buildings. This includes initiating and implementing a construction waste management scheme, which leads to minimization of raw material consumption, waste reduction, less emission, and cost-savings from utilizing the by-products from waste materials generated during construction activities. By-products have to achieve good environmental quality requirements and, at the same time, should be suitable with regard to economic and technical requirements. The ideology of sustainable development calls for a balanced drive to achieve economic, social and environmental goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0734242X10387012">WHO 2005</xref>). It aims to protect the environment, reduce pollution, conserve natural resources, and safeguard the quality of life of all people. As such, the concept of green and sustainable construction is attractive for creating a healthy built environment while balancing the economic, social, and environmental benefits. However, the promotion of co-benefits of CWM is affected by a lack of awareness, inadequate capacity to quantify co-benefits in CWM activities, and difference in priorities or interests of the construction sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X10387012">Goco 2008</xref>). As suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X10387012">Chung &amp; Lo (2003)</xref> the social acceptability and equity are crucial because they refer to how the local community is receptive and supportive to the waste management options currently in use.</p>
<p>Environmental sustainability, the ability to maintain the qualities valued in the physical environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0734242X10387012">CES 2006</xref>), is an important issue for the management of the construction industry. This is a main reason why the sustainable development concept is increasingly recognized and why the general public became more concerned of environmental impacts related to construction activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X10387012">Cole 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0734242X10387012">Tam et al. 2006a</xref>) so that systematic management of construction waste and pollution is increasingly demanded from urban construction projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X10387012">Chen et al. 2000</xref>). Furthermore, consideration of the social sustainability that ensures a better quality of life for the people today and for future generations is also essential. Social acceptability and equity reflects how the community is receptive and supportive of the waste management options currently in use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X10387012">Chung &amp; Lo 2003</xref>). When considering the social impacts in construction industry, the issue of health and safety is largely associated with construction waste management procedures because construction workers and the general public are subject to risks caused by insufficient management of construction waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0734242X10387012">Muller &amp; Schienberg 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X10387012">Cole 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X10387012">Klang et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X10387012">Shen et al. 2004</xref>). Furthermore, in terms of economic sustainability, it is essential to understand the economic growth, which is only sustainable when the quality of life and the environment are simultaneously improved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0734242X10387012">NHS PASA 2008</xref>). As such, this requires a mechanism that balances the interests of gaining both economic and socio-environmental benefits for all stakeholders.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X10387012">McDonald &amp; Smithers (1998)</xref> suggested that the construction industry, as a main polluter, should take a role as major contributor in managing environmental pollution by bringing new ways of construction practices that are environmentally and economically efficient e.g. with the effective CWM plan. In regards of sustainable development, such CWM plan should also be socially-accepted. A concept of green and sustainable construction (GSC) then emerged. The GSC concept combines the ideas of green building and sustainable construction. Green building practices create structures by employing environmentally responsible and resource-efficient processes throughout the life-cycle (design, construction, operation, maintenance, renovation, and deconstruction) of a building (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0734242X10387012">EPA 2010</xref>) while the sustainable construction concept addresses more comprehensively the sustainability issues (social, economic, environmental, and ecological concerns) as they are involved with not only the environmental concerns but also the health aspects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X10387012">Kibert 2008</xref>). GSC is then believed to bring environmental, social, and economic benefits since it creates a healthy built environment based on resource-efficient, ecologically-based principles.</p>
<p>To meet the goals of voluntary corporate social responsibility (CSR), legislated environmental impact assessment (EIA), and the economic interests, it is necessary for the construction industry to recognize and initiate to overcome construction waste problems by bringing new ways of construction practices that are socially acceptable, economically viable, and environmentally sustainable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X10387012">McDonald &amp; Smithers 1998</xref>). However, sustainable construction can hardly be achieved without the construction stakeholders’ strong efforts for CWM. Previous researches found that people’s awareness, attitudes and perceptions towards CWM may have influence on their behaviour and decision making regarding waste handling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0734242X10387012">Lingard et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0734242X10387012">Teo &amp; Loosemore 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0734242X10387012">Tam et al. 2006b</xref>). The construction stakeholders’ awareness and efforts on CWM should therefore be investigated and organized to maximize the probability of achieving practical and effective CWM.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0734242X10387012" sec-type="methods">
<title>Research methodology</title>
<sec id="section4-0734242X10387012">
<title>Theoretical framework, conceptual model and research hypotheses</title>
<p>As the sustainable construction essentially relies on the management of waste and pollution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X10387012">EA 2008</xref>), the achievement of GSC was influenced by the measurement of CWM efforts. It is perceived that the CWM efforts are influenced by the environmental sustainability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X10387012">Chen et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X10387012">Cole 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0734242X10387012">Tam et al. 2006a</xref>), social sustainability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X10387012">Cole 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X10387012">Chung &amp; Lo 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X10387012">Shen et al. 2004</xref>), and economic sustainability variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0734242X10387012">Wong &amp; Yip, 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0734242X10387012">Duran et al. 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>The main objectives of this research are to:</p>
<list id="list1-0734242X10387012" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>explore the current practices of construction waste management in Thailand;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>investigate the influence of sustainability factors on the construction waste management efforts and the achievement of green and sustainable construction;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>contribute research results and findings to the construction operatives and waste management practitioners in Thailand and, when applicable, in other developing countries.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Moreover, the studied literatures provided a theoretical framework for this research and a conceptual model for sustainable construction waste management was developed, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X10387012">Figure 1</xref>, comprising the constructs of sustainability cores and showing their hypothesized influences on construction waste management efforts towards the achievement of the prospective GSC practices.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Conceptual model for sustainable construction waste management.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The following research hypotheses were defined.</p>
<list id="list2-0734242X10387012" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>H1: The environmental sustainability concern has a direct causal effect on CWM efforts and indirect causal effects on green and sustainable construction as mediated by CWM efforts.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>H2: The public health and safety has a direct causal effect on CWM efforts and indirect causal effects on green and sustainable construction as mediated by CWM efforts.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>H3: The gender equality has a direct causal effect on CWM efforts and indirect causal effects on green and sustainable construction as mediated by CWM efforts.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>H4: The economic incentives have a direct causal effect on CWM efforts and indirect causal effects on green and sustainable construction as mediated by CWM efforts.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>H5: The CWM efforts have a direct causal effect on green and sustainable construction.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0734242X10387012">
<title>The structural equation modelling and research variables</title>
<p>The structural equation modelling (SEM) technique was employed to test the hypothesized model in order to analyse the influences and relationships of factors affecting the success of construction waste management practices. General SEM involves two inter-related procedural components; a measurement component and a structural component (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X10387012">Byrne 2001</xref>). The measurement component specifies how latent variables are measured in terms of observed variables. The structural component expresses relationship among the latent variables. The observed variables provided data that can be directly measured such as numeric responses to a rating scale item on a questionnaire. On the contrary, latent variables are under the researchers’ interest but cannot be directly observed. To measure latent variables, it is necessary to construct a model to express latent variables in terms of the observed variables. Hence, the SEM technique enables the development of a causal indicator model in which a latent theoretical construct of interest is represented by measured variables.</p>
<p>The variables in the three constructs of sustainability are moderator variables that induce change in the relationship between the independent and dependent variables. Based on this, a model was constructed to investigate the influence of environmental, social, and economic sustainability on the CWM efforts towards the prospective GSC goals. The variables in each constructs measured in the study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X10387012">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Research Latent Constructs and Observed Variables</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0734242X10387012" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Latent constructs</th>
<th align="left">Code</th>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="left">References</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Environmental sustainability (ES)</td>
<td>ES1</td>
<td>Awareness</td>
<td>Raising awareness on environmental impact</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES2</td>
<td>Waste</td>
<td>Waste generation and management (minimization, generation, source evaluation, collection, storage, separation, treatment, transportation, and disposal)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X10387012">Donatiello (2001)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES3</td>
<td>Air</td>
<td>Air quality and management (provision and density of air pollutant monitoring devices)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X10387012">Donatiello (2001)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES4</td>
<td>Water</td>
<td>Water consumption and wastewater treatment. Water quality and water contamination</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X10387012">Donatiello (2001)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0734242X10387012">UNCSD (2005)</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES5</td>
<td>Land</td>
<td>Land degradation due to construction activities</td>
<td>UNEP RRC.AP (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES6</td>
<td>Noise</td>
<td>Noise control (monitoring device &amp; noise barriers)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X10387012">Donatiello (2001)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES7</td>
<td>Energy</td>
<td>Rate of energy (fuel/gas/electricity) consumption</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X10387012">Donatiello (2001)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES8</td>
<td>Green areas</td>
<td>Availability and density of public green area</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X10387012">Donatiello (2001)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ES9</td>
<td>Resource recovery</td>
<td>Policy and rate of recoverable natural resources</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0734242X10387012">Phillips (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Health &amp; safety (HS)</td>
<td>HS1</td>
<td>Awareness</td>
<td>Activities for raising awareness on H&amp;S issues</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS2</td>
<td>Accident</td>
<td>Rigorous safety measures &amp; procedures to prevent occurrence of the accidents</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS3</td>
<td>Casualty</td>
<td>Rigorous safety measures &amp; procedures to prevent site deaths and casualties</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS4</td>
<td>Health condition</td>
<td>Frequency of illness related to construction activities</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0734242X10387012">ILO (2003)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS5</td>
<td>Waste handling</td>
<td>Procedures for safely handling construction waste</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X10387012">Shen et al. (2004)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS6</td>
<td>Training</td>
<td>Safety training provided</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS7</td>
<td>Health risks</td>
<td>Exposure to risks from construction waste</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X10387012">Cooper (2008)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS8</td>
<td>Quality of life</td>
<td>On-site welfare, community wellbeing, and access to healthcare</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>HS9</td>
<td>Mental health</td>
<td>Relationship within family &amp; relationship among groups of project stakeholders</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X10387012">Ageton et al. 2007</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender equality (GE)</td>
<td>GE1</td>
<td>Gender awareness</td>
<td>Emphasis on gender equality in waste management</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0734242X10387012">Hemmati &amp; Gardiner (2002)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GE2</td>
<td>Respect</td>
<td>Respect among gender of the workforce exists</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0734242X10387012">Miles &amp; Niethammer (2009)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GE3</td>
<td>Diversity</td>
<td>Diversity and biological differences in workplace and society is understood</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0734242X10387012">WEF (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GE4</td>
<td>Fairness</td>
<td>Provided with equality/fairness to receive consideration, to express opinion, and to decide</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GE5</td>
<td>Employment</td>
<td>Rate of employment in the working sector</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0734242X10387012">Russell (2002)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GE6</td>
<td>Participation</td>
<td>Rate of participation in CWM activities</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0734242X10387012">Russell (2002)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GE7</td>
<td>Susceptibility</td>
<td>Susceptibility on waste handling</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X10387012">Cooper (2008)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Economic incentives (EC)</td>
<td>EC1</td>
<td>Cost-effectiveness</td>
<td>Cost-effectiveness of CWM implementation</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>EC2</td>
<td>Expenditures</td>
<td>Project cost reduction (financial incentives)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>EC3</td>
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>Revenue generation from construction waste with good quality for reuse &amp; recycle</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X10387012">Klundert &amp; Anschutz (1999)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>EC4</td>
<td>Recycling interests</td>
<td>Regulatory incentives that attract and encourage using recycled material and making CWM efforts for environmentally sustainable construction</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>EC5</td>
<td>Willingness</td>
<td>Willingness to initiate CWM plan and providing budget to carry out CWM scheme</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Waste management efforts (WME)</td>
<td>WME1</td>
<td>Awareness</td>
<td>Level of awareness on CWM’s importance, effects and potential for 3Rs</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X10387012">Klundert &amp; Anschutz (1999)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME2</td>
<td>Attitude</td>
<td>Attitude &amp; perception of stakeholders have effects on their behaviour in CWM implementation. High demand of good quality waste can change consumers’ attitude</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga (2006)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0734242X10387012">Teo &amp; Loosemore (2001)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME3</td>
<td>Knowledge</td>
<td>Adequate knowledge, understanding and education on CWM’s benefits and practices</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME4</td>
<td>Communication</td>
<td>Development of channels for communication</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. (2006)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME5</td>
<td>CWM guidelines</td>
<td>Availability of instruction &amp; procedures &amp; training for 3Rs operations</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME6</td>
<td>Participation channels</td>
<td>Availability &amp; encouragement of participation channels in CWM activities</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME7</td>
<td>CWM policy</td>
<td>Available CWM strategic policy &amp; plan that drive CWM efforts</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X10387012">Kulatunga et al. (2006)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME8</td>
<td>CWM system</td>
<td>Availability and compatibility of CWM system that facilitate CWM efforts</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME9</td>
<td>Satisfaction</td>
<td>Stakeholders’ satisfaction with availability of CWM plan</td><td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME10</td>
<td>Encouragement</td>
<td>Level of encouragement induced by the established CWM plan</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME11</td>
<td>Alertness</td>
<td>Relevant stakeholders’ alertness and adaptation for changes in their working behaviour</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME12</td>
<td>Legislation</td>
<td>Law &amp; regulation supporting CWM enforcement</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME13</td>
<td>Waste reduction</td>
<td>Level of construction operatives’ effort to reduce waste</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME14</td>
<td>Waste storage</td>
<td>Availability of storage area for construction waste</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME15</td>
<td>Waste transportation</td>
<td>Transportation of construction waste</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME16</td>
<td>Waste separation</td>
<td>Efficiency of construction waste sorting and separation</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME17</td>
<td>Waste disposal</td>
<td>Appropriateness of management/disposal process for construction waste</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME18</td>
<td>Technology readiness</td>
<td>Readiness to employ technology for CWM</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME19</td>
<td>Budget</td>
<td>Financial support from government and relevant organizations</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>WME20</td>
<td>Co-operation</td>
<td>Co-operation/co-ordination between government and private sectors</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X10387012">PCD (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Green &amp; sustainable construction (GSC)</td>
<td>GSC1</td>
<td>Awareness</td>
<td>Society becomes more aware of green/sustainable construction to increases construction efficiency</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC2</td>
<td>Stakeholders development</td>
<td>Stakeholders attain career development through capacity building</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC3</td>
<td>Energy efficiency</td>
<td>Improvement of energy consumption during on-site, off-site and operational activities</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC4</td>
<td>Material consumption</td>
<td>Improved efficiency of building materials and components via new technology</td>
<td>BERR(2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC5</td>
<td>Water consumption</td>
<td>Reduction of wastewater and increased usage of recycled water</td>
<td>BERR (2007)
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC6</td>
<td>Building standards</td>
<td>Design of buildings meet environmental standards, satisfy the occupants, and adaptable to new uses</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X10387012">Haggar (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC7</td>
<td>Site waste generation</td>
<td>Improved on-site, off-site and operational activities that prevent/minimize CW generation</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC8</td>
<td>Site planning</td>
<td>Improved site planning to reduce waste</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC9</td>
<td>Manufacturing</td>
<td>Improve manufacturing process for construction materials manufacturing to reduce environmental impacts</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X10387012">Haggar (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC10</td>
<td>Procurement &amp; logistics</td>
<td>Improved procedures of construction materials supplies and transportation</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC11</td>
<td>Air quality</td>
<td>Air pollution prevention and control</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC12</td>
<td>Water quality</td>
<td>Control and remedy of problems related to water pollution</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC13</td>
<td>Land use</td>
<td>Land degradation problems caused by construction activities</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X10387012">Dixon et al. (2007)</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC14</td>
<td>Workers’ health and safety</td>
<td>Health insurance provided to workers</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC15</td>
<td>Public health &amp; safety</td>
<td>Provision of healthcare and safety precautions</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC16</td>
<td>CESR</td>
<td>Organization’s practices on corporate environmental &amp; social responsibility (CESR)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X10387012">HSE (2007)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC17</td>
<td>Corporate governance</td>
<td>Regular monitoring and reports on the status and performance of construction industry’s initiatives towards sustainability</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC18</td>
<td>Traffic problems</td>
<td>Traffic problems caused by the physical presence and uses of the built facilities leading to health problems as well as wasteful energy consumption</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0734242X10387012">Uher (1999)</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GSC19</td>
<td>Profitability</td>
<td>Profitable construction procedures</td>
<td>BERR (2007)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The factors in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X10387012">Table 1</xref> were selected based on their theoretical relevance and practical potentials to reflect situational and technical problems of CWM in Thailand, where a standard CWM system is not yet established and construction waste recycling is not yet available (PCD 2007). These grouped factors are comprised of lower-level variables that represent actual problems occurred during field practices of CWM. The analysis results will reveal which of these factors are having high, moderate, or low influence on the stakeholders’ effort on construction waste management as well as those facilitating Thailand’s prospective achievement of sustainable construction.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0734242X10387012">
<title>Data collection and analysis</title>
<p>In this research, waste management practices in Thailand’s construction industry were studied through site visits, interviews, and field questionnaire surveys at small, medium and large construction projects in major urban regions that were selected to represent a broad picture of CWM in Thailand. Nine projects from Bangkok metropolitan and peripheral provinces, ten projects from Chiang Mai and Pitsanulok provinces in the northern region, three projects from Udon Thani province in the north-eastern region, and twelve projects from the southern provinces (Phuket and Song Kla) were selected for the research. According to Thailand’s National Economic and Social Development Board (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0734242X10387012">NESDB 2006</xref>), these selected provinces were regarded as centres of urban development within their respective regions and showed a significant rate of economic development and expanded rate of gross productivity in the construction sector.</p>
<p>The targeted respondents were both direct and indirect stakeholders of construction projects. That is, they benefit and/or were affected by construction activities. The group of respondents included project participants (e.g. project owner, managers, designers, site engineers, foremen, workers, waste removing and recycling operators etc.), government officials (e.g. in the Department of Environment &amp; Construction Works), and members of the local community (e.g. people living/working near construction sites). A total of 384 responses were finally considered valid for data analysis. Details of respondents are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0734242X10387012">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Status of survey respondents</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0734242X10387012" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Involvement with construction projects</th>
<th align="left" colspan="6">Respondents</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Male</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Female</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Overall</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Count</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Count</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Count</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Owner</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>100.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Manager</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>85.7</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>14.3</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>3.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Engineer</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>94.1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>5.9</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>8.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Supervisor/foreman</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>96.6</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>15.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Worker</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>54.1</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>45.9</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>9.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Local residents</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>54.2</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>45.8</td>
<td>120</td>
<td>31.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Government officials (construction)</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>87.1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>12.9</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>8.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Government officials (health &amp; environment)</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>58.3</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>41.7</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>9.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Government officials (other departments)</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>61.5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>38.5</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>6.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recycling company</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Others (e.g. architect/safety engineer/contractor/procurement officer)</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>54.2</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>45.8</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>6.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>265</td>
<td>69.0</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>31.0</td>
<td>384</td>
<td>100.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In addition to general statistics, which were applied for a presentation of descriptive analysis as well as correlation coefficients and level of statistical significance, the SEM part measured and tested the measurement model by confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) whereas the structural model was assessed according to the goodness of fit indices. As suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0734242X10387012">Molenaar et al. (2000)</xref>, the model that performed well with regard to both goodness of fit and the theoretical expectations, after refinements, was selected as the best fitted final SEM model.</p>
<p>In this study, the structural equation model was analysed by using a SEM computer program called AMOS (Analysis of MOment Structures) version 16.0. The latent constructs were incorporated with their corresponding measured variables into an initial causal model. The SEM technique was used to refine and confirm the causal relationships among variables. Model modification indices and theoretical justifications were used until a final satisfactory model was identified. The model was revised through several iterations in order to improve the fitness of the model. Four indices were used to examine the goodness of fit of the analysed model. They are the relative chi-square (CMIN/DF; ≤2.0), the comparative fit index [CFI; ≥0.90), the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA; ≤0.08 (acceptable fit) or ≤0.05 (good fit)], and the incremental fit index (IFI; ≥0.90). These indices were selected because they are relatively independent (least affected) of sample size.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0734242X10387012" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section8-0734242X10387012">
<title>Statistical results</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics results show that a majority of respondents (30%) were from Bangkok whereas the numbers of respondents from other locations ranged from 10 to 15%. As for the number of construction projects in Bangkok outnumbered that of other regions in the country, this proportion was reasonable. In terms of occupation, the large groups of respondents were personnel in construction sites (total 41%), local residents (31%), and government officials (24%). The survey was also carried out in such a manner as to avoid gender biases so that the female respondents were 30% of the total number of respondents. As construction is a male-dominated industry, this proportion is normal for research in construction and this number also conformed to findings by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0734242X10387012">Women-Core Consortium (2008)</xref> which indicated that women’s participation in construction research was between 25 and 44%.</p>
<p>Descriptive statistics also show that the respondents could have similar or different opinions on particular issues. For example, the ranking of important factors to be concerned in construction project were differently recognized by different groups of respondents or by gender. The project owners and managers ranked profits and expenses as the most important factors whereas construction workers ranked health and safety as their most important concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0734242X10387012">Manowong &amp; Perera 2008</xref>). As such, in order to prevent biased SEM analysis due to the different backgrounds of the respondents, it was essential to examine the significant difference in their attitudes and perceptions of the respondents towards the importance of construction waste management. As presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0734242X10387012">Table 3</xref>, the analysis of variance (ANOVA) indicated that the difference in their attitudes and perceptions was not statistically significant (Sig. = 0.012 at the 0.05 level of confidence). Furthermore, the respondents similarly recognized that CWM is as important as other issues in construction project management (Sig. = 0.005; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Analysis of variance (ANOVA) of the recognition on importance of CWM</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0734242X10387012" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Issues under consideration</th>
<th align="left">Type of analysis</th>
<th align="left">Sum of squares</th>
<th align="left">df</th>
<th align="left">Mean square</th>
<th align="left">F</th>
<th align="left">Sig.</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Recognition of importance of CWM</td>
<td>Between groups</td>
<td>36.119</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>4.515</td>
<td>2.484</td>
<td>0.012<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0734242X10387012">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Within groups</td>
<td>681.621</td>
<td>375</td>
<td>1.818</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Total</td>
<td>717.740</td>
<td>383</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CWM is equally important compared with other works in construction management</td>
<td>Between groups</td>
<td>45.136</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>5.642</td>
<td>2.790</td>
<td>0.005<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0734242X10387012">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Within groups</td>
<td>758.278</td>
<td>375</td>
<td>2.022</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Total</td>
<td>803.414</td>
<td>383</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0734242X10387012">
<p>Note: * <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ** <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>However, project owners still consider CWM to be less important than profits and indicate that the cost of CWM has a high effect on the project expenses. From correlation analysis, it was found that CWM’s importance level has a moderately significant correlation with the CWM costs (<italic>r</italic> = 0.36; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). As pointed out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0734242X10387012">Wong &amp; Yip (2004)</xref>, the recycling approach for construction waste material is not widely practised because it is not cost-effective. Thus, cost-effectiveness remains an important decision-making factor for CWM practices, particularly in developing countries such as Thailand where financial resources are limited.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0734242X10387012">
<title>Structural equation modelling results</title>
<p>By using the confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) technique, in order to examine whether the observed variables were well factorized into the respective factors, it was initially found that the conceptual model consisted of five latent variables (or factors) altogether. The environmental sustainability comprised two factors (CFI = 0.951); environmental impact and resource consumption. The social sustainability comprised two factors (CFI = 0.955); health and safety and gender equality. Finally, the economic sustainability construct was found to consist only one factor; the economic incentives (CFI = 0.976).</p>
<p>Each of the CFA model was examined by the Kaiser–Meyer–Olkin (KMO) statistics in order to check both predictability of sampling adequacy and wellness of data factorizing. KMO values vary from 0 to 1.0. Overall, KMO should be 0.60 or higher. The result shows that the KMO for CFAs of latent variables in the starter model ranged from 0.63 to 0.94, indicating that the observed variables were well factorized into the respective factors. Regarding the goodness-of-fit of the CFA models, the RMSEA index indicated that all CFA models were adequately fitted (RMSEA &lt; 0.08) whereas the IFI, TLI and CFI indices indicated that these CFA models were a very good fit (fit indices &gt; 0.09). Hence, the CFA models were taken to establish the SEM starter model.</p>
<p>By means of the SEM program AMOS 16.0, the good-fitted starter model was analysed and further revised until the final model with best fit was achieved. Revisions of the analysed model included deletion and relocation of variables; rearrangement of directions of influence; exclusion of insignificant paths; and addition of covariance; which were recommended by modification indices. In the final model, the influences of variables resource consumption construct were found to be not significant in the model’s path analysis. Hence, their paths are not illustrated in the simplified final structural model. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0734242X10387012">Table 4</xref> shows the fit indices of the analysed structural model. It was found that the final model had a very good fit (IFI, TLI, and CFI indices were all greater than 0.90; RMSEA &lt; 0.05; and CMIN/DF &lt; 2.0).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Goodness of fit measures of the analysed structural model</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0734242X10387012" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Model</th>
<th align="left" colspan="6">Goodness of fit measures</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">CMIN</th>
<th align="left">CMIN/DF</th>
<th align="left">RMSEA</th>
<th align="left">IFI</th>
<th align="left">TLI</th>
<th align="left">CFI</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Starter model</td>
<td>4272.822</td>
<td>2.234</td>
<td>0.057</td>
<td>0.831</td>
<td>0.821</td>
<td>0.830</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Revised 1</td>
<td>4118.631</td>
<td>2.153</td>
<td>0.055</td>
<td>0.842</td>
<td>0.832</td>
<td>0.841</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Revised 2</td>
<td>3991.453</td>
<td>2.091</td>
<td>0.053</td>
<td>0.851</td>
<td>0.841</td>
<td>0.850</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Revised 3</td>
<td>3826.822</td>
<td>2.062</td>
<td>0.053</td>
<td>0.858</td>
<td>0.849</td>
<td>0.857</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Revised 4</td>
<td>3647.662</td>
<td>2.031</td>
<td>0.052</td>
<td>0.865</td>
<td>0.857</td>
<td>0.864</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Revised 5</td>
<td>3460.110</td>
<td>1.927</td>
<td>0.049</td>
<td>0.879</td>
<td>0.872</td>
<td>0.878</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Final model</td>
<td>2740.815</td>
<td>1.771</td>
<td>0.045</td>
<td>0.907</td>
<td>0.900</td>
<td>0.906</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the final model, the GSC latent variable was represented in the form of two sub-constructs: preventive/correction measures and resource utilization. The model’s parsimony comparative fit index (PCFI) was 0.85 while its parsimony ratio (PRATIO) was 0.94, indicating that the final model had a better fit.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X10387012">Tables 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0734242X10387012">6</xref> present detailed results of all standardized path coefficients of the final best-fitted model, along with the squared multiple correlations (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) values. Path coefficients in the final model were statistically significant at the 0.001 level of confidence. Paths from the constructs of environmental sustainability to the constructs of construction waste management efforts were not statistically significant. Hence, at this stage, the model data did not support the hypothesis H1 while remaining hypotheses H2, H3, H4, and H5 were supported.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption><p>Path coefficients in the measurement model (sustainability constructs)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0734242X10387012" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Path of model</th>
<th align="left">Causal relations</th>
<th align="left">Standardized loading</th>
<th align="left">Squared multiple correlation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Environmental sustainability (ES)</td>
<td>Environmental impact</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ ES1 (Awareness)</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ ES2 (Waste generation)</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ ES3 (Air quality)</td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>0.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ ES4 (Water quality)</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>0.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Resource consumption</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ ES5 (Land degradation)</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>0.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ ES7 (Energy consumption)</td>
<td>0.67</td>
<td>0.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social sustainability (SS)</td>
<td>Health impact</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS2 (Accident prevention)</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS3 (Casualty prevention)</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>0.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS4 (Health condition)</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>0.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS7 (Exposure to risks)</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS9 (Mental health)</td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>0.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Health policy &amp; practice</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS1 (Health awareness)</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>0.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS5 (Waste handling)</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>0.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ HS6 (Safety training)</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Gender equality</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GE1 (Gender equality)</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GE2 (Gender respect)</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GE3 (Workplace diversity)</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>0.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GE4 (Fairness)</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>0.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GE6 (Stakeholder participation)</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>0.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GE7 (Susceptibility)</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Economic sustainability (EC)</td>
<td>Economic incentives</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ EC1 (Cost effectiveness)</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ EC2 (Expenditures)</td>
<td>0.30</td>
<td>0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ EC3 (Revenues)</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>0.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ EC4 (Recycling interests)</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>0.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ EC5 (Willingness)</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.70</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table6-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption><p>Estimates of path coefficients in the measurement model (construction waste management efforts and GSC constructs)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0734242X10387012" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Path of model</th>
<th align="left">Causal relations</th>
<th align="left">Standardized loading</th>
<th align="left">Squared multiple correlation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Construction waste management efforts (WME)</td>
<td>Recognition</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME1 (Awareness)</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>0.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME2 (Attitudes)</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME3 (Knowledge)</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>0.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME4 (Communication)</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME5 (CWM guidelines)</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Policy &amp; planning enforcement</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME6 (Participation channels)</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>0.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME7 (CWM policy)</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME8 (CWM system)</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Policy &amp; planning effectiveness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME10 (Encouragement)</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME11 (Alertness)</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.71</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME12 (Legislation)</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Management</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME13 (Waste reduction)</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>0.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME14 (Waste storage)</td>
<td>0.77</td>
<td>0.59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME15 (Waste transportation)</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME16 (Waste separation)</td>
<td>0.81</td>
<td>0.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME17 (Waste disposal)</td>
<td>0.81</td>
<td>0.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME18 (Technology readiness)</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME19 (Budget)</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>0.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ WME20 (Co-operation)</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Green &amp; sustainable construction (GSC)</td>
<td>Preventive/Correction measures</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC11 (Air quality)</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC12 (Water quality)</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC13 (Land use)</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC14 (Workers’ health &amp; safety)</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC15 (Public’s health &amp; safety)</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC16 (Corporate E&amp;S responsibility)</td>
<td>0.71</td>
<td>0.51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC17 (Corporate governance)</td>
<td>0.68</td>
<td>0.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Resource utilization</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC1 (Awareness)</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC2 (Human resource development)</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>0.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC3 (Energy efficiency)</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC4 (Material consumption)</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC5 (Water consumption)</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>→ GSC19 (Profitability)</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.07</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the SEM model, it can be seen that the environmental sustainability construct was measured by the environmental impact and resource consumption variables. Results from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X10387012">Table 5</xref> indicate that construction activities (ES1) generated highly adverse environmental impacts, especially the air pollution (ES3) and construction waste (ES2). Meanwhile, the wastewater from construction site (ES4) had moderate impact (standardized loading = 0.62) on the environment conditions. These SEM results conformed to the survey results which indicated that a large volume of construction waste was mostly generated during the construction stage. Some wasted construction materials such as concrete and bricks were largely dumped in landfill sites. The resource consumption (ES5, ES6) variables had no significant influence on the environmental sustainability. This reflects the fact that the resources of natural construction materials in Thailand are plentiful and so it is not yet perceived that current consumption of natural materials would adversely affect the environment.</p>
<p>Concerning the construction of social sustainability, the most influential factors in characterizing the health impact was the risk from construction waste and pollution (HS7) and the mental health impact (HS9). Meanwhile, public health policy and practice were most influenced by the availability of training for construction waste management (HS6) and measures for construction waste management available (HS5). This SEM results support the surveyed responses indicating that health and safety issues are very significant issues, particularly for construction workers who are directly exposed to construction waste. It is suggested that, based on this finding, the protection of stakeholders’ health and safety are the first priority that must be considered by those who have power to make decisions in construction projects. Findings also suggest that, in order to increase gender equality in the management of waste in the construction industry, women should be assigned to construction waste management duties because it was found that women are more sensible in managing construction waste. Furthermore, the SEM analysis shows that the success of such works weare most influenced by the acceptance of women’s working ability (GE3), the number of women working at management level (GE4), and women’s participation in management of construction waste (GE6).</p>
<p>When considering factors of the economic sustainability, willingness of construction operators (EC5) and motivation to implement 3Rs (EC4) had high influence on construction waste management efforts while the remaining factors had moderate influence. Hence, economic incentives and a wide range of CWM alternatives should be initiated.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0734242X10387012">Table 6</xref> shows path coefficients for measures of the construction waste management efforts and sustainable construction factors. From the CFA result, the four major latent constructs of the CWM efforts included CWM recognition, CWM policy and planning (P&amp;P) enforcement, the effectiveness of CWM P&amp;P implementation, and CWM managerial practices. The final structural model shows that the CWM recognition was highly influenced by the availability of CWM procedures and guidelines (WME5), followed by the availability of channels for CWM information exchange (WME4), people’s knowledge and understanding of CWM (WME3). Meanwhile, intention to initiate and implement a CWM plan (WME2) had a moderate influence on CWM recognition. These SEM results reflect that the CWM initiatives would be recognized if the CWM information and detailed process was widely available to the relevant stakeholders in the construction industry. Recognition and improvement of CWM skills and techniques would gradually develop if supports from governing authorities and professional bodies were provided.</p>
<p>Effective enforcement of CWM policies and plans was most influenced by the compatibility of CWM plan and actual situation (WME8). Clarity of CWM policies (WME7) and consultations among government/private/citizen sectors (WME6) also had high influences on the enforcement of CWM policies and plans. Hence, CWM policies should be clear and they must be carried out with participation from the concerned groups of project stakeholders. Further, the relevant stakeholders’ alertness and adaptation for changes in their working behaviour (WME11), particularly the foremen and the on-site construction workers, and the level of encouragement induced by the established CWM plan (WME10), were found to have most influence on the effectiveness of CWM policies and plans. Therefore, construction stakeholders need to be highly motivated and continuously encouraged through all possible means to obtain their co-operation and co-ordination in order to run the introduced CWM plan.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the appropriateness of management/disposal process for construction waste (WME17), the efficiency of construction waste sorting and separation (WME16), transportation of construction waste (WME15), and the availability of storage area for construction waste (WME14) were found to have high influence on the success of CWM efforts. However, high influences from these factors could not be meaningful without the availability of budget (WME19), readiness to employ new CWM technology (WME18), and co-operation/co-ordination between government and private sectors (WME20), which have moderate influence on CWM efforts.</p>
<p>The prospects of Green and Sustainable Construction were measured in the SEM model through the status of resource utilization, and preventive/correction measures for the resolution of social and environmental problems, which was highly influenced by measures for prevention, control and remedy of problems related to water pollution (GSC12), air pollution (GSC11), and land degradation (GSC13). In addition, provision of healthcare and safety precautions (GSC15), worker’s health insurance (GSC14), corporate social responsibility (GSC16), and regular monitoring and reports on the status of construction industry’s initiatives towards sustainability (GSC17) were found to have moderate influence on the GSC status.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the resource utilization was found to be most influenced by an effective use of material in construction activities (GSC4), energy (GSC3), and water (GSC5). Further, resource utilization was also moderately influenced by development and improvement of workers’ skills (GSC2) and recognition on worthiness of CWM plan (GSC1). It is reflected, in this study, that GSC is regarded as being dependent upon not only the success in prevention/solution of these environmental problems but also a balanced achievement of the goals of social and economic sustainability.</p>
<p>For better visualization and clarity, a simplified final structural model is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X10387012">Figure 2</xref> presenting only significant influences (i.e. path coefficients) of sustainability issues upon the construction waste management efforts and on GSC.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0734242X10387012" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Final structural model.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X10387012-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The final model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X10387012">Figure 2</xref> briefly indicates that concerns of economic incentives have the highest influence on the efforts to recognize and manage construction waste problems. When considering the path coefficients in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X10387012">Table 5</xref>, as previously discussed, it was found that stakeholders’ willingness to attain economic incentives and their interests in recycling waste are main factors that drive their efforts to implement CWM practices. As such, these two factors should seriously be taken into account when trying to encourage the construction operatives to participate in CWM programmes or initiatives.</p>
<p>Similarly, the social sustainability issues also have significant influence on CWM efforts. Health impact was found to have significant negative impact on management, meaning that the higher rate of stakeholders’ suffering health problems reflects lower effectiveness of the management in exerting the CWM efforts. The path coefficients in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X10387012">Table 5</xref> suggest that attention must be paid to significant factors such as stakeholders’ exposure to risks when handling construction waste and this can be done by firstly providing CWM training to construction operatives.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X10387012">Figure 2</xref> also indicates that concerns on environmental sustainability have no direct significant influence on CWM efforts. Rather, the concerns on environmental impacts have direct influence GSC achievement, through provision of measures to prevent and correct environmental impacts. These initiatives significantly influence enforcement of CWM policy and plan, which is supported by clear health policy and practical guidelines, leading to the effective implementation of CWM policies and plans.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0734242X10387012">
<title>Factors influencing construction waste management efforts</title>
<p>This study has found a few major factors having influence on CWM efforts. The findings are summarized in the following list.</p>
<list id="list3-0734242X10387012" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Availability of management procedures (collection, separation, transportation, and disposal). This requires allocated budget, standardized CWM guidelines, and enhanced communication channels to increased recognition on CWM.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Enforcement of CWM policies and plans. The CWM system needs to be clearly planned and strongly established with stakeholders’ participation in order to alert and encourage their willingness, possibly through legislation.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Economic incentives. Provision of economic incentives brings stakeholders’ willingness to better manage and interest to recycle construction wastes.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Health assurances. Healthcare and waste handling training are essential to prevent risks from being exposed to wastes on-site and off-site. When this is provided, stakeholders feel more motivated to voluntarily deal with wastes.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Gender diversity recognition. When the construction industry better recognizes gender differences such as female workers’ physical sensitivity or female employees’ managerial capability there can be more CWM efforts.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The aforementioned factors are only those having moderately and highly significant influence on CWM efforts. Other factors having significant influence, but at a lower level, can be observed based on their path coefficients in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X10387012">Table 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0734242X10387012">6</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0734242X10387012">
<title>Case study examples</title>
<p>To provide a clearer picture of the situation of CWM problems in Thailand, two studied cases have been selected to briefly reflect similarities and differences of practices in a big city such as Bangkok and a smaller provincial city in the southern region.</p>
<p>The mass transit infrastructure project of in Bangkok is larger and located in a highly populated area. This project has a better CWM system on-site where waste materials are collected and stored in a designated place. The construction contractor company also has its own special stockpile for construction waste. The company can allocate reusable waste for its own use in other projects in Bangkok and the company can save material costs. Furthermore, the environmental and pollution control law and regulations in Bangkok are more strict so that the construction company has to be careful with its waste-related operations.</p>
<p>In comparison, CWM in the construction of the government’s university building in southern Thailand is less practiced. Only steel is being collected for recycling because its value and recycling potential is already recognized. Other on-site waste materials are mixed together and it is impossible to reuse or recycle. The contractor has no interest in recycling waste materials because fresh materials are locally available with lower prices. Furthermore, there is no clear requirement in local government administration concerning CWM.</p>
<p>It can be seen that both projects have different motives in managing their wastes. The main considerations are involved with local law and regulations and construction operators’ attitudes towards the benefits of implementing CWM in their project management.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0734242X10387012" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="section13-0734242X10387012">
<title>Existing situations</title>
<p>Waste materials from construction projects in Thailand are handled differently depending on their perceived current economic values. Currently, construction waste management practices are not widely familiar to Thai construction stakeholders. They do not know any particular policy or procedures to handle waste materials properly. Bulk and decomposable wastes such as concrete, bricks, and asbestos have not been properly managed. At the construction site’s waste collecting point, construction wastes are left and mixed together so that their quality is worsened. Therefore, they are not taken for reuse or recycling because the processing cost is higher than buying fresh raw materials.</p>
<p>Currently, mixed construction wastes is buried on-site, disposed at landfill sites, or illegally dumped into empty areas, causing environmental and social problems. Only construction wastes with perceived quality and economic value are collected on-site. There are no problems for metal wastes because they can be easily sorted and sold to the existing domestic market. Some type of recyclable wastes from construction such as papers and plastics are less frequently brought to recycling because most of them are normally mixed with other wastes at construction sites. As a result of the unavailability or inadequacy of a sorting process, such waste materials are contaminated and unsuitable for recycling. In fact, the salvage of construction materials and building parts has already been in practice when buildings are demolished. However, a standardized salvage system is needed to promote a wider market for reused/recycled materials. The enhanced salvage system facilitates the assessment of the quality of salvageable building materials and the resources required for the salvaging process. By this approach, the overall value of a building can be evaluated throughout its whole life-cycle. The relevant impacts on sustainability are assessed and proper CWM actions can then be applied. As such, the value of construction waste is maximized while minimizing the costs of waste reuse and recycling.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0734242X10387012">
<title>Attitudinal and regulatory problems</title>
<p>The SEM analysis provides insights into the attitudes and perceptions of stakeholders concerning how to successfully achieve the purpose of GSC in Thailand through exertion of waste management efforts. Lack of construction waste management facilities and economic incentives have caused the Thai construction operatives to have little interest in segregating and storing waste materials for recycling or proper disposal process. In the general view of project owners or managers, additional efforts or resources used for management of waste (such as sorting, storing, and transporting) imposed additional costs to their project. Although they realize that waste management is a good practice, it was considered to be a much less important issue compared with the financial benefits and time consumption. Then, the waste management plan had hardly been integrated into the project management plan. Lack of motivation and encouragement in implementing ‘3R’ practices results in a high rate of landfilling and little presence of a market for recycled material. In addition, there is no specific law to deal with construction and demolition waste and the enforcement of related environmental law and regulations is ineffective. As such, construction activities in those areas with fewer restrictions continue to generate waste and pollution.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0734242X10387012">
<title>Improving construction waste management and achieving sustainable construction</title>
<p>This study recommends that the significance of waste management need to be firstly recognized in order to encourage stakeholders to exert their efforts in waste management. Such recognition has significant influence on the achievement of sustainable construction by focusing on effective utilization of a project’s resources. Successful building of stakeholders’ recognition relies on effective management process. Inclusion of economic incentives and the stakeholders concern about the issue of health impact play a significant role in increasing recognition and waste management effort. Policies and practices on people’s health also significantly push the enforcement of waste management policy and plan. Strong enforcement of construction waste management policies and plans, in combination with emphasis on gender equality issues which strengthens women’s roles and decision-making power in managing construction waste, finally leads waste management initiatives and implementation to be effectively carried out.</p>
<p>An implication of the findings of the study is that, the issues of environmental impact and depletion of resources due to high consumption have no influence on the waste management effort. Rather, the concern on environmental impact significantly influences the improvement of construction practices. Various measures for prevention and correction of bad practices must be implemented in order to attain GSC. Such measures significantly motivate better resource utilization, which is regarded as the most significant factor for GSC achievement. Although the issue of gender equality has no influence on sustainable construction, it has significant influence on stimulating the effectiveness of policies and planning for management of construction waste and pollution. Accepting the ability of women at the management level and encouraging their participation in construction projects can play a noticeable role in driving the success of construction waste management.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0734242X10387012" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The influence of sustainability factors on the efforts on construction waste management and the achievement of GSC practices in Thailand’s construction projects were investigated through field observations and surveys. Collected data was quantitatively analysed by means of statistical packages and the SEM techniques. The result indicates that the management of construction and demolition waste is generally regarded as an important emerging issue. However, the Thai construction owners and managers still consider project profits and related economic benefits as the most important concerns. On the contrary, Thai construction workers and members of the public are most concerned with the issues of health and safety. When there is no agreed position to adequately utilize a project’s budget on waste management scheme initiatives, the efforts on waste management are not actively exerted.</p>
<p>By testing the research hypotheses, it was revealed that the economic and social sustainability factors had significant direct causal effect on the waste management effort. This is not the case for the environmental sustainability factors because they have significant direct causal effect only on the achievement of GSC where preventive and correction measures for environmental problems are applied focusing on effective resource utilization. Hence, in order to initiate and implement construction and demolition waste management policies and practices in Thailand, recognition of the waste problems should be firstly adopted. Moreover, the issues on economic incentives and social concerns such as health and safety or empowerment of women should be emphasized more because these lead to higher recognition of construction waste problems and stronger enforcement of waste management policies and plans in order to achieve effective implementation of construction waste management countrywide.</p>
<p>For developing countries with limited financial resources and construction waste management initiatives, in order to avoid subsequent costly process for managing construction waste, there should be strategies established aiming to take proactive steps and pay attention to both existing and anticipated conditions for construction waste. Sustainable construction in developing countries can be achieved in an affordable manner through effective utilization of resources in construction, material recovery, an improved system for waste management, and energy savings. However, the first objective to be achieved is a change of the stakeholders’ norms. To achieve the goals of GSC in Thailand, as well as other developing countries with similar context, strong regulatory initiatives such as specific laws and policies for construction waste management are as important as the stakeholders’ awareness and willingness to participate.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Part of the research was supported by the SEA-UEMA project, Asian Institute of Technology, Thailand, during 2007–2008 and the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation, Germany, during 2009–2011.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ageton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohannan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruzzin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schultheiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoakes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Social Sustainability Strategic Plan</source>. <publisher-loc>Colorado, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Boulder City Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Business, Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Department (BERR)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Strategy for Sustainable Construction Consultation</source>. <comment>From BERR’s publications (2007): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/sectors/construction/sustainability/page13691.html">http://www.berr.gov.uk/sectors/construction/sustainability/page13691.html</ext-link></comment> <access-date>Accessed 24 May 2008</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS: Basic Concepts, Applications, and Programming</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>CES (Commissioner for Environmental Sustainability)</collab>, (ed.) (<year>2006</year>) <comment>From CES publications. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ces.vic.gov.au/CES/wcmn301.nsf/childdocs/-441BB07721D61152CA256F250028C5FB?open">http://www.ces.vic.gov.au/CES/wcmn301.nsf/childdocs/-441BB07721D61152CA256F250028C5FB?open</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 1 July 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Environmental management of urban construction projects in China</article-title>. <source>Journal of Construction Engineering and Management</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>WHC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Evaluating sustainability in waste management: the case of construction and demolition, chemical and clinical wastes in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Building environmental assessment methods: assessing construction practices</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>957</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Commercial Construction Waste Management Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Western Australia, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Master Builders Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colantonio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shiers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gallimore</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>A Green Profession? A Global Survey of RICS Members and their Engagement with the Sustainability Agenda</source>. <comment>Research Report. June 2007</comment>. <publisher-name>Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors (RICS)</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donatiello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Environmental sustainability indicators in urban areas: an Italian experience</article-title> <comment>Working paper no. 16 of the Commission of the European Communities</comment>, <conf-name>Joint ECE/Eurostat Work Session on Methodological Issues of Environment Statistics</conf-name>, <conf-date>1–4 October</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</conf-loc>: <comment>The United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (UNECE). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unece.org/stats/documents/2001/10/env/wp.16.e.pdf">http://www.unece.org/stats/documents/2001/10/env/wp.16.e.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 15 January 2010</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lenihan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Regan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A model for assessing the economic viability of construction and demolition waste recycling—the case of Ireland</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>EA (Environment Agency)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2008</year>) <source>Social Sustainability</source>. <comment>From UK’s EA publications (2008). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/aboutus/512398/289428/654938/">http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/aboutus/512398/289428/654938/</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 1 July 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>EPA (Environment Protection Agency)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2010</year>) <source>Definition of Green Building</source>. <comment>From US Environmental Protection Agency’s publications (2010). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/greenbuilding/pubs/about.htm">http://www.epa.gov/greenbuilding/pubs/about.htm</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 10 August 2010</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goco</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Climate Change, Governance and Co-Benefits</source>. <publisher-name>Environmental Management Bureau, DENR Compound, Visayas Avenue, Diliman, Quezon Cit</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>The Philippines</publisher-loc>. <comment>From KMIP publications (2007). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kyomecha.org/pdf/Goco.pdf">http://www.kyomecha.org/pdf/Goco.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 10 November 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haggar</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Sustainable Industrial Design and Waste Management: Cradle-to-Cradle for Sustainable Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Maryland Heights, MO, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>HSE (Health and Safety Executive)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2007</year>) <source>Construction (Design and Management) Regulations 2007 (CDM 2007)</source>. <comment>From UK’s HSE publications (2007). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/construction/cdm.htm">http://www.hse.gov.uk/construction/cdm.htm</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 1 August 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hemmati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Gender Equity and Sustainable Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Johannesburg, South Africa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Henrich Böll Foundation’s</publisher-name> <conf-name>Briefing paper towards the World Summit 2002</conf-name>, <conf-date>26 August – 4 September</conf-date>. <comment>From the World Summit’s publications (2002). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldsummit2002.org/publications/wspaper10.pdf">http://www.worldsummit2002.org/publications/wspaper10.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 10 February 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ILO (International Labour Organization)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>ILO standards-related activities in the area of occupational safety and health: An in-depth study for discussion with a view to the elaboration of a plan of action for such activities</article-title>. <comment>Report VI, 91st Session 2003</comment>, <publisher-name>International Labour Office</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kibert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Sustainable Construction: Green Building Design and Delivery</source>. <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons, Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vikman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brattebø</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Sustainable management of demolition waste: an integrated model for the evaluation of environmental, economic and social aspects</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klundert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anschutz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Integrated Sustainable Waste Management: the selection of appropriate technologies and the design of sustainable systems is not (only) a technical issue</article-title>. In: <conf-name>The CEDARE/IETC Inter-Regional Workshop on Technologies for Sustainable Waste Management</conf-name>, <conf-date>13–15 July 1999</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Alexandria, Egypt</conf-loc>. <comment>From the World Bank’s publications (2007). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldbank.org/urban/solid_wm/erm/Annexes/US%20Sizes/Annex%204B.3.pdf">http://www.worldbank.org/urban/solid_wm/erm/Annexes/US%20Sizes/Annex%204B.3.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 1 February 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kulatunga</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amaratunga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rameezdeen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Attitudes and perceptions of construction workforce on construction waste in Sri Lanka</article-title>. <source>Management of Environmental Quality: An International Journal</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lingard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smithers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Employee perceptions of the solid waste management system operating in a large Australian contracting organization: implications for company policy implementation</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manowong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Construction waste management from a gender perspective</article-title>. <source>GMSARN (Greater Mekong Sub-region Academic and Research Network) International Journal</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smithers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Implementing a waste management plan during the construction phase of a project: a case study</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niethammer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Embedding Gender in Sustainability Reporting: A Practitioner’s Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington DC, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The International Finance Corporation (IFC)</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Molenaar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diekmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Structural equation model of construction contract dispute potential</article-title>. <source>Journal of Construction Engineering and Management</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schienberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Gender and Urban Waste Management</source>. <conf-name>A paper presented at the Programme Policy Meeting of the Urban Waste Expertise Programme, organised by WASTE in Gouda, the Netherlands in 1997; and at the Gender, Technology and Development Conference</conf-name>, organized by <conf-loc>TOOL/TOOLCONSULT in Amsterdam</conf-loc>, <conf-date>1997</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>NESDB (National Economic and Social Development Board)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2006</year>) <source>Gross Regional Product and Gross Provincial Product 2006</source>. <comment>From NESDB publications (2006). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nesdb.go.th/Portals/0/eco_datas/account/gpp/book/bookgpp_2549.pdf">http://www.nesdb.go.th/Portals/0/eco_datas/account/gpp/book/bookgpp_2549.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 31 July 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>NHS PASA (NHS Purchasing and Supply Agency)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2008</year>) <source>Social Sustainability</source>. <comment>From NHS publications (2008). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pasa.nhs.uk/PASAWeb/NHSprocurement/Sustainabledevelopment/Socialsustainability/LandingPage.htm">http://www.pasa.nhs.uk/PASAWeb/NHSprocurement/Sustainabledevelopment/Socialsustainability/LandingPage.htm</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 1 July 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>PCD (Pollution Control Department)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2007</year>) <source>Study of the Guideline for Construction and Demolition Waste Management in Thailand</source>. <publisher-loc>Bangkok, Thailand</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministry of Natural Resources and Environment</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Inquiry into Waste Generation and Resource Recovery</source>. <publisher-loc>South Australia, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Productivity Commission Issues Paper (Dec. 05). KESAB environmental solutions (Keep South Australia Beautiful Inc)</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Gender gaps in participation and employment rates</article-title>. In <source>Impact Evaluation of the European Employment Strategy in Ireland</source>. <comment>Report to the Dept of Enterprise</comment>, <publisher-name>Trade and Employment</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dublin, Eire</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>VWY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mapping approach for examining waste management on construction sites</article-title>. <source>Journal of Construction Engineering and Management</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>VWY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yiu</surname><given-names>KTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title>Critical factors for environmental performance assessment (EPA) in the Hong Kong construction industry</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>1123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>VWY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006b</year>) <article-title>Environmental performance assessment: perceptions of project managers on the relationship between operational and environmental performance indicators</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>MMM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loosemore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A theory of waste behavior in the construction industry</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>749</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Uher</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Absolute indicator of sustainable construction</article-title>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>RICS Research Foundation</publisher-name>, <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>, <comment>COBRA 1999</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>UNCSD</collab> (ed.) (<year>2005</year>) <source>Sanitation: Policy Options and Possible Actions to Expedite Implementation</source>. <comment>Report of the Secretary-General, 13th session of the UN Commission on Sustainable Development</comment>, <day>11–22</day> <month>April</month> <year>2005</year>. <publisher-name>UNCSD</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, USA</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>UNEP RRC.AP (UNEP Regional Resource Centre for Asia and the Pacific)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2008</year>) <source>Land Degradation, State of the Environment Reporting</source>. <comment>From UN Publications (2008): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rrcap.unep.org/reports/soe/bhutan_land.pdf">http://www.rrcap.unep.org/reports/soe/bhutan_land.pdf</ext-link></comment> <access-date>Accessed 1 July 2008</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>WEF (World Economic Forum)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2006</year>) <source>The Global Gender Gap Report 2006</source>. <comment>From World Economic Forum publications (2006). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.weforum.org/pdf/gendergap/report2006.pdf">http://www.weforum.org/pdf/gendergap/report2006.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 25 January 2010</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>WHO (World Health Organization)</collab> (ed.) (<year>2005</year>) <source>World Summit Outcome Document</source>. <comment>From WHO publications (2005). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/hiv/universalaccess2010/worldsummit.pdf">www.who.int/hiv/universalaccess2010/worldsummit.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 16 January 2010</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>WOMEN-CORE Consortium</collab> (ed.) (<year>2008</year>) <source>WOMEN in Construction Scientific Research</source>. <comment>Executive summary report no. 017568. From WOMEN-CORE Consortium publications (2008). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.women-core.org/web/files/90/en/WOMEN_CORE_Executive_summary.pdf">http://www.women-core.org/web/files/90/en/WOMEN_CORE_Executive_summary.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 16 February 2010</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>EOW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>RCP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Promoting sustainable construction waste management in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Construction Management and Economics</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0734242X10387012">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yost</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Residential Construction Waste Management: A Builder’s Field Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>MD, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NAHB Research Center</publisher-name>. <comment>Upper Marlboro</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>