<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TVN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptvn</journal-id>
<journal-title>Television &amp; New Media</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1527-4764</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8316</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1527476412455848</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1527476412455848</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Introduction to Civic Cultures</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Annette</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Annette</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1527476412455848">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1527476412455848"><label>1</label>Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1527476412455848">Annette Hill, Lund University, Media and Communication, P.O. Box 201, Lund, SE-221 00, Sweden Email: <email>annette.hill@kom.lu.se</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue on Civic Cultures</issue-title>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>4</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The idea of civic cultures encapsulates our engagement with the political and nonpolitical in social and cultural life. This special issue of <italic>Television and New Media</italic> explores civic cultures in the context of politics, media, and society. Researchers critically examine how civic cultures can be stepping stones toward democratic ideals.</p>
<p>In his book <italic>Media and Political Engagement</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1527476412455848">2009</xref>), Peter Dahlgren proposes a circuit of civic cultures located around ideas of knowledge, values, trust, spaces, practices, and identities:<disp-quote>
<p>Such cultures are important in facilitating engagement in the broad domain of what we might term the politically relevant, in creating a climate that is conducive to citizen participation in the shaping of society’s political life, and in fostering fluid communicative borders between politics and non-politics. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1527476412455848">Dahlgren 2005</xref>, 413)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The characteristics of civic cultures are evident in the ways people engage or disengage with the social and political.</p>
<p>For example, work on political communication has explored how the media system has restyled politics for contemporary citizens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1527476412455848">Corner and Pels 2003</xref>). Politicians are treated like celebrities, and as public figures they incite distrust rather than trust in democratic ideals. Within the circuit of civic cultures, ideas of knowledge, values, and trust are significant to analysis of political disengagement. In another example, popular factual content can offer diverse groups of people both rational and affective experiences, opening up notions of political engagement to popular cultural spheres (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1527476412455848">Hill 2007</xref>). Within the circuit of civic cultures, ideas of popular spaces, practices, and identities are significant to critical analysis of social and cultural participation.</p>
<p>The articles in this special issue consider how the idea of civic cultures connects with critical social and cultural theory. Peter Dahlgren addresses the significance of subjectivity and the self in political, social, and cultural thinking on identity. Tobias Olsson and Fredrik Miegel reflect on a cultural approach to political engagement, through an analysis of the work of John Dewey and civic socialization in relation to contemporary practices for civic cultures. Other researchers explore how the political is embedded within culture and society. Stephen Coleman critically examines televised public debates and proposes how the drama of politics can be communicated on TV in such a way as to encourage political engagement. In their analysis of business reality television, Raymond Boyle and Lisa Kelly draw on production and audience research to show the different ways people produce and engage with the politics of business and entrepreneurship. The issue of political comedy is a rich site for researchers to explore how social and cultural practices open up understanding of political engagement and disengagement. John Corner, Kay Richardson and Katy Parry ask how audiences respond to different types of political comedy, from gentling mocking politicians and institutions, to more passionate critique of scandals, or the economic crisis in Britain. Fadi Hirzala, Liesbet van Zoonen, and Floris Müller focus on political comedy video blogs, looking at the specific context of the anti-Islam video Fitna. Rather than an open exchange of views, they find online debate associated with such a controversial subject to be antagonistic in nature. This range of articles by leading researchers help us to learn more about how social and cultural practices shape and are shaped by the political in people’s lives.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The articles in this special issue were first presented at the Civic Cultures conference Lund University 2011, funded by the Sandbloms and Wahlgrens Foundations.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Annette Hill</bold> is a Professor of Media at Lund University, Sweden, and Visiting Professor at the Communication and Media Research Institute, University of Westminster, United Kingdom. Her research focuses on audiences, with interests in sociology of media, everyday life, genres and cultures of viewing, and media experiences. Her most recent book is <italic>Paranormal Media: Audiences, Spirits and Magic in Popular Culture</italic> (Routledge, 2011).</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1527476412455848">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Corner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pels</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <year>2003</year> <source>Media and the restyling of politics</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1527476412455848">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Television, public spheres, and civic cultures</article-title>. In <source>A companion to television</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wasko</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1527476412455848">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. <source>Media and political engagement</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1527476412455848">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. <source>Restyling factuality</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>