<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spbir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Business Information Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0266-3821</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-6450</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0266382112456272</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0266382112456272</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Gaining additional value from secondary data resources: Using existing internal data and knowledge to create new company-centric resources</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>Denise</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0266382112456272">Merck Serono, Switzerland</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0266382112456272"/>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>About the author</title>
<p>
<bold>Denise Carter</bold> is Associate Director, Knowledge Analytics at Merck Serono based in Geneva. She has been an information professional for the past 25 years. Denise started her career at ICI Chemicals &amp; Polymers, Cheshire UK as Librarian. In 1995 she moved to Geneva to set up a new information unit for Serono, starting with a one-person unit for Serono Corporate HQ, which grew to a five-person team delivering a global service to the entire Serono organization, winning a Chief Executive Officer Award for customer service in 2006. In 2007 when Serono was acquired by Merck, Denise changed departments to work in Business Intelligence and now heads a team, Knowledge Analytics, delivering pipeline analysis, epidemiology information and secondary competitor news and information to Merck Serono. Denise is particularly interested in organization of information for effective retrieval. She has been involved in the development of several proprietary databases at Merck Serono.</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0266382112456272">Denise Carter Email: <email>denise.carter@merckgroup.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>148</fpage>
<lpage>156</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Information teams within biopharmaceutical organizations are usually the decision-makers on purchasing external data resources, matching customer and business requirements to the most useful and cost-effective resource. Many of these resources are provided for end-user access and the information teams also use them to answer regular and ad hoc enquiries and feed into regular operations such as issuing alerts, or creating monthly competitor overviews. In today’s increasingly cost-conscious environment it is important to seek ways to increase value from investments in information resources. Information teams also need to demonstrate the relevance of their skills and services to the organization they serve and show how they contribute to the organization’s aims in tangible ways. This article describes two instances of using data from externally subscribed resources, combined with internal explicit and tacit knowledge to create new company-centric resources: a global epidemiology resource and a market attractiveness platform for assessing commercial-viability for products in emerging markets.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>budget</kwd>
<kwd>business analysis</kwd>
<kwd>databases</kwd>
<kwd>decision-making</kwd>
<kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
<kwd>explicit knowledge</kwd>
<kwd>forecasting</kwd>
<kwd>market attractiveness</kwd>
<kwd>secondary data</kwd>
<kwd>tacit knowledge</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0266382112456272">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sec id="section2-0266382112456272">
<title>The factors affecting value from content investment</title>
<p>Information budgets for corporate libraries can vary enormously: $70,000 to $21million, for example.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0266382112456272">1</xref>
</sup> Database costs represent a significant portion of the budget. Drives to reduce costs by cutting staff (usually also a large budget item) and recognition of the end-user’s increasing familiarity with electronic tools and web searching have stimulated the purchase of end-user resources by organizations. Anecdotal evidence on client use of these tools suggests that, although some users are very adept, for others infrequent use of tools with different functionalities can be an issue. End-users have too little time to learn how to use individual tools; it is also often unclear which data can be extracted from which tool. These factors contribute to tools being under used. In biopharmaceutical companies, it has often been the practice to outsource requests which require data gathered from multiple external sources even when the data is already available internally. This results in significant additional expense.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0266382112456272">
<title>Creating company-centric resources – the drivers</title>
<p>The budget holder for databases has a responsibility to maximize the value of the tools and resources already paid for by the organization. Extracting data from different tools and re-combining it to create company-centric resources can be one very effective way to do this. What would make a useful company-centric resource can be driven by several factors observable by the information professional:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Examples of the same question or types of question being asked multiple times and requiring the extraction and synthesis of information from different resources.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Knowledge of requests made to external consultants where the information professional is aware that the request could have been fulfilled by using internal data resources.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Understanding the organizational objectives and goals stimulating the information professional to anticipate specific information requirements.</p>
</list-item>
</list>By combining data from already purchased tools with explicit and tacit knowledge within the organization, we can try to create resources specific to company needs, that add value by enabling further analysis of the data, and which can aid decision-making.</p>
<p>The biopharmaceutical industry is extremely competitive. It is therefore crucial that it exploits both external and internal information and knowledge effectively to drive quality decisions. Information professionals in the organization play a key role in analyzing published information and combining this with internal knowledge. This analysis is important at all stages of the drug development process from research through clinical development (when drugs are trialled with patients), and as successful drug candidates are registered with the authorities for approval. Information monitoring and analysis to support the sales and marketing of drugs is also important.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0266382112456272">
<title>Company-centric opportunities in Pharma</title>
<sec id="section5-0266382112456272">
<title>Epidemiology and forecasting</title>
<p>To understand how a new drug candidate would impact the current market, one key data requirement is the number of potential patients that could be targeted for treatment. This is defined by understanding the epidemiology of the disease. Epidemiology captures the incidence (number of new cases occurring of a disease) or the prevalence (number of cases at a given point in time). From the total number of patients who may have a disease, only a certain number would be eligible for treatment with a drug and it is necessary to further refine this original number by factoring in other elements, such as the diagnosis rate for the disease, the treatment rate, and, as often the disease is characterized by different stages, which specific stage or stages of the disease the drug candidate will potentially treat. As drug development is a long process the numbers of patients must be forecast over a number of years to allow for changes in population. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0266382112456272">Figure 1</xref> describes a theoretical example.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0266382112456272" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Epidemiology and forecasting: a theoretical example.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0266382112456272-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>This data is essential to developing patient-based forecasts in order to understand what potential share of the market may be realized by a new drug candidate. Forecasts combine the potential patient numbers with other key market data, for example current treatments and other potential new treatments coming on to the market. The data used to derive potential patient numbers are available through multiple sources and in multiple formats.</p>
<p>At Merck Serono, a lack of consistency in epidemiology data gathering and data quality, combined with the fact that this data, once collected for one project, was not centralized and stored for re-use meant this was an ideal candidate for developing a company-centric resource.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0266382112456272">
<title>Market attractiveness</title>
<p>Potential patient numbers are critical in developing patient-based forecasts, but they could also be significant in understanding how attractive a particular country could be as a customer for a drug candidate. Within the biopharmaceutical world the development of emerging markets has become increasingly important. Traditional market forecasts consider only the top seven markets – France; Germany; Italy; Japan, Spain; UK and USA. Forecasts for the Asian and Latin American regions are also now more common. However, these consider only the major Asian and Latin American countries, such as China or Brazil. In parallel, biopharmaceutical companies are increasingly looking at niche diseases where patient numbers are low so that selling in an increased number of countries will be advantageous, making emerging countries more attractive targets.</p>
<p>However, patient numbers are only one factor and marketing drugs in an emerging country means understanding those markets – in terms of structure and how to get the drug approved and reimbursed in those countries – as well as we understand the traditional markets. In Merck Serono there was a gap in the market knowledge for many emerging countries although this data is available in disparate, already available resources.</p>
<p>The decision to develop a tool which built on the patient number data and captured other market measures which could be rated and compared against each other and traditional markets was a natural extension to the epidemiology project. Our pilot project – MAPs (Market Attractiveness Platform) – is an exploratory exercise to identify the value of bringing these market measures together.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0266382112456272">
<title>Example 1 – global epidemiology resource</title>
<sec id="section8-0266382112456272">
<title>Background</title>
<p>What was the rationale for creating an epidemiology resource internally when there are commercial epidemiology resources available? The initial driver for the resource was to support the forecasting team. The requirement started as something rather simple – to capture data already collected for forecasts and store it in an organized manner, with date and full source clearly annotated so it could be easily retrieved and correctly referenced within a forecast. Most forecasts which use patient numbers are for business development cases or early pipeline projects.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0266382112456272">2</xref>
</sup> The former are often done with a high degree of time pressure; this has meant that in the past the quality of searching for epidemiology data was not optimal and often the sources were not referenced adequately. Even for early pipeline projects, where time is less of a factor, there was little consistency in the methodology of sourcing epidemiology data.</p>
<p>On deeper investigation into current practices, we found there was no consistent Merck Serono methodology for obtaining epidemiology data, and no validation process to ensure the best quality data is used. It was clear that the data used in forecasts was often very hurriedly obtained, particularly in the case of business development requests, and the most easily obtainable epidemiology figures were used rather than the most rigorously correct figures. Epidemiological data were collected on an ad hoc basis for each forecast using different sources, both internal and external. Numbers also varied if forecasts were done at a corporate level or at a local company level. As we began to look in more detail at epidemiology data and the sources being referenced in forecasts, it became clear that was a much larger issue which needed to be addressed – the quality of data. Additionally, even if a more systematic approach was used to obtain epidemiological data during a project, i.e. by using an external agency, there was no corporate memory process in place to ensure this data was re-exploited effectively. We were therefore faced with three problems to solve as we aimed to be proactive in meeting demand from our internal customers.</p>
<p>We looked at available commercial products, both those we already purchase and those we do not. However our current tools, although reliable, did not cover all the markets we were interested in or present the data in the formats we needed. We wanted from the onset of the project to collect worldwide epidemiology data and not just focus on the traditional top seven markets.</p>
<p>This was because we understood that the changing biopharmaceutical landscape meant that emerging countries were becoming increasingly key and good quality data on these countries was needed. Additionally we wanted to try to deliver patient numbers that reflected the particular patient segment that the Merck Serono drug would target. Commercial products were not able to deliver consistently on these two key requirements. However we also realized that the products and tools we already had were being under-exploited and that by adding a process and methodology we could deliver data closer to our requirements using already paid for resources. Gaps in data would then be more readily identifiable and we could use external data to fill gaps but in a controlled way, thus managing costs closely.</p>
<p>Our goal for the project then became to create our own searchable database of validated epidemiology data, open to all Merck Serono employees, to serve as a basis for forecast calculations for indications of interest to Merck Serono.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0266382112456272">
<title>The project deliverables</title>
<p>Our specific project goals were to deliver:<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>A tool to capture the data, and provide data in tabular and graphical formats, with supporting literature and bibliography.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>A process to source epidemiological data:<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Internal data review and gap analysis</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>External data to fill gaps</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>A data assessment and validation process to apply to all data, both internal and external.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0266382112456272">
<title>Design and implementation</title>
<p>How did we begin the implementation of the project? The first step was to design and create a tool to capture and store the data. We wanted to create a flexible tool that could grow with demand to store the data and to provide a user interface to extract the data in different formats as required by different user groups. An external provider was used to design an Excel based tool. Previous experience of implementing tools and databases meant we wanted a tool that could be updated and amended by the internal administrator as much as possible without recourse to the external supplier. Selecting Excel was done partly in response to this need and also to improve compatibility of sharing data with forecast models which are developed in Excel. The selected supplier has already worked extensively with our forecasting teams and is aware of their requirements.</p>
<p>The tool contains the epidemiology data and back-up data such as diagnosis and treatment algorithms<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0266382112456272">3</xref>
</sup>, registry sources<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0266382112456272">4</xref>
</sup>, age<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0266382112456272">5</xref>
</sup>, and gender<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0266382112456272">6</xref>
</sup> descriptions. It also includes a bibliography of all references used, with links to full-text, which we chose to store in our internal product literature database to avoid creating yet another repository.</p>
<p>The second step was to introduce a process which covers the data collection, validation and uploading to the tool (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0266382112456272">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0266382112456272" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Data collection, validation and uploading process.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0266382112456272-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The third and most critical step was to introduce a validation stage. This is the key to ensuring we have the right data in the tool. Normally, validation of sources and selection of the best quality resources would be done by a company epidemiologist, but this would not be possible for all projects. We needed to find a way to systematically and consistently interrogate the data with similar basic questions to those that an epidemiologist would ask of the source in order to be able to understand if it was a reliable high or low quality source. This was initially quite a hard brief to describe to potential external suppliers. However, the agency we selected worked with us very closely and we have developed a tool that has met our requirements very precisely. The DQAT– Data Quality Assessment Tool – is our solution to the validation problem and has allowed us to validate references successfully thus ensuring that customers have confidence in the data we input into the tool.</p>
<p>The tool allows side-by-side comparison of data sources, ranking the quality of the data in epidemiological terms. Study attributes ranked include: who initiated the study (e.g. WHO or government or a private company); who funded the study; age of the study (e.g. more or less than ten years old); study design (observational or interventional); sample size; gender and age distribution of population; inclusion and exclusion of study. The tool uses Excel and by answering questions in response to a series of drop down options a score per paper is obtained. Classification of the score is as follows:<disp-quote>
<p>75–100  High quality data</p>
<p>50–74.99 Good quality data</p>
<p>25–49.99 Moderate quality data</p>
<p>0–24.99  Low quality data</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The tool is relatively intuitive and quick to use. The average time to score a scientific paper, for example, is approximately five minutes. The tool is designed to measure the quality of the data rather than the quality of the study. This is an important distinction. The tool measures the quality of data from a variety of sources, not just scientific papers, for example, registries and websites. DQAT has been tested by people with different levels of epidemiology experience and a consistency of scoring has been observed. It has also been assessed by our internal epidemiologists with favourable responses. We therefore have high confidence in its use. It allows us to rank sources and to provide a concrete argument for using one reference in preference to another. This counters situations where the tendency in the past may have been to select the paper with the highest number (which may produce a more positive forecast) or an average between two or more references. The external supplier has since developed a commercial version of this tool.</p>
<p>The scores are included in the epidemiology resource. In this way users of the tool can see both the reference and its validation score. For simplicity within the tool we translate into three scores only: High (60–100); Medium (25–49); Low (0–24.99). The actual DQAT score is also recorded. The scores are linked to a ‘traffic light’ option enabled in the tool. If the DQAT score option is selected then the references are colour-coded to reflect their scoring (High – green; Medium – orange; Low – red). This way the user can see at a glance across a worldwide set of figures the variation in quality of data available. It is important to understand that in many cases there is only one reference for a country available but it may not be of excellent quality. We need to include it, but we also need to ensure that the user of the tool understands the difference in quality level between this reference and others.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0266382112456272">
<title>Sponsorship - senior level buy-in</title>
<p>How did we sell the tool in the organization and encourage adoption of its use? It was important to get senior management buy-in for the project. We obtained a high-level sponsor, in this case a member of the Executive Committee. This was less difficult than we anticipated and our request to have such a sponsor was made and accepted with no issue. Having such a high-level sponsor is valuable in several ways. It helps in improving visibility for the project as well as ensuring the budget gets approved and is available. It also helps overcome any difficulty in getting internal help or support; the sponsor can be asked to provide assistance.</p>
<p>In order to maximize adoption of the database as a trusted resource, we also needed to get cross-functional support and buy-in for using the tool and acceptance of its methodology for selecting the references for inclusion. To this end we created a cross-functional steering committee, meeting annually, which is responsible for directing the project, validating the project methodology, and acting as project ambassadors within their own functions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0266382112456272">
<title>Indication teams</title>
<p>Within the tool we have different levels of data capture. For indications key to Merck Serono where we know forecasts will be generated regularly, we have a more complex capture algorithm in the Excel tool so that we can manipulate the data with pre-set graphs and outputs. We capture the most detailed breakdowns by patient segments and diagnosis and treatment rates can be applied. For these indications, specific indication teams are created; they take decisions firstly on which data points to collect, how the data should be presented in the tool, and which data will be of most value in the project<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0266382112456272">7</xref>
</sup> going forward. Once data is collected, if there are any final decisions on which references to use, the team makes a consensus decision. Team members can include representatives from forecasting, marketing, pricing and health economics, portfolio management, the global product team, clinical/medical, research, commercial, key emerging countries and the US. Each indication team does not necessarily have all these participants but there is always a representative from forecasting, the global product team, clinical/medical and the US.</p>
<p>We also recognized that to create an indication team and collect data to the level of detail for the major indications was not possible for all indications in terms of resources and time required. For the capture of indications less frequently forecasted but still relevant to the company, we use a very simple input sheet and no special outputs and focus on capturing incidence and prevalence data only (always on a worldwide basis). This is done normally by literature search and using other sources such as market reports, registry data for example. All the data collected is scored using the DQAT tool and these scores are recorded. This ensures that we are creating a corporate memory and will be able to build on the information to develop more complex indication platforms in the future without having to re-do work.</p>
<p>Engaging cross-functional teams from the beginning of the individual indication projects ensures we maximize the buy-in to the end results. The indication teams benefit from the knowledge and experience of Merck Serono experts in all the areas – particularly in understanding the specific data we need for each individual indication. Leveraging knowledge from internal people also means we can understand sources or references that have already been used or captured in the project so far. Our goal is to be involved at the beginning of the projects and to work with the global product teams to capture the data required at an early stage and to develop the data with the project as patient segments, etc. are refined.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0266382112456272">
<title>Users</title>
<p>Our primary users are the forecasting teams, and their requirements have driven the key decisions on how to organize and present the data in the tool. However, the tool is also used by those in the business development teams and clinical and marketing teams who need to understand patient numbers and demographics to inform decisions about potential directions for the drug candidate in development. The resource is open to all Merck Serono employees, with no password control.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0266382112456272">
<title>Promotion</title>
<p>How do we get people to use the tool? The most important factor here has been to deliver good quality data. If data is reliable and well-referenced users have greater confidence in using it. We have used as many internal communication channels as we can, to share the availability of this resource with employees across Merck Serono worldwide (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0266382112456272">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0266382112456272" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p> Internal communication channels.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0266382112456272" xlink:href="10.1177_0266382112456272-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Tool</th>
<th>Target audience</th>
<th>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Dedicated intranet page with an easy to remember URL where we can share the tools as well as information on epidemiology good practice, definitions, and explanation of key terms, useful links and contacts internally and externally</td>
<td>All employees</td>
<td rowspan="2">Pull</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Flyers</td>
<td>All employees at corporate</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Internal news screens in corporate office</td>
<td>All employees</td>
<td rowspan="5">Push</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Global news messaging services</td>
<td>All employees</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Presentations at meetings</td>
<td>Key stakeholders</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Presentations on our behalf to affiliates by Business Unit trainers or Marketing Academy</td>
<td>Key stakeholders in affiliate countries</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>e-Learning presentation</td>
<td>All employees</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0266382112456272">
<title>Key lessons</title>
<p>What went well? What not so well? There are several lessons we can take forward:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>We initially launched the project without the necessary focus on the validation component. This deficiency became evident quite early on and we then worked on a solution before continuing with the rest of the project.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>It is easy to underestimate the time needed to work on each individual indication fully.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>The project has now shifted its focus to pipeline rather than marketed projects as we have learnt from our customers that this is where we can add most value.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>We need to create output from the tool that we can ‘push’ to customers – a standard PowerPoint template that in turn will further encourage ‘pull’ of the data from the tool.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>We must continue to talk and listen to our customers to further refine the tool and the outputs to maximize use and value.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0266382112456272">
<title>Benefits and value</title>
<p>How have we added value to tools we are purchasing already? What have been the success factors in using our approach rather than relying on existing commercial sources? The development of the DQAT tool and the ability to rank references with a consistent methodology has been very successful.</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>In project meetings where previously there was disagreement on prevalence numbers to use, we have found that taking the team through the DQAT analysis has enabled better resolution and agreement on the final number we should take into the forecast.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Having an organized and reliable set of data with validated numbers and actual references in a standardized format available quickly has saved time and budget.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>The ability to be able to provide worldwide data rather than top seven country data has been valued by users of the tool, especially as more and more projects are looking at emerging countries.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>One key measure of success is that now we receive epidemiology data requests for indications not yet available in the tool on a much more regular basis demonstrating trust in our methodology.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0266382112456272">
<title>Example 2 – market attractiveness platform – <italic>project still in development</italic>
</title>
<sec id="section18-0266382112456272">
<title>Background</title>
<p>The market attractiveness project came about partly as an extension to the epidemiology resource project and partly in response to a specific internal request. Consolidating epidemiological information, and having it available for emerging countries made us think about the other data that would make a particular country or market, where presently we are not so active, attractive for possible development. At the same time as we began to think about what those elements would be – regulatory<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0266382112456272">8</xref>
</sup> and reimbursement<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0266382112456272">9</xref>
</sup> regimes, distribution channels<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0266382112456272">10</xref>
</sup>, economic situation; for example, the Business Development department asked if data to support the attractiveness of marketing a potential out-licensing candidate to emerging countries in Asia and Latin America could be found. The data we would need in order to put together such an overview was already available in purchased resources or as internal knowledge but not consolidated in a way that enabled decisions to be made.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0266382112456272">
<title>Project scope</title>
<p>We have scoped a pilot project to consolidate data and build a tool – the Market Attractiveness Platform (MAPs) – that will provide access to individual, validated data resources as well as providing a tool for evaluating market attractiveness using a structured and consistent set of parameters.</p>
<p>The platform will help Merck Serono employees to develop greater understanding and identify gaps and unmet needs in traditional and emerging markets in order to make strategic decisions. The specific objectives of the pilot project were:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>To create an internal online platform that will allow Merck Serono decision makers to evaluate the market attractiveness using a consistent set of parameters.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To build a value added platform to take data from different internal and external primary and secondary sources and transform it into validated, structured and consistent data that can be used for analysis.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To establish attributes and relative weighting to the data included in the MAPs platform. The data will be set to reliable, referenced, and standard measures.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To apply forecast elements to the data.</p>
</list-item>
</list>One of the biggest benefits of this project was that data, usually only looked at by country, was collected in a centralized and formatted way, allowing comparison and ranking of countries. The number of different sources here is far greater than for the epidemiology tool. Increased value would be gained in our ability to analyze this data using rating algorithms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0266382112456272">
<title>Platform design</title>
<p>The pilot MAPs consists of 17 example countries representing Latin America and Asia mainly (with Russia also included). We have used three reference countries: Germany, France and the US to serve as benchmarks when rating and ranking the attractiveness of markets.</p>
<p>We are focusing the initial tool in the Rheumatology space and have selected the following data points, most of which are non-indication specific:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Epidemiology (indication-specific).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Uptake of Rheumatology biologics (indication-specific).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Regulatory regime.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Reimbursement and pricing regime.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Health care infrastructure.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Macroenvironment.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Merck Serono infrastructure.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Medical and patient associations (indication-specific).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
The MAPs home page is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0266382112456272">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0266382112456272" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>MAPs home page.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0266382112456272-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Each data point will have a weighting and within each category there could be several individual measurements each of which would have a weighting within that category.</p>
<p>As this is a pilot project and we have limited resources, we have begun by building a simple Excel database. We have used already available secondary data to build the individual data points, except distribution channels, where we have asked an external agency to provide this data as insufficient data was available internally. We have also asked the same agency to work with us on developing the weighting and ranking algorithms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0266382112456272">
<title>Benefits and value</title>
<p>The pilot is almost completed and we will now work closely with potential customers to identify the most useful questions the tool should answer, refining the resource to be fit-for-purpose. The value of having some of this data, particularly the overviews on reimbursement and pricing in emerging countries, is already clear. External suppliers are now putting together tools which have similar overviews so we are ahead in having this data already available and tailored to Merck Serono's needs. Our internal consulting department are already users of the macro-economic data sections. As we show this to other teams we are confident that new uses and users will become evident.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0266382112456272">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Both products – the Epidemiology Resource and MAPs – demonstrate there is additional value to be gained by systematically combining data from internal and external resources and knowledge. In the epidemiology project we have already seen savings in time and money as well as an increase in confidence in epidemiology data. As an information team we have also seen a huge increase in our own use of purchased databases, for examples, the epidemiology database and pharmaceutical country report databases. Previously these were underused even by ourselves but their value has increased as we use them to regularly feed our own company-centric resources. Using them as sources for these projects has in turn raised their profile to our end-users and customers now access these tools more frequently.</p>
<p>Our approach and the availability of these new tools certainly make it easier to identify real gaps in our information sources. Only specific data has to be obtained externally. Additionally, we are improving our corporate memory by storing more analyzed data so that work does not have to be re-done. All this represents budget savings, both in terms of time and money, which in today’s cost-conscious environment is key.</p>
<p>As an information team our profile has been raised in the organization by these kinds of projects, particularly the epidemiology resource. We are now far more frequently asked to provide epidemiology data. This encourages us to look at other areas where we could use a more pro-active approach to deliver packaged information that delivers business benefits. It additionally helps us as information teams to focus secondary data requirements on products which fit identified gaps.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0266382112456272">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Managing Costs &amp; Promoting Value in Corporate Libraries: Key Findings &amp; Profiles of Benchmark Partners. Best Practices, LLC.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0266382112456272">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Forecasts for marketed products are usually sales based, measuring the number of actual and potential drug sales.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0266382112456272">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Diagnosis and treatment algorithms present the standard flow for the patient when presenting to the physician with their symptoms. The diagnosis algorithm will describe the symptoms and/or laboratory test results that need to be present for a positive diagnosis, and may also describe the disease by stages or segments e.g. mild, moderate, or severe form of the disease. The treatment algorithm will present the standard course of treatment(s) recommended. Both are often internationally recognized algorithms. There may be alternative algorithms presented by different international bodies.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0266382112456272">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Registries refer to files of data concerning all cases of a particular disease or other health-relevant condition in a defined population such that the cases can be related to a population base. If a registry exists for a disease, either in one country or across several they are an extremely useful tool for ongoing incidence and prevalence data.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0266382112456272">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Diseases can be linked to age, some diseases affect mainly elderly people, for example Alzheimer’s Disease. If the link between age and the disease is well documented, we note this in the database so that we may also set an age limit to the population number to give a more accurate number of potential patients.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0266382112456272">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Gender, as for age above, if a disease is particularly prevalent in males rather than females we note this in the database as this could also be a potential limit in order to give a more accurate number of potential patients.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0266382112456272">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Projects refer to the development of a drug candidate through its entire lifecycle from research through to marketing. Each project is associated with a Global Product Team which is formed at a very early stage in the drug development process, usually at the stage of a molecule showing potential in a number of indications. The team will change membership as the drug progresses through its lifecycle of clinical testing and eventual launch on the market, however at all stages the number of potential patients is a key data that they need to add into decisions on whether to continue development.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0266382112456272">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Regulatory bodies approve drugs for use in individual countries. The procedures and process for approval by a regulatory authority vary from country to country.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0266382112456272">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Reimbursement refers to the government funding or sponsorship for drugs. Reimbursement policies for prescription and over-the-counter drug vary enormously from country to country. This factor is increasingly significant in all markets, both traditional and emerging as government spending is reduced for healthcare.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0266382112456272">
<label>10.</label>
<p>How drugs are distributed within a country – through pharmacies, hospitals etc. can also be a very significant factor in understanding how attractive a market may be. Especially when considering emerging markets with a high rural population.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</back>
</article>