<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PUN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppun</journal-id>
<journal-title>Punishment &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1462-4745</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3095</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1462474511434435</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1462474511434435</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Less interest, less treatment: Mexican‐American youth and the Los Angeles Juvenile Court in the Great Depression era</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Schlossman</surname><given-names>Michael B.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1462474511434435"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1462474511434435">Princeton University, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1462474511434435">Michael B. Schlossman, Princeton University – Sociology, 106 Wallace Hall, Princeton, New Jersey 08544, USA. Email: <email>mschloss@princeton.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>216</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study uses case records from the Los Angeles Juvenile Court to examine how racial discrimination played out in juvenile justice before the decline of public confidence in rehabilitation in the 1960s and 1970s. Using qualitative and quantitative methodologies, I compare how Mexican‐American and white boys (ages 10–17) were treated by the juvenile court during the Great Depression era. I find that although Mexican‐American boys were more likely to be arrested and petitioned to court, they were less likely to receive out‐of‐family placements because court officials viewed these placements as beneficial and were less interested in rehabilitating minority than white youth. I compare these results with the current overrepresentation of minorities in institutional confinement and with contemporary studies that find that black youth are punished more severely than comparable whites. My research suggests that there have been major philosophical changes in how officials in the juvenile justice system view out‐of‐family placements, and that patterns of discrimination in juvenile justice depend upon how officials in courts and correctional institutions view the rehabilitative potential of their interventions.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>history</kwd>
<kwd>juvenile justice system</kwd>
<kwd>Latinos</kwd>
<kwd>punishment</kwd>
<kwd>rehabilitation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1462474511434435" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Over the course of more than a century, the American juvenile justice system has undergone significant changes. Judge Ben <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1462474511434435">Lindsey (1903: 210)</xref>, a prominent early 20th‐century juvenile court advocate, characterized the court's mission as taking ‘care of these children in adolescence, when character is plastic and can be molded as clay in the potter's hands’. Lindsey and other juvenile court reformers faithfully believed in the malleability of children and the State's ability to transform troubled youth into better citizens. The early juvenile court proponents assumed that fatherly, compassionate judges and well‐trained probation officers would assist parents in guiding their children through adolescence while simultaneously rooting out the causes of crime. When the informal controls of the family and community failed, the court would remove the youth from the adverse environment on the legal grounds of <italic>parens patriae</italic>, or the State acting as parent in the child's best interest.</p>
<p>Today, these early proponents’ blind confidence in the rehabilitative potential of the juvenile justice system seems misguided and out‐of‐date. In particular, beliefs about the positive effect of removing a youth from his home and placing him in an institution have been replaced by profound skepticism about the ability of out‐of‐home placements to rehabilitate and the prospect of doing more harm than good (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1462474511434435">Allen, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1462474511434435">Miller, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1462474511434435">Petrosino et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1462474511434435">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1462474511434435">President's Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice, 1967</xref>). While most Americans and juvenile court officials still believe in trying to rehabilitate delinquent youths (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1462474511434435">Piquero et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1462474511434435">Sanborn, 1994</xref>), there is much greater skepticism about the usefulness of out‐of‐home placements for this purpose in light of the many past and recent reports of physical and sexual abuse in juvenile institutions, and evidence that, in practice, the goals of maintaining order and control often trump that of treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1462474511434435">Governor David Paterson's Task Force on Transforming Juvenile Justice, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1462474511434435">Krisberg, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1462474511434435">Miller, 1991</xref>). Although liberals and conservatives may differ over the number of children who need to be incarcerated, there is a growing consensus in the USA that placement should be utilized primarily to protect the public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1462474511434435">Fagan, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1462474511434435">Maloney et al., 1988</xref>).</p>
<p>Reformers and scholars concerned with the negative effects of institutional confinement on the well‐being of children are particularly concerned about the disproportionate share of racial minorities in juvenile custodial institutions, which has increased as a result of the ‘get tough’ movement of the 1980s and 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1462474511434435">Bishop, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1462474511434435">Piquero, 2008</xref>). In 1999, for every 100,000 non‐Hispanic black juveniles living in the USA, 1004 were in a residential placement facility; the rate was 485 per 100,000 for Hispanics and 212 for non‐Hispanic whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1462474511434435">Feld, 1999</xref>). In addition, while racial differences in offending partially account for these disparities, most studies of sentencing have found that black juveniles are sentenced more harshly than legally comparable whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1462474511434435">Bishop, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1462474511434435">Bishop and Frazier, 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1462474511434435">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1462474511434435">DeJong and Jackson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1462474511434435">Leiber and Johnson, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1462474511434435">Piquero, 2008</xref>; though see contra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1462474511434435">Guevara et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1462474511434435">Leiber, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1462474511434435">Tracy, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Based on contemporary patterns of Disproportionate Minority Confinement (DMC), juvenile justice scholars sometimes assume that court officials have always disproportionately institutionalized blacks and Latinos compared to whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1462474511434435">Feld, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1462474511434435">Piquero, 2008</xref>). However, this argument may ignore the major historical transformation that has occurred in the mission of the juvenile court and the rationale behind its use of out‐of‐home placements, and the effect these changes may have had on patterns of discrimination in sentencing.</p>
<p>Using case files from the Los Angeles Juvenile Court during the Great Depression era (1930–1940), I investigate how Mexican Americans were treated by the juvenile justice system at a time when there was greater confidence in rehabilitation than in later years. While Mexican‐American youth were overrepresented in the Los Angeles Juvenile Court, I find that they were, in fact, <italic>less</italic> likely to be removed from their homes than comparable whites. In a juvenile justice system in which there was still confidence in using out‐of‐home placements to accomplish rehabilitation, I conclude that officials were more interested in ‘saving’ white than minority youths.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-1462474511434435"><title>The Los Angeles Juvenile Court</title>
<p>As the following quotation suggests, the Los Angeles Juvenile Court in the 1930s espoused its philosophy of punishment in the language of <italic>parens patriae</italic>: as treatment for the good of the child (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>). Chief Probation Officer Kenyon J. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1462474511434435">Scudder (1936: 11)</xref> wrote:<disp-quote>
<p>The Juvenile Court is not then interested in the old custom of punishment. In its place we find the new philosophy: Adjustment through Corrective Discipline and Guidance. Even the terms Delinquency and Dependency have no place in the picture. Here is a Court of Treatment.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>From its founding in 1903, the Los Angeles Juvenile Court was considered one of the most advanced courts in the country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1462474511434435">Odem, 1995</xref>). The Court's Chief Probation Officer in the late 1930s and early 1940s, Karl Holton, would eventually be selected as the first director of the pioneering California Youth Authority (CYA). The court's juvenile detention center, or Juvenile Hall, was regarded as one of the best of its kind (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1462474511434435">Mihailoff, 2005</xref>). Likewise, in the 1920s, California's state reform school for younger boys, the Fred C. Nelles School at Whittier, was regarded as advanced for its provision of professional psychological services and comprehensive educational and vocational training programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1462474511434435">Cox and Shelly, 1940</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1462474511434435">Schlossman and Pisciotta, 1986</xref>).</p>
<p>During the Great Depression era, the quality of California's reform schools deteriorated as a result of budget cuts and staff turnover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1462474511434435">Mihailoff, 2005</xref>). Two suicides of Mexican‐American youths being housed in the Lost Privileges Cottage at the Nelles School – and several investigations suggesting that they resulted from the frequent use of corporal punishment and degrading conditions – forced a reevaluation of California's juvenile justice system, and provided momentum for creating the CYA in 1941. The CYA's goal was to provide more oversight of institutions like Whittier, better classification of delinquent youth through scientific methods, and specialized facilities for different types of juveniles. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1462474511434435">Mihailoff (2005)</xref> argues, rather than leading to the abandonment of the rehabilitative ideal – as similar incidents did in the 1960s and 1970s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1462474511434435">Allen, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1462474511434435">Miller, 1991</xref>) – the suicides at Whittier actually led to renewed confidence in the ability of re‐designed, professionally administered state institutions to rehabilitate.</p>
<p>In response to the depression economy of the 1930s, Los Angeles invented forestry camps, which court officials conceived as a cheaper and more effective out‐of‐home placement than traditional reform schools. In the forestry camp programs, the Probation Department partnered with the County Forestry Department. During an average stay of four months, youth participated in projects such as reforestation, fire fighting, and trail clearing; boys earned money from their work that they received upon release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1462474511434435">Scudder, 1936</xref>). Corporal discipline was forbidden at the forestry camps, as was deprivation of food, segregation, or lockups. There were no barbed‐wire fences and the forestry camps mainly depended on youth self‐government and peer pressure to maintain discipline and order (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1462474511434435">Close, 1945</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1462474511434435">Scudder, 1936</xref>). Bernard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1462474511434435">Kogon (1958: 37)</xref>, a probation officer, observed that the forestry camp program was pervaded by ‘the broad philosophy upon which the juvenile court movement is based’. He continued,<disp-quote>
<p>In this sense, the camps do have a philosophy which sees each boy, however delinquent his behavior may have been, as a minor in need of care and protection of the state, rather than as a criminal to be punished.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>In sum, during the height of the Great Depression era, forestry camps were portrayed as therapeutic custodial institutions. They embodied the continuing confidence of juvenile justice officials in Los Angeles in the right kinds of out‐of‐home placements to rehabilitate persistently delinquent youth.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec3-1462474511434435"><title>Mexican Americans in Los Angeles during the Great Depression Era</title>
<p>The case of Mexican‐American youth<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1462474511434435">1</xref></sup> is an especially informative lens for studying racial discrimination more generally. Some scholars have compared the treatment of Mexican Americans in Los Angeles to that of blacks in the South during Jim Crow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>). Mexicans Americans suffered regular discrimination; they were prohibited from certain whites‐only parks and restaurants, and they were assigned mainly to segregated schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1462474511434435">Balderrama and Rodríguez, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1462474511434435">Blanton, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1462474511434435">González, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>In the 1930s, anti‐Mexican sentiment crystallized into a widespread effort by federal, state, and county governments to deport and repatriate Mexican immigrants. Some scholars estimate that over 500,000 Mexicans and Mexican Americans were deported or repatriated to Mexico, including many who were American citizens and were forced out illegally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1462474511434435">Molina, 2006</xref>). Federal immigration agents, state and county welfare workers, local police, social workers, and (as will be illustrated) juvenile court officials all cooperated in this repatriation effort, in spite of the active resistance of Mexican‐American families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1462474511434435">Balderrama and Rodríguez, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Despite this active repatriation effort, by 1940, due to migration from other areas, Mexican Americans probably made up an even greater percentage of Los Angeles's population than in 1930 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>). The Mexican Americans who stayed were more likely to have children than those who left (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1462474511434435">Sanchez, 1993</xref>). This younger ‘Mexican‐American generation’, according to recent scholars, grew up alienated from both their immigrant parents’ cultural traditions and mainstream, white American culture, from which they were socially excluded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1462474511434435">Alvarez, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1462474511434435">Pagán, 2003</xref>). Within this context, some Mexican‐American youth began rebelling against their second‐class status; a relatively small share began symbolizing their rebellion by wearing the provocative ‘zoot suit’ and adopting the ‘<italic>la vida loca</italic>’ (the crazy life) culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>). At the same time, an increasingly professionalized Police Juvenile Division began focusing ‘preventive patrol’ on Mexican‐American neighborhoods, leading to increased surveillance and harassment of Mexican‐American boys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1462474511434435">Pagán, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>While the Los Angeles police may have viewed Mexican‐American youths as particularly criminal and requiring state intervention, juvenile court officials did not respond the same way. Karl Holton argued that the police and the press had overblown the Mexican‐American juvenile crime problem. ‘There is no ‘wave of lawlessness’ among Mexican children,’ he insisted, although he also noted, ‘there is a specific problem of gang violence that must be, and is being dealt with’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1462474511434435">Holton, 1942</xref>: 4). Meanwhile, the police expressed dismay that when a boy was arrested and sent to juvenile court and then received nothing more than a sentence of probation, he became a ‘big shot’ in his neighborhood and other boys emulated his behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>: 212). Thus, there was considerable disagreement, indeed, outright tension during the 1930s and 1940s between police and juvenile court officials in Los Angeles as to the scope and nature of the Mexican‐American crime problem, and what to do about it.</p>
<p>At the same time, court officials were not necessarily sympathetic in their views of Mexican Americans, and sometimes portrayed them in stereotypic language. In 1936, Chief Probation Officer Kenyon Scudder noted that,<disp-quote>
<p>The Mexican family, once their children are cared for by the Court, become themselves serious problems. Naturally the care given is often better than the parents have ever been able to give. Some Mexican families endeavor to take advantage of this situation and rather expect to have the whole family cared for in like manner. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1462474511434435">Scudder, 1936</xref>: 23)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Scudder clearly viewed the interventions of the court as a form of child welfare, and expressed a common view of the time that Mexican Americans were taking advantage of the superior resources that US residency offered them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1462474511434435">Balderrama and Rodríguez, 2006</xref>).</p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-1462474511434435"><title>Data and methods</title>
<p>I turn now to an analysis of juvenile court decision making during the Great Depression era, drawing data from a systematic sample of one of five delinquency<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1462474511434435">2</xref></sup> cases that were formally petitioned to the Los Angeles Juvenile Court in the years 1930 and 1940. The case files are richly detailed for content analysis and enable micro‐level, qualitative assessment of punishment decisions. The qualitative data are drawn primarily from probation reports (both pre‐disposition and follow‐up reports), but also from court transcripts, hearing reports, police reports, psychiatric assessments, school reports, and Juvenile Hall (detention) reports. Probation report information comes primarily from interviews conducted with each boy and at least one family member (usually parents), but also from the other sources listed above, as well as neighbors and other groups the youth associated with. While there is variation in the level of detail provided in probation reports, they consistently record and group data into the following sections: petition; previous court history; family history; boy's history; analysis; and recommendation (to the presiding judge).</p>
<p>In general, of course, probation reports cannot be viewed simply as pure and accurate factual reporting of a youth's situation. If a probation officer had already determined what should happen to a youth, he might have biased the report to emphasize certain facts, or even conceal facts that were inconsistent with his recommendation. For example, one might expect a probation officer to identify extended family members more for Mexican Americans than for whites, if the court anticipated relying more on them to save the expense and reserve the benefit of an out‐of‐family placement for white youth.</p>
<p>That said, the record keeping was quite comprehensive. In 89 percent of the cases, a youth's age, race, family structure, prior criminal record, and family welfare status were all reported. Likewise, most probation officers seemed meticulous about collecting a wide variety of information about each youth's social situation, especially his schooling, work status, and friendship networks.</p>
<p>To complement the rich, textual data in the case files, 95 legal, family, youth, and demographic variables were coded to permit quantitative analysis of court decisions.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1462474511434435">3</xref></sup> Legal variables included the referral source, the most serious offense, additional offenses, previous court appearances, prior problems (whether or not a youth had prior police contacts or prior truancies or disciplinary issues reported by school officials), prior out‐of‐family placements, as well as the initial disposition (sentence). Family variables included family structure, welfare status, parents’ citizenship status, occupation, and income. Juvenile variables included gang membership, race,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1462474511434435">4</xref></sup> IQ, school status and achievement, place of birth, and employment status.</p>
<p>Several of these variables have missing data on more than one‐third of the cases and are, therefore, excluded from the analysis. Also, because of the small sample size and problems of multicollinearity, only a select group of variables are presented in the descriptive and inferential analyses. For the regression analysis presented below, males of any race other than whites and Mexicans were eliminated; female cases were also removed from all analyses. This process of elimination left 679 cases, 82 of which were then removed because of missing data in the independent variables. The final sample size for the two years (1930 and 1940) was 597: 450 white and 147 Mexican.</p>
<p>The dependent variable, out‐of‐family placement (OFP), is a binary measure of whether a youth was given a within‐family or an out‐of‐family placement as his initial disposition on the original petition offense. If the disposition resulted in removal to a county custodial facility (e.g. forestry camp), state reform school, or a private boarding home, the variable was coded as a 1. If the boy received any other disposition, including probation at home (the most common), probation with relatives, dismissal, or transfer to adult criminal court (<italic>n</italic> = 3), or to another county, OFP was coded as 0.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-1462474511434435"><title>Race and punishment in Los Angeles Juvenile Court: A descriptive analysis</title>
<p>Currently, minority youth are highly overrepresented in juvenile arrest and court referral data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1462474511434435">Bishop, 2005</xref>). Similarly, as indicated by <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1462474511434435">Table 1</xref>, blacks and Mexican Americans in Los Angeles in 1930 and 1940 were overrepresented among youth arrested and petitioned to court (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>). Although most historians believe these Census estimates undercount Mexican Americans by a few percentage points, it is extremely unlikely that 23 percent of the population was Mexican‐American in Los Angeles at this time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1462474511434435">Sanchez, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1462474511434435">5</xref></sup> As noted, during the 1930s the police in Los Angeles began to see crime more and more through the lens of race. As the police professionalized, they focused their car patrols on Mexican‐American neighborhoods in particular and, therefore, had increasing contact with and arrested Mexican Americans disproportionately (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>). It is also possible, of course, that Mexican‐American youth – who lived mainly in high‐poverty, socially disorganized neighborhoods – were more likely to be arrested than white youth because they more frequently committed crimes and belonged to organized gangs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1462474511434435">Moore, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1462474511434435">Shaw and McKay, 1942</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1462474511434435">Vigil, 1988</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table1-1462474511434435" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Race of boys in the Los Angeles Juvenile Court compared to Census figures, 1930 and 1940</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1462474511434435" xlink:href="10.1177_1462474511434435-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th colspan="3">1930<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">1940<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Race</th>
<th>Census</th>
<th>Boys</th>
<th>Boys petitioned to</th>
<th>Census</th>
<th>Boys</th>
<th>Boys petitioned to</th></tr>
<tr><th/>
<th>estimates (%)</th>
<th>arrested (%)</th>
<th>juvenile court (%)</th>
<th>estimates (%)</th>
<th>arrested (%)</th>
<th>juvenile court (%)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>White</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>61</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mexican</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>American</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Black</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>10</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>100</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1462474511434435"><p><italic>Note</italic>: Census estimates come from the US Bureau of the Census (1933: 260, 266), <italic>Fifteenth Census</italic>, Population, Bureau of the Census (1943: 629) <italic>Sixteenth Census</italic>, Population, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott (2005: 162–163)</xref>. Census figures are for the general population rather than the age‐relevant (10–17) population, due to this figure not being reported for Mexican Americans in 1940. Statistics on the number of boys arrested are also drawn from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott's (2005)</xref> analysis of the Los Angeles Police Department's annual reports. The race of boys petitioned to court, in contrast to the Census and arrest data, is not a population figure but is drawn from a sample of one out of every five delinquency cases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Today, racial disparities in juvenile court sentencing are not as great as in arrest and referral. Still, nationally, a disproportionate share of black youth who are adjudicated delinquent in juvenile court are given out‐of‐home placements compared to whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1462474511434435">Bishop, 2005</xref>: 33; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1462474511434435">Fagan, 2010</xref>). By contrast, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1462474511434435">Table 2</xref> shows that in both 1930 and 1940, among youth petitioned to court (the majority of whom were adjudicated delinquent), fewer Mexican Americans were placed out of family than whites. In 1930, only four Mexican Americans, or 4 percent, were removed from their homes and placed with a non‐family member, compared to 12 percent of whites, a statistically significant difference (<italic>p</italic> = .03). In 1940, in the heat of what many believed to be a Mexican‐American youth crime wave, only 19 percent of Mexican Americans were given an out‐of‐family placement (OFP), compared to 30 percent of whites; this difference is close to being significant at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 level (<italic>p</italic> = .053).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1462474511434435">6</xref></sup>
<table-wrap id="table2-1462474511434435" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Description of placement by race, 1930 and 1940</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1462474511434435" xlink:href="10.1177_1462474511434435-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th colspan="3">1930<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th colspan="3">1940<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Race</th>
<th>In</th>
<th>Out of</th>
<th>Total</th>
<th/>
<th>In</th>
<th>Out of</th>
<th>Total</th></tr>
<tr><th/>
<th>family</th>
<th>family</th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th>family</th>
<th>family</th>
<th/></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>White</td>
<td>88%</td>
<td>12%</td>
<td>100%</td>
<td/>
<td>70%</td>
<td>30%</td>
<td>100%</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>265</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>301</td>
<td/>
<td>142</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>203</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mexican</td>
<td>97%</td>
<td>4%</td>
<td>100%</td>
<td/>
<td>81%</td>
<td>19%</td>
<td>100%</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>American</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>95</td>
<td/>
<td>65</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>80</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1462474511434435"><p><italic>Note</italic>: Table includes all cases of Mexican‐American and white boys in the sample, not just those included in the regression. Because of rounding, percentages may not add up to 100%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>In 1940, it should also be noted, the Los Angeles Juvenile Court was much more likely to give youth of any race an OFP than in 1930. A large part of this increase can be explained by the addition of the previously mentioned county forestry camps (for youth 16 and older). As a result, while only 0.5 percent of boys (<italic>n</italic> = 2) in 1930 were placed in county‐run institutions, in 1940 16 percent (<italic>n</italic> = 46) were placed in county‐run programs, the great majority in forestry camps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1462474511434435">Holton, 1940</xref>). Only 10 percent of Mexican Americans, compared to 19 percent of whites, were placed in a county‐run program in 1940; this difference is significant at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; .10 level. Similarly, a lower percentage of Mexican Americans in 1930 and 1940 combined were placed in private boarding homes than whites (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10), though there was virtually no difference in the percentage of each group sent to state reform school.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-1462474511434435"><title>Multivariate analysis</title>
<p>While the descriptive analysis is suggestive, without controls to ensure that comparable cases of whites and racial minorities are being compared, we cannot fairly deduce differential treatment or possible discrimination by the juvenile court. A relatively consistent research finding on juvenile court sentencing today is that while offense severity and, especially, prior record are the biggest predictors of OFPs, once these factors are controlled for, race still has an independent effect on sentencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1462474511434435">Bishop and Frazier, 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1462474511434435">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1462474511434435">Feld, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1462474511434435">Leiber and Jamieson, 1995</xref>). Likewise, many studies find that family structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1462474511434435">DeJong and Jackson, 1998</xref>), as well as social class and neighborhood factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1462474511434435">Rodriguez, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1462474511434435">Wu and Fuentes, 1998</xref>), affect court decision making. These latter studies sometimes find that race is still related to sentencing, but partially or completely through the effect of these other variables that are correlated with race (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1462474511434435">Bishop, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1462474511434435">DeJong and Jackson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1462474511434435">Wu and Fuentes, 1998</xref>). Fortunately, the data from Los Angeles Juvenile Court permit a test of both of these hypotheses (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1462474511434435">Table 3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table3-1462474511434435" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Family, demographic, and legal characteristics by race</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1462474511434435" xlink:href="10.1177_1462474511434435-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Variables</th>
<th colspan="2">Race<hr/></th>
<th/></tr>
<tr><th/>
<th>White</th>
<th>Mexican American</th>
<th><italic>P</italic>‐value</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>15.19</td>
<td>14.61</td>
<td>.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">***</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Single mother family</td>
<td>20.89%</td>
<td>27.89%</td>
<td>.078<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Single father family</td>
<td>6.89%</td>
<td>3.40%</td>
<td>.123</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>No parent in home</td>
<td>5.11%</td>
<td>14.29%</td>
<td>.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">***</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>On welfare</td>
<td>8.67%</td>
<td>29.93%</td>
<td>.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">***</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Born in California</td>
<td>39.11%</td>
<td>55.10%</td>
<td>.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">***</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Property offense</td>
<td>70.00%</td>
<td>73.47%</td>
<td>.422</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Status offense</td>
<td>22.67%</td>
<td>15.65%</td>
<td>.069<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Violent offense</td>
<td>4.00%</td>
<td>6.80%</td>
<td>.163</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other non‐property offense</td>
<td>3.33%</td>
<td>4.08%</td>
<td>.668</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Prior problems</td>
<td>57.78%</td>
<td>49.66%</td>
<td>.085<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1462474511434435">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>450</td>
<td>147</td>
<td/></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1462474511434435"><p><italic>Notes</italic>:</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1462474511434435"><p>Table combines cases from 1930 and 1940 and is limited to observations analyzed in the regression in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1462474511434435">Table 4</xref>. For all variables except age, a two‐sample test for a difference of proportions was used. For age, a two‐sample <italic>t</italic>‐test was performed. Over 70 percent of whites and Mexican Americans living with no parent were living with relatives.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1462474511434435"><p>*<italic>p</italic>&lt; .10; **<italic>p</italic>&lt; .05; ***<italic>p</italic>&lt; .01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1462474511434435">Table 4</xref> presents the odds‐ratios for the multivariate analysis. Because the dependent variable, OFP, is dichotomous (out‐of‐family placement is coded as 1, within‐family placement is coded as 0), I chose logistic regression as the method of estimation. The regression combines cases from 1930 and 1940, which gives the analysis greater statistical power than if the years were analyzed separately. Model 1 looks at the effect of being Mexican‐American with only the minimal controls. As previously discussed, the court was much more interventionist in 1940 than in 1930, and this can mainly be explained by the addition of county forestry camps during the mid‐1930s for youth age 16 and older. Likewise, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1462474511434435">Table 3</xref> shows that Mexican‐American boys in court were younger, on average, than white boys. Therefore, age, year, and an interaction between age and year were included to control for these differences and to examine the possible effect of forestry camp for older youth on placement. Model 2 adds variables meant to control for family structure and welfare status, which <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1462474511434435">Table 3</xref> suggests are correlated with being Mexican American. Given that Mexican‐American boys were significantly more likely to be receiving welfare, not living with their parental guardians, and more likely to have been born in California (which I use as a rough proxy of whether a boy had relatives in the area who might help with his supervision in the community), if any of these variables were also related to OFP, then the race effect could be spurious.
<table-wrap id="table4-1462474511434435" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Odds-ratios for logistic regression on out-of-family placement</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1462474511434435" xlink:href="10.1177_1462474511434435-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Variables</th>
<th>Model 1</th>
<th>Model 2</th>
<th>Model 3</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Race (Mexican American = 1)</td>
<td>0.510<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td>
<td>0.450<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td>
<td>0.496<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.156)</td>
<td>(0.152)</td>
<td>(0.171)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Older youth (16+)</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>1.099</td>
<td>1.129</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(.416)</td>
<td>(0.412)</td>
<td>(0.438)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Year (1940 = 1)</td>
<td>1.963<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td>
<td>1.913<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td>
<td>2.200<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.722)</td>
<td>(0.741)</td>
<td>(0.874)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Older youth<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref>1940</td>
<td>2.872<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td>
<td>3.179<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td>
<td>3.286<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(1.400)</td>
<td>(1.584)</td>
<td>(1.700)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Single mother family</td>
<td/>
<td>0.541<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td>
<td> 0.624</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.184)</td>
<td>(0.218)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Single father family</td>
<td/>
<td>1.682</td>
<td>1.695</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.741)</td>
<td>(0.788)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Not living with parents</td>
<td/>
<td>2.339<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td>
<td>2.026</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.980)</td>
<td>(0.884)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Welfare (Yes = 1)</td>
<td/>
<td>2.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">**</xref></td>
<td>1.996<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.704)</td>
<td>(0.710)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Born in California (Yes  = 1)</td>
<td/>
<td>0.623<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td>
<td>0.598<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.160)</td>
<td>(0.160)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Status offense</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.267</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.394)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Violent offense</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>2.887<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(1.633)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other non-property</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.497</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Offense</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.526)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Prior problems (Yes = 1)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>3.729<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1462474511434435">***</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(1.063)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>597</td>
<td>597</td>
<td>597</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Log likelihood</td>
<td>–237.79</td>
<td>–230.05</td>
<td>–215.51</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1462474511434435"><p><italic>Notes</italic>:</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1462474511434435"><p>Standard errors are in parentheses. The omitted category for the family structure variables is all two-parent households (including youth living with stepparents). The omitted category for the offense type variables is property crime.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-1462474511434435"><p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10; **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05; ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Last, Model 3 adds variables meant to control for the seriousness of a youth's offense profile and prior record. If police were more likely to refer Mexican‐American arrestees to court, or if juvenile intake officers were more likely to file petitions against them, it is possible they had less serious offense and prior record profiles than whites. Assuming that court officials took offense severity and prior record into account, and that Mexican Americans had a less ‘hardcore’ profile, the court might have been treating them even‐handedly, even if the police were not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1462474511434435">Emerson, 1969</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1462474511434435">Table 3</xref> tells us that in terms of offense, the Mexican Americans and whites in court were overall very similar, though a significantly greater percentage of whites were charged with a status offense (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10). There is also a significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10) between the groups in the presence of prior problems<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1462474511434435">7</xref></sup> reported by police and school authorities. Conceivably, for non‐status offense cases, there may have been some discrimination at an early stage in the police arrest and referral or court intake process, leading younger and less serious Mexican‐American youth to make their way to court whereas similar white youth were screened out. While these data do not allow for an examination of the intake process, these descriptive patterns suggest the need to examine whether being Mexican‐American has a significant effect on OFP after controlling for offense type and prior record.</p>
<p>The results from the first model show the expected Mexican‐American effect on OFP. Not surprisingly, older youth (&gt; = 16) in 1940 were significantly more likely to be given an OFP as a result of the availability of forestry camps for boys in this age category in 1940. Model 2 is an improvement according to a Chi Squared test that finds a significant difference in the model fit statistics compared to the first model. Even though Mexican Americans are significantly more likely to have been born in California, be on welfare, and not live with either parent – and these variables have a significant effect on out‐of‐family placement – race remains significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) after they are added to the model.</p>
<p>A Chi Squared test found a significant difference in the model fit statistics between Models 2 and 3. While committing a violent offense has a small, significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10) effect on OFP, prior problems has by far the largest effect of any variable (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). This finding is consistent with most recent juvenile court sentencing studies, which find that prior criminal history is the strongest predictor of more intrusive court intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1462474511434435">Feld, 2005</xref>). After controlling for legal, family, and demographic variables, the effect of being Mexican American remains significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) in the final model.</p>
<p>In sum, similar to modern‐day studies that examine the effect of race on sentencing, my analysis of sentencing in Los Angeles Juvenile Court in 1930 and 1940 shows that race affects decision making above and beyond legal and demographic differences between white and minority youths in court. However, unlike most recent studies, which find that minority youth are <italic>more</italic> likely to be given OFPs, my analysis indicates that Mexican Americans were <italic>less</italic> likely to be removed from their homes and confined in a custodial institution.</p>
<p>In the discussion that follows, relying on the rich contextual information reported in the court case files, I interrogate possible reasons for this counter‐intuitive finding.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-1462474511434435"><title>Explaining the Mexican‐American effect on placement</title>
<p>In the relatively few recent studies that have found that minority youths are treated less harshly than whites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1462474511434435">Guevara et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1462474511434435">Leiber, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1462474511434435">Rodriguez, 2007</xref>), one explanation given is that officials at a later stage of the decision‐making process are correcting for bias at an earlier stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1462474511434435">Leiber, 2003</xref>: 117). While it is plausible that some probation officers and judges in Los Angeles gave fewer out‐of‐home placements to Mexican Americans because they were correcting for police discrimination, I do not find support for this in the case files. In my examination of qualitative information reported in approximately 150 cases in 1930 and 1940, I only came across a couple where the probation officers expressed annoyance with the police. In one case, for example, a probation officer who was most likely Mexican‐American uncovered strong evidence that police officers had fabricated their story of seeing two Mexican‐American boys riding in a stolen vehicle.</p>
<p>In general, however, probation officers’ investigations either confirmed or partially modified the police investigation. Formal charges against juveniles were dismissed in only 9 percent of cases. The percentage of charges dismissed was equally small for Mexican Americans and whites (9.1% vs 8.3%). By contrast, in 2005, juvenile courts dismissed charges in one‐fourth of formally processed cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1462474511434435">Puzzanchera and Sickmund, 2008: 58</xref>). In sum, in a juvenile justice system in which youth had few legal rights and in which the offense itself was not considered the central issue of concern, court officials generally did not question the veracity of police reports.</p>
<p>The main difference in the juvenile court's treatment of Mexican‐American and white boys was in the share sentenced to probation in the community versus out‐of family placement. Probation, whether at home or with relatives, was the initial disposition in 66 percent of boys’ cases. However, 75 percent of Mexican Americans were placed on probation compared to 63 percent of whites, a statistically significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). In particular, a significantly higher percentage (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) of Mexican‐American than white boys were placed on probation with relatives (9% vs 4%).</p>
<p>Regarding the latter finding, court officials may have tended to assume that Mexican‐American families were more likely than white families to have relatives living in the area who could take in a crime‐involved cousin or younger brother. From my reading of the case files, probation officers did indeed take into account the availability of nearby relatives when making sentencing recommendations.</p>
<p>In support of this interpretation, the regression analysis found that boys born in California, who we might reasonably infer had more relatives in the area, were significantly less likely (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10) to receive an OFP. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1462474511434435">Table 3</xref>, significantly more Mexican‐American than white boys in court were born in California, and this was particularly the case in 1940 (83 percent of Mexican Americans vs 51 percent of whites). In all likelihood, this was true because the Mexican Americans who stayed in Los Angeles during the Depression years, in comparison to those who were repatriated, were more likely to have strong roots in California and to have children born there (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1462474511434435">Sanchez, 1993</xref>). By contrast, many of the white boys in court were recent arrivals from other states whose parents had moved to California in search of work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1462474511434435">Starr, 1995</xref>). For similar reasons, a greater share of Mexican-American boys might have been placed in their own homes (45% vs 38%, <italic>p</italic> = .11) because officials could rely more on relatives who lived in their neighborhoods to pick up the slack for ineffective parents.</p>
<p>That probation officers took into account the role of nearby relatives in making sentencing recommendations for Mexican‐American boys is illustrated by the case of Edward, a 16‐year‐old who was petitioned to court for stealing a car with two friends. Edward lived with his grandfather and two older sisters. The probation officer (PO) described the grandfather as ‘a pitiable figure, seventy‐eight years of age, apathetic, and with almost immobile features, unable to serve the function of father for a growing boy’. However, his three uncles lived close by and ‘are cooperative in offering what supervision the boy gets from family’. The fact that the boy had relatives monitoring him, as well as his ‘peculiar pride in a good family reputation’, gave the PO confidence that the boy could safely be placed on probation.</p>
<p>On the other hand, probation officers also (correctly) believed that Mexican‐American delinquent boys came from more deprived homes and neighborhoods than whites. Mexican‐American youth in court were, in fact, over three times more likely to be on welfare. In the case of Edward (above), the PO noted that the family was living in ‘a dismal four room shack without lights or gas service and with inadequate sanitary facilities’. He later remarked: ‘Why he has not previously been in trouble is almost a mystery, as he lives in an area of serious juvenile delinquency.’ Other POs tended to be more overtly judgmental of Mexican‐American families. For example, in a report on a 17‐year‐old Mexican‐American boy, John, who was referred to court for burglary, the PO noted that his home was ‘very unsatisfactory, although they may be as good as the average Mexican home’.</p>
<p>Edward's case illustrates the general pattern of how, in spite of serious reservations about the quality of Mexican‐American boys’ home environments, court officials regularly chose to rely on their relatives to supervise them as an alternative to institutionalization. At the same time, however, the court's greater utilization of within‐family resources for Mexican‐American boys was also an adaptation to a stark reality: a lack of out-of-family placement options for non‐white youth. According to the Probation Department's Annual Report in 1941:<disp-quote>
<p>There are some instances, however, when it becomes necessary to leave a maladjusted child in unfavorable surroundings in his own home due to the fact that placement facilities may be lacking. This is particularly liable to occur in cases of Mexican and Negro children for whom there are not sufficient boarding home and institutional facilities. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1462474511434435">Holton, 1941</xref>)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>In the following sections, I present two brief case studies that shed further light on why the Los Angeles Juvenile Court during the Great Depression era was less likely to sentence Mexican‐American than white boys to OFPs. Evidence from the case files helps tease out the explicit nature of race‐based decision making in a juvenile justice system that mainly justified decisions to place youths outside their homes as being for the good of the child.</p>
<sec id="sec8-1462474511434435"><title>Case A</title>
<p>The following case illustrates the extraordinary lengths the court was sometimes willing to go to avoid placing Mexican‐American youth in correctional institutions. It also reveals the high tolerance the court could display toward delinquent acts committed by Mexican‐American youth.</p>
<p>On 1 October 1930, Miguel, 11 years old, was petitioned to court on charges of grand theft auto. The first probation report noted that he lived in a five‐room house that was fairly well furnished with his mother and father and eight brothers and sisters. He was made a ward of the court and placed on probation. Three months later, a new probation report noted that the former PO had never contacted the boy.</p>
<p>In April 1931, Miguel was back in court on a truancy charge. The PO again recommended probation at home because of the boy's young age and ‘due to the fact that they are of the higher type Mexican’. One month later, he was back in court for stealing a car. This time a different PO decided not to recommend removal from home because Miguel was attending school and was seriously involved in athletics. After a burglary and petty theft charge the next year, however, the PO finally recommended that Miguel be committed to the Fred C. Nelles School. The judge, however, granted a stay of execution on the commitment so that the family could be repatriated to Mexico. Interestingly, the family refused to go.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1462474511434435">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Still, the court did not commit Miguel to the reform school; instead, it arranged to have him sent to live with his uncle in Tijuana. A couple of months later, Miguel was back in court in Los Angeles on a burglary charge; his uncle, in the meantime, had written to the court explaining that he could no longer continue to house the boy. Again, Miguel's commitment to reform school was suspended so that his family could move – this time, to the north in order ‘to work in the fruit’. Finally, in November 1933, Miguel was back in court on charges of petty theft. At this point, he was finally committed to the Nelles School.</p>
<p>In part, the juvenile court may have been reluctant to invest its scarce public resources to rehabilitate transient youth whose parents were migrant laborers and who were considered likely to return to Mexico. Nevertheless, as this case illustrates, the juvenile court was actively involved in the repatriation campaign and preferred this option, as well as sending Miguel to an uncle in Mexico who could not care for him, to placing him in the state reform school. Miguel had continually to prove he was persistently delinquent to finally receive an OFP.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec9-1462474511434435"><title>Case B</title>
<p>Besides the high tolerance for delinquency that juvenile court officials sometimes displayed when dealing with Mexican Americans, the case files also reveal that informal racial quotas restricted the court's out‐of‐family placement options for minority youth. Not just private boarding (foster) homes and state reform schools employed race‐based quotas. So, too, did the forestry camps – the most common out‐of‐home placement in 1940 – which were funded and administered by the court's own Probation Department.</p>
<p>Will, a 15‐year‐old Mexican American, was petitioned to court for assault. After a football game, Will, who was training to become a professional boxer, had allegedly punched a white youth in a brawl while he was lying prostrate on the ground. The police officer reported:<disp-quote>
<p>Boy’s assault is but one of the numerous similar assaults that [have] been committed by gangs on different high school grounds following athletic contests. Investigating officer feels subject should be severely disciplined and recommends placement in one of the county forestry camps.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The probation officer agreed that a forestry camp placement might be ideal for Will, but with a notably different rationale. He noted that Will had:<disp-quote>
<p>not yet become accustomed to the gang life into which undesirable companions were leading him. He has the ability and intelligence to become a worthy young citizen under the influence of proper guidance. He is an alert youngster who would benefit by the forestry camp program … but due to the high proportion of Mexican boys in forestry camp, probation officer cannot recommend placement at the time of this hearing.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>In another week, though, the probation officer thought there would be an opening at the camp. Meanwhile, the boy was detained in Juvenile Hall.</p>
<p>A week later, the PO reported:<disp-quote>
<p>It is now understood that it will be the policy of the Court not to allow recommendation for placement at Forestry Camp until some 2 or 3 weeks have elapsed so as to allow the proportion of Mexicans to dwindle. It is realized that too high a proportion of Mexican boys in forestry camp is detrimental to the training value of the Camp.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Will was allowed to go home on probation until a month later, when he was finally sent to forestry camp. If it took over a month for the court to send to forestry camp a gang‐involved Mexican‐American youth who had committed an interracial assault, it seems probable that probation officers were unlikely to recommend this option for less serious cases: either due to their own disinterest or lack of confidence in trying to help Mexican‐American delinquents change their behavior, or to constraints imposed by racially grounded institutional admission policies.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1462474511434435">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>The case files do not provide clear‐cut evidence on why there were caps on the number of Mexican‐American boys in forestry camp, or why a high concentration of Mexican Americans was perceived as detracting from the program's rehabilitative goals. But a 1950 textbook, <italic>The Challenge of Delinquency</italic>, by two well‐known criminologists, Negley K. Teeters and John Otto Reinemann, offers some insight into the rationales behind the racial quotas. Teeters and Reinemann wrote about the experiences of Mexican‐American boys in camps run by the recently established CYA, which were modeled after the Los Angeles forestry camps. ‘In the reform schools and Youth authority camps of California, the Mexican‐American boys naturally tend to clannishness,’ the authors wrote. ‘Many of them persist in wearing their distinctive hair‐do and bizarre tattooing, which represent badges of solidarity. Some camp counselors good‐naturedly permit the unique hair‐do but others insist that the hair be cut in the conventional manner’ (1950: 115).</p>
<p>One might speculate that Mexican‐American boys in forestry camp did indeed tend to stick together – probably, in part, as self‐protection in response to discrimination by the white boys in camp – and that camp supervisors viewed this as a threat to maintaining order and implementing a rehabilitative program. As previously discussed, forestry camps had no barbed‐wire fences or corporal punishment and relied heavily on youth self‐government to maintain discipline and order, supplemented by a limited set of punishments that the staff could impose. In this context, if the Mexican‐American boys stuck together they might have been seen as not fully taking part in the camp's rehabilitative program. In several of the case files I examined, Mexican‐American boys in forestry camp received ‘minor violations’ because they were caught speaking Spanish, which contradicted an informal camp rule. Given that forestry camp was an open institutional setting, speaking a language that staff and the other boys could not understand was probably seen as inherently threatening and a potential harbinger of on‐campus violence or a group plot to run away.</p>
<p>Evidence in the case files also suggests that the court conflated rehabilitation for Mexican Americans with Americanization. A camp report for a 16‐year‐old boy petitioned to court for car theft noted, ‘Your officer feels that the boy has profited greatly from his experience in camp, both physically and socially. He has put on seven pounds in weight and he has a better understanding of the American customs and diet.’ All boys had to pass ‘citizenship’ classes in the first few weeks of forestry camp. The refusal to speak English was likely seen as undermining the rehabilitative, ‘Americanizing’ qualities of the forestry camp program and disrupting the program for Anglo youth, perhaps also tempting them to disobey forestry camp rules. In sum, too high a concentration of Mexican‐Americans was interpreted as a likely threat to the administration of the camp's correctional program.</p>
<p>It is less clear whether such explicit racial quotas were also found in the Fred C. Nelles School or the Preston School of Industry for older teens. Historian Miroslava Chávez‐García, who has analyzed original Nelles School records, found that a much higher percentage of nonwhites were identified as ‘feebleminded’ based on IQ scores. This was, no doubt, due to the language barrier, the intimidating nature of the testing situation, and other factors, but officials believed that significantly lower average IQ scores reflected real differences in innate intelligence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1462474511434435">Chávez‐García, 2006</xref>). It was long‐standing Nelles School policy to have ‘mentally defective’ youths identified by low IQ scores transferred from Nelles to other institutions for the benefit of ‘normal’ boys who were more capable of rehabilitation. As a result, a disproportionate share of nonwhites were either transferred to other institutions or unconditionally released without explanation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1462474511434435">Chávez‐García, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1462474511434435">2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Similarly, the Superintendent of the Preston School of Industry, OH Close, complained about having to house ‘feeble‐minded’ delinquents in the same program as ‘normal’ youth. Close singled out Mexican‐American youth as presenting a special type of disciplinary problem:<disp-quote>
<p>The School also has approximately 15% of its population made up of Mexican-American boys and several American Indians. These boys are more nomadic in their make-up than the average American boy and must be watched rather closely to prevent escapes. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1462474511434435">Cox and Shelly, 1940</xref>: 106)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>With Close's comments in mind, it is interesting that some of the most violent Mexican‐American youth to appear in Los Angeles Juvenile Court in 1930 and 1940 were not incarcerated in either of the state's two main reform schools, as one might have expected. Consistent with the sentencing patterns reported earlier, 39 percent (9/23) of white boys who were referred to juvenile court for violent crimes were given OFPs, as compared to 25 percent (3/12) of Mexican‐American boys. Violent Mexican‐American youth, in other words, were less likely than violent white youth to receive an institutional placement, though this difference was not statistically significant. It thus seems that reform school administrators, like their forestry camp counterparts, also attempted to limit the concentration of Mexican‐American boys in their institutions. Juvenile court judges and probation officers probably took these constraints into account when making sentencing decisions.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec10-1462474511434435" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Due to police discrimination and perhaps real differences in crime rates, Mexican‐American youth were overrepresented in the Los Angeles Juvenile Court during the Great Depression era. If the court had simply treated them as it did whites, Mexican Americans would have been disproportionately sent to forestry camps, boarding homes, and state reform schools compared to their percentage of the Los Angeles population. Since they were also more likely to be on welfare and living in high poverty/high delinquency neighborhoods, Mexican Americans could expectedly have received even more OFPs than their representation (i.e. overrepresentation) among the juvenile court clientele would have predicted. Instead, juvenile court officials during the 1930s and early 1940s appear to have evaluated Mexican‐American boys and their families using a different standard of who should receive an OFP and who should not. In the end, the Los Angeles Juvenile Court mainly reserved OFPs for the rehabilitation of white youth.</p>
<p>A main reason for differential placement rates – with Mexican Americans <italic>under‐</italic> rather than overrepresented – appears to have been restrictions set by correctional program administrators, who believed strongly in the therapeutic mission of OFPs to rehabilitate select delinquent youth through individualized programming (Chávez‐García, 2006; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1462474511434435">Schlossman and Pisciotta, 1986</xref>). For a variety of reasons, correctional officials concluded that Mexican‐American youth were unresponsive to the programming offered at their institutions, and that the presence of too many Mexican Americans detracted from rehabilitative programming designed primarily for whites (Chávez‐García, 2006, 2007). While Los Angeles judges and probation officers were constrained by the racially discriminatory practices of private boarding homes and reform schools, they also contributed to discrimination themselves by limiting the number of Mexican Americans placed in the county's own forestry camps – the out‐of‐home placement that was under their administrative control, and that they believed most confidently could rehabilitate delinquent youth.</p>
<p>The finding that Los Angeles Juvenile Court was less likely in 1940 to give Mexican‐American youth OFPs may conceivably have reflected its slow response to a Mexican‐American youth crime wave that, it was widely alleged, preceded the famous Zoot Suit Riots of 1943 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1462474511434435">Holton, 1942</xref>). In 1942, juvenile court Judge Robert H. Scott created a commission to study the problem of Mexican‐American gang violence and strengthen the court's response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>). While I have no data on how court policies in Los Angeles may have changed around the time of the Zoot Suit Riots, I do have descriptive data regarding court placements several years later, in 1950. The 1950 data show that 15 percent of Mexican Americans were given an OFP, as compared to 17 percent of whites and only 10 percent of blacks. Thus, the gap between white and Mexican‐American OFPs may have begun to close in the aftermath of mutual hostilities stirred by the Zoot Suit Riots – a possibility that merits further investigation.</p>
<p>Still, these preliminary findings, supplemented by my qualitative review of several dozen case files in 1950, suggest that the juvenile court in the post‐Second World War period continued to view its mission as primarily rehabilitative. The court at mid‐century had not yet begun the severely disproportionate confinement of blacks and Latinos that would emerge in later years.</p>
<p>The historical evidence discussed in this essay thus raises the intriguing empirical question of when American juvenile courts began to view minority crime as enough of a societal threat to override the managerial concerns of correctional officials, and to disproportionately incarcerate minority youth. At least in Los Angeles – and some historical literature on juvenile courts suggests that Los Angeles was not anomalous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1462474511434435">Chivers, 1942</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1462474511434435">Tanenhaus, 2005</xref>) – that trend was not conclusively evident by mid‐century. The results from this study suggest that students of American juvenile justice, whether in the past or the present, need to be sensitive to the relationship between trends in Disproportionate Minority Confinement and whether juvenile justice officials perceive their out‐of‐home placements mainly as treatment or punishment.</p></sec>
</body>
<back><ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The author would like to thank Malcolm Feeley, Devah Pager, Sara McLanahan, Martin Ruef, King‐To Yeung, Katherine Newman, Patricia Fernandez‐Kelly, Paul DiMaggio and Steven Schlossman for their helpful comments on early versions of this manuscript.</p></ack>
<notes><title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1462474511434435"><label>1</label><p>I refer to these youths as ‘Mexican Americans’ because the great majority were born in the USA (86.3%), and because all were residing in Los Angeles and were perceived by the wider society as a distinctive group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-1462474511434435"><label>2</label><p>The definition of delinquency included status offenses such as truancy and curfew violation, but excluded cases of dependency, abuse, and neglect.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-1462474511434435"><label>3</label><p>The principal investigator was Steven Schlossman, Professor of History, Carnegie Mellon University. All of the coding and data cleaning took place at the Bureau of Criminal Statistics (BCS), California State Department of Justice, between 1985 and 1987. The undergraduates from the University of California, Davis, who coded the files were guided by explicit written instructions for coding each variable. Coding was completed under the supervision of the principal investigator and a psychologist working for the BCS. Tests of inter-coder reliability were administered and the data were double-entered. An agreement with the Court safeguards the confidentiality and anonymity of all case files.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-1462474511434435"><label>4</label><p>I use the word ‘race’ instead of ‘ethnicity’ because this is the preferred terminology in the USA and among academics writing about Mexican Americans in Los Angeles in the 1930s and 1940s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>). Furthermore, the degree of discrimination that Mexican Americans in Los Angeles encountered was closer to that of African Americans than Euro‐American immigrants, to whom the term ‘ethnicity’ is customarily applied in the USA. The race of the juvenile was usually indicated on the face sheet. If not noted and the name sounded obviously Latino, the case was coded as such.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-1462474511434435"><label>5</label><p>The 1940 Census did not specifically count Mexican Americans, but attempted to define ethnicity through the ‘mother tongue’, or the language spoken in the home. This definition likely undercounted the number of people of Mexican descent; as a result, most historians believe that the 8 percent figure for 1940 is an undercount of the Mexican‐American population by a few percentage points, and that the percentage of Mexican Americans increased between 1930 and 1940 despite active repatriation efforts by federal and state authorities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1462474511434435">Escobar, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1462474511434435">Wolcott, 2005</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6-1462474511434435"><label>6</label><p>A two sample test for a difference of proportions was used for all significance tests except for the calculation of differences by race in out‐of‐family placements in 1930, in which Fisher's exact test was used because of the small number of Mexican Americans receiving placements.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn7-1462474511434435"><label>7</label><p>‘Prior problems’ includes contacts reported by law enforcement and disciplinary problems and truancy reported by school officials, not those noted by parents alone. It is used as a proxy for the seriousness of a boy's prior record profile because it has a stronger relationship with OFP than ‘prior juvenile court appearances’ or ‘prior placements’ and, therefore, serves as a stronger test of whether race continues to have a significant effect on placement. Substituting these other variables for ‘prior problems’ did not reduce the coefficient for race or change the significance level for this variable.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn8-1462474511434435"><label>8</label><p>I came across one other case in which the juvenile court attempted to repatriate a boy and his sister to Mexico in spite of their wishes to stay in the country (Case # 52766).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn9-1462474511434435"><label>9</label><p>Similar explanations for not sending a Mexican‐American boy to forestry camp were provided in several other cases I examined, for example, Case #s 93455, 93472, 93489, 94163.</p></fn></fn-group></notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <source>The Decline of the Rehabilitative Ideal: Penal Policy and Social Purpose</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Power of the Zoot: Youth Culture and Resistance during WWII</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balderrama</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodríguez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</source>. <publisher-loc>Albuquerque, NM</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of New Mexico Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The role of race and ethnicity in juvenile justice processing</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempf‐Leonard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Our Children, Their Children: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Differences in American Juvenile Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>The influence of race in juvenile justice processing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Race effects in juvenile justice decision‐making: Findings of a statewide analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology</source> <volume>86</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanton</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>From intellectual deficiency to cultural deficiency: Mexican Americans, testing, and public school policy in the American Southwest, 1920–1940</article-title>. <source>Pacific Historical Review</source> <volume>72</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Bureau of the Census, US Department of Commerce (1933) <italic>Fifteenth Census of the United States: 1930</italic>. Population Vol. 2: General Reports Statistics by Subjects. Washington, DC: Government Printing Office</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Bureau of the Census, US Department of Commerce (1943) <italic>Sixteenth Census of the United States: 1940</italic>. Population. Vol. II: Characteristics of the Population. Washington, DC: Government Printing Office</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chávez-García</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Youth, evidence, and agency: Mexican and Mexican American youth at the Whittier State School, 1890–1920</article-title>. <source>Aztlan: A Journal of Chicano Studies</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chávez-García</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Intelligence testing at Whittier School, 1890–1920</article-title>. <source>Pacific Historical Review</source> <volume>76</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chivers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1942</year>) <article-title>The Negro delinquent</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Yearbook of the National Probation Association</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Probation Association</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Close</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1945</year>) <article-title>California camps for delinquents</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Yearbook of the National Probation Association</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Probation Association</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelly</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1940</year>) <source>Handbook of American Institutions for Delinquent Juveniles</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Osborne Association</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeJong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Putting race into context: Race, juvenile justice processing, and urbanization</article-title>. <source>Justice Quarterly</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <source>Judging Delinquents: Context and Process in Juvenile Court</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine Publishing Company</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Race, Police, and the Making of a Political Identity</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The contradictions of juvenile crime &amp; punishment</article-title>. <source>Daedalus</source> <volume>139</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Bad Kids: Race and the Transformation of the Juvenile Court</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Race and the jurisprudence of juvenile justice: A tale in two parts, 1950–2000</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempf‐Leonard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Our Children, Their Children: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Differences in American Juvenile Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>González</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Segregation and the education of Mexican children, 1900–1940</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>The Elusive Quest for Equality: 150 Years of Chicano/a Education</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard Educational Review</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Governor David Paterson's Task Force on Transforming Juvenile Justice (2009)</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Charting a New Course: A Blueprint for Transforming Juvenile Justice in New York State</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vera Institute of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guevara</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Spohn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gender and juvenile justice decision making: What role does race play?</article-title> <source>Feminist Criminology</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1940</year>) <source>Annual Report for the Year Ending December 31st, 1940</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Los Angeles County Probation Department</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>) <source>Annual Report for the Year Ending December 31st, 1941</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Los Angeles County Probation Department</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1942</year>) <source>Delinquency in wartime. Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee records</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kogon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>) <article-title>Probation camps</article-title>. <source>Federal Probation</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krisberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>General Corrections Review of the California Youth Authority</source>. <publisher-loc>Sacramento, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>California Attorney General's Office</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Contexts of Juvenile Justice Decision Making: When Race Matters</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Race, decision making and the implications of context in juvenile justice proceedings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Quantitative Criminology</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Being young and black: What are their effects on juvenile justice decision making?</article-title> <source>Crime &amp; Delinquency</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindsey</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1903</year>) <article-title>The reformation of juvenile delinquents through the juvenile court</article-title>. <source><italic>In:</italic> National Conference of Charities and Correction</source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Press of FG Heer</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Romig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Juvenile probation: The balanced approach</article-title>. <source>Juvenile &amp; Family Court Journal</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Mihailoff L (2005) <italic>Protecting Our Children: A History of the California Youth Authority and Juvenile Justice, 1938–1968</italic>. Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Berkeley</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Last One Over the Wall: The Massachusetts Experiment in Closing Reform Schools</source>. <publisher-loc>Columbus, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ohio State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Fit to Be Citizens? Public Health and Race in Los Angeles, 1879–1939</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Homeboys: Gangs, Drugs, and Prison in the Barrios of Los Angeles</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Delinquent Daughters: Protecting and Policing Adolescent Female Sexuality in the United States, 1885–1920</source>. <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagán</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Murder at the Sleepy Lagoon: Zoot Suits, Race, and Riot in Wartime L.A</source>. <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrosino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Turpin‐Petrosino</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Buehler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>‘Scared straight’ and other juvenile awareness programs for preventing juvenile delinquency</article-title>. <source>Campbell Systematic Reviews</source>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrosino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Turpin‐Petrosino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guckenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Formal system processing of juveniles: Effects on delinquency</article-title>. <source>Campbell Systematic Reviews</source>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piquero</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Disproportionate minority contact</article-title>. <source>The Future of Children</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piquero</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Unnever</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Piquero</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Never too late: Public optimism about juvenile rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>Punishment &amp; Society</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>President's Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice (1967)</collab> (<year>1967</year>) <source>Task Force Report: Juvenile Delinquency and Youth Crime</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Government Printing Office, Superintendent of Documents</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puzzanchera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sickmund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Juvenile Court Statistics 2005</source>. <publisher-loc>Pittsburgh, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Juvenile Justice</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Juvenile court context and detention decisions: Reconsidering the role of race, ethnicity, and community characteristics in juvenile court processes</article-title>. <source>Justice Quarterly</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>656</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Sanborn JB (1994) The juvenile, the court, or the community: Whose best interests are currently being promoted in juvenile court? <italic>The Justice System Journal</italic> 17(2): 249–266</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Becoming Mexican American: Ethnicity, Culture, and Identity in Chicano Los Angeles, 1900–1945</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlossman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisciotta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Identifying and treating serious juvenile offenders: The view from California and New York in the 1920s</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Intervention Strategies for Chronic Juvenile Offenders: Some New Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scudder</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>) <source>Annual Report for the Year Ending December 31st, 1935</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Los Angeles County Probation Department</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1942</year>) <source>Juvenile Delinquency and Urban Areas</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Endangered Dreams: The Great Depression in California</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanenhaus</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Juvenile Justice in the Making</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teeters</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinemann</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>) <source>The Challenge of Delinquency: Causation, Treatment, and Prevention of Juvenile Delinquency</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice‐Hall</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Race, ethnicity, and juvenile justice: Is there bias in postarrest decision making?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempf‐Leonard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Our Children, Their Children: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Differences in American Juvenile Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigil</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Barrio Gangs: Street Life and Identity in Southern California</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolcott</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Cops and Kids: Policing Juvenile Delinquency in Urban America, 1890–1940</source>. <publisher-loc>Columbus, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Ohio State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1462474511434435"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Juvenile justice processing: The entangled effects of race and urban poverty</article-title>. <source>Juvenile and Family Court Journal</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio><p><bold>Michael B Schlossman</bold>, is a PhD candidate in sociology at Princeton University. His interests are in the sociology of punishment and his dissertation research examines how juvenile justice officials in the United States responded to the movement to ‘get tough’ on youth crime.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>