<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sperg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Ergonomics in Design: The Quarterly of Human Factors Applications</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1064-8046</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1064804612449124b</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1064804612449124b</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Departments</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Books</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Using Human Factors Engineering to Improve Patient Safety: Problem Solving on the Front Line (2nd ed.)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Alper</surname><given-names>Samuel J.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>30</fpage>
<lpage>31</lpage>
<product>
<source>Using Human Factors Engineering to Improve Patient Safety: Problem Solving on the Front Line (2nd ed.)</source> Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gosbee</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gosbee</surname><given-names>Laura Lin</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>, <page-count count="167"/> pages, <price>$85.00</price> <publisher-loc>Oakbrook Terrace, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Joint Commission Resources</publisher-name> ISBN <isbn>978-59940-411-0</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This second edition of <italic>Using Human Factors Engineering to Improve Patient Safety</italic> is presented in two parts. The first is a broad overview of human factors engineering (HFE), focusing on breadth rather than depth as it introduces ideas, topics, applications, tools, and methodologies of HFE rather than instructing how to conduct an HFE analysis. Readers new to HFE will gain an introduction to the types of problems that can be addressed, whereas those who are experienced human factors practitioners may view the section as a list of human factors topics. An appendix points to a wide variety of highly relevant resources that provide more detailed information on the application of HFE in health care. The first section also provides guidance on teaching HFE and how to identify an HFE practitioner with whom to work.</p>
<p>The second part of the book presents six chapters by authors at different organizations. Each chapter typically starts with how the authors learned about HFE or how they began applying it in the health care field. Sandra Coletta’s description exemplifies how, after learning about human factors, her “lightbulb” turned on, forever changing her worldview.</p>
<p>The chapters also contain a wide range of individual case studies that were in progress or completed at the time of publication, including the redesign of medical equipment, creating forcing functions to ensure that gas lines are not mixed up, full system redesign of an emergency department, and implementation of an ongoing HFE program with descriptions of projects completed in that program. Methodologies for the case studies demonstrate many HFE analysis tools that are used in health care settings, including hazard analysis, task analysis, failure modes and effects analysis, and fault tree analysis. Authors also include insights gleaned from their own HFE work in health care.</p>
<p>Although the case studies provide a limited impression of what is involved in conducting HFE projects, they demonstrate a range of applications and methodologies and demonstrate the kinds of results HFE can produce. The best audience for this book is health care providers who seek to learn more about HFE and HFE professionals who wish to learn how to gain buy-in for HFE in health care.</p>
<p>This book should not be used to answer the question, “How do I do human factors engineering in health care?” Rather, it does an admirable job of helping one understand, “What can human factors engineering in health care do for me?”</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Samuel J. Alper</bold> completed his BS, MS, and PhD degrees in industrial and systems engineering with an emphasis in human factors at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. He participated in research including the evaluation of diagnostic test tracking in outpatient clinics and the study of the implementation of new health information technologies in in-patient pediatric hospital clinics and pharmacies. Samuel works at Exponent Failure Analysis Associates, where he applies human factors engineering to projects in a variety of domains, including health care. He can be reached at <email>salper@exponent.com</email>.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>