<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FOA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spfoa</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Focus Autism Other Dev Disabl</journal-id>
<journal-title>Focus on Autism and Other Developmental Disabilities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1088-3576</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-4829</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1088357611423542</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1088357611423542</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>“What Do You Like/Dislike About the Treatments You’re Currently Using?”</article-title>
<subtitle>A Qualitative Study of Parents of Children With Autism Spectrum Disorders</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>Virginia H.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1088357611423542">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Goin-Kochel</surname><given-names>Robin P.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1088357611423542">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>Barbara J.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1088357611423542">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1088357611423542"><label>1</label>University of Mary Washington, Fredericksburg, VA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1088357611423542"><label>2</label>Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1088357611423542"><label>3</label>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1088357611423542">Virginia Mackintosh, University of Mary Washington, 1301 College Avenue, Fredericksburg, VA 22401, USA Email: <email>vmackint@umw.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>60</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Children with autism spectrum disorders (ASD) often participate in many treatments, requiring parents’ dedication of time, money, and energy, and necessitating dealing with multiple service providers. To learn about parents’ experience in seeking and using treatments for their child with ASD, the authors asked them, “What do you like/dislike about the treatment(s) you’re currently using?” In this web-based, qualitative study, participants consisted of 486 parents (92% mothers) of children (80% boys; children’s <italic>M</italic> age = 8.3 years) with autism (<italic>n</italic> = 290, 59.7%), Asperger syndrome (<italic>n</italic> = 115, 23.6%), or pervasive developmental disorder—not otherwise specified (<italic>n</italic> = 81, 16.7%). The families lived in the United States, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, England, and Ireland. Parents’ written statements addressed more “dislikes” (70%) than “likes” (47%), and there were no universally liked or disliked interventions. Six themes emerged and are discussed: effectiveness of treatments, relationships with professionals, access to treatments, costs, medication concerns, and stress.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>parent preferences</kwd>
<kwd>treatments</kwd>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorders</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Parents of children with an autism spectrum disorders (ASD) often manage a complex array of treatments and therapies for their children, including pharmacological, dietary, behavioral, and educational interventions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1088357611423542">Goin-Kochel, Myers, &amp; Mackintosh, 2007</xref>). Certain treatments are school based, some are conducted in the home, and others require transportation to providers’ offices or clinics. Some treatments require hours of daily effort by the family, whereas others are in the hands of specialists. Expenses vary, with a number of treatments provided free in the community or covered by insurance, while others cost families many thousands of dollars. All of these interventions require negotiations with doctors, educators, occupational therapists, speech pathologists, or other autism professionals. Desired therapies can be difficult, if not impossible, to access if they are not available in a community. Others may be so expensive as to be cost prohibitive for a family. To learn more about parents’ experience in seeking and using treatments for their children with autism, we asked them, “What do you like/dislike about the treatment(s) you’re currently using?”</p>
<p>Individuals with ASD are heterogeneous in terms of symptoms and behaviors, and the outcomes can be uncertain. No one intervention program is appropriate for all children with ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1088357611423542">O’Brien &amp; Daggett, 2006</xref>). Currently, there is no consensus regarding which treatments will help which children in the autism spectrum. All of these uncertainties and unknowns make autism difficult to treat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1088357611423542">Lord et al., 2005</xref>). Unlike disorders with a clear set of accepted treatments, parents can feel as if they are on their own in deciding what to try and for how long.</p>
<p>Parents are faced with a daunting assortment of treatment choices, and children with ASD are often enrolled in numerous treatments and interventions simultaneously. The terms treatment, intervention, and therapy are used in this article as synonymous terms as all can denote some process designed to bring about an improvement in functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1088357611423542">Merriam-Webster Online, n.d.</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1088357611423542">Metz, Mulick, and Butter (2005)</xref> stated that</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>The apparent high prevalence of autism, the lifelong implications of the disorder, its severe impact on the functioning of the child and family, and the limited options for effective intervention have led many families to an often desperate quest for any treatment that might be effective. (p. 237)</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In two studies conducted via the Internet, parents reported that their children were engaged in an average of 7 different interventions aimed at addressing issues associated with the child’s autism spectrum diagnosis. The frequency of interventions reported as being used ranged from none to 15 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1088357611423542">Goin-Kochel et al., 2007</xref>), up to 47 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1088357611423542">Green et al., 2006</xref>). Again, with each of these interventions, parents must coordinate with professionals and manage the possible costs and time commitments that the treatments entail.</p>
<p>With no certain source for the right answers, parents are resourceful in finding treatments to try. While some interventions are suggested by educators and/or autism specialists, the Internet provides a venue for promoting many novel treatments. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1088357611423542">Mackintosh, Myers, and Goin-Kochel (2005)</xref> found that 86% of parents of children with ASD reported turning to websites as a source of information regarding their children’s disorder. (Note: This result may be biased by it being an Internet-based sample.) Only 44% of the parents reported that they accessed information through scientific journals. Less than half the participants reported that they got information from their children’s physicians (48%) or educators (49%), whereas 72% turned to other parents of children with an ASD as information sources.</p>
<p>Parents who learn of experimental treatments may struggle with the possibility of passing up on <italic>the</italic> new intervention that will help <italic>their</italic> child with ASD. For parents desperate to find answers on how to deal with difficult and unpredictable behavior, these purported interventions can be highly seductive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1088357611423542">American Academy of Pediatrics, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1088357611423542">Maurice, Mannion, Letso, &amp; Perry, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1088357611423542">Metz et al., 2005</xref>). News of novel interventions may induce stress, as parents consider whether they should continue a traditional treatment or seek out the latest intervention that claims to have the potential of changing their child’s life forever. “Parents are promised ‘miracles’ if they too undertake a particular form of therapy, while skeptical professionals may be castigated for their intolerance and shortsightedness” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1088357611423542">Howlin, 1998</xref>, p. 76). This can be a source of conflict between parents and the teachers, doctors, and therapists already working with their children. Sometimes, parents avert the conflict by not telling the doctors or other professionals about the treatments they are trying with their child (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1088357611423542">Wong &amp; Smith, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Although it is clear that parents allow their children with ASD to participate in numerous treatments, little is known about their satisfaction with the treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1088357611423542">Lanners &amp; Mombaerts, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1088357611423542">Rodger, Keen, Braithwaite, &amp; Cook, 2007</xref>). Researchers have focused on parents’ satisfaction with a <italic>specific</italic> treatment or intervention, but not with the overall gestalt experience. Thus, in the current study, we sought to learn more about parents’ experiences seeking and using treatments for their children with ASD by asking the open-ended question “What do you like/dislike about the treatment(s) you are currently using?” and analyzing their responses qualitatively. Participants were involved in a broader study where they listed and individually evaluated treatments that had been tried (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1088357611423542">Goin-Kochel et al., 2007</xref>); however, in this question, we were interested in getting an overall report of parents’ thoughts and feelings about all the treatments they were using. By deliberately asking this question in a generic way, we hoped to get an idea about what parents of children with ASD tell each other when sharing their views on interventions.</p>
<sec id="section1-1088357611423542" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section2-1088357611423542">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Participants were recruited through study advertisements that were sent by letter or electronic contact to more than 220 autism-support organizations in the United States and other English-speaking countries. Cooperating organizations placed advertisements or electronic links in their newsletters, websites, and email communications. It is not possible to tell which advertisement a participant saw. A website containing the questionnaire was posted from August 2002 to February 2004. Participants accessed the questionnaire and entered their data through the Internet. Submission of completed questionnaires constituted informed consent to participate, and all submitted data were stored on a secure, university-controlled server. We asked for no identifying information that would allow our knowing the identity or the email addresses of participants. This method of online data collection is considered a valid and reliable technique as compared with mailed or in-person survey approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1088357611423542">Gosling, Vazire, Srivastava, &amp; John, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1088357611423542">Preckel &amp; Thiemann, 2003</xref>) and is now a frequently used tool in behavioral research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1088357611423542">Fraley, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088357611423542">Granello &amp; Wheaton, 2004</xref>). The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board at Virginia Commonwealth University. Participants received no compensation.</p>
<p>Participants were 486 parents (92% mothers) of children (80% boys) with ASD. Parents’ average age at the time of the questionnaire was 37.8 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 6.7). Parents reported their children’s diagnoses; we did not independently confirm the diagnoses. The study was designed with a cutoff at age 21 years, and any responses given for offspring older than 21 were not analyzed. Children’s average age at the time of the survey was 8.3 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 4.3); most were between 3 and 11 years of age (75%), with a range from 2 years to 21 years. The largest percentage of children was identified by parents as White/Caucasian (86.7%), with 6.2% biracial, 2% Black/African American, 2.2% Hispanic, and 2.8% Asian, Native American, or children of other races/ethnicities.</p>
<p>The families came from almost all states in the United States (77%) as well as Canada (5.6%), Australia (2.4%), New Zealand (1.5%), England (3.4%), Ireland (3.2%), and “other outside the United States” (1.5%). International participation comprised 18% of the sample. Locale was not reported by 5% of the respondents. Demographic information can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1088357611423542">Table 1</xref>. Some participants did not answer demographic questions.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1088357611423542" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Demographic Characteristics of Participants (<italic>N</italic> = 486)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1088357611423542" xlink:href="10.1177_1088357611423542-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristic</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Child’s diagnosis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autism</td>
<td>290</td>
<td>59.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asperger syndrome</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>23.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PDD-NOS</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>16.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Parents’ highest level of education completed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Did not complete high school</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High school</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>14.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Some college</td>
<td>198</td>
<td>40.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Bachelor’s degree</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>17.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Post-Bachelor’s degree</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>20.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Annual income (US$)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 10,000</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 10,000–25,000</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>12.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 25,000–40,000</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>16.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 40,000–55,000</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>13.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 55,000–70,000</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>16.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 70,000–100,000</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>17.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> More than 100,000</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>17.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Marital status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married</td>
<td>308</td>
<td>79.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Divorced</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>9.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Separated, single, or widowed</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>9.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1088357611423542">
<p>Note: PDD-NOS = pervasive developmental disorder—not otherwise specified.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1088357611423542">
<title>Instrument</title>
<p>The question being analyzed in this study (i.e., “What do you like/dislike about the treatment(s) you’re currently using?”) was part of a larger online study asking parents to report on their child’s early development and their experience having a child with ASD. The questionnaire was made up of approximately 100 multiple choice questions and several open-ended questions (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1088357611423542">Goin-Kochel et al., 2007</xref> for a complete description of the questionnaire). The questionnaire gave room for parents to write as little or as much as they wanted in response to their preferences regarding treatments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1088357611423542">
<title>Qualitative Coding</title>
<p>The primary coder (first author) read the responses using an inductive analysis approach to see what patterns of information and themes emerged from the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1088357611423542">Patton, 2002</xref>). Initially, statements were classified as likes, dislikes, mixed, or neutral. Parents’ responses, then, were coded inductively for themes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1088357611423542">Miles &amp; Huberman, 1994</xref>). Starting with a set of tentative themes, the themes were refined and expanded until they adequately captured the breadth of the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1088357611423542">Taylor &amp; Bogdan, 1998</xref>). The second and third coders (second and third authors) each examined half the transcripts for themes and worked with the first coder to seek agreement. Questions among coders were resolved by discussion. Once the themes were agreed on, phrases and statements were sorted into the themes. All three coders read the full set of transcripts and came to agreement on the final themes and placement of phrases. The number of statements fitting each theme was tallied.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1088357611423542" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>More parents (<italic>n</italic> = 194, 39.9%) wrote only of things they disliked about the treatment(s) than solely of things they liked (<italic>n</italic> = 82, 16.9%). In addition, 149 participants (30.7%) wrote responses that included both likes and dislikes, a category we call “mixed.” Altogether, the majority of parents (<italic>n</italic> = 343, 70.6%) expressed at least one dislike regarding treatments, and just under half (<italic>n</italic> = 230, 47.3%) made at least one positive comment about their children’s therapies. A total of 23 families (4.7%) provided responses that were neutral in affect. Finally, 39 parents (8%) said that their children were receiving no treatments. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1088357611423542">Table 2</xref> provides examples of each type of response. No single treatment or approach was uniformly liked or disliked.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1088357611423542" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Classification of Parents’ Overall Statements Regarding Their Children’s Autism Spectrum Disorders Treatments as Likes, Dislikes, Mixed, Neutral, or No Treatments (<italic>N</italic> = 487)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1088357611423542" xlink:href="10.1177_1088357611423542-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Affect of response</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center">Example</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Likes</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>16.9</td>
<td>“I really like ABA and the improvements he has made with it.”<break/>“We love the OT – that seems to make the greatest difference in his life because as his motor skills improve, his self esteem increases which makes him more available to make improvements in other areas.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dislikes</td>
<td>194</td>
<td>39.9</td>
<td>“Not enough speech therapy. He only gets 30 minutes a week. He needs more.”<break/>“Trying to find the correct meds. She is withdrawing from one med now while she is being switched. It’s very hard to watch your child not feeling well or feeling zoned out and not be able to do anything.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mixed</td>
<td>149</td>
<td>30.7</td>
<td>“Although it is helping him a lot I hate having to give him Ritalin every day.”<break/>“We like the treatments we are using although they are time consuming, expensive and hard to start because of long waiting lists. We realize it could be so much worse, but we still suffer frustrations about the whole special-needs process.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neutral</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>4.7</td>
<td>“I cannot comment as we have only been part of an early intervention program for a few months.”<break/>“I have no issues.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No treatments</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>“There currently is no treatment available for him.”<break/>“I am not getting any help or treatment at the moment.”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1088357611423542">
<p>Note: ABA = applied behavior analysis; OT = occupational therapy.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section6-1088357611423542">
<title>Themes</title>
<p>The following six themes emerged from analysis of parents’ responses: effectiveness of treatments, relationships with professionals, access to desired treatments, costs (including money, effort, and time), concerns about using medications, and stress. A single statement could fit just one theme or multiple themes. Parents’ responses are presented with only spelling errors corrected (editors’ decision); punctuation, capitalization, and grammar were not edited. Responses written in all caps were changed to sentence-style upper and lowercase. Numbers following each quote correspond to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1088357611423542">Table 3</xref>, which provides information as to the respondent’s relationship to the child, along with the child’s age and diagnosis.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1088357611423542" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Attribution of Quotes</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1088357611423542" xlink:href="10.1177_1088357611423542-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Quote no.</th>
<th align="center">Locale</th>
<th align="center">Relationship to child</th>
<th align="center">Child’s age (in years)</th>
<th align="center">Child’s sex</th>
<th align="center">Child’s diagnosis</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Not designated</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Australia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>Texas</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>Texas</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>California</td>
<td>Stepmother</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>Florida</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>Ohio</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>California</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>Michigan</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>Tennessee</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>No clear diagnosis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>England</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>California</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>New York</td>
<td>Stepmother</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>California</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td>Illinois</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td>Maine</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>26</td>
<td>Australia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>27</td>
<td>Oregon</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>29</td>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31</td>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>Relationship not specified</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>32</td>
<td>Florida</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>33</td>
<td>New York</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>34</td>
<td>Alabama</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35</td>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>37</td>
<td>Texas</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>38</td>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>39</td>
<td>England</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40</td>
<td>South Carolina</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>41</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>42</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>43</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>44</td>
<td>Texas</td>
<td>Father</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45</td>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>46</td>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>Father</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>47</td>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>48</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>49</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Father</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50</td>
<td>New Jersey</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>51</td>
<td>Maryland</td>
<td>Father</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>52</td>
<td>Not designated</td>
<td>Relationship not specified</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>53</td>
<td>California</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>54</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>PDD-NOS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>55</td>
<td>California</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>Asperger syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>56</td>
<td>New York</td>
<td>Mother</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>Autism</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1088357611423542">
<p>Note: PDD-NOS = pervasive developmental disorder—not otherwise specified.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section7-1088357611423542">
<title>Effectiveness of treatments</title>
<p>This theme captured parents’ beliefs of whether or not treatments had helped their children. It is important to note that these responses reflect parents’ perceptions of benefit and should not be interpreted as measures of actual clinical effectiveness or ineffectiveness of any particular treatment. More than half the respondents (<italic>n</italic> = 254, 52.3%) said something about effectiveness. Two thirds of this group (<italic>n</italic> = 167, 65.7%) had only positive things to say (e.g., “love the diet—makes it easier for him to learn” [1]). A total of 50 parents (19.7%) wrote only about ineffectiveness (e.g., “Her medication doesn’t work and the shrink she is seeing doesn’t even care” [2]). A total of 37 parents (14.7%) reported both positive and negative aspects regarding the benefit of their children’s treatments (e.g., “Do not like the fact he takes regular medication but at the same time it allows him to function better. As for behavior modifying. well we will keep on trying till we find one which works” [3]). Some parents did not indicate which specific treatments they were referring to in this response, merely reporting positive feelings about the effectiveness of the intervention(s) in general: “its working;” [4] and from another, “I am content with everything.” [5] More often, however, parents named the specific treatments when they provided an emotional valence for their comment: “I have absolutely nothing but positives to say about ABA, ST, and OT. They have been the driving force behind allowing us to find the child in him and bring him out.” [6] From another parent, “One-on-one Applied Behavior Analysis 30 hours per week has been wonderful!!! Speech therapy starting at age 2 has had a profound impact and allowed him to finally develop speech.” [7]</p>
<p>For parents who said that treatments had not been effective, they either spoke disparagingly about treatments in general (e.g., “Don’t see much progress, but always looking for new things” [8]) or mentioned specific approaches that had not worked for their child: “Social training-INEFFECTIVE!” [9] Another parent wrote, “Occupational Therapy and Speech Therapy seem to have reached a point not ‘helping’ anymore.” [10]</p>
<p>About 15% of parents reported mixed feelings of the effectiveness of their children’s treatments, either because there were some therapies they liked and others they did not find effective (“just started OT and PT, it is going ok so far. meds don’t seem to do much”) [11] or because they saw both positives and negatives regarding a given treatment (e.g., “She is currently on Adderall. This helps her to sit still at school and focus longer. This medicine makes her aggressive at times. When she is not on it, she is silly/slap happy, goofy acting” [12]). Often the rate of progress was an issue: “I like that they are working. I dislike that is not working as fast or accurate as I would like to;” [13] and, “I do not like putting my child on medication, but do feel it has helped a little. Very little. We are trying therapy, once again and are making sloooow progress.” [14]</p>
<p>Other parents were pleased to see improvements in their children, but were distressed that there was no understanding of the underlying cause of the disorder. One parent wrote:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>I feel his therapies are really helping learn how to react to his symptoms however i want to get to the cause of the symptoms and get rid of the cause. A lot of therapy seems like Tylenol just treating the symptoms and they do work but how wonderful if i can alleviate all symptoms the way most have disappeared. [15]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Most parents were intimately aware of what therapies were happening, including at school, and had strong opinions about their effectiveness. For example:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>Speech therapy is totally ineffective, school wants to force socialization on him which has caused a tremendous setback in his life. The most effective therapy we have right now is OT. This is a very stress-free therapy for him, and has helped somewhat in sensory integration. [16]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1088357611423542">
<title>Relationships with professionals</title>
<p>One third of the participants (<italic>n</italic> = 162, 33.3%) wrote about relationships with professionals and/or professional organizations (e.g., schools and local government services). This category encompasses a wide range of service providers, but was grouped together to reflect parents’ feelings of supportive/adversarial relationships with the people and institutions working with their children. Among the responses, nearly three quarters (<italic>n</italic> = 119, 73.5%) reported negative relationships with service providers. Some felt attacked: “I am not getting any treatments. The time the ‘specialists’ take in coming to a diagnosis is extremely long and if I wasn’t strong I would have believed them that it was my parenting skills that caused his behavior problems.” [17] Another parent wrote, “I wish that doctors would listen to parents a little bit more, and with a more open minds. I wish that the doctors had given us an earlier diagnosis, since all of the sign were there.” [18] This perceived lack of respect sometimes led to adversarial relationships between parents and professionals, as expressed by this parent:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>The doctors, psychiatrists, psychologists we see feel they know everything there is to know and they know better than you do and i have to speak my peace and tell them like it is. other than that i am pleased with the treatment they give. [19]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Other parents complained of problems with autism awareness and education in professionals and organizations: “Schools don’t know how to modify curriculum for an autistic child in the full inclusion environment and don’t know enough about autism and how they learn.” [20] Parents expressed a lack of trust in the professionals who were taking care of their children: “I wish i had more control over their diet. I have to trust the daycare provider to not let them get the other children’s bottles or snacks.” [21] Some felt that the professionals did not take into account their individual child’s needs, “I feel as though there isn’t any other child out there with the same problems as my son. He has XYY syndrome, but everyone has ignored that diagnoses.” [22] School districts were faulted for their lack of knowledge: “Treatment is inconsistent, Public school isn’t educated enough to deal with special needs children.” [23]</p>
<p>Although most of the comments concerning institutions were negative, occasionally parents had positive things to say about their children’s school (“we love the preschool he attends and feel that he is getting what he needs” [24]). Only one parent had positive things to say about her local government services (“I am content with everything, J County offers wonderful support for individuals with disability and we, the parents, have the final say in anything and everything that concerns our child” [25]).</p>
<p>Parents wrote of how they felt about particular service providers. Some expressed a deep appreciation for the caring and talented professionals working with their children: “His teachers and aides are so supportive and good with him. There are no aversives whatsoever used and everything is based on an instant reward for all tasks that he attempts.” [26] Just as there were concerns when children’s individual needs were not taken into account, parents were grateful when professionals tailored their programs to meet a child’s specific needs: “We’re not really using any treatments right now, except speech therapy, which is actually more ‘conversation training,’ something he needs. I really appreciate what the therapist is doing with him in that regard.” [27]</p>
<p>Other parents had a mix of good and bad things to say about the individual professionals who worked with their children:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>We love one of our therapists. She uses play and modified ABA. She is totally committed to our son and is very professional. We also are using an ABA organization and have been totally disappointed with them. They seem to have untrained and unmotivated therapists. We are still trying to obtain a therapist that we like with this organization. Our OT is good. Our speech therapist is wonderful but cancels a lot. I guess my biggest dislike about the therapists is their lack of professionalism and their failure to keep appointments. [28]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Parents expressed frustration at the high turnover of professionals:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>It is difficult to maintain qualified therapists in my home. ABA and discrete trials have changed our children in the best way, but turnover is very high and just when we get to like one of the therapists, she leaves for a better paying job . . . .[29]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Having changes in therapists and caregivers made things difficult for both the parent and the child:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>Since his daytime caregivers change often (different school teachers, camp counselors, etc), I have to repeat the “instructions on how to operate my son” a million times. We all know how important routine is for a child like my son, yet, life unavoidably brings change. I would like more consistency in my son’s treatment. [30]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1088357611423542">
<title>Access to desired treatments</title>
<p>The responses in this category (<italic>n</italic> = 164) were almost entirely negative (<italic>n</italic> = 150, 91.5%), and complaints about access came from parents in the United States and in countries with socialized medicine. Parents addressed issues such as waiting lists (“Still in the early stages, but the worst dislike is the length of time spent on waiting lists for treatment” [31]) and the lack of available specialists (“He’s not really receiving any specialized treatment. The school system has mainstreamed him, which isn’t working out too well.” [32]). Even when able to access treatments, many parents were concerned that the interventions were too limited in intensity or in the number of hours provided (“My daughter attends a special needs school daily (for 3 hours). . . . I don’t believe effective therapy can occur in that (short) time span.” [33]).</p>
<p>Some saw access problems related to their school system or town: “I cannot find anyone that knows very much at all about autism. I am from a small town and the medical community has not caught up with the increasing number of children affected by autism.” [34] Many parents saw the issues as being systemic and specific to their state or country: “My state does not offer enough services. I think the therapy they provide is a joke.” [35]</p>
<p>A number of parents said, specifically, that they were receiving no treatments at all for their children (<italic>n</italic> = 35). Some implied that their child had either aged out of available treatments or were too young for the interventions accessible in their area (e.g., “no treatment at this time because of his age” [36]). Others said that nothing was available (e.g., “using? there are none offered;” [37] and from another, “There are no treatments being used right now or have there ever been. I was told there was not anything available” [38]). Another parent wrote, “i am using no treatments now, since diagnosis ive been left alone, its like they say shes this, now get on with it.” [39]</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1088357611423542">
<title>Costs (money, effort, and time)</title>
<p>A theme that had only negative responses was that of cost. Responses under this category mentioned something about the money, effort, and/or time expended in providing treatment (<italic>n</italic> = 125, 25.7%). The most common cost mentioned was monetary (<italic>n</italic> = 55, 11.3%). Parents complained of the lack of government support and/or the fact that many of the treatments do not qualify for insurance reimbursement, “I am having a very hard time getting help. We aren’t poor enough for gov assistance and our ins. won’t pay. Public school is all we have.” [40] Parents wrote of having to do without treatments as a result of the expense, “We use no treatments. Our insurance pays for nothing.” [41]</p>
<p>The effort involved in providing treatments was mentioned by 47 (9.7%) participants. “The gluten-free diet is essential to his health but is labor-intensive, and difficult to follow when eating out.” [42] Although the parents’ effort was an issue, some also mentioned the effort required of the children as well, “ABA seems to be the only viable option, but it is an extremely rigorous and demanding form of schooling. Our son is exhausted by week’s end. And the expense is, of course, astronomical.” [43]</p>
<p>Time was mentioned by 23 parents (4.7%), though time and effort often overlapped, “I wish the behavior system we used wasn’t so time intensive on my part . . . I am tired of having to mark charts and give tokens constantly . . . I just want to live. I am tired.” [44] One parent mentioned all three costs in her response, “Not enough help from government funding. Therefore, I have had to set up my own ABA program in home. This takes a lot of energy and time . . . . not so easy when you have other people who need you, too.” [45]</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1088357611423542">
<title>Concern about using medications</title>
<p>Parents had both good and bad things to say about their children’s medication. Some wrote of whether they felt the medication was working, but a theme, separate from effectiveness, came from parents (<italic>n</italic> = 64, 13.2%) who expressed concern about “giving drugs” to their children. This kind of concern was not voiced for any other treatment. There seemed to be, for these parents, a sense that it was inherently wrong to give medication to their children. Some parents acknowledged the effectiveness of medication but were still sorry to use them (e.g., “I wish my son didn’t need the drugs, however they work;” [46] and “Current drug regime has worked well for several years. Dislike having to use strong drugs” [47]). Others doubted the medicine’s benefit (e.g., “I’ve never been comfortable with medicating my son. I honestly do not see a difference when he’s on medication. I don’t medicate him on the weekends” [48]). Many voiced fears about adverse effects, now or in the future (e.g., “I don’t know the long-term effects or if difficult days have anything to do with the medications” [49]). Others had stopped using medications (“I didn’t like the way he was acting on medication . . . I have since discontinued its use” [50]).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1088357611423542">
<title>Stress</title>
<p>A theme that overlapped all of the previously described categories was stress. More than one third of the responses (<italic>n</italic> = 172, 35.4%) were coded as expressing stress related to treatments (or lack thereof). Stress was rarely the only theme that parents’ statements fit into. Only three participants had responses that showed stress but did not fall under other designations (e.g., “never knowing if you’re doing the right thing or if there is something more effective out there and I’m just missing it.” [51]). Still, it struck us as important to acknowledge the inherent anxiety that parents expressed when writing about choosing and providing the appropriate treatments for their children, “I don’t feel enough is being done for her . . . but we cannot afford intensive training, as 25% of our (one) income goes for her medical needs.” [52] Another parent wrote,</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>I’m like a deer standing in the middle of the highway with headlights shining in my eyes. I feel paralyzed not knowing which way to turn first in getting her help. I’ve exhausted most of my resources on her twin brother’s therapies (he was diagnosed 1.5 years ago), and I’m not getting as much support for her. His needs were more obviously sensory and easier to diagnose. She is just miserable 95% of the time and states that she wants to die at 6 years old. [53]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Clearly, the task of providing treatment to their children with ASD has left many parents exhausted. “It seems I can never be doing enough–the requirements for treating autistics are superhuman.”[54]</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1088357611423542">
<title>Overlapping themes</title>
<p>Most parents wrote responses that could be coded into multiple themes. Here, we show one mother’s full answer with the themes indicated:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>[Relationships with professionals] Her current school district has really let us down, they failed to tell us about options to help her with her aggression problems.</p>
<p>[Access to desired treatments] If we insisted on entering her in those programs under my district now it would take months to even assess her for qualification. So we are transferring her to her father’s district (we’re divorced), where they seem to have a more promising program . . .</p>
<p>[Effectiveness of treatments] We’re also not pleased with the social skills group she’s attended for some time anymore, it’s not doing much for her like it used to . . . .[55]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Without spelling out each theme, here is another full response:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>I dislike the lack of availability of providers in all the areas. I dislike that doctors don’t know anything about autism and that we have to depend on them to sign for tests and medications we need. I dislike the educational system and all the abuse that we must go through to obtain services from the board of education and to get reimbursement for expenses. I dislike having to count on others to give my son his medications such as school. I like the verbal behavior form of ABA. I dislike that he will not be able to get the most out of it due to lack of providers. [56]</p></disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1088357611423542" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The etiology of ASD is not known, the disorders bring difficult and perplexing behaviors, and there is a dearth of clinical studies on treatment effectiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1088357611423542">Lord et al., 2005</xref>). Meanwhile new interventions appear weekly. Few clear answers exist to guide parents in their choice of treatments, to let them know what to expect from those treatments, to help them find practitioners, or to help them pay for the treatments. We were struck by the passion expressed by parents when writing of their children’s current treatments and therapies. It is clearly an emotional topic, with parents being thrilled to see good results and deeply frustrated when unable to see the progress that they would like for their children.</p>
<p>This is an important topic, for parents serve as the gatekeepers to their children’s access to services. How parents feel about treatments can have a direct influence on the choice of therapies, how long the child will continue to receive an intervention, and the level of treatment compliance enforced by the parent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1088357611423542">Green, 2007</xref>). Clearly, from the poignancy of the responses, managing children’s treatments can have a considerable impact on the family’s quality of life. This appears to be a noteworthy source of stress for these families, and it has largely gone unstudied.</p>
<p>In all, 22% of our participants reported difficulties in their relationships with professionals. They spoke of having to argue with doctors, teachers, and other service providers. These disagreements with service providers are likely to be a significant source of stress for the families. Parents expressed strong opinions of what they felt was best for their children and clearly found it emotionally arousing when professionals disagreed with them. These findings are consistent with those of previous authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1088357611423542">Fitzpatrick, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1088357611423542">Nachshen &amp; Jamieson, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1088357611423542">Taylor, 1991</xref>). We do not know just what services and treatments these parents were arguing for. It is possible, at least in some cases, that parents were advocating for newly introduced approaches that professionals were unfamiliar with, or it is likely that some parents were advocating for the use of interventions that have been demonstrated to be ineffective or harmful.</p>
<p>We were struck by the stress that parents revealed when they wrote about treatments. In an earlier article with this same sample, we examined the question of how having a child with autism had affected the parents’ own lives and their families’ lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1088357611423542">Goin-Kochel, Mackintosh, &amp; Myers, 2009</xref>). In the parents’ rich and complex answers, stress was the most frequent theme that arose in their accounts of how their children in the spectrum affected them and their families. More than 70% (<italic>n</italic> = 350, 71%) of the parents’ statements expressed stress. The responses from our participants suggest that the process of accessing desired treatments, managing the costs of money and effort, and dealing with a wide array of ever-changing professionals disrupted the equilibrium of the entire family. It has been well documented that parents of children with ASD experience high levels of stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1088357611423542">Abbeduto et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1088357611423542">Dunn, Burbine, Bowers, &amp; Tantleff-Dunn, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1088357611423542">Eisenhower, Baker, &amp; Blacher, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1088357611423542">Hastings &amp; Johnson, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1088357611423542">Hodapp, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1088357611423542">Koegel et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1088357611423542">Konstantareas &amp; Homatidis, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1088357611423542">Montes &amp; Halterman, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1088357611423542">Pisula, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1088357611423542">Seltzer, Abbeduto, Krauss, Greenberg, &amp; Swe, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1088357611423542">Yamada et al., 2007</xref>). What has not been studied previously is treatment access and treatment delivery as unique sources of stress. In fact, very little is known about the impact of treatment delivery on parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1088357611423542">Lord et al., 2005</xref>). The stress related to interventions is an important area for future investigation.</p>
<sec id="section15-1088357611423542">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Although using a web-based study allows for a large, international sample, there are limitations inherent to this methodology. Participants had to have access to the Internet as well as the wherewithal and time to find and fill out the survey. There was an underrepresentation of both lower income and ethnic minorities in our sample. In addition, because families learned of the study through autism associations, parents not affiliated with such organizations were not likely to know about the project. Our study relied entirely on parental report, so we have no independent verification of ASD diagnosis. We also have no objective measure of actual treatment effectiveness or of the difficulties families encountered in getting treatments. We only know that these are the parents’ perceptions of their experience. Given that less than one fifth of our sample was from countries outside of the United States, we did not undertake a comparison of responses by location, but it is possible that cultural and political influences differentiated responses of U.S. and non-U.S. participants. Finally, these data were collected during a limited time frame (i.e., 2002–2004), so it is possible that parents’ perceptions of treatment effectiveness may have changed since then. We have provided a snapshot of experiences for this particular group of participants; the findings cannot be generalized to other parents of children with ASD today.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1088357611423542">
<title>Future Directions</title>
<p>Parents in this study clearly expressed frustrations in accessing services, in dealing with professionals, and in paying for and delivering interventions. Researchers have already concluded that parents of children with ASD experience higher levels of stress than do parents of children with other disabilities. We do not know from this study to what extent these difficulties and frustrations are unique to parents of children with ASD or are universal to all families of children with special needs. Further studies are needed to determine if these parental issues surrounding treatment help to explain some of the difference found in parenting stress, treatment compliance, and treatment efficacy.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbeduto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shattuck</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osmond</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Psychological well-being and coping in mothers of youths with autism, Down syndrome, or fragile X syndrome</article-title>. <source>American Journal on Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>American Academy of Pediatrics: Committee on Children With Disabilities</collab>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Counseling families who choose complementary and alternative medicine for their child with chronic illness or disability</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>598</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burbine</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tantleff-Dunn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Moderators of stress in parents of children with autism</article-title>. <source>Community Mental Health Journal</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenhower</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blacher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Preschool children with intellectual disability: Syndrome specificity, behaviour problems, and maternal well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Defeating autism: A damaging delusion</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fraley</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>How to conduct behavioral research over the Internet: A beginner’s guide to HTML and CGI/Perl</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goin-Kochel</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Parental reports on the efficacy of treatments and therapies for their children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>528</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goin-Kochel</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Parental report of early autistic symptoms: Differences in ages of detection and frequencies of characteristics among three autism-spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal on Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goin-Kochel</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Parental reports on the use of treatments and therapies for children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gosling</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vazire</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>John</surname><given-names>O. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Should we trust web-based studies? A comparative analysis of six preconceptions about Internet questionnaires</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Granello</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheaton</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Online data collection: Strategies for research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Parental experience with treatments for autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Developmental and Physical Disabilities</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pituch</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Itchon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Reilly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sigafoos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Internet survey of treatments used by parents of children with autism</article-title>. <source>Research in Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Stress in UK families conducting intensive home-based behavioral intervention for their young child with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodapp</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Parenting children with mental retardation</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Handbook of parenting: Vol. 1. Children and parenting</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Children with autism and Asperger’s syndrome: A guide for practitioners and carers</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koegel</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schreibman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Los</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dirlich-Wilhelm</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plienis</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Consistent stress profiles in mothers of children with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Konstantareas</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Homatidis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Assessing child symptom severity and stress in parents of autistic children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lanners</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mombaerts</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of parents’ satisfaction with early intervention services within and among European countries: Construction and application of a new parent satisfaction scale</article-title>. <source>Infants and Young Children</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szatmari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Yoder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Challenges in evaluating psychosocial interventions for autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goin-Kochel</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Sources of information and support used by parents of children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal on Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mannion</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Letso</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Parent voices: Difficulty in accessing behavioral intervention for autism: Working toward solutions</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Interventions</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Merriam-Webster Online</collab> (<year>n.d.</year>). <source>Merriam-Webster</source>. <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.merriam-webster.com">http://www.merriam-webster.com</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mulick</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butter</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Autism: A late-20th-ventury fad magnet</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mulick</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Controversial therapies for developmental disabilities: Fad, fashion and science in professional practice</source> pp. <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huberman</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Qualitative data analysis</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Montes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halterman</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Psychological functioning and coping among mothers of children with autism: A population-based study</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1040</fpage>–<lpage>1046</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nachshen</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Advocacy, stress, and quality of life in parents of children with developmental disabilities</article-title>. <source>Developmental Disabilities Bulletin</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daggett</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Beyond the autism diagnosis: A professional’s guide to helping families</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paul H. Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>M. Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Qualitative research and evaluative methods</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pisula</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A comparative study of stress profiles in mothers of children with autism and those of children with Down’s syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Preckel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thiemann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Online- versus paper-pencil version of a high potential intelligence test</article-title>. <source>Swiss Journal of Psychology</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mothers’ satisfaction with a home-based early intervention program for children with ASD</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbeduto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Comparison groups in autism family research: Down syndrome, fragile X syndrome, and schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Asymmetrical effects of positive and negative events: The mobilization-minimization hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>110</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Introduction to qualitative research methods: A guidebook and resource</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>H. H. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Patterns of complementary and alternative medical therapy use in children diagnosed with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>909</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1088357611423542">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Shindo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toshi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Emotional distress and its correlates among parents of children with pervasive developmental disorders</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry and Clinical Neurosciences</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>