<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="news" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsjp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1403-4948</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1651-1905</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494813487468</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1403494813487468</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>News from the National Institutes of Public Health</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>News from the National Institutes of Public Health</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>436</fpage>
<lpage>436</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 the Nordic Societies of Public Health</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Associations of Public Health in the Nordic Countries Regions</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1403494813487468">
<title>The National Institute for Health and Welfare in Finland (THL)</title>
<sec id="section2-1403494813487468">
<title>Patients living alone have a higher risk of heart attack</title>
<p>Marriage significantly reduces the risk of acute coronary events among both men and women. A recent study, co-ordinated by THL and carried out in collaboration with several hospitals in Finland, also reveals that prognosis of acute coronary events is worse in patients living alone.</p>
<p>The incidence of acute coronary events was, on average, 1.6 times higher in unmarried men and women than in married men and women. Also, the 28-day mortality rate was, on average, 2.1 times higher among unmarried men and women. Most deaths occurred before hospitalization.</p>
<p>The morbidity and mortality data was collected from the population-based FINAMI myocardial infarction register and the study sample consisted of 15 330 acute coronary events in 1993–2002.</p>
<p><bold>Reference</bold></p>
<p>European Journal of Preventive Cardiology:</p>
<p>Prognosis of acute coronary events is worse in patients living alone: the FINAMI myocardial infarction register <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cpr.sagepub.com/content/early/2013/01/29/2047487313475893">http://cpr.sagepub.com/content/early/2013/01/29/2047487313475893</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1403494813487468">
<title>Long-term psychotherapy gives more sustained benefits than short-term therapy</title>
<p>A recent study followed 326 outpatients with mood or anxiety disorder for five years during 1995-2000. The patients were randomly assigned to three types of therapy: 3-year long-term psychodynamic psychotherapy, short-term half-year psychodynamic therapy and short-term solution-focused therapy.</p>
<p>The rate of recovery from psychiatric symptoms and the work ability improvement rate remained higher in the long-term therapy group 5 years after the start of therapy, whereas no differences were found in the effectiveness of the two short-term therapies.</p>
<p>The present results were obtained in a randomized clinical trial with an exceptionally long follow-up. The findings suggest the need for a careful evaluation of the suitability of short-term therapy.</p>
<p>The Helsinki Psychotherapy Study is led by THL and carried out in collaboration with several institutions and hospitals.</p>
<p><bold>Reference</bold></p>
<p>Knekt P, Lindfors O, Sares-Jäske L, Virtala E, Härkänen T. Randomized trial on the effectiveness of long- and short-term psychotherapy on psychiatric symptoms and working ability during a 5-year follow-up. Nord J Psychiatry 2013; 67: 59-68. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://informahealthcare.com/doi/abs/10.3109/08039488.2012.680910">http://informahealthcare.com/doi/abs/10.3109/08039488.2012.680910</ext-link></p>
<p>Helsinki Psychotherapy Study <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thl.fi/en_US/web/en/research/projects/helsinki_psychotherapy_study">http://www.thl.fi/en_US/web/en/research/projects/helsinki_psychotherapy_study</ext-link></p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section4-1403494813487468">
<title>The Norwegian Institute of Public Health</title>
<sec id="section5-1403494813487468">
<title>Can environmental contaminants cause lower sperm count?</title>
<p>The amount of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) that mothers had in their blood during pregnancy was correlated with their sons’ semen quality at 20 years old. These findings appear in a recent study from Aarhus University Hospital, Denmark, in which the Norwegian Institute of Public Health participated.</p>
<p>Read more: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fhi.no/artikler/?id=105443">http://www.fhi.no/artikler/?id=105443</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1403494813487468">
<title>Environmental contaminants may reduce immunity</title>
<p>Exposure to environmental contaminants during pregnancy is associated with an increased risk of infections during the first three years of life and a reduced response to childhood vaccines. This is found in two studies from the Norwegian Mother and Child Cohort Study (MoBa) at the Norwegian Institute of Public Health.</p>
<p>Read more: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fhi.no/artikler/?id=105425">http://www.fhi.no/artikler/?id=105425</ext-link></p>
</sec></sec>
</body>
</article>