<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="introduction" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Politics &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0032-3292</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7514</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0032329213483104</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0032329213483104</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Introduction to the Special Issue</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Real Utopias<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0032329213483104">*</xref></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>Erik Olin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0032329213483104">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0032329213483104"><label>1</label>University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0032329213483104">
<label>*</label>
<p>This article is part of the June 2013 special issue of <italic>Politics &amp; Society</italic> called “Real Utopias.” The papers were originally presented at the 2012 Annual Meeting of the American Sociological Association held in Denver, Colorado. The theme of the conference was “Real Utopias: Emancipatory Projects, Institutional Designs, Possible Futures.”</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="corresp1-0032329213483104">Erik Olin Wright, Department of Sociology, University of Wisconsin, 1180 Observatory Drive, Madison, WI 53706, USA. Email: <email>wright@ssc.wisc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Real Utopias</issue-title>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>169</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Many people are drawn to the social sciences because of moral concerns about harmful social conditions and injustices. Those concerns are reflected in much research in sociology, political science, and other social sciences, but usually they take the form of diagnosis and critique of existing institutions rather than exploration of alternatives. A great deal of scholarship focuses on explaining the sources of social injustice and the causes and consequences of undesirable social conditions; it is rare for academics to explore the design of alternatives to existing institutions that would help realize moral ideals of justice and human flourishing. The idea of “real utopias” is meant to point social research in this direction.</p>
<p>The expression “real utopias” is, of course, an oxymoron: utopia means “nowhere”—a fantasy world of perfect harmony and social justice. When politicians want to summarily dismiss a proposal for social transformation as an impractical dream outside the limits of possibility, they call it “utopian.” Realists reject such fantasies as a distraction from the serious business of making practical improvements in existing institutions. The idea of real utopias embraces this tension between dreams and practice: “utopia” implies developing visions of alternatives to existing institutions that embody our deepest aspirations for a world in which all people have access to the conditions to live flourishing lives; “real” means taking seriously the problem of the viability of the institutions that could move us in the direction of that world. The goal is to elaborate utopian ideals that are grounded in the real potentials of humanity, utopian destinations that have accessible way stations, utopian designs of viable institutions that can inform our practical tasks of navigating a world of imperfect conditions for social change.</p>
<p>Exploring real utopias implies developing a social science of the <italic>possible</italic>, not just of the <italic>actual</italic>. This is a tricky research problem, for while we can directly observe variation in what exists in the world, discussions of possibilities and limits of possibility always involve more speculative and contentious claims about what could be, not just what is. The task is to combine theoretical analysis of normatively desirable institutional designs with the empirical study of real-world cases that prefigure emancipatory alternatives beyond existing institutions.</p>
<p>The six articles in this special issue of <italic>Politics &amp; Society</italic> engage the idea of real utopias in a variety of ways. They were originally presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Sociological Association (ASA) in Denver, August 2012, as part of the theme of the conference: “Real Utopias: Emancipatory Projects, Institutional Designs, Possible Futures.”</p>
<p>Philippe van Paijs, in his article, “The Universal Basic Income: Why Utopian Thinking Matters, and How Sociologists Can Contribute to It,” explores two themes—first, the importance of utopian thinking for dealing with the pressing problems the world faces, and second, the idea of unconditional basic income as a real utopian alternative to the existing institutions of income distribution. Archon Fung’s article, “Infotopia: Unleashing the Democratic Power of Transparency,” examines the problem of how citizens can acquire the information they need to function effectively in complex environments. In recent years the idea of “transparency” has increasingly been held up as an ideal for institutions. But what, precisely, does this mean? What forms of transparency and information diffusion are best suited to create the genuinely informed citizens required of democratic ideals? What institutional devices are needed for an informational utopia? Yochai Benkler, in “Practical Anarchism: Peer Mutualism, Market Power, and the Fallible State,” discusses a distinctive form of productive association that has emerged in the internet age: peer-to-peer collaborative production. This is a way of organizing large-scale cooperation that is very different from either the market or the state and offers new possibilities for human freedom. John Gastil’s article, “Making Direct Democracy Deliberative through Random Assemblies,” proposes an institutional strategy for expanding the possibilities for direct democracy—democracy rooted in the direct participation of citizens in making legislative decisions—in large, complex, modern societies. The basic idea is to create assemblies of randomly chosen citizens who are empowered to make particular kinds of decisions. Gerald Davis, in “After the Corporation,” argues that the modern publicly traded capitalist corporation is in the process of disintegration, in part at least because technological changes connected to new informational technologies have dramatically reduced the advantages of size. This, in turn, opens up the possibility for a variety of forms of more decentralized, democratic, and egalitarian forms of economic organization. Finally, in “Reviving Democratic Citizenship,” Bruce Ackerman elaborates a package of interconnected institutional proposals for supporting a more empowered, civically engaged and politically effective citizenry: a system for publicly funding elections through equal citizen vouchers; a new national holiday for organized public deliberation by citizens of pressing political choices; a system of user-directed public subsidy for news media; and a capital grant to every young adult to give everyone a measure of real autonomy to make critical life choices.</p>
<p>We plan to publish more “real utopia” papers from the 2012 ASA in subsequent issues of the journal and we welcome new submissions that elaborate designs for alternative institutions that are grounded in reality. <italic>Politics &amp; Society</italic> has always encouraged articles that elaborate what Robert Lynd once called “some outrageous hypotheses,” and we see the construction of such alternative visions as an urgent task for the social sciences.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Erik Olin Wright</bold> (<email>wright@ssc.wisc.edu</email>) is Vilas Distinguished Professor at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. Since 1992 he has directed The <italic>Real Utopias Project</italic> which explores a wide range of institutional innovations and proposals that embody emancipatory ideals and yet are attentive to issues of pragmatic feasibility. He was president of the American Sociological Association 2011-2012. His most recent books include <italic>Deepening Democracy: Institutional Innovations in Empowered Participatory Governance</italic> (with Archon Fung. London: Verso: 2003); <italic>Envisioning Real Utopias</italic> (Verso, 2010) and jointly with Joel Rogers, <italic>American Society: How it Really Works</italic> (W. W. Norton, 2011).</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>