<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjap</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of the American Psychiatric Nurses Association</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-3903</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1532-5725</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078390313486617</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078390313486617</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Evidence-Based Decision Making in Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Farchaus Stein</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1078390313486617">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1078390313486617"><label>1</label>Karen Farchaus Stein, PhD, RN, FAAN, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078390313486617">Karen Farchaus Stein, University of Rochester School of Nursing, 601 Elmwood Ave, Box SON, Rochester, NY 14642, USA. Email: <email>KarenF_Stein@URMC.Rochester.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>61</fpage>
<lpage>62</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Psychiatric Nurses Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>March/April 2013</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>We are living in an era in which a myriad of empirical evidence is available and recognized as an essential foundation for effective decision making. A simple Internet search reveals that the use of empirical evidence to guide decision making is not only considered best practice in nursing and medicine but also in areas such as criminal justice, public health, business management, and local, federal, and international policy development. Empirically based decision making refers to the use of the best (e.g., valid and reliable) scientific knowledge to guide the decision process and outcome. Evidence-based decision making is distinguished from decisions that are driven solely by opinions, attitudes, personal experience, or speculation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078390313486617">Segone &amp; Pron, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>As a regular reader of the APNA Member Bridge, I am repeatedly impressed with the number of postings that refer to the literature and published results in the context of clinical questions and problems. Postings addressing evidence to support mental health care decisions are regular and frequent. However, despite our impressive progress, remnants of our disciplinary history of sole reliance on personal experience and opinion are still evident. My last two editorials (see Vol. 18[6] and Vol. 19[1]) addressed this exact point. In the editorial titled, “A Pressing Question: Is There a Place for Psychotherapy in PMHNP Practice” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078390313486617">Stein, 2012</xref>), I argued that psychotherapy will remain an important component of advanced PMH nursing practice only if evidence demonstrating its efficacy and cost-effectiveness is brought to bear. Arguments for the inclusion of psychotherapy as part of advanced practice roles that are based solely on personal values and emotion will do little to convince potential employers of the benefits of this investment of resources. The issue of gun control raised in my last editorial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078390313486617">Stein, 2013</xref>) similarly led to professional exchanges based solely on individual experience and personal preference. Knowledge from studies investigating the effects of gun ownership on household firearm–related fatalities was not included in the discussion (for examples of relevant studies, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078390313486617">Grossman, Reay, &amp; Baker, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078390313486617">Kellermann et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078390313486617">Kellermann et al., 1993</xref>). Likewise, a series of posting related to telemedicine as an efficacious method of mental health service delivery did not draw on the large collection of published studies that have addressed this very issue. These issues are just a few examples of the multiple ways that we are called on as professional nurses to participate in decision-making processes. These examples point to the weight of our decision making in influencing the health and well-being of others and the need for responsible decisions makers who are fully informed with empirically supported facts, as well as professional experience.</p>
<p>As each of us moves forward in our professional roles—whether it is in clinical practice, care delivery administration, policy development, or academics—an important question to consider at each decision making juncture is, “Am I adequately informed of the current evidence/knowledge related to the problem?” If no, what avenues are available to me to acquire updated, unbiased knowledge? Certainly the circumstances will vary in terms of time and resources available to pursue the needed evidence to fully inform your decision. In addition, the added value of personal/professional experience, values, and opinions in determining the fit between the evidence, specific individual, and context cannot be ignored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078390313486617">Sackett, Rosenberg, Gray, Haynes, &amp; Richardson, 1996</xref>). However, each of us must accept responsibility for moving beyond anecdotal experience and opinion as the sole basis of our decision making. The time for viewing research as the sole province of the “ivory tower” is over. As professional nurses, each of us is responsible for acquiring the empirical evidence needed to make informed decisions that will contribute to the health and well-being of those that we serve.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reay</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Self-inflicted and unintentional firearm injuries among children and adolescents: The source of the firearm</article-title>. <source>Archives of Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine</source>, <volume>153</volume>, <fpage>875</fpage>-<lpage>878</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kellermann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rivara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rushforth</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reay</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franccisco</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Gun ownership as a risk factor for homicide in the home</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>329</volume>, <fpage>1084</fpage>-<lpage>1091</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kellermann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rivara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reay</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franccisco</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hackman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Suicide in the home in relation to gun ownership</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>327</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>472</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Evidence based medicine: What it is and what it isn’t</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>312</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Segone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pron</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The role of statistics in evidence-based decision making</source> (UNECE Work Session on Statistical Dissemination and Communication). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/stats/documents/2008/05/dissemination/wp.10.e.pdf">http://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/stats/documents/2008/05/dissemination/wp.10.e.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A pressing question: Is there a place for psychotherapy in PMHNP practice?</article-title> <source>Journal of the American Psychiatric Nurses Association</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078390313486617">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>An unanticipated journey: Barriers to effective gun control in the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal of American Psychiatric Nurses Association</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>