<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VES</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spves</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vasc Endovascular Surg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Vascular and Endovascular Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1538-5744</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-9116</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1538574412449910</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1538574412449910</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Giant True Brachial Artery Aneurysm</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>Sydney Sek Ning</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412449910">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1538574412449910"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roche-Nagle</surname>
<given-names>Graham</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, MBA, FRCSI, EBSQ-VASC</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412449910">1</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1538574412449910"><label>1</label>Department of Vascular Surgery, Toronto General Hospital, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1538574412449910">Sydney Sek Ning Wong, The Banting Institute, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON M5G 1L5, Canada Email: <email>sydney.wong@utoronto.ca</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>46</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>492</fpage>
<lpage>494</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>True brachial artery aneurysms (BAAs) are uncommon peripheral vessel aneurysms that typically occur in the setting of injury. While its relationship with trauma and infectious etiologies are well defined, the association between arteriovenous fistulas (AVFs) and BAA is less well understood. We present a case of a giant true BAA that presented several years post-AVF ligation. A review of BAA, its association with AVF, and its management follows.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>brachial artery</kwd>
<kwd>peripheral aneurysm</kwd>
<kwd>arteriovenous fistula</kwd>
<kwd>arteriomegaly</kwd>
<kwd>hemodialysis</kwd>
<kwd>degenerative aneurysm</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1538574412449910">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>True brachial artery aneurysms (BAAs) are uncommon peripheral vessel aneurysms that are typically associated with trauma or infectious etiologies. An association with arteriovenous fistulas (AVFs) has also been noted. They typically present in the setting of a mass in the upper extremity with a history consistent with local injury or inflammation. The natural history of this disease is not well understood, but once diagnosed, treatment is recommended to prevent possible complications from thrombosis or emboli.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1538574412449910">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 37-year-old gentleman presented to the vascular surgery clinic following an incidental finding of a giant left BAA. Several years previously the patient had a radiocephalic fistula ligated following a successful renal transplant. The radial artery had been tied off during this procedure as the graft appeared quite aneurysmal. Unfortunately, the transplant eventually failed necessitating resumption of hemodialysis, through a dialysis central line.</p>
<p>Despite this large pulsatile mass in the patient’s left upper arm, he was relatively asymptomatic and had not suffered any complications. The distal arm and hand were viable and an ulnar pulse was palpable. There had been no history of trauma or recent intravenous insertion in the area.</p>
<p>Following confirmation with duplex ultrasonography, a computed tomography angiography scan was performed on the upper extremity to delineate the anatomy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1538574412449910">Figure 1</xref>). The images revealed that the patient had an ectatic brachial artery extending proximally to the axilla. The fusiform aneurysm measured 4.4 cm in maximal diameter and extended 8 cm in length. In addition, the aneurysm appeared mostly thrombosed.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1538574412449910" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Three-dimensional reconstruction of a computed tomography angiography scan showing fusiform aneurysm at mid to distal brachial artery (lined arrow). Note significantly ectatic proximal brachial artery and axillary artery (arrow head).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412449910-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Due to the risk of emboli to the remaining perfusing vessel to the hand, operative repair was recommended. Vein mapping identified suitable venous bypass grafts for the procedure. The aneurysm was resected and reconstruction consisted of a brachial to ulnar artery bypass with reverse saphenous vein graft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1538574412449910">Figures 2</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1538574412449910"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1538574412449910">4</xref>). An end-to-side anastamosis was required proximally as the brachial artery was quite ectatic. An end-to-end anastamosis was fashioned distally at the ulnar artery.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1538574412449910" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Intraoperative photograph of exposed aneurysm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412449910-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1538574412449910" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Opening of aneursym and evacuation of thrombus.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412449910-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1538574412449910" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Aneurysm resected and reconstruction with reverse saphenous vein graft. Note ligation of brachial artery stump and end-to-side anastamosis proximally. Distally, the graft is anastamosed to the ulnar artery in an end-to-end fashion.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412449910-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Postoperatively, the patient did well, with a palpable ulnar pulse throughout his stay. During 3 months follow-up, the patient continued to have good function.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1538574412449910">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Brachial artery aneurysms are uncommon<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1538574412449910">1</xref>
</sup> and typically occur in the setting of trauma, intravenous drug use, endocarditis, congenital syndromes, or vasculitis.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412449910">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412449910"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1538574412449910"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574412449910"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574412449910"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574412449910">7</xref>
</sup> True BAA represent an even smaller proportion of all aneurysms occurring in the upper extremity. In a review by the Cleveland clinic, only 1 of 581 procedures done on the brachial artery was for a true aneurysm.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1538574412449910">8</xref>
</sup> The Mayo clinic did a similar review that identified only 2 cases over a 20-year period.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1538574412449910">9</xref>
</sup> Because of its low incidence, the natural history of an untreated brachial aneurysm is difficult to discern. Therefore, management principles are often drawn from recommendations for popliteal aneurysms, which have a high rate of complications if untreated.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1538574412449910">10</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Interestingly, while popliteal aneurysms are highly associated with synchronous aneurysms elsewhere, aneurysms in the upper extremity do not appear to have the same association. The Mayo clinic study showed only an 8% incidence of concurrent aneurysm in 12 cases of true upper extremity aneurysm.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1538574412449910">9</xref>
</sup> This may represent a difference in pathogenesis as aneurysms in this region are related to local vascular injury such as trauma rather than systemic atherosclerotic disease.</p>
<p>An association between BAA and AVFs has been observed for some time.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1538574412449910">11</xref>
</sup> Most cases involve the site of anastamosis or are venous in nature, related to repetitive punctures. Few are true degenerative aneurysms with arteriomegaly as illustrated by our case. A current theory of pathogenesis in this setting involves adaptive arterial wall expansion in the face of sheer forces from increased flow.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1538574412449910">12</xref>
</sup> This may result in tears through the elastic fibers in the internal transverse membrane, predisposing to aneurysm development.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1538574412449910">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1538574412449910">14</xref>
</sup> Interestingly, the process may not be fully arrested by fistula closure,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1538574412449910">15</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1538574412449910"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1538574412449910"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1538574412449910">18</xref>
</sup> leading to the permanent nature of this transformative process.</p>
<p>Renal transplantation, as was the case in our patient, may also be associated with aneurysm progression. Eugster et al followed patients post-AVF and renal transplantation over a period of 10 years with ultrasound. The study concluded that arterial dilatation was time dependent and also showed a trend for higher arterial diameters in transplanted compared with nontransplanted patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1538574412449910">19</xref>
</sup> There is some evidence that immunosuppression and corticosteroids increase the progression and development of aneurysmal disease.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1538574412449910">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1538574412449910">21</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The presentation of BAA is similar to that of other peripheral artery aneurysms. Most commonly, they present as an asymptomatic mass. However, pain and paresthesias from local compression can be observed as well. Much less common are ischemic presentations including distal embolization and a low risk of rupture. Physical examination should involve neurologic evaluation as well as signs of distal embolic disease.</p>
<p>Duplex ultrasonography is the initial diagnostic test of choice. Computed tomography angiography may be performed for operative planning, and limited conventional angiography can be employed in selective cases.</p>
<p>Management of BAA remains consensus based and is most often surgical. In uncommon cases such as endocarditis and vasculitis, medical therapy may be tried initially. Surgical reconstruction is generally recommended for aneurysms that are 1.5 to 2 times the normal arterial diameter.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1538574412449910">8</xref>
</sup> Usually this consists of excision and ligation with reconstruction bypass grafts. Vein patches may be used in anatomically suitable cases. Endovascular techniques have been explored and successfully employed in the treatment of pseudoaneurysms related to vascular access<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1538574412449910">22</xref>
</sup>—however, their use in true BAA has not been validated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1538574412449910">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>True BAAs are uncommon entity and are typically a result of local vascular injury. They are associated with AVFs and there is some evidence that closure of the fistula does not preclude future aneurysm formation. Immunosuppression may also have an impact on its development. Currently, surgical therapy is the mainstay of therapy with medical management in few select cases. Endovascular treatment has not yet been validated for this disease.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1538574412449910">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1538574412449910">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1538574412449910">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mays</surname>
<given-names>ET</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Traumatic aneurysms of the hand</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source>. <year>1970</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1538574412449910">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Got</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thakur</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marcaccio</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eberson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Madom</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Delayed presentation of a brachial artery pseudoaneurysm after a supracondylar humerus fracture in a 6-year-old boy: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Orthop</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1538574412449910">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Konishi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saito</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Misawa</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Crutch-induced bilateral brachial artery aneurysms</article-title>. <source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1038</fpage>–<lpage>1039</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1538574412449910">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wahlgren</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lohman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pearce</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spiguel</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dorafshar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Skelly</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Metachronous giant brachial artery pseudoaneurysms: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Vasc Endovascular Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1538574412449910">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Acikgoz</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tavil</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yazici</surname>
<given-names>HU</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Giant brachial artery aneurysm secondary to infective endocarditis</article-title>. <source>Tex Heart Inst J</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1538574412449910">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">Jones Tr, Frusha JD, Stromeyer FW</collab>. <article-title>Brachial artery aneurysm in an infant: case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1538574412449910">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>De Letter</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Joos</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Multiple congenital aneurysms of unknown origin</article-title>. <source>Eur J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1538574412449910">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schunn</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Brachial arteriomegaly and true aneurysmal degeneration: case report and literature review</article-title>. <source>Vasc Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1538574412449910">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fowl</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, <article-title>Bower TC. management of true aneurysms distal to the axillary artery</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>606</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1538574412449910">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vermilion</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kimmins</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pace</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>WE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A review of one hundred forty-seven popliteal aneurysms with long-term follow-up</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1538574412449910">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chemla</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nortley</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morsy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Brachial artery aneurysms associated with arteriovenous access for hemodialysis</article-title>. <source>Semin Dial</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1538574412449910">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dammers</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tordoir</surname>
<given-names>JHM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Welten</surname>
<given-names>RJTHJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kitslaar</surname>
<given-names>PJEHM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoeks</surname>
<given-names>APG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of chronic flow changes on brachial artery diameter and shear stress in arteriovenous fistulas for hemodialysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Artif Organs</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1538574412449910">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greenhill</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stehbens</surname>
<given-names>WE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Scanning electron microscopic study of afferent arteries on experimental femoral arteriovenous fistulae in rabbits</article-title>. <source>Pathology</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1538574412449910">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stehbens</surname>
<given-names>WE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>PF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Scanning electron microscopic study of hemodynamically induced tears in the internal elastic lamina of rabbit arteries</article-title>. <source>Pathology</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1538574412449910">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Melliere</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hanssen-Khodja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cormier</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LeBas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mikati</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ronsse</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Proximal arterial dilatation after surgical closure of long-standing posttraumatic arteriovenous fistula</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1538574412449910">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hartung</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alimi</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Juhan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Extensive arterial aneurysm developing after surgical closure of long-standing post-traumatic popliteal arteriovenous fistula</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>889</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1538574412449910">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>DQ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ruddle</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Late axillo-brachial arterial aneurysm following ligated Brescia-Cimino haemodialysis fistula</article-title>. <source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1538574412449910">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Battaglia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bucci</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Battaglia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reddler</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Late occurrence of large brachial artery aneurysm following closure of hemodialysis arteriovenous fistula</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1538574412449910">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eugster</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wigger</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bolter</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bock</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hodel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stierli</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Brachial artery dilatation after arteriovenous fistulae in patients after renal transplantation: a 10-year follow-up with ultrasound scan</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1538574412449910">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reilly</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Savage</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brophy</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tilson</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hydrocortisone rapidly induces aortic rupture in a genetically susceptible mouse</article-title>. <source>Arch Surg</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1538574412449910">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sato</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takagi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miyata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Takayama</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Aortic aneurysms in patients with autoimmune disorders treated with corticosteroids</article-title>. <source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1538574412449910">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vesely</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Use of stent grafts to repair hemodialysis graft-related pseudoaneurysms</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Intervent Radiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1301</fpage>–<lpage>1307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>