<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PRF</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spprf</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Perfusion</journal-id>
<journal-title>Perfusion</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0267-6591</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-111X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0267659111412006</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0267659111412006</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Commentary on: Long-term use of the Centrimag<sup>®</sup> ventricular assist system as a right ventricular assist system: a case report</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<role>Presenter</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>71</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. DAVID CLEMENTS (Spokane, Washington):</speaker>
<p>I suspect that the University of Michigan has some fantastic financial resources to accommodate that type of patient care. You see the end product and it is difficult to even have a conversation about money. I did a quick calculation based on my hospital’s per diem Intensive Care Unit (ICU) charges. Just the ICU charges alone were just short of $15 million. Those kinds of charges would bankrupt some programs. I was just wondering if you have some insight into that conversation during the patient’s care?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. KEVIN GRIFFITH (Ann Arbor, Michigan):</speaker>
<p>Thankfully, I am not involved in any of the number crunching regarding costs, but, yes, it was a huge commitment for this patient.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. JOSHUA WALKER (San Antonio, Texas):</speaker>
<p>Have the people from CentriMag<sup>®</sup> (Thoratec, Levitronics<sup>®</sup>) addressed the issue with you of why there is not a hand crank available?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. GRIFFITH:</speaker>
<p>No, I have never really discussed it with them. They have not been forthcoming with that information.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>CO-MODERATOR WILLIAM HARRIS (Luling, Louisiana):</speaker>
<p>At the University of Michigan, are the perfusionists scrubbing in and assembling all the ventricular assist devices?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. GRIFFITH:</speaker>
<p>Yes, we prepare all the devices for implant.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>CO-MODERATOR HARRIS:</speaker>
<p>So, usually these procedures require two perfusionists, one for conducting cardiopulmonary bypass while the other one is assembling the device?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. GRIFFITH:</speaker>
<p>Yes, that is correct. To do that, though, it takes a lot of training and drills to keep everyone’s skills up-to-date, because it can be some time without seeing a device being used. We try to have drills every two weeks on some different device to keep everyone current on preparing the devices for implantation.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>CO-MODERATOR HARRIS:</speaker>
<p>I understand the new HeartMate™ II graft (Thoratec), that will be pre-clotted, will be available probably this year.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. GRIFFITH:</speaker>
<p>We are actually already conducting trials and it is ready. They might have already used it. We have also received the HeartMate™ II inflow sealed conduit as well and they will start distributing that shortly as well. There is a caution with that, though. You will notice that the sealed outflow conduit for the HeartMate™ II is much stretchier than the old conduit. So, when your surgeons are sizing it, they need to put a good stretch on it, because we did have one that was implanted and then kinked later. So, it is an issue and the new conduit is not identical to the old conduit.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>CO-MODERATOR HARRIS:</speaker>
<p>So, in other words, they should stretch it and then make the cut?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. GRIFFITH:</speaker>
<p>Correct.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>CO-MODERATOR HARRIS:</speaker>
<p>Once you stretch it, does it remain longer?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MR. GRIFFITH:</speaker>
<p>It will spring back. Once it is pressurized, however, it will start to snake if you have it too long and then it will kink.</p>
</speech>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>This commentary is taken from the discussion that followed the presentation of the previous paper at the 32<sup>nd</sup> Annual Seminar of the American Academy of Cardiovascular Perfusion. Although the paper has been through <italic>Perfusion</italic>’s stringent peer-review process, the commentary is a transcript of the discussion, edited for clarity, and the views expressed in the commentary are those of the commentators and do not necessarily represent, and should not be attributed to, the journal <italic>Perfusion</italic>, the Editors, or the Publisher, SAGE.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>