<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcre</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Rehabil</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Rehabilitation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0269-2155</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0873</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269215511426803</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269215511426803</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Evaluative studies</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Immediate effects of electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement on gait velocity and spasticity in persons with hemiparetic stroke: a randomized controlled study</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Tomofumi</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0269215511426803">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>Shigeo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0269215511426803">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>Yoshihiro</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0269215511426803">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Masakado</surname><given-names>Yoshihisa</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0269215511426803">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Akio</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0269215511426803">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>Tetsuya</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-0269215511426803">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Meigen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-0269215511426803">6</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0269215511426803"><label>1</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Keio University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0269215511426803"><label>2</label>Faculty of Rehabilitation School of Health Sciences, Fujita Health University, Aichi, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0269215511426803"><label>3</label>Faculty of Human Sciences, Waseda University, Saitama, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0269215511426803"><label>4</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Tokai University School of Medicine, Kanagawa, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0269215511426803"><label>5</label>University Tsukigase Rehabilitation Center, Shizuoka, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff6-0269215511426803"><label>6</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Keio University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0269215511426803">Meigen Liu, Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Keio University School of Medicine, 35 Shinanomachi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan Email: <email>meigenliukeio@mac.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>619</fpage>
<lpage>628</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>5</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>24</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Objective</bold>: Research to examine the immediate effects of electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement on gait velocity and spasticity.</p>
<p><bold>Design</bold>: A single-masked, randomized controlled trial design.</p>
<p><bold>Subjects</bold>: Twenty-seven stroke inpatients in subacute phase (ischemic <italic>n</italic>=16, hemorrhagic <italic>n</italic>=11).</p>
<p><bold>Interventions</bold>: A novel approach using electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement.</p>
<p><bold>Main measures</bold>: We assessed the maximum gait speed and modified Ashworth scale before and 20 minutes after the interventions.</p>
<p><bold>Results</bold>: The gait velocity of the electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement group showed the increase form 0.68±0.28 (mean±SD, unit: m) to 0.76±0.32 after the intervention. Both the electrical stimulation group and passive locomotion-like movement group also showed increases after the interventions (from 0.76±0.37 to 0.79±0.40, from 0.74±0.35 to 0.77±0.36, respectively). The gait velocity of the electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement group differed significantly from those of the other groups (electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement versus electrical stimulation: <italic>P</italic>=0.049, electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement versus passive locomotion-like movement: <italic>P</italic>=0.025). Although there was no statistically significant difference in the modified Ashworth scale among the three groups, six of the nine subjects (66.6%) in the electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement group showed improvement in the modified Ashworth scale score, while only three of the nine subjects (33.3%) in the electrical stimulation group and two of the nine subjects (22.2%) improved in the passive locomotion-like movement group.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion</bold>: These findings suggest electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement could improve gait velocity in stroke patients.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0269215511426803" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The improvement of ambulation is among the most important goals in patients with stroke. Recently, research indicated the effectiveness of training for hemiparetic gait, such as treadmill walking with partial body weight support<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269215511426803">1</xref></sup> and robot-assisted locomotor training,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269215511426803">2</xref></sup> possibly combined with functional electrical stimulation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269215511426803">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>There are symptoms which are associated with hemiparetic gait, for example spasticity, sensory information, postural stability and strength. Especially, the spasticity of the affected ankle planter flexors is reported as the most important factor influencing temporal and spatial gait asymmetry.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269215511426803">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511426803">5</xref></sup> Lamontagne <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269215511426803">6</xref></sup> also indicated the relationship between the spasticity of the plantar flexors and ambulatory function. Accordingly, the spasticity of the plantar flexors could disturb the ambulation function in patients with stroke. Bakheit <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269215511426803">7</xref></sup> reported a relation between the Ashworth scale, a measure of spasticity, and the soleus H-reflex, which indicates the excitability of the monosynaptic reflex pathway, in patients with stroke. In our previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269215511426803">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269215511426803">9</xref></sup> we investigated the soleus H-reflex during passive locomotion-like movement, and found that the amplitude of the soleus H-reflex in patients with stroke, compared with that in healthy persons, was higher during the end of the hip extension phase and the initial hip flexion phase. In contrast, it was lower during the initial hip extension phase. These results suggested a disturbed phase-related modulation of the reflex.</p>
<p>Previously, we proposed an approach for soleus spasticity that uses electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269215511426803">10</xref></sup> This method consists of phase-related electrical stimulation for inducing modulation of the excitability changes of the soleus H-reflex during passive hip flexion-extension movements. Our previous single-case study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269215511426803">10</xref></sup> suggested that electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement combined with conventional therapy was significantly superior to conventional therapy alone for the improvement of gait function. However, whether electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement is more effective than its individual components alone, i.e. electrical stimulation or passive hip movement, remains unclear. Thus, electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement should be directly compared with these components, since both electrical stimulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269215511426803">11</xref></sup> and passive hip movement are reported to reduce spasticity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269215511426803">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>The purpose of the present study was to compare the immediate effects of electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement, electrical stimulation and passive hip movement on gait velocity and spasticity in persons with hemiparetic stroke using a single-masked, randomized controlled trial design. We hypothesized that electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement might be superior to electrical stimulation or passive hip movement alone for the improvement of gait ability and spasticity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0269215511426803" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Patients were recruited from the Keio Tukigase Rehabilitation Center. The inclusion criteria for the study were as follows:</p>
<list id="list1-0269215511426803" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>first episode of unilateral hemiparetic stroke occurring within the six-month period prior to enrolment;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>age between 40 and 75 years;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Functional Ambulation Categories<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269215511426803">13</xref></sup> score greater than 3 (ambulator-dependent for supervision);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>modified Ashworth scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269215511426803">14</xref></sup> score greater than 1 (slight increase in muscle tone) for the affected side ankle dorsiflexors.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The exclusion criteria were:</p>
<list id="list2-0269215511426803" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>unstable medical conditions;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>implanted electronic pacing or defibrillation devices;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>existing residual weakness caused by lower motor neuron lesions of either lower extremity;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mini Mental State Examination Test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269215511426803">15</xref></sup> score of 21 or lower;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>marked sensory deficit of the affected lower extremity.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>We adopted a single-masked, randomized controlled trial design. A board-certified physiatrist who was unaware of the intervention grouping performed the outcome measurements. The block randomization method was used to assign the patients to one or the two groups. The randomization sequence was generated using a permuted block sequence from a random number generator and placed into sequentially numbered envelopes by a member of the administrative staff in our department, not involved in this study, drawing lots. The patients were not masked to the intervention. The treatment allocation was concealed to the assessor. The procedures were designed so as to maximize masking for all study patents and personnel.</p>
<p>The patients were then randomly allocated to one of the following three groups: those receiving electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement, those receiving electrical stimulation alone, or those receiving passive locomotion-like movement alone. After randomization, 27 patients were assigned to the three groups (nine in each group).</p>
<p>Electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement consisted of electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0269215511426803">Figure 1a</xref>). For the electrical stimulation, we used a domestic constant voltage stimulator controlled by a personal computer running LabView 7.1 (National Instruments Corp., USA). Electrical stimulation was applied to the end-plate zone of the tibialis anterior and the soleus, using self-adhesive electrodes (HV-LLPAD, 9.8×6.4cm, Omuron Corp., Japan). The stimulation was a biphasic current with a frequency of 30 Hz, and pulse duration of 0.3 ms,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269215511426803">10</xref></sup> because these simulation parameters are known to be high enough to produce fused contractions without contractions fatigue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0269215511426803">16</xref></sup> The intensity was adjusted to be slightly above the motor threshold (e.g. visible muscle contraction). Previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269215511426803">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269215511426803"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269215511426803">19</xref></sup> have clearly shown that the electrical stimulation of antagonist muscles produces a reciprocal inhibition of agonist muscles both in healthy persons and in hemiparetic patients. Conversely, another report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269215511426803">20</xref></sup> suggested that the electrical stimulation of agonist muscles increased their H-reflex. As stated above, the soleus H-reflex amplitude of the patients was relatively high during the end of the hip extension phase and the initial hip flexion phase and relatively low during the initial hip extension phase. Therefore, the tibialis anterior, an antagonist of the soleus, was inhibited during the higher H-reflex phase. During the lower H-reflex phase, the soleus was stimulated for facilitation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269215511426803">Figure 1b</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0269215511426803" position="float">
<label>Figure 1a</label>
<caption>
<p>shows the subject’s posture and the device configuration. The patient lied in the supine position with knee and ankle joints locked with a rigid brace (full knee extension and ankle in mid-position). During passive movement, the angle measured with an electric goniometer was inputted to a computer and a stimulator attached to the computer was used to stimulate the patient.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511426803-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0269215511426803" position="float">
<label>Figure 1b</label>
<caption>
<p>shows the experimental protocol used for electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement. Electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement consisted of electrical stimulation combined with passive hip movement. The hip joint was passively flexed and extended in the range from 0° to 40° with the knee locked in full extension by a rigid knee brace. The tibialis anterior (TA) was stimulated during the end of the hip extension phase and the initial hip flexion phase. The soleus (SOL) was stimulated during the initial hip extension phase. ‘On’ and ‘off’ timing of the stimulation for the TA and SOL stimulation were controlled by change of the hip angle.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511426803-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>As a passive hip movement device, we used a therapeutic exercise machine (Yasukawa Electric Corp., Japan). The patients lied in a supine position with their knees and ankle joints locked with a rigid brace (full knee extension and ankle in mid-position). The affected lower extremity was passively raised and lowered within a range of from 0 to 40 degrees.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269215511426803">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269215511426803">10</xref></sup> During this movement, the hip joint angle was measured using an electric goniometer (Penny and Giles Electrogoniometer: Penny &amp; Giles Blackwood Ltd., Gwent, UK). The movement velocity was 8 degrees/s, which was decided by considering contractions fatigue caused by electrical stimulation. The electrical stimulation group received only the electrical stimulation, which was performed in the same manner as it was in the electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement group. Furthermore, the passive hip movement was equal to the passive hip movement used in the electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement group. Each session lasted for 20 continuous minutes.</p>
<sec id="section3-0269215511426803">
<title>Outcome measures</title>
<p>To assess the patients’ ambulatory capacity, we measured the maximum gait velocity by having them walk the length of a 10-meter walkway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269215511426803">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269215511426803"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269215511426803">23</xref></sup> A distance of 1 meter was allowed at both ends of the walkway for acceleration and deceleration. The patients were instructed to stand behind the start line and to walk as fast as possible. They were asked to repeat the procedure twice more with short rests between walks. A stopwatch was used to measure the total time taken to walk 10 meters. The mean times for the two trials was then determined and used to calculate the velocities (10 meters/second).</p>
<p>The modified Ashworth scale score (0 to 5) reflected the muscle tone of the ankle dorsiflexors on the affected side while the patient was lying, with 0 indicating no increase in tone and 5 indicating that the affected part was rigid in a flexion or extension position.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269215511426803">14</xref></sup> These assessments were performed before and immediately after each intervention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0269215511426803">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The effect of treatment on the maximum gait velocity was analyzed using analysis of covariance (ANCOVA). In ANCOVA, pretreatment maximum gait velocity was adjusted for differences in each group. The significance of differences of the treatment effects among the three groups was determined by a two-tailed multiple t-test with Bonferroni correction.</p>
<p>The modified Ashworth scale was transformed into an ordinal change score (1 = aggravated, 2 = unchanged, 3 = improved), and analyzed with Chi-squared test. Bonferroni correction multiplied by 3 was applied to correct <italic>P</italic>-values for group comparisons. We analyzed the data using a SPSS 15.0 software package for Windows (SPSS Inc., USA). The significance level was set at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0269215511426803" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Of the 51 consecutive inpatients with subacute stroke admitted during the period from September 2006 to December 2007, 36 patients met the inclusion criteria and all of them agreed to participate in the study. However, nine of them were excluded based on the exclusion criteria. The remaining 27 patients fulfilled the criteria and provided their written informed consent prior to participating in the present study, which was approved by our institutional ethics committee (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269215511426803">Figure 2</xref>). Patient characteristics for each group are referred to in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0269215511426803">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0269215511426803" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Flow diagram of randomization.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511426803-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0269215511426803" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Patient characteristics for each treatment group</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0269215511426803" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511426803-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Groups</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement(<italic>n</italic>=6)</th>
<th align="left">Electrical stimulation(<italic>n</italic>=9)</th>
<th align="left">Passive locomotion-like movement(<italic>n</italic>=9)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Gender (male/female)</td>
<td>4/5</td>
<td>5/4</td>
<td>6/3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean age±SD(y)</td>
<td>61.7±10.4</td>
<td>66.4±11.0</td>
<td>64.9±6.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Side affected (right/left)</td>
<td>5/4</td>
<td>5/4</td>
<td>3/6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time since stroke(day)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511426803">※</xref></sup></td>
<td>92(23–169)</td>
<td>98(21–150)</td>
<td>65(36–150)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mechanism of stroke(Ischemia/hemorrhage)</td>
<td>6/3</td>
<td>5/4</td>
<td>5/4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lower extremity Brunnstrom stage(III/IV/V)</td>
<td>4/3/2</td>
<td>4/4/1</td>
<td>3/5/1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Functional Ambulation Categories(3/4)</td>
<td>4/5</td>
<td>3/6</td>
<td>3/6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0269215511426803">
<label>※</label>
<p>Median (range, min to max). Lower extremity Brunnstrom stage III: voluntary synergistic movement (combined hip flexion, knee flexion, and ankle dorsiflexion, both sitting and standing); IV: some movements deviating from synergy (knee flexion &lt;90° and ankle dorsiflexion with the heel on the floor in the sitting position); V: independence from basic synergies (isolated knee flexion with the hip extended and isolated ankle dorsiflexion with the knee extended in the standing position).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0269215511426803">
<p>Functional ambulation category 3: patient requires verbal supervision or stand-by help from one person without physical contact; 4: patient can walk independently on level ground, but requires help on stairs, slopes or uneven surfaces.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0269215511426803">Table 2</xref> shows gait velocity in the three groups before and after the treatment. The gait velocity of the electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement group showed an increase from 0.68±0.28 m/s (mean±SD) to 0.76±0.32 m/s after the intervention. Both the electrical stimulation group and passive locomotion-like movement group also showed increases after the interventions (form 0.76±0.37 m/s to 0.79±0.40 m/s, and from 0.74±0.35 m/s to 0.77±0.36 m/s, respectively).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0269215511426803" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Walking velocities in the electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement, electrical stimulation, and passive hip movement groups</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0269215511426803" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511426803-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Group</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">Pretreatment</th>
<th align="left">Posttreatment</th>
<th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-values (95% confidence intervals)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>0.68±0.28</td>
<td>0.76±0.32</td>
<td>Electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement versus Electrical stimulation: <italic>P</italic>=0.049 (0.00–0.11)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0269215511426803">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Electrical stimulation</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>0.76±0.37</td>
<td>0.79±0.40</td>
<td>Electrical stimulation combined with passive locomotion-like movement versus passive locomotion-like movement: <italic>P</italic>=0.025 (0.00–0.11)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0269215511426803">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Passive locomotion-like movement</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>0.74±0.35</td>
<td>0.77±0.36</td>
<td>Electrical stimulation versus passive locomotion-like movement: <italic>P</italic>=0.16 (-0.05–0.06)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0269215511426803">
<p>Values: mean ± SD m/s. 95% confidence intervals showed the estimated (average) difference in treatment effects for walking velocity. *Indicates significant differences were revealed; <italic>P</italic>-value was performed to specify the effect of group difference.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>No statistically significant interactions among the groups (electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement, electrical stimulation and passive locomotion-like movement) and the test session (before treatment) were observed for gait velocity (<italic>F</italic> [2, 21] =1.14, <italic>P</italic>=0.34). ANCOVA showed statistically significant main effect among the groups (electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement, electrical stimulation and passive locomotion-like movement) (<italic>F</italic> [2, 23] =4.63, <italic>P</italic>=0.02). The gait velocity of the electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement group was significantly different from those of the other two groups (electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement versus electrical stimulation: <italic>P</italic>=0.049, electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement versus passive locomotion-like movement: <italic>P</italic>=0.025).</p>
<p>There was no statistically significant difference in the modified Ashworth scale of the affected ankle dorsiflexors among the three groups (χ<sup>2</sup>=83.99, <italic>df</italic>=2, <italic>p</italic>=0.23). Six of the nine subjects (66.6%) in the electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement group showed improvement in the modified Ashworth scale score, while only three of the nine subjects (33.3%) in the electrical stimulation group and two of the nine subjects (22.2%) in the passive locomotion-like movement group improved (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0269215511426803">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0269215511426803" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>The numbers of patients in modified Ashworth scale pre- and posttreatment</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0269215511426803" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511426803-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="3">Group</th>
<th align="left" colspan="6">Modified Ashworth scale</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="3">Improved numbers (%)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="3">Unchanged numbers (%)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="3">Chi-squared test</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Grade 1</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Grade 2</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Grade 3</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Pre</th>
<th align="left">Post</th>
<th align="left">Pre</th>
<th align="left">Post</th>
<th align="left">Pre</th>
<th align="left">Post</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6/9 (66)</td>
<td>3/9 (33)</td>
<td>χ<sup>2</sup>=83.99, <italic>P</italic>=0.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Electrical stimulation</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3/9 (33)</td>
<td>6/9 (66)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Passive locomotion-like movement</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2/9 (22)</td>
<td>7/9 (77)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0269215511426803">
<p>Modified Ashworth scale grade 1: slight increase in muscle tone, manifested by a catch and release or by minimal resistance at the end of the range of motion when the affected part is moved in flexion or extension; grade 2: slight increase in muscle tone, manifested by a catch, followed by minimal resistance throughout the remainder (less than half) of the range of motion; grade 3: more marked increase in muscle tone through most of the range of motion, but affected part easily moved.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0269215511426803" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results demonstrated that the immediate effects of electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement on gait velocity were significantly greater than those of either electrical stimulation or passive locomotion-like movement alone in patients with hemiparetic stroke. These results support the hypothesis that electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement might have a greater effect on gait ability than the individual treatment components (electrical stimulation and passive locomotion-like movement). Our study is the first to report the effectiveness of electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement over electrical stimulation or passive locomotion-like movement alone using a randomized controlled study design.</p>
<p>Regarding the quality of the randomized controlled design in the present study, several drawbacks exist. First, the sample size was relatively small. Thereby, we applied the baseline measurement as covariate to the model to take into consideration the differences in each treatment effects. We did not test the difference in the baseline characteristics of the three groups, because doing so is not meaningful in a small study. Furthermore, the inclusion and exclusion criteria were clearly stated, no dropouts occurred, and all the participants completed the study protocol.</p>
<p>Secondly, the participants were not masked as to their treatment group because of technical difficulties. Instead, we tried to minimize the possible bias by having the observer evaluate treatment outcomes without knowledge of the treatment groups. Possible biases arising from therapies other than the target interventions were minimized by assessing the treatment effects immediately after each intervention.</p>
<p>The improvements observed after electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement can be attributed to the following factors. First, although there was no statistically significant difference in the modified Ashworth scale of the affected ankle dorsiflexors among the three groups in our results, electrical stimulation alone might have beneficial effects for decreasing the spasticity of the plantar flexors by stimulating the tibialis anterior, which might have led to the improvement in the gait velocity. Other studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269215511426803">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269215511426803">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269215511426803">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269215511426803">25</xref></sup> have shown that electrical stimulation of the tibialis anterior can reduce spasticity and improve motor performance. Lamontagne <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269215511426803">6</xref></sup> also indicated the relationship between the spasticity of the plantar flexors and ambulatory function. This plantar flexor spasticity was positively related to temporal asymmetry during gait and negatively related to gait velocity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269215511426803">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511426803">5</xref></sup> In the present study, electrical stimulation to the soleus was used to facilitate monosynaptic reflex pathway. Kitago <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269215511426803">20</xref></sup> stated that the soleus H-reflex was increased by transcutaneous electrical stimulation to the tibial nerve. Other research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269215511426803">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269215511426803">27</xref></sup> has mentioned that the stimulation of the spastic muscle itself is a method of treatment based on recurrent inhibition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269215511426803">28</xref></sup> This effect is thought to be caused by Renshaw cells, which provide a negative feedback loop to the motoneurons, and this mechanism is decreased in spastic patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269215511426803">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0269215511426803"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0269215511426803"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269215511426803">32</xref></sup> Agonist muscle stimulation can be used to enhance recurrent inhibition as an inhibitory pathway for agonist muscles.</p>
<p>Second, the passive locomotion-like movement alone is also known to reduce spasticity in patients with stroke.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269215511426803">12</xref></sup> Bressel <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0269215511426803">33</xref></sup> indicated that passive movements could reduce spasticity in stroke patients through a combination of reflexive and mechanical factors. In addition, the habituation of reflex activity to repeated stretching may result from a decrease in synaptic transmission caused by the inactivation of presynaptic calcium channels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0269215511426803">34</xref></sup></p>
<p>Regarding electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement, the mechanism responsible for the observed improvements in gait velocity and modified Ashworth scale is not obvious. However, our previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269215511426803">10</xref></sup> reported an improvement in the excitability of the monosynaptic reflex pathway, as demonstrated by a decrease in the abnormal excitability changes of the soleus H-reflex during passive hip flexion-extension movements. This effect accompanied the improvement of ambulation in a patient with chronic hemiparetic stroke who attended four therapy phases over a four-week period in an ABAB single-subject design. These results indicate that the improvement brought about by electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement might result from the synergistic effects of phase-related electrical stimulation combined with passive hip flexion-extension movements.</p>
<p>Lower extremity spasticity is a major problem in rehabilitation because it leads to impaired motor function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269215511426803">35</xref></sup> and disturbs gait performance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269215511426803">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511426803">5</xref></sup> Several studies reported on the positive effects on the gait velocity and/or the modified Ashworth scale after locomotor training approaches such as treadmill walking with partial body weight support,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269215511426803">1</xref></sup> and robot-assisted locomotor training,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269215511426803">2</xref></sup> possibly combined with functional electrical stimulation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269215511426803">3</xref></sup> Electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement might also have the potential to act as an effective treatment for improving spasticity and gait function beyond that attainable with either intervention alone.</p>
<p>Our study has several limitations. First, we do not know how long the improvement in ambulation lasts after electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement. With regard to electrical stimulation, the reduction in spasticity reportedly lasts for 30 minutes to several hours or even a day after stimulation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269215511426803">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0269215511426803">37</xref></sup> Furthermore, Motl <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269215511426803">38</xref></sup> indicated that passive cycling likewise decreased the soleus H-reflex and induced a 30-minute sustained decrease after cycling. These findings suggest that electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement might have carry-over and long-term effects, but further confirmation is needed.</p>
<p>Secondly, we did not analyze the relationship between patient characteristics, such as the degree of spasticity, voluntary control, sensory impairment and so on, with the therapeutic response to electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement. Also, we do not know the optimum conditions for intervention, i.e. the intensity, pulse duration and frequency of the electrical stimulation and the velocity and range of the movement task.</p>
<p>Lastly, the physiological mechanisms responsible for the improvement after electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement must be elucidated using electrophysiological parameters, such as the H-reflex, because in the present study, we used the modified Ashworth scale which is a qualitative evaluation with unproven reliability. These topics should be examined in future studies with larger samples to obtain more reliable and conclusive evidence of electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement treatment for the clinical management of gait disturbances in patients with hemiparetic stroke. Despite these limitations, our study demonstrated that electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement could be superior to electrical stimulation or passive locomotion-like movement alone for improving gait velocity in these patients.</p>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-0269215511426803">
<title>Clinical messages</title>
<list id="list3-0269215511426803" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Electrical stimulation combined simultaneously with passive locomotion-like movement could have an immediate effect on gait velocity in stroke patients.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>It is necessary to identify the long-term effects of combined electrical stimulation with passive locomotion-like movement on gait disturbances in stroke patients in future study.</p></list-item>
</list>
</boxed-text>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research was partly supported by the Graduate School Doctorate Student Aid Program (2009) of Keio University and the Research Fellowships and Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellows, Japan (10J01697).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0269215511426803">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Von Frankenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Treig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Konrad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treadmill training with partial body weight support and an electromechanical gait trainer for restoration of gait in subacute stroke patients: a randomized crossover study</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>2895</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0269215511426803">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kofler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quirbach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matzak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fröhlich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saltuari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective, blinded, randomized crossover study of gait rehabilitation in stroke patients using the Lokomat gait orthosis</article-title>. <source>Neurorehabil Neural Repair</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0269215511426803">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peurala</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tarkka</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pitkänen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sivenius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effectiveness of body weight-supported gait training and floor walking in patients with chronic stroke</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1557</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0269215511426803">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relation between ankle impairments and gait velocity and symmetry in people with stroke</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0269215511426803">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of impairments influencing gait velocity and asymmetry of hemiplegic patients after mild to moderate stroke</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>1185</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0269215511426803">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lamontagne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malouin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Locomotor-specific measure of spasticity of plantarflexor muscles after stroke</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>1696</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0269215511426803">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakheit</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Curnow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kodapala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relation between Ashworth scale scores and the excitability of the alpha motor neurones in patients with post-stroke muscle spasticity</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0269215511426803">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masakado</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Disorder of phase-related modulation of soleus H-reflex during hip movement in stroke patients</article-title>. <source>Electromyogr Clin Neurophysiol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0269215511426803">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masakado</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of the soleus H-reflex during static and dynamic imposed hip angle changes</article-title>. <source>Int J Neurosci</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0269215511426803">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masakado</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of transcutaneous electrical stimulation combined with locomotion-like movement in the treatment of post-stroke gait disorder: a single-case study. Short report</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0269215511426803">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakhtiary</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fatemy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does electrical stimulation reduce spasticity after stroke? A randomized controlled study</article-title>. <source>Clin Rehabil</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0269215511426803">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nuyens</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Weerdt</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spaepen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Kiekens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feys</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reduction of spastic hypertonia during repeated passive knee movements in stroke patients</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>930</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0269215511426803">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magliozzi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piehl-Baker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical gait assessment in the neurologically impaired. Reliability and meaningfulness</article-title>. <source>Phys Ther</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0269215511426803">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leathley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reliability of the Tone Assessment Scale and the modified Ashworth scale as clinical tools for assessing poststroke spasticity</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0269215511426803">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>‘Mini-mental state’. A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinician</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res</source> <year>1975</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0269215511426803">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clair</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lagerquist</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Okuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Neuromuscular electrical stimulation: implications of the electrically evoked sensory volley</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>2409</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0269215511426803">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hui-Chan</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relief of hemiparetic spasticity by TENS is associated with improvement in reflex and voluntary motor functions</article-title>. <source>Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0269215511426803">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Neural mechanisms underlying the effect of transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation in humans</article-title>. <source>Electromyogr Clin Neurophysiol</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0269215511426803">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Joodaki</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olyaei</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagheri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effects of electrical nerve stimulation of the lower extremity on H-reflex and F-wave parameters</article-title>. <source>Electromyogr Clin Neurophysiol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0269215511426803">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kitago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazzocchio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liuzzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of H-reflex excitability by tetanic stimulation</article-title>. <source>Clin Neurophysiol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>858</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0269215511426803">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maggs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langton Hewer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Walking after stroke. Measurement and recovery over the first 3 months</article-title>. <source>Scand J Rehabil Med</source> <year>1987</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0269215511426803">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liston</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of measures obtained from stroke patients using the Balance Master</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0269215511426803">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magliozzi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piehl-Baker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical gait assessment in the neurologically impaired. Reliability and meaningfulness</article-title>. <source>Phys Ther</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0269215511426803">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hui-Chan</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Functional electrical stimulation improves motor recovery of the lower extremity and walking ability of subjects with first acute stroke: a randomized placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0269215511426803">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woodbury</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The therapeutic effect of functional and transcutaneous electric stimulation on improving gait speed in stroke patients: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0269215511426803">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Franek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turczynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Opara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of spinal spasticity by electrical stimulation</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Eng</source> <year>1988</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0269215511426803">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van der Salm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veltink</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ijzerman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groothuis-Oudshoorn</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nene</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hermens</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of electric stimulation methods for reduction of triceps surae spasticity in spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0269215511426803">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vodovnik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hufford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of electrical stimulation on spinal spasticity</article-title>. <source>Scand J Rehabil Med</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0269215511426803">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shefner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent inhibition is decreased in patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2148</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0269215511426803">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazzocchio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of spinal recurrent inhibition in spasticity. Further insight into the regulation of Renshaw cell activity</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>1003</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0269215511426803">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazzocchio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent inhibition in human spinal spasticity</article-title>. <source>Ital J Neurol Sci</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0269215511426803">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierrot-Deseilligny</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent inhibition in humans</article-title>. <source>Prog Neurobiol</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0269215511426803">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bressel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNair</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of prolonged static and cyclic stretching on ankle joint stiffness, torque relaxation, and gait in people with stroke</article-title>. <source>Phys Ther</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0269215511426803">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Management of spastic hypertonia after stroke</article-title>. <source>J Neuro Rehabil</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0269215511426803">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Altered contractile properties of the gastrocnemius muscle poststroke</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1802</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0269215511426803">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsolais</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rymer</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stefanovska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolpaw</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Therapeutic neural effects of electrical stimulation</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Rehabil Eng</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0269215511426803">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Given</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rymer</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-lasting reductions of spasticity induced by skin electrical stimulation</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Rehabil Eng</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0269215511426803">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Motl</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dishman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute bouts of active and passive leg cycling attenuate the amplitude of the soleus H-reflex in humans</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>347</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>