<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOU</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjou</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1464-8849</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3001</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1464884911421703</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1464884911421703</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Citizen video journalists and authority in narrative: Reviving the role of the witness</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>Mary Angela</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1464884911421703">Kutztown University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1464884911421703">Mary Angela Bock, Assistant Professor, Kutztown University, Department of Speech and Theatre, Rickenbach Learning Center 232-A, Kutztown PA 19530, USA Email: <email>bock@kutztown.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>639</fpage>
<lpage>653</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>New media technologies allow for unprecedented participation in the public sphere, with financial investments on a par with other mainstream hobbies. Citizen video journalists (VJs) are acquiring the technical, and in some cases, narrative skills needed to participate in online discourse. Yet citizen VJs lack the institutional authority enjoyed by professional journalists. This project compares the narrative strategies employed by professional and non-professional VJs to assert their authority. Practitioners were observed in a variety of professional and activist contexts in the UK and the USA over the course of two years and their stories were subjected to textual analysis. The project identifies emerging strategies used by citizen VJs to establish authority.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>authority</kwd>
<kwd>citizen-journalism</kwd>
<kwd>convergence</kwd>
<kwd>multi-media journalism</kwd>
<kwd>narrative</kwd>
<kwd>new media</kwd>
<kwd>video</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1464884911421703" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The capability for the larger population to participate in both video production and dissemination seems taken for granted today but is relatively new, having developed largely in the 21st century. The technologies of video production are both more affordable and user-friendly in terms of size and required skill sets. A camera and edit system that once cost the equivalent of a middle-class home is now on a par with what’s required for other hobbies. Just as significantly, the products of home video production are easily disseminated worldwide thanks to the growth of broadband internet use in industrialized countries. Amateurs, multi-media bloggers and would-be citizen journalists are able to participate in the visual public sphere in unprecedented numbers.</p>
<p>Access to the public sphere, however, is not equivalent to authoritative power within it. Citizen video journalists (VJs) do not have the power of news organizations behind them, nor can they claim the authority of membership in a socially recognized interpretive community. Instead, based on multiple interviews, observations from fieldwork and textual analysis, this project argues that citizen VJs make unique strategic narrative choices to establish authority, resulting in a more variable narrative form than that found in the professional realm.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1464884911421703">
<title>Defining video and citizen journalism</title>
<p>Technological advances and financial constraints have made it increasingly possible, if not advantageous, for one person to produce video stories alone. For professional news organizations this has precipitated changes in work practices, as traditional television news has typically employed two specialists (or more) in the field: one to use the camera, the other to appear on camera, write, and vocally narrate a story. To adapt to the online environment, newspapers are adding VJs to their roster and incorporating video on to their websites. Many terms and acronyms have been coined for those who shoot, write and edit video: multimedia journalists, (MMJs), solo-journalists (SOLOJOS) and one-man bands (OMBs.) For the sake of simplicity, this project applies the term ‘video journalist’, or VJ. Four technological advancements have fostered singular news production: (1) smaller, lighter cameras, (2) flip screen viewfinders (which allow a user to operate a camera without holding it to his or her face), (3) user-friendly editing software, and (4) wireless broadband technologies. Together with the decreased cost of entry, these advancements allow for unprecedented participation in visual news discourse.</p>
<p>Citizen journalism, sometimes called ‘Indy-journalism’, takes advantage of the democratizing nature of video journalism. In 2009, <italic>YouTube</italic> added journalism tutorials to its news contribution section and Apple™ sold an application for the iPhone that made it easy for amateur VJs to post their news to the web. The <italic>IMC</italic> (Independent Media Centers, also known as <italic>Indymedia</italic>) is another pioneer in the genre, with its roots in the ‘Battle of Seattle’ riots in 1999. The organization teaches activists to produce video stories and post them to the web; an effort intended to create multi-media counter-narratives to traditional news programming.</p>
<p>At their core, these efforts propose that anyone can have the opportunity to make multi-media contributions to the public sphere and participate more fully in democratic debate online. Unlike typical news websites, community video websites do not use balanced language or make claims to journalistic objectivity. Their purpose is to give voice to new and discernible points of view (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1464884911421703">Coffman, 2009</xref>). Community video can also be used as a way of building group cohesion among like-minded VJs. They might work on their individual presentations independently, but if they are working as part of an activist collective, there are often opportunities for discussion and debate during the production process. This may help individuals acquire the sorts of language skills necessary to articulate their views (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1464884911421703">Ananny and Stohecker, 2002</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1464884911421703">
<title>Theoretical framework: Authority and narrative</title>
<p>To claim authority is to claim legitimate power. In the public sphere, authority is claimed as a discursive power to make declarations: to name things, frame things, or present them as ‘true’. Journalism is a specialized discursive practice that presumes to tell the truth – that is – to act authoritatively. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1464884911421703">Max Weber (1947)</xref> identified three sources of authority: rational, (rooted in law or social sanction), traditional (rooted in established social beliefs), and charismatic (derived from exemplary behavior or heroic acts on the part of an individual). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1464884911421703">Carlson (2006)</xref> noted that conventional journalism can claim all three legitimating dimensions. Citizen VJs, however, cannot claim rational authority because they operate outside of, and contest with, conventional journalistic institutions. Because they challenge traditional journalistic boundaries, they are also unable to draw upon Weber’s notion of ‘traditional’ authority. All that remains for the citizen is the charismatic authority that rests in the individual.</p>
<p>Whether rational, traditional or charismatic, how, in practice, is such authority claimed? What discursive strategies are available to professional and citizen journalists? Two primary bodies of discourse can be identified: first, the discourse surrounding practice, and second, the products of that work. For example, professional journalists continually defend their ‘territory’ as cultural arbiters of truth through discourse about their own work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1464884911421703">Bennett et al., 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1464884911421703">Carlson, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1464884911421703">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1464884911421703">Zelizer, 1990a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1464884911421703">1993</xref>). Studies of journalists at work find that members of the profession share an ideology based in the norms of objectivity and public service, and they delineate their territory through discourse regarding those norms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1464884911421703">Carlson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1464884911421703">Deuze, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1464884911421703">Zelizer, 1990b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1464884911421703">1993</xref>). Citizen VJs similarly delineate their boundaries through discourse, but it is a discourse of contestation, of working as outsiders to ‘big’ or ‘mainstream’ media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1464884911421703">Garcelon, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1464884911421703">Platon and Deuze, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1464884911421703">Rosen, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>The second discursive arena for establishing authority lies within the stories themselves, which are the focus of this article. Here the everyday decisions for crafting a story are elements in constructing authority: the choice of facts to include or emphasize, the choice of literary voice, the choice of quotations or soundbites, the choice of visuals and sound, and the employment of vocal narration all become part of the way a story represents the authority of its creator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1464884911421703">Allan, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1464884911421703">Chatman, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1464884911421703">Hall, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1464884911421703">Knobloch et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1464884911421703">Montgomery, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1464884911421703">Raymond, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1464884911421703">Van Dijk, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1464884911421703">Zelizer, 1990a</xref>). Televisual stories present pictures and sound in real time, a format that does not always easily incorporate the inverted pyramid. With filmic presentation, narrative is essential to a viewer’s comprehension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1464884911421703">Bird and Dardenne, 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>TV news, which until recently was the primary journalistic genre that used video, has especially been criticized for favoring the most convenient narrative components, by relying upon staged events, experts with publicists, and the testimony of elites over that of less powerful but direct witnesses to events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1464884911421703">Cook, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1464884911421703">Gitlin, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911421703">Glasgow University Media Group, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1464884911421703">Molotch and Lester, 1974</xref>). In a video story, narration can be multi-layered, with a voiced, scripted ‘voice of God’, a more reflexive voice of a subjective observer, the voices of story participants or sources, or any number of combinations thereof.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1464884911421703">
<title>Elements of authority in narrative</title>
<p>While many elements of narrative can be tied to authoritative claims within a story, three dimensions of video news stand out. The first is the choice of literary voice, that is, the use of first or third person within a script, what might also be characterized as a diegetic or mimetic approach to film. A second dimension is the degree to which the author is made ‘known’ to the viewer or reader. The third dimension is deeply rooted in the discourses of journalism, namely the means by which a story incorporates testimony of witnessing. These dimensions are not discrete and may overlap or appear to conflict: a citizen VJ might make himself ‘known’ through script and camera work, or a professional VJ might use a strict third-person presentation with objective declarations, while also appearing on camera in a standup<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1464884911421703">1</xref></sup> that implies direct witnessing. The nature of filmic news narrative, with its blending of soundbites, script, background noise and visuals, demands a nuanced evaluation.</p>
<sec id="section5-1464884911421703">
<title>The choice of voice</title>
<p>Filmic storytelling techniques rely on a combination of showing and telling, or what rhetorical scholars call mimesis and diegesis. Film scholar Bill Nichols has categorized various formats of documentary according to narration, modes of address, and (cinematic) voice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1464884911421703">Nichols, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1464884911421703">2001</xref>). His categories represent a continuum between diegesis and mimesis, with ‘observational’ documentary representing the most mimetic, as it operates without a seen or heard narrator, and ‘expository’ documentary, which places authority in a narrator’s vocal presence, at the other extreme:
<disp-quote>
<p>The voices of others are woven into a textual logic that subsumes and orchestrates them. They retain little responsibility for making the argument, but are used to support it, or provide evidence or substantiation for what the commentary addresses. The voice of authority resides with the text itself rather than with those recruited to it. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1464884911421703">Nichols, 2001</xref>: 37)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Expository documentary is the voice of TV news, a discursive format that diverged from other styles of filmmaking in the early 20th century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1464884911421703">Aitken, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1464884911421703">1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1464884911421703">Barnouw, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1464884911421703">Nichols, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1464884911421703">Vaughn, 1995</xref>). Socially conscious, long-form documentary filmmakers continued to experiment observational styles, but short-form newsreels needed the efficiency of exposition, and these newsreels provided the earliest model for TV news presentation. Early television did air long-form documentaries, but as television news programs evolved into tightly timed ‘shows’ in need of systematic production, the diegetic style of storytelling prevailed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1464884911421703">Tuchman, 1978</xref>). In his analysis of television news discourse, Peter Dahlgren describes the way authority is located in this expository, diegetic style of television scripting that is</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>… matter of factual and self-assured, with little or no trace of self-doubt, emotionality or uncertainty about the material it presents. It conveys seriousness, and where appropriate, urgency and even light touches of irony. News talk is confident talk, secure in its professionalism. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1464884911421703">Dahlgren, 1987</xref>: 42)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>The diegetic form is not only efficient for television producers; it is efficient for the audience. There is no self doubt on the part of the speaking narrator; a member of the journalistic community can authoritatively declare: ‘That’s the way it is.’</p>
<p>In contrast, Nichols’s mimetic, ‘observationalist style’ eliminates the objective, all-knowing, third-person narrator by editing together quotations (soundbites) from news subjects in order to construct a coherent narrative. This mimetic style has no voiced-over narrative, no formal interviews with subjects, no direct address to the audience, and it utilizes editing that emphasizes real time and spatial realism. Because it is not declarative, it encourages viewers to work harder to interpret the film. Documentary filmmakers who championed this ‘fly on the wall’ style perceived it as somehow <italic>more truthful</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1464884911421703">1</xref></sup>in that it locates authority in the scenes and subjects recorded, to be interpreted by the viewer without mediation by a vocal narrator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1464884911421703">Rouch, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1464884911421703">Stoller, 1992</xref>). Mainstream TV news makes use of this form occasionally, dubbing such pieces ‘NATPAKs’ for their use of natural sound, but these pieces are not the norm. They are usually features or filler items and might even be seen as a reward for a video photographer to create.</p>
<p>Time constraints, both in the form of real-time presentations and in the form of frequent ‘news factory’ deadlines, demand the efficiency of the diegetic/declarative form a voice track from someone presented as a correspondent or presenter/anchor. Because of these trends and styles, TV news is often criticized as a cheaper, poorer representation of events, and the work of long-form documentarians as more serious, in-depth social activism. From this perspective, to claim a higher step in the non-fiction hierarchy is a matter of embracing photography’s aesthetic and synecdochic power to independently <italic>show</italic>, rather than merely illustrate. In other words, the mark of ‘serious’ photographers and filmmakers is their choice to let images (relatively) ‘speak for themselves’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1464884911421703">
<title>Known and unknown creators</title>
<p><italic>Textual</italic> narrative theory notes that writers can assume various forms of narration, and that these choices change the audience’s perception of the identity of a narrator and author: sometimes they are one in the same, sometimes they are not; sometimes the author is revealed, sometimes not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1464884911421703">Chatman, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1464884911421703">1990</xref>). Similarly, a filmic narrator might be seen or unseen, known or unknown, heard or not heard, and may or may not be the project’s author or producer. The choices made with regard to authorship and narrative may be dictated by institutional demands and serve as indicators of the ways members of those institutions establish authority.</p>
<p>Authorship in conventional TV news is generally shared. A reporter might voice a script written by a producer, and an anchor might voice over images shot by a photographer in the field. A reporter’s standup implies complete authorship of a story, but this often occludes the true processes by which television news is produced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1464884911421703">Hartley, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1464884911421703">Zelizer, 1990c</xref>). Hiding the creator is one way to shore up the story’s authority, as the subjective nature of human choice is subsumed by declarative narration. This strategy has been especially prevalent in journalism’s relay of images: news photographers are generally not made known to the audience. In this way, journalism has been able to claim the ‘truthful’ authority of images by shifting responsibility for an image from a human practitioner to the perfect recording technology of a camera.</p>
<p>Because video journalism is the work of one creator responsible for image and script, it is possible that authorship might be presented in new ways. During the Hurricane Katrina disaster, CNN correspondent Anderson Cooper’s challenge to the claims of federal authorities regarding the disaster was bolstered by Cooper’s use of his own video camera. In combination with decisions regarding narrative voice, images can take on authority rooted in their creators, who might explain the circumstances through which a particular image was made. Citizen video journalists, who are not bound by longstanding institutional practices, have even more options for how and when to become known to their audience, intentionally or not.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1464884911421703">
<title>Discourses of witnessing</title>
<p>Eyewitness testimony is the most ancient source of authority for a truthful storyteller. The import of the eyewitness remains a cornerstone of western courts of law; to bear witness is to carry moral responsibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1464884911421703">Peters, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1464884911421703">Zelizer, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1464884911421703">2004</xref>). The aphorism that to be a journalist is to have a ‘front row seat’ to history is rooted in the notion that reporters and journalists are direct witnesses to world events. Yet journalism’s application of eyewitnessing is not always evenly applied. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1464884911421703">Zelizer (2007)</xref> found the term used sometimes to describe witnessing by a mediated source, by an amateur contributor, or by the audience watching a scene live on television with (seemingly) autonomous cameras. In their classic article, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1464884911421703">Molotch and Lester (1974)</xref> detailed an account in which reporters themselves were direct witnesses to an environmental mess, yet made use of quotations and accounts from political leaders who proclaimed that the problem was solved. Contemporary newsgathering often relies on second-order witnessing, with journalists viewing speeches or events by way of closed circuit television, or government controlled video feeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1464884911421703">Lang, 2004</xref>). Conventional journalists are also often inclined to rely on the witnessing of others, that is, testimony or material provided by sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1464884911421703">Cook, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1464884911421703">Hess, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1464884911421703">Sigal, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1464884911421703">Tuchman, 1978</xref>).</p>
<p>Only actual acts of physical viewing constitute ‘pure’ witnessing as conceived by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1464884911421703">Durham Peters (2001)</xref>. Witnessing in its purest form is imbued with a moral imperative to give testimony, whereas mediated witnessing does not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1464884911421703">Ellis, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1464884911421703">Sontag, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1464884911421703">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1464884911421703">Taylor, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1464884911421703">Zelizer, 1998</xref>). Peters’s typology situates forms of witnessing in time and space, with its purest form requiring presence in both. Witnessing might also take place in space but separated by time, for instance at a historic site; in time separated by space, as with live television coverage; or separated by both time and space as is typical for most television coverage.</p>
<p>Video journalism potentially constitutes a form of pure witnessing, in that recording an image requires bodily presence. For the accidental video journalist, those direct witnesses to major news events (such as the Virginia Tech shootings or the 7 July bombings in London), pure witnessing is a source of nearly total truthful authority. Yet the way a VJ chooses to frame his or her witnessing of events will vary, and as previous scholarship has noted, it may not always be ‘pure’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1464884911421703">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Contemporary video technology, when coupled with citizen journalism, opens the door to new strategies for establishing authority within narrative. The three dimensions presented here, namely voice, authorship and witnessing, might be employed in part or completely, separately or in concert with one another. They lead to the research question that guides the rest of this article, specifically: <italic>How do citizen video journalists establish their authority in narrative?</italic></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1464884911421703">
<title>Method</title>
<p>This project combines ethnographic and textual methods to analyze materials collected as part of a two-year project that examined the daily work of video journalists in a variety of contexts, including the professional realm and that of citizen journalists. The study includes more than 15 observational sites and 93 interviews with VJs, VJ trainers or still photographers learning to use video, working in a variety of contexts. Their experience ranged from neophyte to more than two decades. Data were collected in six different cities in the USA and three in the UK. VJs at work and in training were observed in newsrooms and in the field. Of particular interest for this article is a multi-session workshop in Philadelphia, <italic>Our City Our Voices</italic>, (<italic>OCOV</italic>) in 2008. <italic>OCOV</italic> was established with a grant from the news-oriented <italic>Knight Foundation</italic>. The organization provided free instruction on how to shoot, write and edit video stories to a class made up of union organizers, taxi drivers and immigration activists. Their projects were eventually posted to an <italic>Indymedia</italic> website.</p>
<p>The ethnographic material collected for the project is helpful for examining the process of video journalism. To determine whether its emerging processes have an impact on narrative form, it was also necessary to examine the stories produced by those who participated in the research. In 44 cases, it was possible for the researcher to observe subjects working on a specific story, or to view a specific story and discuss it in detail with the VJ. In a few cases, stories were available online and could be recorded and transcribed, making it possible to illustrate the analytic method utilized with a subset of archetypical examples. The analytical method was adapted from propaganda scholar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1464884911421703">Siegfried Kracauer (1947)</xref> and allows for the examination of the verbal text, the images, and – significantly – their interrelationships in terms of diegetic and mimetic dimensions. Mapping the stories this way made it possible to analyze specific narrative strategies as outlined earlier: What is the overall ‘voice’ of the story? Is the author somehow made ‘known’ to the audience? How is the VJ’s role as witness presented in the story?</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1464884911421703" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Findings and discussion</title>
<p>The notion that ‘everyone has a story to tell’ has become a catchall for the independent media movement, and, as with all aphorisms, it has an element of truth. What it ignores, however, is that effective storytelling is a skill: constructing narratives from events seems quite natural in everyday speech, but this is not the case with mediated discourse. Professional VJs work within organizations with set expectations about narrative form. Moreover, professional journalists are <italic>presumed</italic> to have the authority to tell news stories; in contrast, citizen VJs must use other strategies for establishing authority. Three trends emerged in the strategies citizen VJs employ in their storytelling when compared with professional VJs, namely:</p>
<list id="list1-1464884911421703" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The literary voice becomes more fluid.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The creator is more likely to be known through script and image.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Testimony of witnessing takes a more subjective tone.</p></list-item>
</list>
<sec id="section11-1464884911421703">
<title>A more fluid conception of ‘voice’</title>
<p>Those VJs observed working for conventional television organizations scripted their stories according to the diegetic style customary for American and British broadcast news. Even though they often performed and appeared as reporters in their stories, their language was declarative, not reflexive. VJs from television operations arranged their shooting schedules in order to include expert interviews wherever possible.</p>
<p>All the VJs in the study seemed to extend at least some attention to <italic>non-elite</italic> sources, a tendency that seems to reflect a divergence not between professional and non-professional, but between word-based and image-based practice. The legacy of photojournalism and its emphasis on the visually unusual seems to lend itself to the presentation of such non-elites. Stories produced by this study’s informants include interviews with Chinese parents who lost children in the Sichuan earthquake, voters lining up to see the Hillary Clinton rally, unemployed physical therapy students and so on. These VJs, often photojournalists who have transitioned from shooting stills to video, prefer to establish authority with the camera. One of the informants, DT, explains, ‘I like to stay in the background whenever I can, it’s just my nature.’ Another participant, EJ, who trains newspaper journalists in multimedia skills, endorses this approach: ‘We teach them to use the subject’s narration, the interview. Nine times out of ten the narrative spoken will be the subject speaking.’</p>
<p>Yet although the final stories produced by professional VJs included many interviews with non-elite sources, edited mimetically, members of this group chose to contextualize the material <italic>diegetically</italic>. Even those VJs who profess to be strong advocates of the mimetic/cinema verité style used their own voice to start their stories with a diegetic sentence or two, establishing their own position as author, and telling the audience what it is about to view. The linkage (to use Kracauer’s term) between the interviews with everyday individuals and these preliminary contextualizations (whether spoken or captioned) is primarily declarative. In contrast, citizen VJs relied more heavily on non-elites and they were more likely to speak for themselves, using a collage of mimetic, diegetic and performative strategies as needed. Few elites appeared in the citizen stories examined here.</p>
<p>In keeping with citizen journalism’s impulse to contest traditional journalistic norms, the non-professional stories did not use the language of conventional TV news. ‘There ought to be a law’, states the narrator of the gun control story without any pretense of objectivity. VJs from <italic>OCOV</italic> took turns performing in the Gun Control story. One provided an expository voice track and was joined midway by other members of the team in vocally eliciting questions from an interviewee before the entire group appeared on camera chanting, ‘Keep the guns off the street.’ Another <italic>OCOV</italic> video, called ‘Community Outreach’ starts with a mock conversation between two neighbors accompanied by a musical track and video of an actual police investigation. This mix of a performative and observational style does not assume the traditional authoritative voice of professional journalism. Similarly, an <italic>OVOC</italic> story on labor unions uses long, mimetic passages from a meeting with a union organizer, edited in conjunction with play-acted scenes under narration that declares unions to be a workers’ only protection from unfair bosses.</p>
<p>A story on the Jena Six Rally from an independent web-based citizen VJ starts off entirely as exposition with no diegetic script. About halfway through the four-minute piece, the citizen VJ appears on camera with a performative (though not reflexive) appearance using a colloquialism to describe the size of the media contingent, calling it ‘deep’. The story resumes with the mimetic, observational style to present the sights and sounds of the rally. Music from an African-style drumming group, playing at the scene, is layered under most of the story. There are full-screen graphics to open and close the story and superimposed labels identify each of the people interviewed. The story ends with a comment from the father of the jailed boy, whose words end with the phrase, ‘in Jena’, closing the narrative with a mirror to its beginning.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1464884911421703">
<title>Known and unknown creators</title>
<p>As noted earlier, in conventional journalism, the authority of photographic images is rooted in part in the anonymity of their creators. Images are presented as truthful representations of scenes because of the supposition of a camera’s technical perfection, while photographers remain behind the scenes, letting the images speak for them. In the professional realm, these images are generally well composed, lit, and crafted, which often causes an audience to forget about camera technique.</p>
<p>While the one-person VJ system has come under fire by long-time professional photographers for producing less-than-perfect video, the flaws might seem likely to be too subtle for the average viewer to discern. Even so, one of the objections raised by professional print journalists who were learning to use a video camera was the concern that they would not be able to produce professional-looking video.</p>
<p>Interestingly, camera technique seemed to be taken for granted by the <italic>OCOV</italic> participants. During the workshops participants were somewhat subdued when instructors discussed scripts, the target audience, and metaphor. When the presentation turned to camera shots and film vocabulary however, the students picked up their pens and started taking notes. The tangibility of filmmaking seemed far more accessible and interesting. When they were able to pick up a camera, they did so with enthusiasm and without much concern about lighting and composition.</p>
<p>The resulting video, as well as that from other citizen VJs who participated in the study, is far more variable in quality than that produced by professionals, with the shakiness and unplanned lighting that makes a viewer aware of the camera work by a human being. One <italic>OCOV</italic> story uses video from a dark room; another uses street scenes that are out of focus. The <italic>OCOV</italic> gun control story has a very limited number of scenes. There are a few basic views of Philadelphia’s city hall, a close-up of a sign from a gun store, and shots of taxi-cabs in traffic. The illustration used to discuss a specific shooting was recorded and borrowed from a TV newscast.</p>
<p>What is most unusual about the gun control story is the way its creators appear and disappear without explanation <italic>and yet</italic> without destroying the viewer’s understanding. The beginning features a female voice and she is heard eliciting a question during an interview. Another VJ appears without introduction, speaking from the driver’s seat of his taxi-cab about his experiences on the streets of Philadelphia and his own fears about gun violence. It is not possible to know from this appearance that he is also one of the story’s creators, nor that he questioned a teenage boy in another scene. (The latter was only discernible by observing the group at work.) The taxi driver reappears in the closing chanting scene with three other co-creators.</p>
<p>Other citizen VJ stories included in this study make the creator known through camera use and vocal narration. BD’s story from Jena opens with unlit, somewhat shaky video of his partner, who is driving, saying, ‘It’s Thursday, the day of the rally. This is it, we’re headed to Jena.’ The viewer then sees and hears what BD and his partner hear in the car, a radio report about the upcoming rally. The scene moves to a parking area where a police officer waves them through, and again, the driver comments about being allowed to pass. The scenes at the start of the story do not advance anything about the rally itself; instead they serve to establish that BD and his partner were there together, with a camera, to cover it.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1464884911421703">
<title>Subjective witnessing</title>
<p>Traditional journalistic narrative blends testimonies of witnessing with the language of objectivity. A reporter is expected to observe, not participate; to report, not feel. The narratives of professional VJs rarely invoked the language of witnessing or testimony, shifting that responsibility to other contextualizing elements: an introduction from a studio anchor, for instance, or text posted to a news website that connected the VJ to the scene. One exception to this was the work of a west coast television VJ whose job on the technology beat required him to write occasional reviews. His managers directed him to use first person and to inject his personal observations into his reports. Reviews, however, like opinion columns, usually do invoke a more subjective account of witnessing.</p>
<p>The professional VJs observed for this project did not focus their stories on personal experience but on events and controversies in the public sphere. They also spent very little time considering what constitutes a story, instead relying on traditional newsroom norms. Newspaper employees at a week-long, corporate video-workshop spent little time discussing what sorts of topics lend themselves to video in contrast to other storytelling formats. Television VJs similarly took for granted what constitutes a story, and instead focused their efforts on gaining access to film the elements they need to create a story. NC, a mid-market TV VJ, planned her story according to its visual elements, asking as part of her daily process, ‘What video can I use?’</p>
<p>In stark contrast, the citizen VJs observed in this study embraced the narrative of subjective testimony. Workshop leader MK and her colleagues spent the bulk of their time helping students with conceptualization, eliciting ideas from the group about what stories they would like to tell. Indeed, many of the participants of <italic>OCOV</italic> were motivated by a desire to tell their own stories, stories they perceived as passed over by the mainstream media. Many of their suggestions were rooted in personal experience, such as the woman from Asia who struggled to establish herself as a registered nurse in the USA because her home country’s credentials were deemed worthless here. Other group members wanted to talk more broadly about peace and harmony. One of the reasons TC joined the <italic>OCOV</italic> class was that she perceived mainstream news organization’s coverage of issues dear to her, such as union activities and the situation in her own neighborhood, as incomplete:
<disp-quote>
<p>Video lets you show what you feel is more important. ‘Cause you watch some things, you read things and it don’t have all the necessary information sometimes. Sometimes it’s just a little bit of this and not enough of that.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>TC wanted to present a video about her neighborhood that focused on its positive aspects: barbecues, the safety of children playing outside, and community cohesion. She was weary of TV news portrayals of crime. Other <italic>OCOV</italic> participants wanted to create a video about the importance of union membership, something not event- but experience-driven. Citizen journalist BD chose to create a video of his visit to the political rally in Jena, Louisiana, focusing on his personal experience there – in contrast to the way a typical TV reporter might present it:
<disp-quote>
<p>If I was reporting on air, I’d look like the same dime-a-dozen reporter in any market in America, you know, it’s like blah blah blah: Police say ‘what it is’, track, sound bite, track sound bite end of package, stand-up, whatever. Having the freedom to do my own media … it sits outside the box; [I] tell the story how I want to tell it. So in that, I’m trying to stay fresh and do something different each time. That’s where my focus is: Issues that are my experiences, my life stories, it’s reality-slash-news-slash journalism … A hybrid of all those genres out there.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>This subjective witnessing is part of the citizen VJ impulse. Workshop leader MK says video has long functioned as an evidentiary tool for activists, but it is fast-becoming a part of community organization strategy in the USA:
<disp-quote>
<p>it does get used a lot and increasingly more and more. I think people are using kind of social documentary or different types of video work for… policy, advocacy, for educators, for all sorts of ways that I think that previously it was more constricted to… activists talking to activists. And now it’s sort of more about how people are using video to talk more broadly to different audiences.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Unlike the previous two characteristics of citizen VJ narrative, (the looser conception of ‘voice’ and the opportunistic revelations of a story’s creator), the dimension of subjective witnessing was observed to be more deliberate. Citizen VJs, it seems, not only desire to create narratives that contrast with the mainstream, they desire to reveal how their personal experience contrasts with what they see in the mainstream.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1464884911421703">
<title>Comparing treatment of a single event</title>
<p>So far this analysis has relied on disparate stories produced by professional and citizen VJs, each one a unique creation. To remedy this comparison of apples and oranges, and to allow for a comparison based on differences between VJs, the study includes material from a major news event: a campaign stop by then presidential candidate Hillary Clinton.</p>
<p>Here, the professional TV stories used steady video with clear, crisp, understandable sound, presented with declarative scripting. A story created by a professional newspaper VJ utilized steady images and interviews edited in mimetic fashion, with minimal scripted narration. In contrast, a video story posted to <italic>YouTube</italic> the day of the rally provides perhaps the best illustration of the difference between professional and citizen VJ notions of authority. Only the caption on <italic>YouTube</italic> indicated that it was from the Hillary Clinton rally. The video itself is shaky, strangely focused, and depicts only the gym floor. Clinton can be heard making a joke in the background, and it is possible to hear laughter from the person holding the camera and others nearby. The young woman who posted the video explains her motivation:
<disp-quote>
<p>I think it works because it’s the truth, you can’t manufacture a moment like that. It probably would have been better if we could have seen her face or the faces of people reacting to what she said, but you hear the mike cutting out, you hear the joke, you have all the elements that make the joke funny.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Her concern was not in presenting the larger event but in her – and her friends’ – enjoyment of the moment. What matters is that she was there to witness an event, and the audience is invited along. The authority of the image rests in her having been in a particular place at a critical time, not the technical quality of the image.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1464884911421703" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This article used observations of professional and citizen VJs working in a variety of settings to explore the research question: <italic>How do citizen video journalists establish their authority in narrative?</italic> The study was informed by observations of VJs in the field and analyses of the stories they produced. Lacking what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1464884911421703">Weber (1947)</xref> identified as the rational and traditional authority that comes with working for an institution, citizen VJs relied more on charismatic authority rooted in their individual experience, and this was reflected their narrative strategies. Three characteristics of citizen VJ narrative were identified: a more fluid conception of narrative voice, opportunistic revelations of a story’s creator, and greater reliance on the language of subjective witnessing. Both professional and citizen VJs made significant use of non-elite sources, but their story presentation and scripting varied widely. Citizen VJs changed authorial voice in the middle of stories and they mixed performance and observation without explanation. Such presentations have come under fire by one <italic>Columbia Journalism Review</italic> critic for turning ‘even the most compelling footage into a mish-mash’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1464884911421703">Massing, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Is it possible though, that even ‘mish-mash’ stories might have a place in public discourse given their connection to the life experience of their creators? Supporters of citizen journalism and <italic>Indymedia</italic> argue that the rawness of pure witnessing and crude camera work bolster the authority of amateur stories. At what point, however, does storytelling skill (or the lack thereof) impede appreciation for the product? As more people participate in video discourse, the audience may demand more sophisticated scripting.</p>
<p>A more significant impediment to full participation in the mediated public sphere for citizen VJs is the matter of time and money. The challenge of producing quality stories on a regular basis quickly occurred to the participants in <italic>OCOV</italic>, who were not always able to fit in the Sunday afternoon class into their schedules and opted to take the cameras home to shoot. Taxi drivers from the class shot part of their stories from their cabs between fares. The many challenges to citizen journalists have been noted elsewhere. One non-professional who runs a local news website in San Mateo was initially enthusiastic about providing an alternative to the mainstream, but quickly discovered that, ‘I wish I’d known how hard it is to do journalism well. I’ve now learned by doing it how time-consuming it is to report, write, edit and fact-check news stories with integrity’(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1464884911421703">Parr, 2005</xref>). <italic>Current TV</italic>, considered a leading project of this kind, laid off 80 people in 2009 and shifted to a more traditional form of production in order to attract advertising (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1464884911421703">Flint and James, 2009</xref>). The democratization of video technology, therefore, is only part of the equation: without significant support and resources, it is difficult for the occasional, unpaid citizen journalist to consistently produce counter-narratives.</p>
<p>One of the values of a project like this is that it helps shape the questions for further research. For instance, will citizen video journalism develop into its own form? Will it remain on the margins of public discourse? It remains unclear whether citizen organizations will sustain journalistic activity, or whether projects such as <italic>OCOV</italic> will be short-lived. The barrier between non-professional and professional journalistic activity is as porous as it has ever been, and seems to be changing faster than it can be studied. To use a photographic metaphor, this study is a series of snapshots: helpful, it is hoped, in explaining what is under way, even thought it cannot predict what will be.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1464884911421703">
<label>1</label>
<p>Part of a video story in which the correspondent appears and speaks.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1464884911421703">
<label>2</label>
<p>Filmmakers in the <italic>Cinéma verité</italic> or <italic>Realist Cinema</italic> tradition tended not to make objective/realist truth claims; however, they only made claims to a form of truthfulness that lets the audience do more interpreting than the filmmaker.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Biographical note</title>
<p><bold>Mary Angela Bock</bold> (PhD, University of Pennsylvania) is an assistant professor of Speech and Theatre at Kutztown University in Pennsylvania. Her previous career was in television news. Her research interests include visual rhetoric and photojournalistic practice. Bock’s work has appeared in <italic>Visual Communication Quarterly</italic>, the <italic>International Journal of Press and Politics</italic>, and the <italic>Encyclopedia of Journalism</italic> (SAGE, 2009). She co-edited <italic>The Content Analysis Reader</italic> with Klaus Krippendorff.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>Film and Reform: John Grierson and the Documentary Film Movement</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>1998</year>) <source>The Documentary Film Movement: An Anthology</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>News from NowHere: Televisual news and the construction of hegemony</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Approaches to Media Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ananny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stohecker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Sustained, Open Dialogue with Citizen Photojournalism Development by Design Conference</source>. <publisher-loc>Bangalore, India</publisher-loc>. <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.75.4739">http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.75.4739</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnouw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <source>Documentary: A History of the Non-Fiction Film</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gresett</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haltom</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Repairing the news: A case study of the news paradigm</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dardenne</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Myth, chronicle, and story: Exploring the narrative qualities of news</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Media, Myths and Narratives: Television and the Press</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>War journalism and the ‘KIA Journalist’: The cases of David Bloom and Michael Kelly</article-title>. <source>Critical Studies in Mass Communication</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Blogs and journalistic authority</article-title>. <source>Journalism Studies</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chatman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Story and Discourse: Narrative Structure in Fiction and Film</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chatman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Coming to Terms: The Rhetoric of Narrative in Fiction and Film</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Documentary and collaboration: Placing the camera in the community</article-title>. <source>Journal of Film and Video</source> <volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Governing the News: The News Media as a Political Institution</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, Il</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Tuning in the news: TV journalism and the process of ideation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Vidal-Beneyto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Focused Screen</source>. <publisher-loc>Strasbourg, Amela</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Council of Europe</publisher-name>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deuze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>What is journalism?</article-title> <source>Journalism</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>442</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>Seeing Things: Television in the Age of Uncertainty</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IB Tauris</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Current TV to shift from video format</article-title>. <source>LA Times</source> (<day>12</day> <month>November</month>). <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://articles.latimes.com/2009/nov/12/business/fi-ct-current12">http://articles.latimes.com/2009/nov/12/business/fi-ct-current12</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garcelon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The ‘Indymedia’ experiment: The internet as movement facilitator against institutional control</article-title>. <source>Convergence</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gitlin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>The Whole World is Watching: Mass Media in the Making and Unmaking of the New Left</source>, <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Glasgow University Media Group</collab> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Bad News</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge and Kegan Paul</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Encoding and decoding in the television discourse</article-title>. <comment>Stencilled Paper 7</comment>. <publisher-name>University of Birmingham</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>CCCS</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>Understanding News</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Methuen</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Washington reporters</article-title>. <source>Society</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knobloch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patzig</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mende</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hastall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Affective news: Effects of discourse structure in narratives on suspense,curiousity and enjoyment while reading news and novels</article-title>. <source>Communication Research</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kracauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1947</year>) <source>From Caligari to Hitler: A Psychological History of the German Film</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Trapped by Deadline, Hammered by Spinners</source>. <comment>Behind the News. CJR on the media, CJR.org/bet</comment> (<day>5</day> <month>October</month>). <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cjr.org/behind_the_news/trapped_by_deadline_hammered_b.php">http://www.cjr.org/behind_the_news/trapped_by_deadline_hammered_b.php</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Massing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Out of focus</article-title>. <source>Columbia Journalism Review</source> <volume>March/April</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Molotch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>News as purposive behaviour: On the strategic use of routine events, accidents and scandals</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Broadcast news, the live ‘two-way’ and the case of Andrew Gilligan</article-title>. <source>Media Culture and Society</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Representing Reality: Issues and Concepts in Documentary</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Introduction to Documentary</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Things I wish I’d known before I became a citizen journalist</article-title>. <source>Neiman Reports</source> <volume>Winter</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Witnessing</article-title>. <source>Media, Culture and Society</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Platon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deuze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Indymedia journalism</article-title>. <source>Journalism</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The voice of authority: The local accomplishment of authoritative discourse in live news broadcasts</article-title>. <source>Discourse Studies</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Questions and answers about public journalism</article-title>. <source>Journalism Studies</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rouch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Ciné-Ethnography</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sigal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <source>Reporters and Officials: The Organization and Politics of Newsmaking</source>. <publisher-loc>Lexington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>DC Heath and Co</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Regarding the Pain of Others</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Farrar, Staus and Giroux</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regarding the torture of others</article-title>. <source>New York Times Magazine</source> (<day>23</day> <month>May</month>): <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>, <fpage>42</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stoller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>The Cinematic Griot</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Body Horror</source>. <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tuchman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Making News: A Study in the Construction of Reality</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Free Press, A division of Macmillan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Structures of news in the press</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Discourse and Communication: New Approaches to the Analysis of Mass Media Discourse and Communication</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>deGruyter</publisher-name>, <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The man with the movie camera</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>The Documentary Tradition: from Nanook to Woodstock</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hopkinson and Blake</publisher-name>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1947</year>) <source>The Theory of Social and Economic Organization</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990a</year>) <article-title>Achieving journalistic authority through narrative</article-title>. <source>Critical Studies in Mass Communication</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990b</year>) <source>Covering the Body: The Kennedy Assassination, the Media, and the Shaping of Collective Memory</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990c</year>) <article-title>Where is the author in American TV news? On the construction and presentation of proximity, authorship and journalistic authority</article-title>. <source>Semiotica</source> <volume>80</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>37</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Journalists as interpretive communities</article-title>. <source>Critical Studies in Mass Communication</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Text, talk and journalistic quoting practices</article-title>. <source>The Communication Review</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Remembering to Forget: Holocaust Memory through the Camera’s Eye</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>When facts, truth and reality are God-terms: On journalism’s uneasy place in cultural studies</article-title>. <source>Communication and Critical/Cultural Studies</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1464884911421703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>On ‘having been there’: Eyewitnessing as a journalistic key word</article-title>. <source>Critical Studies in Media Communication</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>408</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>