<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpr</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Preventive Cardiology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2047-4873</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2047-4881</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1741826711403252</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1741826711403252</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Rehabilitation</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original scientific papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Controlled study of myocardial recovery after interval training in heart failure: SMARTEX-HF – rationale and design</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Støylen</surname><given-names>Asbjørn</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711403252">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1741826711403252">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Conraads</surname><given-names>Viviane</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1741826711403252">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Halle</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1741826711403252">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>Axel</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1741826711403252">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-1741826711403252">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ellingsen</surname><given-names>Øyvind</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711403252">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1741826711403252">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-1741826711403252">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1741826711403252"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1741826711403252"><label>1</label>St. Olavs Hospital, Trondheim, Norway.</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1741826711403252"><label>2</label>Norwegian University of Science and Technology, (NTNU) Trondheim, Norway.</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1741826711403252"><label>3</label>Antwerp University Hospital, Edegem, Belgium.</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1741826711403252"><label>4</label>Technische Universität, Klinikum rechts der Isar, Munich, Germany.</aff>
<aff id="aff5-1741826711403252"><label>5</label>Universtät Leipzig, Herzzentrum GmbH, Leipzig, Germany.</aff>
<aff id="aff6-1741826711403252"><label>6</label>Bispebjerg University Hospital, Copenhagen, Denmark.</aff>
<aff id="aff7-1741826711403252"><label>7</label>K.G.Jebsen centre of exercise in medicine, NTNU.</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1741826711403252">Øyvind Ellingsen, Department of Circulation and Medical Imaging, Medical Technology Research Centre, PO Box 8905, NO-7491 Trondheim, Norway Email: <email>oyvind.ellingsen@ntnu.no</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>813</fpage>
<lpage>821</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The European Society of Cardiology 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">European Society of Cardiology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background:</bold> The large randomized controlled multicentre clinical trial, HF-ACTION, recently demonstrated that a programme of recommendation of regular exercise training at moderate intensity is safe, improves quality of life, and reduces the combined endpoint of all-cause death and hospitalization in patients with chronic heart failure. However, the size of beneficial effects was modest compared to results published in smaller single studies and meta-analyses.</p>
<p><bold>Objective:</bold> Based on results of a pilot study, the objective of the present investigation is to test the hypothesis that a programme comprising interval training at high relative intensity would yield significantly larger effects in terms of left ventricular remodelling compared to moderate continuous exercise training.</p>
<p><bold>Study design:</bold> In a three-armed randomized multicentre study of stable heart failure patients with left ventricular ejection fraction ≤35%, the effects of a 12-week programme of high-intensity interval training (HIT; 85–90% of peak oxygen uptake, VO<sub>2peak</sub>) will be compared to actual practice in Europe, represented by either an isocaloric programme of moderate continuous training (MCT; 50–60% of VO<sub>2peak</sub>) and a recommendation of regular exercise (RE) of the individual patients’ own preference based on clinical practice at the local centre. The primary endpoint is reverse remodelling, defined as change in left ventricular end-diastolic diameter assessed by echocardiography. Secondary endpoints include peak oxygen uptake (VO<sub>2peak</sub>), biomarkers, quality of life, and level of physical activity assessed by questionnaires. In addition, long-term maintenance of effects after the supervised training period will be determined. Assessments will be made at baseline, after the 12-week intervention programme, and at 1-year follow up. A total number of 200 patients on treatment per protocol, randomized to the three groups in a 1 : 1 : 1 manner, is estimated to detect clinically relevant differences in effect with HIT vs. MCT and RE (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; statistical power 0.90) for the primary endpoint. Inclusion of patients started May 2009 and will run until total number has been reached.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Left ventricular remodelling</kwd>
<kwd>training intensity</kwd>
<kwd>echocardiography</kwd>
<kwd>VO<sub>2max</sub></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1741826711403252"><title>Background</title>
<p>The prevalence of chronic heart failure (CHF) is increasing in the Western world, and it has been estimated that at least 10 million people suffer from heart failure in Europe.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711403252">1</xref></sup> The prognosis of heart failure has improved with the advent of new medication and implantable electrical devices. However, mortality rates remain high; in the Care HF study, patients on optimal medical therapy with New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II–III had an annual mortality of 10–12% with an ejection fraction of 25%, and 6–8% with an ejection fraction of 35%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1741826711403252">2</xref></sup> In addition, heart failure is a significant cause of hospitalization, impaired function, and reduced quality of life (QoL), which represents a burden on the individual and society.</p>
<sec id="sec2-1741826711403252"><title>Beneficial effects of exercise training in CHF</title>
<p>Several studies have shown that exercise training yields additional beneficial effects to pharmacological and electrical therapy. Until recently, evidence was based on relatively small single-centre studies, with training regimens varying substantially in terms of intensity, modality and load. Training in CHF has a class IA recommendation in the present guidelines for the treatment of CHF, issued by the European Society of Cardiology.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711403252">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1741826711403252">3</xref></sup> Still only a minority of patients are offered systematic exercise treatment. Overall, pooling of the existing studies shows a significant increase in QoL and exercise performance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741826711403252">4</xref></sup> Although QoL is probably the most important endpoint from a patient point of view, measurement of QoL is subject to bias and personal interpretation. Objective measures of physical capacity (exercise time, 6MWD, peak performance etc), better work economy, improved anaerobic threshold, and improved peak oxygen uptake (VO<sub>2peak</sub>) have consistently been reported. A meta-analysis found a mean increase in anaerobic threshold of 1.91 ml/kg/min (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), an 11.6% increase in 6-minute walking distance (6MWD), and an improvement inVO<sub>2peak</sub> of 2.06 ml/kg/min (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1741826711403252">3</xref></sup> However, the large HF-ACTION study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711403252">5</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711403252">7</xref></sup> which included 2331 patients randomized to training intervention vs. usual care, found only a modest, but highly significant increase of exercise time (1.5 vs. 0.3 minutes), 6MWD (5% vs. 1% increase), and VO<sub>2peak</sub> (0.6 vs. 0.2 ml(kg/min), after a 12-week training programme.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1741826711403252"><title>Training and reverse left ventricular remodelling</title>
<p>Very few single-centre studies have explicitly focused on the effect of exercise on cardiac remodelling. Some authors have found improvement in cardiac function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1741826711403252">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> whereas others have not detected any significant differences between exercise training and usual care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1741826711403252">10</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1741826711403252">12</xref></sup> However, a recent meta-analysis of 14 trials with a total of 814 patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1741826711403252">13</xref></sup> indicated that endurance training increases left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) and reduces left ventricular end-systolic and end-diastolic volumes, although differences between groups were modest. The effect was limited to endurance training programmes only, in subgroup analysis. In contrast, the meta analysis by van Tol et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741826711403252">4</xref></sup> detected only a modest decrease in end diastolic volume (EDV), even though it included more studies. Thus, the effect of exercise on remodelling requires further investigation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1741826711403252"><title>Training and prognosis in CHF</title>
<p>As resources to study exercise training are small compared to pharmacological interventions, most studies are small and characterized by a short-term follow up. Hence, their ability to demonstrate a significant reduction in clinical endpoints is limited. In a randomized study of 99 subjects by Belardinelli et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1741826711403252">10</xref></sup> patients underwent moderate-intensity endurance training during an induction programme of 8 weeks, followed by a maintenance programme for 1 year. VO<sub>2peak</sub> and QoL improved in the initial period, with no further increase during maintenance. Importantly, the study also showed an absolute reduction in mortality (40% in the control group vs. 18% in the training group) during the follow-up period of 4 years, and combined endpoints were reduced even more (76% vs. 34%). However, few of the enrolled patients were on beta-blocker therapy. Pooling of nine studies in the ExTRaMATCH meta-analysis indicated that survival improved by 35%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1741826711403252">14</xref></sup> However, pooling of small studies is subject to bias and results need to be confirmed in larger trials. The HF-ACTION trial is the only large-scale international and multicentre randomized study evaluating the long-term effect of endurance training vs. ‘usual care’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711403252">5</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711403252">7</xref></sup> After a mean and of 2.5 years, adjusted all-cause mortality and combined cardiovascular mortality/heart failure related hospital admissions were significantly reduced,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1741826711403252">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711403252">7</xref></sup> but only when analysed according to pre-determined covariate analysis. Moreover, training yielded better QoL and exercise performance. However, effects were moderate compared to previous smaller studies. Adherence to prescribed training load seemed of importance for improvement of prognosis, but was rather difficult to achieve. It has been suggested<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1741826711403252">15</xref></sup> that there is a ‘dose–response relationship’, at least in terms of training volume, probably also in terms of intensity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1741826711403252"><title>Training intensity</title>
<p>The majority of investigators have implemented exercise training levels of 40–75% of VO<sub>2peak</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711403252">1</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741826711403252">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1741826711403252">15</xref></sup> Theoretically, interval training with bouts of high relative exercise intensity might be more efficient in CHF patients. Indeed, it is well known that in healthy subjects and athletes, interval training improves aerobic capacity more effectively than moderate training.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1741826711403252">16</xref></sup> Measurable improvement of maximal stroke volume and cardiac output in healthy humans can only be induced by training of high intensity at about 90% of VO<sub>2max</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1741826711403252">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1741826711403252">17</xref></sup> At this level of intensity, training is generally near and just above the anaerobic threshold, and has to be performed as interval training with short high-intensity bouts, separated by active pauses below anaerobic threshold, in order to eliminate accumulated lactate. High-intensity interval training leads to superior increases in VO<sub>2max</sub> and improves myocyte function compared to moderate continuous training (MCT).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1741826711403252">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1741826711403252">19</xref></sup> This has been shown also in experimental heart failure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1741826711403252">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>So far, only one clinical study has assessed high-intensity interval training (HIT) guided by oxygen uptake testing in CHF.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> In this randomized study of 27 patients with post-infarction heart failure, mean age was 75.5 years, male/female ratio was 20/7, mean creatinine was 118, and all were on angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and beta-blockers. Twelve weeks of HIT increased VO<sub>2peak</sub> from 13 to 19 ml/kg/min, improved left ventricular ejection fraction from 28 to 38 %, reduced end-diastolic left ventricular volume from 248 to 202 ml, led to a decrease in end-diastolic left ventricular diameter from 67 to 59 mm, and increased both systolic and diastolic tissue velocities. Increased QoL was documented by use of the MacNew questionnaire. In contrast, the group of patients that trained at isocaloric MCT at 70% of VO<sub>2peak</sub> increased VO<sub>2peak</sub> significantly less (13 to 15 ml/kg/min). There were no change in left ventricular dimensions and function and the improvement in QoL was significantly smaller. Based on these findings, it can be hypothesized that training intensity needs to be considerably higher than previously assumed in order to achieve optimal results and that HIT may have the potential to induce clinically relevant improvements in cardiac function.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1741826711403252"><title>Sustainability of results</title>
<p>Only few studies of exercise training in CHF reported sustainability of results after stopping the intervention, and all found a rapid decrease of outcome measures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1741826711403252">21</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1741826711403252">23</xref></sup> The HF-ACTION trial<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711403252">7</xref></sup> found no difference from baseline to 12 months in 6MWD, exercise time, and peak VO<sub>2</sub> after 12 months, although the exercise group maintained a difference to the control group. However, one study maintained improvement of exercise capacity and QoL after 1 year.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1741826711403252">24</xref></sup> This study applied a group-based exercise-intervention with interval principle with a relatively high-intensity regimen, but without VO<sub>2</sub> and heart rate measurements for objective measures of exercise intensity. It has been suggested that patients experiencing marked improvement by intensive interval training may be more likely to maintain physical activity after supervised programmes. We therefore hypothesize that a greater improvement in fitness will lead to a higher activity level that in turn may sustain a significant part of the beneficial effects of the intervention.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1741826711403252"><title>Rationale of the study</title>
<p>As shown in the recently conducted HF-ACTION study, it is very likely that the effects of a moderate-intensity endurance training intervention in CHF is smaller than previously assumed. Hence, other exercise modalities should be explored. The study by Wisløff et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> provides the somewhat provocative working hypothesis that HIT is superior to MCT in patients with CHF.</p>
<p>The primary objective of the SMARTEX-HF study is to determine whether a 12-week supervised HIT programme will result in significant reverse remodelling of the left ventricle compared to either training at moderate intensity or a control group that is recommended to exercise regularly without supervised sessions.</p>
<p>The primary endpoint is change in left ventricular end diastolic diameter, assessed by echocardiography. Secondary endpoints will be left ventricular volumes and ejection fraction, N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP), quality of life assessed by the Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ) as well as the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), and the Global Mood Scale (GMS). In addition, VO<sub>2peak</sub> will be assessed as a primary measure of training effect and the abbreviated International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) will be the measure of physical activity level.</p>
<p>Secondary objectives are sustainability of results. Participants will be re-assessed for all primary and secondary endpoints after a period of 12 months to determine whether results are sustainable.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1741826711403252"><title>Study population</title>
<p>The study will include stable CHF patients in NYHA class II–III on optimal medical therapy including beta-blocker, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, and/or angiotensin II receptor blocker, diuretics, and spironolactone, as judged by the treating physician, with a left ventricular ejection fraction of ≤35% as determined by echocardiography by local measurement. To allow for regression towards the mean in repeated measurement at core lab, the patient will only be excluded if core lab EF is &gt;40%. Inclusion and exclusion criteria are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1741826711403252">Table 1</xref>. These will largely exclude more transient states such as myocarditis etc. Any intervention in the form of cardiac resynchronization therapy and revascularization should be prior to 6 months before enrolment. Cardiopulmonary exercise testing and echocardiography will be performed before randomization as part of the screening for exclusion criteria. If a patient gets an intervention during the training period that is not due to an acute event, this will be considered as a violation of the inclusion criteria.
<table-wrap id="table1-1741826711403252" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1741826711403252" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711403252-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Inclusion criteria</th>
<th>LVEF ≤35% by measurement at local centre</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td/>
<td>NYHA class II/III</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Clinically stable for 6 weeks</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Optimal medical treatment for ≥3 months</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Exclusion criteria</td>
<td>Revascularization and CRT within last 6 months</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Planned revascularization and CRT</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Significant inter-current illness last 6 weeks</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Known significant ventricular arrhythmia without ICD</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Other heart disease that limits exercise tolerance (valve disease and hypertrophic cardiomyopathy)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Co-morbidity that may influence 1-year prognosis</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Functional and mental disability that limits exercise</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Scheduled for heart-transplant</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Regular vigorous exercise/exercise programme within 6 months</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Oral corticosteroid treatment</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>COPD with FEV<sub>1</sub> &lt;50% predicted</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ICD ATP-threshold incompatible with testing/training</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Significant ischaemia, arrhythmia, and haemodynamic deterioration at exercise testing</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>ICD activation at exercise testing</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Renal failure requiring dialysis</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Evidence of malignancy</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Participation in another clinical trial</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CHF secondary to congenital heart disease</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1741826711403252"><p>CHF, chronic heart failure; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; CRT, cardiac resynchronization therapy; FEV<sub>1</sub>, forced expiratory volume in one second; ICD, implantable cardioverter defibrillator; LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; NYHA, New York Heart Association.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1741826711403252" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec10-1741826711403252"><title>Exercise testing</title>
<p>A cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET) will be performed using individualized treadmill and bicycle ergometer protocols. Oxygen consumption and CO<sub>2</sub> production will be measured by ventilatory gas exchange. Patients will be encouraged to exercise to levelling off of VO<sub>2</sub> despite an increase in workload and to respiratory exchange ratio &gt;1.05. This is a quality assessment of the test, but not a requirement for inclusion. Data derived from CPET will be additionally analysed at the core laboratory.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1741826711403252"><title>Echocardiography</title>
<p>A standard echocardiography will be performed to rule out cardiac disease that will limit exercise tolerance. Left ventricular diameters and volumes will be measured. Doppler flow recordings and tissue Doppler will be acquired as supplementary data of systolic and diastolic function. Data will be stored digitally and analysed at the core laboratory. In selected centres, an additional cardiac MRI scan will be performed for calibration of the echocardiography volume measurements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1741826711403252"><title>Randomization and exercise intervention</title>
<p>The patients will be randomized 1 : 1 : 1 to three groups: (1) high-intensity interval training (HIT); (2) moderate continuous training (MCT); and (3) recommendation of regular exercise (RE). Randomization will be stratified according to aetiology (ischaemic vs. non-ischaemic) and enrolling centre, to allow for post-hoc analysis.</p>
<p>After the 12-week programme of supervised training and RE, patients will receive usual care. This will include encouragement to continue training at home for HIT and MCT patients, as well as a telephone call every 4 weeks in order to resolve questions, detect adverse events, and assess physical activity level (IPAQ). Home-based training will consist of uphill walking, stair climbing, bicycling, and other activities at appropriate level of exertion.</p>
<p>Exercise training will be terminated at signs of any serious adverse event, and all serious adverse events will be reported to an independent safety monitoring committee and to the central database within 48 hours.</p>
<p>Moderate training has been found to be safe in patients with CHF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711403252">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1741826711403252">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741826711403252">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1741826711403252">25</xref></sup> as confirmed in the HF-ACTION study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711403252">7</xref></sup> but there is no safety data on HIT in CHF patients.</p>
<p>Death, hospitalization for cardiovascular disease, worsening of heart failure that requires intensified (diuretic) treatment, and atrial as well as ventricular arrhythmia, occurring during and within 3 hours after training in the intervention period, are considered to be training-related serious adverse events (SAE). In addition, less serious adverse events such as muscle, tendon, back, and joint problems leading to cessation and postponement of training will be registered as adverse events (AE). The total number of clinical endpoints from randomization to the end of follow-up period will be registered, and events occurring later in the observation period will be considered clinical endpoints. Some patients will probably become in need for interventions in the observation period (from 12 weeks to 1 year) and this will be considered clinical endpoints.</p>
<sec id="sec13-1741826711403252"><title>High-intensity interval training</title>
<p>Patients will warm up for 10 minutes at moderate intensity (corresponding to 50–60% of VO<sub>2peak</sub>, 60–70% of peak heart rate, 11–13 Borg scale, no shortness of breath) before walking/cycling four 4-minute intervals at high intensity (corresponding to 85–90% of VO<sub>2peak</sub>, 90–95% of peak heart rate, 15–17 Borg scale, shortness of breath). Each interval will be separated by 3-minute active pauses at 50–70% of peak heart rate. The training session will be terminated by a 3-minute cool-down at moderate intensity. Total exercise time will be 38 minutes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1741826711403252"><title>Moderate continuous training</title>
<p>Patients will walk and cycle continuously at moderate intensity (corresponding to 50–60% of VO<sub>2peak</sub>, 60–70% of peak heart rate, 11–13 Borg scale, no shortness of breath) for 47 minutes each session to assure that the supervised training protocols are isocaloric.</p>
<p>All subjects will use a heart rate monitor to obtain the assigned exercise intensity. The Borg 6–20 scale will be used to measure the extent of perceived exertion during each training session, and in some, randomly chosen patients, lactate after randomly selected training sessions will be measured for quality control of training intensity. The speed and inclination of the treadmill and the load on the bicycle ergometer will continuously be adjusted, to ensure that every training session will be carried out at the assigned heart rate, thus maintaining a constant relative exercise intensity throughout the 12-week training period. All sessions will be supervised at the training facility. As the VO<sub>2peak</sub> is influenced by the type of exercise used (bicycle vs. treadmill), the training will be done in the same modality as the testing, according to the preferences at each centre.</p>
<p>Training per protocol is defined as:
<list id="list1-1741826711403252" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>70% compliance to training (25 sessions)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>70% compliance to training the last 4 weeks (minimum eight sessions) – to avoid detraining</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Permit prolonging of training intervention by up to 4 weeks – to avoid detraining</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>No more than 2 consecutive weeks without training – to avoid detraining.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Patients that have an intervention during the training period, will automatically fall outside the per-protocol definition due to sustained inactivity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-1741826711403252"><title>Recommendation of regular exercise</title>
<p>Patients will be advised to exercise regularly in activities of their own preference. In addition, they will meet for continuous treadmill walking/bicycling at 50–70% of peak heart rate for 20–30 minutes every 3 weeks, in order to motivate for post-intervention testing and to reduce the impact of learning on the post-intervention test results.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-1741826711403252"><title>Baseline and follow-up investigations</title>
<p>All patients will be examined at baseline, after 12-week training and 1 year after randomization. Examination will include echocardiography, CPET, NT-proBNP, basic biochemistry, bio-impedance, IPAQ, accelerometer measurements (in some patients), KCCQ, and depression and personality traits (HADS, GMS, type D personality). In addition, patients will be followed up by telephone contact registering adverse events and physical activity (IPAQ). The flow chart is summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1741826711403252">Figure 1</xref>. Core labs will analyse echocardiographic recordings and questionnaires blinded to randomization.
<fig id="fig1-1741826711403252" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Flow chart for patient inclusion and follow up, showing screening, inclusion and exclusion, randomization, and tests at follow up. CRF, case report form; AE, adverse events; CPET, cardiopulmonary exercise test; HIT, high-intensity interval training; IPAQ, physical activity assessment (questionnaire); LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; MCT, moderate-intensity continuous training; NYHA, New York Heart Association; Pathological CPET, significant arrhythmia, ischaemia, and haemodynamic deterioration during test; QOL, quality of life assessment (questionnaire); RE, recommendations of exercise.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711403252-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-1741826711403252"><title>Statistics</title>
<p>According to estimates based on data from the previous smaller study by Wisløff et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> with the same training programme, a total number of 200 patients randomized 1 : 1 : 1 to the three intervention groups is sufficient to detect larger beneficial effects with HIT compared to either MCT or RE with a <italic>p</italic>-value of 0.05 (two-sided test) and statistical power of 0.90. The primary endpoint is reduction of LVEDD (left ventricular end-diastolic diameter) measured by M-mode echocardiography as the change from baseline before the intervention to follow up after the 12-week training programme within each individual patient.</p>
<p>In the final analysis, three comparisons will be made: HIT vs. MCT; HIT vs. RE; and MCT vs. RE. A conservative Bonferroni correction yields a <italic>p</italic>-value of 0.017 for each comparison. To estimate the standard deviation, we used a coefficient of variance of 0.04 from repeated measurements and an LVEDD of 70.0 mm, which yields a standard deviation (SD) of 2.8 mm. Since the variance of the difference between two measurements is SD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1741826711403252">2</xref></sup>, the SD of the reduction in LVEDD will be 4 mm. Since we will continue inclusion until we have the calculated number of adherent patients within each arm, drop-out rate will be set to 0. Since patients will be assessed immediately after the intervention, we estimate loss to follow up will be less than 10%. Because of the close follow up of the intervention, there will be no cross-over between groups. In the study by Wisløff et al., a significant reduction in LVEDD (mm) from baseline to follow up occurred in HIT only.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> The results are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1741826711403252">Table 2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table2-1741826711403252" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Effect of different training effects from the study by Wisløff et al. (2007), and a more conservative estimate of the effect as it will be attenuated in a multicentre design</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1741826711403252" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711403252-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th colspan="3">RE (control)<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">MCT<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">HIT<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Baseline</th>
<th>Follow up</th>
<th>Reduction</th>
<th>Baseline</th>
<th>Follow up</th>
<th>Reduction</th>
<th>Baseline</th>
<th>Follow up</th>
<th>Reduction</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="9">Findings in the study of Wisløff et al. (2007)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>67.2</td>
<td>67.8</td>
<td>−0.6</td>
<td>69.1</td>
<td>68.2</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>66.7</td>
<td>59.0</td>
<td>7.7</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9">Conservative estimate of effect in multicentre study</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>69.5</td>
<td>70.0</td>
<td>−0.5</td>
<td>69.5</td>
<td>68.0</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>69.5</td>
<td>65.5</td>
<td>4.5</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>These results were obtained in a relatively small number of patients who were followed up closely, with over 90% adherence to the training sessions during the 12-week programme. In the SMARTEX-HF study, final calculations will be based on data from patients who fulfil slightly less strict criteria of adherence. In a multicentre study, predicted effect size and the difference between interventions should be more conservative. We therefore based our calculations on the following more conservative assumptions, also given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1741826711403252">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<p>In conclusion, conservative estimates based on 1 : 1 : 1 randomization to three treatment arms with equal group size and the assumption that the differences between HIT vs. MCT and HIT vs. RE are 44% and 60%, respectively (3.0 vs. 6.8, 5.0 vs. 8.3) of those observed in the pilot study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> yield a group size of 55, including loss to and of 10%. For good measure, a total of 200 patients should be enough to detect a difference between HIT and MCT for the primary endpoint, and the inclusion will continue until a total of 200 patients have been included and fulfilled training intervention per protocol.</p>
<p>The primary analysis will be according to initial randomization, regardless of fulfilling the training regimen, but allowing for those lost to follow up. However, in order to assess the physiological effects of different training intensities, a per-protocol analysis will also be performed, of those patients that fulfil training intervention per protocol.</p>
<p>The study is not powered to detect significant differences in clinical endpoints. However, endpoints will be registered, and if there are non-significant trends towards differences, this may be considered a hypothesis for a full-scale clinical endpoint trial. Given insufficient power to detect a difference in the clinical endpoints of death, arrhythmias, and worsening heart failure due to training in 1-year follow up, the power is even less to detect this during the 12 weeks of training intervention. Thus, the safety issue of high vs. moderate exercise intensity, as well as exercise vs. controls, cannot be answered in this study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-1741826711403252"><title>Project organization</title>
<p>The study is conducted at seven centres in Europe. The organization includes:
<list id="list2-1741826711403252" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Study Group. The Study Group consists of all active investigators, including local coordinators from centres which recruit a significant number of patients, heads of core labs, members of steering and endpoint committees, and other investigators that fulfil Vancouver criteria for authorship, judged by the Steering Committee.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Steering Committee. The Steering Committee decides questions regarding the study on a daily basis, and prepares the agenda for the Study Group meetings. The Steering Committee has the main responsibility for data analysis and publication of results from the present protocol.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Coordinating Centre. The Coordinating Centre will maintain the randomization database, as well as clinical report forms, and the adverse effect registry and data monitoring.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Core lab – echocardiography. Readings of echocardiography will be done at the core laboratory by files transferred in digital format. The core lab will be blinded to randomization.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Core lab – cardiopulmonary exercise testing. The core lab for exercise testing will supervise quality of testing and results.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Core lab – MRI. Examinations will be performed at local centres, recorded on CD-ROM, and transferred to the core lab for central reading.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Endpoint Committee. The Endpoint Committee reviews AEs for evaluation and classification, blinded to the randomization groups.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Safety and Monitoring Committee. The Safety and Monitoring Committee is independent and will be unblinded to the randomization groups, monitoring SAEs during the exercise intervention, as well as monitoring the closure of the database at the appropriate time.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec19-1741826711403252" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>The multicentre study aims to reproduce earlier single-centre findings that HIT may be more efficient than moderate-intensity training in inducing reverse left ventricular remodelling. In addition, the study will address if this may be the case in both ischaemic and non-ischaemic heart failure. The study is not powered to detect differences in clinical endpoints. However, the number of endpoints will still be interesting, even if not significant, as any difference will be hypothesis generating for the clinical effect. As in all training studies, there is an inclusion bias in terms of motivation, as training studies will only recruit those who are motivated. In order to assess physiological effects, the most effective approach is per protocol analysis, but the drop-out rate may in itself induce some bias.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec20-1741826711403252" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In CHF, endurance training at moderate intensity has been shown to be beneficial in terms of improved physical capacity and QoL, and meta-analyses have suggested that improved cardiac function and reverse left ventricular remodelling might be achieved. However, the HF-ACTION trial,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711403252">5</xref></sup> in which 2331 patients with stable heart failure were randomized to long-term intervention and control, questioned the size of the beneficial effects and found only moderate effects on mortality outcomes. A recently conducted small study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711403252">9</xref></sup> suggests that HIT may yield results that are superior to moderate-intensity training.</p>
<p>The SMARTEX-HF is a multicentre study of CHF-patients, designed to assess the effects of high- vs. moderate-intensity training intensities with a primary focus on left ventricular remodelling. Secondary objectives include physical capacity, QoL, biomarkers, sustainability of results, and safety of interval training.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec21-1741826711403252"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by the Norwegian University for Science and Technology (NTNU) Grant number: 46039800, the Central Norway Regional Health Authority Grant number 4603550, and the National Council on Cardiovascular Disease, Norway, grant number 47063100.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec22-1741826711403252"><title>Endorsement</title>
<p>This work is endorsed by the European Association for Cardiovascular Prevention and Rehabilitation.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1741826711403252"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickstein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen-Solal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippatos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>McMurray</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponikowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole-Wilson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ESC guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure 2008: the Task Force for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure 2008 of the European Society of Cardiology. Developed in collaboration with the Heart Failure Association of the ESC (HFA) and endorsed by the European Society of Intensive Care Medicine (ESICM)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Heart Fail</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>933</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1741826711403252"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Daubert</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Freemantle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappenberger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Longer-term effects of cardiac resynchronization therapy on mortality in heart failure the CArdiac REsynchronization-Heart Failure (CARE-HF) trial extension phase</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>1928</fpage>–<lpage>1932</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1741826711403252"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganiats</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>2009 focused update: ACCF/AHA Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Management of Heart Failure in Adults: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines: developed in collaboration with the International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>119</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>1977</fpage>–<lpage>2016</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1741826711403252"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Tol</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijsmans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schothorst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwakkel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of exercise training on cardiac performance, exercise capacity and quality of life in patients with heart failure: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Heart Fail</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>850</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1741826711403252"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whellan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keteyian</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Heart failure and a controlled trial investigating outcomes of exercise training (HF-ACTION): design and rationale</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>153</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1741826711403252"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pina</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whellan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of exercise training on health status in patients with chronic heart failure: HF-ACTION randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>301</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1459</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1741826711403252"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whellan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keteyian</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of exercise training in patients with chronic heart failure: HF-ACTION randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>301</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>1439</fpage>–<lpage>1450</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1741826711403252"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hambrecht</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gielen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiehn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of exercise training on left ventricular function and peripheral resistance in patients with chronic heart failure: a randomized trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>283</volume>(<issue>23</issue>): <fpage>3095</fpage>–<lpage>3101</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1741826711403252"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisløff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoylen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Loennechen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruvold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognmo</surname><given-names>Ø</given-names></name><name><surname>Haram</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Superior cardiovascular effect of aerobic interval training versus moderate continuous training in heart failure patients: a randomized study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>115</volume>(<issue>24</issue>): <fpage>3086</fpage>–<lpage>3094</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1741826711403252"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belardinelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgiou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cianci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Randomized, controlled trial of long-term moderate exercise training in chronic heart failure: effects on functional capacity, quality of life, and clinical outcome</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>99</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1741826711403252"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giannuzzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Temporelli</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrà</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Imparato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term physical training and left ventricular remodeling after anterior myocardial infarction: results of the Exercise in Anterior Myocardial Infarction (EAMI) trial. EAMI Study Group</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1821</fpage>–<lpage>1829</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1741826711403252"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giannuzzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Temporelli</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Corra</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antiremodeling effect of long-term exercise training in patients with stable chronic heart failure: results of the Exercise in Left Ventricular Dysfunction and Chronic Heart Failure (ELVD-CHF) Trial</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>108</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1741826711403252"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haykowsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pechter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A meta-analysis of the effect of exercise training on left ventricular remodeling in heart failure patients: the benefit depends on the type of training performed</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>24</issue>): <fpage>2329</fpage>–<lpage>2336</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1741826711403252"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piepoli</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Davos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coats</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><collab>ExTraMATCH Collaborative</collab>. <article-title>Exercise training meta-analysis of trials in patients with chronic heart failure (ExTraMATCH)</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>328</volume>(<issue>7433</issue>): <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1741826711403252"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keteyian</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brawner</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Piña</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role and benefits of exercise in the management of patients with heart failure</article-title>. <source>Heart Fail Rev</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1741826711403252"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helgerud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoydal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjerkaas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic high-intensity intervals improve VO2max more than moderate training</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1741826711403252"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tjonna</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognmo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stølen</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haram</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic interval training versus continuous moderate exercise as a treatment for the metabolic syndrome: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>118</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1741826711403252"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kemi</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Condorelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisløff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Myocardial sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca2+ ATPase function is increased by aerobic interval training</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1741826711403252"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kemi</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellingsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Condorelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic interval training enhances cardiomyocyte contractility and Ca2+ cycling by phosphorylation of CaMKII and Thr-17 of phospholamban</article-title>. <source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1741826711403252"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisløff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Loennechen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellingsen</surname><given-names>Ø</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic exercise reduces cardiomyocyte hypertrophy and increases contractility, Ca2+ sensitivity and SERCA-2 in rat after myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Res</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1741826711403252"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willenheimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rydberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Broms</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillberger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects on quality of life, symptoms and daily activity 6 months after termination of an exercise training programme in heart failure patients</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1741826711403252"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kayanakis</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aros</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Borau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rehabilitation of patients with chronic cardiac insufficiency. Immediate and midterm effects</article-title>. <source>Presse Med</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1741826711403252"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjardem-Hansen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dela</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ørkild</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Teisner</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of a 14-month low-cost maintenance training program in patients with chronic systolic heart failure: a randomized study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>437</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1741826711403252"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Westheim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Risberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term effects of a group-based high-intensity aerobic interval-training program in patients with chronic heart failure</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>102</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1220</fpage>–<lpage>1224</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1741826711403252"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marwick</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exercise training for patients with heart failure: a systematic review of factors that improve mortality and morbidity</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>116</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>