<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjag</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Applied Gerontology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0733-4648</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4523</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0733464811423647</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0733464811423647</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Balancing Eldercare and Employment</article-title>
<subtitle>The Role of Work Interruptions and Supportive Employers</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jeungkun</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0733464811423647">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingersoll-Dayton</surname><given-names>Berit</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0733464811423647">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>Minyoung</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0733464811423647">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0733464811423647"><label>1</label>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0733464811423647">Jeungkun Kim, Samsung Economic Research Institute, Seocho 2-dong, Seocho-gu, Seoul 137-955, Korea. Email: <email>jkun.kim@samsung.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>347</fpage>
<lpage>369</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>24</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Southern Gerontological Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study investigates pathways by which employed caregivers’ stress is related to their work performance appraisal, with particular attention to work interruptions and supportive employers. Based on a nationally representative sample from the 2004 National Long-Term Care Survey (NLTCS), the study focuses on caregivers to older adults who are currently participating in paid employment (<italic>N</italic> = 652). Results from structural equation modeling indicate that work interruptions mediate the relationship between caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal. In addition, the support of employers moderates the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work interruptions as well as the relationship between their work interruptions and work performance appraisal. These results point to the need for training supervisors and helping them to understand the potential dual effects of their support on employed caregivers’ work interruptions and performance.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>employed caregivers</kwd>
<kwd>caregivers’ stress</kwd>
<kwd>work performance</kwd>
<kwd>informal support</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>As more women participate in paid jobs and more men share family responsibilities with women, there has been an increasing number of workers who must combine work with family responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0733464811423647">Bond, Galinsky, &amp; Swanberg, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0733464811423647">Kossek, 2005</xref>). Such changes in the demographic complexion of employment have had repercussions on the proportion of individuals who are undertaking both work and eldercare responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0733464811423647">Sterns, Barrett, Czaja, &amp; Barr, 1994</xref>). The resulting conflict between their work and caregiving responsibilities may influence employees’ work attendance as well as their job performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0733464811423647">Eby, Casper, Lockwood, Bordeaux, &amp; Brinley, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0733464811423647">Hammer, Bauer, &amp; Grandey, 2003</xref>). Increasingly, to address the negative effects of these dual responsibilities, employers are providing supportive programs and services to their employees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0733464811423647">Breaugh &amp; Frye, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0733464811423647">Kossek &amp; Nichol, 1992</xref>).</p>
<p>To date, however, most efforts to enhance employees’ abilities to balance their work and family responsibilities have focused on two particular areas. One major effort has focused on support to those who have childcare responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal, Chapman, Ingersoll-Dayton, &amp; Emlen, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0733464811423647">Neal &amp; Hammer, 2007</xref>). Although older persons make up a growing proportion of the general population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0733464811423647">OECD, 2006</xref>) and there are increasing numbers of employees who take care of older adults with long-term care needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0733464811423647">Neal &amp; Wagner, 2001</xref>), there remains a limited awareness of employees’ eldercare responsibilities, compared with employees’ childcare responsibilities. Therefore, support programs for employees with eldercare responsibilities are not as common as support programs for employees with childcare responsibilities, although employees caring for the elderly are more likely to be interrupted at work than those caring for children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0733464811423647">Sahibzada, Hammer, Neal, &amp; Kuang, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0733464811423647">Scott, Hwang, &amp; Rogers, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>A second effort has focused on formal support to employees with caregiving responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0733464811423647">Neal &amp; Wagner, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0733464811423647">Potter, Churilla, &amp; Smith, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0733464811423647">Thompson, Beauvais, &amp; Lyness, 1999</xref>). Formal workplace supports include policies (e.g., flexible work arrangements), benefits (e.g., dependent-care tax credits), and services (e.g., resources and referral services), which are designed to diminish difficulties in managing dual roles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0733464811423647">Neal &amp; Hammer, 2007</xref>). Although formal support can help employed caregivers to balance work and caregiving responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0733464811423647">Lechner &amp; Gupta, 1996</xref>), its availability does not remove some important barriers that can prevent employees from successfully using formal support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0733464811423647">Allen, 2001</xref>). For example, if employers and supervisors do not encourage the use of formal support programs, employed caregivers are hesitant to use them; they worry that making use of these formal benefits may jeopardize their careers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0733464811423647">Morris, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0733464811423647">Sahibzada et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Several studies suggest that informal support, such as supervisor or employer support and a family supportive culture at work, may play an important role in determining whether or not employed caregivers use formal supports and whether use of these formal supports addresses the concerns of employees with work and family responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0733464811423647">Hammer, Colton, Caubet, &amp; Brockwood, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0733464811423647">Lobel &amp; Kossek, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0733464811423647">Mesemer-Eagnus &amp; Viswesvaran, 2006</xref>). Despite the probable importance of informal support, relatively few studies have examined the effects of informal support at the workplace. Those that have conducted such research have been limited by restricted samples (e.g., employees from specific geographical areas and specific types of organizations) thus reducing the generalizability of their findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0733464811423647">Atienza &amp; Stephens, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0733464811423647">Sahibzada et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>To expand the scope of research on balancing work and family responsibilities, this study uses a nationally representative sample and focuses on informal eldercare support by employers. We focus on informal support because this form of support may be more likely than formal eldercare policies to impact employed caregivers’ ability to balance work and eldercare responsibilities as well as their work performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0733464811423647">Scharlach, Lowe, &amp; Schneider, 1991</xref>). In so doing, we examine the extent to which one kind of informal support (i.e., having an understanding employer) influences the relationships among caregiver stress, work interruptions, and work performance appraisal.</p>
<sec id="section1-0733464811423647">
<title>Conceptual Framework</title>
<p>Our study builds on a conceptual framework that examines the relationships among caregiving demands, support at work, stress, and work interruptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal et al., 1993</xref>). In the model developed by Neal and colleagues, work and family demands influence stress and work interruptions directly and indirectly through support at work. We extend their framework to include employed caregivers’ work performance appraisal and to consider the mechanisms that may influence the impact of employed caregivers’ stress on their work performance appraisal. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0733464811423647">Figure 1</xref>, our adaptation of the framework developed by Neal and colleagues examines the relationships among caregivers’ demands, stress, support at work (i.e., supportive employers), work interruptions, and work performance appraisal. This study investigates three key relationships: (a) the relationships between the demands of employees with eldercare responsibilities and their stress level, (b) the mediating effects of work interruptions on the relationship between employed elder caregivers’ stress and work performance appraisal, and (c) the moderating effects of supportive employers on two distinct relationships: between employed elder caregivers’ stress and their work interruptions and between work interruptions and work performance appraisal.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0733464811423647" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Analytical framework for the study.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0733464811423647-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>To address the first set of relationships, this study examines the demands of employed elder caregivers that contribute to their stress level. Because employed caregivers are likely to experience stress as they juggle eldercare and work responsibilities, it is important to understand the predictors of employed caregivers’ stress.</p>
<p>The second set of hypothesized relationships focuses on the indirect (i.e., mediating) effect of work interruptions on the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal as well as the direct effect of employed caregivers’ stress on their work performance appraisal. In particular, we are exploring the extent to which employees who are experiencing caregiver stress may also experience more work interruptions such as making or receiving phone calls related to eldercare, missing days at work, and worrying about their care recipients while at work. These work interruptions may then contribute to employees’ perception that their work performance is inadequate. Previous studies provide some support for these hypothesized pathways by showing that employees with caregiving responsibilities are more likely to have high levels of stress and are, therefore, more likely to miss days at work and to receive frequent calls than their counterparts without caregiving responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0733464811423647">Lee, Walker, &amp; Shoup, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0733464811423647">Neal &amp; Wagner, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>As for the third set of hypothesized relationships, our work highlights the moderating effects of informal support at the workplace. That is, when employers are understanding, it may enable employees who experience work interruptions to view their own work performance more positively than do employees whose supervisors are not aware of or understanding about their caregiving situation. In this way, the informal support from employers may interact with employed caregiver stress to influence work interruptions, and this informal support may also interact with work interruptions to influence work performance appraisal.</p>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0733464811423647">Figure 1</xref>, we examine a conceptual model in which employed caregivers’ stress is associated with their work performance appraisal both directly and indirectly through employees’ work interruptions and, in turn, their work interruptions are related to employed caregivers’ appraisal of their own job performance. In the following section, we present the empirical research that provides support for these hypothesized pathways.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0733464811423647">
<title>Employed Caregivers’ Demands and Their Caregiving Stress</title>
<p>There is considerable evidence that employed caregivers’ demands are positively related to their stress level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0733464811423647">Kramer &amp; Kipnis, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0733464811423647">Lee et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0733464811423647">Scharlach &amp; Boyd, 1989</xref>). One important set of demands for caregivers is the impairment level of their care recipients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0733464811423647">Ingersoll-Dayton &amp; Raschick, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0733464811423647">Schulz, O’Brien, Bookwala, &amp; Fleissner, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0733464811423647">Starrels, Ingersoll-Dayton, Dowler, &amp; Neal, 1997</xref>). Some researchers have found that care recipients’ impairment has a positive association with caregivers’ stress levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0733464811423647">Gottlieb, Kelloway, &amp; Fraboni, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0733464811423647">Ingersoll-Dayton &amp; Raschick, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0733464811423647">Pinquart &amp; Sorensen, 2003</xref>). Second, caregivers’ demands include their own employment situation. The number of hours of employment has been associated with greater stress among employed caregivers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal et al., 1993</xref>). In addition, another important demand to consider is the caregivers’ own health status because it is a predictor of caregiving stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0733464811423647">Lawton, Moss, Kleban, Glickman, &amp; Rovine, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0733464811423647">Lecovich, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0733464811423647">Mui &amp; Morrow-Howell, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, demands of the caregiving situation include the extent to which caregivers have or do not have resources that enable them to provide care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0733464811423647">Pearlin, Mullan, Semple, &amp; Skaff, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0733464811423647">Starrels et al., 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0733464811423647">Krause (1997)</xref> as well as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0733464811423647">Wethington and Kessler (1986)</xref> have suggested that back-up helpers (i.e., those who would provide caregiving assistance when needed) play an important role in decreasing stress levels. When employed caregivers do not have back-up helpers, they may experience a higher degree of stress. Given these previous results, this study poses the following hypothesis.</p>
<list id="list1-0733464811423647" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>: Caregiving demands (including characteristics of care recipients, caregivers, and the caregiving situation) are positively related to employed caregivers’ stress.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0733464811423647">
<title>Employed Caregivers’ Stress, Work Interruptions, and Work Performance Appraisal</title>
<p>Most research has focused on the direct effect of employed caregivers’ stress on work performance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0733464811423647">Wagner and Neal (1994)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0733464811423647">Scott and colleagues (2006)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0733464811423647">Sherman and Reed (2008)</xref> demonstrated that stress from work and eldercare responsibilities was related to decreased work performance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0733464811423647">Meiner and Lueckenotte (2005)</xref> reported that 67% of employed caregivers experienced difficulties in balancing work and caregiving that resulted in decreased work productivity.</p>
<p>Our work builds on this previous research by examining one of the mechanisms by which caregiver stress influences caregivers’ performance at work. Specifically, we are exploring the role of work interruptions. When exhausted by caregiving and feeling overwhelmed, it is likely that caregiving stress will spill over into the workplace (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0733464811423647">Thoits, 1995</xref>). Caregivers who are experiencing stress and are unable to complete their responsibilities at home may need to use work time to attend to caregiving concerns and obligations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0733464811423647">Shoptaugh, Phelps, &amp; Visio, 2004</xref>). One way in which caregiver stress can spill over to work is via interruptions while at work. Several studies have found that employed caregivers experience a variety of work interruptions related to their caregiving responsibilities such as missing time at work, receiving phone calls related to eldercare, and worrying about care recipients while at work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0733464811423647">Cullen, Hammer, Neal, &amp; Sinclair, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0733464811423647">Scharlach &amp; Boyd, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0733464811423647">Stephens &amp; Christianson, 1986</xref>). Such work interruptions are likely to affect, in turn, caregivers’ ability to perform well at work. We are exploring the extent to which such work interruptions may account for the relationship between caregiver stress and their poor work performance.</p>
<p>In the present study, we examine both the direct and indirect effects of caregiver stress on work performance appraisal via work interruptions. In so doing, we propose the following hypothesis:</p> <list id="list2-0733464811423647" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: Work interruptions have a mediating effect on the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0733464811423647">
<title>The Role of Supportive Employers in the Relationship Between Caregivers’ Stress and Work Performance Appraisal</title>
<p>Although underexplored, informal support at the workplace may play a key role in helping caregivers perform well at work despite the stress they are experiencing as caregivers. A few studies have reported that supportive employers may provide a more flexible environment at work that allows employees to interrupt their work to address their family responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0733464811423647">Eaton, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0733464811423647">Mennino, Rubin, &amp; Brayﬁeld, 2005</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0733464811423647">Eaton (1999)</xref> observed that informal support from supervisors or employers can enhance employees’ work flexibility (e.g., allowing for time off from work). Under such conditions, employees with caregiving responsibilities may feel more free to interrupt work (e.g., to take time off to meet their caregiving obligations) if their supervisors or employers understand their caregiving demands. Thus the following hypothesis is posed:</p>
<list id="list3-0733464811423647" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: For employees whose employers support their caregiving responsibilities, the effect of stress on work interruptions is stronger than when employers are not supportive.</p></list-item></list>
<p>The extent to which employers are supportive of their employees’ caregiving demands may also influence the way in which work interruptions are related to work performance. A meta-analysis conducted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0733464811423647">Riggle, Edmonson, and Hansen (2008)</xref> found that employees who felt that their organizations provided high levels of support were more likely to have better work performance as compared to their counterparts who felt that their organizations provided low levels of support. Applying the results of this meta-analysis to the context of balancing work and family suggests that caregiving employees who feel understood by their employers will perceive work interruptions as more legitimate and that the negative effect of work interruptions on appraised work performance will be reduced. We, therefore, propose the following hypothesis:</p>
<list id="list4-0733464811423647" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>: For employees whose employers support their caregiving responsibilities, the negative effect of work interruptions on work performance appraisal is less strong than when employers are not supportive.</p></list-item></list>
<p>Using the adapted conceptual framework developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal and colleagues (1993)</xref>, the present study adds to the existing literature on employed caregiver stress in two important ways. First, we consider the mediating effect of work interruptions between caregiver stress and work performance appraisal. Second, this study focuses on the role of the supportive employer and analyzes the extent to which the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal is moderated by employers’ informal support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0733464811423647" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section6-0733464811423647">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>This study is based on the National Long-Term Care Survey (NLTCS) interviews that were conducted in 2004. The NLTCS includes a nationally representative sample of older adults age 65 and above who were selected from Medicare beneficiary enrollment files. The NLTCS was first conducted in 1982 and then follow-up surveys were conducted in 1984, 1989, 1994, 1999, and 2004. This study used data from the most recent 2004 survey to complete the first step in testing the adapted conceptual framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal et al., 1993</xref>); that is, we focused on examining the relationships among the key variables from a cross-sectional perspective. The total sample size of the 2004 survey was 6,171 older adults who were divided into two groups: those living in the community and those living in institutions. Among older adults living in the community, 4,472 older adults had disabilities or health problems and received help from 2,303 unpaid informal caregivers. A total of 1,924 of these caregivers completed interviews and were involved in the 2004 NLTCS. Among these caregivers, this study focuses on those who were employed (<italic>N</italic> = 642). Thus, the study sample is employed caregivers who provided some type of assistance for an older adult who was chronically frail, ill, or disabled.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0733464811423647">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section8-0733464811423647">
<title>Employed elder caregivers’ demands</title>
<p>Caregivers’ demands were measured by four latent constructs: (a) care recipients’ impairment, (b) caregivers’ working hours, (c) back-up support availability, and (d) caregivers’ health status. Each latent construct was measured with a scale such that higher scores represented a more demanding caregiving situation. The first latent construct, care recipients’ impairment, was measured using two variables: activities of daily living (ADL) score and a total number of disruptive behaviors of the care recipient. To obtain an ADL score, caregivers were asked whether the care recipients had difficulty in each of six activities (0 = <italic>no</italic>, 1 = <italic>yes</italic>): walking, eating, getting in or out of bed, dressing, bathing, and toileting. The total ADL score represents the number of areas with which the older adult needs assistance for their routine daily activities. Disruptive behaviors was a composite score based on the caregivers’ assessment of the extent to which 15 care recipient behaviors were disruptive during the past week (0 = <italic>no days</italic>, 1 = <italic>1-2 days</italic>, 2 = <italic>3-4 days</italic>, 3 = <italic>5 or more</italic>). Thus, a higher score indicates more care recipient disruptive behaviors. The second latent construct, caregivers’ working hours, was measured by the number of hours they were employed per week. To assess the third latent construct, back-up support availability, caregivers were asked the following question: “If you were unable to help [a care recipient], is there someone else who would do the things you do?” The resulting measure was scored dichotomously (0 = <italic>yes</italic>, 1 = <italic>no</italic>). The fourth latent construct, caregivers’ health status, was measured by a dichotomous variable (0 = <italic>good health</italic>, 1 = <italic>poor health</italic>) to obtain a clear distinction in health status.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0733464811423647">
<title>Employed caregivers’ stress</title>
<p>Caregivers’ stress was measured by four items: (a) “You are exhausted when you go to bed at night”, (b) “You have more things to do than you can handle”, (c) “You don’t have time just for yourself”, and (d) “You work hard as a caregiver but never seem to make any progress” (1 = <italic>not at all</italic>, 2 = <italic>somewhat</italic>, 3 = <italic>quite a lot</italic>, 4 = <italic>completely</italic>). A higher score indicates more caregiver stress. These items were also used to measure caregivers’ stress in a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0733464811423647">Ingersoll-Dayton &amp; Raschick, 2004</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0733464811423647">
<title>Employer support at the workplace</title>
<p>Employer support at the workplace was measured by the caregivers’ response to the question, “How would you rate your employers’ attitude toward the demands of your caregiving: would you say they were very understanding, somewhat understanding, or not very understanding?” The responses were recoded and resulted in a dichotomous score (0 = <italic>not very understanding or unaware of it</italic>, 1 = <italic>very and somewhat understanding</italic>) so that we could compare the two groups of employers in our analyses. The definition of supportive employers in this study is consistent with that of previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0733464811423647">Behson, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0733464811423647">Mennino et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0733464811423647">
<title>Work interruptions</title>
<p>Since employed caregivers of older adults take days off to provide help to their care recipients and check on them several times daily by telephone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0733464811423647">Azarnoff &amp; Scharlach, 1988</xref>), we attempted to capture these kinds of work interruptions in this study. Specifically, we used three variables that were based on the employed caregivers’ assessments of the occurrence of the following work interruptions during the previous 2 months: (a) “You have missed too many days,” (b) “Phone calls about or from a care recipient interrupt you,” and (c) “You worry about a care recipient while you are at work.” Each variable was scored dichotomously (0 = <italic>disagree</italic>, 1 = <italic>agree</italic>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0733464811423647">
<title>Work performance appraisal</title>
<p>The employed caregivers’ appraisal of their own work performance was measured by two items: (a) “You have been dissatisfied with the quality of your work” and (b) “You have had less energy for your work.” Each variable was scored dichotomously so that a higher score indicates better work performance appraisal (0 = <italic>yes</italic>, 1 = <italic>no</italic>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0733464811423647">
<title>Analytical Method</title>
<p>The data were first summarized using descriptive statistics and correlations. The main analytical method in this study was structural equation modeling (SEM) that includes both observed variables and latent constructs, and examines causal relationships among the variables. Using LISREL 8.7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0733464811423647">Jöreskog &amp; Sörbom, 1993</xref>), we first estimated a measurement model to determine the relationships between observed variables and their latent constructs before identifying a structural model. As ordinal variables used in this study did not fulfill the assumption of a multivariate normal data distribution, we first normalized the variables. To compute the normal scores for the ordinal variables, we used the Normal Scores option on the Statistics menu in PRELIS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0733464811423647">Jöreskog &amp; Sörbom, 1999</xref>). After normalizing those variables, this study employed a Maximum Likelihood (ML) estimator and estimated the relationships between observed variables and their latent constructs.</p>
<p>To evaluate the fit of the models, this study employed chi-square analyses and four goodness-of-fit-indices: the Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA), the Goodness-of-Fit-Index (GFI), the Comparative Fit Index (CFI), and the Normed Fit Index (NFI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0733464811423647">Bentler, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0733464811423647">Bentler &amp; Bonett, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0733464811423647">Browne &amp; Cudeck, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0733464811423647">Jöreskog &amp; Sörbom, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0733464811423647">Steiger, 1990</xref>). A good fit is achieved if the chi-square statistic is not significant, the value of RMSEA is less than 0.05 and for the other indices, a value that exceeds 0.95 is considered to be an acceptable fit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0733464811423647">Green, Camilli, &amp; Elmore, 2006</xref>). Because the chi-square statistic is sensitive to sample size, especially if the sample size is more than 200 or less than 100, we did not rely on this statistic as the primary indicator of model fit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0733464811423647">Hair, Anderson, Tatham, &amp; Black, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0733464811423647">Jöreskog &amp; Sörbom, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0733464811423647">Tanaka, 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>To test for the mediating effect of work interruptions, we compared the direct and indirect effects between employed caregivers’ stress and work performance appraisal, using significance tests, which LISREL provides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0733464811423647">MacKinnon, 2008</xref>). In particular, mediating effects are indicated when the indirect effects are statistically significant. To test for the moderating effects of supportive employers, we assessed the same model within two subgroups: employed caregivers with supportive employers versus employed caregivers without supportive employers. We tested whether or not path coefficients between (a) employed caregivers’ stress and work interruptions and (b) work interruptions and work performance appraisal differed between the two groups, using a chi-square difference test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0733464811423647">Bollen, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0733464811423647">Kline, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>To investigate the moderating effects of supportive employers in the relationships among the three latent constructs (employed caregivers’ stress, work interruptions, and work performance appraisal), we conducted subgroup analyses. That is, after each of the path coefficients and factor loadings was first constrained to be equal across the two groups (i.e., employed caregivers with and without supportive employers), the constrained model was compared to the model that allowed the path coefficients among the three latent constructs to vary as a function of a supportive employer. If the χ<sup>2</sup> difference between the two models is significant, the model without the constraints fits better than the model that constrained the relationships among the three latent constructs, indicating that there is a significant interaction effect of a supportive employer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0733464811423647" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section15-0733464811423647">
<title>Descriptive Analysis</title>
<p>The means, standard deviations, and correlations among all the variables in this model are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0733464811423647">Table 1</xref>. The average ADL score of care recipients was 1.0 out of 6 (<italic>SD</italic> =1.7) and the average score for disruptive behaviors was 4.2 out of 26 (<italic>SD</italic> = 5.3). The average working hours of caregivers was 37 hours a week and 72% of caregivers had a back-up helper for their care recipients, whereas 77% of caregivers answered that their employers understood their caregiving demands. Most (84%) of them reported that their health status was either good or excellent.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0733464811423647" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Means, Standard Deviation, and Correlations of Study Variables.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0733464811423647" xlink:href="10.1177_0733464811423647-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
<th align="center">6</th>
<th align="center">7</th>
<th align="center">8</th>
<th align="center">9</th>
<th align="center">10</th>
<th align="center">11</th>
<th align="center">12</th>
<th align="center">13</th>
<th align="center">14</th>
<th align="center">15</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>ADL score</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Disruptive behavior</td>
<td>0.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>CGPoorHealth</td>
<td>0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">**</xref></td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>CGWorkhour</td>
<td>−0.06</td>
<td>−0.04</td>
<td>−0.07</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>No helper</td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.06</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Stress 1</td>
<td>0.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>Stress 2</td>
<td>0.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>Stress 3</td>
<td>0.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.73<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>Stress 4</td>
<td>0.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>Supportive</td>
<td>0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">**</xref></td>
<td>0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>Frequent calls</td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>Missing days</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>Less energy</td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">**</xref></td>
<td>0.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">**</xref></td>
<td>0.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>Worry</td>
<td>0.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">**</xref></td>
<td>0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>Dissatisfaction</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">*</xref></td>
<td>0.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0733464811423647">***</xref></td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Mean</td>
<td>0.99</td>
<td>4.15</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>36.7</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>1.82</td>
<td>1.85</td>
<td>1.78</td>
<td>1.45</td>
<td>0.77</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><italic>SD</italic></td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>5.34</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>0.45</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.81</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>0.23</td>
<td>0.45</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>0.30</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0733464811423647">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Disruptive behavior = total number of disruptive behaviors of a care recipient, CGPoorHealth = caregivers’ poor health status, CGWorkHour = number of hours caregivers are employed per week, No helper = caregivers’ back-up support, Stress 1 = exhausted, Stress 2 =more to do than can handle, Stress 3 = no time for self, Stress 4 = work hard, no progress, Supportive = employers’ support at the workplace, Frequent calls = frequent calls from a care recipient, Missing days = Missing days by caregiving, Less energy = less energy at the work place, Worry = worry about a care recipient at work, Dissatisfaction = dissatisfied with the quality of work.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0733464811423647">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0733464811423647">
<title>Structural Equation Models</title>
<p>After the confirmatory factor analysis confirmed a relationship between the observed variables and latent constructs (RMSEA = .033, NFI = .99, CFI = 1.0, GFI = .91, and χ<sup>2</sup> (<italic>df</italic> = 24) = 39.49 with <italic>p</italic> = .024; not shown here), we tested the overall hypothesized model. The results of the structural equation parameter estimation, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0733464811423647">Figure 2</xref>, show the standardized path coefficients representing the relationships among employed caregivers’ demands, employed caregivers’ stress, work interruptions, and work performance appraisal. Coefficients are standardized betas, or standardized lambdas. The fit indices provide strong support for the hypothesized model: NFI = .96, CFI = .98, GFI = .96, RMSEA = .047 and χ<sup>2</sup> (<italic>df</italic> = 67) = 151.67 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0733464811423647" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of structural equation modeling for all employed caregivers.</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Coefficients are standardized betas, or standardized lambdas. All the paths in solid lines are statistically significant at *<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05, **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, or ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 while dotted lines are not statistically significant.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0733464811423647-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0733464811423647">
<title>The Effects of Employed Caregivers’ Demands on Caregiving Stress</title>
<p>With regard to the first hypothesis concerning the relationship between employed caregivers’ demands and their caregiving stress, two of the caregiver demands (i.e., caregivers’ working hours and care recipients’ impairment) are significantly associated with employed caregivers’ stress. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0733464811423647">Figure 2</xref>, care recipients’ impairment is positively associated (β = .77, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) with employed caregivers’ stress. Caregivers who work more hours are more likely to have higher levels of stress than those who work fewer hours (β = .11, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). The effects of having a back-up helper and the caregivers’ health status on their stress levels are not statistically significant. Therefore, the first hypothesis is partially supported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0733464811423647">
<title>The Mediating Effects of Work Interruptions</title>
<p>The second hypothesis concerning the mediating effects of work interruptions between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal is also supported. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0733464811423647">Figure 2</xref>, although the direct effect of employed caregivers’ stress on work performance appraisal is not statistically significant (β = –.16, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05), the indirect effect through work interruptions is statistically significant (β = –.52, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, not shown here). This indirect effect is computed by multiplying the standardized effect (β = .66, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) of employed caregivers’ stress on work interruptions by the standardized effect (β = –.79, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) of employed caregivers’ stress on work performance appraisal.</p>
<p>The finding that the indirect effect is statistically significant indicates that work interruptions mediate the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal. Specifically, when employed caregivers experience stress, they tend to have more work interruptions and when work interruptions increase, employed caregivers’ work performance appraisals tend to decrease.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0733464811423647">
<title>The Moderating Effects of Supportive Employers</title>
<p>We used a multigroup invariance procedure to test the third and fourth hypotheses that focus on the moderating effect of supportive employers. Due to missing data in 22 cases with regard to supportiveness of employer, the total sample size for the analysis was 620. After fitting the model for the total sample, as described above, we conducted two subgroup analyses using the same model. One is for employed caregivers with a supportive employer (<italic>N</italic> = 478) and the other for employed caregivers without a supportive employer (<italic>N</italic> = 142).</p>
<p>To determine whether the relationships among employed caregivers’ stress, work interruptions, and work performance appraisal are significantly different across the two groups, we conducted the chi-square difference test by comparing the constrained model to the model without constraints. The constrained model across the two groups results in the following fit indices: NFI = .93, CFI = .97, GFI = .86, RMSEA = .047 and χ<sup>2</sup> (<italic>df</italic> = 172) = 280.38 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). Allowing the paths among the three latent constructs to be free, while constraining the remaining paths and factor loadings to be equal across the two groups, results in a good fit (NFI = .93, CFI = .97, GFI = .96, RMSEA = .045 and χ<sup>2</sup> (<italic>df</italic> = 169) = 269.041 with <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). When the model without the constraints is compared with the constrained model, we find that the difference in χ<sup>2</sup> is significant, Δχ<sup>2</sup> (3) =11.34 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). The results show that the path coefficients among the three latent variables (employed caregivers’ stress, work interruptions, and work performance appraisal) are significantly different across the two groups (i.e., employed caregivers with a supportive employer and employed caregivers without a supportive employer).</p>
<p>Thus, the third hypothesis which focuses on the moderating role of supportive employers on the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and work interruptions and between work interruptions and work performance appraisal is supported. Specifically, the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work interruptions is significantly stronger for employed caregivers with supportive employers (β = .68, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) than for employed caregivers without supportive employers (β = .30, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0733464811423647">Figure 3</xref>. This finding indicates that employed caregivers with supportive employers are more likely than those without supportive employers to miss days, make frequent calls, and to worry about care recipients at work when their stress increases.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0733464811423647" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of structural equation modeling by two subgroups: Employed caregivers with supportive employers versus without supportive employers.</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Coefficients are standardized. All the paths in solid lines are statistically significant at *<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05, **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, or ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 while dotted lines are not statistically significant. Numbers without parentheses indicate standardized coefficients of employed caregivers with supportive employers while numbers within parentheses indicate standardized coefficients of employed caregivers without supportive employers. Factor loadings between observed variables and latent constructs are constrained to be equal across groups; therefore, the rest of the model is omitted in this figure.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0733464811423647-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>The fourth hypothesis pertaining to the moderating role of supportive employers on the relationship between work interruptions and work performance appraisal is also supported. That is, the negative relationship between employed caregivers’ work interruptions and their work performance appraisal is weaker for employed caregivers with supportive employers (β <italic>=</italic> –.73, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) than for employed caregivers without supportive employers (β = –.91, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). This finding indicates that support from employers (i.e., understanding the demands of the employee’s caregiving situation) is associated with a reduction in the negative effects of work interruptions on employed caregivers’ appraisals of their work performance.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section20-0733464811423647" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our study confirms the utility of our model that expanded the conceptual framework developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal and colleagues (1993)</xref>. By building on their previous work, this research highlights the pathways between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal. We found that poorer health of care recipients and more hours of work are related to employed caregivers’ stress. These results show that employed caregivers’ demands are predictors of their stress. Specifically, consistent with previous studies, the demands associated with caregivers stress were care recipients’ impairments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0733464811423647">Lee et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0733464811423647">Starrels et al., 1997</xref>) and caregivers’ hours of work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0733464811423647">Neal et al., 1993</xref>). Furthermore, employed caregivers’ stress is indirectly related to their work performance appraisal through their experiences of work interruptions. That is, stress is associated with work interruptions which, in turn, are related to poorer work performance appraisal. In addition, we found that the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal is also associated with an employer’s informal support.</p>
<p>One of our key findings is that work interruptions play an important role in the relationship between employed caregivers’ stress and their work performance appraisal. Although we hypothesized that employed caregivers’ stress would have both a direct and an indirect effect on their work performance appraisal, only the indirect effect was statistically significant. This means that work interruptions play a critical role in mediating the relationship between stress and work performance appraisal. The high level of employed caregivers’ stress is associated with work interruptions which, in turn, are related to their poor work performance appraisal. Whereas others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0733464811423647">Reid, Stajduhar, &amp; Chappell, 2010</xref>) have identified work interruptions as common among employed caregivers, our work has taken this finding a step further. Specifically, we find that work interruptions contribute to employees’ feeling that their work is inadequate. Taken together, work interruptions appear to be a key mechanism for explaining how employed caregivers’ stress is associated with their work performance appraisal.</p>
<p>A second key finding is that employers play a role in helping employees adapt to their dual caregiving and work responsibilities. Consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0733464811423647">Eaton (1999)</xref>, these results demonstrate that when employed caregivers feel understood by employers, the employed caregivers are more likely to interrupt their work to address caregiving responsibilities. This study finding suggests that employees feel more free to interrupt their work (e.g., to take time off to meet their caregiving obligations) if their employers or supervisors understand the demands of their elder caregiving situation. It may be that when employers are supportive of employees’ caregiving responsibilities, employed caregivers anticipate fewer penalties if they attend to these responsibilities while at work and are therefore more likely to interrupt their work to focus on caregiving.</p>
<p>Another significant discovery is that when employers understand employees’ elder caregiving situations, employees are less likely to feel that their caregiving-related work interruptions are negatively related to their work performance. This finding along with those of other researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0733464811423647">Allen, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0733464811423647">Eaton, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0733464811423647">Thompson et al., 1999</xref>) highlights the potential impact of informal support in the workplace on work performance. It is possible that the negative effects of work interruptions on work performance are mitigated by the positive effects of supportiveness of employers or supervisors on employees’ job commitment and job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0733464811423647">Thomas &amp; Ganster, 1995</xref>). Furthermore, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0733464811423647">Eaton (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0733464811423647">Hill, Hawkins, Ferris, &amp; Weitzman (2001)</xref> suggested, support from employers increases the flexibility and autonomy of employed caregivers at the workplace and ultimately improves their productivity, thereby diminishing the negative effects of work interruptions on work performance.</p>
<p>Our study has implications for the workplace. It is important that employers understand the caregiving responsibilities of their employees and that they convey support to them. Feeling supported by their employers is associated, as we found, with employees feeling less self-critical about their work performance when they were interrupted at work due to caregiving. Our findings suggest that workplace training for supervisors should include a component focused on how to deal with employees who have caregiving responsibilities. When employers and supervisors understand the circumstances surrounding employees’ caregiving responsibilities at an early stage, they may be able to diminish the adverse effects of work interruptions by providing caregivers with resources in advance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0733464811423647">Mennino et al., 2005</xref>). In so doing, supportive employers and supervisors may be able to help employees with caregiving responsibilities to find ways of accommodating their work situations so that they can better balance their work and eldercare responsibilities and lessen the negative effects of work interruptions on work performance. In addition, this kind of support can make it possible for employers to retain employed caregivers in the long term and reduce management and administrative costs related to hiring new employees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0733464811423647">MetLife Mature Market Institute &amp; National Alliance for Caregiving, 2006</xref>). It may be that informal support at work, such as family supportive employers, benefits not only employed caregivers but also the employers.</p>
<p>Despite the important findings described above, our research is subject to several limitations. One limitation is that our analyses are based on cross-sectional data. Longitudinal research would allow for a clearer picture of causal relationships, and a more careful exploration of the relationships over time among eldercare responsibilities, caregivers’ stress, work interruptions, and work performance. Future research should examine the long-term impact of informal support from employers. It may be, for example, that when employers understand and provide support for their employees’ caregiving responsibilities in the short run, their employees’ work performance will actually increase over time, especially when caregiving responsibilities diminish.</p>
<p>In terms of measurement, our study also has some limitations. First, the measure of informal employer support was only a single item indicator. Although single item measures of informal support are not uncommon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0733464811423647">Behson, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0733464811423647">Mennino et al., 2005</xref>), they may not tap into the multiple ways in which employers can be supportive. Follow-up research on informal employer support should use multi-item measures. Furthermore, one of the measures of work interruptions (i.e., “you missed too many days”) was not specifically related to eldercare. Future research should include eldercare-specific measures of work interruptions. In addition, this study relied on self-reported measures to conceptualize work interruptions and job performance. The respondents may have been reluctant to acknowledge the extent to which they actually experienced work interruptions related to their eldercare or they may have overrated their work performance. For this reason, it would be helpful for future research to incorporate measures of work interruptions and work performance that are provided by supervisors and employers.</p>
<p>Another limitation is that our model focused only on one source of support in the workplace; that is, informal support from an employer. Formal support such as flexible work policies, benefits, and services can diminish difficulties in balancing work and caregiving (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0733464811423647">Neal &amp; Hammer, 2007</xref>) and may also influence work interruptions and performance. As the conceptual framework used in this study is further refined and tested, researchers should include formal as well as informal support in the model.</p>
<p>Last, it is important to note that this research was limited to employed caregivers of people aged 65 and above. In so doing, we excluded a large proportion of employees who cared for adults who were younger as well as those who cared for children with disabilities. We also did not consider variations in job type when examining the relationships among employer support, work interruptions, and work performance appraisal of employed caregivers. It is quite possible that the effects of supportive employers may vary by job type. For example, blue-collar employed caregivers may have different kinds of relationships with their employers and may interrupt their work in ways that differ from white-collar employed caregivers. Further research on employed caregivers should incorporate the broader population of caregivers and consider variations in the types of jobs that they hold.</p>
<p>In conclusion, this study contributes to a greater understanding of the dynamics that occur between caregiver stress and work performance. In particular, we highlight the role played by informal support from employers. As more employees are expected to have caregiving responsibilities in the near future, the role of a supportive employer is crucial in helping employed caregivers balance work and eldercare roles and in enhancing their work performance. Our findings point to the importance of helping employers and supervisors to understand and support employees’ eldercare situations. We urge other gerontological researchers to focus on the ways in which family friendly environments can influence employees who are balancing work and eldercare responsibilities.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><label>Funding</label><p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research was supported by a National Institute on Aging (NIA) Fellowship (T32-AG000117).</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Jeungkun Kim</bold>, PhD, is a research fellow at the Samsung Economic Research Institute. His research interests include work and retirement, employed caregivers, and social welfare policy for older adults.</p>
<p><bold>Berit Ingersoll-Dayton</bold>, PhD, is a professor at the University of Michigan School of Social Work and Director of the Joint Doctoral Program in Social Work and Social Science. Her research focuses on social support and clinical research with respect to families in later life.</p>
<p><bold>Minyoung Kwak</bold> is a doctoral candidate in social work and sociology at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Her research focuses on family caregiving for older adults and the relationship between the receipt of informal care and mental health among older adults.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Family-supportive work environments: The role of organizational perspectives</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M. A. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Social interactions at work and the well-being of daughters involved in parent care</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Azarnoff</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scharlach</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Can employees carry the eldercare burden?</article-title> <source>Personnel Journal</source>, <volume>67</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Behson</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The relative contribution of formal and informal organizational work-family support</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>-<lpage>500</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Comparative fit indexes in structural models</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>-<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonett</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Significance tests and goodness of fit in the analysis of covariance structures</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>588</fpage>-<lpage>606</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Structural equations with latent variables</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galinsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanberg</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The 1997 national study of the changing workforce</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Families and Work Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breaugh</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Work-family conflict: The importance of family-friendly employment practices and family-supportive supervisors</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business and Psychology</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>-<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cudeck</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Alternative ways of assessing model fit</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Testing structural equation models</source> (pp. <fpage>136</fpage>-<lpage>162</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Development of a typology of dual earner couples caring for children and aging parents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Issues</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>458</fpage>-<lpage>483</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Surprising opportunities: Gender and the structure of work in biotechnology firms</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>869</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>If you can use them: Flexibility policies, organizational commitment, and perceived performance</article-title>. <source>Industrial Relations</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eby</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bordeaux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brinley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Work and family research in IO/OB: Content analysis and review of the literature (1980-2002)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>124</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelloway</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraboni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Aspects of elder care that place employees at risk</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>815</fpage>-<lpage>821</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Camilli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elmore</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Handbook of complementary methods in education research</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tatham</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Multivariate data analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>T. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grandey</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Work-family conflict and work-related withdrawal behaviors</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business and Psychology</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>436</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colton</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caubet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brockwood</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The unbalanced life: Work and family conflict</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hersen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of mental health in the workplace</source> (pp. <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weitzman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Finding an extra day a week: The positive influence of perceived job flexibility on work and family life balance</article-title>. <source>Family Relations</source>, <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingersoll-Dayton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raschick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The relationship between care-recipient behaviors and spousal caregiving stress</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>318</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jöreskog</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sörbom</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>LISREL 8: Structural equation modeling with the SIMPLIS command language</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jöreskog</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sörbom</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>PRELIS2: User’s reference guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Lincolnwood, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scientific Software</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Principles and practice of structural equation modeling</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kossek</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Workplace policies and practices to support work and families</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Work, family health and well-being</source> (pp. <fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kossek</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nichol</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The effects of on-site child care on employee attitudes and performance</article-title>. <source>Personnel Psychology</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>-<lpage>509</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kipnis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Eldercare and work-role conflict: Toward an understanding of gender differences in caregiver burden</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>340</fpage>-<lpage>348</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Anticipated support, received support, and economic stress among older adults</article-title>. <source>Journal of Gerontology: Series B Psychological sciences and social sciences</source>, <volume>52B</volume>, <fpage>P284</fpage>-<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kleban</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rovine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A two-factor model of caregiving appraisal and psychological well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Gerontology: Psychological Sciences</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>189</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Employed caregivers: A four-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>102</fpage>-<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lecovich</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Caregiving burden, community services, and quality of life of primary caregivers of frail elderly persons</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shoup</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Balancing elder care responsibilities and work: The impact on emotional health</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business and Psychology</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lobel</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kossek</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Human resource strategies to support diversity in work and personal lifestyles: Beyond the “family friendly” organization</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kossek</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lobel</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Managing diversity: Human resource strategies for transforming the workplace</source> (pp. <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>243</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Introduction to statistical mediation analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meiner</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lueckenotte</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Gerontologic nursing</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mennino</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brayﬁeld</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Home-to-job and job-to-home spillover: The impact of company policies and workplace culture</article-title>. <source>Sociological Quarterly</source>, <volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mesemer-Eagnus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viswesvaran</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>How family-friendly work environments affect work/family conflict: A meta-analytic examination</article-title>. <source>Journal of Labor Research</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>555</fpage>-<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>MetLife Mature Market Institute &amp; National Alliance for Caregiving</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>The MetLife Caregiving Cost Study: Productivity losses to U.S. business</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pascenter.org/frames/pas_frame.php?site=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.caregiving.org%2Fpubs%2Fdata.htm">http://www.pascenter.org/frames/pas_frame.php?site=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.caregiving.org%2Fpubs%2Fdata.htm</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Is your family wrecking your career?</article-title> <source>Fortune</source>, <volume>135</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mui</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrow-Howell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Sources of emotional strain among the oldest caregivers</article-title>. <source>Research on Aging</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ingersoll-Dayton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Emlen</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Balancing work and caregiving for children, adults, and elders</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Working couples caring for children and aging parents: Effects on work and well-being</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Working caregivers: Issues, challenges, and opportunities for the aging network</article-title>. <source>NFCSP Issue Brief</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.caregiverslibrary.org/Portals/0/Working%20Caregivers%20-%20Issues%20for%20the%20Aging%20Network%20Fin-Neal-Wagner.pdf">http://www.caregiverslibrary.org/Portals/0/Working%20Caregivers%20-%20Issues%20for%20the%20Aging%20Network%20Fin-Neal-Wagner.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Live longer, work longer</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris, France</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>OECD</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearlin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mullan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Semple</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skaff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Caregiving and the stress process: An overview of concepts and their measures</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>-<lpage>594</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinquart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Differences between caregivers and noncaregivers in psychological health and physical health: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychology and Aging</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>250</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Churilla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An examination of full-time employment in the direct-care workforce</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>356</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stajduhar</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The impact of work interferences on family caregiver outcomes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Riggle</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edmondson</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A meta-analysis of the relationship between perceived organizational support and job outcomes: 20 years of research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>1027</fpage>-<lpage>1030</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sahibzada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The moderating effects of work-family role combinations and work-family organizational culture on the relationship between family-friendly workplace supports and job satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Issues</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>820</fpage>-<lpage>839</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scharlach</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Caregiving and employment: Results of an employee survey</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>-<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scharlach</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Elder care and the work force: Blueprint for action</source>. <publisher-loc>Lexington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bookwala</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleissner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Psychiatric and physical morbidity effects of dementia caregiving: Prevalence, correlates, and causes</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>771</fpage>-<lpage>791</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The impact of multiple care giving roles on fatigue, stress, and work performance among hospital staff nurses</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nursing Administration</source>, <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Eldercare and job productivity: An accommodation analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leadership Studies</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shoptaugh</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Visio</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Employee eldercare responsibilities: Should organizations care?</article-title> <source>Journal of Business and Psychology</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Starrels</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ingersoll-Dayton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dowler</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The stress of caring for a parent: Effects of the elder’s impairment on an employed adult child</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and the Family</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>860</fpage>-<lpage>872</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steiger</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Structural model evaluation and modification: An interval estimation approach</article-title>. <source>Multivariate Behavioral Research</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Informal care of the elderly</source>. <publisher-loc>Lexington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sterns</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czaja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Issues in work and aging</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>“ How big is big enough?” Sample size and goodness of fit in structural equation models with latent variables</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>134</fpage>-<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thoits</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Stress, coping, and social support processes: Where are we? What next?</article-title> <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ganster</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Impact of family-supportive work variables on work-family conflict and strain: A control perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beauvais</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyness</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>When work-family benefits are not enough: The influence of work-family culture on benefit utilization, organizational attachment, and work-family conflict</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>392</fpage>-<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Caregiving and work: Consequences, correlates, and workplace responses</article-title>. <source>Educational Gerontology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>654</fpage>-<lpage>663</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0733464811423647">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wethington</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Perceived support, received support, and adjustment to stressful life events</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>