<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spiss</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0268-5809</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7242</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0268580912452374a</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0268580912452374a</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews: Sociology of culture</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Marc L Moskowitz (ed.), <italic>Popular Culture in Taiwan: Charismatic Modernity</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Akinwale</surname><given-names>Akeem Ayofe</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0268580912452374">University of Lagos, Nigeria</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>680</fpage>
<lpage>682</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>Marc L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.), <source>Popular Culture in Taiwan: Charismatic Modernity</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>; <page-count count="xi"/> + <page-count count="187"/> pp.: ISBN <isbn>9780415582636</isbn>, <price>US$130.00</price></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Modernity</kwd>
<kwd>popular culture</kwd>
<kwd>Taiwan</kwd>
<kwd>Taiwanese culture</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Marc Moskowitz’s edited book depicts the dynamic lifestyles and cultural production in Taiwan. The contributors to the book jointly expand the frontiers of knowledge on cultural studies through a critical analysis of the dynamics of cultures in the light of Taiwan’s experience from the seventeenth to the twenty-first century. The book is based on the 2008 Conference on Charismatic Modernity and Popular Culture in Taiwan. The conference was sponsored by the Taiwan Economic and Cultural Office (TECO). Beyond the introductory chapter written by Marc Moskowitz, the book comprises two parts. The first part comprises four chapters (2–5) dealing with historical contexts of the development of popular culture in Taiwan. The second part likewise comprises four chapters (6–9), which focus on the influence of technological development on popular culture in Taiwan.</p>
<p>All nine chapters of the book dwell on social change and development of hybrid cultures in Taiwan. The chapters are written by experienced authors from diverse disciplines such as anthropology, sociology, literature and history. The book is thus based on a multidisciplinary perspective. Chapter 1 introduces the main focus of the book, showing the origin and development of various dimensions of popular culture in Taiwan. This chapter also introduces the matrix of external influences which characterize the Taiwanese society from its colonization by the Dutch East India Company in 1624 to 1661 when it was recolonized by a pirate of mixed Japanese and Chinese descent. Moskowitz shows that Taiwan remained a Chinese territory till 1895, although Japan also subjugated it for 50 years (1895–1945).</p>
<p>In Chapter 2, Andrew Morris contextualizes popular culture in the light of collective identification with baseball and the controversy over the ownership of the culture of baseball in Taiwan. Morris explains the development of the Taiwanese culture of baseball from its origin during the course of the Japanese colonialism and the attempt made by the KMT to situate baseball within the ambit of the Chinese heritage. The author of Chapter 3, Krista van Fleit Hang, dwells on the Taiwanese pathways to industrialization based on her literary description of the Taiwanese experience of transition from agricultural to industrial society. Hang questions the observed discrepancy between the Taiwanese literature and the Chinese literature.</p>
<p>Chapter 4 is based on Joseph Allen’s observation of the reflection of classical Chinese poetry in Taiwanese popular culture. This chapter focuses on social construction of Chinese language and its dissemination and modifications by various groups of people in Taiwan. In Chapter 5, Allen Chun examines the coexistence of modernity and traditionalism in the Taiwanese pop music industry. Chun begins with an analysis of pop music culture in Asia and then situates his analysis in the light of paradoxical situations in the development of the International Community Radio Taipei (ICRT) in a changing Taiwan where people can consume foreign music without the benefit of foreign language media or affinity to foreign culture.</p>
<p>In Chapter 6, Anru Lee and Chien-hung Tung dwell on the modernization of transport technology and its implications for urban culture and social life in Taiwan. They focus on people’s experience of change following the development of subways and high speed railways. They equally discuss the general satisfaction with efficient operations of the Taipei Mass Rapid Transit (TMRT) and the high speed rail system. As shown by Lucia Huwy-min Liu, Chapter 7 deals with the increasing popularity and persistence of betel nut consumption with reference to the experience of modernity in Taiwan. She describes the nature of betel nut and the socioeconomic and cultural factors that reinforce its continued consumption in the context of masculinity and class.</p>
<p>In Chapter 8, Teri Silvio explores the youth culture of sexuality from the narratives of Boys Love (BL) exemplified by women’s reactions to the aesthetics of the Pili International Multimedia Company’s puppetry fan fiction. She describes a wide range of activities among Pili fans in video clubs and online discussion groups. Apart from his editorial comments in Chapter 1, Marc Moskowitz also writes Chapter 9, which depicts the reading culture and translation of foreign novels into indigenous languages in Taiwan. He dwells on people’s obsession with the Harry Porter series and their identification with characters in the novel. He links the plot in the novel with some aspects of Taiwanese culture, especially the use of the work ethic in a bid to ensure prosperity.</p>
<p>Marc Moskowitz’s edited book is well written and it deals with a relevant subject examined from a multidisciplinary perspective. Moskowitz neatly combines the various approaches used by different authors in their writings on popular culture in Taiwan, showing the diversity of popular culture in Taiwan as demonstrated in the book. The authors give considerable attention to various dimensions of popular culture in Taiwan, including baseball, music, literature, poetry, novels, betel nut, video clubs, online discussion groups and transportation. All nine authors recognize the beauty of Taiwan and the resilience of the Taiwanese in terms of their ability to promote their traditional culture despite their long history of colonialism and exposure to external influences.</p>
<p>The book equally shows a general admiration for modernity following the socioeconomic and political transformation of Taiwan since the 1980s. The Taiwanese admiration is reflected in the forward and backward linkages from Taipei to other parts of Taiwan and elsewhere. In the words of Moskowitz, Taipei has become a central stage for the exhibition of Taiwan’s mass mediated cultural production. Taipei is equated with American cities such as Los Angeles, New York and Washington DC. It is also noted that the rest of Taiwan is hooked to Taipei for television, music, art and fashion in a bid to create new meaningful lifestyles.</p>
<p>The Taiwanese experience of popular culture symbolizes unity in diversity showing an amalgamation of foreign and local cultures. This is evidenced by the use of multiple languages in Taiwan’s public sphere. The dominant languages in Taiwan include Mandarin Chinese, English, Hokklo and Hakka. The book also depicts the use of other languages such as Japanese, Korean, German, Thai, Vietnamese, French, Spanish, Indonesian and Malaysian. The discussion of cooperation among the various linguistic communities in Taiwan reinforces the coexistence of local and foreign languages in the country. In fact, Moskowitz notes that ‘popular culture in Taiwan is in many ways a merging of Chinese, Japanese, American, and indigenous cultures, among others, and is therefore a form of hybridity that arose long before the term became popular’ (p. 7).</p>
<p>The book suggests that Taiwan has clearly emerged as a melting pot of popular cultures reinforced by the geometry of Chinese and Japanese hegemony as well as American influence. It equally shows the dynamics of non-western colonialism and its implications for an understanding of continuity and change in the use of indigenous cultures. This appears in Liu’s description of continuity in the tradition of betel nut consumption in an environment characterized by rapid social change. Lee and Tung also observe that the development of the high speed railway system in Taiwan cannot be divorced from the Japanese Shinkansen technologies.</p>
<p>The book is quite interesting; it is to be recommended for students of the social sciences and humanities as well as general readers with an interest in cultural studies and development in Asia.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Akeem Ayofe Akinwale</bold> is Senior Lecturer in the Department of Industrial Relations and Personnel Management, Faculty of Business Administration, University of Lagos, Akoka, Yaba, Lagos State, Nigeria. He has authored 42 publications including books and articles in reputable journals. His areas of research include industrial sociology and development studies. He is a member of the International Sociological Association (ISA) as well as the Council for the Development of Social Science Research in Africa (CODESRIA). Address: Department of Industrial Relations and Personnel Management, Faculty of Business Administration, University of Lagos, Akoka, Yaba, Lagos State, Nigeria. Email: <email>akinwale.akeem@yahoo.com</email></p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>