<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="introduction" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Research Studies in Music Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1321-103X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1864-5530</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1321103X13488485</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1321103X13488485</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Perspectives in Music Education</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Introduction: Perspectives on the power of music</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1321103X13488485">University of London, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>Raymond</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1321103X13488485">University of Edinburgh, UK</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1321103X13488485">Susan Hallam, Institute of Education, University of London, 20 Bedford Way, London WC1H 0AL, UK. Email: <email>S.Hallam@ioe.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<lpage>86</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SEMPRE</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>All kinds of music are now available to most people, 24 hours every day, at the touch of a switch. Over many years, research has demonstrated that music is a very powerful medium and influences many human behaviours and activities. In some societies, this has been recognized and attempts are made to control or ban music by those in power. Music is powerful at the level of the social group because it facilitates communication which goes beyond words, induces shared emotional reactions and supports the development of group identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1321103X13488485">Miell, MacDonald, &amp; Hargreaves, 2005</xref>). It is powerful at the individual level because it can induce multiple responses – physiological, mood, emotional, cognitive and behavioural (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1321103X13488485">Clayton, 2009</xref>). Few other stimuli have effects on such a wide range of human functions. Despite this, it is difficult to predict specific individual responses to music as musical preferences play an important role in our emotional and behavioural responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1321103X13488485">Pothoulaki, MacDonald, &amp; Flowers, 2008</xref>). Despite this, we know that music has powerful therapeutic effects which can be achieved through listening or active music making (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1321103X13488485">Hurt-Thaut, 2009</xref>). It can promote relaxation, alleviate anxiety and pain, promote appropriate behaviour in vulnerable groups and enhance the quality of life of those who are beyond medical help (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1321103X13488485">MacDonald, Kreutz, &amp; Mitchell, 2012</xref>). People can and do use music in their lives to manipulate their moods, alleviate the boredom of tedious tasks and create environments appropriate for particular social events. The easy availability of music in everyday life has encouraged individuals to use music to optimize their sense of well-being (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1321103X13488485">Sloboda, Lamont, &amp; Greasley, 2009</xref>). It is important to point out that as individual listeners we are all aware of the powerful effects of music. For example, when selecting music to listen to in any particular situation, a number of sophisticated and highly nuanced psychological assessments are made in an instant. This type of assessment may include questions such as: How do I feel right now? How do I want to feel in five minutes or one hour and what music will help me achieve this goal? Is anybody else listening and what will they think?</p>
<p>There has also been considerable research on the way that active engagement with music can enhance a range of skills in children and young people. The development of technologies which have facilitated our study of the brain have increased our understanding of the way that active engagement with music influences other skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1321103X13488485">Altenmuller &amp; Schlaug, 2012</xref>). Although our knowledge of the way the brain works is still in its infancy, some of the fundamental processes involved in learning have been established. We now know that the cerebral cortex changes in specific ways as we engage with a range of activities including music. The changes brought about through participation in music have been shown to enhance other skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1321103X13488485">Pantev, Engelien, Candia, &amp; Elbert, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Speech and music have a number of shared processing systems. Musical experiences which enhance aural perception can therefore sharpen the brain’s early encoding of linguistic sound. Children with quite short periods of musical training have shown improvement in perceptual aural skills compared with those without training. As a result, children as young as 8 years old, who have had musical training, outperform those without training on musical and language tests. Learning to read music seems to transfer to improved phonemic awareness, which contributes to the development of literacy skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1321103X13488485">Magne, Schon, &amp; Besson, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Research exploring the relationships between mathematics and active musical engagement has had mixed results, in part, because not all mathematics tasks share underlying processes with those involved in music. Transfer is dependent on the extent of the match; for instance, children receiving instruction on rhythm instruments score higher on part–whole maths problems than those receiving piano and singing instruction (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1321103X13488485">Hallam, 2010</xref>) .</p>
<p>Learning an instrument has an impact on intellectual development, particularly spatial reasoning. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1321103X13488485">Hetland (2000)</xref> in a review found a “strong and reliable” relationship, the author likening the differences to one inch in height or about 84 points on standardized school tests. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1321103X13488485">Schellenberg (2004)</xref> contrasted the impact of standard keyboard or Kodaly music lessons with drama tuition or no lessons and found that the music groups had reliably larger increases in IQ. In all but two of the 12 subtests, the music group had larger increases than control groups. Over time it has been noted that there has been a consistent relationship between active engagement in music and general attainment. However, it has not been possible to assert that participating in musical activities is the cause of the higher achievement as there are many confounding factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1321103X13488485">Costa-Giomi, 2012</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1321103X13488485">Southgate and Roscigno (2009)</xref>, adopting more sensitive statistical modeling, were able to overcome these difficulties. Two nationally-representative data sources with data from over 45,000 children found that associations between music and achievement persisted even when prior attainment was taken into account. Measured creativity is also enhanced by participation in music, particularly when the musical activity itself is creative, for instance, improvisation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1321103X13488485">Koutsoupidou &amp; Hargreaves, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The impact of music participation on general attainment may result from its impact on personal and social development. Playing an instrument can lead to a sense of achievement, an increase in self-esteem, increased confidence, persistence in overcoming frustrations when learning is difficult, self-discipline and can provide a means of self-expression. These positive benefits may increase motivation for learning in general, thus supporting enhanced attainment (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1321103X13488485">Hallam, 2010</xref>, for a review). There are a range of social benefits which can develop through participating in musical groups. Being in an orchestra, band, choir or other type of group promotes friendships with like-minded people, and a wide range of social and personal skills in addition to providing an outlet for relaxation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1321103X13488485">Kokotsaki &amp; Hallam, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Adolescents spend many hours each week listening to music. The type of music that they listen to makes a major contribution to the development of self-identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1321103X13488485">MacDonald, Hargreaves, &amp; Miell, 2009</xref>) and is seen as a source of support when young people are feeling troubled or lonely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1321103X13488485">Zillman &amp; Gan, 1997</xref>). Music also has the capacity to increase emotional sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1321103X13488485">Västfjäll, Juslin, &amp; Hartig, 2012</xref>). The recognition of emotions as expressed in music is linked to measured emotional intelligence, the capacity to understand one’s own emotions and those of others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1321103X13488485">Resnicow, Salovey, &amp; Repp, 2004</xref>). Increasing the amount of classroom music within the curriculum can increase social cohesion within class and lead to greater self-reliance, better social adjustment and more positive attitudes, particularly in low ability, disaffected pupils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1321103X13488485">Spychiger, Patry, Lauper, Zimmerman, &amp; Weber, 1993</xref>). However, the positive effects of actively participating in music making on personal and social development will only occur if, overall, it is an enjoyable and rewarding experience. The quality of the teaching, the extent to which individuals perceive that they are successful, and whether in the long term it is a positive experience determine the extent of the benefits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1321103X13488485">Hallam, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>There is also a large industry concerned with the effects of music on workers and consumers. Music can influence our purchasing behaviour in subtle ways in a range of environments. It can assist our ability to remember product names and enhance the product through association with liked music. When consumers are actively involved in making a decision about buying a product, music is likely to play a more peripheral role (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1321103X13488485">North &amp; Hargreaves, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>As this brief summary indicates, music pervades our everyday lives and influences our behaviour to a great extent. Whether in a personal, social, consumer, educational or motivational context, there is clear and unequivocal evidence that music affects behaviour. This capacity of music to affect our behaviour has been harnessed in numerous contexts to change behaviours in beneficial ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1321103X13488485">Hallam &amp; MacDonald, 2009</xref>). The demand for music is likely to continue to increase in the future. To support our appetite for music, the music industries in the developed world constitute a major element of the economies of many countries. They are in danger of losing their skilled work force because of the extent to which music is taken for granted. This can lead to neglect in considering how the infrastructure supporting music and musicians is resourced, maintained and developed. This is particularly acute in times of austerity. There is therefore a need for ongoing research which raises awareness of the wider benefits of music. The articles included here form part of that work. Two focus on the wider benefits of music for older adults where increases in the ageing population are putting a strain on health and care resources, while the other considers the role of computer games in generating interest in engaging with music in young people with the benefits that this brings. The power of music derives from its universal and timeless potential to influence how we behave and how we feel and think. It is these qualities that underpin the important and ongoing research into the effects of music listening and participation.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Altenmuller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Music, brain and health: Exploring biological foundations of music’s health effect</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreutz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Music, health, and well-being</source> (pp. <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa-Giomi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Music instruction and children’s intellectual development: The educational context of music participation</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreutz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Music, health, and well-being</source> (pp. <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The social and personal functions of music in cross-cultural perspective</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Oxford handbook of music psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The power of music: Its impact on the intellectual, personal and social development of children and young people</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Music Education</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>).<article-title>The effects of music in educational and care settings</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Oxford Handbook of Music Psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hurt-Thaut</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Clinical practice in music therapy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Oxford handbook of music psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hetland</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Learning to make music enhances spatial reasoning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Aesthetic Education, 34</source>(<issue>3/4</issue>), <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kokotsaki</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The perceived benefits of participative music making for non-music university students: a comparison with music students</article-title>. <source>Music Education Research</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koutsoupidou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>An experimental study of the effects of improvisation on the development of children’s creative thinking in music</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Music</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Musical identities</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds), <source>Oxford handbook of music psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R. A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreutz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2012</year>). <source>Music, health and wellbeing</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Magne</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Besson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Musician children detect pitch violations in both music and language better than nonmusician children: Behavioural and electrophysiological approaches</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Miell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R. A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2005</year>). <source>Musical communication</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>North</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Music and consumer behaviour</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds), <source>Oxford handbook of music psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>490</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pantev</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engelien</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Candia</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elbert</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Representational cortex in musicians</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The cognitive neuroscience of music</source> (pp. <fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pothoulaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R. A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>An investigation of the effects of music on anxiety and pain perception in patients undergoing haemodialysis treatment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Psychology</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>912</fpage>–<lpage>920</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Resnicow</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salovey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Repp</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Is recognition of emotion in music performance an aspect of emotional intelligence</article-title>. <source>Music Perception</source>, <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellenberg</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Music lessons enhance IQ</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sloboda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamont</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greasley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Choosing to hear music: Motivation, process and effect</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Oxford handbook of music psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roscigno</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The impact of music on childhood and adolescent achievement</article-title>. <source>Social Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>90</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spychiger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lauper</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Does more music teaching lead to a better social climate</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Olechowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svik</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Experimental research in teaching and learning</source> (pp. <fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Bern, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Västfjäll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Juslin</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartig</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Music, subjective well-being, and health: The role of everyday emotions</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreutz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Music, health, and well-being</source> (pp. <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1321103X13488485">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zillman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Musical taste in adolescence</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>North</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The social psychology of music</source> (pp. <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>