<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MCR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmcr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Care Res Rev</journal-id>
<journal-title>Medical Care Research and Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-5587</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6801</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558712466293</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077558712466293</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Data and Trends</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Race and Ethnicity Data Quality and Imputation Using U.S. Census Data in an Integrated Health System</article-title>
<subtitle>The Kaiser Permanente Southern California Experience</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Derose</surname><given-names>Stephen F.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712466293">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712466293">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>Karen J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712466293">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Koebnick</surname><given-names>Corinna</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712466293">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>Steven J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712466293">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1077558712466293"><label>1</label>Kaiser Permanente Southern California, Pasadena, CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1077558712466293">Stephen F. Derose, Department of Research &amp; Evaluation, Kaiser Permanente Southern California, 100 South Los Robles, Floor 2, Pasadena, CA 91101, USA. Email: <email>stephen.f.derose@kp.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>70</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>330</fpage>
<lpage>345</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>31</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>27</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Research on racial and ethnic disparities using health system databases can shed light on the usual health care and outcomes of large numbers of individuals so that health inequities can be better understood and addressed. Such research often suffers from limitations in race/ethnicity data quality. We examined the quality of race/ethnicity data in a large, diverse, integrated health system that repeatedly collects these data on utilization of services. We tested the accuracy of Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding for imputation of race/ethnicity data. Administrative race/ethnicity data were accurate as judged by comparison with self-report in adults. The Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding method produced imputation results far better than chance assignment for the four most common race/ethnicity groups in the health system: Whites, Hispanics, Blacks, and Asians. These results support renewed efforts to conduct studies of racial and ethnic disparities in large health systems.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>race/ethnicity</kwd>
<kwd>disparities</kwd>
<kwd>imputation</kwd>
<kwd>integrated health systems</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Large health systems with electronic health records (EHRs) can contribute a wealth of information about health care utilization, treatment, and outcomes for people with a wide range of health conditions. When EHR are linked with other membership information, such as benefits and copayments, or combined with targeted data collection in prospective cohort studies, the opportunities expand. Such research relates directly to real populations, services, and the actual experience of patients in a way that complements clinical trials. When a question can be answered with clinically obtained data, large health systems may provide a more timely and cost-effective source of information than prospective cohort studies.</p>
<p>Among the many opportunities for research in large health systems with extensive EHR are studies of racial/ethnic variation in health and health care. In the United States, there are clear racial and ethnic disparities in the incidence and prevalence of chronic diseases, infant mortality, and life span (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1077558712466293">Institute of Medicine [IOM], 2009</xref>). Under conditions of equivalent and known health insurance benefits, a potential source of confounding between race/ethnicity and health outcomes can be minimized. Moreover, disparities can be examined in light of the clinical care experienced by patients. Further insights into the causes and remedies of disparities may be possible when national and community samples are compared with health systems.</p>
<p>Epidemiologic studies using EHR and that rely on individual-level race/ethnicity data face a common problem: A sizeable proportion of race/ethnicity data are missing for reasons that are not random. Moreover, the accuracy of existing data is often unclear. Research limited to persons with nonmissing data may produce results that are biased to an uncertain extent. As a result, research on race/ethnic differences within our own Kaiser Permanente health system often relies on survey data, is limited to nonmissing data, or uses imputation in cases where it is deemed accurate.</p>
<p>Self-report, as opposed to observation by another person, is the criterion standard for race/ethnicity data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1077558712466293">IOM, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1077558712466293">Hasnain-Wynia &amp; Baker, 2006</xref>). In large medical systems, however, race/ethnicity may be “assigned” to an individual patient by a health professional (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1077558712466293">Hasnain-Wynia &amp; Baker, 2006</xref>). When these data have been compared with self-reported race/ethnicity, the accuracy for ethnic minorities was poor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1077558712466293">Moscou, Anderson, Kaplan, &amp; Valencia, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1077558712466293">West et al., 2005</xref>). Until better methods to capture self-reported data are more fully developed, sufficiently accurate and generally applicable methods to identify race/ethnicity are needed to conduct research on pressing questions that only large EHR data may feasibly answer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1077558712466293">Hasnain-Wynia &amp; Baker, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1077558712466293">IOM, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Several methods have been developed to impute missing race/ethnicity data. These may include the use of geographic location (i.e., geocoding; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1077558712466293">Chen, Petitti, &amp; Enger, 2004</xref>), surname (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1077558712466293">Nasseri, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1077558712466293">Wei, Virnig, John, &amp; Morgan, 2006</xref>), language, or approaches using multiple sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott, Fremont, Morrison, Pantoja, &amp; Lurie, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1077558712466293">Fiscella &amp; Fremont, 2006</xref>). The Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding (BISG) method developed by Elliott et al. at RAND uses publicly available U. S. Census data, can be expanded to accommodate additional data (such as first name) to increase accuracy, and has shown promising results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>). The population used for BISG validation was from a national health insurance plan, which included primarily Whites, and the data were gathered on enrollment rather than utilization of services. It is not clear if similarly good prediction accuracy will be seen when researchers use this methodology in other settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1077558712466293">Fiscella &amp; Fremont, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>We hypothesized that data quality may be quite good in integrated health systems because these data are used not just for administrative purposes but also for ongoing clinical care. In such a setting, there are opportunities to correct errors during clinical care episodes. Moreover, standardized systems can be implemented to capture data by self-report on utilization of inpatient and outpatient services, as well as on enrollment. In this study, we examined the accuracy of race/ethnicity data available within a large integrated health system with significant racial and ethnic diversity and tested the accuracy of the BISG method of imputation for missing data. Such results within one health system may have limited generalizability, yet serve as an example of the potential for leveraging EHR data.</p>
<sec id="section1-1077558712466293">
<title>New Contribution</title>
<p>This research demonstrates the accuracy of race/ethnicity data available from integrated health systems using EHR and validates a published and generally applicable race/ethnicity imputation method in a large and diverse population. The completeness and accuracy of data and imputation open up new possibilities for disparities research in settings in which large, diverse populations have the same health care benefits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1077558712466293" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-1077558712466293">
<title>Setting</title>
<p>Kaiser Permanente Southern California (KPSC) is part of Kaiser Permanente, the nation’s largest not-for-profit health plan. KPSC is an integrated health system that provides comprehensive care at 14 medical centers and hundreds of clinics and service sites throughout Southern California. KPSC members comprise approximately 15% of the region’s population. KPSC has electronic health data, such as membership information, utilization, common laboratory tests, and pharmacy records, dating back about 20 years. Member race, ethnicity, and language data have been available for members using inpatient services and those on Medicare or Medicaid since the mid-1990s. KPSC in the past collected data on Hispanic as a separate race category but for about 10 years has collected Hispanic as a separate ethnicity category, allowing for comparison with U.S Census data. During 2006-2008, Kaiser Permanente converted to a comprehensive EHR that links medical records, utilization, and other administrative data. The EHR allowed for race/ethnicity data to be viewed, entered, or updated during any health care encounter. In 2008, processes were systematized for standardized collection of self-reported race/ethnicity on use of outpatient services. This systematization was completed in late 2010.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1077558712466293">
<title>Data Sources for Race/Ethnicity</title>
<p>Four main sources of health plan race/ethnicity data are used for research in KPSC. These sources are (a) utilization data collected at the time of service, which historically have been assigned by observation or self-report and are currently collected by self-report alone; these data can be corrected at subsequent visits; (b) enrollment data, which is self-reported; (c) preferred language for communication with health care providers, which is also self-reported on enrollment; Spanish is used to identify Hispanics and a list of Asian languages is used to identify Asians; and (d) birth certificate data for both mothers and infants when births occur at health plan hospitals; these data are largely self-reported by the mother. The race/ethnicity data available from these sources varies in terms of the populations represented and the accuracy of the data. When one or more sources disagree, self-reported race/ethnicity and official documents are given preference followed by other sources in order of estimated reliability. For this study, we created an administrative race/ethnicity file that combined the first three of the data sources above, which are obtained on enrollment and utilization of services. Birth certificate data were withheld for comparison, as described below.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1077558712466293">
<title>Implementation of BISG Imputation</title>
<p>We followed the BISG calculation steps described by Elliott et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1077558712466293">McCaffrey &amp; Elliott, 2008</xref>) and assigned individuals a set of probabilities for membership in each racial/ethnic group. In so doing, we used the U. S. Census data file that provides the distribution of self-reported race/ethnicity for common surnames in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>). The surname file provided a name match in 88.7% of health plan members. In no case was a health plan member missing a surname. We followed the BISG procedure of assigning the overall population distribution for uncommon surnames with no associated race/ethnicity data (about 20% of all surnames in the United States). We then used each person’s address of residence to determine their corresponding U. S. Census block group (an area containing about 1,000 persons). The race/ethnicity probability distributions for each block group were based on projections from Census 2000 to Year 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1077558712466293">Esri, 2012</xref>) to maximize accuracy for predicting our current membership. When address of residence was missing (12.4% of members), the surname probabilities alone were used to assign race/ethnicity.</p>
<p>We also created a categorical assignment of race/ethnicity using the BISG probabilities. Categorical assignment is sometimes necessary when a decision must be made about race/ethnicity (e.g., assigning kidney function using prediction formulas that depend on race). In this cut-point approach, when the probability of a race/ethnicity exceeded the cut-point threshold, that race/ethnicity was assigned. We chose a fairly conservative cut-point of &gt;75% for imputation of race/ethnicity; therefore, race/ethnicity remained missing if no single probability exceeded 0.75.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1077558712466293">
<title>Race/Ethnicity Categories</title>
<p>The six major race groups defined by the U.S. Census are as follows: American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, Black or African American, Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, White, and multiracial. The only category for ethnicity is Hispanic or Latino versus not Hispanic or Latino (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1077558712466293">U.S. Census Bureau, 2010</xref>). In preparing surname and block group data for the calculation of probabilities, the BISG method uses Census sources that allow assignment of Hispanic ethnicity as a mutually exclusive race/ethnicity; thus, all other race/ethnicity groups are non-Hispanic. BISG also combines Asian, Native Hawaiian, and Pacific Islander into one group, and categorizes non-Hispanics of two or more races as of “multiple” race.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1077558712466293">
<title>Analysis Plan</title>
<sec id="section8-1077558712466293">
<title>Distribution of race/ethnicity</title>
<p>The distribution of race/ethnicity among health plan members from January 1998 to May 2011 was determined from the administrative race/ethnicity file prepared from enrollment and utilization data. Two cohorts were created—all historical members and a subgroup of members active on January 1, 2009. The BISG probabilities were summed for each race/ethnicity and divided by the total number of members to estimate the distribution of race/ethnicity for these two cohorts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1077558712466293">
<title>Assessment of data quality</title>
<p>We assessed the quality of existing administrative race/ethnicity data, BISG imputation, and administrative data augmented by BISG imputation since any of these may be used for research studies. Accuracy was assessed by comparison with two criterion standards. The first was mother’s race/ethnicity from infant birth certificates for births from January 1, 1998 to December 31, 2010. The second was self-reported race/ethnicity collected via mail for the California Men’s Health Study (CMHS), a survey of 80,000 male health plan members aged 45 to 69 years in 2002-2003 (mean age 58 years), of whom half were from KPSC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1077558712466293">Enger et al., 2006</xref>). We also compared BISG imputation with administrative data to assess how well BISG can replace existing data since many health plans may have limited race/ethnicity data.</p>
<p>The accuracy of categorical race/ethnicity data (i.e., administrative data and BISG imputation using the cut-point method) compared with self-report was tested using sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV), and negative predictive value (NPV). Sensitivity measured the proportion of all members of a given race (based on the criterion standard) who were correctly assigned that race; specificity measured the proportion of all members who were not of a given race who were correctly not assigned to that race. PPV measured the proportion of members who were correctly assigned a given race; NPV measured the proportion of members who were correctly not assigned a given race. These common test statistics cannot be applied to continuous data, such as probabilities. The accuracy of BISG probabilities was tested following the lead of Elliott et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1077558712466293">Elliott, McCaffrey, et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>). Two concordance statistics assessed the accuracy of prediction in individuals by race/ethnicity: the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve and the Gini coefficient, which represents chance (coefficient = 0) to perfect prediction (coefficient = 1). Pearson correlations were used to compare across race/ethnicity; average correlations across all race/ethnicity groups were prepared by weighting the individual group correlations by population size. The area under the receiver operating characteristic curve, Gini coefficient, and correlation can be applied to categorical data. We used these statistics when we compared the accuracy of administrative data and BISG probabilities.</p>
<p>As a final step, we tested the accuracy of race/ethnicity data as commonly used in research: administrative data augmented by imputation for members whose data are missing. For imputation, we used BISG probabilities and the cut-point, categorical race/ethnicity assignment described above. For each type of imputation, we compared the accuracy of augmented data and administrative data without imputation. When probabilities were used, the race/ethnicity known from administrative files was given probability = 1 while the other race/ethnicities were given probability = 0.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1077558712466293" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section11-1077558712466293">
<title>Population Data</title>
<p>The race/ethnicity distribution of health plan members based on existing administrative data and on BISG imputation is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712466293">Table 1</xref>. KPSC has 12,764,185 historic members with various enrollment start dates from decades ago up to May 31, 2011 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712466293">Table 1</xref>). Among this historic cohort, administrative data on race/ethnicity were available for 38.4%. A subgroup of the larger cohort composed of active members who were living and enrolled in the health plan on January 1, 2009 is also shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712466293">Table 1</xref>. For this subgroup, as of November 2010, administrative data on race/ethnicity were available for 71.7%. Among these active members, 51.5% were female, and the mean (<italic>SD</italic>) age was 36.7 (21.9) years on January 1, 2009.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1077558712466293" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Health Plan Membership Race and Ethnicity Distribution Based on Administrative Data and the Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding (BISG) Method.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1077558712466293" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712466293-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Percentage by Race and Ethnicity<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Administrative Data<hr/></th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Race and Ethnicity</th>
<th align="center">Including Unknown</th>
<th align="center">Excluding Unknown</th>
<th align="center">BISG Probabilities</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Historical members up to May 31, 2011 (<italic>n</italic> = 6,327,218 males and 6,436,967 females)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>15.1</td>
<td>39.3</td>
<td>39.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>15.1</td>
<td>39.5</td>
<td>39.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>9.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian and Pacific Islander</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>7.6</td>
<td>8.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> American Indian and Alaskan Native</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multiracial</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown (missing)</td>
<td>61.6</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Active members on January 1, 2009 (<italic>n</italic> = 1,611,923 males and 1,711,665 females)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>25.6</td>
<td>35.8</td>
<td>35.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>30.1</td>
<td>42.0</td>
<td>43.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>7.6</td>
<td>10.6</td>
<td>8.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian and Pacific Islander</td>
<td>6.2</td>
<td>8.6</td>
<td>9.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> American Indian and Alaskan Native</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multiracial</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown (missing)</td>
<td>28.3</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1077558712466293">
<p>Note: BISG probabilities were created by summing the probabilities for each race across all members and dividing by the total number of members. Excluded were 1,656 of 12,765,831 historical members with missing gender (0.01%) and 117 of 3,323,705 active members with missing gender (0.004%).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Based on administrative race data and aggregated BISG probabilities (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712466293">Table 1</xref>), the large majority of health plan members are Whites and Hispanics, in about equal numbers. Both Blacks and Asian and Pacific Islanders are 8% to 11% of the membership. American Indian and Alaskan Natives and persons identified as multiracial are a few percentage points or less. Aggregating BISG probabilities to estimate membership leaves no missing data and provides similar estimates to the nonmissing administrative data with the exception of multiracial persons, where the BISG estimate was higher by a factor of 10.</p>
<p>The racial/ethnic distributions of the two criterion standard databases that have self-reported race/ethnicity are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1077558712466293">Table 2</xref>. The CMHS population (<italic>n</italic> = 32,020 men, mean age 64.0 years on January 1, 2009) is composed of relatively less Hispanics and more Whites than occurs in the health plan membership. The population of women giving birth (<italic>n</italic> = 409,952, mean age 36.4 years on January 1, 2009) is composed of relatively more Hispanics than occurs in the health plan membership. The two criterion standards thus complement each other to include each gender, a broad age range, and good representation of overall health plan race/ethnicity.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1077558712466293" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Members in the Criterion Standard Databases in Which Race and Ethnicity Are Self-Reported.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1077558712466293" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712466293-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Race and Ethnicity</th>
<th align="center">CMHS (<italic>n</italic> = 39,216 males)</th>
<th align="center">Birth Certificate: Mothers of Infants (<italic>n</italic> = 451,712 females)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>White</td>
<td>58.8</td>
<td>27.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hispanic</td>
<td>17.6</td>
<td>47.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Black</td>
<td>9.1</td>
<td>10.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Asian and Pacific Islander</td>
<td>8.4</td>
<td>10.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>American Indian and Alaskan Native</td>
<td>0.3</td>
<td>0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Multiracial</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>0.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unknown (missing)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>2.9</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1077558712466293">
<p>Note: Criterion standards include male participants from the California Men’s Health Study (CMHS) who were health plan members during 2002 or 2003 and women giving birth in health plan hospitals from birth certificates spanning 1998 through 2010.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1077558712466293">
<title>Administrative Data Quality</title>
<p>The accuracy of administrative data compared with the criterion standards is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712466293">Table 3</xref>. Administrative data were far better at accurately identifying health plan members from the four higher frequency race/ethnicity groups (White, Hispanic, Black, Asian, and Pacific Islander) than those from the two lower frequency race/ethnicity groups (American Indian and Alaskan Native, multiracial). When nonmissing administrative race/ethnicity data were compared with the two criterion standards, the specificities were all greater than 90%, except for White males (87.7%). The sensitivities were all greater than 90% except for Asian and Pacific Islander males (86.7%) and females (83.3%); sensitivities were much lower for American Indian and Alaskan Natives and multiracial persons (21.4% maximum). The PPV was greater than 90% in the more common racial and ethnic groups, except for Hispanic men (81.9%) and White women (84.9%). In American Indian and Alaskan Natives and multiracial persons, the PPV was no higher than 43%. A negative identification was reliable across higher and lower frequency race/ethnicity groups: The NPV was never less than 93% in all groups.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1077558712466293" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Administrative Data Accuracy Based on the Two Criterion Standards.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1077558712466293" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712466293-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Race and Ethnicity/Accuracy Statistic</th>
<th align="center">White</th>
<th align="center">Hispanic</th>
<th align="center">Black</th>
<th align="center">Asian and Pacific Islander</th>
<th align="center">American Indian and Alaskan Native</th>
<th align="center">Multiracial</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">CMHS (<italic>n</italic> = 29,003 males)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sensitivity</td>
<td>95.8</td>
<td>91.9</td>
<td>92.7</td>
<td>86.7</td>
<td>13.4</td>
<td>0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Specificity</td>
<td>87.7</td>
<td>95.1</td>
<td>99.3</td>
<td>99.5</td>
<td>99.9</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PPV</td>
<td>91.3</td>
<td>81.9</td>
<td>93.5</td>
<td>93.5</td>
<td>32.4</td>
<td>42.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NPV</td>
<td>93.9</td>
<td>98.0</td>
<td>99.2</td>
<td>98.8</td>
<td>99.8</td>
<td>95.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>0.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Birth certificate: Mothers of infants (<italic>n</italic> = 427,044 females)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sensitivity</td>
<td>93.4</td>
<td>93.0</td>
<td>92.5</td>
<td>83.3</td>
<td>21.4</td>
<td>4.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Specificity</td>
<td>93.5</td>
<td>95.0</td>
<td>99.2</td>
<td>99.2</td>
<td>99.9</td>
<td>99.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PPV</td>
<td>84.9</td>
<td>94.7</td>
<td>93.4</td>
<td>92.1</td>
<td>36.2</td>
<td>18.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NPV</td>
<td>97.3</td>
<td>93.3</td>
<td>99.1</td>
<td>98.0</td>
<td>99.8</td>
<td>99.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>0.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1077558712466293">
<p>Note: PPV = positive predictive value; NPV = negative predictive value; AROC = area under the receiver operating characteristic curve; CMHS = California Men’s Health Study. There were 9,782 CMHS survey respondents with missing administrative race and ethnicity data and 12,539 women giving birth in the health plan with missing administrative race and ethnicity data. Accuracy was measured by sensitivity, specificity, PPV, NPV, and correlation and concordance statistics: AROC and the Gini coefficient. The average (weighted) correlation was 0.87 for birth certificate data and 0.81 for CMHS data.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1077558712466293">
<title>BISG Imputation Accuracy</title>
<p>We tested the accuracy of the BISG method as a stand-alone source for race/ethnicity data. This comparison is potentially useful for health plans with little race and ethnicity data or for research on members who do not use services since BISG probabilities are available. BISG results were tested against nonmissing administrative data and the two criterion standards (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1077558712466293">Table 4</xref>). Among the four common race/ethnicity groups, concordance as judged by the Gini coefficient ranged from 0.76 to 0.96; BISG probabilities agreed least well among Whites. There was substantially lower agreement in the less frequent race/ethnicity groups in our sample: American Indian and Alaskan Natives and multiracial persons. The agreement of BISG with administrative and birth certificate data were similar; the agreement of BISG with CMHS data was better. BISG probabilities thus agreed less in women of childbearing age than in middle-aged to older men. The accuracy of BISG was nearly identical in historic members and in members active during January 2009.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1077558712466293" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Accuracy of BISG Probabilities Compared With Health Plan Administrative Data and the Two Criterion Standards: The CMHS and Mother’s Race From Birth Certificates.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1077558712466293" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712466293-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Race and Ethnicity/Accuracy Statistic</th>
<th align="center">White</th>
<th align="center">Hispanic</th>
<th align="center">Black</th>
<th align="center">Asian and Pacific Islander</th>
<th align="center">American Indian and Alaskan Native</th>
<th align="center">Multiracial</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Administrative data: Historical members from January 1, 1998 to May 31, 2011 (<italic>n</italic> = 4,897,022)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Administrative data: Active members on 1/1/2009 (n = 2,383,013)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">CMHS (<italic>n</italic> = 37,781 males)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.77</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Birth certificate: Mothers of infants (<italic>n</italic> = 438,757 females)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.64</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.71</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.67</td>
<td>0.71</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>0.42</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1077558712466293">
<p>Note: BISG = Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding; CMHS = California Men’s Health Study; AROC = area under the receiver operating characteristic curve. Accuracy was measured as correlation and concordance statistics: AROC and the Gini coefficient. All nonmissing administrative data were used. Criterion standards included male participants from the CMHS and women who gave birth in health plan hospitals and who had nonmissing race. The average (weighted) correlation was 0.72 for administrative data historical members and active members, 0.75 for CMHS data, and 0.70 for birth certificate data.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1077558712466293">
<title>Imputation-Augmented Administrative Data</title>
<p>We tested the accuracy of administrative data augmented by imputation to reduce missing race/ethnicity. The availability of address of residence or surname for all members in our health system resulted in no missing data using BISG probabilities. The accuracy of administrative data augmented using BISG probabilities is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1077558712466293">Table 5</xref>. Compared with <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712466293">Table 3</xref> in which no imputation was performed, the concordance statistics demonstrate only a small decrease in accuracy among Whites (Gini coefficient decrease of 0.01-0.02). The elimination of missing data is reflected by the increased sample size of the criterion standard for comparison (29,003 to 38,781 for CMHS; 427,044 to 438,757 for birth certificates).</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1077558712466293" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Accuracy of Administrative Data After Imputation of Missing Values Using the BISG Method Compared With the Two Criterion Standards: The CMHS and Mother’s Race From Birth Certificates.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1077558712466293" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712466293-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Race and Ethnicity/Accuracy Statistic</th>
<th align="center">White</th>
<th align="center">Hispanic</th>
<th align="center">Black</th>
<th align="center">Asian and Pacific Islander</th>
<th align="center">American Indian and Alaskan Native</th>
<th align="center">Multiracial</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">CMHS (<italic>n</italic> = 38,781 males)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.59</td>
<td>0.51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Birth certificate: Mothers of infants (<italic>n</italic> = 438,757 females)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>0.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AROC</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gini coefficient</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.08</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1077558712466293">
<p>Note: BISG = Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding; CMHS = California Men’s Health Study; AROC = area under the receiver operating characteristic curve. Accuracy was measured as correlation and concordance statistics: AROC and the Gini coefficient. Criterion standards included male participants from the CMHS and women who gave birth in health plan hospitals and who had nonmissing race. The average (weighted) correlation was 0.86 for birth certificate data and 0.79 for CMHS data.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The accuracy of administrative data augmented using the cut-point approach for categorical race/ethnicity assignment is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1077558712466293">Table 6</xref>. Using this approach, missing data in the historical cohort decreased from 61.6% to 19.1%, and missingness in the 2009 active members decreased from 28.3% to 8.6%. Compared with administrative data without augmentation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712466293">Table 3</xref>), augmentation using the cut-point approach resulted in little loss in accuracy among women (birth certificate data). Among men (CMHS data), there were slight gains in accuracy among Whites and Hispanics, and a slight loss among Blacks. Thus, the cost of augmenting administrative data with BISG imputation (either using probabilities or the cut-point approach) was a minimal loss in accuracy among the four major race/ethnicity groups for the benefit of large reductions in missingness.</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-1077558712466293" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Accuracy of Administrative Data After Imputation of Missing Values Using the Cut-Point Approach Compared With the Two Criterion Standards: The CMHS and Mother’s Race From Birth Certificates.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1077558712466293" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712466293-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Race and Ethnicity/Accuracy Statistic</th>
<th align="center">White</th>
<th align="center">Hispanic</th>
<th align="center">Black</th>
<th align="center">Asian and Pacific Islander</th>
<th align="center">American Indian and Alaskan Native</th>
<th align="center">Multiracial</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">CMHS (<italic>n</italic> = 36,151 males)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sensitivity</td>
<td>96.3</td>
<td>93.0</td>
<td>91.1</td>
<td>86.5</td>
<td>10.8</td>
<td>0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Specificity</td>
<td>87.2</td>
<td>95.3</td>
<td>99.3</td>
<td>99.5</td>
<td>99.9</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PPV</td>
<td>91.4</td>
<td>82.2</td>
<td>93.1</td>
<td>93.8</td>
<td>32.4</td>
<td>42.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NPV</td>
<td>94.3</td>
<td>98.3</td>
<td>99.1</td>
<td>98.8</td>
<td>99.7</td>
<td>95.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Birth certificate: Mothers of infants (<italic>n</italic> = 434,405 females)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sensitivity</td>
<td>93.1</td>
<td>92.9</td>
<td>92.4</td>
<td>82.9</td>
<td>20.9</td>
<td>4.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Specificity</td>
<td>93.4</td>
<td>94.8</td>
<td>99.2</td>
<td>99.1</td>
<td>99.9</td>
<td>99.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PPV</td>
<td>84.7</td>
<td>94.5</td>
<td>93.4</td>
<td>92.0</td>
<td>36.2</td>
<td>18.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NPV</td>
<td>97.2</td>
<td>93.3</td>
<td>99.1</td>
<td>98.0</td>
<td>99.8</td>
<td>99.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1077558712466293">
<p>Note: BISG = Bayesian Improved Surname Geocoding; CMHS = California Men’s Health Study; PPV = positive predictive value; NPV = negative predictive value. Cut-point assignment of race was made when the BISG probability was &gt;75% for any given race and ethnic group. Criterion standards included male participants from the CMHS and women who gave birth in health plan hospitals and who had nonmissing race. The number remaining unassigned after cut-point imputation was 2,630 men (previously 9,782, a 73% reduction) and 4,352 women (previously 12,539, a 65% reduction).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1077558712466293" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We found that administrative data derived from health care utilization and the EHR accurately represented self-reported race/ethnicity in middle-aged to older men and young to middle-aged women. We also found that race/ethnicity imputation using U. S. Census data and the BISG method can reduce or eliminate missing data while maintaining accuracy. The accuracy of BISG imputation for health plan members compared with administrative data was quite good for the four most common race/ethnicity groups (Whites, Hispanics, Blacks, and Asian and Pacific Islanders) and represented a substantial improvement over chance assignment.</p>
<p>Despite more racial diversity in our health plan, our findings correspond well with the accuracy of BISG prediction among enrollees of a national health insurance plan who self-reported race/ethnicity on enrollment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>). The primary weakness for both administrative data and imputation are in making inferences regarding lower prevalence racial and ethnic groups. In addition, there is some decrease in accuracy in predictions for women, perhaps because of the use of surnames in assigning probabilities, which women are more likely to change on marriage. The latter issue may be addressed in part by the addition of first names to the Bayesian calculation. Age stratification of probabilities for use in the Bayesian formula may also improve results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1077558712466293">Sandberg et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The validity of research on racial and ethnic disparities using health plan data collected for administrative purposes has been questioned for two key reasons. First, the degree of missing data is often uncomfortably large and may introduce bias into analyses when persons with missing data are excluded. Second, the available data are often not self-reported or collected in a standardized way, which may introduce identification bias and classification errors. Our experience suggests that not all “administrative” data are alike, and that data resources can be of sufficiently high quality to motivate studies of racial and ethnic disparities.</p>
<p>The prognosis for research using health plan administrative race/ethnicity data in the EHR era seems quite good for a few reasons. First, based on our study results, administrative data from an EHR can be accurate in comparison with the standard of self-report. Second, given our results and the original BISG study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>) the BISG method of imputation is accurate for more common race/ethnicity groups and can impute data to anyone with a last name and address, helping reduce the impact of selection bias. Third, data capture can be improved with effort over time. While attempts to collect self-reported race/ethnicity during outpatient visits can be costly and may not yield substantial increases in information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>), the experience of our health system suggests that such strategies can be successful. Procedures to standardize collection of self-reported race/ethnicity at the time of outpatient and inpatient services have resulted in a boost in data capture over the first few years of rolling implementation. As of December 2011, missing data have been reduced to less than 20%. This effort involved training of outpatient clerical staff to collect self-reported race/ethnicity using a standardized approach and response template: a handheld list of major racial and ethnic groups, and a secondary, expanded list for diverse ethnicities.</p>
<p>There was minimal loss of accuracy when supplementing administrative data using either a cut-point approach or BISG probabilities. The cut-point approach, however, suffers from arbitrariness in choice of a cut-point, increased missingness, and the potential for sample selection bias toward persons from racially homogenous geographic areas. Additionally, in a cut-point approach to imputation, the measurement error is not accounted for using naïve regression analyses. Nevertheless, a sufficiently stringent cut-point for a high positive predictive value remains useful for risk stratifying and conducting research. Using the BISG probabilities directly in analysis results in a loss of efficiency compared with known (i.e., self-reported) race/ethnicity. The confidence intervals on linear regression estimates reflect this loss of efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1077558712466293">McCaffrey &amp; Elliott, 2008</xref>). The large sample size found in EHR from large health systems can compensate for this loss. The probability scores for race/ethnicity can be used in combination with nonmissing data (coded as 0/1 for each race/ethnicity category) for estimation in regression analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1077558712466293">McCaffrey &amp; Elliott, 2008</xref>). Thus, estimates of the effect of race/ethnicity can be obtained by imputing only missing data with probabilities.</p>
<p>The accuracy of the BISG method depends in part on the assumption that the racial and ethnic distribution for health plan members and nonmembers is the same for persons of the same surname from the same Census block group. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al. (2009)</xref> provided a means to test for health plan selection by predicting known race/ethnicity from imputed race/ethnicity using multinomial logistic regression and correcting the individual probability estimates (i.e., corrected BISG). We computed these statistics and found minimal differences between individuals’ race/ethnicity probabilities. The absolute mean (<italic>SD</italic>) difference in BISG and corrected BISG probabilities by race/ethnicity ranged from 0.0029 (0.0091) in Native Americans to 0.0702 (0.0466) in Whites. The correlations between BISG and corrected BISG were 0.99, except for Native Americans (0.68) and multiracial persons (0.56). Thus, we found no need to correct the BISG probabilities for our health plan when using imputation to identify the four most common racial and ethnic groups.</p>
<sec id="section16-1077558712466293">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>While this study provides important insights into the potential for imputation of race and ethnicity data, there are several limitations that should be taken into account. Our validation against self-report included women of childbearing age (not older women) and middle-aged to older men (not young men). While the consistency of our results across criterion standards makes extrapolation to adults reasonable, our results cannot be applied to children, where imputation may be less accurate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1077558712466293">Smith et al., 2010</xref>). Our estimates of the accuracy of BISG imputation apply to health plan members with known race; these estimates are assumed to apply similarly to members with missing data.</p>
<p>These data are from a population within a single, integrated health system with an EHR, and the findings may not generalize to other types of health systems. Integrated systems obtain data on enrollment and use of health services, and these efforts may not be as easily coordinated in other types of health plans. We used data on Spanish and Asian languages to identify race as Hispanic or Asian, and these data may not be available to many health systems. It is reassuring, however, that the observed BISG probabilities were similarly accurate to previously reported validation results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712466293">Elliott et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712466293">Elliott, Morrison, et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Based on previous work in our department, geocoding based on address of residence and Census block groups was not deemed to be reliable for imputation in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1077558712466293">Chen et al., 2004</xref>), although subsequent analyses showed accuracy among Blacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1077558712466293">Derose et al., 2009</xref>). Our current efforts show the accuracy of the BISG method among the more frequently occurring race/ethnicity groups. Although BISG accuracy was somewhat less in women based on birth certificate data, race/ethnicity data from California birth certificates does appear to be very accurate and is thus a reasonable criterion standard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1077558712466293">Baumeister, Marchi, Pearl, Williams, &amp; Braveman, 2000</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1077558712466293">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In summary, integrated health systems can provide sufficiently high-quality race/ ethnicity data to leverage the vast amounts of clinically obtained patient care data for studies of health disparities. New imputation methods, such as BISG, supplement existing race/ethnicity data and improve the availability of such data for research. This study suggests that the BISG method can be used to accurately identify race/ethnicity in adults for the four most common groups: Asian and Pacific Islanders, Blacks, Hispanics, and Whites. Better methods are still needed to impute American Indian and Alaskan Natives, and the multiracial group. These results are encouraging for studies of health disparities within and across health care systems, where utilization of services is often well understood and outcomes are well captured.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank Luther Scott, MS, of Kaiser Permanente for his assistance in the validation of programming and output. We thank Marc Elliott, PhD, for his assistance to the national Kaiser Permanente effort to institute the BISG method for race imputation. We also thank Virginia P. Quinn, PhD, Reina Haque, PhD, Bette Caan, DrPH, Barbara Sternfeld, PhD, and Stephen K. Van Den Eeden, PhD, of the California Men’s Health Study for their contribution of data for validation of race/ethnicity.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research was internally funded by Kaiser Permanente Southern California.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marchi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Braveman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The validity of information on “race” and “Hispanic ethnicity” in California birth certificate data</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>869</fpage>-<lpage>883</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petitti</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Enger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Limitations and potential uses of census-based data on ethnicity in a diverse community</article-title>. <source>Annals of Epidemiology</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>345</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Derose</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutkowski</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Incidence of end-stage renal disease and death among insured African Americans with chronic kidney disease</article-title>. <source>Kidney International</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>629</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fremont</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pantoja</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A new method for estimating race/ethnicity and associated disparities where administrative records lack self-reported race/ethnicity</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>5 Pt. 1</issue>), <fpage>1722</fpage>-<lpage>1736</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCaffrey</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Improving disparity estimates for rare racial/ethnic groups with trend estimation and Kalman filtering: An application to the National Health Interview Survey</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>44</volume>(<issue>5 Pt. 1</issue>), <fpage>1622</fpage>-<lpage>1639</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freement</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCaffrey</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pantoja</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Using the Census Bureau’s surname list to improve estimates of race/ethnicity and associated disparities</article-title>. <source>Health Services Outcomes and Research Methodology</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Enger</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van den Eeden</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sternfeld</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quesenberry</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Rowell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caan</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>California Men’s Health Study (CMHS): A multiethnic cohort in a managed care setting</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Esri</collab>. (<year>2012</year>). <source>Esri: Data</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esri.com/data/find-data.html">http://www.esri.com/data/find-data.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fiscella</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fremont</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Use of geocoding and surname analysis to estimate race and ethnicity</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>4 Pt. 1</issue>), <fpage>1482</fpage>-<lpage>500</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hasnain-Wynia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Obtaining data on patient race, ethnicity, and primary language in health care organizations: Current challenges and proposed solutions</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>4 Pt. 1</issue>), <fpage>1501</fpage>-<lpage>1518</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Institute of Medicine</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Race, ethnicity, and language data: Standardization for health care quality improvement</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCaffrey</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Power of tests for a dichotomous independent variable measured with error</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1085</fpage>-<lpage>1101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moscou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valencia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Validity of racial/ethnic classifications in medical records data: An exploratory study</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>1084</fpage>-<lpage>1086</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nasseri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Construction and validation of a list of common Middle Eastern surnames for epidemiological research</article-title>. <source>Cancer Detection Prevention</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bargman</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobmeyer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plocher</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Improving the imputation of race: Evaluating the benefits of stratifying by age</article-title>. <source>Population Health Management</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>-<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langer-Gould</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Getahun</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koebnick</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Health plan administrative records versus birth certificate records: Quality of race and ethnicity information in children</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Services Research</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>316</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>U. S. Census Bureau</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>2010 Census form (Form-61)</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/schools/pdf/2010form_info.pdf">http://www.census.gov/schools/pdf/2010form_info.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Virnig</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>John</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Using a Spanish surname match to improve identification of Hispanic women in Medicare administrative data</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>4 Pt. 1</issue>), <fpage>1469</fpage>-<lpage>1481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1077558712466293">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Emmons</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Race and ethnicity: Comparing medical records to self-reports</article-title>. <source>Journal of the National Cancer Institute, Monographs</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>