<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spvis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Vision: The Journal of Business Perspective</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0972-2629</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/097226291201600109</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_097226291201600109</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>General Management</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Change Anything: The New Science of Personal Success</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>Wallace</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-097226291201600109">Tolani Maritime Institute Induri, Talegaon-Chakan Road Talegaon Dabhade Pune, Maharashtra 410507, India</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>16</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>64</fpage>
<lpage>65</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>Kerry</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grenny</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxfield</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>Ron</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Switzler</surname><given-names>Al</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Change Anything: The New Science of Personal Success</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gopsons Papers Ltd</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>, <page-count count="xvi"/> + <page-count count="262"/> pp, ₹ <price>275</price> (<comment>Paperback</comment>), <isbn>ISBN: 9780749955731</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 MDI SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Management Development Institute</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It may not be an exaggeration to say that whenever managers try to implement a change they encounter some kind of resistance which might manifest itself in several forms. At the same time it is perhaps imperative to embrace and drive change to survive in this world. This superlative tome will be helpful not only to those individuals who have a heroic commitment to change but also to those whose motivation to change has been eroded or terminated.</p>
<p>The book under review has been effectively divided into three parts. The first part contains two chapters. The second part consists of five chapters and the third part consists of six chapters. If the reader reads only one chapter a day, even then the book can be easily read in almost 13 days. The authors of the book have refrained from preaching and have given only practical solutions which are helpful in general understanding of the change process and developing a sound base towards becoming a successful change maestro.</p>
<p>The first chapter offers many brilliant insights through a dissection of the experiment of the legendary psychologist Walter Mischel. The chapter in a subtle way answers several questions as: Why do casinos in Las Vegas do a thriving business? Why do some people tend to overeat? Why do some people overreact? Why do some people overspend? Why do some people smoke, drink or sleep too much? Why do some people play video games excessively? The chapter discusses the roles of personal motivation, personal ability, social motivation, social ability, structural motivation and structural ability. One reason why many change makers might fail is that they look for convenient and cool-sounding influence methods when in fact they should look for relevant methods. The second chapter explains how using the relevant methods, the science of change can be applied to work in a person’s day-to-day life. The third chapter dwells on the concept of worst-case scenarios and explains how and why a glimpse into worst-case scenarios propels people to change. It also explains how the use of strong words and vivid language can help in changing oneself. The fourth chapter explains some of the forces other than willpower which are constantly acting on a person and create problems. The chapter contains a splendid business example which will invariably help the reader in improving his/her performance on the job. The fifth chapter contains a riveting account of a research carried out almost half a century ago. It also contains the account of another study which is now known as Silence Kills study. Many organizations are able to motivate positive behaviour but the positive behaviour cannot be sustained for long. The sixth chapter examines why the positive behaviour cannot be sustained, why and how an incentive system can go wrong? It also dwells on a concept which is drawn from a Nobel Prize winning idea. The chapter also explains how carrots and the threat of losing carrots can be instrumental in achieving goals. The seventh chapter explains how the design of a room may help or thwart a person from realizing his/her goals. It also examines the role that SMSes and Social Networking Sites play in our lives. Studies have shown that at times there can be considerable gap between the amount of energy, effort and the creativity an employee offers and the amount of energy, effort and creativity the employee could have actually given if he or she had so desired. The eighth chapter discusses this gap and provides possible methods of bridging the gap. The ninth chapter brings out the truth that the wants which were advantageous centuries ago result in several disadvantages today. The tenth chapter is devoted to financial fitness. This chapter is warranted as finance is the lifeblood of an enterprise. In 1970 the US government was alarmed because it was waiting for 69,000 heroin-addicted soldiers to return from Vietnam. But 88 per cent of the troops diagnosed with the addiction problem were able to get rid of the habit. Today many people might be checking emails and visiting social networking sites or playing video games all too often. The eleventh chapter contains practical advice to get rid of such addictions and which in fact makes quitting such undesirable habits more pleasurable rather than painful. The twelfth chapter is devoted to a concept known as colonoscopy and examines the study of a Nobel laureate by the name of Daniel Kahneman. The thirteenth chapter offers practical tips to the readers which enable him/her to become the scientist as well as the subject.</p>
<p>Change management is highly demanding and requires out-of-the-box thinking, but as a subject it can be abstract at times. A few images/pictures related to the experiments described in the book could have made the book more lively and absorbing. Nonetheless, the book provides a mesmerizing theoretical description.</p>
<p>The book will be very helpful to the champions of image management, motivational theories and quality of work-life (QWL). It will also be helpful to marketers as well as consumers. The beauty of the book is the fact that nothing needs to be taken for granted. Change management has been explained with much care and understanding. The authors have offered detailed descriptions of the experiments they have meticulously carried out in their labs (Change Anything Labs). The book contains interesting accounts of experiments conducted at Stanford University’s famous research lab—Bing Nursery School, Cornell University, Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania and several other leading institutions or organizations such as Nielsen. The reader will in no case be left in a lurch as these experiments can easily be replicated and hence verified. The book can be very helpful to social science researchers as it contains several experiments which can be used for exploring the psychology of the workers in an organizational setting. The authors have explained several concepts such as <italic>proximal goals, default bias, discretionary effort, redefining normal.</italic> The book is indeed an eye-opener and a collector’s item.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold>Wallace Jacob</bold><break/>
Tolani Maritime Institute<break/>
Induri, Talegaon-Chakan Road<break/>
Talegaon Dabhade<break/>
Pune, Maharashtra 410507, India</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>