<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922812441664</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922812441664</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Factors Associated With Low Moderate-to-Vigorous Physical Activity Levels in Pediatric Patients With Kawasaki Disease</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812441664">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Yahui Tammy</given-names></name>
<degrees>BSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812441664">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chahal</surname><given-names>Nita</given-names></name>
<degrees>MN, CNS-NP</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812441664">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Manlhiot</surname><given-names>Cedric</given-names></name>
<degrees>BSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812441664">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>Rae S. M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0009922812441664">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>McCrindle</surname><given-names>Brian W.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812441664">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922812441664"><label>1</label>Labatt Family Heart Centre, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0009922812441664"><label>2</label>Division of Rheumatology, Department of Pediatrics, University of Toronto, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922812441664">Brian W. McCrindle, Labatt Family Heart Centre, Department of Pediatrics, University of Toronto, The Hospital for Sick Children, 555 University Avenue, Toronto, Ontario, Canada M5G 1X8 Email: <email>brian.mccrindle@sickkids.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<fpage>828</fpage>
<lpage>834</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0009922812441664">
<title>Background/Methods</title>
<p>We sought to determine functional health status and physical activity determinants in 27 patients with Kawasaki disease (KD; 20 males, 11 ± 3 years old). Patient physical activity data were compared with a population-based study of healthy children (Canadian Health Measures Survey).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922812441664">
<title>Results</title>
<p>KD patients performed less moderate-to-vigorous physical activity (MVPA) than healthy children (males, 27 vs 61 min/d, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001; females, 10 vs 47 min/d, P &lt; .001). Male KD patients performed more MVPA than female KD patients (median = 27; quartiles [Q1 15, Q3 26] min/d vs 10 [Q1 7, Q3 11] min/day, <italic>P</italic> = .009). Lower MVPA in KD patients was significantly associated with female gender; lower child self-efficacy score; lower Child Health Questionnaire (CHQ-PF50) scores for role functioning behavioral issues, physical functioning, and family cohesion; and higher CHQ-PF50 scores for self-esteem and family activity limitations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922812441664">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Physical activity counseling should be a focus of management for children with a history of KD.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Kawasaki disease</kwd>
<kwd>physical activity</kwd>
<kwd>health status</kwd>
<kwd>health-related quality of life</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section4-0009922812441664" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The long-term cardiovascular implications of Kawasaki disease (KD) may include a proatherogenic alteration of lipid profile and increases in arterial stiffness, carotid artery intima-media thickness, endothelial dysfunction, and inflammation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812441664">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812441664"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812441664"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812441664">4</xref></sup> Regular physical activity has been shown to be effective in both the primary and secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease and their associated risk factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812441664">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922812441664">6</xref></sup> Thus, physical activity may be beneficial for improving cardiovascular risk in patients after KD. Although the aerobic capacity of children after KD is within the normal ranges for age and gender, moderate-to-vigorous physical activity (MVPA) levels and their determinants remain unclear.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812441664">7</xref></sup> Furthermore, although caregivers of KD patients have previously reported that their children are less healthy than the general population,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812441664">8</xref></sup> the association between physical activity and functional health status has not been well documented in patients with KD. The purpose of this study was to determine physical activity levels and determinants in children after KD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0009922812441664" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section6-0009922812441664">
<title>Participant Characteristics</title>
<p>The study was approved by the research ethics board, and all participants gave informed consent. Potential participants between the ages of 7 and 18 years with a previous history of KD were identified during regular medical assessment at the cardiology outpatient clinic at The Hospital for Sick Children. A detailed medical record review was performed. Complete KD presentation was defined as fever for at least 5 days and at least 4 out of 5 main KD clinical features.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812441664">9</xref></sup> Cardiac complications other than coronary artery aneurysms,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922812441664">10</xref></sup> were defined as: congestive heart failure, life-threatening arrhythmia, left ventricular dysfunction, and severe hemodynamic instabilities. Patients with severe coronary artery involvement at our center are counseled about the type of physical activities that are appropriate when on anticoagulation and are strongly encouraged to be physically active. Physical activity restrictions are limited to high-impact sports, but participation in recreational team sport is strongly supported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0009922812441664">
<title>Accelerometry</title>
<p>All subjects wore a uniaxial accelerometer (Actigraph 7164; Actigraph, LLC, Fort Walton Beach, FL) at the mid-axillary line using an elastic waist strap, except during sleeping and water activities, for a total of 7 days. The Actigraph accelerometer is a small (5.0 cm × 4.0 cm × 1.5 cm), lightweight (43 g) unit with a time sampling mechanism that senses acceleration in the vertical plane 0.05<italic>g</italic> to 2.00<italic>g</italic> in magnitude with a frequency response of 0.25 to 2.50 Hz. It uses transducers and microprocessors to convert recorded accelerations to digital signals in 60-second sampling intervals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922812441664">11</xref></sup> This activity monitor provides reliable and valid measures of physical activity levels during walking, running, and free-living activities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0009922812441664">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922812441664">13</xref></sup> The physical activity counts stored in the unit were transferred to a computer for data reduction and analysis. Activity counts per time block were converted to level of physical activity intensity (metabolic equivalent tasks or METS) of either light (&lt;3 METS), moderate (3-5.9 METS), or vigorous physical activity (&gt;6 METS) based on age-specific cut-points.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0009922812441664">14</xref></sup> Time spent in each physical activity category (min/d) was summed and moderate and vigorous physical activity levels were combined.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0009922812441664">
<title>Study Questionnaires</title>
<p>The Physical Activity Questionnaire (PAQ) is a recall questionnaire that measures physical activity habits and attitudes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0009922812441664">15</xref></sup> It also assesses how the participants feel they compare with their peers in terms of physical activity capabilities. This questionnaire was developed to fulfill a need for quantification of physical activity in the lives of patients and their families and determines types, durations, and patterns of daily activities as reported by the participant.</p>
<p>The 50-item, Child Health Questionnaire–Parent Form (CHQ-PF50) was used to assess whether perceived functional health status is associated with physical activity levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0009922812441664">16</xref></sup> The CHQ assesses domains related to physical and psychosocial functioning and well-being. Some of these concepts directly assess the child and include physical functioning, freedom from bodily pain/discomfort, limitations in schoolwork and activities with friends because of physical health, general health perceptions, change in health, limitations in schoolwork and activities with friends because of emotional/behavioral difficulties, mental health, and general behavior and self-esteem. The other domains assess impact on the parent who completes the questionnaire and include the degree he or she feels limited in personal time because of the child’s health, the degree of limitations in family activities, and the overall cohesion of family relationships. Most of the item–scale correlations (79%) on the questionnaire have adequate internal consistency (Cronbach’s α &gt; .40). The CHQ has a median reliability coefficient of .80.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0009922812441664">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Self-Efficacy Questionnaire was used to assess self-belief in the respondent’s ability to perform physical activity and to determine the extent of patient-perceived restrictions on physical activity imposed by caregivers. This questionnaire was based on concepts outlined in previous studies, which found that greater confidence of both the child and the parent for physical activity are associated with greater levels activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922812441664">18</xref></sup> It was administered to participants to determine if self-efficacy for physical activity was associated with measured levels of physical activity. The questionnaire consisted of 2 sets of 9 questions assessing the subject’s confidence in his or her ability to perform both general everyday activities and physical activities. In the first set of questions, patients were asked, “How certain am I that I can do the following activities . . .,” whereas the second set of questions asked, “What would your parent or guardian say if you asked for permission to do the following activities?” Patients answered these questions for the following 9 activities: running, dancing, swimming, riding a bicycle, skating/rollerblading, leisure activities or games, chores, team sports, and mini-putt/golf. Possible answers were any integer between 0 and 10, anchored with “you cannot do it” at position 0, “sometimes you can do it” at position 5, and “you can do it” at position 10. Two scores were derived from these answers, the average response from 0 to 10 for the first set of questions (children confidence) was calculated and became the child self-efficacy for physical activity, whereas the average response for the second set of questions (caregivers’ limitation) became the child-perceived parental restrictions for physical activity. The questionnaires were given to all study participants and parents during their regular follow-up clinic visit at the cardiology outpatient clinic along with verbal and written instructions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0009922812441664">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Student <italic>t</italic> tests were used to compare CHQ-PF50 scores between KD patients’ and healthy children.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922812441664">19</xref></sup> Data are presented as means with standard deviation. One-sample median tests were used to compare patients’ physical activity levels with population-based accelerometry data from the Canadian Health Measures Survey.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922812441664">20</xref></sup> Data are presented as median with quartiles [Q1, Q3]. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used to compare physical activity levels between male and female participants. Associations between physical activity and potentially associated variables were sought in regression models using maximum likelihood estimates. Data are presented as a parameter estimate with standard error. Appropriate mathematical transformations were applied to physical activity levels to account for its skewed distribution. All statistical analyses were performed using SAS version 9.1 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0009922812441664" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>We enrolled 27 patients with a previous diagnosis of KD (74% males). Patient characteristics are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922812441664">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0009922812441664" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Patients’ Demographics and Clinical Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0009922812441664" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812441664-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mean age at diagnosis (years)</td>
<td>7 ± 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean age at study enrolment (years)</td>
<td>11 ± 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender (male)</td>
<td>20/27 (74%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Complete presentation (fever ≥5 days + ≥4 Kawasaki disease symptoms)</td>
<td>17/27 (63%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intravenous immunoglobulin</td>
<td>25/27 (93%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cardiac complications other than coronary artery aneurysms</td>
<td>7/27 (26%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Regressed small coronary artery aneurysms (2.5 &lt; <italic>z</italic> score &lt; 5.0)</td>
<td>5/27 (19%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Persisting medium/large coronary artery aneurysms (<italic>z</italic> score &gt; 5.0)</td>
<td>11/27 (41%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>On anticoagulation at study enrolment</td>
<td>8/27 (30%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean body mass index at time of study enrolment (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td>18 ± 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Median body mass index <italic>z</italic> score at time of study enrolment</td>
<td>−0.1 (−1.3 ± 1.8)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Overall median duration of MVPA measured in study participants was 18 [Q1 9, Q3 20] min/d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922812441664">Figure 1</xref>). Both male and female KD patients performed less MVPA than healthy children (males: 27 vs 61 min/d, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001; females: 10 vs 47 min/d). Among KD patients, males performed more MVPA than females (median: 27 [Q1 15, Q3 26] min/d vs 10 [Q1 7, Q3 11] min/d, <italic>P</italic> = .009; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922812441664">Figure 1</xref>). Notably, only 1 KD patient achieved the recommended level of daily physical activity, and only 4 KD patients had more than 30 minutes of MVPA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812441664">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0009922812441664">21</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig1-0009922812441664" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Daily time spent in moderate-to-vigorous physical activity for each Kawasaki disease patient by gender</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812441664-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In the PAQ, participants reported a median of 51 minutes (range 0-180) of physical activity per day, along with 180 minutes (range 30-540) of television watching or computer time per day. Also, 74% of participants reported involvement in team sports, and 19% did not consider themselves physically active enough.</p>
<p>There was no significant difference between KD patients and a normal control population in the CHQ-PF50 domains of general health, physical functioning, family activities, and family cohesion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0009922812441664">Table 2</xref>). In contrast, the domains of freedom from bodily pain, behavior problems, and self-esteem were significantly higher in the study population when compared with the reported normal control population.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0009922812441664" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Self-Efficacy for Physical Activity and Functional Health Status</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0009922812441664" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812441664-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Study (Mean ± SD)</th>
<th align="center">Population norm<sup>a</sup> (Mean ± SD)</th>
<th align="center">
<italic>P</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Self-Efficacy Questionnaire (/10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child’s self-efficacy for physical activity</td>
<td>6.9 ± 1.7</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child-perceived parental restrictions of physical activity</td>
<td>9.2 ± 1.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Parent-completed Child Health Questionnaire (/100)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Global health</td>
<td>83 ± 19</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> General health</td>
<td>72 ± 15</td>
<td>73 ± 18</td>
<td>.78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Physical functioning</td>
<td>98 ± 4</td>
<td>96 ± 14</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Freedom from bodily pain</td>
<td>91 ± 13</td>
<td>82 ± 19</td>
<td>.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Freedom from behavior problems</td>
<td>85 ± 11</td>
<td>76 ± 17</td>
<td>.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-esteem</td>
<td>90 ± 11</td>
<td>80 ± 18</td>
<td>.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Family activities</td>
<td>86 ± 16</td>
<td>90 ± 19</td>
<td>.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Family cohesion</td>
<td>74 ± 22</td>
<td>72 ± 22</td>
<td>.65</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section11-0009922812441664">
<title>Demographic and Clinical Factors Associated With Lower Levels of MVPA</title>
<p>Female gender was associated with a decrease in MVPA of 23.5 (8.7) min/d. Greater body mass index <italic>z</italic> score at time of study enrollment was not associated with a decrease in MVPA (5.5 [4.0] min/d, <italic>P</italic> = .17).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0009922812441664">
<title>Functional Health Status Factors Associated With Lower Levels of MVPA</title>
<p>Each decrement (ie, per decrease in score of 1/100 on the CHQ-PF50) in parents’ perceived ratings of lower physical functioning was associated with a decrease in MVPA of 4.5 (1.2) min/d (<italic>P</italic> = .0002). Each decrement (ie, per decrease in score of 1/100 on the CHQ-PF50) in parents’ perceived ratings of lower freedom from behavior problems was associated with a decrease of MVPA of 0.9 (0.4) min/d (<italic>P</italic> = .017). Each decrement (ie, per decrease in score of 1/100 on the CHQ-PF50) in parents’ perceived rating of lower self-esteem was associated with an increase in MVPA of 2.1 (0.5) min/d (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001). Each decrement (ie, per decrease in score of 1/100 on the CHQ-PF50) in parents’ perceived ratings of lower family cohesion and freedom from family activity limitations was associated with a decrease in physical activity of 0.7 (0.2) min/d (<italic>P</italic> = .0001) and 1.0 (0.2) min/d (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001), respectively. In contrast, changes in the child’s daily minutes of MVPA was not associated with parents’ perceived ratings of their child’s global health (0.2 [0.2] min/d, <italic>P</italic> = .45), general health (−0.2 [0.3] min/d, <italic>P</italic> = .63), and freedom from bodily pain (0.3 [0.3] min/d, <italic>P</italic> = .21).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0009922812441664">
<title>Self-Efficacy Associated With Lower MVPA</title>
<p>Each decrement (ie, per decrease in score of 1/10 on the Self-Efficacy Questionnaire) in a child’s perceived rating of lower physical activity self-efficacy was associated with a decrease in MVPA of 4.5 (2.0) min/d (<italic>P</italic> = .03). However, a child’s perceived parental restrictions of physical activity was not associated with changes in MVPA (7.5 [4.8] min/d, <italic>P</italic> = .12).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0009922812441664" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our study sought to objectively determine physical activity levels and factors associated with physical activity participation in children with a history of KD. We have revealed that patients with KD perform significantly less physical activity than healthy peers, failing to meet daily physical activity recommendations of 60 to 90 minutes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922812441664">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0009922812441664">22</xref></sup> Cardiac rehabilitation with an emphasis on healthy lifestyle, avoidance of a sedentary lifestyle, and behavior modification should be the primary focus for clinicians treating patients with a history of KD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0009922812441664">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0009922812441664">24</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="section15-0009922812441664">
<title>Low MVPA in Patients With a History of Kawasaki Disease</title>
<p>Although we have determined that KD patients perform significantly less MVPA than healthy normal peers, only 19% of patients reported that they considered themselves not physically active enough. Lower physical activity for participants is not likely because of physiological impairment, as studies have shown that maximal oxygen consumption and exercise capacity are unaltered after KD and independent of coronary artery status.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812441664">7</xref></sup> Instead, low MVPA may be associated with imposed limitations and physical and psychosocial factors. The lower measured daily physical activity in female participants has been previously reported in the literature on healthy children.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0009922812441664">25</xref></sup> We have previously reported that discrepancies between cardiologist and caregivers on physical activity restrictions exist,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0009922812441664">26</xref></sup> which may also contribute to lower physical activity participation in children; however, no physical activity–related body contact restriction discrepancies were found between cardiologists and caregivers when children on anticoagulation therapy were considered. Clinicians need to provide physical activity recommendations for all children with a previous diagnosis of KD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0009922812441664">
<title>The Association Between Functional Health Status and Physical Activity</title>
<p>We have reported that freedom from bodily pain, behavior problems, and self-esteem were significantly higher in KD patients when compared with a healthy population. Comprehensive, long-term medical management in patients with a history of KD may in part explain these findings. Previous studies have also demonstrated that children diagnosed with aneurysms after KD had lower self-reported physical health outcomes, and caregivers of KD patients had lower general health perception of their children, regardless of the presence of coronary artery sequelae.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812441664">8</xref></sup> Our findings further indicate that these lower reported scores on the functional health status (including physical functioning, role functioning behavior, and family cohesion) are significantly related to decreased physical activity levels. This suggests that even though patients after KD have a lower level of MVPA, those with higher MVPA levels may demonstrate better functional health status. Thus, increases in physical activity may play an active role in helping improve perceived functional health (or vice versa). The positive associations between higher MVPA and family domains (ie, greater family cohesion and activity) found in our study support the need for a family approach when providing counseling to increase physical activity levels in children. Previous work has emphasized the importance of parental support and family involvement in promoting a child’s physical activity level.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0009922812441664">27</xref></sup> This aspect should be explored in future physical activity intervention studies involving children with a history of KD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0009922812441664">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0009922812441664">29</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0009922812441664">
<title>The Association Between Self-Efficacy and Physical Activity</title>
<p>An association between lower child self-efficacy and decreased physical activity levels may indicate that patients with worse outcomes have problems with perceived ability to participate in physical activities. Similarly, a study of 100 adolescents with varying severities of congenital heart disease found that subjects’ self-efficacy influenced their degree of participation in physical activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922812441664">18</xref></sup> Physical activity interventions in KD patients should include strategies to increase self-efficacy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0009922812441664">
<title>Benefits of Cardiac Rehabilitation in Pediatric Cohorts</title>
<p>Cardiac rehabilitation with an emphasis on increasing physical activity levels through counseling and/or interventions may be effective in this cohort. First, rehabilitation may enable participants and their caregivers to realize that moderate intensity physical activity can be performed without significant risk.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0009922812441664">30</xref></sup> Second, rehabilitation may attenuate declines in aerobic capacity and prevent cardiovascular morbidity into adulthood.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0009922812441664">31</xref></sup> Future studies are needed to investigate the role of cardiac rehabilitation and/or physical activity counseling in increasing physical activity levels and promoting long-term physical and psychosocial health in children with a history of KD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0009922812441664">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Our patient cohort may not be representative of all children with a previous diagnosis of KD. Patients enrolled in this study were more likely to have coronary artery involvement given the study setting. However, these participants were recruited as they are possibly at higher risk for anxiety related to physical activity and may benefit from physical activity monitoring. The mean age at diagnosis of this cohort was older than the “typical” KD population, because physical activity measurement using accelerometers in children younger than 5 years is not possible; thus, those patients could not be included. Cardiologist-imposed physical activity restrictions because of anticoagulation therapy does not preclude all MVPA and thus cannot fully explain the very low physical activity levels observed in this cohort relative to healthy children.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0009922812441664" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our study findings indicate that patients with previous history of KD, especially females, perform significantly less physical activity than healthy peers and fail to meet daily physical activity recommendations of 60 to 90 minutes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922812441664">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0009922812441664">22</xref></sup> We found a significant discrepancy between perceived and actual physical activity participation in KD patients; thus, accelerometry-based physical activity measurements are recommended to accurately characterize this cohort. Cardiac rehabilitation and counseling to increase physical activity levels in patients after KD should be investigated in future studies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work is supported in part by the CIBC World Markets Children’s Miracle Foundation (Brian W. McCrindle) and Arthritis Society Investigator Award (Rae S. M. Yeung).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922812441664">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Novel and traditional cardiovascular risk factors in children after Kawasaki disease: implications for premature atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922812441664">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dalla Pozza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bechtold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urschel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kozlik-Feldmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Netz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Subclinical atherosclerosis, but normal autonomic function after Kawasaki disease</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>243</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922812441664">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iemura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long term consequences of regressed coronary aneurysms after Kawasaki disease: vascular wall morphology and function</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922812441664">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Niboshi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamaoka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Endothelial dysfunction in adult patients with a history of Kawasaki disease</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922812441664">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review of the health benefits of physical activity and fitness in school-aged children and youth</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922812441664">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bredin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health benefits of physical activity: the evidence</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>801</fpage>-<lpage>809</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922812441664">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paridon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galioto</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomassoni</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bricker</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Exercise capacity and incidence of myocardial perfusion defects after Kawasaki disease in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1420</fpage>-<lpage>1424</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922812441664">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gauvreau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newburger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundel</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical and psychosocial health in children who have had Kawasaki disease</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>583</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922812441664">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Newburger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis, treatment, and long-term management of Kawasaki disease: a statement for health professionals from the Committee on Rheumatic Fever, Endocarditis and Kawasaki Disease, Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young, American Heart Association</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>2747</fpage>-<lpage>2771</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922812441664">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manlhiot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCrindle</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Improved classification of coronary artery abnormalities based only on coronary artery z-score after Kawasaki disease</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Cardiology</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0009922812441664">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stickland</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bouffard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of maximal aerobic power from the 20-m multi-stage shuttle run test</article-title>. <source>Can J Appl Physiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0009922812441664">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenmann</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strath</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shadrick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rigsby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Validity of uniaxial accelerometry during activities of daily living in children</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0009922812441664">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Objective measurement of physical activity in youth: current issues, future directions</article-title>. <source>Exerc Sport Sci Rev</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0009922812441664">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haskell</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and public health: updated recommendation for adults from the American College of Sports Medicine and the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1423</fpage>-<lpage>1434</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0009922812441664">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thavendiranathan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association between physical activity, adiposity, and lipid abnormalities in children with familial hyperlipidemia</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0009922812441664">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abetz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The CHQ: A User’s Manual</source> (<comment>2nd printing</comment>). <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Health Institute</publisher-name>; <year>1999</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0009922812441664">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maunsell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Speechley</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Canadian-French, German and UK versions of the Child Health Questionnaire: methodology and preliminary item scaling results</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>-<lpage>445</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0009922812441664">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bar-Mor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bar-Tal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krulik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeevi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self-efficacy and physical activity in adolescents with trivial, mild, or moderate congenital cardiac malformations</article-title>. <source>Cardiol Young</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>-<lpage>566</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0009922812441664">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonsel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Essink-Bot</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gemke</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of comprehensive health status measures in children: the Child Health Questionnaire in relation to the Health Utilities Index</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0009922812441664">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Colley</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garriguet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity of Canadian children and youth: accelerometer results from the 2007 to 2009 Canadian Health Measures Survey</article-title>. <source>Health Rep</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0009922812441664">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kho</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duggan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Process description and evaluation of Canadian Physical Activity Guidelines development</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0009922812441664">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Public Health Agency of Canada</collab>. <source>Canada’s Physical Activity Guide to Healthy Active Living</source>. <publisher-loc>Edmonton, Alberta, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Public Health Agency of Canada</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0009922812441664">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kavey</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allada</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular risk reduction in high-risk pediatric patients: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Expert Panel on Population and Prevention Science; the Councils on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young, Epidemiology and Prevention, Nutrition, Physical Activity and Metabolism, High Blood Pressure Research, Cardiovascular Nursing, and the Kidney in Heart Disease; and the Interdisciplinary Working Group on Quality of Care and Outcomes Research: endorsed by the American Academy of Pediatrics</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>2710</fpage>-<lpage>2738</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0009922812441664">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hambrecht</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gielen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of exercise on coronary endothelial function in patients with coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>342</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>460</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0009922812441664">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macera</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blanton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Levels of physical activity and inactivity in children and adults in the United States: current evidence and research issues</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>11</issue>)(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>S526</fpage>-<lpage>S533</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0009922812441664">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Longmuir</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCrindle</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity restrictions for children after the Fontan operation: disagreement between parent, cardiologist, and medical record reports</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>157</volume>:<fpage>853</fpage>-<lpage>859</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0009922812441664">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mulhall</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Early adolescent participation in physical activity: correlates with individual and family characteristics</article-title>. <source>J Phys Act Health</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0009922812441664">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Parental correlates of physical activity in children and early adolescents</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0009922812441664">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Sluijs</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMinn</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of interventions to promote physical activity in children and adolescents: systematic review of controlled trials</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>335</volume>:<fpage>703</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0009922812441664">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pastore</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turchetta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Attias</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiorespiratory functional assessment after pediatric heart transplantation</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Transplant</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0009922812441664">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Twisk</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Mechelen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tracking of activity and fitness and the relationship with cardiovascular disease risk factors</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1455</fpage>-<lpage>1461</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>