<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmsj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mult Scler</journal-id>
<journal-title>Multiple Sclerosis Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1352-4585</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0970</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458512454771</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1352458512454771</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Impaired regulatory function and enhanced intrathecal activation of B cells in neuromyelitis optica: distinct from multiple sclerosis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512454771">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512454771">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1352458512454771">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Baoguo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1352458512454771">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1352458512454771">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Guixian</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512454771">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Zhiying</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512454771">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1352458512454771">–3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Zhenxin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512454771">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Chuanzhen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512454771">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1352458512454771">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1352458512454771"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology, Huashan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1352458512454771"><label>2</label>Institute of Neurology, Huashan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1352458512454771"><label>3</label>Institutes of Brain Science and State Key Laboratory of Medical Neurobiology, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1352458512454771">Chuanzhen Lu, Department and Institute of Neurology, Huashan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University, 12 Wulumuqi Zhong Road, Shanghai 20040, China. Email: <email>chuanzhenlu@yahoo.cn</email></corresp>
<corresp id="corresp2-1352458512454771">Zhenxin Li, Department of Neurology, Huashan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University, 12 Wulumuqi Zhong Road, Shanghai 200040, China. Email: <email>zhenxinli@yahoo.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>289</fpage>
<lpage>298</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>13</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>14</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>3</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>19</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1352458512454771">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>The effective treatment of neuromyelitis optica (NMO) with rituximab has suggested an important role for B cells in NMO pathogenesis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1352458512454771">
<title>Objective:</title>
<p>To explore the antibody-independent function of B cells in NMO and relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1352458512454771">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>Fifty-one NMO patients and 42 RRMS patients in an acute relapse phase and 37 healthy controls (HC) were enrolled in the study. The B cell expression of B cell activating factor receptor (BAFF-R), CXCR5 and very late antigen-4 (VLA-4), the B cell production of interleukin (IL)-10 and interferon (IFN)-γ and the proportion of circulating memory and CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> regulatory B cells were evaluated by flow cytometry. The cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) levels of BAFF and CXCL13 were determined by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1352458512454771">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>The CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> regulatory B cell levels and the B cell expression of IL-10 were significantly lower in NMO patients than in RRMS patients and the HC. In aquaporin-4 antibody (AQP4-ab)-positive NMO patients, the B cell IL-10 production and CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> regulatory B cell levels were even lower than in AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients. The CSF BAFF and CXCL13 levels were significantly higher in NMO patients than in patients with RRMS and other non-inflammatory neurologic diseases (ONDs).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1352458512454771">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>The immuno-regulatory properties of B cells are significantly impaired in NMO patients and particularly in AQP4-ab-positive NMO patients. The elevated CSF levels of BAFF and CXCL13 in NMO suggest an enhanced intrathecal B cell recruitment and activation. Our results further define the distinct immunological nature of NMO and RRMS from the B cell perspective.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Neuromyelitis optica</kwd>
<kwd>regulatory B cells</kwd>
<kwd>multiple sclerosis</kwd>
<kwd>autoimmunity</kwd>
<kwd>B cell activating factor</kwd>
<kwd>CXCL13</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-1352458512454771" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Neuromyelitis optica (NMO) is an idiopathic inflammatory demyelinating disease of the central nervous system (CNS) that is characterized by severe attacks of optic neuritis and longitudinally extended transverse myelitis. The disease is more prevalent in Asia and is an important cause of irreversible neurological disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1352458512454771">1</xref></sup> There is a long-standing controversy regarding whether NMO is a variant of multiple sclerosis (MS) or a distinct disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1352458512454771">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458512454771">3</xref></sup> Recently, increasing clinical, serological, immunopathological and neuroimaging evidences have indicated that NMO and MS are likely to be two different diseases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1352458512454771">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458512454771"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458512454771"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458512454771">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Aquaporin-4 antibody (AQP4-ab), a disease-specific autoantibody, has significantly contributed to differentiating NMO from MS, which strongly indicates that NMO may be a humoral-mediated disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1352458512454771">4</xref></sup> MS has predominantly been regarded as a disease triggered by auto-reactive T cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458512454771">5</xref></sup> However, the promising results from treating MS and NMO with rituximab have raised questions about the role of B cells in the two diseases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1352458512454771">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1352458512454771">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>During an inflammatory process, peripherally activated B cells express very late antigen-4 (VLA-4) which binds to its counterreceptor VCAM-1 on the endothelial cell of the blood brain barrier and transmigrate into the CNS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1352458512454771">10</xref></sup> CXCL13, a selective B cell chemoattractant, is another key regulator of B cell recruitment into the CNS through its binding to CXCR5 on B cells. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) CXCL13 levels are elevated in MS patients and are found to be even higher in NMO patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1352458512454771">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1352458512454771"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1352458512454771"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1352458512454771"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1352458512454771">15</xref></sup> Once within the CNS, B cell activating factor (BAFF), which is secreted by astrocytes, further enhances the clonal expansion of B cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1352458512454771">16</xref></sup> BAFF-receptor (BAFF-R) mRNA levels in B cells are elevated in MS patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1352458512454771">17</xref></sup> CSF BAFF levels are observed to be even higher in NMO patients than in MS patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1352458512454771">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1352458512454771">19</xref></sup> Under the action of BAFF, B cells subsequently mature into long-lived plasma cells that can produce autoantibodies in situ.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1352458512454771">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>In addition to antibody production, B cells perform multiple functions in an antibody-independent manner, including antigen presentation and cytokine production.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1352458512454771">10</xref></sup> CD19<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup> memory B cells are considered to be a source of proinflammatory cytokines responsible for the pathogenic effects that occur during autoimmune processes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1352458512454771">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1352458512454771"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1352458512454771">23</xref></sup> There is also mounting evidence for the existence of regulatory B cell subsets that may play a protective role in autoimmune diseases through producing interleukin (IL)-10.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1352458512454771">24</xref></sup> Recently, CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> B cells have been reported to possess regulatory properties and have been found to be functionally impaired in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1352458512454771">25</xref></sup></p>
<p>The roles of B cells in CNS demyelinating diseases are still not fully understood. In this study, we compared the distribution of memory and regulatory B cell subgroups, the levels of BAFF-R, VLA-4 and CXCR5 expression on B cells, the production of IL-10 and interferon (IFN)-γ by B cells in the peripheral blood and the levels of BAFF and CXCL13 in the CSF of NMO, relapsing–remitting MS (RRMS) and control groups. Our results precisely defined the distinct immunological nature of NMO and RRMS from the B cell perspective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1352458512454771" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section8-1352458512454771">
<title>Patients</title>
<p>From 2008 to 2011, we analyzed peripheral blood samples from patients with NMO (<italic>n</italic>=51) and RRMS (<italic>n</italic>=42) and from healthy donors (<italic>n</italic>=37) at Huashan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University. All of the patients were in the acute phase (within two weeks of the onset of a relapse or exacerbation). RRMS was diagnosed by the McDonald criteria (revised 2005).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1352458512454771">26</xref></sup> NMO was diagnosed based on the criteria established by Wingerchuk et al. in 2006.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1352458512454771">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>Nine (17.6%) of the 51 NMO patients and one (2.4%) of the 42 RRMS patients were positive for co-existent serum autoantibodies. Among the 10 patients, one NMO patient was diagnosed with Sjögren’s syndrome; the other nine patients did not fulfill the diagnostic criteria for any other autoimmune disease. Of the 51 NMO patients, 46 (90.2%) patients had a relapsing course and 5 (9.8%) patients had a monophasic course. The clinical and laboratory findings in the NMO and RRMS groups are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1352458512454771">Table 1</xref>. The age- and sex-matched healthy controls (HC) (25 women, 12 men; median age 36 years; range 18–56 years) had not taken any medications for at least four weeks prior to sample collection.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1352458512454771" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinical and laboratory findings in neuromyelitis optica (NMO) and relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS) groups.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1352458512454771" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458512454771-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">NMO</th>
<th align="left">RRMS</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>No. of patients</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female/male</td>
<td>39/12</td>
<td>24/18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Median age, y, (range)</td>
<td>39 (16–72)</td>
<td>34 (16–50)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease duration, mo, mean±SD</td>
<td>23.8±14.2</td>
<td>19.8±12.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of exacerbations, mean±SD</td>
<td>3.0±1.5</td>
<td>2.9±1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MRI spinal cord lesion</td>
<td>51/51</td>
<td>25/42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MRI spinal cord lesion &gt;3 vertebral segments</td>
<td>48/51</td>
<td>0/42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MRI brain lesion</td>
<td>16/51</td>
<td>42/42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MRI lesion fulfilling Barkhof criteria</td>
<td>1/51</td>
<td>40/42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EDSS score, mean±SD</td>
<td>3.9±1.9</td>
<td>2.5±1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CSF cell counts/mm<sup>3</sup>, median (range)</td>
<td>8.0 (0–45)</td>
<td>7.0 (0–18)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CSF protein, mg/L, median (range)</td>
<td>345.0 (121–764)</td>
<td>250.5 (34–523)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OB positive, %</td>
<td>16/51, 31.4%</td>
<td>38/42, 90.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IgG index, mean ±SD</td>
<td>0.71±0.34</td>
<td>0.83±0.41</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serum AQP4-ab-positive, %</td>
<td>29/51, 56.9%</td>
<td>0/42, 0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serum autoantibody-positive, %</td>
<td>9/51, 17.6% 1 ANA+(1:1000), SSA+, SSB+, and was diagnosed with Sjögren’s syndrome; 1 ANA+(1:320), pANCA+, SSA+; 1 ANA+(1:320); 6 ANA+(1:100)</td>
<td>1/42, 2.4% 1 ANA+(1:100)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1352458512454771"><p>ANA: antinuclear antibody; AQP4-ab: aquaporin-4 antibody; EDSS: Expanded Disability Status Scale; OB: oligoclonal band; p-ANCA: anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (perinuclear); SD: standard deviation; MRI: magnetic resonance imaging.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>None of the patients had been treated with immunosuppressive agents, such as azathioprine, cyclophosphamide or mitoxantrone, within six months before sampling. Seven NMO patients had been taking low dose oral prednisone during a steroid withdrawal process before the relapse. The other NMO patients and all of the RRMS patients had not taken any dose of steroid during a period of 12 weeks preceding inclusion in our study. All specimens were collected from 7:00 to 10:00 am and before the therapy with high-dose corticosteroid or immunoglobulin for the current relapse commenced. The elapsed time from the onset of relapse to specimen sampling was less than two weeks.</p>
<p>CSF was obtained from 37 of the 51 NMO patients (29 women, 8 men; median age 39 years; range 16–56 years) and 21 of the 42 RRMS patients (13 women, 8 men; median age 36 years; range 22–50 years). Control CSF samples were obtained from 30 patients (19 women, 11 men; median age 37 years; range 20–48 years) with other non-inflammatory neurologic diseases (ONDs), such as migraine, diabetic oculomotor nerve palsy, idiopathic epilepsy and mitochondrial encephalopathy. All of the control CSF samples were oligoclonal band (OB)-negative and had an immunoglobulin (IgG) index&lt;0.7.</p>
<p>We obtained written informed consent from each participant. The study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of Huashan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1352458512454771">
<title>Flow cytometry analysis</title>
<p>Blood samples were collected in heparinized tubes and washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) supplemented with 0.5% fetal calf serum (FCS). The samples were then resuspended in PBS containing 0.5% FCS. Subsequently, aliquots of the cell suspensions were stained in the dark with monoclonal antibodies and the appropriate isotype controls for 30 min at 4°C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1352458512454771">Table 2</xref>). After lysing the red blood cells with FACS Lysing Solution (BD Biosciences, San Jose, California, USA), the cells were washed with PBS and resuspended in 0.5 ml PBS. The proportions of various lymphocyte subsets were determined using a Coulter Epics XL flow cytometer (Beckman Coulter, Miami, Florida, USA).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1352458512454771" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The combinations of anti-human monoclonal antibodies used.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1352458512454771" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458512454771-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Phenotypes of B and T lymphocyte subsets</th>
<th align="left">Combinations of anti-human monoclonal antibodies</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup> memory B cell</td>
<td>CD19 PE-Cy5 and CD27 PE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup> CD38<sup>high</sup> cell</td>
<td>CD19 PE-Cy5, CD24 PE and CD38 FITC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>BAFF-R<sup>+</sup> cell</td>
<td>CD19 PE-Cy5 and BAFF-R FITC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>CXCR5<sup>+</sup> cell</td>
<td>CD19 PE and CXCR5 PerCP/Cy5.5<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1352458512454771">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>VLA-4<sup>+</sup> cell</td>
<td>CD19 PE-Cy5 and CD49d PE</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1352458512454771"><p>AQP4-ab: aquaporin-4 antibody; BAFF-R: B cell activating factor receptor; CXCR5: the receptor of the B cell chemoattractant CXCL13; IFN: interferon; IL: interleukin; NMO: neuromyelitis optica; VLA-4: very late antigen-4.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1352458512454771">
<label>a</label>
<p>CXCR5 PerCP/Cy5.5 was purchased from BioLegend, San Diego, California, USA. The other antibodies were purchased from eBioscience, San Diego, California, USA.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1352458512454771">
<title>Cytokine detection</title>
<p>Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) from about 5 mL of heparinized blood were separated by Ficoll-Hypaque density gradient centrifugation (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, Piscataway, New Jersey, USA). Cells from the interface were washed with PBS and adjusted to a concentration of 1×10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL in RPMI 1640 containing L-glutamine and NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (Sigma, St. Louis, Missouri, USA) supplemented with 100 U/mg/mL penicillin/streptomycin (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, California, USA) and 10% FCS in 24-well U-bottom plates (Nunc, Langenselbold, Germany). The cells were then stimulated with 0.1 mg/mL CpG ODN 2006 (InvivoGen, San Diego, California, USA) at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 72 hr. During the last 5 hr, the cells were incubated with 25 ng/mL phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA, Sigma), 2 μg/mL ionomycin (Alexis, Postfach, Lausen, Switzerland) and 10 μg/mL brefeldin A (BFA, Alexis) in addition to CpG ODN 2006.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1352458512454771">25</xref></sup> The cells were then stained with anti-human CD19 PE-Cy5 (eBioscience, San Diego, California, USA) and subsequently washed, fixed and permeabilized using a Fix&amp;Perm kit (Invitrogen, Camarillo, California, USA) and stained with anti-human IFN-γ FITC and IL-10 PE (eBioscience) to detect intracellular cytokines. To detect CD4<sup>+</sup>IL-17<sup>+</sup> (Th17) cells, PBMCs were incubated with PMA, ionomycin and BFA for 5 hr. After being stained with anti-human CD4 FITC (eBioscience), the cells were fixed, permeabilized and stained with anti-human IL-17A PE (eBioscience). Appropriate isotype controls were used to establish the cytokine detection gates.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1352458512454771">
<title>BAFF and CXCL13 detection</title>
<p>To isolate cells and larger particles, CSF samples were centrifuged immediately after sampling and stored at -80°C until analysis. The CXCL13 and BAFF levels were measured using commercially available enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits (Quantikine, R&amp;D Systems, Abingdon, UK) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. All of the assessments were performed in duplicate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1352458512454771">
<title>AQP4-ab detection</title>
<p>Serum AQP4-ab status was evaluated with an indirect immunofluorescence assay using a commercially available kit (EUROIMMUN AG, Luebeck, Germany) following the manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1352458512454771">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Non-normally distributed data were expressed as medians with ranges and were compared between groups using Kruskal-Wallis H-test and post hoc Mann-Whitney U test with Bonferroni correction. CSF BAFF and CXCL13 levels were normally distributed; they were presented as mean±standard deviation (SD) and were compared between groups using one way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with post hoc least significant difference (LSD) test. Student’s t test or Whitney U test was applied to compare the experimental data from AQP4-ab-positive and -negative NMO patients. Statistical significance was set at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1352458512454771" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section15-1352458512454771">
<title>Regulatory and memory B cell subsets in NMO, RRMS and HC</title>
<p>The proportions of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> regulatory B cells out of the total CD19<sup>+</sup> B cells were significantly lower in NMO patients (6.7%, 1.2–21.6%) than in RRMS patients (12.7%, 3.8–56.2%) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) or HC (11.6%, 3.6–25.1%) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). The CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cell levels were not significantly different between RRMS and HC (<italic>P</italic>=0.566) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1352458512454771">Figure 1(A)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1352458512454771">1(B)</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1352458512454771" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Decreased numbers of regulatory B cells in neuromyelitis optica (NMO) patients.</p>
<p>(A) Representative flow cytometry analysis of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells of a healthy donor. (B) The CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup> CD38<sup>high</sup> cell levels were significantly lower in NMO patients than in relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS) patients and healthy controls (HC). (C) Absolute numbers of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells in each group. (D) The percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells out of the total lymphocytes in each group.</p>
<p>NS: not significant</p>
<p>The data are represented by scatter plots in which the horizontal line indicates the median.</p>
<p>**<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01 after multiple comparison adjustment.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1352458512454771-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Because co-existent autoimmune diseases may decrease the number of regulatory B cells, we repeated the analysis after excluding the 10 patients with positive serum autoantibodies, and found that the decrease in the proportions of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells in NMO group was still significant compared with RRMS and HC. We also conducted the analysis after excluding the seven NMO patients that had been taking oral prednisone before sampling. Similarly, the decrease of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cell proportions in NMO group was still significant.</p>
<p>The absolute numbers of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells in the peripheral blood, which were calculated according to the results of synchronous routine blood tests, were also significantly lower in NMO group than in RRMS and HC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1352458512454771">Figure 1(C)</xref>). A comparison of the percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells out of the total lymphocytes between groups produced essentially the same results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1352458512454771">Figure 1(D)</xref>).</p>
<p>The percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup> memory B cells were not significantly different between RRMS (1.7%, 0.0–11.2%), NMO (1.8%, 0.2–4.6%) and HC (1.5%, 0.6–6.3%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.913) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1352458512454771">Figure 2(A)</xref>). No significant difference in total CD19<sup>+</sup> B cell percentages was found between groups (NMO, 15.2%, 3.0–45.0%; RRMS, 14.8%, 2.2–29.1%; HC, 12.6%, 6.5–20.2%; <italic>P</italic>=0.909).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1352458512454771" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Flow cytometry figures representative of healthy controls (HC).</p>
<p>(A) The detection of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup> memory B cells. (B, C) The detection of B cell activating factor (BAFF-R) and CXCR5 expression on B cells. (D, E) The detection of intracellular expression of interleukin (IL)-10 and interferon (IFN)-γ in B cells. (F) The detection of Th17 cells.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1352458512454771-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1352458512454771">
<title>The expression of BAFF-R, CXCR5 and VLA-4 on peripheral blood B cells</title>
<p>The percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>BAFF-R<sup>+</sup> cells out of the total lymphocytes were significantly higher in NMO (13.5%, 0.5–43.3%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.001) and RRMS (11.7%, 1.9–28.4%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.044) patients than in HC (10.0%, 1.1–16.2%) but were similar in NMO and RRMS groups (<italic>P</italic>=0.112) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1352458512454771">Figures 2(B)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">3(A)</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-1352458512454771" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>The percentages of lymphocyte subsets with different phenotypes and CSF B cell activating factor (BAFF) and CXCL13 levels in relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS), neuromyelitis optica (NMO) and the control groups.</p>
<p>AQP4-ab-: AQP4-ab-negative; AQP4-ab+: AQP4-ab-positive; HC: healthy controls; NS: not significant; OND: other non-inflammatory neurologic diseases.The data are represented by scatter plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(A)</xref> -<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">(E)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">(H)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">(I)</xref>), in which the horizontal line stands for the median; CSF BAFF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(F)</xref>) and CXCL13 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(G)</xref>) levels are presented by column bars showing mean and SD. *<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01 after multiple comparison adjustment.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1352458512454771-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>The percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>CXCR5<sup>+</sup> cells were significantly higher in NMO patients (9.0%, 2.5–23.9%) than in HC (7.1%, 4.2–10.6%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.002) but did not differ significantly between RRMS (7.8%, 1.3–18.3%) and NMO patients (<italic>P</italic>=0.182) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1352458512454771">Figures 2(C)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">3(B)</xref>).</p>
<p>No significant difference in the percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>VLA-4<sup>+</sup> cells was found between groups (NMO, 5.5%, 0.8–22.5%; RRMS, 6.6%, 1.7–16.2%; HC, 5.9%, 0.9–12.9%; <italic>P</italic>=0.785).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1352458512454771">
<title>The expression of IL-10 and IFN-γ by circulating B cells</title>
<p>The proportions of IL-10-expressing B (CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup>) cells out of the total lymphocytes were significantly lower in NMO group (2.0%, 0.2–13.7%) compared with RRMS (3.6%, 0.1–11.3%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.023) and HC (5.4%, 0.6–14.8%) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001), but were not significantly different between RRMS and HC (<italic>P</italic>=0.095) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1352458512454771">Figures 2(D)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">3(C)</xref>). Similar results were obtained when the analysis was done after the 10 patients with positive co-existent serum autoantibodies or the seven NMO patients that had taken oral prednisone were excluded as well as when the analysis was based on absolute CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup> cell numbers.</p>
<p>The percentages of IFN-γ-expressing B (CD19<sup>+</sup>IFN-γ<sup>+</sup>) cells in NMO patients (4.8%, 0.1–25.8%) were significantly higher than those in HC (1.7%, 0.1–10.8%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.012), but were not different from those in RRMS patients (3.2%, 0.2–13.9%) (<italic>P</italic>=0.123) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1352458512454771">Figures 2(E)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">3(D)</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1352458512454771">
<title>Th17 cells</title>
<p>The proportions of Th17 cells out of the total lymphocytes were dramatically elevated in RRMS patients (4.2%, 0.2–12.8%) compared with NMO patients (2.2%, 0.0–12.5%) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) and HC (1.9%, 0.0–10.9%) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) but did not differ significantly between NMO and HC (<italic>P</italic>=0.998) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1352458512454771">Figures 2(F)</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">3(E)</xref>). When the 10 patients with positive co-existent serum autoantibodies or the seven NMO patients that had taken oral prednisone were excluded, essentially the same results were obtained.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1352458512454771">
<title>BAFF and CXCL13 concentrations in CSF</title>
<p>The CSF BAFF concentrations were higher in NMO group (202.0±29.6 pg/mL) than in RRMS (132.4±17.4 pg/mL) (<italic>P</italic>=0.041) and OND groups (132.0±12.3 pg/mL) (<italic>P</italic>=0.031), but were similar between RRMS and OND patients (<italic>P</italic>=0.991) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(F)</xref>).</p>
<p>The CSF CXCL13 concentrations were significantly higher in NMO patients (52.3±18.7 pg/mL) than in RRMS (37.7±10.1 pg/mL) (<italic>P</italic>=0.012) and OND patients (14.0±2.1 pg/mL) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001), and were also higher in RRMS group than in OND group (<italic>P</italic>=0.048) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(G)</xref>).</p>
<p>CSF of the 10 patients with positive co-existent serum autoantibodies or the seven NMO patients on oral prednisone was not included in BAFF and CXCL13 detection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1352458512454771">
<title>Correlation of B cell function with AQP4-ab status in NMO patients</title>
<p>All of the 42 RRMS patients were AQP4-ab-negative. Among the 51 NMO patients, 29 were AQP4-ab-positive and 22 were AQP4-ab-negative. We compared the above-mentioned experimental results between AQP4-ab-positive and -negative NMO patients. Interestingly, the percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> and CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup> cells were even lower in AQP4-ab-positive NMO patients than in AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients (<italic>P</italic>=0.011 and <italic>P</italic>=0.039, respectively) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458512454771">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(H)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">3(I)</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1352458512454771" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Lymphocyte subsets with different phenotypes and CSF cytokine/ chemoattractant levels in AQP4-ab-positive and -negative neuromyelitis optica (NMO) patients.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1352458512454771" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458512454771-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Lymphocyte subsets with different phenotypes and cytokine/chemoattractant levels</th>
<th align="left">AQP4-ab-positive NMO patients (<italic>n</italic>=29)</th>
<th align="left">AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients (<italic>n</italic>=22)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1352458512454771">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup> (%)</td>
<td>1.8±1.0</td>
<td>2.1±1.2</td>
<td>0.467</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> (%)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1352458512454771">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>5.3</td>
<td>8.9</td>
<td>0.011<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458512454771">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>BAFF-R<sup>+</sup> (%)</td>
<td>15.0±8.1</td>
<td>15.2±8.8</td>
<td>0.907</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>CXCR5<sup>+</sup> (%)</td>
<td>9.0±3.8</td>
<td>10.6±5.5</td>
<td>0.228</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>VLA-4<sup>+</sup> (%)</td>
<td>5.2</td>
<td>5.9</td>
<td>0.482</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup> (%)</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458512454771">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD19<sup>+</sup>IFN-γ<sup>+</sup> (%)</td>
<td>6.2±3.9</td>
<td>5.0±5.3</td>
<td>0.367</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Th17 (%)</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>0.857</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CSF BAFF (pg/ml)</td>
<td>195.8±32.1(<italic>n</italic>=19)</td>
<td>208.5±28.3(<italic>n</italic>=18)</td>
<td>0.428</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CSF CXCL13 (pg/ml)</td>
<td>59.0±20.7(<italic>n</italic>=19)</td>
<td>45.3±17.7(<italic>n</italic>=18)</td>
<td>0.702</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1352458512454771"><p>AQP4-ab: aquaporin-4 antibody; BAFF: B cell activating factor; CXCR5: the receptor of the B cell chemoattractant CXCL13; IFN: interferon; IL: interleukin; NMO: neuromyelitis optica; VLA-4: very late antigen-4.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1352458512454771"><p>Normally distributed data are expressed as means±SD and non-normally distributed data are expressed as medians.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-1352458512454771">
<label>a</label>
<p>Significance evaluated by Student’s <italic>t</italic> test or Mann-Whitney U test as appropriate for the data distribution. <sup>b</sup>The percentage out of total B cells.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1352458512454771">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cell percentages were also lower in AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients compared with RRMS patients (<italic>P</italic>=0.012) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(H)</xref>). The percentages of CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup> cells were lower in AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients than in RRMS patients, but this difference was not statistically significant (<italic>P</italic>=0.053) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1352458512454771">Figure 3(I)</xref>).</p>
<p>We also analyzed the correlations of the above-mentioned immunological parameters with disease duration, number of exacerbations, Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score, CSF protein level, CSF cell count, and CSF OB status of NMO and RRMS patients. However, no significant correlation was defined.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1352458512454771" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results revealed that regulatory B cell numbers and B cell expression of IL-10 were significantly decreased in NMO patients in comparison with RRMS patients. We also observed higher CSF levels of BAFF and CXCL13 in NMO patients than in patients with RRMS. These findings further defined the distinct immunological background of NMO and RRMS from the B cell perspective.</p>
<p>Regulatory B cells carry out essential protective functions that might prevent or suppress autoimmunity by secreting regulatory cytokines, such as IL-10 and transforming growth factor (TGF)-β.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1352458512454771">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1352458512454771">24</xref></sup> Deficits in the number or function of regulatory B cells are highly likely to break immunologic self-tolerance and lead to autoimmune disease. The CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> phenotype has been used to identify immature human transitional B cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1352458512454771">28</xref></sup> Afterwards, CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> B cells have been proved to possess immuno-regulatory capacities by producing IL-10 and are functionally impaired in SLE patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1352458512454771">25</xref></sup> A previous report has shown that B cells from MS patients exhibit a decreased average production of IL-10.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1352458512454771">29</xref></sup> However, the regulatory B cells in NMO has not been explored. We demonstrated that CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> regulatory B cells exhibited a profound numerical deficit and that the B cell production of IL-10 was decreased in NMO patients. Even when patients with other co-existent serum autoantibodies or patients on low dose prednisone were excluded, the decrease of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> and CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup> cell levels in NMO group was still significant in comparison with RRMS group. The results indicate that the regulatory function of B cells in NMO patients is impaired. Although we detected less IL-10-expressing B cells in RRMS patients than in HC, the difference was not statistically significant. Moreover, the frequencies of IFN-γ-expressing B cells were higher in NMO patients than in HC, suggesting an enhanced proinflammatory and pathogenic activity of B cells in NMO.</p>
<p>The B cell expression of IL-10 and CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup> CD38<sup>high</sup> regulatory B cell levels was even lower in AQP4-ab-positive NMO patients than in AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients, implying that the suppressive immuno-regulatory function of B cells is even more seriously impaired in AQP4-ab-positive NMO patients.</p>
<p>The numerical deficit of regulatory B cells was found in all of the NMO patients, not only AQP4-ab-positive patients, since the levels of CD19<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>high</sup>CD38<sup>high</sup> cells were also lower in AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients compared with RRMS patients. No significant difference in CD19<sup>+</sup>IL-10<sup>+</sup> cell levels was observed between AQP4-ab-negative NMO patients and RRMS patients, although the <italic>P</italic> value (0.053) was close to 0.05. However, the difference in the sample sizes of the AQP4-ab-negative NMO (<italic>n</italic>=22) and RRMS (<italic>n</italic>=42) groups may have reduced the statistical power of this comparison.</p>
<p>Excess BAFF rescues self-reactive B cells from peripheral deletion and plays an important role in maintaining inflammation and developing autoimmune conditions through its interaction with BAFF-R.<sup><italic>10,30</italic></sup> In the present study, we found an increased percentage of BAFF-R-expressing B cells in NMO patients compared with HC; the CSF BAFF concentrations were also significantly higher in NMO patients than in RRMS and OND patients, in line with a previous report.<sup><italic>18</italic></sup> These findings indicate an enhanced intrathecal activation of B cells in NMO, and further support the pivotal role of B cells and humoral immunity in NMO pathogenesis. However, the alteration of the BAFF-BAFF-R axis was less prominent in RRMS. The levels of BAFF-R-expressing B cells in RRMS patients did not exceed those in NMO patients. The CSF BAFF levels were similar in RRMS and OND patients, consistent with a previous report.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1352458512454771">31</xref></sup></p>
<p>CXCL13 is a selective chemoattractant for B lymphocytes and B helper T cells through its specific receptor CXCR5.<sup><italic>32</italic></sup> CXCL13 is present in active MS lesions and is elevated in the CSF of MS patients.<sup><italic>33</italic></sup> We demonstrated that B cell CXCR5 expression was significantly higher in NMO patients than in HC; the CSF CXCL13 levels were even higher in NMO patients than in RRMS and OND patients, similar to a previous report.<sup><italic>15</italic></sup> Our results indicate that the circulating B cells of NMO patients exhibit a stronger tendency to transmigrate to the site of inflammation within the CNS and that the CNS microenvironment of NMO has a more intense attraction for peripheral B cells.</p>
<p>CSF levels of BAFF and CXCL13 were elevated in the NMO group during relapse. IgG has also been reported to be slightly increased in acute-stage CSF samples from NMO patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1352458512454771">34</xref></sup> However, the median of CSF protein was still within normal range (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1352458512454771">Table 1</xref>) in the NMO group. A possible explanation is that as IgG and small protein molecules such as BAFF and CXCL13 only account for a very limited portion of total CSF protein, the elevation of these molecules might not obviously affect the total CSF protein level. The median of CSF cell counts in NMO group during relapse was 8 /mm<sup>3</sup> (upper limit of normal, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1352458512454771">Table 1</xref>). Almost half of the 51 NMO patients had elevated CSF cell counts. However, the positive correlation between CSF cell count and CSF CXCL13 level, which has been reported by a previous study,<sup><italic>14</italic></sup> was not observed in our investigation.</p>
<p>Moreover, we reported higher Th17 percentages in the peripheral blood of RRMS patients. Previous studies have shown that Th17 cells are important players in the immunopathogenesis of MS.<sup><italic>5</italic></sup> In contrast, higher circulating Th17 cell numbers have been reported in NMO patients compared with MS patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1352458512454771">35</xref></sup> Future investigations of this discrepancy are warranted.</p>
<p>In summary, we demonstrated that the immuno-regulatory abilities of B cells were significantly impaired in NMO patients, particularly in AQP4-ab-positive NMO patients. The elevated CSF BAFF and CXCL13 levels in NMO patients suggested an enhanced intrathecal recruitment and activation of B cells. In contrast, RRMS was characterized by a significant predominance of peripheral Th17 cells. The distinct immunological patterns observed in NMO and MS further support the theory that NMO should not be viewed as a subtype of MS but rather as an independent disease entity that is separate from MS; therefore, the therapeutic strategies used for NMO should be carefully discriminated from those used for MS.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research was supported in part by the Institutes of Brain Science, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest statement</label>
<p>C Quan has received speaker honoraria from Merck Serono and Roche; has received funding for travel from Bayer Schering Pharma; and has received scientific research funding from the institutes of Brain Science, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University.</p>
<p>H Yu has received speaker honoraria from Merck Serono.</p>
<p>J Qiao, G Zhao and B Xiao report no disclosures.</p>
<p>Z Wu has received research grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (30971013, 30911120488); has received Chinese National Natural Science Funds for Distinguished Young Scientists (81125009); and has received funding for travel from Biogen Idec.</p>
<p>Z Li has received speaker honoraria from Merck Serono and Bayer Schering Pharma and has received funding for travel from Bayer Schering Pharma.</p>
<p>C Lu serves as honorary editor-in-chief of the Chinese Journal of Neurology and Chinese Journal of Clinical Neurosciences; has received speaker honoraria from Merck Serono and Bayer Schering Pharma; and has received funding for travel from Bayer Schering Pharma</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1352458512454771">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the clinical phenotypes of multiple sclerosis during the past 50 years in Japan</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1352458512454771">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Multiple sclerosis in the Japanese population</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1352458512454771">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wingerchuk</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogancamp</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The clinical course of neuromyelitis optica (Devic’s syndrome)</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1107</fpage>–<lpage>1114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1352458512454771">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wingerchuk</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kryzer</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A serum autoantibody marker of neuromyelitis opica: distinction from multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>2106</fpage>–<lpage>2112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1352458512454771">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jadidi-Niaragh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mirshafiey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Th17 cell, the new player of neuroinflammatory process in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Scand J Immunol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1352458512454771">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roemer</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pattern specific loss of aquaporin 4 immunoreactivity distinguishes neuromyelitis optica from multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1194</fpage>–<lpage>1205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1352458512454771">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krecke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Brain abnormalities in neuromyelitis optica</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1352458512454771">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waubant</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>B-cell depletion with rituximab in relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Eng J Med</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>358</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1352458512454771">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Repeated treatment with rituximab based on the assessment of peripheral circulating memory B cells in patients with relapsing neuromyelitis optica over 2 years</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>1412</fpage>–<lpage>1420</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1352458512454771">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dalakas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Invited article: inhibition of B cell functions: implications for neurology</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>2252</fpage>–<lpage>2260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1352458512454771">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krumbholz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cepok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Chemokines in multiple sclerosis: CXCL12 and CXCL13 up-regulation is differentially linked to CNS immune cell recruitment</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1352458512454771">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalinowska-Łyszczarz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szczuciński</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawlak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical study on CXCL13, CCL17, CCL20 and IL-17 as immune cell migration navigators in relapsing−remitting multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>300</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1352458512454771">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sellebjerg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bornsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khademi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increased cerebrospinal fluid concentrations of the chemokine CXCL13 in active MS</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>2003</fpage>–<lpage>2010</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1352458512454771">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khademi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kockum</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cerebrospinal fluid CXCL13 in multiple sclerosis: a suggestive prognostic marker for the disease course</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1352458512454771">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cerebrospinal fluid levels of CXCL13 are elevated in neuromyelitis optica</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimmunol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>240–241</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1352458512454771">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krumbholz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Derfuss</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>BAFF is produced by astrocytes and up-regulated in multiple sclerosis lesions and primary central nervous system lymphoma</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>201</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1352458512454771">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thangarajh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masterman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Expression of B-cell-activating factor of the TNF family (BAFF) and its receptors in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimmunol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1352458512454771">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>B-cell activating factor of the TNF family is upregulated in neuromyelitis optica</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1352458512454771">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaknin-Dembinsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orpaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preferential increase of B-cell activating factor in the cerebrospinal fluid of neuromyelitis optica in a white population</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1453</fpage>–<lpage>1457</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1352458512454771">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knopf</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harling-Berg</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cserr</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Antigendependent intrathecal antibody synthesis in the normal rat brain: tissue entry and local retention of antigenspecific B cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>692</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1352458512454771">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duddy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adatia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Distinct effector cytokine profiles of memory and naïve human B cell subsets and implication in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>6092</fpage>–<lpage>6099</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1352458512454771">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Cytokine-producing B lymphocytes - key regulators of immunity</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Immunol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1352458512454771">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>B cells as therapeutic targets in SLE</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Rheumatol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1352458512454771">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mauri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ehrenstein</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>The ‘short’ history of regulatory B cells</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1352458512454771">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norena</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flores-Borja</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>CD19+CD24hiCD38hi B cells exhibit regulatory capacity in healthy individuals but are functionally impaired in systemic lupus erythematosus patients</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1352458512454771">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Polman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic criteria for multiple sclerosis: 2005 revisions to the McDonald Criteria</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>840</fpage>–<lpage>846</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1352458512454771">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wingerchuk</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Revised diagnostic criteria for neuromyelitis optica</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1485</fpage>–<lpage>1489</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1352458512454771">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carsetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosado</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wardemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Peripheral development of B cells in mouse and man</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1352458512454771">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hirotani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fukazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decreased IL-10 production mediated by Toll-like receptor 9 in B cells in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimmunol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>221</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1352458512454771">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Cracking the BAFF code</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1352458512454771">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiFrancesco</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fusco</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cerebrospinal fluid levels of BAFF and APRIL in untreated multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimmunol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1352458512454771">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krensky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Chemokines, chemokine receptors, and allograft rejection</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1352458512454771">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brettschneider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czerwoniak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Senel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The chemokine CXCL13 is a prognostic marker in clinically isolated syndrome (CIS)</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e11986</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1352458512454771">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cerebrospinal fluid/serum gradient of IgG is associated with disability at acute attacks of neuromyelitis optica</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>258</volume>: <fpage>2176</fpage>–<lpage>2180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1352458512454771">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interleukin-17-secreting T cells in neuromyelitis optica and multiple sclerosis during relapse</article-title>. <source>J Clin Neurosci</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1313</fpage>–<lpage>1317</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>