<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwmr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Waste Manag Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Waste Management &amp; Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-242X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-3669</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734242X12455089</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734242X12455089</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New developments in waste management in the Netherlands</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Goorhuis</surname><given-names>Maarten</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X12455089">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Reus</surname><given-names>Pieter</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0734242X12455089">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nieuwenhuis</surname><given-names>Ellen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0734242X12455089">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Spanbroek</surname><given-names>Natascha</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0734242X12455089">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sol</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0734242X12455089">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>van Rijn</surname><given-names>Jørgen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0734242X12455089">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0734242X12455089"><label>1</label>NVRD, Dutch Solid Waste Association, Arnhem, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0734242X12455089"><label>2</label>SRE Milieudienst, Eindhoven, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0734242X12455089"><label>3</label>N.V. ROVA, Zwolle, the Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0734242X12455089"><label>4</label>Ryck, de Nederlandse Recycle bank, Nootdorp, the Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0734242X12455089">Maarten Goorhuis, NVRD, Dutch Solid Waste Association, Arnhem, the Netherlands, P.O. Box 1218, Arnhem, 6801 BE, the Netherlands Email: <email>goorhuis@nvrd.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>9_suppl</issue>
<issue-title>Florence 2012 Special Issue Leading papers from the ISWA World Solid Waste Congress</issue-title>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<lpage>77</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Solid Waste Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>With a current recycling rate of 51% the Netherlands has one of the leading positions in the recycling of household waste in Europe. However, in the last 10–15 years there have been few developments made in the recycling of household waste. The introduction of producer responsibility for waste electrical and electronic equipment in 1999 and for packaging in 2005 have been the biggest changes in this period. However, these measures have, so far, not significantly influenced the overall recycling rate for household waste. In order to plan the next steps, which are necessary to reach the goals of the National Waste Management plan, new innovative methods are needed. A number of Dutch municipalities and waste collection companies are investigating promising new paths to enhance separate collection and recycling of household waste. This article reports on three of the most interesting initiatives.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Household waste</kwd>
<kwd>recycling</kwd>
<kwd>separate collection</kwd>
<kwd>innovation</kwd>
<kwd>waste policy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0734242X12455089" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>With a current recycling rate of 51% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X12455089">Ministerie van VROM, 2010</xref>) the Netherlands has one of the leading positions in the recycling of household waste in Europe. However, in the last 10–15 years there have been few developments made in the recycling of household waste. The introduction of producer responsibility for waste electrical and electronic equipment (WEEE) in 1999 and for packaging in 2005 have been the biggest changes in this period. However, these measures have, so far, not significantly influenced the overall recycling rate for household waste. In order to plan the next steps that are necessary to reach the goals of the National Waste Management plan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X12455089">Ministerie van VROM, 2010</xref>), new, innovative methods are needed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X12455089">NVRD, 2012</xref>). A number of Dutch municipalities and waste collection companies are investigating promising new paths to enhance separate collection and recycling of household waste. This article reports on three of the most interesting initiatives. Not all of these have reached a final evaluation phase yet. Therefore, most of the results shown in this article are still preliminary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0734242X12455089">
<title>Current waste management and policy development</title>
<p>The annual waste generation in the Netherlands has risen since 1985 from 47 Mton to 63 Mton in 2000, and then decreased to 60 Mton in 2006. Over this period a total rise of 27% was measured, whereas gross domestic product (GDP) has risen with 73% over the same period. In this timeframe, waste treatment has shifted from disposal towards recovery. The total material recovery rate of all Dutch waste (excluding contaminated soil, sludge and manure) has risen from 50% to 83%, and the landfilling of waste has decreased from 35% to 4% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X12455089">Ministerie van VROM, 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12455089">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the development of the total waste production and treatment since 1985.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Development of total waste amounts (excluding contaminated soil, sludge and manure) and treatment methods in the Netherlands.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The management of household waste in this period also changed significantly. In 1985 there was hardly any infrastructure for separate collection and recycling available. Some municipalities had bottle banks, but any other form of recycling was scarce and organized mainly through charity organisations that collected material streams (clothing, paper/cardboard). Most household waste was landfilled or incinerated.</p>
<p>In the 1990s the policy focus shifted from the disposal of waste towards the recycling of waste. In 1993 the separate collection and treatment of organic and garden waste became mandatory. The separate collection of other recyclable waste streams was encouraged through the programme for the separate collection of household waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X12455089">AOO, 1995</xref>). In this programme the so-called ‘most desirable methods’ were established for organic waste, paper and cardboard, glass and textiles. Although every municipality is responsible for the management of municipal waste in its own region and is free in choosing the waste collection methods and instruments, this has resulted in a more or less a common collection scheme than can be recognised in most Dutch municipalities. The core of this system consists of an alternate kerbside collection of organic and garden waste, and residual waste supplemented by different collections systems for recyclables, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X12455089">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Common collection scheme for household waste in the Netherlands.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0734242X12455089" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Kerbside</th>
<th align="left">Bring facility</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Organic and garden waste</td>
<td>Every other week</td>
<td>Recycling centre</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Paper/cardboard</td>
<td>Monthly</td>
<td>Drop off point</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Glass</td>
<td/>
<td>Drop off point</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Textile</td>
<td>Quarterly</td>
<td>Drop off point</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plastic packaging</td>
<td>Monthly</td>
<td>Drop off point</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WEEE</td>
<td/>
<td>Recycling centre/retail</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hazardous waste</td>
<td/>
<td>Recycling centre</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bulky waste</td>
<td>Differs</td>
<td>Recycling centre</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Residual waste</td>
<td>Every other week</td>
<td>Recycling centre</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0734242X12455089">
<p>WEEE, waste electrical and electronic equipment.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Besides the mandatory collection of organic and garden waste, and residual waste, most municipalities will have at least a collection system for paper and cardboard, glass, plastic packaging, WEEE, and hazardous and bulky waste. Municipalities are also obliged to have a Municipal Recycling Centre, where separated waste can be delivered. Most of these sites have been built to accept more than 20 different separated waste streams. The collection and recycling of WEEE and packaging is managed on the basis of extended producer responsibility.</p>
<p>Over the years this system, which may vary among municipalities, has lead to a total recycling rate for household waste of 51% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X12455089">CBS, 2011</xref>). This rate has not changed significantly over the last 10 years. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0734242X12455089">Table 2</xref> shows the average amount of segregated and non-segregated (residual) waste streams of Dutch households in 2010.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Amounts of segregated and residual waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X12455089">CBS, 2011</xref>).</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0734242X12455089" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">kg/cap (2010)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Non-segregated residual waste streams</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Residual household waste</td>
<td>226</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Residual bulky waste</td>
<td>37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Residual construction and demolition waste</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Separated waste streams</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Organic waste</td>
<td>76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Paper and cardboard</td>
<td>64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Packaging glass</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Textile</td>
<td>4.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hazardous waste</td>
<td>1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Metal packaging (cans)</td>
<td>0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Beverage cartons</td>
<td>0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Plastic packaging</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other plastics</td>
<td>0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Carpets</td>
<td>0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> WEEE</td>
<td>5.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Garden waste</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Reusable furniture</td>
<td>2.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Window panes</td>
<td>0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Metals</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Wood</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Clean bricks, etc.</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asbestos</td>
<td>0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tires</td>
<td>0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Clean soil</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tarmac roof-toppings</td>
<td>0.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other separated waste</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total household waste</td>
<td>534.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0734242X12455089">
<p>WEEE, waste electrical and electronic equipment.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the National Waste Management Plan the Dutch government stated its ambitions and targets for the period 2010–2022. The ambition is to raise the total recovery rate of all Dutch waste from 83% to 85% in 2015. For the recycling of household waste, the ambition is to raise the recovery rate from 51% to 60% in 2015 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X12455089">Ministerie van VROM, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>The composition of the Dutch residual waste is monitored annually. The results, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12455089">Figure 2</xref>, show that residual waste still contains large quantities of usable/valuable waste streams that could have been offered for recycling. More than one third of the residual waste consists of organic and garden waste, and more than 20% consists of paper and cardboard. In fact, nearly the entire contents of a Dutch residual waste bin could be recycled. This means that there is still plenty of room for improvement.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Composition of residual household waste.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Given the fact that the Dutch recycling rate has made no significant improvement over the last 10 years, it is not likely that this 9% extra can be reached through optimisation of the current waste management system; instead, a new shift is needed in the management of household waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X12455089">NVRD, 2012</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0734242X12455089">
<title>New developments in waste collection</title>
<p>A number of municipalities, regions and waste collection companies are, at this moment, investigating new methods to innovate the separate collection and recycling of household waste with the aims of yielding higher amounts of recyclables and decreasing the amount of residual waste. Essentially, these methods are based on two principles:</p>
<list id="list1-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>enhancing service for the collection of recyclables and at the same time decreasing service for the collection of residual waste;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>rewarding source separation of recyclables.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Three of the most interesting projects in this area are highlighted in the following sections.</p>
<sec id="section4-0734242X12455089">
<title>Eindhoven region</title>
<p>The organisation <italic>Cityregion Eindhoven</italic> (SRE) is an intermunicipal co-operative union in which municipalities co-operate in order to promote common interests. The working area covers 21 municipalities with a total population of 740,000 residents and 45,000 businesses.</p>
<sec id="section5-0734242X12455089">
<title>SRE programmes: Energy transition and materials transition</title>
<p>To assist the need for transition into a more sustainable economy SRE started two regional programmes to drive tangible results in renewable energy and reusable materials. The aim of the programme for material transition is re-design of the current linear production systems into sustainable circular production systems to provide clean, reliable, reusable and affordable materials for Eindhoven. The strategy of these programmes is based on co-creation between local government, knowledge and research institutes, and industry. The focus is on the whole production chain (starting with an eco-effective design and ending the production chain with a reverse system for disposed materials ).</p>
<p>The focus in the projects described here is on optimisation and innovation of collection systems for materials of which households daily dispose of.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0734242X12455089">
<title>Pilots for kerbside waste collection in Cranendonck</title>
<p>In 2010 SRE assisted the municipality of Cranendonck during the preparation of a new tender for kerbside waste collection. Prior to the tender a system analysis was made with the following key insights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X12455089">SRE Milieudienst, 2009</xref>):</p>
<list id="list2-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>each inhabitant discards an average of 174 kg residual waste per year;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>98.5% of collected residual waste is recyclable;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>20% of all households offers the grey bin for residual waste every possible moment; 10% never offers a residual waste bin for collection;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>an average household offers 12 grey bins for waste collection a year; singular person household: 8 bins; 2-person households offer 12 bins; and multiple-person households: 16 bins;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the average volume of the residual waste bin is large (240 l) compared with municipalities with similar collection systems;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>each inhabitant discards on average 43 kgs of organic and garden waste a year;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>65% of all organic and garden waste is discarded in the residual waste bin instead of the organic and garden waste bin;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>60% of all households never offer the green bin for organic and garden waste for collection;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>an average household offers three bins for organic and garden waste a year for collection;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the volume/frequency based pay-as-you-throw (PAYT) system does not encourage residents to separate organic waste as there is no price or service differentiation between organic and residual waste.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Other elements for a more effective system were presented by SRE to the municipality. Advised key elements were:</p>
<list id="list3-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>change of tariffs for organic and garden waste, and residual waste;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>increase the collection frequency for organic waste and plastic packaging;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>reduce the collection frequency of residual waste;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>use smaller bins for residual waste.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In consultation with the contracted waste management company, the key elements to implement first were tariffs and collection frequencies.</p>
<p>The plan was to organize 4 pilots in 2 (out of 7) representative villages within a 12-month period. A project approach (including targets, preconditions, timeframe, mile stones, communication, budget, etc.) was designed to implement a range of pilots with the following targets:</p>
<list id="list4-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>collection of more organic and garden waste than the amount of residual waste;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>40% reduction of residual waste in relation to 2008.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The most important preconditions were:</p>
<list id="list5-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>support and commitment of the neighbourhood council for the pilots;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>obliged participation of all residents.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Communication was an important factor for success. In each village two information sessions were held to obtain support for the pilots and to organise a community participation group. The start up of the process was made top-down, as well as bottom-up, to ensure a broad co-operation. Volunteers were asked to assist the municipality with the distribution of flyers informing participants about the first results of the pilots. This request resulted in local ambassadors supporting the pilots and a changed mind-set of participants.</p>
<p>In the next sections these four pilots are discussed, starting with a description of three pilots aimed at optimization. The fourth pilot describes an innovative reverse system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0734242X12455089">
<title>Pilots 1, 2 and 3 for optimisation of separate collection</title>
<p>The villages of Budel-Schoot and Soerendonk are representative, with 3800 residents out of 20,300 citizens of the rural municipality of Cranendonck. The first pilot in these two villages was the separated collection of three components, namely incontinence waste (absorbent hygiene products, diapers), metal, and beverage carton packaging by means of extended neighbourhood drop-off facilities (three in total) in both villages.</p>
<p>In addition to these extended drop-off facilities the collection frequency for plastic packaging was increased from a monthly basis to a two-weekly basis in one village, but unchanged in the other pilot village. After three months the collection scheme of plastic packaging was switched between the two villages (second pilot). After six months the third pilot started with an increased collection frequency for organic and garden waste, and a reduced collection frequency for residual waste. The plan to change tariffs in the pilot areas (to investigate the impact of tariffs on the behaviour of respondents to do more waste separation) was rejected because of possible claims from residents in other areas. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0734242X12455089">Table 3</xref> provides an overview of the interventions in the different pilot areas.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Overview of interventions in the different pilot areas. The results of these pilots can be distinguished between social, environmental and financial results.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0734242X12455089" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Before</th>
<th align="left">Intervention</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Pilot 1</bold><break/>Four thousand inhabitants<break/>Two small villages<break/></td>
<td>Volume/frequency PAYT-system (€7.40 for residual waste and €7.40 for organic waste)</td>
<td>Plastic packaging collection increased to 26 times a year</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Alternate kerbside collection of residual waste (240 l) and organic waste (240 l), each 26 times a year</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Kerbside collection of plastics packaging in orange bags (60 l) each month</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Paper and cardboard collection and drop-off points (e.g. containers at associations and schools)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Pilot 2</bold><break/>Four thousand inhabitants<break/>Small villages</td>
<td>See pilot 1</td>
<td>Volume/frequency PAYT-system (€8.50 for residual waste and €5.50 for organic waste)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Thirteen times a year collection for residual waste and 26 times a year for organic waste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Pilot 3</bold><break/>Twenty thousand inhabitants<break/>Residential area and small villages</td>
<td>See pilot 1</td>
<td>Volume/frequency PAYT-system (€12.50 for residual waste and €1.25 for organic waste)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Thirteen times a year collection for residual waste and 26 times a year for organic waste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Plastic packaging collection increased to 26 times a year</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Metal and beverage carton packaging collection for 26 times a year with a yellow bag (60 litres)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0734242X12455089">
<p>PAYT, Pay As You Throw.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<list id="list6-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Social</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>A broad inquiry in the pilot areas learned that saving the environment and reducing individual costs for respondents were the main reasons for participants to separate waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X12455089">SRE Milieudienst, 2010a</xref>). Despite the several system changes, 92% of people knew what they had to do. However, respondents deliberately disposed of waste in the residual waste bin that could have been separated in the organic waste bin. The decrease in collection frequency after three months for plastic packaging resulted in an unpleasant surprise for the residents who missed this extra service in the new pilot phase. In particular, organic and garden waste was disposed of in the residual waste bin because of hygiene issues and smell. The drop-off facilities became unwanted owing to dump and hygiene problems. These facilities were not under surveillance and turned into public dump areas after four months.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list7-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Environmental</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The results of a new collection scheme for residual waste was a reduction of 43% residual waste in the pilot areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X12455089">SRE Milieudienst, 2010b</xref>). The quantity of organic and garden waste was slightly higher, and the quantity of packaging and incontinence waste showed a strong increase. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12455089">Figure 3</xref> shows the trend of the main three waste fractions from 1997 to 2011. In 1999 a fortnight-alternating collection scheme for organic and garden waste, and residual waste was implemented with an equal pay per throw tariffs for organic waste and residual waste. In 2009 the separate collection of plastic packaging waste was introduced. The plan to change tariffs in the pilot areas was not possible. In order to achieve an extra reduction of residual waste tariffs were changed for the whole municipality in 2011. As a result this change gave an extra reduction of residual waste.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<fig id="fig3-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Cranendonck: trend of residual waste, organic and garden waste, and plastic packaging waste for the years 1997–2011. VFG or VGF waste, organic and garden waste.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<list id="list8-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Finance</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The execution of pilots gave extra costs in 2010, but the broad introduction in 2011 of the best practices gained from the pilots gave an overall budget reduction of 25% for the entire municipality. This reduction was achieved by higher yields of recyclable materials and avoided residual waste. The budget cut was 19% for the year 2011 in comparison with 2010 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X12455089">SRE Milieudienst, 2010b</xref>).</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In general, the implementation process ran smoothly and according to plan. The timeframe of three months per pilot was too short; after four months the results became regular and reliable. The extra work for municipal servants gave some friction with daily responsibilities, but external assistance helped out.</p>
<p>After these three optimization pilots the municipality council agreed to:</p>
<list id="list9-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>close down the extended drop-off facilities in the pilot areas;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>introduce an extra bag for metal and beverage cartons packaging (which are not included in the producer responsibilities schemes) with a kerbside collection for all residents in substitution for the closed down-drop-off facilities;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>implement a weekly collection of organic and garden waste with a low pay-per-throw tariff (€1.25 per collection) for all residents;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>implement a two-weekly collection of plastic packaging for all residents, preferably combined with metal and beverage carton packaging (all packaging materials in one storage facility);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>implement a four-weekly collection of residual waste with a high pay-per-throw tariff (€12.50 per collection) for all residents.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0734242X12455089">
<title>Pilot 4: Innovation for a house-to-house reverse system in Soerendonk (Cranendonck)</title>
<p>One of the main purposes of the regional SRE programme ‘Material Transition’ is substitution of prime materials by recovered materials as recourses for production facilities. Quality, quantity and (lack of) contamination of materials are key issues for that purpose. After the implementation of three successful pilots for optimisation the municipality agreed to a showcase. The objective of this showcase was to prove that a reverse system for material disposals, delivering high quality and quantity of recyclables, is already possible in the Netherlands. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0734242X12455089">Figure 4</xref> illustrates the questions that shaped the conditions for a system, with a major focus on convenience at home, as well as delivery of desired materials to the recycling business.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Helping the residents at home.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The village of Soerendonk was asked to arrange 50 households, divided in co-operative and non-co-operative (mandatory) ‘volunteers’ and with (very) young and old(er) families. All participants signed an agreement to exchange the residual waste bin for a home storage set of bins and boxes (in co-operation with local bin producer, Brabantia). The design of this reverse system was kept deliberately close to the habits and hygienic needs of participants and simplified with pre-coloured bags for use in the provided storage system, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0734242X12455089">Table 4</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Storage facilities for different types of waste.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0734242X12455089" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Waste type</th>
<th align="left">Storage facility</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Garden waste</td>
<td>Regular 240 l bin (outside use)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Organic kitchen waste</td>
<td>Small (20 l) compostable green bag at home</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Incontinence waste</td>
<td>Foldable cardboard box with white plastic bag at home</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plastic packaging waste</td>
<td>Bin (50 l) with orange plastic bag at home</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Glass packaging waste</td>
<td>Foldable cardboard box at home</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Textile waste</td>
<td>Foldable cardboard box at home</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stuff (various objects)</td>
<td>Foldable cardboard box at home</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hazardous waste</td>
<td>Small bin (25 l) with blue plastic bag</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>A comprehensive ABC-list with clear instructions gave users insight on how items should be stored in eight fractions. The participants were free to hand over any fractions three times a week (Monday, Wednesday and Friday). The municipality collected all disposed bags and boxes in one collection round.</p>
<p>Again, the results of this pilot can be distinguished between social, environmental and financial results.</p>
<list id="list10-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Social</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>A brief inquiry learned that 75% of the participants did not miss the residual waste bin. In addition, 20% indicated a weekly collection of recyclables to be sufficient, 37% requested collection twice a week and 43% three times per week. The provided set of bins was used partly by the participants. In particular, the storage systems for paper (foldable box), kitchen waste and glass-packaging waste suited the residents well. At the final meeting the participants requested that the system be continued, even when it meant they had to pay more. The most important motives were the extra service and the personal reward that one could actually make a difference between waste and recovered materials.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list11-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Environmental</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>After 10 weeks a sound examination of the collected materials was made with the result that only 165 kgs of residual waste was collected compared with 4400 kgs of separated materials. In previous years the amount of residual waste for the same period and group was about 4000 kgs. The pilot ended after 26 weeks and gave an extrapolated result of 6 kgs residual waste per capita in a year. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X12455089">Figure 5</xref> illustrates the collected quantity of materials extrapolated from 26 weeks to 52 weeks.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<fig id="fig5-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Cranendonck: Collected quantities of recovered materials in kg per capita per year. inco waste, Absorbent Hygiene Products; VF waste, organic kitchen waste (Source: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0734242X12455089">SRE Milieudienst, 2011</xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<list id="list12-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Financial</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>This pilot was meant to be a showcase. The small scale gave no clear insight in costs for logistics and yields for recovered materials. A calculation with components as extra costs for logistics, avoided costs for incineration and extra yields for recovered materials gave, theoretically, a positive budget cut on a larger scale. However, this result needs to be tested at a significant scale.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>It was concluded that a near zero waste system is already possible when residents are offered an extensive service both in terms of collection frequency and in terms of convenient storage facilities for the collection of recyclables. Such as system needs to be combined with elaborate guidance of the participants using the system. A weekly collection round is the minimum, otherwise the organic kitchen waste will develop too much odour. Most participants in the pilot, however, requested a higher collection rate of 2–3 collections per week.</p>
<p>The regular collection trucks and methods were not suited for this type of waste collection. Therefore, in the pilot, it has not become clear whether the tested system could be economically viable.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section9-0734242X12455089">
<title>Reverse collection system</title>
<sec id="section10-0734242X12455089">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>ROVA is a non-profit, public waste collection company, producer of sustainable energy and sustainable public space management. Their stakeholders are 18 municipalities in the east of the Netherlands. ROVA is specialised in waste management, consultancy and directing, and serves 2 cities with an urban environment and 16 more rural villages, together more than 300,000 households and over 750,000 inhabitants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0734242X12455089">ROVA, 2011a</xref>). ROVA developed a strategy for contribution to an ambitious waste reduction target between 2012 and 2020.</p>
<p>ROVA has introduced a frequency based PAYT (Pay As You Throw)-system in 2000. The introduction of PAYT has lead to a reduction of 20% on the cost of household waste collection and generated a residual waste reduction of 25%. Social awareness on waste prevention has risen among the residents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X12455089">ROVA, 2011b</xref>).</p>
<p>After the introduction of PAYT a decline in the quantity of residual waste per household was noticed. However, stabilisation of this decrease has been observed since 2010. To again achieve a significant reduction of residual waste improvement in the collection of reusable waste flows, a new change was felt to be necessary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0734242X12455089">
<title>Aim</title>
<p>“From waste to resource” has been ROVA’s strategy since October 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X12455089">ROVA, 2009</xref>). From that perspective a residual waste reduction from 174 kg per capita in 2011 to 30 kg in 2020 is aspired to. Separating waste into a number of main reusable flows grants a higher service on these flows and discouraging residual waste is ROVA’s main method in achieving the objective of further waste reduction. A collection model was developed in which organic and garden waste, plastics, paper and cardboard is collected at kerbside. Residual waste is no longer collected at kerbside but has to be taken to drop-off facilities, such as underground containers. This model is called “Reverse Collection system”.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0734242X12455089">
<title>Design</title>
<sec id="section13-0734242X12455089">
<title>Pilots. 2010–2011: Testing new systems</title>
<p>To test this new system and the effect of a higher service on reusable flows three pilot studies were carried out from 2010 to 2011. A higher service level and a restraining measure on solid waste was tested. Making it easier and attractive to separate reusable materials.</p>
<p>In three districts more or less similar collecting schemes have been tested. Two districts were situated in an urban area and one in a more rural area with a PAYT-system.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X12455089">Table 5</xref> shows the approach in the different pilot areas.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption><p>Overview of the interventions in the different pilots areas.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0734242X12455089" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Before</th>
<th align="left">Intervention</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Raalte (pilot area )</bold></td>
<td>PAYT-system (volume + frequency)</td>
<td>Extra containers for plastics (240 l and paper and cardboard (180 l).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One thousand nine hundred and seventy-five inhabitants</td>
<td>Alternate kerbside collection of residual waste (240 l) and organic waste (140 l or 240 l )</td>
<td>Change of collection frequency for organic waste and residual waste: once every three weeks instead of every two weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Small village</td>
<td>Kerbside collection of plastics packaging in bags (60 l).</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Paper and cardboard at drop-off points (e.g. containers at associations and schools).</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Amersfoort (pilot area)</bold></td>
<td>Kerbside collection of residual waste (240 l), organic waste (140 l) and paper &amp; card board (180 l)</td>
<td>Extra container for plastics (240 l)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One thousand four hundred and ninety-five inhabitants
<break/>Residential area</td>
<td>Plastics at drop-off points (street-containers)</td>
<td>Smaller container for residual waste (140 l instead of 240 l)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Zwolle (pilot area)</bold></td>
<td>Kerbside collection of residual waste (240 l or 140 l), organic waste (240 l), and paper and cardboard (180 l)</td>
<td>Extra container for plastic packaging (240 l)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One thousand six hundred and fifty inhabitants</td>
<td/>
<td>Residual waste in a drop-off point (underground containers)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Residential area</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0734242X12455089">
<p>PAYT, Pay As You Throw.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0734242X12455089">
<title>Pilot study aim: Reverse collection</title>
<p>In January 2012 a new pilot in the village Hoonhorst was introduced. In this study a reduction of residual waste to 76 kg per household (30 kg/capita) in 1 year is challenged. Before the pilot the village produced an average of 387 kg per household, which came down to a reduction target of 80% in 12 months (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0734242X12455089">ROVA, 2012</xref>). In this pilot offering residual waste was discouraged by means of a physical barrier (i.e. taking the residual waste to a collection point) or by a lower collection frequency Two underground containers for 722 households have been located in the heart of the village and these households have removed their residual waste bin. In addition, for the bin for organic and garden waste every household received two extra containers, one for plastics, metals and beverage cartons, and one for paper and cardboard.</p>
<p>Households in the more rural part of the village kept their bin for residual waste. Only the collection frequency has changed from once every two weeks, to once every four weeks. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0734242X12455089">Table 6</xref> provides an overview of the interventions in this pilot.</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption><p>Overview of the interventions in the Hoonhorst pilots area.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0734242X12455089" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Before</th>
<th align="left">After</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Hoonhorst (pilot area)</bold></td>
<td>PAYT-system (volume/frequency) on organic waste and residual waste</td>
<td>PAYT-system (volume/frequency) on residual waste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One thousand nine hundred inhabitants</td>
<td>Kerbside collection of residual waste ( 140 l or 240 l) in both the heart of the village as in the more rural part</td>
<td>Underground collection system for residual waste (in the heart of the village)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Small village</td>
<td>Kerbside collection of organic waste (140 l or 240 l) only in the heart of the village</td>
<td>Change of collection frequency for residual waste in the more rural part of the village</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Organic waste (240 l) collection in the whole village</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Extra container for plastic, metals and beverage cartons (240 l)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Extra container for paper and cardboard (240 l)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0734242X12455089">
<p>PAYT, Pay As You Throw.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Before the pilot started a residents survey has been carried out, where the residents have been questioned on their, knowledge, opinion and behaviour towards source sorting separation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0734242X12455089">
<title>Results</title>
<list id="list13-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Environmental</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The aim of the new collection system is a significant reduction of residual waste and increase of source separation. Through testing three different schemes in different environments getting more insight into what scheme is more efficient depending on the properties of area was attempted.</p>
<p>The introduction of the separate collection bin for plastic packaging in Amersfoort, Raalte and Zwolle resulted in a significant decrease in residual waste, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X12455089">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<fig id="fig6-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Residual waste reduction in pilot areas.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Owing to the increased service level on resource materials the following outcomes became clear on the first results of the pilot in Hoonhorst. The residual household waste results show that there has been discouragement by introducing in a physical barrier for the inhabitants. There has been an average decrease of 60% of residual household waste in Hoonhorst. For the rural population, a 45% decrease was measured and for the centre of the village 80% of the residual household waste was reduced (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X12455089">Figure 7</xref>). Based on the results of the first quarter of the testing phase, it is estimated that Hoonhorst will reach their set targets over time. It was unexpected that by introducing a physical barrier and increasing the service on resource materials that it would change the mind-set of its inhabitants with such strong results .</p>
<fig id="fig7-0734242X12455089" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Residual waste reduction in Hoonhorst.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12455089-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>For the rural population, however, there are still measures and challenges to overcome to reach the target goals set.</p>
<list id="list14-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Social</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>In the pilot districts a majority inhabitants was not positive toward the pilot from the beginning onward. In Amersfoort and Raalte they did not accept a third or fourth container, and in Zwolle and Hoonhorst the residents were not enthusiastic about taking their residual waste to an underground street container. The citizens have been informed as completely as possible and there have been several forums where they could discuss with representatives from ROVA and the municipality. This resulted in considerably more understanding why the models were tested.</p>
<p>Raalte, Amersfoort and Zwolle have a participation rate of more than 85%. During the studies inhabitants became more aware of their behaviour and were willing to co-operate and change their waste behaviour. Halfway through the studies resident surveys were carried out in the three districts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X12455089">Marintel and Onderzoek en Advies, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X12455089">Onderzoek and Statistiek Zwolle, 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X12455089">20011b</xref>) . Ninety-two percent of the participants in Zwolle are offering their plastics separated. Eighty percent did not separate plastics previously. This is a remarkable result and shows that a higher service at home (a container for plastics) realises a positive behaviour change. Also, 70% of the participants in Amersfoort state that they separate more plastics during the study than before.</p>
<p>In advance of the pilot in Hoonhorst a survey of residents was carried out which focused on knowledge, motivation and behaviour related to waste. Also, the residents have participated in giving their vote for the location of the underground street containers. Ninety-three percent of the residents accepted the container for paper and cardboard, and ninety-six percent accepted the container for plastic packaging, metal cans and beverage cartons. The residents’ survey shows that knowledge on waste processing can be improved. The attitude towards waste separation is positive, basically because of the perceived environmental benefit, the sense of personal responsibility and because they feel it’s a small effort to make. Sixty percent of the respondents say their waste behaviour will improve when this leads to a lowered waste disposal.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list15-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Financial</italic></p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The challenge is to enhance the environmental performance of the waste management system without raising the costs to our citizens. It would be even better if a financial reward for those who perform very well on waste separation could be attributed. The ideal model is a double service on reusable materials: infrastructural and financial.</p>
<p>Based on the cost calculation from ROVA it is possible to implement the system of ‘reverse collection’ without extra cost to the citizens and with the possibility of financially rewarding those with good results on waste separation. The higher service on the collection of recyclables is financed by the lower cost on the processing of waste.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0734242X12455089">
<title>Implementation</title>
<p>Based on the results of the pilots ROVA has presented the model of reverse collection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X12455089">ROVA, 2011b</xref>) to its municipalities. The core message of the new measurements is:</p>
<list id="list16-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>high service for the inhabitants on recyclables, lower service on residual waste;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>confidence in the participation of inhabitants;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>no overall increase in cost and rewarding active citizens.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>What is different to the original system is the physical barrier (implemented in the ultimate phase of the reverse collection system) by taking the residual waste to a drop-off point. Kerbside collection is reversed from residual waste collection to only material streams collection.</p>
<p>Important in the implementation is a phased approach. This is necessary for several reasons. Most important is the current financial uncertainty in the Netherlands owing to the negotiations concerning the fee for local governments for the separate collection of plastic packaging from the packaging industry. Another reason is to have the necessary time to prepare citizens on their ‘task’ (changed attitude).</p>
<p>In the first quarter of 2012 four municipalities started with phase one of reverse collection. The first reactions of citizens and results are promising.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0734242X12455089">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The model of reverse collection is not finished. There are challenges to be taken and further improvements are possible.</p>
<sec id="section18-0734242X12455089">
<title>Producer. responsibility</title>
<p>Owing to the producer responsibility for packaging waste the industry has a legal responsibility to organise and finance the system of collection and recycling of packaging. Local authorities have a legal responsibility to take care of household waste collection. Public and private domains touch each other at the front door of our citizens. A new agreement between local governments, the Dutch government and the packaging industry is in preparation. A critical point in the model of reverse collection is the fee for local governments from the packaging industry for collecting packaging materials.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0734242X12455089">
<title>What. motivates our residents?</title>
<p>The most important aspect in separating waste and collecting reusable materials is the attitude, motivation and behaviour of residents. Although the waste industry is familiar with the customer satisfaction survey, there is hardly any scientific knowledge about which factors influence generation and recycling of waste. The results of various studies are not unambiguous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0734242X12455089">Barr, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0734242X12455089">Jones, 2008</xref>). Variables that influence reducing and reusing seem to conflict with variables that influence recycling. Situational factors (e.g. service provision, knowing where and how to recycle) seem to have the most effect on recycling behaviour. Although this possibly has a negative effect on reduction. More research on attitude, motivation and behaviour is necessary to improve the model of reverse collecting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0734242X12455089">
<title>Apartment-and block-buildings</title>
<p>Citizens living in apartment buildings often have less space in their kitchen or close to their front door to separate their household waste. Apartment buildings therefore share (underground) street containers. Studies show that they are recycling significant less household waste than families living in detached houses. More insight is needed into what is helpful and hygienic for residents in apartment buildings to better separate their waste.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section21-0734242X12455089">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The results of the pilots and the first promising results of reverse collection show that a significant reduction of residual waste and an increase of source separation is possible. The basic principles of reverse collection are:</p>
<list id="list17-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>a high service for citizens on collection of recyclables and a lower service on the collection of residual waste;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>confidence in the participation of citizens;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>no overall increase in cost and rewarding active citizen.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section22-0734242X12455089">
<title>Waste pays</title>
<sec id="section23-0734242X12455089">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Ryck’s mission statement is ‘together, we save nature’. Saving nature does not only mean taking measures to reduce the negative impacts on nature, it also means saving money. Ryck is a new and innovative method for collecting recyclables from households. In short, Ryck—cash for trash—pays inhabitants, clubs, schools and institutions (participants) money for separated (household) waste which they bring to the Ryck shops. By doing so, Ryck aims to increase recycling and decrease the amount of residual waste.</p>
<p>Ryck aims to have a positive influence on the perception and actions of people in regard to waste. Rewarding people for separating waste combines environmental sustainability with socio-financial viability and creates a more positive attitude towards waste. Recyclables contain value because of the elements and energy which they contain and is therefore worth money. With this approach Ryck tries to reduce the amount of residual waste, as well as the amount of litter. Trash is cash, which makes it logical not to throw it away or leave it on the street.</p>
<p>In each Ryck shop an employee checks and weighs the waste the participants bring. This creates employment. However, the work is not physically or mentally challenging, making it suitable for people with a distance to the labour market. Ryck’s goal is that a certain percentage of Ryck employees are people who are partially disabled.</p>
<p>Ryck also aims to concentrate high quality waste at a few strategically placed shops. This leads to more efficient operational and logistic processes. Garbage trucks can drive more efficient routes owing to the limitation of collecting points and the household waste decrease, allowing the garbage collector to reduce costs. The Ryck shops are located next to shopping malls, schools, sports complexes, etc. so people do not have to drive extra miles. Moreover, the inspection of the separated waste by the employees guarantees a better quality of the recyclable goods, requiring less processing before it can be transformed by manufacturers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0734242X12455089">
<title>Project design</title>
<p>Ryck began a six-month pilot project in the municipality of Pijnacker-Nootdorp (18,000 households) on the 17 September 2011. The objective of the pilot was to test the concept, shops, system, operations and logistics. Moreover, as there are no similar projects in the Netherlands, the pilot was also meant to assess the participation on the citizens of Pijnacker-Nootdorp.</p>
<p>Waste collection company Avalex, the municipality Pijnacker-Nootdorp and Ryck set up criteria for the evaluation of Ryck at the end of the six-month pilot period. These criteria concern the amounts of recyclables that need to be collected by Ryck, the decrease in residual household waste and a cost–benefit analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0734242X12455089">
<title>Project execution</title>
<p>The preparations for the pilot started in October 2010. In an early phase a project group was formed by Ryck, in which staff of waste collector Avalex and the municipality of Pijnacker-Nootdorp were placed together with Ryck staff. During the meetings the conditions for the co-operation and the roles of each person became clear, and actions were formed and monitored. The knowledge and expertise of the project group members was useful for the realisation of Ryck. Avalex members were important in regard to the logistics, for example, while officials of Pijnacker-Nootdorp played a big role in communicating with stakeholders (i.e. sports clubs) and determining the locations of the Ryck shops.</p>
<p>Ryck also worked together with other partners, mainly suppliers. Ryck forms a new and durable sales channel with great potential. The selected suppliers believe in this potential and were willing to provide discounts on their services for the pilot. The effort of each partner has been of great value. For example, good communication is key for a completely new service. As the waste industry is a relatively traditional one, the communication partner helped to form a bold and humorous communication strategy to stand out. An example of this is the interior of the Ryck shops which are decorated with a large image of an actual park, giving people the impression of standing in the middle of nature.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0734242X12455089">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The results of the pilot are better than forecasted. On Friday, 16 March 2012 more than 1,000,000 kilograms of recyclables had been collected, of which approximately 75% was paper and cardboard, 10% was plastic, 10% was textiles and 5% was small electric appliances. The results indicate that Ryck has a positive influence on the recycling rate of Pijnacker-Nootdorp. Financial figures will be available as soon as the pilot evaluation is completed.</p>
<p>During the same period over 6000 people—roughly a third of the households—have registered and picked up a membership card (Ryckkaart), with which they are saving money for the goal of their choice. However, Ryck reaches more than one third of the households, as some citizens do not wish to register but others also collect their neighbour’s recyclables.</p>
<p>Ryck aims to have a positive impact on the attitude and actions of people with regard to separating waste. Ryck’s market research shows that:</p>
<list id="list18-0734242X12455089" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>54% of participants (n = 741) indicate that they separate more types of waste and/or separate the waste more accurately;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>96% of participants (n = 741) would like to bring more types of recyclables; 61% of participants are ready to do so without any compensation;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>74% of participants come to the Ryck shops at least once every two weeks (based on 5.513 Ryck participants on 30 January 2012).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The Ryck service is much appreciated by the participants. The vast majority of the participants is pleased with the shop employees and shop opening times, and finds the Ryck website easy to comprehend.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0734242X12455089">
<title>Learning points</title>
<p>The unique combination of environmental sustainability with socio-financial viability and the way it has been communicated has seemed to have worked out well in Pijnacker-Nootdorp, as over one third of the households are participating in a completely new project.</p>
<p>The pilot has yielded several learning points, which will increase the chance of success in future municipalities. For example, the Ryck shops near shopping malls have shown excellent results, while the results of the shops near sport complexes could have been better. Also, the design of the opening to the underground container has been improved, combining security with greater ease of disposing the recyclables for the participant. Finally, several adjustments have been made to the hardware and software configuration to ensure that the system continues to operate without errors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0734242X12455089">
<title>Future</title>
<p>The evaluation of the pilot is ongoing and the final decision on the continuation of Ryck in Pijnacker-Nootdorp is expected to be taken before the summer of 2012. The plan is to implement Ryck in other Avalex municipalities (135,000 households in total) and in other Dutch cities as soon as possible. Ryck is in contact with approximately 60 cities. The first new municipalities that implement Ryck are expected right after the summer of 2012. Ryck’s focus is on the Dutch market at the moment, but it has already has drawn international attention from several countries.</p>
</sec></sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0734242X12455089">
<title>Overall conclusions</title>
<p>With a current recycling rate of 51% the Netherlands is at the forefront of recycling in Europe. However, in the last 10–15 years there have been few developments in the recycling of household waste, apart from the introduction of producer responsibility for WEEE and for packaging. The overall recycling rate for household has more or les stabilized, and has been stable for over 10 years. In order to set the next steps, which are necessary to not only reach the goals of the National Waste Management plan, but also to become more resource efficient, new, innovative methods are needed.</p>
<p>Not all of the described pilots have reached a final evaluation phase. Therefore, the results shown in this article are still preliminary and not yet complete. Nevertheless, the pilots in the Eindhoven region have showcased that with a very high level of service and good communication it is possible to reach a near zero waste situation. The results were, however, too uncertain to justify an enhancement or continuation of the project. Nevertheless, it shows where the bottom line in source separation can be found.</p>
<p>The projects with reverse collection are built on these same pillars of significantly enhancing separate collection and recycling through enhanced service of the collection of recyclables. A further significant improvement of waste separation does, however, seem to be possible with this system. The results of the pilot in Hoonhorst are promising. Residual waste has been decreased significantly to almost 80%. The enthusiasm among Dutch municipalities for this system is, therefore, very high.</p>
<p>A very different approach is the Waste Pays system from Ryck. The final results, particularly the cost–benefit ratio, have yet to be established. It is clear, however, that the concept in itself does bring new energy. In particular, the system could attract youth and charities who will engage themselves as the new waste collectors. It has already been observed that children start raising customers for whom they collect the recyclables. The Ryck system is especially interesting for larger cities where it is difficult to implement solutions for source-separation of waste.</p>
<p>It seems that a re-invention of separate collections of household waste is taking place in the Netherlands. At this time it is still unclear in which precise direction and with whatresults, but it is likely that these initiatives will show a further growth in the overall rate.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>AOO</collab> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Programma Gescheiden Inzamelen van Huishoudelijk Afval</source>. <publisher-loc>Utrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AOO</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Factors influencing environmental attitudes. Case study of household waste management</article-title>. <source>Environment and Behaviour</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>CBS</collab> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Gemeentelijke afvalstoffen, hoeveelheden</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://statline.cbs.nl/StatWeb/publication/?VW=T&amp;DM=SLNL&amp;PA=7467&amp;D1=0-156&amp;D2=0&amp;D3=(l-11)-l&amp;HD=120620-0940">http://statline.cbs.nl/StatWeb/publication/?VW=T&amp;DM=SLNL&amp;PA=7467&amp;D1=0-156&amp;D2=0&amp;D3=(l-11)-l&amp;HD=120620-0940</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 20 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Factsheet no. 2: Factors which Influence Household Waste Generation</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Open University Household Waste Study</publisher-name>. <comment>Factsheet No 2</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Marintel Onderzoek en Advies</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Bewonersonderzoek Afval; in opdracht van gemeente Amersfoort</source>. <publisher-loc>Amersfoort</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Marintel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Ministerie van VROM</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Landelijk Afvalbeheerplan 2009–2021</source>. <publisher-loc>Den Haag</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministerie van VROM</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>NVRD</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Hoe kunnen we 2/3 van het huishoudelijk afval recyclen?</source> <publisher-loc>Arnhem</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NVRD</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Onderzoek en Statistiek Zwolle</collab> (<year>2011a</year>) <source>Bewonersonderzoek pilot Raalte</source>. <publisher-loc>Zwolle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Onderzoek en Statistiek</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Onderzoek en Statistiek Zwolle</collab> (<year>2011b</year>) <source>Bewonersonderzoek pilot Zwolle</source>. <publisher-loc>Zwolle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Onderzoek en Statistiek</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ROVA</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Van Afval naar Grondstof</source>. <publisher-loc>Zwolle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ROVA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ROVA</collab> (<year>2011a</year>) <source>Jaarverslag 2010, De groene mens</source>. <publisher-loc>Zwolle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ROVA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ROVA</collab> (<year>2011b</year>) <source>Van Afval naar Grondstof, van Idee naar Aanpak, van Betalen naar Belonen - Op weg naar een afvalloze en duurzame leefomgeving</source>. <publisher-loc>Zwolle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ROVA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ROVA</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Pilot Hoonhorst; Nul onderzoek</source>. <publisher-loc>Zwolle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ROVA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>SRE Milieudienst</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>20090409 Memo proef inzamelscenario’s voor Cranendonck</source>. <publisher-loc>Eindhoven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SRE Milieudienst</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>SRE Milieudienst</collab> (<year>2010a</year>) <source>20100728 Bewonersonderzoek gemeente Cranendonck</source>. <publisher-loc>Eindhoven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SRE Milieudienst</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>SRE Milieudienst</collab> (<year>2010b</year>) <source>20101004 Evaluatierapport afvalproef Cranendonck</source>. <publisher-loc>Eindhoven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SRE Milieudienst</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0734242X12455089">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>SRE Milieudienst</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Soerendonk Afvalloos, gemak zonder grijze bak</source>. <publisher-loc>Eindhoven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SRE Milieudienst</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>