<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Soc Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Social Psychiatry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-7640</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2854</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020764012438477</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0020764012438477</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Depression risks in mothers of children with developmental disabilities: A cross-cultural comparison of Brazil, Colombia, Malaysia and Thailand</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Osada</surname><given-names>Hirokazu</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0020764012438477">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0020764012438477">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Coelho de Amorim</surname><given-names>Annibal</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0020764012438477">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0020764012438477">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Velosa</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0020764012438477">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Wong Poh</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-0020764012438477">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lotrakul</surname><given-names>Panpimol</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-0020764012438477">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>Hitoshi</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-0020764012438477">8</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9-0020764012438477">9</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0020764012438477"><label>1</label>Department of Psychology, Graduate School of the Humanities, Faculty of Law, Senshu University, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0020764012438477"><label>2</label>Division of Mental Health Services and Policy Research, New York State Psychiatric Institute, Department of Psychiatry, Columbia University, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0020764012438477"><label>3</label>Educateur Institute, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0020764012438477"><label>4</label>The National Memory Project at the National Humanization Policy, Ministry of Health, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0020764012438477"><label>5</label>Corp Sindrome de Down, Bogotá, Colombia</aff>
<aff id="aff6-0020764012438477"><label>6</label>Malaysian Care, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</aff>
<aff id="aff7-0020764012438477"><label>7</label>Rajanukul Institute, Bangkok, Thailand</aff>
<aff id="aff8-0020764012438477"><label>8</label>Yokohama Chubu Chiki Ryoiku Center, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff9-0020764012438477"><label>9</label>Japanese League on Developmental Disabilities, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0020764012438477">Hirokazu Osada, Department of Psychology, School of Human Sciences, Senshu University, 3-8, Kanda-Jimbo-Cho, Chiyoda,Tokyo 101-8245, Japan. Email: <email>hiro-o@umin.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>59</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>398</fpage>
<lpage>400</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0020764012438477">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Compared with US or European countries, there are fewer mental health services for mothers of children with developmental disabilities in Latin American and/or Southeast Asian countries.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0020764012438477">
<title>Aims:</title>
<p>To explore the risk of depression in mothers of children with developmental disabilities in countries with a lack of mental health professionals, we conducted cross-cultural comparisons for four countries: Brazil, Colombia, Malaysia and Thailand.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0020764012438477">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>Using the CES-D, we compared the participants’ depressive symptoms, by which we also estimated the probability of morbid depression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0020764012438477">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>In every country, participants tended to show depressive symptoms. In the CES-D total scores and the numbers of mothers who were observed to have a high level of depressive symptoms, there were significant differences among countries (<italic>F</italic> = 4.36, <italic>p</italic> = .006; <italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic> = 10.3, <italic>p</italic> = .015).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0020764012438477">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>Considering cultural models, we could apply evidence-based intervention to depressive mothers of children, and conduct intervention and treatment for those mothers and evaluate ways of providing better mental health services to these individuals.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>CES-D</kwd>
<kwd>cross-cultural comparison</kwd>
<kwd>depression</kwd>
<kwd>mental health</kwd>
<kwd>mothers of children with developmental disabilities</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-0020764012438477" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Parenting a child with developmental disabilities is very demanding for any mother. A comparison of mothers of typically developing children and mothers of children with developmental disabilities revealed that the latter group experienced poorer mental health and maternal well-being (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0020764012438477">Baker, Blacher, Kopp, &amp; Kraemer, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020764012438477">Pearson et al., 2000</xref>). There is extensive evidence suggesting that mothers of children with developmental disabilities are vulnerable to depression. However, little attention has been given to this phenomenon in the Latin America and Southeast Asia. Most recently, parenting stress and its relationship with depression in mothers of children with autism spectrum disorders was studied in Thailand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0020764012438477">Phetrasuwan &amp; Shandor Miles, 2009</xref>). As far as we know, however, very few studies have focused on depression in mothers of children with developmental disabilities in Latin American and Southeast Asian countries. Detecting clinically depressive mothers of children with developmental disabilities is very important for the professionals to provide them appropriate services. However, reviewing the previous literatures, we found that both in Latin America and in Southeast Asia, there have not been established services systems that are suitable to each cultural background, to support the mothers of children with developmental disabilities. The present study is the first cross-cultural comparative examination of mothers of children with developmental disabilities in two Latin American countries (Brazil and Colombia) and two Southeast Asian countries (Malaysia and Thailand). The aims of the study are to examine the risks and actual presence of depression in these countries among mothers of children with developmental disabilities, and to describe their depressive features. In each country, ethical issues were precisely approved in appropriate manners.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0020764012438477" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section8-0020764012438477">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>We recruited a total of 161 mothers from two Latin American countries (Brazil and Colombia) and two Southeast Asian countries (Malaysia and Thailand) as participants. The participants were mothers of children with developmental disabilities. All of them filled out forms at the respective programmes and their children received professional care, but the mothers themselves had never consulted with a mental health professional.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0020764012438477">
<title>Measurement</title>
<p>We used the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0020764012438477">Radloff, 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0020764012438477">1991</xref>). Although the CES-D was originally developed in English, it has been translated into many languages. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0020764012438477">Gupta, Punetha and Diwan (2006)</xref>, the CES-D must be validated for each cultural group on which it is used. In this study, the researchers in every country except for Malaysia used a version of the CES-D that had been translated into their own language. Usability was verified for every language version of the CES-D.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0020764012438477">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>We compared participants’ demographic data, including mother’s age and years of education; household size; age, gender and diagnosis of the child with developmental disabilities; and CES-D scores. Statistical comparisons used a significance level of <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 (two-tailed). One-way ANOVA was conducted for continuous variables, while <italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic> tests were used for categorical data. For comparison of continuous data, we also calculated <italic>η<sup>2</sup></italic> for showing effect size. In order to avoid Type I error, we used Dunn/Sidák correction to adjust the <italic>α</italic> level in the ANOVA post-hoc comparison. SPSS 16.0 for Windows was used for statistical analysis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0020764012438477" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>We confirmed internal consistency of CES-D based on data of all the samples in each country. Cronbach’s <italic>α</italic> = .82 (Brazil), .85 (Colombia), .88 (Malaysia) and .89 (Thailand).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0020764012438477">Table 1</xref> shows a comparison of the participants’ demographic data and CES-D scores for the four countries. There were no significant differences for any demographic data. In the CES-D total scores and the numbers of mothers who were observed to have a high level of depressive symptoms, there were significant differences among countries. A post-hoc comparison revealed statistically significant differences between Brazil and Malaysia (Fisher’s exact test, <italic>p</italic> = .008), and between Colombia and Malaysia (Fisher’s exact test, <italic>p</italic> = .006). There were no significant differences in the number of mothers with high depressive symptoms between any other pairings of countries.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0020764012438477" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of participants’ demographic data and CES-D from four countries<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0020764012438477">a</xref></sup>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0020764012438477" xlink:href="10.1177_0020764012438477-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Countries<hr/></th>
<th align="left"><italic>F</italic> (d.f. = 3, 157)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="left">η<sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Brazil</th>
<th align="left">Colombia</th>
<th align="left">Malaysia</th>
<th align="left">Thailand</th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic> = 29</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic> = 83</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic> = 30</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic> = 19</th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td>41.0</td>
<td>44.4</td>
<td>42.6</td>
<td>39.9</td>
<td>.535</td>
<td>.662</td>
<td>.054</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Years of education<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0020764012438477">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>9.67</td>
<td>11.8</td>
<td>12.3</td>
<td>11.3</td>
<td>.396</td>
<td>.757</td>
<td>.041</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Household size</td>
<td>5.17</td>
<td>4.60</td>
<td>4.38</td>
<td>6.25</td>
<td>1.78</td>
<td>.174</td>
<td>.160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Child’s age</td>
<td>9.67</td>
<td>13.6</td>
<td>9.88</td>
<td>5.50</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>.067</td>
<td>.222</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Child’s gender (%)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0020764012438477">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>83.3</td>
<td>90.0</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>75.0</td>
<td>2.44<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0020764012438477">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>.568</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Child’s diagnosis of disability (%)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.175<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0020764012438477">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>.790</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ASD</td>
<td>41.3</td>
<td>46.1</td>
<td>37.5</td>
<td>47.4</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> AD/HD</td>
<td>14.0</td>
<td>21.3</td>
<td>12.5</td>
<td>21.1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ID</td>
<td>44.7</td>
<td>32.6</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>31.5</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="8">CES-D</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Total score</td>
<td>23.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">*</xref></td>
<td>19.2</td>
<td>14.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">**</xref></td>
<td>16.6</td>
<td>4.36</td>
<td>.006</td>
<td>.081</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Positive ratio (%)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0020764012438477">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>58.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">*</xref></td>
<td>53.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">*</xref></td>
<td>23.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">**</xref></td>
<td>36.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">*</xref>, <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0020764012438477">**</xref></td>
<td>10.3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0020764012438477">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>.015</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0020764012438477">
<p><italic>N</italic> = 161.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0020764012438477">
<p>CES-D: Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0020764012438477">
<p>ASD: autism spectrum disorder, ADHD: attention deficit / hyperactivity disorder, ID: intellectual disability.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0020764012438477">
<label>a</label>
<p>cumulative years of education starting with primary school.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0020764012438477">
<label>b</label>
<p>percentage of boys.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0020764012438477">
<label>c</label>
<p>Pearson’s χ<italic><sup>2</sup></italic> test.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0020764012438477">
<label>d</label>
<p>cut-off was set at 16.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0020764012438477">
<label>*</label>
<p>, ** different number of asterisks indicate significant differences.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0020764012438477" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The four countries showed no significant differences in any of the demographic data. Owing to sampling inclusion criteria, our study participants could be regarded as representative of the population of mothers of children with developmental disabilities.</p>
<p>According to the CES-D scores, the four countries had different distributions for the number of mothers with depressive symptoms. Although the present study might be formative, this result can be interpreted as an indication that morbid depression is more common among mothers of children with disabilities in Latin America than in Southeast Asia. Our results coincide with the previous reports. The cultural characteristics of Latin America are markedly different from those in Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0020764012438477">de Toledo Piza Peluso &amp; Blay, 2004</xref>), and the rates of depression in Pacific Asia are lower and comparable to rates in western countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020764012438477">Chiu, 2004</xref>). In this study, Thailand was found to be comparable to the two Latin American countries in terms of rate of depression in the mothers of children with developmental disabilities, while the mothers of Thailand were apt to be more depressed than Malaysian mothers. Asian countries have a lifetime rate of depression that is less than that of western countries, with the exception of Thailand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020764012438477">Chiu, 2004</xref>). Our result can be supported by the previous study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0020764012438477" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Due to small sample size, except for Colombia, it seems to be difficult to generalize our results for mothers of children with developmental disabilities. However, our results still deserve to be raised as the first step towards better provision of mental health services to mothers of children with developmental disabilities in Latin America or Southeast Asia.</p>
<p>Because the concept of disability is defined differently across cultures, the potential for cross-cultural miscommunication is extremely high when service providers’ cultural frameworks differ from those of the families they serve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0020764012438477">Kalyanpur &amp; Harry, 1999</xref>). In our study, due to the lack of an established cultural model, we could not discuss and suggest what kinds of services should be provided to depressive mothers of children with developmental disabilities. In addition to this study, we have been conducting in-depth interviews with some of the participants. After we finish analysing their verbatim data qualitatively, we hope to establish a theoretical framework suitable to each cultural model in the near future.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This study was a part of research sponsored by the Japanese League on Developmental Disabilities (JLDD) and the Japan International Cooperation Agency (JICA). We are very grateful to the mothers for participating in the study. We would like to thank Miss Chiyoko Numata for coordinating and leading this research project. Finally, we are extremely grateful to Dr Satoru Shima for helpful and professional comments on depression. We are thinking of him and praying for him in this time of loss.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blacher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Parenting children with mental retardation</article-title>. <source>International Review of Research in Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Epidemiology of depression in the Asia Pacific region</article-title>. <source>Australas Psychiatry</source>, <supplement>12 Suppl</supplement>, <fpage>S4</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Toledo Piza Peluso</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blay</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Community perception of mental disorders: A systematic review of Latin American and Caribbean studies</article-title>. <source>Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>961</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Punetha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diwan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The revised CES-D scale for caregivers of the elderly in India</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Aging and Human Development</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalyanpur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Culture in special education: Building reciprocal family–professional relationships</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paul H. Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lachar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loveland</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azzam</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Patterns of behavioral adjustment and maladjustment in mental retardation: Comparison of children with and without ADHD</article-title>. <source>American Journal on Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phetrasuwan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shandor Miles</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Parenting stress in mothers of children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Special Pediatric Nursing</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>The CES-D scale: A self-report depression scale for research in the general population</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0020764012438477">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The use of the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale in adolescents and young adults</article-title>. <source>Journal of Youth and Adolescence</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>