<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VES</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spves</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vasc Endovascular Surg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Vascular and Endovascular Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1538-5744</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-9116</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1538574412452160</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1538574412452160</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Clinical Controversy Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Current Debate on the Role of Embolic Protection Devices</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Bornak</surname>
<given-names>Arash</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412452160">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1538574412452160"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Milner</surname>
<given-names>Ross</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1538574412452160">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1538574412452160"><label>1</label>Vascular &amp; Endovascular Surgery, Miller School of Medicine, University of Miami, FL, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1538574412452160"><label>2</label>Vascular &amp; Endovascular Surgery, Pitzker School of Medicine, University of Chicago, IL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1538574412452160">Arash Bornak, Vascular &amp; Endovascular Surgery, University of Miami, Miller School of Medicine, Holtz Bldg Suite 3016, 1611 NW 12th Ave (C229), Miami, FL 33136, USA Email: <email>abornak@med.miami.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>46</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>441</fpage>
<lpage>446</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The role of embolic protection devices (EPDs) during percutaneous arterial revascularization is still debated. This article discusses the use, the limitations, and issues of the variety of EPDs in different vascular beds, with a particular focus on the lower extremity arterial interventions.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>embolization</kwd>
<kwd>embolic protection device</kwd>
<kwd>distal filter</kwd>
<kwd>occlusive protection</kwd>
<kwd>percutaenous mechanical thrombectomy</kwd>
<kwd>atherectomy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1538574412452160">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The role of distal EPDs in different vascular beds during standard endovascular revascularization (angioplasty, stenting, atherectomy, percutaneous mechanical thrombectomy, and thrombolysis) is still debated. This role is mainly investigated for percutaneous cardiac and carotid interventions, to a lesser degree for renal and extremity interventions. During these procedures atherosclerotic plaques, fibrous debris, or thrombotic material of various size can dislodge, resulting in distal embolization. This phenomenon is more frequent than previously thought based on studies using more sensitive imaging technologies such as diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging or transcranial Doppler studies. Despite frequent embolization, the clinical significance of the phenomenon varies depending on, but not restricted to, the size and nature of the embolic particle, as well as the vascular territory involved. The EPDs were developed in order to provide a mechanical protective system distal to the target lesions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1538574412452160">
<title>Different Types of EPDs</title>
<p>The most common type of EPD involves delivery and placement of a filter distal to the target lesion. These devices include the Angioguard (Cordis, Bridgewater, NJ), Accunet (Abbott, Santa Clara, CA), Emboshield (Abbott, Santa Clara, CA), FilterWire EZ (Boston Scientific, Natick, MA), FiberNet (Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN) and Spider FX/RX (Ev3, Plymouth, MN). The Mo.Ma (Medtronic-Invatec, Roncadelle, Italy) is also a proximal protection device, which additionally uses a second distal balloon that prevents retrograde flow to the target zone. The filter (either a ninitol mesh or drilled polyurethane membrane) is, either advanced over, or more frequently mounted on a 0.014-in guide wire. The filter crosses the lesion, expands distally to capture particles during revascularization, then collapses and is finally removed at the end of the procedure. Filters are nonocclusive and the size of the captured particles is limited by the pore size. The pore size of the majority of the filters is &gt;80 μm and emboli smaller than the EPD pores can still reach the distal vasculature. The only exception is the FiberNet (Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN) with a pore size as small as 40 μm.</p>
<p>Less frequently, balloon occlusive devices are used to provide embolic protection. The system uses a balloon inflated either distal to the target lesion or proximal in order to arrest antegrade flow. The lesion is then treated, and the mobilized debris is removed with an aspiration catheter. Finally the balloon is deflated, antegrade flow is restored, and the device is removed.</p>
<p>Proximal protection devices are extremely useful when lesions cannot be crossed with other distal embolic protection devices (EPDs). The potential disadvantages of both occlusive devices (proximal and distal) include ischemic time and difficult angiographic visualization of the treatment target.</p>
<p>Distal occlusive devices include the Guardwire (Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN) and the Triactiv (Kensey Nash, Exton, PA). A proximal protection device includes the Proxis system (St Jude's Medical, St. Paul, MN). The Mo.Ma (Invatec, Roncadelle, Italy) is also a proximal protection device, which additionally uses a second distal balloon that prevents retrograde flow to the target zone. Used during carotid stenting to interrupt antegrade flow to the brain, the distal balloon is inflated in the external carotid artery, while the proximal balloon inflates in the common carotid. Applying the same principle, the Gore flow reversal system (Gore, Flagstaff, Arizona) creates a shunt. A continuous retrograde flow is created through the proximal balloon by continually redirecting the blood flow via external venous access (commonly femoral vein) preventing cerebral embolization during intervention. This device is particularly useful in difficult internal carotid anatomy when filters cannot be adequately advanced and deployed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1538574412452160">
<title>Limitations and Complications</title>
<p>As one can expect, the use of these EPDs also has limitations and complications. Crossing lesions for distal deployment of EPDs can cause embolization. The EPD has a larger and stiffer profile than an 0.014-in guide wire. This property may render trackability through the lesion difficult and deployment challenging in tortuous vessels. Body wiring to straighten the distal vessel or lesion predilation with a 2 mm balloon can also cause embolization.</p>
<p>Once deployed the EPD should be able to capture particles. The EPD should appose the vessel wall appropriately in order to create a seal and be stable to avoid intimal injury.</p>
<p>Filter sizing or balloon inflation, as well as device stability are important in order to avoid vessel spasm, intimal injury, and/or dissection.</p>
<p>When a distal filter is used, smaller pore size may decrease the chances of microembolization. However, this may also result in a higher incidence of filter thrombosis by capturing too many particles.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1538574412452160">1</xref>
</sup> Currently, most pore sizes are between 100 and 150 μm. When an occlusive protection device is used, the aspiration catheter may fail to aspirate all the emboli either due to large particle size for aspiration or due to ineffective aspiration.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412452160">2</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Once the lesion is treated, the EPD needs to be retrieved. Embolization can occur during retrieval if the volume of the debris exceeds the volume of the filter. This discrepancy can be estimated by the completion angiogram and a suction catheter can potentially help reduce the amount of debris from the filter before retrieval.</p>
<p>Other potential complications can result from detachment embolization of the EPD or EPD system components during retrieval. Although rare, the filter can per example get caught by the stent during retrieval.</p>
<sec id="section4-1538574412452160">
<title>Cardiac Experience</title>
<p>The clinical significance of distal embolization dictates indications of EPD use. Most experience in EPD use with large randomized trials comes from the cardiology literature, particularly in 2 settings: percutaneous revascularization of native coronaries during ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) and percutaneous revascularization of saphenous vein coronary bypass grafts (SVG).</p>
<p>Several large randomized trials fail to demonstrate an improvement in outcome when proximal or distal EPD was used in native coronary arteries during STEMI. In a meta-analysis of 8 randomized STEMI trials with 1467 patients,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412452160">3</xref>
</sup> no survival benefit was shown when EPDs were used, despite a lesser degree of microcirculation damage. Subsequent randomized trial DEDICATION<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1538574412452160">4</xref>
</sup> including 626 patients also showed no difference in terms of major adverse cardiac events or ventricular wall motion when EPD was used. However, some investigators argue that these studies did not assess the size of the thrombus burden and culprit vessel size and suggest there may be a role in using EPD during percutaneous mechanical thrombectomy (PMT) of native coronaries with large thrombotic burden.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574412452160">5</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Compared to native coronary revascularization, there has been extensive data supporting EPD use during SVG revascularization. The SVGs have a progressive closure rate estimated to be 12% to 20% at the end of the first year and approximately 50% by 10 years. Compared to native artery, graft atheroma is more prone to fragment and embolize. These atheroma are soft, friable with poor or absent fibrous cap or calcification.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574412452160">6</xref>
</sup> Several randomized trials have shown clear advantage for revascularization with EPDs in terms of major adverse cardiac events (42%reduction) and myocardial infarctions.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574412452160">7</xref>
</sup> Proximal and distal occlusive devices or filters are equally efficient.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1538574412452160">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1538574412452160">9</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1538574412452160">
<title>Carotid Experience</title>
<p>Although EPDs are widely used during carotid stenting, no large randomized trial has clearly demonstrated their safety and cerebral protection benefits. The largest relevant prospective randomized study includes only 35 patients and failed to demonstrate any cerebral protection benefits with distal filters. Diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging at 24 hours did not show reduction of microemboli when EPD was used.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1538574412452160">10</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Support and consensus for EPD use is based on one hand on its performance during SVG revasularization and on the other hand on retrospective data and meta-analysis.</p>
<p>The most recent meta-analysis includes 134 studies, with 12 263 protected carotid artery stenting (CAS) patients and 11 198 unprotected CAS patients. The study showed a relative risk (RR) for stroke of .62 in favor of protected CAS, for both symptomatic (RR .67) and asymptomatic (RR .61) patients (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1538574412452160">11</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Some investigators point to the theoretical advantage of proximal occlusive devices and flow reversal systems. This approach avoids potential plaque disruption during advancement of distal protection devices and is useful when dealing with tortuous internal carotid arteries. Proximal occlusion is however limited by patients' intolerance to carotid occlusion; in the recent ARMOUR trial<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1538574412452160">12</xref>
</sup> 12.9% of patients had transient symptoms that resolved, and an additional 0.9% had persistent symptoms &gt;20 minutes. Despite the lack of randomization, this trial using the MO.MA device (Medtronic-Invatec, Roncadelle, Italy) shows promising results with all stroke and major stroke rates at 30 days of 2.3% and 0.9%, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1538574412452160">
<title>Renal Experience</title>
<p>The only prospective randomized trial that addressed the role of EPDs devices and the preservation of renal function during renal artery percuataneous intervention included 100 patients undergoing renal artery stenting at 7 centers. The study showed a similar decline in Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR) at a 1-month follow-up after renal artery stenting alone, stenting with distal protection filter, and stenting with abciximab; there was however no decline in GFR when embolic protection and abciximab were used in tandem.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1538574412452160">13</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1538574412452160">
<title>Lower Extremity Experience</title>
<p>Lesions in the lower extremity can be proximal or distal, focal, or extensive; stenotic or occlusive; acute, subacute, or chronic. Depending on the location, the extent, nature of these lesions different percutaneous treatment modalities can be used including balloon angioplasty, stenting, cryoplasty, atherectomy (directional, rotational, laser), thrombolysis, or PMT.</p>
<p>The only EPD approved by the Food and Drug Administration for lower extremity use is the Spider (EV3) filter. Conflicting data exist with respect to distal embolization during lower extremity revascularization, as well as their clinical significance, and the role of DEPs in the prevention of major complications. Although the lower extremities can tolerate distal embolization due to collateral blood supply, embolization in patients with poor runoff vessels may result in cases of major amputation.</p>
<p>Distal embolization during endovascular treatment of chronic lesions occurs at relatively high rate in some series, they are however rarely clinically significant. In the PROTECT<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1538574412452160">14</xref>
</sup> registry, 56 infrainguinal lesions were treated using angioplasty, stenting, and/or directional atherectomy all with DEP. Overall, 55% macroembolization was reported; in 45% of cases the particles were larger than 2 mm. Frequent distal embolization was also reported by Lam et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1538574412452160">15</xref>
</sup> In this study, a US Doppler was used to document embolic signals (ES) during superficial femoral artery (SFA) revascularization by PTA, stenting, and/or atherectomy. Sixty patients were treated and ES was noted in each patient while crossing the lesion, during angioplasty, stenting, or plaque excision. The frequency of ES was higher during stent deployment and plaque excision. Only one complication resulted in major amputation in a patient with 1 vessel runoff. Surprisingly, the study did not find differences in ES—neither the TransAtlantic InterSociety Consensus Classification (TASC) classification nor calcification did influence the frequency of embolic events. Shammas et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1538574412452160">14</xref>
</sup> and Suri et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1538574412452160">16</xref>
</sup> along with other investigators have reported a positive correlation of atherectomy and distal embolization. Zeller et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1538574412452160">17</xref></sup> in their early reports of 71 femoropopliteal atherectomy reported 5 cases with significant distal embolization on angiogram; embolic particles were all successfully aspirated. Subsequently, Suri et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1538574412452160">16</xref>
</sup> used distal embolic filters in 10 SFA atherectomy. In all cases debris was extracted from the filter, pieces ranging in length of 0.5 to 10 mm. This debris was significant enough to cause potential occlusions of the tibial vessels. The emboli are typically a combination of atherosclerotic debris, cholesterol, calcified material, and platelet emboli<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1538574412452160">18</xref>
</sup>; they can potentially be aspirated but thrombolysis would be inefficient. This may be particularly relevant in patients with single-vessel runoff and EPD should be strongly considered.</p>
<p>Acute and subacute lesions seem to be particularly prone to embolize during percuataneous revascularization. These lesions have thrombus components, are soft, friable with poor or absent fibrous cap or calcification. Chemical thrombolysis or PMT are usually used in this setting.</p>
<p>The AngioJet system PMT catheter uses hydrodynamic forces to fracture thrombus and simultaneously aspirate fragments by the vacuum created at the tip of the catheter. Thrombus fragmentation can be enhanced by first initiating clot lysis with thrombolytics using the power pulse mode of the AngioJet device. Despite the advantage of simultaneous fragment aspiration, distal embolization by residual debris is a potential devastating complication.</p>
<p>The use of PMT for the treatment of acute and subacute occlusions of lower extremity vasculature is becoming extremely common, and a few relevant articles report cases of distal embolizations after PMT. Only 1 case resulted in limb loss. Most cases were treated with further aspiration and/or thrombolysis.</p>
<p>Reekers et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1538574412452160">19</xref>
</sup> reported their experience in 28 patients with infrainguinal acute or subacute occlusion (11 native arteries and 17 bypass grafts) treated by PMT (Hydrolyser, Cordis Europa, Roden, the Netherlands). Twenty-six patients were successfully treated, with 5 patients (18%) having distal thrombotic embolization. All cases were reported in bypass occlusions. All but one (required amputation) embolization was solved with further thrombolysis. They contributed these embolizations to their initial technique which was subsequently modified. They recommended several steps to avoid embolization: (1) start PMT 1 to 2 cm proximal to the occluded segment, (2) advance only with good suction, (3) no passage through stenotic lesions with distal runoff and distal thrombus to stenosis treated with local thrombolysis, and (4) PMT should be stopped when the inflow of saline greatly exceeds the outflow, since this may represent wall-adherent thrombus that surrounds the tip of the catheter.</p>
<p>Ansel et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1538574412452160">20</xref>
</sup> reported their experience in thrombotic occlusions using the AngioJet rheolytic thrombectomy catheter (Possis Medical, Inc, Minneapolis, Minnesota) with PMT. In this study, 99 patients (with underlying stenosis in 81 patients) underwent lower extremity PMT for thrombotic occlusions in native arteries (n = 80) or bypass grafts (n = 19). Due to the retrospective nature of this study, precise rates of procedure-related embolization could not be determined. However, in all cases, any embolization resulting from operation of the rheolytic throbectomy catheter was successfully managed with catheter removal or thrombolytic infusion; in no case was emergent surgery required.</p>
<p>Kasirajan et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1538574412452160">21</xref>
</sup> reported 2 cases of distal embolization after successful PMT of 70 patients with acute or subacute lower extremity native arterial or bypass (n = 21) occlusion. Underlying stenosis was diagnosed in 53 (75.7%) of the 70 patients. In both cases, distal embolizations resolved with adjuvant pharmacological thrombolysis.</p>
<p>The EPD use during PMT is reported in 2 relevant articles. Karnabatidis et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1538574412452160">22</xref>
</sup> conducted a prospective study in which 48 patients were treated with infra-aortic stenosis and/or occlusions. They all had standard endovascular procedures with EPD. Particles retrieved were found in 29 (58%) with &gt;1 mm and 6 (12%) &gt;3 mm in size. Their multivariate analysis implicated declotting procedures as the only independent predictor of increased embolic events. The particles were primarily atheromatous plaque and thrombus. Acute thromboses and occlusive lesions were correlated with higher amounts of captures particles; they recommended EPD use in all declotting procedures.</p>
<p>Siablis et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1538574412452160">23</xref>
</sup> treated 16 patients with lower extremities occlusions using EPD. Five acute occlusions were treated by PMT. Embolic material was collected in all 5 patients. They also concluded that the use of EPD was safe, feasible, and efficacious in preventing distal embolization.</p>
<p>The following case presents an acute arterial occlusion with a culprit lesion that was successfully treated by PMT and angioplasty. Distal macroembolization was prevented by EPD use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1538574412452160">
<title>Case</title>
<p>A 57-year-old man presented with an acute right lower extremity ischemia and absent right femoral pulse. He has a history of alcohol abuse, congestive heart failure (ejection fraction 15%), and atrial fibrillation, noncompliant with his coumadin therapy.</p>
<p>Six months prior to this admission, he underwent a right common femoral thrombectomy, endarterectomy, and patch angioplasty for femoral thromboembolism. He had been unreliable with his coumadin treatment and stopped it.</p>
<p>Therapeutic heparinization was started. Due to the patient’s multiple comorbidities, treatment by percutaneous means was initiated.</p>
<p>Patient underwent an angiogram through contralateral femoral approach. This revealed complete occlusion of the right common (CIA) and external iliac (EIA) arteries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1538574412452160">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1538574412452160" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Initial angiogram reveals complete occlusion of the CIA and proximal EIA. CIA indicates common iliac artery; EIA, external iliac artery.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412452160-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The occlusion was easily crossed with an angle glide wire. A catheter was subsequently placed distal to the occlusion in the proximal common femoral artery (CFA). The angiogram revealed stenosis of the distal CFA but widely patent CFA, SFA, and profunda. A stenotic lesion was present at the distal CFA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1538574412452160">Figure 2</xref>). The popliteal artery was patent with severely diseased posterior tibial and peroneal runoff arteries.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1538574412452160" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Angiogram reveals patent CFA, SFA, and profunda. A stenotic culprit lesion is present at the distal CFA. CFA indicates common femoral artery; SFA, superficial femoral artery.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412452160-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Due to the extensive iliac thrombosis and patient's poor runoff, it was thought prudent to use an EPD in the SFA. The SFA was then selected and a 5 mm SpiderFx (ev3 Inc) EPD was positioned distal to the CFA stenosis in the proximal SFA.</p>
<p>Due to the acute nature of the thrombosis, percutaneous mechanical thrombolysis (PMT) with the Angiojet DVX catheter (Possis Medical, Inc) of the right CIA and EIA was performed as follows. The occlusion was laced with approximately 10 mg of tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) in 50 cc saline solution, using the power-pulse technique. The lysis time of 15 minutes was allowed. This was followed by PMT of the occluded segment with heparinized saline (5000 units in 1000 cc saline solution) starting 2 cm proximal to the occlusion and stopping at the proximal CFA. The completion angiogram after three passages revealed a residual stenosis of the distal CFA. Angioplasty of the stenosis using 5 mm cutting balloon was successful. Completion angiogram revealed patent vessels with no flow-limiting stenosis. The SFA was widely patent however there clearly was embolic debris in the EPD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1538574412452160">Figure 3</xref>). The EPD containing thrombotic debris was successfully removed. Completion angiogram after retrieval of the EPD showed no distal embolization.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1538574412452160" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Completion angiogram reveals embolic debris in the embolic protection filter.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412452160-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1538574412452160">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Randomized studies have established the role of EPDs during percutaneous SVG revascularization. Retrospective data support and have established the use of EPDs during carotid stenting; based on these results, a large randomized study investigating the role of EPDs would be ethically difficult to justify.</p>
<p>The EPD costs more than $1000, and its use in lower extremities is off-label in the United States and is not reimbursed. Moreover, EPDs as stated earlier have limitations and complications.</p>
<p>In chronic lesions, EPD should be strongly considered in patients with poor runoff vessels undergoing atherectomy. Acute and subacute lesions treated during PMT embolize frequently due to their nature, but they rarely result in clinically significant complications. However, the treatment of distal embolization can complicate and prolong procedures by further distal aspiration, PMT, or extensive chemical thrombolysis and intensive care unit (ICU) monitoring. This could result in longer treatment time, patient discomfort, and cost. Despite the cost and potential complications, we believe EPD use should be strongly considered in patients with acute and subacute occlusive disease, poor distal runoff vessels, and in large and/or extensive thrombus burden, such as in the above reported case. Further randomized studies and larger series with cost analysis are necessary to evaluate the extent and type of lesions that would benefit from EPD.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1538574412452160">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1538574412452160">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1538574412452160">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kindel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spiller</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Transient occlusion of an Angioguard protection system by massive embolization during angioplasty of a degenerated aortocoronary saphenous vein graft</article-title>. <source>Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1538574412452160">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tubler</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schluter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dirsch</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Balloon-protected carotid artery stenting: relationship of periprocedural neurological complications with the size of particulate debris</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>2791</fpage>–<lpage>2796</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1538574412452160">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>De Luca</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Suryapranata</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adjunctive mechanical devices to prevent distal embolization in patients undergoing mechanical revascularization for acute myocardial infarction: a meta-analysis of randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1538574412452160">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelbaek</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Terkelsen</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Helqvist</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Randomized comparison of distal protection versus conventional treatment in primary percutaneous coronary intervention: the drug elution and distal protection in ST-elevation myocardial infarction (DEDICATION) trial</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>899</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1538574412452160">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Srinivasan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rihal</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adjunctive thrombectomy and distal protection in primary percutaneous coronary intervention: impact on microvascular perfusion and outcomes</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1538574412452160">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Motwani</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Topol</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Aortocoronary saphenous vein graft disease: pathogenesis, predisposition, and prevention</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>916</fpage>–<lpage>931</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1538574412452160">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baim</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wahr</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>George</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Randomized trial of a distal embolic protection device during percutaneous intervention of saphenous vein aorto-coronary bypass grafts</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1285</fpage>–<lpage>1290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1538574412452160">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hermiller</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Randomized comparison of distal protection with a filter-based catheter and a balloon occlusion and aspiration system during percutaneous intervention of diseased saphenous vein aorto-coronary bypass grafts</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>548</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1538574412452160">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mauri</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hermiller</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The PROXIMAL trial: proximal protection during saphenous vein graft intervention using the Proxis Embolic Protection System: a randomized, prospectcerebral protection</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>765</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1538574412452160">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barbato</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dillavou</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Horowitz</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A randomized trial of carotid artery stenting with and without cerebral protection</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>765</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1538574412452160">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Garg</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karagiorgos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pisimisis</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cerebral protection devices reduce periprocedural strokes during carotid angioplasty and stenting: a systematic review of the current literature</article-title>. <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1538574412452160">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ansel</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hopkins</surname>
<given-names>LN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaff</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Safety and effectiveness of the INVATEC MO.MA proximal cerebral protection device during carotid artery stenting: results from the ARMOUR pivotal trial</article-title>. <source>Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1538574412452160">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haller</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Colyer</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Embolic protection and platelet inhibition during renal artery stenting</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2752</fpage>–<lpage>2760</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1538574412452160">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shammas</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dippel</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coiner</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preventing lower extremity distal embolization using embolic filter protection: results of the PROTECT registry</article-title>. <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1538574412452160">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Faries</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and clinical significance of distal embolization during percutaneous interventions involving the superficial femoral artery</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1538574412452160">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Suri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wholey</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Postoak</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal embolic protection during femoropoliteal atherectomy</article-title>. <source>Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1538574412452160">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zeller</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rastan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwarzwalder</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Percutaneous peripheral atherectomy of femoropopliteal stenoses using a new-generation device: six-month results from a single-center experience</article-title>. <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1538574412452160">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ohki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marin</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyon</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ex vivo human carotid artery bifurcation stenting: correlation of lesion characteristics with embolic potential</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1538574412452160">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reekers</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kromhout</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spithoven</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arterial thrombosis below the inguinal ligament: percutaneous treatment with a thrombosuction catheter</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>198</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1538574412452160">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ansel</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>George</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Botti</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rheolytic thrombectomy in the management of limb ischemia: 30-day results from a multicenter registry</article-title>. <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1538574412452160">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kasirajan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beavers</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rheolytic thrombectomy in the management of acute and subacute limb-threatening ischemia</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Interv Radiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1538574412452160">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Karnabatidis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katsanos</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kagadis</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal embolism during percutaneous revascularization of infra-aortic arterial occlusive disease: an underestimated phenomenon</article-title>. <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>
<issue>(3)</issue>:<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1538574412452160">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Siablis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karnabatidis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katsanos</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outflow protection filters during percutaneous reca- nalization of lower extremities' arterial occlusions: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Radiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>