<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhl</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hum Lact</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Human Lactation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0890-3344</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-5732</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0890334411435990</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0890334411435990</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Research</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>“BreastfeedingBasics”</article-title>
<subtitle>Web-Based Education that Meets Current Knowledge Competencies</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>Linda Orkin</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0890334411435990">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>Mary E.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0890334411435990">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0890334411435990"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0890334411435990"><label>2</label>Denver Health and Department of Pediatrics, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Denver CO</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0890334411435990">Mary E. O’Connor, MD, MPH, Westside Family Health Center, 1100 Federal Blvd, Denver, CO 80204. Email: <email>Mary.O’Connor@dhha.org</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>407</fpage>
<lpage>413</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>12</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Lactation Consultant Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0890334411435990">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>The United States has not met the majority of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention goals for breastfeeding duration. Studies have shown a lack of knowledge about breastfeeding by health care professionals and students (HCP/S). Web-based education can be a cost-effective manner of education for HCP/S. “BreastfeedingBasics” is an online free educational program available for use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0890334411435990">
<title>Aims:</title>
<p>This study compares information in “BreastfeedingBasics” to the breastfeeding knowledge competencies recommended by the US Breastfeeding Committee (USBC). It also evaluates usage of “BreastfeedingBasics” by users and health care professional faculty.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0890334411435990">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>Using anonymous information from Web site users, the authors compared mean pre-test and post-test scores of the modules as a measure of the knowledge gained by HCP/S users. They evaluated usage by demographic information and used a Web-based survey to assess benefits of usage of “BreastfeedingBasics” to faculty.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0890334411435990">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Overall, 15 020 HCP/S used the Web site between April 1999 and December 2009. “BreastfeedingBasics” meets 8 of the 11 USBC knowledge competencies. Mean post-test scores increased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) for all modules. Faculty reported its benefits to be free, broad scope, and the ability to be completed on the students’ own time; 84% of the faculty combined the use of “BreastfeedingBasics” with clinical work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0890334411435990">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>Use of “BreastfeedingBasics” can help HCP/S meet the USBC core breastfeeding knowledge competencies and gain knowledge. Faculty are satisfied with its use. Wider use of “BreastfeedingBasics” to help improve the knowledge of HCP/S may help in improving breastfeeding outcomes.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>breastfeeding</kwd>
<kwd>health care professionals</kwd>
<kwd>Web-based education</kwd>
<kwd>curricula</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-0890334411435990">
<title>Well Established</title>
 <p><italic>Breastfeeding rates are below desired levels in the United States. Health care professionals lack breastfeeding knowledge. Education of health care professionals about breastfeeding has been shown to improve breastfeeding rates but has been difficult to implement on a large scale</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0890334411435990">
<title>Newly Expressed</title>
<p><italic>“BreastfeedingBasics,” a Web-based educational program, has been used by more than 15 000 health care professionals and students. Knowledge increased as measured by pre-test and post-test scores. It meets the majority of knowledge competencies recommended by the US Breastfeeding Committee and has been successfully incorporated into health care professional curricula</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0890334411435990">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Breastfeeding is vitally important to the health of mothers and infants. Although the United States reached the Surgeon General’s Healthy People 2010 goal of a breastfeeding initiation rate of 75%, none of the goals related to duration of breastfeeding have been met on a national level.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0890334411435990">1</xref></sup> The health care professionals caring for breastfeeding women and children include physicians, nurse practitioners, physician assistants, midwives, lactation consultants, nurses, dieticians, doulas, and students in all these fields. These health care professionals and students (HCP/S) need to have basic knowledge about breastfeeding to develop the skills to support and provide appropriate care to breastfeeding mothers and their infants if the national breastfeeding goals are to be met and maternal and infant health is to be improved.</p>
<p>The US Breastfeeding Committee (USBC) published a list of competencies in 2010, including 11 knowledge competencies, 5 skills competencies, 11 attitude competencies, 10 overall competencies, and 5 hands-on competencies for those health care professionals who provide primary care for women of childbearing age and/or infants and young children.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0890334411435990">2</xref></sup> This mirrors the trend of moving toward competency-based curricula throughout medicine. Assessment of competency relies on the measurement of the ability of learners to perform the real tasks of their discipline by faculty to judge their preparedness for unsupervised practice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0890334411435990">3</xref></sup> The demonstration of competence is a complex task, building “on a foundation of scientific knowledge, basic clinical skills, and moral development.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0890334411435990">4</xref></sup> For health care providers who work with breastfeeding women and their babies, provision of the appropriate knowledge base must be combined with the opportunity to practice the skills and cultivate the attitudes that allow successful promotion of breastfeeding. This is in keeping with the notion that learners have to “know” before they “know how.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0890334411435990">5</xref></sup> Several breastfeeding curricula were evaluated before the publication of the recent USBC competencies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0890334411435990">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0890334411435990"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0890334411435990"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0890334411435990"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0890334411435990"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0890334411435990"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0890334411435990">12</xref></sup> Four of these showed improved outcomes as measured by increased breastfeeding rates,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0890334411435990">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0890334411435990">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0890334411435990"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0890334411435990">10</xref></sup> and 2 documented improvements in provider behavior.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0890334411435990">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0890334411435990">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>“BreastfeedingBasics,” a free, self-study Internet-based curriculum, was developed in 1999 to address resident breastfeeding knowledge, long before the education community began revolving its activities around competencies and over a decade before the 2010 USBC competencies were published. The need for a strong knowledge base in this important clinical area remains. Therefore, the authors undertook this study to evaluate the effectiveness of “BreastfeedingBasics” in meeting the knowledge competencies recommended for health care professionals by the USBC, to measure the knowledge gained by HCP/S, and to assess the benefits of using “BreastfeedingBasics” as parts of structured curricula in breastfeeding education.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0890334411435990" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section10-0890334411435990">
<title>Description of “BreastfeedingBasics”</title>
<p>“BreastfeedingBasics,” at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.BreastfeedingBasics.org">www.BreastfeedingBasics.org</ext-link>, is a free online breastfeeding education course designed for health care professionals. It was developed by the authors (faculty at Case Western Reserve University and Rainbow Babies and Childrens Hospital) and has been available since April 1999. Content updates were completed (by the author M.E.O.) in 2000, 2002, 2005, 2008, and 2010. It has 7 modules: (1) benefits and barriers, (2) anatomy and physiology, (3) the growth and development of the breastfed infant, (4) breastfeeding around the world, (5) the breastfeeding couple, (6) the term infant with problems, and (7) breast milk and drugs. Each module has learning objectives; didactic information including pictures, x-rays, and case studies; and a pre-test and post-test composed of 3 questions with varying numbers of correct multiple-choice answers. After completing a pre-test, the user is given the total number of correct answers achieved but not which answers are correct. After completing the post-test, the learner receives all the correct answers. Faculty who incorporate “BreastfeedingBasics” into a formal curriculum can receive their students’ pre-test and post-test scores electronically to monitor completion of the course.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0890334411435990">
<title>User Demographics</title>
<p>Users of “BreastfeedingBasics” register for the course by picking a log-on and password and providing demographic information including gender, age group, location, and profession. They are also asked to indicate whether they are registering as part of a course or job requirement and whether they or their partners have ever breastfed an infant. All registered users are assigned an anonymous random identification number that links the demographic information to pre-test and post-test scores. We excluded users who were not HCP/S from the analysis. All others were placed in the following professional categories: physicians, residents, lactation consultants, midlevel providers (midwives, nurse practitioners, and physician assistants), nurses, students, and other health professionals. Location categories used were United States, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Europe, and other.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0890334411435990">
<title>Relationship of Course Content to USBC Competencies</title>
<p>We compared the module contents of “BreastfeedingBasics” to the 11 knowledge competencies recommended by the USBC to determine how well they aligned and where gaps existed. Each module was reviewed by 2 outside unpaid reviewers and the last author. Characteristics of the outside reviewers were 1 registered nurse certified as a lactation counselor, 1 general pediatrician with an interest in education, and 2 general pediatricians who have been medical directors of a newborn nursery. The last author reviewed all 7 modules, while each outside reviewer completed a review of 3 or 4 modules. When the outside 2 reviewers agreed that a competency was covered in a module, it was listed as covered. The last author reviewed the list for accuracy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0890334411435990">
<title>Acquisition of Knowledge</title>
<p>Pre-test and post-test scores were calculated for each individual by adding the total number of correct answers and dividing by the total number of possible answers. Mean pre-test and post-test scores were calculated for all registered users who completed both the pre-test and post-test in a module.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0890334411435990">
<title>Benefits of “BreastfeedingBasics” as Part of Structured Courses</title>
<p>During February and March 2009, a Web-based link to a survey was sent via email to all faculty using “BreastfeedingBasics” in a curriculum who had requested students’ test scores. Faculty were identified only by email address, available only to the principal investigator. Faculty reported their location and job title, as well as descriptions of their students by profession or planned profession and the modules used. They also answered questions about benefits of using the course, whether the Web-based course was combined with clinical work, and if the faculty had evaluated knowledge gained or behavioral change in their students after completion of “BreastfeedingBasics.” Responses were collected and analyzed using descriptive statistics, χ<sup>2</sup> test, and χ<sup>2</sup> test for trend.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0890334411435990">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Data analysis was completed using SPSS for Windows version 14.0 and OpenEpi version 2.3.1. Because of non-normality of pre-test and post-test scores, the means were compared using Wilcoxon signed rank test. This project was classed as exempt research by the Colorado Multiple Institutional Research Board.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0890334411435990" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section17-0890334411435990">
<title>Demographics</title>
<p>Between April 13, 1999, and December 31, 2009, 18 522 users registered to use “BreastfeedingBasics.” Of these, 15 020 (81%) were HCP/S in the health care fields; HCP/S were predominately from the United States (85%), with another 11% from Canada, Europe, Australia, or New Zealand. These percentages were stable over the 11 years.</p>
<p>The total number of HCP/S users increased annually from 319 in 1999 to more than 2300 in 2009. The HCP/S users in different professional fields are shown by year in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0890334411435990">Figure 1</xref>. Student users increased from 14% to 39% of the total users annually. The usage by nursing students and other health professional students increased with unchanged usage by medical students over the 11 years. There was no increase in use by residents over the years. The annual usage by lactation consultants and physicians decreased from 22% to 10 % and from 27% to 7% of the total, respectively, over the same time period.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0890334411435990" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Percentages of different health care professionals and students using “BreastfeedingBasics” from 1999 to 2009.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0890334411435990-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>From 1999 to 2009, HCP/S who were required to complete “BreastfeedingBasics” for a job or school requirement increased from 32% to 78%, and those with personal or partner breastfeeding experience decreased from 68% to 50%. The increase in usage by students was associated with an increased percentage of users younger than 25 years from 4% to 22% and decreased percentage of users 41 years and older from 39% to 22% (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001, χ<sup>2</sup> for trend for each of these changes). The percentage of users between 25 and 40 years was unchanged.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0890334411435990">
<title>Meeting USBC Competencies</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0890334411435990">Table 1</xref> compares the USBC core breastfeeding knowledge competencies for primary care providers with information in “BreastfeedingBasics.” “BreastfeedingBasics” meets 8 of the 11 knowledge competencies.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0890334411435990" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of USBC Knowledge and Overall Competencies Recommended for Primary Care Providers Caring for Women of Childbearing Age, Infants, and Young Children with Content in “BreastfeedingBasics” Web Site<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0890334411435990">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0890334411435990" xlink:href="10.1177_0890334411435990-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Knowledge Competency</th>
<th align="center">Modules that Address this Topic</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1.1 Basic anatomy and physiology of the breast</td>
<td>Anatomy and physiology</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.2 Role of breastfeeding and human milk in maintaining health and preventing disease</td>
<td>Benefits and barriers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Growth/development of breastfed infant, Breastfeeding around the world</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.3 Importance of exclusive breastfeeding and its correlation with optimal health outcomes</td>
<td>Benefits and barriers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Growth/development of breastfed infant</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.4 Impact of pregnancy, birth, and other health care practices on breastfeeding outcomes</td>
<td>Breastfeeding around the world</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.5 Role of behavioral, cultural, social, and environmental factors in infant feeding decisions and practices</td>
<td>Benefits and barriers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Breastfeeding around the world</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Breastfeeding couple</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.6 Potentially adverse outcomes for infants and mothers who do not breastfeed</td>
<td>Growth/development of breastfed infant</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.7 Potential problems associated with the use of human milk substitutes</td>
<td>Growth/development of breastfed infant</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.8 Few evidence-based contraindications to breastfeeding</td>
<td>Benefits and barriers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Breastfeeding around the world</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Breast milk and drugs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.9 Indications for referral to lactation services</td>
<td>Not covered</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.10 Resources available to assist mothers seeking breastfeeding and lactation information or services</td>
<td>Not covered</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.11 Effects of marketing of human milk substitutes on the decision to breastfeed and the duration of breastfeeding</td>
<td>Not covered</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0890334411435990">
<label>a</label>
<p>For complete listing of competencies, see US Breastfeeding Committee (USBC).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0890334411435990">3</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0890334411435990">
<title>Acquisition of Knowledge</title>
<p>During the study period, 8680 learners completed 1 or more paired pre-test and post-test. All modules showed a significant increase in post-test scores (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001, Wilcoxon signed rank test, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0890334411435990">Table 2</xref>). The mean increase from pre-test to post-test scores was ≥17 percentage points in the modules of anatomy and physiology, growth and development of the breastfed infant, and the term newborn with problems.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0890334411435990" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of Paired Pre-test and Post-test Scores for All Health Care Professionals and Health Professional Students Using “BreastfeedingBasics”<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0890334411435990">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0890334411435990" xlink:href="10.1177_0890334411435990-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Percentage Correct (1 SD)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Module</th>
<th align="center">No. of Users<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0890334411435990">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Mean Pre-test Correct</th>
<th align="center">Mean Post-test Correct</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Benefits and barriers</td>
<td>7603</td>
<td>89.4 (9.2)</td>
<td>94.3 (7.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Anatomy/physiology</td>
<td>6470</td>
<td>72.5 (16.3)</td>
<td>89.8 (10.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Growth and development</td>
<td>4738</td>
<td>70.2 (15.5)</td>
<td>86.5 (12.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Breastfeeding around the world</td>
<td>4475</td>
<td>83.5 (13.1)</td>
<td>92.3 (9.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Normal newborn</td>
<td>5519</td>
<td>77.6 (16.7)</td>
<td>91.3 (10.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Term newborn with problems</td>
<td>5180</td>
<td>66.0 (18.6)</td>
<td>85.9 (14.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Breast milk and drugs</td>
<td>4449</td>
<td>79.6 (13.0)</td>
<td>88.7 (11.7)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0890334411435990">
<label>a</label>
<p>The number of users reflects those completing both the pre-test and post-test of the module. <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001 for each paired comparison by Wilcoxon signed rank test.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0890334411435990">
<title>Benefits of “BreastfeedingBasics” as Part of Structured Courses</title>
<p>In January 2009, 69 faculty were receiving scores for their students, of which 58 were teaching active courses unrelated to the authors. After 3 emails over 6 weeks, 37 (63%) responded to the survey, of which 34 faculty were in the United States and 3 were in Canada. Eight (22%) of the faculty classified themselves as clinicians in nursing; 8 (22%) as clinicians in medical school or residency programs; 8 (22%) as managers of doulas, lactation programs, or hospital departments; 7 (19%) as faculty in graduate programs for nurse practitioners, nutrition, or nurses; and 5 (14%) as faculty in undergraduate nursing programs.</p>
<p>The 3 most common benefits of using “BreastfeedingBasics” noted by the faculty were cost (it is free), having a broad scope, and that it can be completed on the students’ own time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0890334411435990">Figure 2</xref>). Of 20 faculty who reported that using “BreastfeedingBasics” saved lecture time, 9 (45%) and 7 (35%) reported a saving of 1 to 2 hours and 3 to 5 hours per year, respectively. Other benefits reported by 7 faculty were that the content was in depth, evidence based, well-annotated, and up to date. Thirty-one (84%) of the faculty combined the use of BreastfeedingBasics with clinical work in breastfeeding. This was most commonly described as working with lactation consultants and breastfeeding mothers and infants in labor and delivery, the newborn nursery, and postpartum care areas.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0890334411435990" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Percentage of 37 faculty reporting each benefit as important to them.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0890334411435990-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p>Twenty-six of the faculty (72%) relied on the pre-test and post-test scores as their only measure of their students’ gain in knowledge. Only 5 of the faculty (14%) reported measuring behavioral change in their students. Two observed clinical interactions of their students, and 3 measured changes in clinical outcomes or process measures used for certification as a Baby-Friendly Hospital.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0890334411435990" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>BreastfeedingBasics is an 11-year-old online curriculum that meets the majority, 8 of 11, of the breastfeeding knowledge competencies recommended in 2010 by the USBC. It has been used by more than 15 000 health care professionals and students to gain knowledge about breastfeeding at no cost. It was developed to provide an easy and inexpensive way to teach pediatric residents but has expanded to serve learners in a large variety of health care disciplines. Total usage has increased over the 11-year period, with increasing numbers of users who were required to complete the course as part of a school or work requirement.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, this is not the case for the residents who were envisioned as the target learners. A national survey in 2000 of young pediatricians reported that 75% of men and 64% of women surveyed felt only somewhat or not confident handling breastfeeding problems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0890334411435990">13</xref></sup> In a recent survey, 70% of responding pediatric residency program directors reported a mean of 9 hours of breastfeeding education during 3 years of pediatric residency with a range of 0.5 to 68 hours. Most of the education was reportedly delivered via lectures or grand rounds with some teaching in continuity clinic or rounds with physicians. Major barriers to increasing breastfeeding education reported in these pediatric residencies were lack of resident time, lack of faculty time, and lack of faculty with breastfeeding knowledge.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0890334411435990">14</xref></sup> Because “BreastfeedingBasics” is an online resource, it can meet all 3 of the above needs while being a more interactive method of learning than listening to lectures. Feldman-Winter et al evaluated a breastfeeding curriculum on a randomized group of pediatric, family medicine, and obstetrics/gynecology residency programs that applied for inclusion in the study. This multisite trial included education in breastfeeding knowledge and clinical care. It improved knowledge, confidence, and practice patterns of the residents with resultant increased breastfeeding rates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0890334411435990">6</xref></sup> Use of “BreastfeedingBasics” to present didactic information combined with hands-on training in clinical breastfeeding care is another manner of presenting a breastfeeding curriculum.</p>
<p>With regard to competencies, “BreastfeedingBasics” meets 8 of the 11 breastfeeding knowledge competencies recommended by the USBC. To our knowledge, there are no other comparisons of a breastfeeding educational program with these competencies. Although it was not designed for this purpose, the knowledge needed to provide care to breastfeeding mothers and infants is the same, whether one is interested only in measuring knowledge or in taking the next step and building on that knowledge with additional educational activities to ensure competence. In fact, 84% of the faculty using “BreastfeedingBasics” as part of a formal curriculum combined it with clinical experience for exactly that reason. Combining the knowledge piece with clinical experience in labor and delivery, newborn infant care, and postpartum maternal care should allow ample attention to at least 3 of the 5 USBC hands-on competencies, including assisting in initiation of breastfeeding, being able to recognize normal and abnormal feeding patterns, and developing and communicating a breastfeeding care plan.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0890334411435990">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>“BreastfeedingBasics” is being used in a wide variety of settings from undergraduate nursing to postgraduate nurse practitioner, medical school, and residency education. It provides course leaders and faculty with an easily accessible and free curriculum for their students that can be used by learners on their own time. Using online education can allow content to be addressed even if there is not a teacher with expertise available.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0890334411435990">14</xref></sup> Our data show a statistically significant increase in post-test scores in all modules as a measure of the ability of “BreastfeedingBasics” to provide knowledge to its users. Scores increased the greatest in the modules with the lowest pre-test scores. The effectiveness of electronic medical education has been compared to non–computer-based interventions in increasing knowledge in several studies. These have shown either equivalent or increased gains in knowledge using online education compared to non–computer-based educational methods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0890334411435990">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0890334411435990"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0890334411435990"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0890334411435990">18</xref></sup> Although having basic breastfeeding knowledge does not ensure that a health care professional will provide appropriate patient care, knowledge is 1 of the 7 dimensions of professional competence, including the technical, integrative, contextual, relational, affective, and self-reflective elements described in the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0890334411435990">4</xref></sup> Knowledge is also the base of Miller’s framework for clinical assessment; therefore, it must be the first step in reaching competence of care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0890334411435990">5</xref></sup> The modules of “BreastfeedingBasics” provide an effective platform for obtaining the requisite knowledge base so that face-to-face teaching time can be used to work on the other dimensions of competence.</p>
<p>Assessment of educational interventions remains a challenge. Most of the faculty using our course in a formal curriculum did not measure change in behavior or clinical outcomes. However, 3 clinicians reported that they incorporated “BreastfeedingBasics” as part of their educational interventions in the hospital setting as they achieved Baby Friendly Hospital certification. The recent <italic>The Surgeon General’s Call to Action to Support Breastfeeding</italic> released in January 2011 focuses 1 of its 20 goals on ensuring that hospital maternity care practices are fully supportive of breastfeeding. Hospitals can accomplish this by meeting the criteria to become a Baby-Friendly Hospital.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0890334411435990">19</xref></sup> Use of “BreastfeedingBasics” can help hospitals achieve this goal.</p>
<p>Limitations to our study include that the users of “BreastfeedingBasics” are a selected group of learners who either identified their own need to take the course or were required to do so as part of a formal curriculum. Their baseline and final knowledge scores might not be representative of all learners of their kind. In addition, knowledge retention over time has not been studied, and erosion of knowledge is a concern. However, other breastfeeding curricula and other online curricula have measured knowledge retention and have shown that knowledge can be retained.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0890334411435990">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0890334411435990">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0890334411435990"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0890334411435990">22</xref></sup> We were not able to compare the knowledge gained by use of “BreastfeedingBasics” to knowledge gained by use of other curricula, such as curriculum evaluated by Feldman-Winter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0890334411435990">6</xref></sup> et al or Wellstart curriculum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0890334411435990">23</xref></sup></p>
<p>In summary, “BreastfeedingBasics” is a free Web-based breastfeeding education program that can help health care professionals meet the USBC core breastfeeding knowledge competencies. Use of the course shows knowledge gain as measured by pre-tests and post-tests. It has been used as part of curricula for HCP/S in different disciplines. Wider use of “BreastfeedingBasics” can help improve the breastfeeding knowledge of HCP/S. This is the first step in improving health care professional support to breastfeeding mothers to help them meet their breastfeeding goals. Helping mothers succeed in breastfeeding will help meet the goals of the <italic>Surgeon General’s Report for Healthy People 2020</italic> and <italic>The Surgeon General’s Call to Action to Support Breastfeeding</italic>. Further study evaluating the effect of usage of “BreastfeedingBasics” and clinical training on provider behavior and patient outcomes should be undertaken.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This project would not have been possible without the computer programming skills and support from Emil W. Brown, BEE, MSCS. The authors thank J. Lindsey Lane, MB, Bch, and Carol Carraccio, MD, MA, for reviewing an earlier version of this article and the reviewers who compared the USBC competencies to the content of “BreastfeedingBasics”: Megan Henderson, MD, Karyn Gregory, RN, BSN, Jill Kempthorne, MD, and Maria Martinez-Cardona, MD.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: Northern Ohio Chapter of the March of Dimes and the University Center for Innovation in Teaching and Education of Case Western Reserve University.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0890334411435990">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Breastfeeding report card: United States</article-title>, <year>2010</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/breastfeeding/data/reportcard.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/breastfeeding/data/reportcard.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed December 7, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0890334411435990">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>US Breastfeeding Committee</collab>. <source>Core Competencies in Breastfeeding Care and Services for All Health Professionals</source>. <edition>Rev ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Breastfeeding Committee</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usbreastfeeding.org/AboutUs/PublicationsPositionStatements/tabid/70/Default.aspx">http://www.usbreastfeeding.org/AboutUs/PublicationsPositionStatements/tabid/70/Default.aspx</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed December 7, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0890334411435990">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Competency-based residency training: the next advance in graduate medical education</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1178</fpage>-<lpage>1183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0890334411435990">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hundert</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Defining and assessing professional competence</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>287</volume>:<fpage>226</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0890334411435990">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The assessment of clinical skills/competence/ performance</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>9 suppl</issue>):<fpage>S63</fpage>-<lpage>S67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0890334411435990">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feldman-Winter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milcarek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Residency curriculum improves breastfeeding care</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>126</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>297</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0890334411435990">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ogburn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Espey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leeman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A breastfeeding curriculum for residents and medical students: a multidisciplinary approach</article-title>. <source>J Hum Lact</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>458</fpage>-<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0890334411435990">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taddei</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venancio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Breastfeeding training for health professionals and resultant changes in breastfeeding duration</article-title>. <source>Sao Paulo Med J</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0890334411435990">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Philipp</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merewood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Baby Friendly Hospital initiative improves breastfeeding initiation rates in a US hospital setting</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>677</fpage>-<lpage>681</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0890334411435990">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buzzetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>, and <collab>Breastfeeding Research and Training Working Group</collab>. <article-title>Effect on rates of breastfeeding of training for the Baby Friendly Hospital initiative</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>323</volume>: <fpage>1358</fpage>-<lpage>1362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0890334411435990">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hillenbrand</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of an educational intervention about breastfeeding on the knowledge, confidence and behaviors of pediatric resident physicians</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>e59</fpage>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pediatrics.org/cgi/content/full/110/5/e59">http://www.pediatrics.org/cgi/content/full/110/5/e59</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed December 7, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0890334411435990">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bunik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An investigation of the field trip model as a method for teaching breastfeeding to pediatric residents</article-title>. <source>J Hum Lact</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0890334411435990">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nationwide survey of pediatric residency training in newborn medicine: preparation for primary care practice</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>1081</fpage>-<lpage>1087</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0890334411435990">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Osband</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Breastfeeding education and support services offered to pediatric residents in the US</article-title>. <source>Acad Pediatr</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0890334411435990">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wutoh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boren</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balas</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>eLearning: a review of Internet- based continuing medical education</article-title>. <source>J Contin Educ Health Prof</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0890334411435990">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lockyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of learning outcomes in Web-based continuing medical education</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>10 suppl</issue>):<fpage>S30</fpage>-<lpage>S34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0890334411435990">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farside</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dupras</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montori</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Internet-based learning in the health professions: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>300</volume>:<fpage>1181</fpage>-<lpage>1196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0890334411435990">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lam-Antoniades</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ratnapalan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tait</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Electronic continuing education in the health professions: an update on evidence from RCTs</article-title>. <source>J Contin Educ Health Prof</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0890334411435990">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>US Department of Health and Human Services</collab>. <source>The Surgeon General’s Call to Action to Support Breastfeeding</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Department of Health and Human Services, Office of the Surgeon General</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/topics/breastfeeding/index.html">http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/topics/breastfeeding/index.html</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed December 7, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0890334411435990">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term impact of four different strategies for delivering an online curriculum about herbs and other dietary supplements</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Educ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6920/6/39">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6920/6/39</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed December 7, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0890334411435990">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Surprenant</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <article-title>A community-based trial of an online intimate partner violence CME program</article-title>. <source>Am J Pre Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0890334411435990">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fordis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ballantyne</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of the instructional efficacy of Internet-based CME with live interactive CME workshops</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>294</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>-<lpage>1051</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0890334411435990">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Wellstart International</collab>. <source>Lactation Management Self-study Modules: Level 1</source>. <edition>3rd ed, rev.</edition> <publisher-loc>Shelbourne, Vt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wellstart International</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wellstart.org">www.wellstart.org</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed December 7, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>