<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"> <front> <journal-meta> <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IRV</journal-id> <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spirv</journal-id> <journal-title>International Review of Victimology</journal-title> <issn pub-type="ppub">0269-7580</issn> <issn pub-type="epub">2047-9433</issn> <publisher> <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc> </publisher> </journal-meta> <article-meta> <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269758012447217</article-id> <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269758012447217</article-id> <article-categories> <subj-group subj-group-type="heading"> <subject>Articles</subject> </subj-group> </article-categories> <title-group> <article-title>Crime and compassion</article-title> <subtitle>Women in prostitution at the intersection of criminality and victimization</subtitle>  </title-group> <contrib-group> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"> <name> <surname>Shdaimah</surname> <given-names>Corey S</given-names> </name> <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0269758012447217"/> </contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"> <name> <surname>Wiechelt</surname> <given-names> Shelly A</given-names> </name> </contrib> <aff id="aff1-0269758012447217">University of Maryland, USA</aff> </contrib-group> <contrib-group content-type="issue"> <contrib contrib-type="guest-editor"> <name> <surname>Balfour</surname> <given-names>Gillian</given-names> </name> </contrib> </contrib-group> <author-notes> <corresp id="corresp1-0269758012447217">Corey S. Shdaimah, School of Social Work, University of Maryland, Baltimore, 525 W. Redwood St., Baltimore, MD 21201, USA. Email: <email>cshdaimah@ssw.umaryland.edu</email> </corresp> </author-notes> <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"> <month>1</month> <year>2013</year> </pub-date> <volume>19</volume> <issue>1</issue> <issue-title>Special issue: Theorizing the intersectionality of victimization, criminalization and punishment of women</issue-title> <fpage>23</fpage> <lpage>35</lpage> <permissions> <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement> <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year> <copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder> </permissions> <abstract> <p>Women who are charged with prostitution sit at an intersection of victimization and criminality. It is widely acknowledged that many women who engage in prostitution, especially those engaged in street prostitution, suffer from a variety of problems including past and current trauma and abuse, substance abuse, mental and physical health disorders, and housing instability. Our interviews and focus groups with 17 women currently and formerly engaged in prostitution reveal that survival needs and coercion are factors in their involvement in prostitution. They are also commonly victimized prior to and during their involvement in prostitution. In August 2007, the State’s Attorney’s Office of the City of Baltimore began an initiative to create an alternative for people who are charged with prostitution, which is a crime in Maryland. These efforts stem from what may be considered a discomfort and ambivalence with a criminological approach to offenders who are simultaneously considered victims. Diversionary approaches are an attempt to manage these ambivalent and often conflicting constructions of women who engage in prostitution. However, such programs will largely serve as a palliative rather than a long term solution if they fail to address the personal and structural factors that severely circumscribe the choices available to this marginalized population.   </p> </abstract> <kwd-group> <kwd>criminality</kwd> <kwd>diversion programs</kwd> <kwd>prostitution</kwd> <kwd>trauma</kwd> <kwd>victimization</kwd> <kwd>women </kwd> </kwd-group> </article-meta> </front> <body> <sec id="section1-0269758012447217"> <title>Prostitution refracted through a criminal justice lens</title> <p>Concerned citizens of Baltimore identify prostitution as a problem in their local communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269758012447217">Pierce, 2008</xref>). They complain about men driving through the community in search of sex and the effluvia generated by prostitution such as used condoms, syringes, and drug vials strewn about neighborhoods and parks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269758012447217">Hermann, 2009</xref>). Citizens expect a public response that will eradicate prostitution in their communities. Many also recognize that the women engaging in prostitution may be vulnerable and need help to exit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269758012447217">Anderson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0269758012447217">Robarge, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0269758012447217"> <italic>The Baltimore Sun</italic>, 2009</xref>). Citizens of Baltimore are not atypical; prostitution has been seen as a nuisance to communities for centuries. </p> <p>Responses to prostitution historically have ranged from complete criminalization and prosecution of all those involved in buying and selling sex to legalization of prostitution as a business enterprise with government regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269758012447217">Evans, 1979</xref>). Proponents of legalized prostitution argue that the professionalization of sex work legitimizes women’s choice to provide sexual services, thereby empowering them. Additionally, a legalized sex industry can be regulated and controlled, thereby reducing the criminality and public health risks associated with prostitution. In the United States, prostitution is illegal except in Nevada, where the determination of legality is left up to each individual county. Prostitution is classified as a misdemeanor with possible punishments of fines or imprisonment that vary across state or county jurisdictions. In Maryland those who are found guilty of prostitution face penalties that include fines up to $500, up to one year in prison, or both (Maryland Code, §11-306). The criminalization of prostitution in the USA is rooted in both public health and morality concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0269758012447217">Weitzer, 2010</xref>). In this article, we use the term ‘prostitution’ rather than the term ‘sex work’, which was created to encompass a broader range of activities including lap dancing, stripping, and pornography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0269758012447217">Quan, 2006</xref>). While we recognize the debate around terminology, we choose this term because of its legal connotations and because this is the term that our respondents used in interviews and focus groups. </p> <p>Social science literature has paid some attention to pathways into prostitution, but these largely focus on individualized experiences such as trauma or drug use. The harm experienced by women in prostitution may be rooted in experiences they had prior to entering prostitution, such as childhood physical or sexual abuse, domestic violence, drug abuse, homelessness, and poverty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269758012447217">Farley, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269758012447217">Hood-Brown, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0269758012447217">Sloss and Harper, 2004</xref>). Once women enter prostitution, they are at increased risk of additional violence and victimization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269758012447217">Dalla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269758012447217">El-Bassel et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0269758012447217">Sanders, 2004</xref>). They are also at increased risk of psychological problems (depression, posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), complex-PTSD, and substance use disorders) and health problems (HIV/AIDS, hepatitis, cervical cancer, other sexually transmitted diseases, dental problems) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269758012447217">Farley, 2003</xref>). Stigmatization and shame, coupled with the effects of substance abuse and trauma, may make it difficult for women in prostitution to have intimate and meaningful relationships, thereby increasing their sense of isolation and loneliness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269758012447217">Farley, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269758012447217">Sallman, 2010</xref>; Sanders, 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0269758012447217">Williamson and Folaron, 2003</xref>). </p> <p>More recently, scholars have examined some of the more systemic factors that influence prostitution, such as poverty, limited employment opportunities, and cultural understandings of women’s roles and options that may make prostitution the best of extremely circumscribed options that women have to survive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269758012447217">O’Connell Davidson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269758012447217">Phoenix, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269758012447217">Shdaimah and Wiechelt, 2012</xref>). Others have noted the importance of legal regimes in structuring the experience of prostitution and impacting on the safety of women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0269758012447217">Scoular, 2010</xref>). However, the exploitation and harm experienced by many women in prostitution have been rendered largely invisible in both legal and treatment processes, as these are often designed to encourage desistance without recognizing or addressing the poverty and trauma that is so often prevalent and intertwined with prostitution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269758012447217">Baldwin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269758012447217">Farley, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269758012447217">2004</xref>). Not only does criminalization generally take no account of systemic or individual motivations to enter into or continue engaging in prostitution, but it can also increase harm. Criminalization often reduces the power and leverage of women engaged in prostitution, making it even more dangerous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269758012447217">Brewis and Linstead, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269758012447217">International Union of Sex Workers, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269758012447217">Sanders, 2005</xref>).</p> <p>Some argue that legalization of prostitution would render the whole operation visible and subject to regulation, thereby reducing the risk for coercion and harms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269758012447217">Nussbaum, 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269758012447217">Raymond (2004</xref>), however, contends that an examination of the effects of social policy regarding prostitution both historically and currently reveals that harms against women remain whether prostitution is legalized or criminalized. Where legalization has occurred, there are reports of increases in illegal and unregulated prostitution and trafficking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269758012447217">Raymond, 2004</xref>). In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0269758012447217">Weitzer (2010</xref>) describes the experience of countries where legalized prostitution has coexisted with compliance with international anti-trafficking measures as well as a <italic>decrease</italic> in trafficking in the Netherlands. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269758012447217">Kuo (2002</xref>) praises the Dutch approach that combines legalization with open discussion of prostitution in a straightforward rather than moralistic manner, allowing for a more rational and inclusive policy process. These indicate that the legalization of prostitution needs not be seen as state approval of trafficking or a slippery slope that leaves trafficking unaddressed. Even where this is legal, however, women engaged in prostitution may continue to operate outside the system to avoid the permanent stigma associated with governmental identification as a prostitute. </p> <p>Abolitionists who do not want to cause further harm to women engaged in prostitution advocate policies that decouple the criminalization of solicitation from prostitution, such as in the Swedish or Canadian models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269758012447217">Almog, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269758012447217">Freeman, 1989</xref>−90). Such approaches aim to curb commercial sex by punishing clients, often referred to as johns, but not those who sell sex. Attempts have also been made to further regulate all forms of commercial sex through civil sanctions or through use of criminal sanctions that do not cite prostitution <italic>per se</italic> but rather target related activities such as ‘kerb-crawling’ or soliciting in public spaces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269758012447217">Melrose, 2006</xref>). These efforts are largely aimed at removing prostitution from certain public spaces, rather than any concern for those engaging in it who have little say in official policies, even if some are adept at learning to work within and around policy changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269758012447217">Sanders, 2005</xref>).   </p> <p>While the prevailing policy response to prostitution in the USA is criminal sanction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0269758012447217">Weitzer, 2000</xref>), some jurisdictions are experimenting with punitive responses that include a supportive or therapeutic component. These are part of the broader problem-solving court efforts across the country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0269758012447217">Porter et al., 2010</xref>). Like their mental health and drug court counterparts, prostitution problem-solving efforts are premised on the belief that current criminal justice responses that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0269758012447217">Wolf (2001)</xref> refers to as ‘revolving door justice’ are insufficient. This is because they do not address the underlying problems such as addiction, poor education or employment skills, and lack of affordable housing that may give rise or contribute to continued engagement in prostitution. The goal of these court-related programs is to decrease prostitution by providing services and attempting to rehabilitate offenders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0269758012447217">Shively et al., 2008</xref>). They represent the profound ambivalence that society has toward women who engage in prostitution. On the one hand, those engaged in prostitution are prosecuted as criminals; on the other hand, proponents of these efforts seek alternatives to the dominant criminal justice framework that defines them <italic>exclusively</italic> as perpetrators. One reason that this tension may remain entrenched in court-based programs, even as some try to resolve it through the provision of desperately needed services, is that criminal justice attempts remain individually focused and do not interrogate or challenge underlying societal factors that motivate women to engage in prostitution.</p> <p>Baltimore City’s efforts to address street-level prostitution resulted in the creation of the Specialized Prostitution Diversion Program (SPD: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269758012447217">Kearney, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0269758012447217">Shdaimah, 2010</xref>). The SPD allows eligible participants to recategorize themselves as victims in need of services. If they successfully complete the 90-day program, the charges against them are <italic>null-processed</italic> and can be expunged, and the re-categorization from alleged offender to (now-treated) victim is complete. In this article, we present our analysis of the perspectives of people engaged in prostitution who are rarely consulted in policy debates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269758012447217">Dalla, 2000</xref>) on the provision of court-based services. </p> </sec> <sec id="section2-0269758012447217" sec-type="methods"> <title>Methods</title> <p>This study is based on interviews and focus groups with people who attended a drop-in program for women engaged in prostitution at an agency called ‘You Are Never Alone’ (YANA), located in a low-income Baltimore City neighborhood. YANA’s Executive Director was a stakeholder on the SPD steering committee, and therefore would be likely to encourage clients to participate in the SPD. YANA allowed us to conduct research on location during drop-in hours, providing a safe, relatively quiet, and private space. YANA has a particular philosophy regarding prostitution − one that largely characterizes it as a survival strategy of last resort rather than an empowered decision or profession; this is likely to have influenced our respondents’ characterization of people engaged in prostitution. </p> <p>Study methods were vetted by YANA clients and staff. They helped refine our questions and informed us on which study procedures would be conducive to eliciting candid responses and avoid giving offense. All study procedures were reviewed and approved by the authors’ respective Institutional Review Boards. The three members of the research team spent a total of approximately 100 hours at YANA between August 2009 and August 2010. We conducted two focus groups that centered on building rapport and understanding how women saw themselves. During the focus groups, women made collages that expressed their dreams and hopes and were asked to share these and talk about them. Focus groups were followed by individual interviews using a semi-structured interview guide. We obtained background information from the 11 participants who completed individual interviews (four completed interviews and focus groups and seven completed interviews only). An additional six participants participated in focus groups but did not complete interviews, for a total sample size of 17. Participants who completed the interviews ranged from 22 to 55 years of age (<italic>M</italic> = 40.55, <italic>SD</italic> = 10.70). Five participants identified their race as White and six as African American. Their years of education ranged from 9 to 15 (5 did not complete high school, 1 obtained a GED, 2 completed high school, and 3 had some college education). The age that participants first entered prostitution ranged from 13 to 36 (<italic>M</italic> = 22.27, <italic>SD</italic> = 6.34). All participants who completed the interview reported traumatic events, most typically physical or sexual violence. Most of the women experienced childhood physical and sexual abuse and physical and sexual violence as adults, including assaults that occurred while they engaged in prostitution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0269758012447217">Wiechelt and Shdaimah, 2011</xref>).</p> <p>All interviews were recorded and transcribed verbatim. We use pseudonyms to protect the confidentiality of our respondents; where respondents chose their own pseudonyms, we use these. Data were analyzed to build and generate descriptive analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269758012447217">Sandelowski, 2000</xref>) and to build theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269758012447217">Charmaz, 2006</xref>) rather than start out with a specific testable hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269758012447217">Padgett, 2008</xref>), which was most appropriate in light of our limited knowledge of participants’ experiences.  We employed a constant comparative method of data analysis to allow us to check emerging themes with subsequent respondents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269758012447217">Charmaz, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0269758012447217">Glaser and Strauss, 1967</xref>). In order to enhance the rigor of our analysis, the researchers developed independent coding schemes. These were reviewed and merged through discussion and consensus in order to create a unified coding scheme, which was then applied to all transcripts including those already coded. NVIVO qualitative data software was used to assist in the analysis. In this article, we draw from data that pertain to how prostitution and people engaged in prostitution were characterized, which was identified by our respondents as the most important information that they would like the courts and policymakers to consider.</p> </sec> <sec id="section3-0269758012447217"> <title>Results</title> <sec id="section4-0269758012447217"> <title>Pathways to prostitution: A matter of choice?</title> <p>One of the key elements of criminal responsibility is <italic>mens rea</italic>, or intent, which implies a level of volition. Prosecutors, law enforcement, and community representatives on the SPD steering committee struggled with punishment as a response to activities that originate in coercion or dire circumstances. This is because when alternatives to prostitution are not available, punishment is likely to be an ineffective deterrent. For some, punishment may also be morally concerning in that it does not seem to be an appropriate response to such a vulnerable group. The sense that people sell sex for money because they have no other choice was pervasive in our interviews and focus groups. Mouse, an African American woman who engaged in prostitution for 20 years but is now an HIV/AIDS educator, said: ‘And everybody that I know of that prostituted did not raise their hand and say, “When I grow up, I want to be a prostitute”.’ All participants described prostitution as something that they felt they were compelled to do. Whether coerced by relatives or partners, economic survival, or addiction, they explained that prostitution was not a profession or activity they would have chosen had they believed that realistic alternatives existed.</p> <p>Nalia, a 22-year-old African American woman who first engaged in prostitution at 16, described YANA as ‘a community of women that are trying to upgrade their life to the point that we’re not in bondage anymore.’ Vu was an African American woman who described herself as ‘a former prostitute.’ Her career aspirations thwarted when she became pregnant at 16, she came from a ‘family of alcoholics’ and has ‘struggled with addiction for the past 30 years.’ Like Nalia, she sought help because ‘it’s hard out on the street. I try to find all the support I can get. Oh, God, I take every opportunity, because we really don’t want to be this way.’ As Nalia’s characterization of bondage implies, escape may be possible but very difficult. The women in our sample, like Vu, told us that while their desire to make changes that will enable them to stop engaging in prostitution was strong, they needed help. In this section, we describe some of the circumstances that led women to feel as though they must engage in prostitution. </p> </sec> </sec> <sec id="section5-0269758012447217"> <title>Vulnerability and exploitation</title> <p>Some women began selling sex for money because they were coerced by others. Kara, a 48-year-old White woman, explained how her childhood influenced her life choices. Her mother ‘tried to get [me and my sister], when we were like 11 and 12, to get into engaging in sexual activity for money.’ <disp-quote> <p>I had to survive because my parents were alcoholics and they fought all the time and would put us out on the street. My sister was 12 and I was 13 … I would watch out for my baby sister. I would say, ‘You sit right here and I’ll be right back.’ And, she would say, ‘Don’t you go with that man.’ And I said, ’I’ll be alright.’ She was only 12, but she would get the tag numbers [of their cars]. </p> </disp-quote> Women also told us that they or others were encouraged or forced into prostitution by partners. Mouse explained: <disp-quote> <p>They think everybody out here wants to do it, but many of them are being forced into prostitution. You know, when you have a boyfriend that you love and you’re trying to make them happy. Or some people are forced by parents. I had a mother that told me that if you didn’t trick to make money that you couldn’t live in her house. </p> </disp-quote> Vision, 52, was an African American woman who engaged in prostitution as a teenager, was married and off the streets for 30 years, and returned to prostitution and addiction after her husband died. She saw prostitution as something that women are forced into: ‘They want to be good women and good mothers to their children, they really do.’ She currently did outreach, talking to women who she said ‘really want to get off the streets, but they don’t have anywhere to go. Then, some of the men that they have to stay with, they just make them do awful things.’ </p> <p>Elana, a 55-year-old White woman, explained that when she first engaged in prostitution, at 26, she thought she had no choice. She worried about other young women whose vulnerability may be exploited.<disp-quote> <p>[A]t the time, I thought I didn’t have any choice and I know a lot of these kids and young women leave home and go out there. They’re such an easy prey. They’re made to feel that they are being taken care of, but all of the time … their pimp is just lulling them into their false security. That’s another place; if anybody can do it − get to these bus stations and stuff, because that’s where a lot of the young ones come in at. </p> </disp-quote> Elana described young people who have no guidance or support as particularly vulnerable. The vulnerability and lack of options perceived by the women in our sample made prostitution seem as though it was their only option for survival. </p> </sec> <sec id="section6-0269758012447217"> <title>Survival</title> <p>Most of the women who participated in our study described their need to engage in prostitution as a means to get money, food, clothing, housing, drugs, or even love. They saw no other way of surviving even though they knew that they were placing themselves at high risk for harm. They also knew that others viewed them as bad, shameful, and criminal.  Maggie, a 32-year-old White woman who had engaged in prostitution for about 8 years, was troubled by the stigma associated with prostitution. She explained: ‘Just because we went out to prostitute doesn’t mean we’re bad people. It just means that that is the only thing we thought we could do to survive.’ Lala, a 26-year-old African American mother, fled an abusive husband, arriving in Baltimore friendless and alone. She got her start in prostitution when a newly found so-called friend suggested prostitution as a means of getting food.<disp-quote> <p>And, in my case, it was usually people who posed to be my friend. They would say, ‘Well, I got a way that you could make some money so that you could go and get something to eat’, or, ‘Well, I’ll go get you something to eat if you do this favor for me’. And that’s pretty much how it started. </p> </disp-quote> </p> <p>She continued to engage in prostitution even though she personally witnessed the violent events that often occur in the lives of women in prostitution. She stated ‘I’ve seen a lot of things happen to girls. From almost getting raped, to getting raped, being beaten, shot at [pause] you know it’s not a pretty thing’. Even though the dangerous risks associated with prostituting herself were evident to her, Lala saw no other way to get housing and care for herself. <disp-quote> <p>I went down there to the rental assistance place and explained my situation to them. I told them that my mother was getting ill and that I need to step up and the only way I really see myself doing that is with a little Section 8 or an income-based apartment, or something along those lines. I really have been turning up every rock I could find to try to do that. Right now, I just feel really helpless.</p> </disp-quote> Vision also described the physical need to survive. <disp-quote> <p>When you’re walking the streets and stuff, you seem like you just worry about where your next meal is going to come from, where you’re going to take your next shower, and where you’re going to lay your head, so this is why a lot of us out there turn to those different men, because, we want somewhere comfortable to lay our heads. When it’s cold out there, you want to get out of the cold. </p> </disp-quote> Like Vision, many others in our sample mentioned housing as a major obstacle to change. Vu explained that even women who do not sell sex on the streets will often engage in unwanted sex in order to remain housed. </p> <p>Nalia got into prostitution for three reasons: being sexually assaulted as a child, not being loved, and needing money. She reported that the two main reasons were the ‘sexual assault and not be[ing] loved’. She described her failed efforts to feel loved through prostitution.<disp-quote> <p>Yea, I would like them to know about the sexual assault and not feeling like you’re loved  so the only way you can feel loved is to go out and do that and maybe I’ll feel loved. And, to be honest, it doesn’t turn out that way. But people don’t see you that way. They just see you as a breaking the law person, as a trick, you just a ho. </p> </disp-quote> She had stopped engaging in prostitution for over two years, but went back to it because she needed money. <disp-quote> <p>I still do it nowadays, I’m still not going to say I’m an angel, because I’m not. I need money, just like everybody else needs money. So, they ask, what do you do it for and I say the money. I need my phone bill paid and I need food, so if you can provide them two, then I don’t have to do it. But if you can’t, then I’m stuck. And, it’s hard because you don’t want to go back, but at the same time, you don’t have nothing.</p> </disp-quote> Kara said she used drugs and alcohol to cope with mental illness and trauma. Kara developed an addiction to heroin and needed to make money so that she could purchase drugs and avoid withdrawal symptoms. She stated: ‘So I was a heroin addict. I didn’t care; I worked the streets for $10 … whatever I could get.’ While she engaged in prostitution as a means to support her addictions, it also led to further trauma and abuse which she suffered as an adult at the hands of partners and johns, as well as myriad health problems including HIV/AIDS and hepatitis. Kara was able to stop using heroin with the help of a methadone maintenance program and got out of prostitution for several years until physical survival needs drove her back. <disp-quote> <p>Like, they call me grandma or mama [pause] but, they know I’m going to do what I’m going to do. And I haven’t been out on the street for 10 years, until two weeks ago when my sister threw me out and I have nowhere else to stay, so I turned back to prostitution to try and survive …</p> <p>To make sure I survive and eat because I’m HIV positive and I gotta take care of myself. And there is no other means of support. I’ve tried everything. They cut me off, and I have no other money, and I can’t go hungry, because I keep ending up in the hospital [pause] dehydrated or something else. So, I’m not doing that anymore [pause] I need to eat.</p> </disp-quote> As for many of our respondents, it could be hard to separate childhood and adult trauma, illness, addiction, economic distress, and prostitution, all of which seemed to be co-occurring and mutually reinforcing.</p> <p>The need to survive, along with the real or perceived absence of other options, clearly influences women’s entrance into prostitution. Access to money and resources provides a fleeting sense of security at tremendous cost. Lala described the motivation, the reward, and the costs of prostitution:<disp-quote> <p>Because they just want to live. That’s all people want to do anyway. That’s why anybody does what they do. Where people see these people as criminals and that they should be locked up, but in all actuality, they’re just people trying to survive. That’s it. They may not be doing it the best way, but hey, nobody was there showing them how to do it any differently. With drugs, it doesn’t really matter where you grew up, there’s no discrimination. But when it comes to criminal activity out here in the poverty stricken neighborhood and nobody has any money. Then someone tells you, ‘all you have to do is this.’ And then you start getting a lot of fast cash and of course that’s gonna feel good and make you feel powerful. But in the process, you have to understand the emotional and physical stress and destruction that they are putting themselves through every night that they get dressed up.</p> </disp-quote> The women we interviewed described very real survival needs that drove them, kept them, or returned them to prostitution. These included the need for shelter, food, love, and addressing physical health concerns. While some might argue whether drugs are necessary for survival, women who struggle with addiction and withdrawal perceived this as a survival need, particularly in the absence of available addiction or mental health treatment. Although prostitution might help women meet immediate survival needs, engaging in prostitution conversely creates and increases risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0269758012447217">Wiechelt and Shdaimah, 2011</xref>). As we discuss below, it also reduces the likelihood that women will be able to ensure their survival in ways other than engaging in prostitution, especially if it reduces their employability by other means through legal, physical and mental health consequences. </p> </sec> <sec id="section7-0269758012447217"> <title>The futility of punishment</title> <p>Respondents told us that programs like the SPD that are designed to help women cease engagement in prostitution should consider the very real survival needs that prostitution allows these women to meet. Punishment for prostitution is likely to have little effect when the need for food, housing, clothing, drugs, or love overrides the shame, degradation, and fear they experience with prostitution. As Lala described:<disp-quote> <p>But, when you’re in that situation, it’s like, okay, you care about me, but what can you do to help my situation? And, if some people really want to change, then they’ll show up for support groups and things like that. But, they’ll wind up dwindling off because they need time to make money, basically. It’s just a vicious cycle.</p> </disp-quote> Help must go beyond support and efforts to transform women in prostitution; it should include a means of meeting basic survival needs in order to be effective over the long term. Even treatment, if not accompanied by concrete material assistance and a means to survive otherwise, is likely not to have a long-term impact. Criminalization of prostitution as a mechanism of deterrence actually sets up the circumstances for women to return to prostitution. It not only fails to provide alternatives for survival, it places additional limitations on women’s options by giving them a criminal record. Nalia explains how:<disp-quote> <p>Because I have so many charges on my record, the state wasn’t trying to get me a job. So I was seen as unemployable. And the state is seen as unforgiving. You’ve broken the law or been given a diagnosis, you’re not going to ever be forgiven for that one act. So it’s almost like you’re continually being punished for something that you did a long time ago. </p> </disp-quote> Many of our respondents indicated that women who leave prison face extreme difficulties finding legal employment. Public benefits (such as public housing) may also be curtailed by convictions. Respondents told us that many women will return to prostitution, especially if they return to their old friends or neighborhoods, for assistance when all else fails. </p> <p>Women’s description of lack of choice may be to some extent self-serving to avoid the stigma and shame associated with prostitution. It is clear from the interviews, however, that women believed that their choices were severely circumscribed. Not only was the perception pervasive, but women told us that they engaged in prostitution despite their awareness of the danger it posed to their health and safety. Reba, a 43-year-old African American woman who first engaged in prostitution when she was 27, learned about YANA when she was in jail. Reba explained succinctly: ‘We lay in bed with people we don’t want to. We make money. We have sex for money.’ She told us ‘I was forced to do stuff I didn’t want to do. I almost got killed several times and managed to get out. ‘Cause I needed the money.’ Similar occurrences of violence at the hands of johns and near fatal incidents to themselves or others were described by most participants. When asked if she felt traumatized by these incidents, Reba replied ‘At the time I was prostituting, no. You do what you have to do and that’s the risk that you take.’ The extreme vulnerability and lack of choice presented by the women in our sample is at the base of court efforts to provide alternatives to incarceration and is consistent with the focus of the SPD. Women engage in prostitution largely because they have been exploited and/or suffer from a variety of personal, health, and economic challenges that make prostitution a rational choice in the absence of other options.</p> </sec> <sec id="section8-0269758012447217"> <title>Discussion</title> <p>While victimization and vulnerability are pervasive, we do not claim that they are always or exclusively present in all cases of prostitution. There is a body of literature, some of it written by sex workers, which sees sex work as legitimate employment that should not be stigmatized or criminalized and, in fact, may be a means to empowerment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269758012447217">Kuo, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0269758012447217">Quan, 2006</xref>). While we do not disagree theoretically that this may fit some people in particular social contexts, this is not an accurate description of our sample of women involved in street-level prostitution work, which is often considered the most stigmatized and risky form of sex work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269758012447217">Chapkis, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0269758012447217">Weitzer, 2009</xref>). None of our study participants used the term sex work or identified prostitution as a volitional career choice or means to empowerment. The women in our sample can best be described by what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269758012447217">O’Connell Davison (1998</xref>) claims is the overwhelming reason that women engage in prostitution: ‘because the economic, political, and social circumstances in which they live make it either the best or the only means of subsisting, or they are people who are forced into prostitution by a third party’ (p. 5). This definition recognizes both the limited range of choices available to women who engage in prostitution and their exercise of varying degrees of agency. Those who were apprehended in the street sweeps that represent the bulk of cases on the Baltimore City during the time frame of our study docket were generally low-income women with histories of drug addiction and trauma and were extremely vulnerable like the women in our sample from YANA (S. Diehl, personal communication, 4 August 2010). </p> <p>We are well aware of the sociology and criminology literature that discusses agency (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269758012447217">Ajzenstadt, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0269758012447217">Rosen and Vankatesh, 2008</xref>; and the literature reviewed there). We searched for expressions of such agency specifically in our analysis of the data and, indeed, found that women did assert agency in a number of ways. Most identified themselves as survivors and had exercised choices, even if these were severely limited by their job opportunities, educational backgrounds, personal histories of trauma, addiction, and other health and mental health problems: Elana, who began charging her husband for sex in order to assert some control over frequent and unexpected rapes; Kara, who asked her sister to write down license plate numbers; all of the women who sought out and provided mutual assistance to fellow YANA members. The women we spoke with displayed dignity, strength, and a strong will to survive. However, the expressions of agency were in circumstances that were so severely circumscribed as to make them pale in comparison to the lack of better alternatives, so that they often seemed theoretical and unrealistic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269758012447217">Baldwin, 2006</xref>). Like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269758012447217">Freeman (1989</xref>−90), while we do not doubt accounts of empowerment and agency by some women engaged in prostitution, they do not accurately describe the experiences of the women in our study. </p> <p>The acquisition of money in an impoverished environment is in some ways empowering. The internal logic of our respondents is consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0269758012447217">Rosen and Venkatesh’s (2008)</xref> assertion, based on ethnographic research on prostitution in one Chicago community, that prostitution may be a rational choice given social and personal circumstances. While context and social environment may make engaging in prostitution rational, it would be hard to suggest that the social circumstances that make prostitution a viable and even preferable alternative are ideal or should be celebrated. The dangers, particularly of street level prostitution, are real and severe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269758012447217">Dalla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269758012447217">El-Bassel et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0269758012447217">Sanders, 2004</xref>). The social stigma of engaging in prostitution is also very real, even if it may be lessened in communities that recognize prostitution as a logical option. </p> <p>The very real problem of limited agency is particularly troubling in criminal cases. While women intend to engage in prostitution in the sense that this term is used to construct criminal responsibility under the law, their highly circumscribed choices lead them to feel compelled to do so despite both a desire to desist and fear of legal consequences. Prosecution and punishment generally serve goals of deterrence and rehabilitation. Criminalization makes little sense if prostitution is understood as coercion, or as the best and most logical choice under severely limited personal, social, and economic circumstances. Criminalization, prosecution, and punishment will not deter or rehabilitate women engaging in prostitution if the underlying circumstances and prevailing socio-economic arrangements go unchanged. Interviews with women in YANA tell us that punitive criminal responses to women who sell sex for money are unlikely to be successful. </p> <p>Some have suggested that problem-solving court models are adaptations to the result of failed punitive policies such as the USA War on Drugs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269758012447217">McCoy, 2003</xref>), which can do little to meet the needs of its target population. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269758012447217">Phoenix (2007</xref>) asserts that neo-liberal tactics of managing prostitution are a hybrid form of governance from above (top down coercive state) and below (volunteer and social service agencies). Thus, the SPD may be about governance intended to manage street-level prostitution as much as (or more than) it is about rectifying a mismatch between policy response to prostitution and the needs of women engaged in prostitution. Regardless of policy frameworks and shifts in criminalization logics, the material realities of poverty and violence against women cannot be managed nor remedied by a coercive state. The legal system has been able to sidestep a more contentious debate over a prostitution policy rife with internal contradictions through programs such as the SPD. Such programs allow the state to continue criminal sanctions as a societal expression of disapproval for prostitution while acknowledging the limited options facing those who engage in it but without having to grapple with the systemic and societal forces that so severely circumscribe these choices. The offer of services through the courts or the prosecution such as the SPD and similar problem-solving efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0269758012447217">Shively et al., 2008</xref>) is an important and welcome palliative for the mismatch between a penal approach and the underlying causes of prostitution and the social factors that make it a viable ‘choice’ for women like those in our sample. However, it is also concerning if it deflects our attention from challenging the societal conditions that allow for the circumscription of women’s choices and the exploitation of victimization and vulnerability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269758012447217">Bumiller, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0269758012447217">Shdaimah, 2010</xref>). So long as these diversionary programs do not grapple with the underlying concerns they can only go so far as a remedy in individual cases or as a broader social phenomenon. </p> </sec> </body> <back> <ack> <title>Acknowledgements</title> <p>We wish to thank the women at YANA, both staff and clients, who shared their experiences and fellowship with us. We also acknowledge our research assistant Briana Walters, who worked with us on this project.</p> </ack> <ref-list> <title>References</title> <ref id="bibr1-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Ajzenstadt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The relative autonomy of women offenders’ decision making</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Criminology</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr2-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="web"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Almog</surname> <given-names>S</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Prostitution as exploitation: An Israeli perspective</article-title>. <source>Georgetown Journal of Gender and Law</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>711</fpage>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1691198#">http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1691198#</ext-link>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr3-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Prostitutes could find help, not jail time; city group wants court to reach out</article-title>. <source>The Baltimore Sun</source>, <issue>18 June</issue>: <fpage>A1</fpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr4-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Baldwin</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Split at the root: Prostitution and feminist discourse</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"> <name> <surname>Spector</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (ed.) <source>Prostitution and Pornography: Philosophical Debate about the Sex Industry</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr5-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Brewis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Linstead</surname> <given-names>S</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The worst thing is the screwing: Consumption and the management of identity in sex work (1)</article-title>. <source>Gender, Work &amp; Organization</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr6-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Bumiller</surname> <given-names>K</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>In an Abusive State: How Neoliberalism Appropriated the Feminist Movement Against Sexual Violence</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr7-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Chapkis</surname> <given-names>W</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Power and control in the commercial sex trade</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"> <name> <surname>Weitzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> </person-group> (ed.) <source>Sex for Sale</source>. <publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr8-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Charmaz</surname> <given-names>K</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Constructing Grounded Theory: A Practical Guide Through Qualitative Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr9-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Dalla</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Exposing the ‘pretty woman’ myth: A qualitative examination of the lives of female streetwalking prostitutes</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Sex Research</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr10-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Dalla</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Night moves: A qualitative investigation of street-level sex work</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Women Quarterly</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr11-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>El-Bassel</surname> <given-names>N</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Witte</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Wada</surname> <given-names>T</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Gilbert</surname> <given-names>L</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Wallace</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Correlates of partner violence among female street-based sex workers: Substance abuse, history of childhood abuse, and HIV risks</article-title>. <source>AIDS Patient Care and STDS</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr12-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>H</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>The Oldest Profession: An Illustrated History of Prostitution</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>David &amp; Charles</publisher-name>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr13-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Farley</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Prostitution and the invisibility of harm</article-title>. <source>Women and Therapy</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr14-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Farley</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>‘Bad for the body, bad for the heart’: Prostitution harms women even if legalized or decriminalized</article-title>. <source>Violence Against Women</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1125</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr15-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Freeman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1989−90</year>) <article-title>The feminist debate over prostitution reform: Prostitutes’ rights groups, radical feminists, and the (im)possibility of consent</article-title>. <source>Berkeley Women’s Law Journal</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr16-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Glaser</surname> <given-names>B</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Strauss</surname> <given-names>A</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <source>The Discovery of Grounded Theory: Strategies for Qualitative Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine</publisher-name>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr17-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Hermann</surname> <given-names>P</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Working ‘girls’ stymie police and neighbors; Residents of Old Goucher seek solution for long-standing problem</article-title>. <source>The Baltimore Sun</source>, <issue>27 May</issue>: <fpage>A3</fpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr18-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Hood-Brown</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Trading for a place: Poor women and prostitution</article-title>. <source>Journal of Poverty</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr19-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="web"> <collab collab-type="author">International Union of Sex Workers</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>IUSW calls for decriminalisation of sex work to increase worker safety</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iusw.org/2010/10/iusw-calls-for-decriminalisation-of-sex-work-to-increase-worker-safety/">http://www.iusw.org/2010/10/iusw-calls-for-decriminalisation-of-sex-work-to-increase-worker-safety/</ext-link>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr20-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="web"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Kearney</surname> <given-names>B</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A pilot program to rehabilitate commercial sex workers has given some graduates a way out</article-title>. <source>Maryland Daily Record</source>, <issue>15 February</issue>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mddailyrecord.com/article.cfm?id=11929andtype=UTTM">http://www.mddailyrecord.com/article.cfm?id=11929andtype=UTTM</ext-link> </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr21-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Kuo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Prostitution Policy: Revolutionizing Practice through a Gendered Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr22-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>McCoy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The politics of problem-solving: An overview of the origins and development of therapeutic courts</article-title>. <source>American Criminal Law Review</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1513</fpage>–<lpage>1534</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr23-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Melrose</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Trying to make a silk purse from a sow’s ear? A comment on the government’s prostitution strategy</article-title>. <source>Community Safety Journal</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr24-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Nussbaum</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>‘Whether from reason or prejudice’: Taking money for bodily services</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Legal Studies</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr25-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>O’Connell Davison</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Prostitution, Power and Freedom</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr26-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Padgett</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Qualitative Methods in Social Work Research</source>, <edition>2nd edition</edition>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr27-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Phoenix</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Making Sense of Prostitution</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>St. Martin’s Press</publisher-name>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr28-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Phoenix</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Governing prostitution: New formations, old agendas</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Law and Society</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr29-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Pierce</surname> <given-names>C</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>State grant money to fund prostitution court</article-title>. <source>Examiner</source>, <issue>13 August</issue>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr30-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="web"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Porter</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Rempel</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Masky</surname> <given-names>A</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>What makes a court problem-solving: A report submitted to the State Justice Institutes</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.courtinnovation.org/_uploads/documents/What_Makes_A_Court_P_S.pdf">http://www.courtinnovation.org/_uploads/documents/What_Makes_A_Court_P_S.pdf</ext-link>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr31-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Quan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The name of the pose: A sex worker by any other name?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"> <name> <surname>Spector</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (ed.) <source>Prostitution and Pornography: Philosophical Debate about the Sex Industry</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr32-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Raymond</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ten reasons for <italic>not</italic> legalizing Prostitution and a legal response to the demand for prostitution</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma Practice</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr33-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="web"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Robarge</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Prostitution court is well-intentioned, but resources could be put to better use [Letter to the editor]</article-title>. <comment>Maryland Daily Record, 20 July.</comment> <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mddailyrecord.com/2009/07/20/letter-to-the-editor-24/">http://mddailyrecord.com/2009/07/20/letter-to-the-editor-24/</ext-link>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr34-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Rosen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Venkatesh</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A ‘perversion’ of choice: Sex work offers <italic>just enough </italic>in Chicago’s urban ghetto</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr35-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Sallman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>‘Going hand-in-hand’: Connections between women’s prostitution and substance use</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social Work Practice in the Addictions</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr36-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Sandelowski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Whatever happened to qualitative description?</article-title> <source>Research in Nursing and Health</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr37-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Sanders</surname> <given-names>T</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The risks of street prostitution: Punters, police and protesters</article-title>. <source>Urban Studies</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1703</fpage>–<lpage>1717</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr38-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Sanders</surname> <given-names>T</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Sex Work: A Risky Business</source>. <publisher-loc>Portland, OR</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan</publisher-name>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr39-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Scoular</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>What's law got to do with it? How and why law matters in the regulation of sex work</article-title>. <source>Journal of Law and Society</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr40-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Shdaimah</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Taking a stand in a not-so-perfect world: What’s a critical supporter to do?</article-title> <source>University of Maryland Law Journal of Race, Religion, Gender, and Class</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<fpage>123</fpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr41-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Shdaimah</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Wiechelt</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Converging on empathy: Perspectives on Baltimore City’s Specialized Prostitution Diversion Program</article-title>. <source>Women and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr42-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="web"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Shively</surname> <given-names>M</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Jalbert</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Kling</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Rhodes</surname> <given-names>W</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Finn</surname> <given-names>P</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Flygare</surname> <given-names>C</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Tierney</surname> <given-names>L</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Hunt</surname> <given-names>D</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Squires</surname> <given-names>C</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Dyous</surname> <given-names>C</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Wheeler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Final report on the evaluation of the First Offender Prostitution Program (Grant #2005-DD-Bx-0037)</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Justice, Office of Research and Evaluation</publisher-name>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/grants/222451.pdf">www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/grants/222451.pdf</ext-link> </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr43-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Sloss</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>When sex workers are mothers</article-title>. <source>Archives of Sexual Behavior</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>. </citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr44-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <collab collab-type="author"> <italic>The Baltimore Sun</italic> </collab> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Shame for the shameful: Our view: For a besieged neighborhood, prostitution is hardly a ‘victimless’ crime</article-title>. <issue>28 December</issue>: <fpage>A14</fpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr45-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Weitzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The politics of prostitution in America</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"> <name> <surname>Weitzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> </person-group> (ed.) <source>Sex for Sale</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr46-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Weitzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sociology of sex work</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr47-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Weitzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The movement to criminalize sex work in the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal of Law and Society</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr48-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Wiechelt</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Shdaimah</surname>  <given-names>CS</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Trauma and substance abuse among women in prostitution: Implications for a specialized diversion program</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic Social Work</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>159</fpage>–<fpage>184</fpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr49-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Williamson</surname> <given-names>C</given-names> </name> <name> <surname>Folaron</surname> <given-names>G</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Understanding the experiences of street level prostitutes</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Social Work</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation> </ref> <ref id="bibr51-0269758012447217"> <citation citation-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"> <name> <surname>Wolf</surname> <given-names>RV</given-names> </name> </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Management note: New strategies for an old profession: A court and a community combat a streetwalking epidemic</article-title>. <source>The Justice System Journal</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</citation> </ref> </ref-list> </back> </article>