<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LTR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spltr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Language Teaching Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1362-1688</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0954</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1362168813475950</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1362168813475950</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The use of literacy bags promotes parental involvement in Chinese children’s literacy learning in the English language</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SuHua</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1362168813475950">Midwestern State University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1362168813475950">SuHua Huang, College of Education, Midwestern State University, 3410 Taft Boulevard, Wichita Falls, TX 76308, USA. Email: <email>suhua.huang@mwsu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>251</fpage>
<lpage>268</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study employed an ethnographic methodology to explore the use of ‘literacy bags’ (LBs) to promote parental involvement in Chinese children’s literacy learning in the English language. It was conducted with a first-grade class consisting of 18 students and their parents in Taiwan. Data resources were obtained from teaching questionnaires, classroom observation, home visits, and parental interviews. Each LB contained an English language children’s picture book and CD or audiotape, along with some extension activities. Students took an LB home every Friday and parents spent time reading and doing the activities with their children. The results of this study highlighted the way in which LBs encouraged, supported, and enriched book reading and literacy learning in families. This study also demonstrated that parents expanded their understanding of how a child develops a new language, and they were able to apply effective literacy strategies to engage and discuss books with their children. Reading activities promoted social interactions between parents and children, parents and teachers, and peer interactions. The project also influenced parental attitudes and perceptions of their children’s English literacy development, viewing themselves as teachers of their own children. In addition, this study expanded the scope of the findings of Western scholars to include understandings of the cultures, languages, and families of East Asia.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Chinese students</kwd>
<kwd>literacy bags</kwd>
<kwd>parental involvement</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1362168813475950" sec-type="intro">
<title>I Introduction</title>
<p>Research has widely reported that literacy development begins to evolve when the child is very young through the process of sharing and interacting with family members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1362168813475950">Baker, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362168813475950">Cohen &amp; Cowen, 2011</xref>). Early literacy research has also indicated that a high frequency of reading support could foster children’s ability to attend to text and school learning, and provide motivation for literacy learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1362168813475950">Robinson, Larsen, &amp; Haupt, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1362168813475950">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1362168813475950">Whitmore, Martens, Goodman, &amp; Owocki, 2005</xref>). Some researchers have recently also found that home support is a major factor in fostering higher achievement especially when parents read regularly to their children, promote positive attitudes toward literacy development, and enhance their children’s oral language skills (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1362168813475950">Adams, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1362168813475950">Baker, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1362168813475950">Dever, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1362168813475950">Dever &amp; Burts, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1362168813475950">Neuman &amp; Roskos, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1362168813475950">Opitz, Rubin, &amp; Erekson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1362168813475950">Whitehead, 2002</xref>). These previous studies have found that many parents foster a home environment that supports their children’s reading development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1362168813475950">Dever &amp; Burts, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1362168813475950">Opitz et al., 2011</xref>), but that they lack high-quality reading materials and knowledge of the reading process, and thus are unable to provide effective strategies to support their children’s reading development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1362168813475950">Brock &amp; Dodd, 1994</xref>). Providing diverse families and parents with a variety of reading resources and strategies to promote literacy at home is needed.</p>
<p>The positive effects of parental involvement in their children’s literacy development are now universally recognized and accepted by policy makers and educators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1362168813475950">Barbour, 1999</xref>). The phenomenon of parental involvement in the field of early literacy learning and development is ever present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1362168813475950">Opitz et al., 2011</xref>) and has even expanded to the Chinese societies in Asian nations. Although children’s academic achievement is given a more central role in these societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1362168813475950">Huang, 2011a</xref>), the issue of Chinese parental involvement and engagement in the area of their children’s English literacy skills and language development has neither been addressed nor fully explored.</p>
<p>Teaching English in the primary grades has been highlighted as a national educational objective, and English is a mandatory course in the primary grades in Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1362168813475950">Ministry of Education, 2003</xref>) and other Asian nations. Many researchers, educators, and parents want to know what to do to improve children’s literacy skills and what strategies can improve students’ English skills and interest in learning English at an early stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362168813475950">Huang, 2011b</xref>). Despite the proliferation of studies on English as second language (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1362168813475950">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>), few studies have specifically investigated English language development and learning for Chinese children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1362168813475950">Chen &amp; Harris, 2009</xref>), and even fewer have used English picture books to develop early English literacy skills for Chinese young readers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362168813475950">Huang, 2011b</xref>). Little is known about the use of English picture books for young Chinese children’s second language development and learning.</p>
<p>To meet the above mentioned research limitations and to explore diverse Chinese family needs, this study employed two of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1362168813475950">Epstein’s (1995)</xref> six conceptual frameworks: communicating (designing effective programs between school-to-home and home-to-school communication about children’s progress), and learning at home (helping families to create a literacy-rich home). These two categories advocate a variety of ways in which to involve parents in their children’s education. This study is also grounded in the concept of scaffolding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1362168813475950">Vygotsky, 1978</xref>), which emphasizes the importance of providing for children’s learning through scaffolding and effective instructional strategies as well as helping parents to be supporters. The concept of scaffolding encourages adults to provide a variety of opportunities and optimal levels of learning activities for children so that they can be successful in gradually meeting challenging tasks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1362168813475950">Gambrell &amp; Morrow, 1996</xref>). Scaffolding also emphasizes the need of children to interact with more experienced members of their learning community in order to transfer control of cognitive activity from the teacher to the learner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1362168813475950">Gauvain, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>By merging Vygotsky’s concept of scaffolding and Epstein’s frameworks a model of parental involvement and engagement in the literacy domain was created, and this is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1362168813475950">Figure 1</xref>. This model depicts disposition, knowledge, and skill as the essential bases of reading and language development of a child. Teaching–learning follows together with the three major bases of reading and language development outside of the triangle and is presented as a continual relationship. Parents, teachers, and students are the center of the literacy family inside of the triangle (knowledge–disposition–skill). There are nine major elements of literacy (curriculum, subject matter, new literacy, speaking, listening, writing, reading, assessment, and activities) within the literacy family. This model was also used to examine parental involvement and engagement in literacy development and learning.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1362168813475950" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Parental involvement in literacy learning and development.</p>
<p><italic>Note. This framework is based on Epstein’s framework, and Vygotksy’s concept of scaffolding.</italic></p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1362168813475950-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1362168813475950">
<title>II Literacy bag project</title>
<p>Each ‘literacy bag’ (LB) in this study contained an English language children’s picture book, a CD or audiotape, and a parent’s guidebook (similar to lesson plans) along with related activities involving reading fluency, phonics, vocabulary, comprehension, and writing (see the attached picture in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-1362168813475950">Appendix 1</xref>). All teaching materials were also included in each bag. The guidebook provided details for teaching procedures for each individual and group activity. An example of parental instructions in the guidebook is contained in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app2-1362168813475950">Appendix 2</xref> and selected literacy activities used by the Chinese parents and children are provided in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app3-1362168813475950">Appendix 3</xref>. This LB was similar to Barbour’s developing the home LBs, and the family LBs that were created by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1362168813475950">Dever and Burts (2002)</xref>.</p>
<p>The children took an LB home from school every Friday and they had a week to finish the reading and activities with their parents. The bag then rotated to another student the following week. All the CDs/audiotapes were recorded by professional native English speakers with the proper reading rate. All parents and children were encouraged to listen and follow along with the CDs/audiotapes and work activities together. To consider the children’s various levels of English literacy development, books of different levels of difficulty, themes, genres, and authors were made available to them for use both at home and at school. Over 100 books were selected, based on the Chinese children’s interests and the parents’ and teachers’ recommendations, including <italic>Brown bear, brown bear what do you see, Dr. Seuss’ ABC, Is your mama a llama?, Five little monkeys jumping on the bed</italic>, and a series of <italic>Curious George</italic> books. Some popular Chinese–English children’s storybooks (<italic>If you give a mouse a cookie, The very hungry caterpillar, The foot book</italic>, and <italic>Papa, please get the moon for me</italic>) were also included. For details of these books, see the further reference list ‘Children’s books’ at the end of this article.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1362168813475950" sec-type="methods">
<title>III Methods</title>
<p>This study employed an ethnographic methodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1362168813475950">Merriam, 2009</xref>) in which broad and in-depth case data were gathered from 18 participating parents to investigate the use of LBs to promote parental involvement in Chinese children’s literacy learning in the English language. The aims of the research questions were investigated: How do the LBs foster Chinese parental involvement and engagement in their children’s English language development and literacy learning? How do these Chinese parents use literacy strategies to assist their children’s English development?</p>
<sec id="section4-1362168813475950">
<title>1 Setting and participants</title>
<p>The participating school was a first-6 public elementary school in a suburban area in Taiwan. The school has 6 first-grade classes, and each class has approximately 20 students. Total school enrollment averaged around 700. Classes were held from Monday through Friday, typically from 7:30am though 4:00pm, except that the primary grades’ classes (first grade to third grade) are ended at noon on Wednesdays. The general school curriculum included Chinese, English, mathematics, social studies, science, computers, music, dancing, drawing, crafts, and PE. Since English is a pivotal subject in Chinese-speaking countries and other Asian nations, the school begins teaching English in the first grade. The students were given a two-hour English lesson per week. However, many Chinese parents send their children to English kindergarten before they actually attend school. Kindergarten is not part of compulsory education but there are various types of English kindergarten programs that have been well established, such as Montessori and Sesame Street. In addition, a large number of school aged children attend after-school English programs. Therefore, children have been introduced to the printed and written forms of English before they reach primary school.</p>
<p>One of the first grade classes was randomly selected to participate in this project, and the class has 18 students (9 boys and 9 girls), ranging in age from 6 years to 7 years (<italic>M</italic> = 6 years 7 months). They voluntarily participated in the project for one semester, which ran from January to June. The participating parents of this study included 17 mothers and one father. The father held a master’s degree in teaching English as a second language (TESOL) from the UK. Two of the mothers had master’s degrees; one of them received her degree from the USA. Six other mothers earned bachelor’s degrees, and the remaining participants obtained associate degrees or high-school diplomas. All participants were employed with the exception of three stay-at-home mothers. All parents mentioned that they took a form of the General English Proficiency Test (GEPT), which measures language usage on four levels: elementary, intermediate, high-intermediate, and advanced. Some government agencies and private businesses require employees to take the GEPT. Overall, all the parents in this study could read English above middle or high-school level. Some parents who are school teachers and researchers had higher levels of English proficiency. In the interest of confidentiality, all the names in this study are pseudonyms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1362168813475950">
<title>2 Data collection and analysis</title>
<p>The research involved six data sources: the participating parents; three school teachers (the classroom teacher, the English teacher, and the computer teacher); bi-weekly phone calls with the parents; classroom observational notes; home visits; and parental interviews.</p>
<p>At the end of the semester, the teachers responded to an open-ended questionnaire regarding what they viewed as the strengths and weaknesses of the LB project and what their conversations with the parents revealed. Then the researcher interviewed the parents individually. Specifically, the researcher asked questions regarding what they liked about the project, what they observed about the development of each student’s English language skills, what they found challenging, what they will continue to do in the future, and what they will do differently. The researcher also communicated with the parents on the phone bi-weekly in order to find out how they were doing with the project, and what they thought about the materials. To assure the reliability and validity of the research resources, the role of the researcher during data collection was that of an observer in the classroom and households.</p>
<p>The researcher visited the class once a week and observed the teacher read a book or conduct group activities. The books were used for varied purposes, some emphasized reading fluency and comprehension, and others were focused on vocabulary learning and writing skills. Some books (<italic>The enormous carrot, The doorbell rang, To market, to market</italic>, and <italic>The surprise garden</italic>) were used for group activities including Bingo, Literature Circle, World Theater (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1362168813475950">Boning, 1978</xref>), WORD-A-RADES, Vocabulary Operation, Guess What, and Jeopardy. The researcher observed a total of 22 lessons in the classroom. In addition, each month the researcher observed how each student did activities with their parents and what types of reading materials and activities the children liked. The researcher generally spent about 30–35 minutes for each home visit. Finally, all the parents’ interview data was audiotaped and transcribed into English for analysis.</p>
<p>The constant comparative method was used to analyse the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1362168813475950">Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967</xref>). The researcher used a triangulation strategy by reading and rereading the data, making notes in the margins commenting on the data, interpreting meaning and moving back and forth between inductive and deductive reasoning, and also reflecting between description and interpretation of what participants said and what the researcher had seen and read. The process of the analysis involved coding individual units, creating categories, comparing incidents applicable to each category, integrating categories, deleting overlapping categories, finalizing categories, and developing themes. Data analysis was ongoing when categories were being identified and refined. Data analysis was completed when new information was no longer uncovered and appropriate categories were identified. Quotes or information about themes were identified to support the findings. The four final themes were identified and examined to determine the use of scaffolding and Epstein’s framework and how the research questions related to each other.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section6-1362168813475950" sec-type="results">
<title>IV Results</title>
<p>Four major themes emerged from this study. The first theme was termed resources, which included quality English children’s picture books and CDs/audiotapes for parents to use at home. It also included the contents of the books and activities in the LB. The second theme, instruction, encompassed many units of analysis that revealed the overall structure of this project and utilized a parent guidebook (similar to lesson plans). It also included some culture relevant materials, Chinese and American holidays (Chinese New Year, Easter holiday, Mother’s Day, and Independence Day), and activities, which were selected for each month. The third theme, opportunity, included statements about the quality of the total time spent that involved reading activities between parents and children. Motivation emerged as the final theme. The theme of motivation was covered in many areas of the parents’ interview data, phone communications, and field notes. The theme of motivation was incorporated in parents’ statements saying they learned a great deal about their children’s reading interests, curiosity, learning attitudes, language development, and reading progress. It also included statements about the role of the parents in their children’s English language and literacy development.</p>
<sec id="section7-1362168813475950">
<title>Theme 1: The literacy bag project served as a major resource for parents to work with their children’s literacy development and learning</title>
<p>Two subthemes were found:</p>
<list id="list1-1362168813475950" list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>resources for parents, teachers, and children; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>resources from the content of the books.</p></list-item></list>
<sec id="section8-1362168813475950">
<title>a Resources for parents, teachers, and children</title>
<p>All the parents and teachers commented that the LB provided them with a wide array of children’s picture books, including informational books. It also served as the most prominent reading resource for the children. All parents indicated the repetitive text was an effective resource to improve reading skills. Lily, a medical researcher, said, ‘My son, Jeffery, felt more comfortable and confident when he read easy and repetitive question-and-response texts such as <italic>Brown bear, brown bear what do you see?, Polar bear, polar bear what do you hear?</italic>, and <italic>Is your mama a llama?</italic> The home-visit field notes indicated that the repeated pattern books drew most children into joyful interaction allowing children to make predictions and to share reading experiences with their parents and peers. The home-visit field notes also found that the repetitive texts helped children become better readers as they read aloud and repeated sentences fluently. Being able to read aloud and to orally repeat sentences could also raise the children’s competence in reading and learning English, particularly those who were still working in the letter–sound stage.</p>
<p>Speaking of the availability of resources, all the parents and the teachers commented that the LBs helped children become visually literate through fine picture books, which curbed the numbing effect of mindless television viewing. The researcher’s field notes also found that some of the children sometimes forgot to watch their favorite cartoons while they were reading their favorite books. The field notes found that even if young children could just browse through a book and enjoy the pictures then that indicated an interest in reading. Some parents commented that the LB provided fun and playful activities and resources for parents and children to work purposefully. The participating father indicated, ‘My children and I especially liked to play word-making games, word-puzzles, and word sorts.’ In addition, incorporating interesting children’s books along with the CDs/audiotapes provided great benefits that helped Chinese children to speak proper English rather than a blended dialect or ‘Chi-nglish’. They liked to imitate the American accent when they were listening to the CDs/audiotapes. Some commented that ‘Listening and following along with the CDs/audiotapes are great resources for parents to teach children accurate pronunciation and intonations.’</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1362168813475950">
<title>b Resources from the content of the books</title>
<p>All of the parents and teachers said that the content of each book provided a rich reading resource for them to work with their children in a variety of learning situations. The content of the book was also critical in developing Chinese children’s English skills because they were so often captivated by colorful illustrations and fun stories. Linda, an elementary music teacher and mother noted, ‘My daughter, Annie, loves reading the <italic>Dr. Seuss, Curious George</italic> and <italic>Clifford’s first Christmas</italic> books because of the fun characters, plots, and settings. She often giggled when she read the books.’ During the home visits, the majority of the parents indicated that the contents of the picture books were perfect tools for opening a child’s eyes to the beauty and power of art. Such comments were similar to the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1362168813475950">Hadaway, Vardell, and Young (2002)</xref>, which found high quality children’s books promoted reading interests and reading engagement. The parents further indicated some children were more interested in reading informational books such as how a road is built, threats to the environment of Antarctica, etc. The researcher also observed that informational books were striking and interesting to the children because photographs and illustrations showed the wonders of nature and provided accurate details about virtually every topic imaginable. Boys especially were more curious about the human body and the real world around them.</p>
<p>Some of the children’s books that contained rich cultural value were also interesting to a number of families and parents, for example, <italic>Amazing Grace, Corn is maize: The gift of the Indians, Everybody cooks rice</italic>, and <italic>The relative came</italic>. The parents and children also obtained some information about American social structures such as family values, school environments, and social activities through the given materials. Some parents discovered that there were some similarities and differences between Chinese and American children’s books. Such multicultural children’s books also provided appropriate themes for building cross-cultural understanding. Parents made comments such as, ‘Many Western stories used both impersonal and personalized figures related to cultures, languages, social activities, and life styles from different ethnic groups and backgrounds.’</p>
<p>All the parents and teachers also noticed that children’s books contain rich and descriptive language that can help children learn English grammar structure naturally and effectively. Children encountered a great variety of new words and became familiar with the syntax of complex sentences. The English teacher, Judy, noted that ‘Many children were able to use the subject–verb–object sentence pattern correctly in oral speaking and even in the written form.’ However, some comments about the LBs were negative; some of the children’s books contain a number of infrequently and rarely used words, prompting comments such as, ‘It was very difficult for children to remember these high-level words and [to use] them in daily spoken English.’</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section10-1362168813475950">
<title>Theme 2: The literacy bag provided effective literacy instruction to shape parents’ strategies used in a variety of ways and drew parents’ work together</title>
<p>The parents and the three teachers mentioned that many activities in the parents’ guidebook engaged students in literacy learning with step-by-step instructions for each strategy, helping them work with their children. Some parents, who are school teachers, reported that the guidebooks helped them expand their understanding of increasing language learning through students reading books of interest. These parents found that effective literacy instruction fosters children’s development of reading and writing skills. The majority of the children could read easy-to-read books individually and write simple sentences such as: ‘I like reading funny picture books’ and ‘I want to read more books about monkeys.’</p>
<p>The field notes about classroom observation and home visits found that parents started to realize there were a variety of teaching strategies and instructions that could be used on a daily basis. More specifically, a test-driven approach is still strongly existent in the Chinese elementary classrooms. Parents and teachers often gravitate toward spoon-fed styles of teaching that promote the pattern of rote memorization in students along with worksheets and tests, still prevalent in most family households and even in many classrooms. These parents indicated that they placed too much stress on accuracy and making no errors, particularly in phonics and spelling. Other parents made similar comments, saying that ‘We normally asked our children to memorize English vocabulary and gave them extra spelling tests.’ These comments from parents demonstrate the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1362168813475950">Warden and Lin’s (2000)</xref> research study. Within different cultural contexts, teaching English as a Foreign Language (EFL) in Asian school systems, such as Taiwan, Japan, and Hong Kong, has traditionally been characterized by memorizing vocabulary and teaching the mechanics of English grammar.</p>
<p>The parents’ guidebooks not only provided a variety of methods for teaching reading and writing, but showed the relationship between reading and writing. The majority of parents indicated the guidebooks changed their beliefs about reading practices and their attitudes toward language development. The field notes showed that the parents slowly adjusted their attention from the traditional teaching method (drill on a worksheet) to effective literacy instruction strategies such as creating rhyming families, making word activities, asking questions, drawing story maps, manipulating Dinah Zike’s foldables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1362168813475950">Zike, 2009</xref>), and developing graphic organizers. Some of the parents became quite proficient in the use of new strategies. Some parents said, ‘Asking questions and using different types of graphic organizers can foster higher-order thinking skills and understanding of the text in depth.’ A few parents, who are school teachers, also used some of the reading and writing instructions to teach their students at school. One mother, an English elementary school teacher, commented, ‘My colleagues and I have adopted some vocabulary and reading comprehension activities in our class. They are more fun than asking them to do worksheets.’</p>
<p>The parents further indicated that using fun activities effectively encouraged students to read English texts fluently and correctly. They made comments such as, ‘Some children have made some progress in phonics, word recognition, and fluency, through reading aloud and sharing reading with the parents.’ The field notes also found that these parents gained a better understanding about a variety of literary forms as they became effective teachers of reading. Parents made similar comments saying, ‘Students also need to be given an opportunity to reflect about the strategy, how it helped them, and why.’</p>
<p>The home-visit field notes also revealed that parents were working with each other. Sometimes parents were not sure how to interpret the teaching instructions and use activities in the bags. They often called parents who had used the materials previously to find out what they did. Several parents even worked collaboratively to create a book club in their homes. The children in the book club also became ‘reading buddies’ with their peers and siblings. Five of the parents, the classroom teacher, and the English teacher also reported that ‘These children were very active in discussing and sharing the books with their friends after school.’</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1362168813475950">
<title>Theme 3: The book bag project offered opportunities for parents and children to become reading partners</title>
<p>The LB project increased opportunities for the parents to interact with their children during their reading time. Some parents indicated that ‘The literacy bags gave us more opportunities to read with our kids.’ Similarly, others noted, ‘We spent more time reading and discussing fun books together in our family.’ The field notes also found that the parents very often would interrupt their busy schedules and would focus on reading stories and extension activities with the children.</p>
<p>Being given opportunities for storybook experiences with children also provided the parents with a time of closeness and a time of building shared memories. The field notes found that when the children were given more opportunities for exposure to books, they viewed reading as a pleasurable and enjoyable home activity. Parents and children reading books together provided a good opportunity for promoting speaking skills and language usage, which is consistent with other research studies in family literacy and language learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1362168813475950">Dale, Crain-Thoreson, Notari-Syverson, &amp; Cole, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1362168813475950">Piper, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1362168813475950">Snow, Burns, &amp; Griffin, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>Sharing reading activities not only increased social interaction between parents and children, but also between parents and teachers who began to work together more closely. Having access to books, and to related activities was also an important factor in increasing opportunities for promoting home and school engagement in reading. The computer teacher and the English teacher mentioned that ‘We spent time in searching for English supplemental reading materials for some of the parents.’ The field notes also showed that this was a time for the parents to learn about their children’s ideas and responses to what they read. It also enabled communication between parents and children as well as providing positive reinforcement of literacy and language. The parents discovered that language acquisition relies heavily on communicative interaction, and language affords children opportunities for expanding their social interaction. Positive social interaction with the parents and peers was a huge motivator for the children to develop their oral language skills.</p>
<p>The participating parents further discovered that children differed in cognitive abilities, and the social environment where children live may produce different ways of communicating and thinking in different children. The field notes also found that some of the children’s language learning processes were obvious as they could switch between two languages quickly when playing and/or reading; in contrast others seemed to struggle to put English words in the right position.</p>
<p>All the parents and teachers noticed that the children were more highly engaged in reading and writing when they were given opportunities to make personal reading choices and had available reading resources. The field notes found that generally, in the Chinese school contexts, students often read materials of little interest to them and they were not allowed to make personal choices at school. A wide variety of English children’s books were not available in the school. The monthly themes also offered opportunities for students to develop their reading interests. The classroom teacher said, ‘Children often tended to choose books of personal interest and books that were related to the monthly themes’ activities, such as hunting words for the Easter Bunny.’ The field notes also indicated that when the children were having more opportunities to share their stories at school, they enthusiastically shared books during show-and-tell time. They also liked to play some word games or related activities at the reading corner or at recess.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1362168813475950">
<title>Theme 4: The literacy bag influenced Chinese parents’ attitudes and fostered Chinese parents’ motivation to work with their children’s English skills</title>
<p>The field notes found that the participating parents originally did not feel confident in helping their children develop a second language accurately and appropriately. They did not see themselves as instructors and mentors of their children and they believed teachers would do a better job.</p>
<p>The field notes indicated that reading and listening to the children’s books sparked both children and parents’ imagination and gave them a sense of wonder. The project also gave substantial motivational activities to the parents so they were also motivated to learn and to be actively involved in their children’s reading and writing activities. The parents also were more curious about a given book. Some parents said, ‘We like reading children’s books as much as the children do.’</p>
<p>The field notes found that Chinese parents had high expectations for their children, and they expressed concern about their children’s academic performance. Given the strong motivation for academic achievement, these Chinese parents established a rich literacy environment for their children’s learning. Participating parents learned to encourage the child’s individual reading interests, by allowing the child to make personal choices for reading material. They simultaneously noted, ‘We have realized that understanding the children’s reading habits and interests was more important than testing scores.’ The parents also noticed that the children were very curious and interested in what American kids like to eat and how they play. For example, ‘Do American children eat hamburgers every day?’ ‘Do American children play baseball?’ ‘Do American children learn a second language at school?’ These questions were often asked by students toward the end of the project.</p>
<p>The field notes discovered that children’s curiosity about the texts and the real world also benefited the parents’ cultural-language knowledge. These Chinese parents noticed that language is culturally bound. Culture played an equally important role in the acquisition of literacy, and the children’s literacy learning is influenced by their language and cultural backgrounds. They noticed children’s literature is an excellent way to convey values of their own culture as well as others. Some parents mentioned that carefully selected literature can illustrate the contributions and values of Western cultures. They even found that some children were able to distinguish the East/West difference in cultures and language. These children have compared the <italic>Journey to the West</italic> series and the <italic>Curious George</italic> series, in which both protagonists are monkeys. <italic>Journey to the West</italic> is a Chinese classic, and it is one of the most popular materials recommended for after-school reading in many schools in Taiwan. <italic>Curious George</italic> has received more attention in the USA. Both of them have been made into cartoon TV shows. These students reported, ‘Chinese stories often are about becoming immortals or supernatural beings with magical power, whereas Western stories have more personalized characters.’ This is similar to the finding of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362168813475950">Strickland (1994)</xref>, who reported that the use of literature and related learning activities reflects a wide variety of cultures and languages, especially the children’s own.</p>
<p>The field notes found that English has become an imperative subject and skill in elementary Chinese schools. The high value of education and the value of English were strong motivators. The participating Chinese parents believed that better English skills would provide students with opportunities for social advancement and better financial success in the future. Like many Chinese parents’ beliefs, these parents tended to set a high standard of achievement for their children. Some parents, especially parents who were school teachers, set up higher requirements and standards such as reading more books and doing supplemental reading tasks. At the end of the project, several parents celebrated their children’s completion of 40 books by purchasing a cake with a colored bookmark on it and bringing the cake to the class. The whole class celebrated the fun of reading.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section13-1362168813475950" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>V Conclusions</title>
<p>This study demonstrated that parents expanded their understanding of how a child develops a new language, and they are able to apply effective literacy strategies to engage and discuss books with their children. The LBs educated parents in the use of picture books, effective literacy instructions, and strategies that encourage children to read and utilize some extension activities, including asking critical questions, writing activities, and word games. This also confirmed the previous finding about family LBs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1362168813475950">Barbour, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1362168813475950">Dever &amp; Burts, 2002</xref>). This study also indicated that students were more likely to be engaged readers when they were immersed in environments rich in print, oral language, and social interaction with adults. The findings were consistent with Baker’s report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1362168813475950">2000</xref>) that children see reading as enjoyable and important when parents believe reading is a valuable activity within the family. The LB project empowered parents to become teachers of their own children and encouraged them to provide a home environment that supported children’s literacy learning. Efforts to involve parents were very challenging, but very rewarding as well. The project also influenced parental attitudes and perceptions of their children’s English language and literacy development, fostering the independent choice of reading material by the children.</p>
<p>It also must be pointed out that scaffolding was a very important part of this project. This was done through explicit and individualized instructions. Scaffolding helped parents to focus on essential information in each book and activity and allowed children to make connections between the book and the real world. Moreover, parents gained information about their children’s reading interests, dispositions, and acquired knowledge.</p>
<p>In other findings, the LB project accomplished Epstein’s frameworks, a family/school partnership that promoted children’s English literacy. Refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1362168813475950">Figure 1</xref> for a model of parental involvement in literacy. The contents provided continuity of communication and cooperation between home and school. Connections between home and school are important as parents are creating a home literacy environment and fostering family literacy. The project also facilitated interconnectedness between and among the members of the literacy family (teachers, students, and parents). This triangular relationship enabled parents and teachers to share in the school’s activities by providing scaffolding instruction, social interaction, and communication with the children. Effectiveness of the mutual partnership between teachers (school) and family (community) has also been well established.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1362168813475950">
<title>VI Implications</title>
<p>The study has found that parental involvement was a major factor in fostering children’s English language development and skills. Little data exists describing the extent to which the LBs are employed as reinforcement for literacy learning in non-English speaking countries. Noticeably absent is the research studying Chinese-language-speaking students in the area of English language development. Various kinds of research are needed, especially research with a longitudinal qualitative design on the family influences of Chinese children’s English language development, and research that promotes motivation for literacy learning.</p>
<p>Given that relations between home and school have been characterized by separation, little is known about the contribution of parents to early literacy development among the Chinese and EFL populations. Future studies in this area are needed. The result of this study raises some questions that relate to educational systems, social structures, cultures, values, and perceptions. Parents from different cultural or ethnic groups all want and expect their children to succeed in school but have different views of their roles in the process. Future cross-cultural research studies of parental expectations for reading achievement are also needed.</p>
<p>This study also calls for more attention to the need for teachers of EFL to diversify and expand their teaching pedagogies as they instruct EFL students. Specifically, in Asian countries English language instruction has traditionally focused on drilling and rote learning of the text. Instead teachers could implement more creative activities in the classroom, trying new teaching strategies and offering various incentives that might encourage students’ desire to learn. I would like to suggest that classroom teachers can create daily opportunities or devote some time to reading for enjoyment as part of their classroom routines and have a wide variety of books available. Teachers should also initiate action to create more home–school-based opportunities that provide the essential scaffolding for parents working with their children’s literacy learning. The children are more likely to be engaged and motivated readers and writers when they grow up in environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1362168813475950">Baker, 2000</xref>) where the connections between home and school are based on mutual respect and reciprocity.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1362168813475950">
<title>Appendix 1</title>
<fig id="fig2-1362168813475950" position="float">
<caption>
<p>An example of the literacy bag.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1362168813475950-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</app>
<app id="app2-1362168813475950">
<title>Appendix 2. An example for the parent’s guidebook</title>
<p>Book entitled: <italic>The very hungry caterpillar</italic> by Eric Carle</p>
<p>To students, parents, and teachers: This book bag is intended to be used by people who enjoy reading stories and using your own imagination. You may do as few or as many activities as you have time available.</p>
<list id="list2-1362168813475950" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Listen to the CD of <italic>The very hungry caterpillar</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Go to the author, Eric Carle’s website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eric-carle.com">www.eric-carle.com</ext-link>. You may ask him questions about his books. Read another book that was written by Eric Carle. Compare the illustrations in that book with those in <italic>The very hungry caterpillar</italic>. Are they alike? Are they different? How are they different?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Using the flannel board characters, retell the story, in your own words.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Think of an environment you would like to live in or a feature of an animal you would like to have. On a sheet of paper write: ‘I wish I could live in__________’ or I wish I had a ______________like a ______________. Now, using the materials in the bag, design a picture of yourself like that.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Write a poem for nature; e.g. ‘A little star’</p>
<p>   Bright and Shining</p>
<p>   Guide me home</p>
<p>   Say Good night</p>
<p>   See you again!</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Play the animal CVCe phonic game that is adopted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1362168813475950">Bear, Invernizzi, Templeton &amp; Johnston, 2004</xref>). This strategy helps students develop CVCe phonic patterns. Direction: (1) one player shuffles and deals five cards and five wings to each player; (2) remaining cards are placed facedown for the draw pile; (3) each player puts down pairs that match by pattern. For example, cake/bake would be a pair, but pain/bake would not be a pair. Each time a pair is laid down, the players puts one wing on his/her peacock; (4) the dealer goes first, says a word from his or her hand, and asks if the second player has a card that has the same pattern; (5) if player 2 has a card that matches the pattern, player 1 gets a wing; if not, player 1 must draw a card. If the player draws a card that matches any word in his or her hand, the pair can be discarded, a wing is earned. Player 2 proceeds in the same manner; (6) the player wins when she/her uses all the cards before the other player’s turn.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Literature theater: This activity helps students develop fluency. Have students work in small groups and using the flannel board characters. One student should be a narrator and others play different characters. Have them add their own voices. For example, when the caterpillar eats an apple, whoever plays an apple may say ‘Do not eat me’ or ‘Please let me go.’</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Permanent items in this bag: (1) The book: <italic>The very hungry caterpillar</italic> and CD, (2) board games, (3) flannel board/characters.</p>
<p>Consumable items in this bag: (1) paper, (2) glue, (3) pencils.</p>
</app>
<app id="app3-1362168813475950">
<title>Appendix 3. Some selected literacy activities.</title>
<table-wrap id="table1-1362168813475950" position="float">
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1362168813475950" xlink:href="10.1177_1362168813475950-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Activity</th>
<th align="left">Objectives</th>
<th align="left">Materials included</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Sound match</td>
<td>Helps students recognize different sounds, such as beginning sounds, ending sounds, and rhyming words.</td>
<td>1. flash cards<break/>2. rhyming book: <italic>Hop on Pop</italic> (1963)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Word walls</td>
<td>Helps students develop their vocabulary and recognize words’ relationships; students could also learn about the English or ethnographic system through spelling activities.</td>
<td>1. a large pack of colored paper<break/>2. a pocket chart (home use)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Word poster</td>
<td>Develops students’ vocabulary knowledge and reading comprehension.</td>
<td>1. words from the reading books<break/>2. writing paper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dramatizing words</td>
<td>Uses dramatic methods to increase students’ knowledge of word meanings.</td>
<td>1. reading book: <italic>Three little pigs</italic>
<break/>2. word cards</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Making sentences</td>
<td>Helps young children to understand sentence structures and reorganize sentences.</td>
<td>four sets word cards including family, fruit, animals, and transport</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Poetry writing</td>
<td>Creates word pictures and plays with rhymes and other stylistic devices as they create poems.</td>
<td>1. word cards<break/>2. colored paper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Narrative writing</td>
<td>Helps students retell familiar stories, develop sequels for stories they have read, write stories called personal narratives about events in their own lives, and create original stories.</td>
<td>1. reading books: teachers read these books aloud: <italic>Stone soup</italic> (1975); <italic>The first strawberries</italic> (1993)<break/>2. paper and pencils</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cooperative reading</td>
<td>Encourages students to work with a small group and practice reading together.</td>
<td>1. <italic>The missing tarts</italic> (1989)<break/>2. <italic>Miss Mary Mack</italic> (1998)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Paired reading</td>
<td>Supports students’ reading fluency; students are paired and read orally to each other.</td>
<td>1. <italic>Brown bear, brown bear what do you see?</italic> (1996)<break/>2. <italic>Dr. Seuss’ ABC</italic> (1993)<break/>3. <italic>Is your mama a llama?</italic> (1997)<break/>4. <italic>Five little monkeys jumping on the bed</italic> (1998)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>K-W-L</td>
<td>To encourage students to see their own purposes for reading and develop comprehension skills after reading the texts</td>
<td>1. reading book: <italic>Antarctica</italic> (1990)<break/>2. DVD<break/>3. K-W-L chart</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1362168813475950"><p><italic>Note</italic>. K-W-L = What did students already know? – What do students want to know? – What did students learn after the lesson?</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack><p>I would like to give special thanks to the Dean of the College of Education, Dr Matthew Capps for reviewing the research design, to Dr Pat Andersen for writing assistance, and to Mr Russell Morris for proof-reading the article prior to submission.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research was supported by three private businesses in Taiwan. These businesses denoted US$10,000 for carrying out the project.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Beginning to read: Thinking and learning about print</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Opportunities at home and in the community that foster reading engagement</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dreher</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Engaging young readers: Promoting achievement and motivation</source> (pp. <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barbour</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Home literacy bags promote family involvement</article-title>. <source>Childhood Education</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Invernizzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templeton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Word their way: Word study for phonics, vocabulary, and spelling instruction</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boning</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>Word theater: Staring the students</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Barnell Loft</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>A family lending library: Promoting early literacy development. Young Children</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Becoming school literate parents: An ESL perspective</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Language and Literacy</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowen</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Literacy for children in an information age: Teaching reading, writing, and thinking</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crain-Thoreson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Notari-Syverson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Parent–child book reading as an intervention technique for young children with language delays</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dever</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Family literacy bags: A vehicle for parent involvement and education</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Education and Family Review</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dever</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burts</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>An evaluation of family literacy bags as a vehicle for parent involvement</article-title>. <source>Early Child Development and Care</source>, <volume>172</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>School/family/community partnerships: Caring for the children we share</article-title>. <source>Phi Delta Kappan</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>701</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gambrell</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Creating motivating contexts for literacy learning</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Afflervach</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reinking</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Developing engaged readers in school and home communities</source> (pp. <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gauvain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Sociocultural contexts of learning</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Learning in cultural context</source> (pp. <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic/ Plenum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>The discovery of grounded theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hadaway</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vardell</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>‘Just right’ books for the ESL library</article-title>. <source>Book Links</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011a</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting in middle school students’ reading motivation in Asian nation</article-title>. <conf-name>Unpublished paper presented at the American Education Research Association (AERA) Annual Meeting</conf-name>, <conf-loc>New Orleans, LA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011b</year>). <article-title>The use of effective vocabulary instruction for foster middle school students’ reading skills</article-title>. <conf-name>Unpublished paper presented at the annual meeting of the Oklahoma Reading Association</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Oklahoma City, OK</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Qualitative research: A guide to design and implementation</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Ministry of Education, Taiwan</collab> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Education in the Republic of China 2003</source>. <publisher-loc>Taipei</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Taiwan Ministry of Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roskos</surname><given-names>K.A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>1993</year>). <source>Language and literacy learning in the early years</source>. <publisher-loc>Orlando, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Opitz</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erekson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Reading diagnosis and improvement: Assessment and instruction</source>. <edition>6th ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Language and learning: The home and school years</source>. <publisher-loc>Columbus, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Merrill Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Picture book reading at home: A comparison of Head Start and middle-class preschoolers</article-title>. <source>Early Education and Development</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The influence of selecting and taking picture books home on the at-home reading behaviors of kindergarten children</article-title>. <source>Reading research and Instruction</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Preventing reading difficulties in young children</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington. DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Educating African American learners at risk: Finding a better way</article-title>. <source>Language Arts</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vygotsky</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Interaction between learning and development</article-title> (<person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Lopez-Morillas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, translation). In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>John-Steiner</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scribner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Souberman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Mind in society: The development of higher psychological processes</source> (pp. <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warden</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Existence of integrative motivation in an Asian EFL setting</article-title>. <source>Foreign Language Annals</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Dylan’s routes to literacy: The first three years with picture books</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Owocki</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Remembering critical lessons in early literacy research: A transactional perspective</article-title>. <source>Language Arts</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Cross-language transfer of insight onto the structure of compound words</article-title>. <source>Reading and Writing</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zike</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Dinah Zike’s photographic reference guide to kinesthetic graphic organizers</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dian-Might Adventures, LP</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<ref-list>
<title>Further references: Children’s books</title>
<ref id="bibr34-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Aliki</collab>. (<year>1976</year>). <source>Corn is maize: The gift of the Indians</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Crowell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dempster</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Three little pigs</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bridwell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Clifford at the circus</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bridwell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Clifford, we love you</source>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Turtleback Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bridwell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>).<source>Clifford’s first Christmas</source>. <publisher-loc>Topeka, KS</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Topeka Bindery</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bridwell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Clifford and the big parade</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cartwheel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <source>Stone soup</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Atheneum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bruchac</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The first strawberries</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Puffin Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Papa, please get the moon for me</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Little Simon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>The very hungry caterpillar</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Philomel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christelow</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Five little monkeys jumping on the bed</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarion Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cowcher</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Antarctica</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Everybody cooks rice</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carolrhoda</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Dr. Seuss</collab> (<year>1993a</year>). <source>Dr. Seuss’ ABC</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Beginner Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Dr. Seuss</collab> (<year>1993b</year>). <source>The foot book</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Beginner Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Dr. Seuss</collab> (<year>1963</year>). <source>Hop on Pop</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Beginner Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guarino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>1997</year>). <source>Is your mama a llama?</source> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>The missing tarts</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoberman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Miss Mary Mack</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>1991</year>). <source>Amazing Grace</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dial</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutchins</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>The doorbell rang</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Brown bear, brown bear what do you see?</source> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Polar bear, polar bear what do you hear?</source> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>To market, to market</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Numeroff</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>If you give a mouse a cookie</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper Trophy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Curious George</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Curious George makes pancakes</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Curious George goes camping</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Curious George’s first day at school</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>).<source>Curious George's First Day of School</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin Harcourt.</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rylant</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The relative came</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Atheneum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source xml:lang="zh">Journey to the West</source> (<trans-source>西遊記</trans-source>). (Series.) <publisher-loc>Taipei</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Modern Publishing House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vladimir</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The enormous carrot</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1362168813475950">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zoe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The surprise garden</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scholastic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>