<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CCS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spccs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Case Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1534-6501</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3802</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1534650112457811</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1534650112457811</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Improving Recall in a Person With Dementia</article-title>
<subtitle>Investigating the Effectiveness of Memory Priming and Spaced Retrieval in an Older Adult With Dementia</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Fiksdal</surname><given-names>Britta L.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534650112457811">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Houlihan</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534650112457811">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534650112457811">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1534650112457811"><label>1</label>Minnesota State University, Mankato, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1534650112457811">Britta L. Fiksdal, Minnesota State University, 23 Armstrong Hall, Mankato, MN 56001, USA Email: <email>britta.fiksdal@mnsu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>393</fpage>
<lpage>405</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Because it is often perceived that individuals with dementia cannot relearn information that has been forgotten, few nonpharmacological memory-enhancing interventions have been developed for this population. The current study involved the investigation of a novel memory-enhancement procedure called <italic>memory priming</italic> (MP) with a 95-year-old individual with dementia. MP is based on the assumption that an individual’s ability to learn is enhanced when learning trials are preceded by an activity that is enjoyable and can be done successfully. MP required the individual to engage in a 5-min preferred conversation followed by the presentation of target questions every 2 min. A memory-enhancement procedure known as spaced retrieval was then used to maintain the information learned through MP. Results provide initial evidence for the utility of MP followed by spaced retrieval for enhancing the recall and retention of meaningful information. MP may provide a simple means for helping individuals with dementia relearn forgotten information.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>dementia</kwd>
<kwd>memory enhancement</kwd>
<kwd>cognitive rehabilitation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1534650112457811">
<title>1 Theoretical and Research Basis for Treatment</title>
<p>The term <italic>dementia</italic> refers to decline in a number of cognitive abilities such as attention, receptive and expressive communication, reasoning, carrying out familiar motor tasks, and memory that negatively interferes with daily functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1534650112457811">American Psychiatric Association, 2000</xref>). Dementia can be caused by many different conditions, some of which are reversible (e.g., vitamin B12 deficiencies) and some that are not reversible (e.g., Alzheimer’s disease [AD], vascular dementia, frontotemporal dementia). In cases where dementia is progressive and irreversible, deficits in short-term memory are often the most noticeable and frustrating symptoms for patients and their caregivers. Memory deficits are manifested in day-to-day life in many ways such as problems remembering to carry out steps in a multistep task; problems remembering people’s names, faces, and relation; problems remembering dates, instructions, and appointments; and difficulties remembering how to complete tasks of daily living such as cooking, turning off appliances, taking medications, and getting lost in familiar places. These impairments can lead to a host of negative consequences such as loss of independent functioning, embarrassment, loss of self-esteem, and social withdrawal and isolation.</p>
<p>Because the older adult population (i.e., those above the age of 65) is growing at such a rapid rate, it is expected that the number of older adults diagnosed with dementia will also increase dramatically. For example, recent statistics reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1534650112457811">Alzheimer’s Disease International (2009)</xref> suggest that the worldwide prevalence of dementia in 2010 was 35.6 million and may reach as high as 115.4 million by 2050. Furthermore, AD alone affects approximately 5.4 million Americans and is projected to affect 13 million people by 2050 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1534650112457811">Alzheimer’s Association, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1534650112457811">Hebert, Scherr, Bienias, Bennett, &amp; Evans, 2003</xref>). These numbers clearly suggest that dementia represents a significant public health concern.</p>
<p>Although most diseases that cause progressive dementia cannot currently be cured (e.g., AD, frontotemporal dementia, vascular dementia), nonpharmacological interventions that focus on improving memory have produced some encouraging results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1534650112457811">Buchanan, Christenson, Houlihan, &amp; Ostrom, 2011</xref>). One such intervention is called spaced retrieval. Spaced retrieval is a technique used to enhance memory for specific pieces of information for individuals with memory impairment. The procedure involves asking participants to remember information for increasingly longer time intervals. For example, if the participant is told the name of an object is an “orange,” he or she is then asked to name that object again after 10 s (or some other chosen time interval) to test for retention. If the participant answers correctly, the interval is doubled such that the question will be asked again after 20 s. If the participant answers incorrectly, however, the interval is cut in half (i.e., to 5 s). Spaced retrieval has been compared with shaping in that the desired goal is long-term retention of the target information and the longer intervals are the successive approximations to that goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1534650112457811">Camp, Foss, O’Hanlon, &amp; Stevens, 1996</xref>). Between questions, the participant and researcher engage in some activity the participant enjoys such as conversation or a game.</p>
<p>Although it is not clear precisely how spaced retrieval works, there are many advantages to the procedure such as sessions can be conducted in the context of a casual social interaction, the nature of the procedure increases the likelihood for high rates of success, the interval length between questions is determined according to the participant’s performance, training can take place in familiar settings, it increases independence among individuals with cognitive impairment, and it has been shown to be effective in improving a variety of target behaviors in persons with different forms of dementia (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1534650112457811">Camp, Bird, &amp; Cherry, 2000</xref>, for review of the spaced retrieval literature).</p>
<p>Although a growing body of research suggests that memory-enhancement procedures can be effective in helping individuals with dementia retain previously learned information, this research is still in its infancy. Therefore, new procedures should be investigated with the hopes of developing additional effective and user-friendly techniques. The current study involved the investigation of a novel memory-enhancement procedure for persons with dementia called <italic>memory priming</italic>. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1534650112457811">Tulving and Schacter (1990)</xref>, priming works at a presemantic level and influences memory systems from early in life into old age to varying degrees. The term <italic>priming</italic> means to use a cue or stimulus to improve response potential (i.e., recall). Memory priming as described here is analogous to a “warm-up” such as stretching before running a mile or heating up a frying pan before cooking. During their careers working with persons with dementia, the second and third authors have observed anecdotally that some individuals with more advanced dementia tend to have a limited number of topics (e.g., previous jobs, their families, or their children or pets) that they can communicate about effectively and in detail. The rationale behind memory priming is that if participants talk about these preferred topics for a period of time (i.e., they “warm up”), they will more effectively learn new material or relearn material that has been lost. Therefore, memory priming attempts to take advantage of an individual’s existing strengths and abilities (i.e., the ability to converse and recall autobiographical information) to improve a cognitive deficit (i.e., the ability to learn and retain new information). It should be noted that the goal of memory priming is not to reverse the disease; it is simply to enhance recall for specific pieces of information that have been forgotten. Being able to recall personal information such as children’s names, birthdays, and so on may have important implications for patients such as improved self-esteem, increased socialization and communication with family members and friends, and decreased embarrassment over not remembering personal information. Overall, the purpose of the current study was to determine whether memory priming could benefit an older adult male with dementia who was having difficulty remembering information about his family.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1534650112457811" sec-type="intro">
<title>2 Case Introduction</title>
<p>The current study describes the assessment and treatment of a 95-year-old Caucasian man previously diagnosed with dementia (cause unknown) by his family physician. His dementia was characterized by memory impairment that resulted in difficulties in daily living such as forgetting his daily schedule and the names of family members. These problems in daily living became severe and frequent enough to warrant placement in an assisted living facility. The participant had been living in this facility for approximately 24 months when the study began. When the study began, the participant was taking vitamin B12 as well as a cholinesterase inhibitor to manage his dementia. Throughout the study, the dosages of both medications were held constant.</p>
<p>The participant was recruited for this study due to presence of cognitive impairment that resulted in difficulties recalling the names of objects and people. The participant reported having some difficulties with memory and expressed an interest in possibly improving his ability to remember information. In addition, the participant’s son reported that his father often had difficulties at family events due to memory problems. For example, he would forget family member names or forget information such as what a particular family member did for a living. The participant was going to be attending a family reunion, and his son was interested in determining whether the participant could improve his ability to recall important information regarding his family (e.g., names of grandchildren).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1534650112457811">
<title>3 Presenting Complaints</title>
<p>The participant presented with memory impairment associated with dementia. He displayed difficulty remembering his children’s and grandchildren’s names. He also had difficulties remembering what day it was, what he did earlier in the day, and any future plans for the day. He was still able to independently complete some activities of daily living such as making his own breakfast, using the bathroom, making his bed, and walking. He required assistance with other activities such as driving, remembering scheduled activities or events, and using public transportation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1534650112457811">
<title>4 History</title>
<p>During his employed years, the participant was an office manager (accountant) and eventually rose to the rank of president of a school supply company in a midwestern city. He had a history of being strong willed and hardworking. For example, he built a log cabin at age 64. He was father to three successful children. Widowed in 1991, he remarried not long after. However, it was during this time (1992-1993) that the early signs of memory loss became apparent to his children. He was diagnosed with dementia at about age 87 after a baseline test by a neurologist. It was during this time period that he also had a serious car accident in which he suffered injuries from which he would eventually recover. His doctor told him 14 times that he could no longer drive before he finally stopped. The dementia became more serious when he couldn’t drive and second wife divorced him, likely due to complications of the disease. During much of his final 9 years, the participant lived in assisted living facilities, including the one where this investigation took place.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1534650112457811">
<title>5 Assessment</title>
<p>To estimate the severity of cognitive impairment, the Modified Mini Mental Status Exam (3MS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1534650112457811">Teng &amp; Chui, 1987</xref>) was administered. Scores on the 3MS range from 0 to 100, with a cut-off score of 77 or higher generally indicating intact cognitive functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1534650112457811">Tombaugh, McDowell, Kristjansson, &amp; Hubley, 1996</xref>). This cut-off score is not adjusted for age or education; however, normative data for different age groups and levels of education are available and were used to interpret the scores of the participant. The 3MS targets object naming, concentration, immediate and delayed recall, orientation, registration, language, executive functioning, and ability to follow commands. Because the 3MS is an expanded version of the commonly used Mini Mental Status Examination (MMSE), an MMSE score can also be derived from the 3MS. The participant scored 69 on the 3MS and 15 on the MMSE. The participant’s 3MS score of 69 placed him below the 2nd percentile for his age and education level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1534650112457811">Tombaugh et al., 1996</xref>). The participant’s MMSE score of 15 indicated cognitive impairment of moderate severity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1534650112457811">Tombaugh et al., 1996</xref>). Therefore, it is clear that although the participant was functioning reasonably well in his daily life, he was experiencing significant cognitive impairment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1534650112457811">
<title>6 Case Conceptualization</title>
<p>According to the participant’s medical record and reports from his son, the participant was clearly suffering from progressive dementia, although the specific cause was unknown. Although the participant’s dementia could not be reversed, it was believed that he could perhaps benefit from a structured cognitive rehabilitation program designed to teach him to remember important personal information. This assumption was based on research described above that demonstrates improvements in recall can be achieved with persons with dementia.</p>
<p>The participant was considered a good candidate for the memory-enhancement intervention used in this study based on several criteria. First, he was able to engage in some activities independently. Second, he was very talkative, had the ability to talk in great detail about a few life events, was open to new experiences, and was not prone to negative affect such as frustration or anxiety. These characteristics were important because memory priming required regular conversation about life events that could be recalled in some detail. Third, his memory impairment was in the moderate range of severity based on cognitive screening measures, although he was able to remember some information about his personal life. Previous research with other memory-enhancement interventions has demonstrated that success can be achieved even with those with cognitive impairment in the moderate range of severity (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1534650112457811">Abrahams &amp; Camp, 1993</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1534650112457811">
<title>7 Course of Treatment and Assessment of Progress</title>
<sec id="section8-1534650112457811">
<title>Pre-Baseline</title>
<p>Before meeting with the resident, an interview with a family member who was close to the participant (i.e., his son) was conducted to obtain information, including (a) possible target questions that could be asked during the intervention phase and (b) stories/topics the participant liked to frequently talk about. Examples of questions that were provided included, “What is your first wife’s name?” and “What is your daughter’s name?” Examples of stories/topics that were provided included riding the rails as a young man, building a cabin, his father’s jewelry store, activities he enjoyed as a child (swimming, ice skating, skiing), and traveling.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1534650112457811">
<title>Baseline</title>
<p>The purpose of the baseline phase was to identify two categories of questions: low probability/target questions and moderate probability/control questions. Criteria for the selection of low probability/target questions were that the participant answered them correctly 0% of the time. These questions were used as the target questions, and the goal of the intervention was to increase correct responding to these questions. Criteria for the selection of moderate probability questions were that the participant answered them correctly an average of 30% to 75% of the time. Moderate probability questions served as controls and were identified to assess for possible generalizability of the memory priming procedure to nontargeted questions. Therefore, it was not expected that the frequency of correct responding to moderate probability would improve during the intervention. A pool of 45 potential low and moderate probability questions was identified by family during pre-baseline.</p>
<p>Baseline sessions (and all subsequent sessions) were conducted in the participant’s room located in an assisted living facility. During baseline data collection sessions, two researchers conversed with the participant and then periodically interrupted the conversation to ask questions. Each session lasted approximately 15 min and involved asking a total of 15 to 21 questions. The primary researcher was in charge of asking questions and recording the order in which the questions were asked. The secondary researcher was in charge of recording whether the participant answered each question correctly. During the baseline phase, the participant was not given feedback as to whether he answered questions correctly or not. A total of four questions were identified that met “low probability/target” criteria and a total of five questions met “moderate probability” criteria. The first low probability/target question, however, was dropped due to the complications of the answer, which will be described later.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1534650112457811">
<title>Memory Priming Phase</title>
<p>After the moderate and low probability questions were identified during the baseline phase, the memory priming intervention was implemented. Only one low probability/target question was taught at a time, and all five moderate probability questions were used throughout the entire intervention. Each session started by asking each moderate probability question once and the low probability question 3 times while conversing with the participant about daily activities. No feedback was given to the participant regarding whether he answered correctly, and this “probe” conversation lasted about 3 min. The purpose of this probe conversation was to assess for retention of the learned material across sessions.</p>
<p>Once the probe conversations were completed, the memory priming intervention began. These sessions started by “priming” the participant before asking low and moderate probability questions. Priming involved asking the participant about one of the preferred topics identified during pre-baseline and engaging in a 5-min conversation related to this topic. After this 5-min conversation, the target question was asked (e.g., “What does your granddaughter’s husband (name) do for a job?”). If the participant answered the question correctly, praise was provided (e.g., “Yes that’s correct, nice job”); however, if the participant answered incorrectly or did not respond, the correct answer was given to him. After feedback was provided, the preferred conversation was continued. Throughout the conversation, the low probability question was asked 5 times (every 2 min) and all five moderate probability questions were asked once. The timing devices used by the researchers included an I-pod Touch that was reset to count to 2 min after the resident finished answering the question and a stop watch that allowed the researchers to record at what time during the session each question was asked. Sessions ended after all the questions had been asked and lasted between 25 and 35 min. Memory priming sessions were conducted 3 to 5 days per week over the course of 3 to 5 weeks.</p>
<p>Once the participant answered the low probability/target question correctly 100% of the time during the probe conversation, the question was considered “mastered.” Once the mastery criterion was met, spaced retrieval training began immediately for that question and memory priming sessions for the second low probability/target question were started.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1534650112457811">
<title>Spaced Retrieval Phase</title>
<p>Spaced retrieval was implemented to maintain and strengthen gains made during memory priming sessions. For each of the three low probability/target questions, spaced retrieval was started after the question was mastered during memory priming. During these sessions, only the targeted low probability question was asked. Spaced retrieval sessions started by asking the individual the targeted low probability question and providing feedback as described above regarding whether he answered correctly. After the participant answered the question and feedback was given, a conversation with the participant ensued. After 30 s, the researcher asked the question again. If the participant answered correctly, praise was provided and the researcher doubled the interval before asking the question again. If the participant answered incorrectly, the researcher cut the interval in half before asking the question again. This procedure continued for 20 to 35 min.</p>
<p>For each target question, spaced retrieval sessions continued until the participant was able to answer the question correctly at the beginning of three consecutive sessions. In other words, once the participant was able to demonstrate retention of information across sessions for three consecutive sessions, the answer was considered mastered (i.e., successful learning had occurred). This procedure continued until all three low/target questions had been mastered using memory priming and were being successfully maintained through the use of spaced retrieval. Once a question had been mastered through memory priming and spaced retrieval, it was included in the list of questions to be probed during the memory priming sessions done with other questions to monitor maintenance of treatment gains.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1534650112457811">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The answers to four low probability questions were targeted for improvement (i.e., retention) in the memory priming intervention. The target questions were as follows: Target 1, “What does your granddaughter’s husband (name) do for a job?” Target 2, “What is (name of youngest son) oldest daughter’s name?” Target 3, “What is (name of oldest son) son’s name?” and Target 4, “What is (name of youngest son) youngest daughter’s name?” The moderate questions chosen for comparison were, “What was your first wife’s name?” “What is your pastor’s name?” “What is your youngest son’s name?” “What is your oldest son’s name?” and “What is (name of brother’s) wife’s name?” It should be noted that Target 1 was discontinued after 6 days of intervention due to the complexity of the answer. Therefore, the intervention was completed with only three low probability questions (Targets 2-4).</p>
<p>It appears as if the memory priming intervention was effective in teaching the three target questions selected. For example, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1534650112457811">Figure 1</xref> shows the results for Target Question 2. As can be seen, after four sessions of memory priming, the participant answered 100% of the probes (i.e., target questions asked at the beginning of the memory priming with no feedback) correctly. This indicates that a piece of information that could not be retained for even a few minutes during baseline was now being retained over the period of hours/days following four memory priming sessions. A total of three spaced retrieval sessions were needed to achieve mastery for Question 2. During all three spaced retrieval sessions, correct responding occurred between 66% and 100% of the time. Following spaced retrieval training, baseline was then reinstated for Target 2. During this return to baseline, the highest percent correct was 50%. After the fourth session, however, the participant was no longer able to answer the question correctly, indicating that learning achieved during the previous phases had been lost. In addition, retention was not demonstrated for this target question at the 1-, 2-, and 3-week follow-ups.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1534650112457811" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Percentage of correct responding for Target 2</p>
<p>Note: MP = memory priming; SR = spaced retrieval.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534650112457811-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1534650112457811">Figure 2</xref> shows the results for Target Question 3. As can be seen, after only two sessions of memory priming, the participant answered 100% of the probes correctly. A total of three spaced retrieval sessions were needed to achieve mastery for Question 3. During all three spaced retrieval sessions, correct responding occurred between 66% and 100% of the time. Following spaced retrieval training, baseline was reinstated for Target 3. During this return to baseline, the participant answered the question correctly 100% of the time except for the first and third sessions in which the participant answered them correctly 0% and 50% (respectively) of the time, indicating learning achieved during the previous phases had generally been retained. In addition, retention was demonstrated for this target question at the 1-, 2-, and 3-week follow-ups. The participant responded correctly 100% of the time for all three follow-up sessions, demonstrating retention for the material learned for 7 weeks.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1534650112457811" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Percentage of correct responding for Target 3</p>
<p>Note: MP = memory priming; SR = spaced retrieval.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534650112457811-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1534650112457811">Figure 3</xref> shows the results for Target Question 4. As can be seen, after six sessions of memory priming, the participant answered 100% of the probes correctly. A total of three spaced retrieval sessions were needed to achieve mastery for Question 4. During all three spaced retrieval sessions, correct responding occurred between 50% and 100% of the time. Following spaced retrieval training, partial retention was demonstrated for this target question at the 1-, 2-, and 3-week follow-ups. The participant responded to the target question correctly 50% of the time at the 1- and 3-week follow-ups and responded incorrectly at the 2-week follow-up.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1534650112457811" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Percentage of correct responding for Target 4</p>
<p>Note: MP = memory priming; SR = spaced retrieval.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534650112457811-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>As can be seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1534650112457811">Figure 4</xref>, the participant answered the moderate probability questions correctly an average of 53% of the time. The percent correct for these moderate questions remained stable throughout the study between 20% and 80%. During the 1- and 3-week follow-ups, the participant answered 40% of the moderate questions correctly and during the 2-week follow-up, the participant answered 60% of the moderate questions correctly. These data indicate that the effect of the memory training procedures used in this study did not generalize to the moderate probability questions.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1534650112457811" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>Percentage of correct responding for moderate questions</p>
<p>Note: MP = memory priming.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534650112457811-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Anecdotal observation suggested that the participant was often pleased when he answered items correctly and appeared to enjoy the positive feedback and social interaction associated with the intervention. It is also worth noting that although the results suggest improvements in recall over time, the participant never indicated that he was aware of this improvement. In essence, improvement was observed, but it was unclear whether the participant recalled or noticed this improvement. The ability of persons with dementia to recall new information without awareness of where or when the information was learned has been noted by other authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1534650112457811">Camp et al., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Results were also shared with the participant’s son who provided consent for participation. The son indicated that he was pleasantly surprised by the outcomes and eagerly shared the results of the study with other family members. Family and the participant expressed appreciation for the work that had been done, and on several occasions, the son remarked how he and his family were proud that their father was able to contribute to research in this area.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1534650112457811">
<title>8 Complicating Factors</title>
<p>In general, the procedures described above were carried out efficiently and the findings were quite encouraging with this particular individual. One complication that did occur, however, involved the wording of Target Question 1. It appears as though complex multiple-word answers might not be ideal for this type of memory rehabilitation procedure. Target 1 involved a two- or even three-part answer and was clearly too much for the participant to remember. As a result, Target 1 was dropped from the study. The researchers wanted one-part answers, meaning answers that were one word as well as clear and concise. The answer to Target 1, “What does your granddaughter’s husband (name) do for a job?” was that he “works for the FBI protecting America.” The answer to this question could be interpreted and stated in multiple ways. The participant responded sporadically with “works for the government,” which was considered correct; however, as the sessions went on, the participant expanded his answer to, “works for the government making sure people get what they paid for.” The researchers are unsure as to where this second half of the response came from, but when the participant was corrected and told he works to protect America from enemies and terrorists, he said that is too big of a job for one individual and appeared upset. The researchers tried to get the participant to simply answer, “works for the FBI” or “works for the government,” but the participant insisted on elaborating and adding that “he made sure people get what they paid for.” After 6 days of memory priming intervention, the question was dropped and the researchers moved onto the second target question that had a simple one-part answer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1534650112457811">
<title>9 Access and Barriers to Care</title>
<p>None.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1534650112457811">
<title>10 Follow-Up</title>
<p>As described in the “Results” section, treatment gains were generally maintained throughout the spaced retrieval sessions. Retention of learned material at the 1-, 2-, and 3-week follow-ups was variable across target items. For the second target question, the participant could no longer remember the answer during the follow-up sessions. One possible explanation for this is that follow-up was completed for all items only after spaced retrieval training was completed with all three target questions. Because the second target question was the first item trained, the time between the last spaced retrieval session and the first follow-up session was quite long (i.e., several weeks) and no additional maintenance procedures were implemented during this interval. This interval between the end of training and the start of follow-up may have been too long to expect retention to occur without the implementation of maintenance procedures. An additional explanation for why maintenance of treatment gains did not occur for the second target question is that during the return to baseline, the third and fourth target questions were being taught, which could have interfered with his ability to remember the answer to the second target.</p>
<p>The third target question was successfully taught and retained at the 1-, 2-, and 3-eek follow-ups. For the fourth target question, the participant displayed partial retention. When the participant answered incorrectly, he tended to recall one of the three girls name instead of responding with, “I don’t know,” as he did during baseline. Overall, follow-up data tentatively suggest that retention of newly learned material is possible over the period of 3 weeks, even in someone with progressive dementia. It is unclear from this study, however, just how long retention of material can be maintained without further intervention. It is more likely the case, however, that some degree of continued intervention will be needed to ensure maintenance of gains over time. Future research will be necessary to determine the optimal schedule of postintervention booster sessions for maintaining retention of learned material.</p>
<p>About 2 months following completion of the formal investigation described here, the participant suffered a serious stroke and was moved to a skilled nursing facility. Unfortunately, he was unable to attend his family reunion. Approximately 4 months later, the participant passed away. He lived to be 96.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1534650112457811">
<title>11 Treatment Implications of the Case</title>
<p>The current intervention was effective in teaching three of the four target questions selected. Correct responding increased during memory priming for Targets 2, 3, and 4 compared with baseline, and these improvements were maintained throughout spaced retrieval. During baseline, all targets were correct 0% of the time. This investigation indicates that the procedure the researchers are calling “memory priming” may indeed aid in relearning and retaining specific pieces of personal information in older adults with cognitive impairment. The results of this study are consistent with previous studies indicating that spaced retrieval can be used to successfully teach cognitively impaired individuals specific pieces of information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1534650112457811">Camp et al., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Although results of this study are very preliminary, these findings suggest that memory priming may be useful for helping individuals recall previously acquired knowledge. It remains to be seen, however, whether this procedure can be used to teach individuals with dementia new information. The findings of the current study along with findings by other researchers are encouraging given that it is often assumed (incorrectly) that individuals with dementia cannot learn/relearn information. If future research substantiates the findings from this study, memory priming could prove to be a simple, effective, and structured nonpharmacological method for caregivers to help older adults with memory impairments relearn important pieces of information (e.g., names of family members). Improvements in quality of life, independence, and self-esteem may result from successful learning of this kind of information.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1534650112457811">
<title>12 Recommendations to Clinicians and Students</title>
<p>Because this is the first study to implement this memory priming procedure, recommendations based on this case are only made quite tentatively. First, this intervention appears to be useful for persons with memory impairment associated with dementia. Therefore, one recommendation is that a diagnosis of dementia be established before implementing this procedure. A diagnosis of dementia should be made only after the completion of a thorough evaluation that includes a neurological examination, clinical interviewing (of the patient and a collateral informant), laboratory tests (e.g., blood tests), brain imaging, and neuropsychological testing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1534650112457811">Lipton &amp; Rubin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1534650112457811">Petersen, 2006</xref>). Furthermore, knowing the specific cause of dementia may prove important because different causes of dementia progress differently over time and affect memory systems in different ways. For example, dementia of the Alzheimer’s type (DAT) tends to cause significant impairments in episodic memory (particularly memory for new or recent events) with more variable effects on semantic memory (i.e., knowledge of previously acquired facts). In addition, persons with DAT have more difficulty recalling recent events versus recalling more temporally remote events. Of course, other causes of dementia may be associated with different patterns of memory loss in terms of their effect on episodic and semantic memory systems.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, one significant limitation of this study is that the etiology of the participant’s dementia was unknown. Reports by his family and facility staff indicate an Alzheimer’s-type dementia given that he had difficulty learning new information and showed problems with executive functioning (e.g., difficulties with everyday problem solving) but could recall events from his childhood, adolescence, and early adulthood quite well. However, this is only speculative, and it is impossible to confirm what the specific cause of his dementia was. Future research should take into account the cause of dementia and its associated pattern of memory loss in determining appropriate treatment targets.</p>
<p>Another recommendation is that one should not rule out the possibility of learning in persons with a diagnosis of dementia. This case demonstrated that memory priming may be useful for helping individuals recall previously acquired knowledge, whereas other research using similar techniques (e.g., spaced retrieval) indicates that new learning can also occur. Overall, the existing literature suggests that structured procedures that minimize errors, involve relatively frequent repetition of material, provide feedback, and are done in the context of a preferred activity can result in the reacquisition of previous knowledge or bring about new learning. Furthermore, retention of this information over relatively long periods of time (days, weeks) can be achieved.</p>
<p>Future implementation of this procedure should consider additional factors. For example, the participant described here was very sociable and verbose. He enjoyed the intervention sessions and never became upset or agitated when he was interrupted, so questions could be asked. These characteristics likely made him a good fit for this kind of intervention. The implication is that the role of client personality factors should be taken into account when considering using this intervention. In addition, as mentioned above, questions should be carefully worded so as to be clear and only require brief answers.</p>
<p>Although not done in the current investigation, future applications of this intervention should consider periodically implementing training and feedback for mastered material to increase the chances that individuals will retain learned information.</p>
<p>Because this is the first study to implement this memory priming procedure, future research will be needed to determine the optimal manner by which to implement the procedure. For example, future research will need to answer the following questions before more detailed recommendations can be made: (a) Does the priming activity (in this case conversation) promote learning above and beyond simple repetition and feedback on a regular schedule? This question would be essential to answer to differentiate memory priming from spaced retrieval, which is by itself a well-established intervention for improving memory in persons with dementia. (b) How long does the priming activity need to be to produce optimal results. Five minutes was arbitrarily chosen for this case because the researchers wanted the entire procedure to be relatively short so as to be practical. It is possible, however, that activities need to be conducted for longer periods of time to achieve better results. (c) Can priming be done using other forms of stimulation other than conversation? Older adults typically have physical or cognitive activities they enjoy doing (e.g., walking, puzzles, reading) that might serve the same function as the preferred topic of conversation. (d) Would intervention effects be enhanced if pictures were used in addition to verbally administered questions? (e) How many targets can be successfully taught at one time? This study trained targets one at a time, but it may be possible to teach multiple targets at once.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Britta L. Fiksdal</bold> is a school psychology doctoral student at Minnesota State University in Mankato. Her research interests are applied behavioral interventions to reduce problem behaviors in schoolchildren and to improve the quality of life of individuals with dementia.</p>
<p><bold>Daniel Houlihan</bold> is a professor of psychology and director of doctoral training in school psychology at Minnesota State University in Mankato. His research interests are internationally applied behavioral interventions with schoolchildren and behaviorally based interventions with older adults.</p>
<p><bold>Jeffrey A. Buchanan</bold> is an associate professor of clinical psychology at Minnesota State University in Mankato. His primary clinical and research interests involve improving the quality of life of individuals with dementia and their caregivers.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abrahams</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Maintenance and generalization of object naming training in anomia associated with degenerative dementia</article-title>. <source>Clinical Gerontologist</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Alzheimer’s Association</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>2011 Alzheimer’s disease facts and figures</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alz.org/downloads/Facts_Figures_2011.pdf">http://www.alz.org/downloads/Facts_Figures_2011.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Alzheimer’s Disease International</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>World Alzheimer’s report 2009: Executive summary</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alz.co.uk/research/statistics">http://www.alz.co.uk/research/statistics</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>. (<year>2000</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>, text rev.). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houlihan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ostrom</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The role of behavior analysis in the rehabilitation of persons with dementia</article-title>. <source>Behavior Therapy</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Retrieval strategies as a rehabilitation aid for cognitive loss in pathological aging</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stigsdotter</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Cognitive rehabilitation in old age</source> (pp. <fpage>224</fpage>-<lpage>248</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Hanlon</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Memory interventions for persons with dementia</article-title>. <source>Applied Cognitive Psychology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scherr</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bienias</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Alzheimer disease in the US population: Prevalence estimates using the 2000 census</article-title>. <source>Archives of Neurology</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1119</fpage>-<lpage>1122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Medical evaluation and diagnosis</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Textbook of Alzheimer’s disease and other dementias</source> (pp. <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Mayo clinic guide to Alzheimer’s disease</source>. <publisher-loc>Rochester, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mayo Clinic Health Information</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chui</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The modified Mini-Mental State (3M S) examination</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>314</fpage>-<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tombaugh</surname><given-names>T. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kristjansson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hubley</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Mini-mental state examination (MMSE) and the modified MMSE (3MS): A psychometric comparison and normative data</article-title>. <source>Psychological Assessment</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>48</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1534650112457811">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tulving</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Priming and human memory systems</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>247</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sceicne.2296719</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>