<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JLA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjla</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Laboratory Automation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2211-0682</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1540-2452</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2211068213478031</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2211068213478031</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Regular Columns</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>World News</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Automated Systems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>123</fpage>
<lpage>125</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Society for Laboratory Automation and Screening</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Laboratory Automation and Screening</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-2211068213478031">
<title>Advion</title>
<sec id="section2-2211068213478031">
<title>CMS for Agilent HPLC and (U)HPLC Liquid Chromatography Systems</title>
<p>The Advion expression compact mass spectrometer (CMS) is now fully integrated with Agilent Technologies’ full range of HPLC and (U)HPLC liquid chromatography systems. Full integration (control, data acquisition, and analysis) of the single quadropole CMS allows users a streamlined approach for LC/MS methods. Users now have full control of more than 70 Agilent (U)HPLC modules, using a single software platform and single PC through Advion’s Mass Express software.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.advion.com">www.advion.com</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-2211068213478031">
<title>Alfa Wassermann Separation Technologies</title>
<sec id="section4-2211068213478031">
<title>EMPAT Automatic Aseptic Sampling System for Biologics</title>
<p>EMPAT is an automated sampling system that collects samples directly from bioreactors aseptically and automatically, saving time, removing the risk of potential error, and improving the precision of quality control measures. The system is easy to install and program, operates continuously around the clock, and seamlessly integrates with existing data systems, giving users real-time process characterization. The EMPAT system can be set up in 10 min to provide 24-h, walk-away operation. Through a menu of preauthorized and programmable sampling procedures, the system automatically collects samples for transfer to gamma-irradiated, single-use bag sets. In between sample extractions, a patented method is used to avoid cross-contamination between samples and to ensure sterility. Operating and batch data are captured, stored, and archived in an SQL database, with capabilities for report generation and barcode label printout for sample identification. A secure touchscreen user interface with multilevel password authorization and paperless operation adheres to 21CFR Part 11 guidelines.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.awst.com/empat.html">www.awst.com/empat.html</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-2211068213478031">
<title>Beckman Coulter</title>
<sec id="section6-2211068213478031">
<title>Optima MAX-TL Tabletop Ultracentrifuge</title>
<p>Joining Beckman’s Optima line of floor and tabletop ultracentrifuges, this entry-level instrument offers context-sensitive onscreen help and is available in multiple native languages. Users can set multiple programs of up to five steps each using an easily navigated, full-color LCD touch screen accessible in nine languages: English, Spanish, German, Japanese, French, Italian, Russian, Portuguese, and Chinese (simplified). Fully compatible with Beckman Coulter TL labware and fixed-angle, swinging bucket, and unique near-vertical tube rotors, the Optima MAX-TL can be used in applications including separation of subcellular particles, viruses and viral particles, rate-zonal separation of proteins in sucrose gradient, separation of lipoproteins, pelleting of RNA through a CsCl gradient, isopycnic separation of plasmid DNA, and others.</p>
<p>With a maximum speed of 120 14;000 rpm and maximum rcf of 657 14;000 × <italic>g</italic>, the instruments control speed within ±50 rpm of set point. Temperatures can be set from 0 °C to 40 °C in 1 °C increments and controlled within ±2 °C of set point (after equilibrium). The units operate in ambient temperatures from 15 °C to 35 °C. Thermoelectric refrigeration eliminates chlorofluorocarbons and ozone-depletion chemicals.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.beckmancoulter.com">www.beckmancoulter.com</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-2211068213478031">
<title>Cellectricon</title>
<sec id="section8-2211068213478031">
<title>Cellaxess ACE Adherent Cell Electroporation System</title>
<p>Developed for in situ transfection of hard-to-transfect adherent cell types, this new platform enables transfection and delivery of nongenetic material in any adherent cell type at any developmental stage. The platform enables in situ primary and induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC)–derived cell types directly in 96- and 384-well microplates and cell culture dishes at any cellular developmental stage with excellent viability and completely retained cellular morphology. Cellaxess ACE is available as a complete system but can also be integrated with third-party pulse generators.</p>
<p>Applications for the Cellaxess ACE include transfection of various types of neuronal cells such as hippocampal and cortical neurons, dorsal root, and superior cervical ganglia from rat as well as mouse and human iPSC-derived dopaminergic neurons, to mention a few. Protocols are available for a wide range of neuronal cells as well as other adherent cell types.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cellectricon.com">www.cellectricon.com</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-2211068213478031">
<title>Computype</title>
<sec id="section10-2211068213478031">
<title>Flex TVF</title>
<p>This system automatically feeds tubes or vials downstream to the Tube Pro for labeling. This bulk feeder is fast, easy, and virtually noiseless. The Flex TVF separates individual tubes or vials from bulk storage and ensures each item that exits the system is feeding in the correct orientation before it hits the printer.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.computype.com">www.computype.com</ext-link></p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section11-2211068213478031">
<title>FEI Company</title>
<sec id="section12-2211068213478031">
<title>Helios NanoLab 450HP and 1200HP DualBeam Systems</title>
<p>The Helios NanoLab 450HP and 1200HP DualBeam systems can prepare 15-nm-thick samples with less than a 2 nm damage layer in 90 min, two times faster than competitive alternatives. iFast automation software maximizes ease of use while ensuring consistency among multiple operators and systems. QuickFlip grid holders facilitate inverted sample preparation to improve sample quality while maintaining high throughput. Cell Navigation software allows automated navigation within nonunique memory arrays that can locate a single designated bit cell in a 50 nm lateral field. Together, these features enable a robust process to prepare high-quality, ultra-thin lamella across multiple tools in a consistent manner, independent of operator skill level. The 450HP model can accommodate samples up to 100 mm, whereas the 1200HP system can handle full 300 mm wafers.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fei.com/TemPrep">www.fei.com/TemPrep</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-2211068213478031">
<title>GE Healthcare Life Sciences</title>
<sec id="section14-2211068213478031">
<title>IN Cell Analyzer 2200</title>
<p>GE Healthcare’s IN Cell Analyzer 2200 is a high-speed, flexible, modular imaging system suitable for both investigative microscopy and automated high-content screening of organelles, cells, tissues, and whole organisms. The IN Cell Analyzer 2200 can be configured to the specific needs of users, with a wide range of optional modules and accessories available.</p>
<p>The IN Cell Analyzer 2200 can image a two-colored 96-well plate assay in less than 2.5 min and a one-color 1536 plate in less than 20 min. This speed is possible because of a bright, seven-wavelength solid-state light source and scientific-grade CMOS camera coupled with an optimized stage and efficient, easy-to-use control software. Design features such as preview scan also save time in assay set up by enabling users to locate wells, samples, or regions of interest quickly and efficiently.</p>
<p>The flexibility of the IN Cell Analyzer 2200 enables the system to be used in multiple modes including whole-well imaging, online cell counting, and manual microscope. This allows users to optimize the assay set up efficiently and develop and conduct both simple and complex high-throughput, high-content assays. The system is designed to maximize the quantitative accuracy of the captured images for any sample type, including image restoration for dim samples.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gelifesciences.com/INCell">www.gelifesciences.com/INCell</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-2211068213478031">
<title>Hamilton Robotics and GE Healthcare Life Sciences</title>
<sec id="section16-2211068213478031">
<title>easyPunch STARlet Workstation</title>
<p>Manufactured by Hamilton Robotics, the fully automated easyPunch STARlet system integrates punching of GE Healthcare Whatman FTATM and drug metabolism and pharmacokinetics (DMPK) sample collection cards with automated sample extraction, eliminating common bottlenecks in laboratory processes. The system minimizes human error and enables high-throughput sample preparation for a variety of applications, such as forensic reference databasing as well as preclinical and clinical DMPK and toxicology studies.</p>
<p>The easyPunch workstation is based on the Hamilton Robotics Microlab STARlet platform and features two special modules and robotic arms for transporting and punching paper cards. The samples are monitored by tracking software to eliminate sample identification errors. The entire process is tracked using imaging recognition. Hamilton’s software, based on industrial machine vision technology, provides complete control and monitoring of the punching process. The software recognizes the position and size of the card, identifies the sample by reading the barcode, and determines the punch area. The workstation also takes a picture of the target well to ensure the punch has arrived in the designated well.</p>
<p>Compatibility with library information management systems and full traceability ensure that the data can be linked confidently to each sample. The modular nature of the system enables integration of other devices, such as a centrifuge and a plate sealer, thus potentially integrating the entire workflow.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hamiltonrobotics.com">www.hamiltonrobotics.com</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-2211068213478031">
<title>Hudson Robotics</title>
<sec id="section18-2211068213478031">
<title>PA1000 Print &amp; Apply Automated Barcode Labeling System</title>
<p>Hudson’s PA1000 Print &amp; Apply prints multiple-format barcode labels on any SLAS footprint microplate. It can print 1D, 2D, and/or human-readable text on one, two, or all four sides of a plate. It can print all common barcode formats, applies every label with ±0.020″ precision, and will operate with standard and deep-well microplates. Users can load up to 420 microplates per run. The PA1000 comes with easy-to-use software.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hudsonrobotics.com/products/microplate-handling/bar-code-print-and-apply">www.hudsonrobotics.com/products/microplate-handling/bar-code-print-and-apply</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-2211068213478031">
<title>Porvair Sciences</title>
<sec id="section20-2211068213478031">
<title>Microlute SPE Sample Preparation System</title>
<p>This alternative to cartridges for high-throughput sample clean up can handle samples as small as 150 µL. The Microlute SPE sample preparation system helps increase assay sensitivity by providing preinjection clean up and concentration. As a complete package, including filter plate, collection plate, waste tray, and manifold, the Microlute SPE sample preparation system offers all the advantages of automated and high-throughput SPE sample preparation in a convenient microplate format capable of rapidly processing 96 samples in one go repeatedly and precisely.</p>
<p>Constructed from a single piece of molded ultrapure polypropylene, the Microlute plate will not bend or distort because individual SPE cartridges do not have to be repeatedly plugged in and out. A sorbent slurry loading technique eliminates channeling effects that can limit the performance of dry powder–loaded SPE columns. Each well on a Microlute plate has an individual drain spout ensuring 100% sample transfer and zero crossover contamination. To recover dried or concentrated sample, the Microlute SPE sample preparation system may be coupled with a Porvair MiniVap sample concentrator. Microlute plates are available with a choice of sorbent and filter, and sample collection plates in a selection of well volumes (350 µL, 1 mL, or 2 mL).</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.porvair-sciences.com">www.porvair-sciences.com</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-2211068213478031">
<title>TAP Biosystems</title>
<sec id="section22-2211068213478031">
<title>ambr 250 Automated Bioreactor System</title>
<p>The ambr 250 is a new automated bioreactor system for parallel fermentation or cell culture, using single-use 250 mL bioreactors controlled by an automated workstation. The system builds on TAP’s micro bioreactor technology, adding increased fermentation volumes as well as individual bioreactor temperature and impeller control. This allows rapid testing of a range of conditions and microbial strains to select the optimum ones for efficient scale-up to large-scale bench-top, stirred tank bioreactors.</p>
<p>The ambr 250 workstation uses novel single-use bioreactors (100–250 mL working volume) including versions suitable for fermentation or cell culture. The microbial bioreactors, which are independently controlled, have a cap for automated sampling and include baffles, a dual Rushton impeller, and all gas (O<sub>2</sub>, air, N<sub>2</sub>), liquid, and sensor connections. They are considered ideal for use in assessing different fermentation parameters with production microbes such as <italic>Escherichia coli, Pichia pastoris</italic>, and <italic>Aspergillus</italic>.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tapbiosystems.com">www.tapbiosystems.com</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-2211068213478031">
<title>Tecan and Promega</title>
<sec id="section24-2211068213478031">
<title>Freedom EVO HSM Workstation</title>
<p>This new turnkey workstation for fully automated extraction of gDNA from whole-blood samples is designed to meet the needs of biobanks and high-throughput genomic laboratories. It provides reliable walkaway extraction of gDNA from large-volume blood samples using Promega’s ReliaPrep Large Volume HT gDNA Isolation System. It also is designed to streamline biobanking workflows, offering intelligent one-tube gDNA extraction from up to 32 samples in less than 4 h. The compact system is controlled by Tecan’s intuitive TouchTools touchscreen interface and features preinstalled protocols that have been tested and verified by Promega. Using the platform’s liquid level detection function, the system is able to automatically calculate the reagent volumes for each sample, ensuring efficient walkaway extraction of high-quality DNA from 1 to 10 mL of blood and meeting the specific requirements of next-generation sequencing methods.</p>
<p>More: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tecan.com/reliaprep">www.tecan.com/reliaprep</ext-link></p>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-2211068213478031" position="float"><p><bold>About JALA World News</bold>: E-mail new product announcements for consideration to <email>nhallock@slas.org</email>. MSWord documents and 300+ dpi image files are preferred. Deadlines are at least two months prior to publication. JALA editors reserve the right to select the products they deem most appropriate for the section and may revise copy as necessary. Product descriptions are based on information provided by the manufacturer. Inclusion in this section in no way implies endorsement by the <italic>Journal of Laboratory Automation</italic> or the Society for Laboratory Automation and Screening.</p>
</boxed-text>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>