<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SAE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsae</journal-id>
<journal-title>South Asia Economic Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1391-5614</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">0973-077X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1391561413477946</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1391561413477946</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Saman Kelegama (Ed.), <italic>Foreign Aid in South Asia: The Emerging Scenario</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rajapatirana</surname><given-names>Sarath</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1391561413477946">Independent Economics Consultant, Colombo, Sri Lanka</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>188</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kelegama</surname><given-names>Saman</given-names></name></person-group> (Ed.), <italic>Foreign Aid in South Asia: The Emerging Scenario</italic>, <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publications India Pvt. Ltd</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>, pp. <page-count count="317"/>, ₹750, ISBN: <isbn>978-81-321-0972-3</isbn> (PB).</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Research and Information System for Developing Countries &amp; Institute of Policy Studies of Sri Lanka</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1391561413477946">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Including the introduction by the editor, the volume consists of 12 chapters in five categories. These are as follows: Aid Debate and Emerging Donors (Overview of Global Reforms in Foreign Aid, South–South Cooperation), Aid Effectiveness and India (Aid and Growth in India: Evidence from Disaggregated Data); Nexus between Aid and Security (Pakistan and Afghanistan); Policy Priorities and the Role of Aid in Post-Conflict Economies (Sri Lanka and Nepal); Policy Priorities and the Role of Aid in Least Developed Countries (Bangladesh and Bhutan); and the Role of Aid in a Small and Vulnerable Economy (Maldives). As these categories and chapters suggest, the volume covers a wide range of issues and country experiences.</p>
<p>This collection of essays addresses an important issue of foreign aid effectiveness in the region at a time when aid flows and degree of concessionality have begun to decline even before the onset of the recession in developed countries in 2008. Meanwhile, some new donors from the developing world have begun to emerge in what the volume calls South–South Cooperation (SSC). The major donors represented by the OECD countries have initiated a series of efforts to improve aid architecture during the period 2002–2011. Research into the contribution of foreign aid to economic development of developing countries has produced an array of results from those that have found that, overall, aid has been beneficial to poor countries under a certain milieu but less so in other circumstances, even when the policy environment for aid had been thought to be conducive. Other researchers led by Bill Easterly, Raghu Rajan and Subramanium have found that traditional aid could even be harmful when delivered in the well-established ways. Consequently, the aid effectiveness area is full of discussions and debate on the proper approaches needed. In this context, the present volume serves an important need for policy-makers and the citizens of the South Asian countries, as well as for bilateral and multilateral donors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1391561413477946">
<title>Region-wide Generic Issues</title>
<p>The foreword written by Nihal Kappagoda sets off a good lead for the analysis and discussions that follow from this veteran of aid use and foreign exchange budget planning in Sri Lanka in the 1960s and from a donor perspective as a high official of the International Development Research Centre in Canada in the 1980s. The main message this reviewer could gather from this practitioner is that aid coordination and use are challenging tasks, made more difficult by the entry of non-governmental organizations (NGOs) into the fray and with multilateral institutions including the United Nations (UN) with its wide array of objectives, procedures and processes. It is no surprise that UN agencies are at the bottom of the lot with respect to measured successes of aid practices based on transparency, specialization, selectivity, delivery and overhead costs (Easterly &amp; Williamson, 2010).</p>
<p>Chapter 1, ‘Foreign Aid and South Asia’ by Saman Kelegama, the editor of the volume of essays, is a wide ranging and engaging discussion of the main issues relating to foreign aid practices, use, effectiveness and results. The analysis is highly competent, useful and does a masterly job of putting it all together in a stand-alone comprehensive chapter. Several aspects of the chapter are noteworthy. The chapter traces the means by which the donors and recipients agreed on the processes to increase the quality and quantity of aid following the adoption of the UN’s Millennium Development Goals (MDGs). The initial step began with the Monterrey meeting in 2002. The second stage was the Rome High Level Forum (HLF) in 2003 followed by another HLF in Paris in 2005. The last mentioned led to the Paris Declaration (PD), which was signed by 91 countries, 26 international donor organizations and 14 civil society organizations. The PD is based on five principles, namely, aid recipients forge their own national development strategies (ownership), donor support for these strategies (alignment), work to streamline efforts in each country (harmonization), strategies to have clear goals and progress towards them be monitored (managing development results), and donors and recipients be jointly responsible for achieving these goals (mutual accountability). Progress towards implementation of PD was monitored in 2006, 2008 and 2011.</p>
<p>The chapter notes that there was an unprecedented alliance among developing countries, donors represented by the Development Assistance Committee (DAC) and civil society organizations, emerging economies, the UN and multilateral institutions in the Accra Agenda for Action (AAA). These parties agreed to seek improvements in ownership, partnership and delivering results to lead to measurable impacts on people’s lives. A report on aid (2008) done by an independent group criticizes the PD in that it does nothing to check the imbalance of power between donor and recipients. The report also criticized the PD for not addressing tied aid, donor conditionality and the institutional framework to monitor implementation. Moreover, recipients continue to find fault with donors for not being able to meet their pledge of providing 0.7 of GDP in Overseas Development Assistance (ODA). This reviewer notes that the claim only recognizes official assistance, whereas large amounts of assistance have been granted from non-official channels to poor countries. One has to agree with Kelegama that exit from aid, as some advocate, is neither viable, nor is the continuation of bad practices in giving and receiving aid. Hence, the need for a better design of aid.</p>
<p>South Asia has been a recipient of large amounts of foreign aid for over six decades. And the purpose of the volume is to examine aid experience in the region with the type of PD focus. Some aid recipients in the region have not developed their own priorities to use the aid in the most beneficial way, leave aside the different approaches and motivations of donors. Thus, such an evaluation is timely, especially at a time when aid amounts are declining while long-term needs of some of the South Asian countries to undertake development efforts have not waned. While a few countries in the region will graduate from aid dependency as their income rise, others will continue to need aid because South Asia has the largest percentage of the world’s poor and significant disparities in per capita income persist. Meanwhile, the region has four least developed countries (LDCs)—Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan and Maldives—that have special access to markets and aid from developed countries.</p>
<p>The editor’s chapter makes an important contribution to the discussion on foreign aid that follows by identifying key issues that must be taken into account in analyzing aid to South Asia. These are the role played by new economies (China, Middle East and to a lesser extent, India) in official assistance with different practices compared to the traditional donors, the decline in multilateral aid to the region and consequences for aid from the financial crisis of 2008–2009. Kelegama identifies a number of issues that South Asian countries must address to make the best use of aid. They must assess the extent to which foreign aid priorities are driven by them as against the donors, realize that the bulk of ODA must be repaid with interest in foreign exchange and alternative uses of financing must be explored including domestic savings. The best use of the funds will differ from country to country. He makes a comprehensive list of issues that have to be addressed to get the best use of foreign aid. These include the recent trends in foreign assistance to that country, their role in the development process, effectiveness of aid and future aid priorities. It is an important list to evaluate the individual chapters in the volume.</p>
<p>Chapter 2, ‘Overview of Global Reforms in Foreign Aid’ by Indrajit Coomaraswamy, provides a pithy and informative survey of aid architecture. In one sense, it covers somewhat similar ground to that of the first chapter save for country experiences. In another sense, in this short chapter he notes the importance of taking advantage of the PD to reform aid utilization, the opportunities afforded by falling interest rates in the world and notes that even if PD were to be implemented effectively, it would not lead to a rationalization of aid. He believes that what is needed is an ‘architect’ rather than a ‘tinker’. While this reviewer agrees with this view, it is not clear in which way this architecture needs to be designed. This volume provides elements of that architecture for South Asia.</p>
<p>Chapter 3, ‘South–South Cooperation: Aid Effectiveness and India’, by Rajiv Kumar, Michael Dickerson and Surabhahi Tandon, examines the question how the five principles of the PD could be better served by cooperation among the developing countries in general and the South Asian countries in particular. They claim that the MDGs have better prospects with an integrated approach among many countries to improve aid effectiveness. The chapter attempts to provide a rationale for this approach. The authors have noted that AAA (2008) welcomed an integrated approach but donors have continued to retain their status as principal actors while aid recipients continue as passive players. They remark that the role of emerging donors had only received a passing reference in the PD. The authors indicate that SSC has a special role in achieving both environmental sustainability and capacity building in aid use and effectiveness. First, emerging economies can undertake capacity building especially in post-conflict and fragile states due to their good understanding of the context in which aid takes place. Second, emerging donors can identify critical sectors from their own experience. Third, emerging economy experts often demonstrate greater tolerance and flexibility to adapt to specific situations. Finally, local capacity building can be done in a cost-effective and self-sustaining manner by emerging donors like India. The authors also claim that emerging donors have a lower likelihood of imposing ‘discredited or fashionable’ conditions. They also claim that SSC will permit greater possibility of enforcing mutual accountability of both donors and recipients. The latter two points may be true, but there is no demonstrable evidence that this has been the case, especially due to absence of adequate experience to date. Also, when the authors refer to the Marshall Plan as an example when the conditions were stringent, they miss two important points about that experience, namely, that assistance was largely through actual investment choices that were made by the private sector even though the donor governments provided guarantees, and further, the intrusiveness they ascribe to the Marshall Plan is an overstatement. The authors cite the case of India’s potential role as a donor, especially for LDCs given that its experience is closer to that of LDCs. The authors exhort that ‘it is the opportune time for moving the SSC from the sidelines to the centre stage of the discourse and delivery of aid globally’. One cannot find fault with this sentiment. However, not all developing countries would be willing to accept the dominance of emerging donors, in as much as the role of the OECD countries and multi-national agencies was questioned by the developing countries at large.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1391561413477946">
<title>Country-specific Issues</title>
<p>Chapter 4, ‘Aid and Growth in India: Some Evidence from Disaggregated Data’ by George Mavrotas, is a unique chapter in the volume for several reasons. It applies to the largest country in South Asia, one with the longest record of aid implementation, the largest amount of aid received and an emerging donor. The chapter uses an econometric model to evaluate aid effectiveness in contrast to most other country-focused chapters. The main thrust of the chapter is to evaluate the impact of aid on growth using the composition of aid as a factor. There are different forms of aid in total aid. Thus, project aid has a long gestation period, while programme aid is disbursed rapidly. Technical assistance has a different character largely as an input into a project aid, while food and commodity aid adds directly to consumption. Consequently, their impacts are different.</p>
<p>The econometric model begins with a well-defined objective function. The public sector policy-maker is assumed to maximize a utility function based on the objective function. Then elements of a budget constraints are defined noting different targets, such as the government wanting to minimize borrowing, increasing tax revenues, with a portion of tax revenue going to government investment, and using different aid elements with the prominence given to the aid composition issue. In addition, other constraints are built into the model. They are a growth constraint and a private investment constraint. Using these constraints, a reduced form growth equation is derived closing the model in which the aid recipient country maximizes the utility function subject to constraints, using a standard Lagrange approach. Other aspects, such as human capital, international capital flows, trade openness and uncertainty, are introduced into the model at different points to take into account these critical factors on growth. In addition, a number of policy variables are considered (money supply, budget surplus/deficit, total tax and expenditures) in the final stage of the estimation of the growth equation. These are variables that capture uncertainty, including the real exchange rate and the GDP deflator. Using co-integration procedures developed by Hendry and Johansson, unit root tests are used to test stationarity. The estimates have attempted to answer the question whether policies adopted by the recipient country have an overall impact on growth through aid effectiveness.</p>
<p>The results indicate that the composition of aid matters for aid effectiveness. However, it is also to be noted that both programme and project aid have a negative effect on growth in India in the period considered, that is, 1982–1992 period. The estimates show that policy changes have a positive effect on the share of money supply to GDP ratio, which is a measure of financial deepening in the country. This reviewer believes that while the results are somewhat disappointing on account of their negative effect on growth, the positive element is that the composition of aid seems to matter at least for some limited variables. The chapter is long on methodology but short on usable results. Perhaps this was inevitable given the data limitations and the state of econometrics in the late 1990s when the study seems to have been done. Also, Indian economic policy changed significantly after the 1991 crisis and India was able to attain high rates of growth well into 2007. Perhaps a study done over a later period, say up to 2010, would have yielded more robust results. Nevertheless, the attempt has some value in using time series techniques and looking into aid composition as a factor in aid effectiveness. Finally, the chapter stands somewhat different from most other chapters as it inquires into aid effectiveness and its impact on growth, while others seek to examine the application of the five principles (ownership, alignment, harmonization, management by results and joint accountability) of the PD on aid effectiveness.</p>
<p>Chapter 5, on Pakistan, is by Vaqar Ahmed and Abdul Wahab who study the link between aid, development and security. It provides a good summary of the record of growth and policy changes amidst periods of intense conflict, radical political changes, floods and changes in external conditions. The chapter describes the role of aid in Pakistan’s economy comprehensively with respect to quantities, sources and types. Perhaps, Pakistan has the most varied aid experience compared to other countries in the region, as it is at the centre of geopolitical factors including rivalry among the big powers. Motives for aid, such as geopolitics and security, are also included in the analysis.</p>
<p>They use a computable general equilibrium (CGE) model to examine the macro–micro impact of foreign savings (linked to a Social Accounting Matrix [SAM]). The simulations show a host of interesting results. An increase in foreign savings by 50 per cent leads to an increase in real private consumption by 2.8 per cent. With a greater amount of foreign exchange with the infusion of increased aid, imports increase by 3.7 per cent while exports decline by 6.5 per cent. This leads to a declining trade balance. However, nominal GDP increases by 1.8 per cent. While the foreign savings to GDP ratio increases by 2.0 per cent, both investment and private savings as a proportion of GDP declines by 0.3 per cent and 2.4 per cent, respectively. Other changes observed by the simulation are significant. As expected, the aid inflow has effects on the exchange rate through changes in the prices of non-tradable and tradable goods. Value added price of tradable goods fall and that of non-tradables rise, particularly housing and private services. While the authors do not comment on the nature of the outcome, there are signs of a Dutch disease with a presumed appreciation of the real exchange rate. It is, of course, quite possible that a PPP rate and the ratio of tradables to non-tradables move in opposite directions. Of course, many of the changes in prices and sectors depend on the nature of the model used and what assumptions are made in the CGE. The welfare of the stimulations is also significant. With the foreign savings inflow, large and medium-sized farms lose while small farms gain. Rural agricultural workers and small farmers gain leading to a redistribution of income in favour of low-income households. Consequently, poverty declines by 3.1 per cent for an increase in foreign savings by 50 per cent. Among regions, Punjab has a higher decline in poverty by 3.3 per cent.</p>
<p>Pakistan is one of the largest recipients of foreign aid in the region and has remained a frontier state in the war against terrorism. The chapter notes that the empirical evidence of the impact of foreign aid on economic development is inconclusive due to fragmented approaches to aid, poor coordination among and with the donors and weak follow-up of implementation. But it is not without some success in a few individual cases, such as the support for rural networks, microfinance opportunities and cluster approach for earthquake relief and recovery. Pakistan has made efforts to improve aid effectiveness along the lines of PD principles, and while the results are not yet evident, a good effort appears to have been made.</p>
<p>All in all, the Pakistan chapter is comprehensive and connects the facts on the ground to smart simulations even though the simulations could be very sensitive to the assumptions typically made in a CGE. The chapter has a good narrative and it indicates some common themes with other chapters with respect to the initial conditions, changes over time in Pakistan from floods to terrorism and being somewhat of a surrogate theatre for competition among the superpowers.</p>
<p>Chapter 6 on Afghanistan is authored by Anneka de Silva. It is more war-torn in scope and depth than Pakistan, the other country where security is closely linked to aid. In fact, after the fall of the Taliban regime in 2001, the invasion of a multinational force led by the US saw an escalation of both war and aid. Taking into account military aid (not counted in normal aid accounting), Afghanistan is a high recipient of aid. Yet, it has low absorptive capacity given weak institutions, lack of cohesion in administration of the provinces, corruption and high illegal transactions in large parts of the economy growing illegal crops. The country is responsible for 90 per cent of the world’s opium production. One implication of the high proportion of illegal activities is that tax collections are very low with only 3.2 per cent of GDP in 2002–2003. Though it was raised to 7.0 per cent during 2006–2008, the low rate of tax collection is the main reason for high aid dependency. By international standards, the country is in need of large social expenditures from health to education, particularly for women. While the country has had large commitments, disbursement rates are low, and projects are delayed due to undue bureaucratic control. The total capital budget as well as around 35 per cent of recurrent expenditures are financed by aid. Afghanistan National Development Strategy (ANDS) was initiated in 2008 which recognized the need for greater development efforts which had been hitherto somewhat neglected due to the security situation. Without security, national development strategy cannot be implemented. Equally, without a national development strategy, long-term security cannot be realized. With the ANDS, donors have shifted their support towards development while the support to security has been reduced. There is greater emphasis put on infrastructure, education, agricultural development, health, economic governance and the rule of law. The present challenges for foreign aid is to support the improvement of fiscal management (IMF support provided by a Poverty Reduction and Growth Fund, PRGF). The target for domestic revenue effort is to support 58 per cent of recurrent expenditure. While this was agreed at the 2006 London Conference, which outlined the Afghanistan compact, some of the agreed ratios for public revenue support have not been met by 2009–2010 and the date has been extended to 2012–2013. Other efforts included measures to strengthen institutional capacity, given that such efforts are made difficult by the fragmented nature of the administration with different ethnic communities dominant in different provinces. In addition, corruption is rife and huge parts of the economy operate in the informal sector. The chapter concludes by identifying the challenges of meeting the PD principles. These include the alignment donor support for country priorities. In the area of fiscal management, this implies increasing the predictability of aid, augmenting domestic resource mobilization efforts and enhancing domestic institutional capacity. There is also the challenge of implementing the priorities supported by donors in an environment of low security where the government’s outreach is limited and where the connection between the central government and the province is tenuous. The chapter does a good job of bringing out the main challenges facing the country where security is weak, institutions are similarly weak and aid dependence is expected to continue for a long time. Some preliminary steps have been taken but it is too early to gauge the results.</p>
<p>Chapter 7 on Sri Lanka by Deshal de Mel and Anneka de Silva examines the role of aid in post-conflict economies and it shares this category with Nepal. The authors provide a comprehensive chapter ranging from macroeconomic implications of aid to Sri Lanka to priorities for enhancing aid effectiveness in Sri Lanka. They note that foreign aid has played an important role in Sri Lanka’s development in the past by providing long-term capital for the government budget and that this effort has been led by the World Bank and the Asian Development Bank. Sri Lanka benefited with low interest and long grace period for long-term loans (mostly IDA credits) until around 2005 and then received blend loans with lesser concessions. During the nearly 30 years of conflict that led to the defeat of the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Elam (LTTE), aid flows declined and indeed the aid community introduced conditions that attempted to force the country to make peace with the LTTE. The high watermark of this effort was reached at the Tokyo Aid Forum in 2003 when the main donors promised to commit $4.5 billion if the Government of Sri Lanka (GOSL) came to a permanent peace agreement with the LTTE, a separatist organization. The use of aid as an inducement for forging (or some would say forcing) a peace was unprecedented for Norway, UK, Japan and Canada. The amount was exceedingly large and the conditions for peace unacceptable to the GOSL, as it would have effectively divided the country. And, it would have led to a part of the country (North and the East) to be ruled in a non-democratic way mostly by the use of the gun. There was a stalemate after the 2003 Tokyo conference at which the four donors made this offer. GOSL was not ready to meet the political conditions of the aid group. Meanwhile, the LTTE was invited for the Tokyo conference but decided to boycott it.</p>
<p>By 2005, aid had fallen to its lowest level. The new Left of central government of the United Peoples Freedom Alliance (UPFA) that came into power put more emphasis on domestic sources of saving and investment and looked to China and others rather than the traditional donors. But multilateral aid did pick up in 2009 after the defeat of the LTTE combatants. There was increased assistance to the North and the East, the war-torn areas of the country. China became the largest lender to Sri Lanka to replace some of the traditional donors who alleged violations of human rights in the last stage of the LTTE war. In one sense, China is not a traditional donor, because it does not consider non-economic factors, nor are the terms of their loans generally discussed beyond the amounts especially with respect to the terms of those loans. India has also become a large new lender to Sri Lanka in the post-conflict phase. While its earlier engagements were Indian lines of credit of the non-project variety, it has since 2009 switched to financing development projects, especially in the past conflict regions. Given that Sri Lanka began to receive lower amounts of aid from the traditional Western donors, Sri Lanka also took recourse to commercial loans, with shorter maturities. This has implications for the service of future debt, given the higher interest rates, reduced maturities and that many projects do not generate surpluses in the tradable sectors. Meanwhile, export growth has slowed while import growth has also slowed but at a lower rate leading to growing current account deficits in the balance of payments. This has implications for debt service. One saving grace has been the consistent flow of worker remittances, without which Sri Lanka would have a harder time meeting external obligations.</p>
<p>The authors evaluate the effectiveness of the PD in Sri Lanka in relation to its five principles. With respect to ownership, the government has provided a 10-year development framework (2007–2016) known as Mahinda Chintana. The Annual Development Forum acts as a pledging where the government presents development plans and donors commit financial support. However, the authors remark that the government’s selection of donors do not always follow their comparative advantage to provide that particular project or programme. The authors feel that this could be remedied by better coordination. With respect to alignment, there is good progress since nearly 90 per cent of aid is to the public sector with 78 per cent of aid going through the public budget. The remainder outside these parameters is largely bilateral aid. It is noteworthy that approximately 80 per cent of all aid has been from three sources, World Bank, ADB and Japan. Harmonization of aid would help to ensure greater efficiency in aid delivery. However, the Sri Lankan PD report for 2005 found that this aspect had fallen short of PD targets. Only 16.5 per cent of 236 donor missions that year was coordinated among the donors. But some have claimed that harmonization is not a high priority with the GOSL. In regard to managing for development results and mutual accountability, the authors feel that more efforts have to be made in this regard. They remark that there should be larger participation of stakeholders and adoption of results-based budgeting. The authors note correctly that Sri Lanka’s dependence on concessional aid has to decline as its income increases and better management of aid resources is needed to get best results. They exhort the donors to be sensitive to capacity constraints of domestic institutions and the potential detrimental effect of donor dominance in projects.</p>
<p>Chapter 8 on Nepal is authored by Bishwambher Pyakuryal. Nepal began receiving foreign aid in the early 1950s led by the US and India providing more than 30 per cent of the grants received. Other donors to Nepal were China, Soviet Union, Britain, Switzerland, Australia, Japan and New Zealand. The US concentrated its aid in the early years on agriculture, rural development and basic infrastructure and added health and education in the 1960s. In 1976, the World Bank helped to create the Nepal Aid Group. That led to the leadership of multilateral donors of aid to the country. Following the formation of the Aid Group, more than 70 per cent of aid was provided by multilaterals with a large percentage of concessional assistance. In the 1980s, there was an increase in lending on non-concessional terms which led to larger amounts of overall foreign assistance. During the 1990s, the Nepal Aid Group formed the core for the Nepal Development Forum (NDF). NDF had wider objectives. It helped to chart a road map for sustained peace and resulting socio-economic transformation with support from the development partners. It was committed to create a reform agenda to meet the challenges of implementing priority projects. It developed a national action plan for aid effectiveness and built a road map for trade, investment and private sector development through the creation of a conducive environment and increased competitiveness. Foreign aid provided a large amount of budget support. For instance, nearly all capital expenditure was provided by foreign aid. Nepal financed some 75 per cent of the budget deficit from aid in 1999–2000. This percentage declined over the years to some 30–50 per cent. From the very beginning, Nepal had development plans, the latest reported in the chapter being a three-year interim plan (2007/08–2009/10), all of which provided a guide for foreign aid support. There is no doubt according to the author that foreign aid contributed to the development of Nepal. He notes that the issue is then how best foreign aid is to be used effectively.</p>
<p>Commenting on the implementation of aid, the author notes that like in many other aid recipients, there has been a large discrepancy between commitments and disbursements. The problem has got worse in the last decade and is ascribed to political instability in the country. On the issue of the effectiveness of foreign aid, the chapter reports on a survey done by the Government of Nepal which monitored 2005 PD in 2008 and found the following: there were many discrepancies on the part of the donors to comply with their own commitments, that these had a negative effect on development and put pressure on the already overworked bureaucracy to find funds. The report of the survey on PD principles was done through the use of 12 indicators ranging from partners having an operational development strategy, reliable country systems, aid flows aligned to national priorities, use of the public finance management system and a results-oriented framework. The survey found that only 74 per cent of the money extended in aid to Nepal passed through the government budget. The rest was outside government which probably was implemented by donors directly. The author notes that in Nepal, studies have found a negative relationship between aid and growth of per capita real GDP. These studies also found that when aid exceeds absorptive capa­city, it is counter-productive. Higher levels of aid were found to erode institutional quality and increased rent seeking. The author concludes that the country has some way to go to increase aid effectiveness and calls for economic rather than political restructuring to achieve this goal.</p>
<p>Chapter 9 on Bangladesh is by Selim Raihan. Bangladesh is in the LDC category, as designated by the UN. The chapter analyzes the change in importance focus, and composition of foreign aid to the country. It also discusses issues related to the effectiveness of aid and the critical factors that should be taken into account in using aid effectively. It has been a large recipient of foreign aid, with around $60 billion committed during the 1971–1972 to 2007–2008 period. Some 75 per cent of the commitments were disbursed and of the amount disbursed, about 44 per cent was in grants. The grant element declined over time with spectacular increases in exports and remittances. The increase in exports is associated with improved competitiveness of the economy and duty-free access to Western markets as an LDC. These developments effectively made the country from an aid dependent to a trade dependent economy.</p>
<p>The sources of aid also changed over time. During this period, 51.5 per cent was disbursed from bilateral sources and the rest from multilateral sources which was the case until 1990s and 2000s, when multilateral sources provided a large percentage of aid. A long-term perspective prepared by the government, Vision 2021, provides a key message that the country will become a prosperous progressive nation with food and energy security and drastic reductions in poverty. Within this perspective, it is envisaged that the country would need foreign assistance of US$3 billion to US$5 billion for a baseline growth scenario and a high growth scenario, respectively. The chapter provides a retrospective on aid effectiveness noting that donors have considered investment loans more successful than policy loans. It notes that poor policy reform was not only due to domestic factors but due in part to the multiplicity of donors with diverse reporting and accounting requirements and the heavy demands on scarce domestic management capacity. The chapter reports on an error correction model that examines the relationship among per capita savings, real per capita GDP and per capita real foreign aid for the 1973–2006 period. The results indicate that there has been a negative relationship between foreign aid and real per capita income both for the short run and the long run. The chapter concludes that the government should not look at foreign aid as a means of financing the fiscal deficit, but rather treat it as a source for enhancing investments. It indicates that poor design, lack of ownership, multiple controls, divergence between development and current revenue budgets as well as poor coordination among the ministries as the reasons for weak implementation of aid financed development programmes in the country. The chapter is conspicuous for its absence of discussion of the PD that has been found in other chapters. This reviewer does not consider it as a weakness of the chapter but as a different view from other chapters.</p>
<p>Chapter 10 on Bhutan is by Thinley Namgyel. A small, mountainous and landlocked country, it has a population of no more than 600,000 plus persons. Planned development of the country began in 1961, and it has made impressive socio-economic development progress. Its per capita income has grown from US$835 in 2002 to US$1,980 in 2008. It was US$2,070 by the World Bank Atlas method in 2011. It is a lower-middle income country today. Its human development index ranked 131 in 2006. The country is guided by the philosophy of maximizing and achieving a Gross National Happiness (GNH) which seeks to balance material well-being with emotional and cultural needs of the individual and society. Its five-year development plan (2008–2013) aims to reduce the poverty headcount from 23.2 per cent in 2007 to less than 15 per cent in 2013. Bhutan’s domestic revenue is expected to finance 51 per cent of the total outlay with external grants of 32 per cent, external borrowing of 8 per cent and domestic borrowing of 9 per cent. India has been the oldest and the largest development partner to Bhutan. Following Bhutan’s membership in the UN, it received assistance from UN agencies. Other development partners joined in including Austria, Canada, Denmark, EU, Japan, Switzerland, Norway and Thailand. Other support came from the ADB, International Agricultural Development Fund and a host of UN agencies. Bilateral aid accounted for nearly 80 per cent, while multilateral aid accounted for 6 per cent and international financial institutions provided 14 per cent in the tenth five-year plan (2008–2013). Education and agriculture received the largest aid allocation and was in line with government priorities. While not a member of the PD, Bhutan has been following its principles on aid effectiveness. The tenth five-year plan serves as the instrument of ownership, with alignment of aid through the World Bank Country Assistance Strategy and United Nations Development Framework. Efforts are made to harmonize procedures for implementing aid with respect to financial and procurement management, auditing, budgeting and accounting and monitoring systems. Also, results-based management is made possible by the use of the five-year plan framework sanctioned projects and programmes. While the author is satisfied with the state of meeting the PD principles, he notes that there is room for improvement both on the side of the country and the donors.</p>
<p>Chapter 11 on Maldives is authored by Hussain Niyaaz. The country became independent in 1965 and joined the UN in 1968. Its main activities are tourism and fishing that have undergone significant modernization over the last 40 years. In 2008, it had a per capita income of US$2,912 according to the chapter. The World Bank Atlas method puts per capita income at US$6,530 in 2011 which makes it an upper middle-income country. Maldives was making good progress in socio-economic conditions when the Asian Tsunami struck in late 2004, and which physically washed away 60 per cent of the country’s GDP. Consequently, the country received an unprecedented level of humanitarian assistance. Meanwhile, the country had experienced a political transition in recent years. Foreign grant receipts reached the peak in 2005 with help following the tsunami. However, as the reconstruction period ended, donors gradually pulled out. The author offers as evidence of aid effectiveness the high levels of educational enrolment, childhood immunizations, high life expectancy at birth, low prevalence of communicable disease and reduced childhood mortality rates and birth rates. The chapter notes the efforts that are being made to achieve ownership, alignment, harmonization and managing results through a well-established coordination mechanism, annual Maldives Partnership Forums and the Donor Conference. The National Planning Council chaired by the President is represented by key ministries of finance, economic development, housing and the environment. Despite these efforts, some deficiencies remain and in particular, aid coordination needs to be improved using the External Resources Coordinating committee by making it more effective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1391561413477946">
<title>Evaluation of Generic and Region-wide Issues</title>
<p>The country studies give specifics on the generic issues relevant to the region and they provide valuable lessons and evidence of where to make changes in order to improve aid effectiveness. That being said, it is important to note that even if the five principles of the PD were followed to the letter, that would not by themselves lead to improved aid effectiveness in the sense that the aid receipts are best used to address growth and poverty reduction goals of the region. However, they would go a long way. They are a necessary but not a sufficient condition. Going beyond these goals, it is worth noting that the motivations of the recipients and donors cannot be neatly wrapped in the PD principles. As some analysts have noted, not all aid ends up in investments and not all investments (both in physical and human capital) provide high returns. Much depend on overall policy environments, domestic politics and indeed international politics whether it be aid to Pakistan, Afghanistan or Sri Lanka. There have been instances where the economics have been overshadowed by donor politics and also where domestic politics have not allowed proper reform of the aid architecture both within and without countries. The generic issues and country cases discussed and analyzed in the volume offer a rich tapestry of varied experiences. That is the strength of this volume. However, by the same token, it must be noted that the eight countries are at different stages of development, policy and institutional maturity.</p>
<p>Some country cases have not addressed the PD principles and their implementation directly, while others have almost used them as a checklist to make their observations. This reviewer values that variety even though some effort has to be made to evaluate the aid regime to offer advice to the recipient and donor governments. In addition, some have attempted to quantify the relationship between aid amounts, the impact of the particular composition and the types of aid given. It is a good thing to quantify these relationships for the benefit of policy-makers, and for scholars and students to look at comparative experience. Some quantitative evidence that has been marshalled in a couple of cases have not been encouraging as the chapters on India, Pakistan, Nepal and Bangladesh indicate. Then, at the other end of the spectrum, little could have been done on quantitative work on Afghanistan, Bhutan and Maldives. But their narratives presented by the authors are informative and at times compelling. It is also to be noted that some narratives were very broad based. This review found them interesting to get a flavour of the challenges faced for increasing aid effectiveness. Thus, for example, aid issues cannot be discussed meaningfully without reference to fiscal policy, the overall macroeconomic policy environment and institutional make-up of a country. These the authors have provided in good measure in all the studies in the volume, and these enhance the value of the volume. Some specific examples which may be mentioned are the cases of Bangladesh and Nepal which transformed themselves from aid dependent economies to trade dependent economies. Many of the countries reduced their dependence on aid with trade, remittances and better use of resources through improved policy environments. Bangladesh, Nepal, Sri Lanka and India have good growth records arising from improved policies.</p>
<p>At times, some authors have made strong claims for greater South–South Cooperation, that emerging economies could be more relevant donors, but there is no assurance that they are necessarily superior to current donors. They will face the same challenges as traditional donors in designing and implementing their projects and programmes. Regional politics may not always help to make their role easier or more effective. One hopes that with some experience in a decade or so in the future, we would be able to better assess their role.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1391561413477946">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Starting with the introductory chapter by the editor, the volume is a valuable addition to the literature on foreign aid in the South Asian region. The introductory chapter sets a high standard for the volume. Using it as a benchmark for the other chapters, this reviewer overall found a highly competent treatment of aid issues in the region, with special focus on ways and means of increasing aid effectiveness through the adoption of the PD principles. Not all chapters reached the same high standard, given data and other problems. Also, as noted earlier, following those principles would be necessary to improve design, delivery and implementation but they by themselves are not sufficient. This message comes through the volume. The accompanying narrative on the development of foreign aid in the region is valuable to understand what both donors and recipients have to do to improve aid architecture in the region. Of course, PD applies to all countries receiving and giving aid worldwide.</p>
<p>Overall, this is a valuable study for its focus on a hitherto under-researched area of study for the region. The study should be widely read and discussed among policy-makers and the academia alike.</p>
</sec>
<sig-block>
<sig>Sarath Rajapatirana<break/>
<italic>Independent Economics Consultant</italic><break/>
<italic>Colombo, Sri Lanka</italic>
</sig></sig-block>
</body>
</article>