<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jclinpharm</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Pharmacol</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0091-2700</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4604</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0091270010396710</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0091270010396710</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Pharmacokinetics</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Time-Dependent Pharmacokinetics of 5-Fluorouracil and Association With Treatment Tolerability in the Adjuvant Setting of Colorectal Cancer</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>Toni</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>Antonello</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Amatori</surname><given-names>Federica</given-names></name>
<degrees>PharmD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mercatali</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name>
<degrees>BS</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ravaioli</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name>
<degrees>BS</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Flamini</surname><given-names>Emanuela</given-names></name>
<degrees>BS</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sacanna</surname><given-names>Emanuele</given-names></name>
<degrees>BS</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Del Tacca</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Danesi</surname><given-names>Romano</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Amadori</surname><given-names>Dino</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0091270010396710">Osteoncology Center, Istituto Scientifico Romagnolo per lo Studio e la Cura dei Tumori, Meldola, Italy (Dr Ibrahim, Dr Mercatali, Dr Ravaioli, Dr Flamini, Dr Sacanna, Dr Amadori)</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0091270010396710">Division of Pharmacology and Chemotherapy, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy (Dr Di Paolo, Dr Amatori, Dr Del Tacca, Dr Danesi)</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0091270010396710">Romano Danesi, MD, PhD, Division of Pharmacology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Pisa, Via Roma 55, 56126 Pisa, Italy; e-mail: <email>r.danesi@med.unipi.it</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>52</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>361</fpage>
<lpage>369</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>12</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American College of Clinical Pharmacology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American College of Clinical Pharmacology, Inc.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The authors evaluated the influence of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) on treatment tolerability in 81 colorectal cancer patients given adjuvant 5-FU intravenously plus folinic acid for 6 cycles. The pharmacokinetics of 5-FU and its inactive metabolite 5-fluoro-5,6-dihydrouracil (5-FDHU) were measured on days 1 and 5 of the first chemotherapy cycle, 5 and 45 minutes after bolus administration. 5-FU clearance was significantly lower on day 5 (62.64 ± 20.16 L/h/m<sup>2</sup>) than on day 1 (74.83 ± 31.61 L/h/m<sup>2</sup>). The lower 5-FU clearance values also predicted the side effects during the entire course of chemotherapy. In particular, patients with low clearance values on day 1 had a further reduction in this parameter on day 5, associated with severe toxicities. In conclusion, 5-FU alters its clearance, which could be partly due to a reduction in 5-FDHU biotransformation. These findings have safety implications for poor metabolizers whose drug clearance may fall below the threshold during repeated treatment cycles.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>5-Fluorouracil</kwd>
<kwd>pharmacokinetics</kwd>
<kwd>metabolism</kwd>
<kwd>toxicity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>More than 1 million new cases of colorectal cancer (CRC) are diagnosed worldwide annually.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0091270010396710">1</xref></sup> 5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) was first introduced in the therapeutic armamentarium in the early 1960s, and since then it has been prescribed for the treatment of solid neoplasms, including CRC, gastric and esophageal carcinomas, breast cancers, and head and neck tumors. Indeed, 5-FU continues to produce a survival advantage, and it is widely used in adjuvant and advanced settings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0091270010396710">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0091270010396710">3</xref></sup> Although the introduction of oral prodrugs such as capecitabine and tegafur has been a major step forward in recent administration schedules, 5-FU has been reported to cause severe or life-threatening toxicities in patients with reduced activity of dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase (DPD), an enzyme that catalyzes transformation of the drug to 5-fluoro-5,6-dihydrouracil (5-FDHU). Alterations in 5-FU and 5-FDHU pharmacokinetics have been confirmed to be associated with treatment-induced toxicities due to the reduction in DPD-dependent systemic clearance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0091270010396710">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0091270010396710">6</xref></sup> Consequently, a number of studies have attempted to predict severe or life- threatening toxicities based on these parameters.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0091270010396710">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0091270010396710">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>DPD gene expression and activity are thought to be influenced by 5-FU and cisplatin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0091270010396710">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0091270010396710">11</xref></sup> Notably, 5-FU cytotoxic activity is highly dependent on the administration schedule, with thymidylate synthase inhibition prevailing when 5-FU is given as a continuous infusion. In contrast, 5-FU incorporation into RNA is considered to be the main mechanism of action when the drug is administered as a bolus,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0091270010396710">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0091270010396710">13</xref></sup> interfering with messenger RNA function and altering protein synthesis. On the basis of the latter finding, one may argue that 5-FU has the potential to influence its own metabolism by interfering with DPD gene expression, progressively reducing DPD protein synthesis and enzyme activity.</p>
<p>Preliminary data by Di Paolo et al in CRC patients receiving adjuvant 5-FU by the Machover’s schedule showed a significant decline in 5-FU clearance from day 1 to 5 of the first chemotherapy cycle.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0091270010396710">14</xref></sup> This important observation supports the hypothesis that 5-FU may influence its own metabolism, most likely through alterations in RNA function. Indeed, this decrease in 5-FU clearance was also found to be significantly correlated with treatment tolerability. However, this pilot study was conducted in a small group of patients, and the results still have to be confirmed in a larger cohort of patients.</p>
<p>The aim of the present study was to investigate the influence of 5-FU exposure on its own pharmacokinetics and its metabolite 5-FDHU and on treatment tolerability in CRC patients receiving 5-FU-based chemotherapy. These findings may be particularly relevant in poor-metabolizer patients whose drug clearance is critically reduced during repeated treatment cycles, thus explaining the severe late toxicities observed with 5-FU and its prodrugs.</p>
<sec id="section1-0091270010396710" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section2-0091270010396710">
<title>Patients</title>
<p>After signing an informed consent form, CRC patients of both sexes were enrolled in the present study as candidates to receive adjuvant treatment consisting of 5-FU as intravenous boluses (370-425 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) plus folic acid (20-100 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) for 5 consecutive days every 4 weeks for 6 cycles. Inclusion criteria included a metastases-negative abdomen computed tomography scan, radiograph or computed tomography scan of the thorax, an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status ≤ 2, a leukocyte count ≥ 3000/µL, an absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1000/µL, a platelet count ≥ 100,000/µL, a hemoglobin level ≥ 10 g/L, a serum bilirubin concentration ≤ 1.6 mg/dL, an aspartate aminotransferase and alanine aminotransferase ≤ 2.5 times normal values, and a serum creatinine level ≤ 1.6 mg/dL.</p>
<p>All patients were surgically treated for the primary tumor, while 4 patients (2 men and 2 women) received neoadjuvant radiochemotherapy before excision of the neoplasm. All patients were treated in the Oncology Department of Morgagni-Pierantoni Hospital in Forlì, Italy, from April 2003 to August 2006. The present study was approved by the local ethics committee.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0091270010396710">
<title>Blood Sampling and Laboratory Analyses</title>
<p>On days 1 and 5 of the first chemotherapy cycle, a basal 15-mL blood sample was collected in heparinized tubes, and 2 further samples (5 mL each) were taken 5 and 45 minutes after 5-FU administration, on the basis of a previous 5-FU pharmacokinetics study that validated a limited sampling approach (LSA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0091270010396710">15</xref></sup> Blood samples were centrifuged at 1000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 minutes and plasma stored at −20°C until measurement of 5-FU and 5-FDHU with a validated liquid chromatography diode-array detector method (ie, high-performance liquid chromatography).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0091270010396710">16</xref></sup> Briefly, plasma samples were prepared by liquid-liquid extraction (7 mL of diethyl ether/n-propanol, 84:16, vol/vol) and injected into the chromatographic system equipped with a diode-array detector (measurement and reference wavelengths of 215 and 360 nm, respectively). Separation of analytes was performed isocratically through a Hypersil C<sub>18</sub> stationary phase (25 × 4.6 cm, 10 µm) with retention times of 9.6 ± 0.2 and 11.2 ± 0.1 minutes for 5-FDHU and 5-FU, respectively. The method was proved to be linear (<italic>r</italic> = .999) over the entire range of concentrations up to the limit of quantitation of 5-FU (3.2 ng/mL) and 5-FDHU (16 ng/mL), with coefficients of variability lower than 10%, while precision and accuracy were in the range 0.2% to 13.0% and 96.2% to 105.9%, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0091270010396710">
<title>Pharmacokinetic Analyses</title>
<p>Pharmacokinetic analysis was performed by calculating the predicted area under the curve (AUC) values of 5-FU and 5-FDHU with the following equations:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0091270010396710">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0091270010396710">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>AU</mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>FU</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>mg</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>119</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>436</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>45</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>066</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>and</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0091270010396710">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0091270010396710">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>AU</mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>FDHU</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>mg</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>059</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>930</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>45</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>426</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where C<sub>5</sub> and C<sub>45</sub> represent the 5-FU and 5-FDHU plasma levels 5 and 45 min after drug administration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0091270010396710">15</xref></sup> In particular, both equations were obtained by adopting a backward stepwise regression comparing plasma concentrations measured at different time points (ie, from 5 to 180 minutes) after bolus injection, with the AUC value calculated on the basis of pharmacokinetic analysis in 80 CRC patients. The results of the backward stepwise regression analysis were used to derive the equations and their coefficients, which were successfully validated in a further 80 patients. In fact, the equations were able to predict the 5-FU and 5-FDHU AUC values with a low bias, good precision, and high correlation (<italic>r</italic> &gt; .950). 5-FU clearance was calculated by dividing the drug dose by the AUC value; the 5-FU:5-FDHU AUC ratio was also estimated.</p>
<p>To confirm the possible influence of drug administration on 5-FU disposition, a population pharmacokinetic analysis was performed with Monolix 3.1. Briefly, selection of the best structural model was obtained by considering the data, goodness of fit plots, plausibility and precision of parameter estimates, and the minimum objective function value.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0091270010396710">17</xref></sup> A 1-compartment model with first-order elimination was chosen as the first model. The distribution of interindividual random effects was assumed to be log-normal,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0091270010396710">17</xref></sup> while the residual error was initially described as an additive and proportional error model. The possible relationship among continuous/categorical covariates and pharmacokinetic parameters was evaluated on the basis of covariate range in the dataset, scientific interest, and possible mechanistic involvement in drug disposition. The best model was chosen when the considered covariates led to a reduction in objective function value, after which their effect on the model was assessed by the Wald test; otherwise, covariates were excluded from any further evaluation. Moreover, the goodness of the model was assayed by evaluating the individual parameter estimate shrinkage, since high shrinkage values were considered a consequence of uninformative data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0091270010396710">18</xref></sup> Finally, the interoccasion variability was introduced within the model with consideration of the 2 sampling days as distinct occasions (ie, the first and fifth days of the first chemotherapeutic cycle), and its effect on pharmacokinetic parameters was estimated. The same pharmacokinetic approach was adopted for 5-FDHU, choosing a 1-compartment model with first-order elimination, and the rate of metabolite formation was modeled as a zero- and first-order process. The reduction of objective function value and the shrinkage of the parameters evaluated, with covariate effects as assessed by the Wald test, were adopted to judge the goodness of the model.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0091270010396710">
<title>Treatment-Associated Toxicity</title>
<p>For each patient, all 5-FU-associated toxicities were recorded throughout the entire adjuvant chemotherapy course and graded according to the CTC-NCI score (ie, common toxicity criteria–National Cancer Institute; version 2.0). Patients were divided into 2 groups based on the toxicity grade (ie, grade ≤ 2 vs grade ≥ 3 CTC-NCI), not on the toxicity type.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0091270010396710">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics (mean, median, standard deviation, 95% confidence intervals [95% CI]) were used to analyse the present data, and normal distributions were assessed by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Receiver operating characteristic analysis was applied to identify the best predictive values for the main pharmacokinetic parameters. Next, results were matched with treatment-induced toxicities and appropriate statistical tests applied: Fisher exact test, paired and unpaired <italic>t</italic> tests, Mann-Whitney test, nonparametric paired Wilcoxon test. For all calculations, Microsoft Excel and Prism 4.0 (GraphPad, San Diego, California) were used and the level of significance set at <italic>P</italic> = .05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0091270010396710" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section8-0091270010396710">
<title>Patients</title>
<p>Of the 81 patients enrolled in the study, 48 were men and 33 were women (median age, 66.4 ± 8.0 years and 65.1 ± 9.3 years, respectively), and no significant differences were revealed between sexes for age, tumor stage, and lymph node involvement (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0091270010396710">Table I</xref>). The primary site of disease was the colon in 63 patients and the rectum in 18.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Table I</label>
<caption>
<p>Patient Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">All (N = 81)</th>
<th align="center">Men (n = 48)</th>
<th align="center">Women (n = 33)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">n (%)</th>
<th align="center">n (%)</th>
<th align="center">n (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age, years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0091270010396710">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>65.9 ± 8.5 (68)</td>
<td>66.4 ± 8.0 (68)</td>
<td>65.1 ± 9.3 (65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Neoadjuvant chemotherapy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>4 (5)</td>
<td>2 (4)</td>
<td>2 (6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>77 (95)</td>
<td>46 (96)</td>
<td>31 (94)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Site of disease</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Colon</td>
<td>63 (78)</td>
<td>38 (79)</td>
<td>25 (76)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rectum</td>
<td>18 (22)</td>
<td>10 (21)</td>
<td>8 (24)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">TNM<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0091270010396710">b</xref></sup> staging</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> N0</td>
<td>42 (52)</td>
<td>22 (46)</td>
<td>20 (61)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> N1</td>
<td>28 (35)</td>
<td>19 (40)</td>
<td>9 (27)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> N2</td>
<td>11 (14)</td>
<td>7 (15)</td>
<td>4 (12)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T2</td>
<td>8 (10)</td>
<td>6 (13)</td>
<td>2 (6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T3</td>
<td>61 (75)</td>
<td>37 (77)</td>
<td>24 (73)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T4</td>
<td>12 (15)</td>
<td>5 (10)</td>
<td>7 (21)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0091270010396710">
<label>a</label>
<p>Mean ± standard deviation (median).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0091270010396710">
<label>b</label>
<p>Tumor, lymph node, metastasis.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0091270010396710">
<title>Treatment Tolerability</title>
<p>Of 81 patients, 21 (26%, 9 men and 12 women) experienced severe 5-FU toxicities (grade 3 CTC-NCI) after the first treatment cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0091270010396710">Figure 1A</xref>). In particular, 13 (16%) experienced granulocytopenia (associated with lymphopenia in a single patient), plus 1 case of febrile neutropenia. Vomiting, diarrhea, and mucositis occurred in 1, 5, and 6 patients, respectively, while a single patient experienced paresthesia. Women more often appeared to experience severe toxicities, but these sex differences were not statistically significant. Furthermore, even though a 63-year-old man was hospitalized for a subocclusion after the first cycle, he recovered completely and continued adjuvant 5-FU therapy at a reduced dose. In 4 patients, the first treatment was interrupted because of severe toxicities (diarrhea alone or in combination with febrile neutropenia, vomiting, and mucositis in 2 women), a transient ischemic attack (a 78-year-old woman), or refusal (1 patient).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Incidence of treatment-associated toxicities in colorectal cancer patients after (A) the first cycle (n = 81) and (B) subsequent cycles of chemotherapy (n = 69) in men (white columns) and women (gray columns). N/V, nausea and vomiting; D, diarrhea; M, mucositis, Hem, hematological toxicities; Other, other toxicities (i.e., paresthesia, asthenia).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>After subsequent chemotherapy cycles, 32 patients (42%, 18 men and 14 women) experienced severe toxicities of granulocytopenia (n = 22, 29%) and diarrhea (n = 10, 13%), especially after the second cycle, with asthenia/anorexia, mucositis, and hand-foot syndrome affecting 6 patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0091270010396710">Figure 1B</xref>). Eight patients discontinued therapy (7 men and 1 woman) due to severe toxicity during the second and third treatment cycles (3 and 5 patients, respectively). The 5-FU dose was reduced by a median of 20% in 12 additional cases and by 30% in a 53-year-old man who had severe diarrhea after the third cycle. Finally, the moderate toxicities (grade ≤ 2 CTC-NCI) reported in the remaining patients did not hinder subsequent treatments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0091270010396710">
<title>Pharmacokinetics of 5-FU and 5-FDHU</title>
<p>The plasma profiles of 5-FU and 5-FDHU were evaluated in all 81 patients. On day 1, the AUC values of 5-FU and 5-FDHU were 8.16 ± 9.88 and 11.24 ± 7.28 hxmg/L, respectively, suggesting high patient variability. The mean clearance was 74.83 ± 31.61 L/h/m<sup>2</sup>, and no significant sex-related pharmacokinetic differences were observed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0091270010396710">Table II</xref>). Interestingly, the 5-FU/5-FDHU AUC ratio was lower for men than for women, but this difference was not significant, probably due to the large interpatient variability. On day 5, there were no significant differences in 5-FU AUC for all patients nor for the male and female subgroups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0091270010396710">Table II</xref>). In the same patients, the mean 5-FDHU AUC value decreased by approximately 10% compared to day 1. More interesting, a 15% decrease in 5-FU clearance was observed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0091270010396710">Table II</xref>), which was significant for all patients and for men but not women, even if a trend was noticed (<italic>P</italic> = .096). Furthermore, plasma concentrations 5 and 45 minutes after bolus injection differed significantly on day 1 and day 5 for both 5-FU and its metabolite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0091270010396710">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Table II</label>
<caption>
<p>Pharmacokinetic Parameters of 5-FU and 5-FDHU on Day 1 and Day 5 of the First Chemotherapy Cycle</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="4">5-FU</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">5-FDHU</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">5-FU:5-FDHU</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">AUC (hxmg/L)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Clearance (L/h/m<sup>2</sup>)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">AUC (hxmg/L)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">AUC Ratio</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>All patients</td>
<td>8.16 ± 9.88</td>
<td>8.00 ± 9.25</td>
<td>74.83 ± 31.61</td>
<td>62.64 ± 20.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091270010396710">*</xref></td>
<td>11.24 ± 7.28</td>
<td>10.10 ± 3.70</td>
<td>0.68 ± 0.84</td>
<td>0.88 ± 1.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> n = 81</td>
<td>(5.01)</td>
<td>(6.20)</td>
<td>(74.22)</td>
<td>(61.55)</td>
<td>(8.87)</td>
<td>(8.86)</td>
<td>(0.47)</td>
<td>(0.63)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Males</td>
<td>8.01 ± 10.45</td>
<td>7.78 ± 10.03</td>
<td>77.58 ± 31.94</td>
<td>64.43 ± 18.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091270010396710">*</xref></td>
<td>11.93 ± 9.00</td>
<td>10.38 ± 3.93</td>
<td>0.57 ± 0.63</td>
<td>0.85 ± 1.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> n = 48</td>
<td>(5.02)</td>
<td>(6.095)</td>
<td>(77.65)</td>
<td>(64.35)</td>
<td>(9.31)</td>
<td>(8.84)</td>
<td>(0.45)</td>
<td>(0.63)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Females</td>
<td>8.38 ± 9.14</td>
<td>8.32 ± 8.14</td>
<td>70.82 ± 31.18</td>
<td>60.06 ± 22.93</td>
<td>10.28 ± 3.76</td>
<td>9.69 ± 3.35</td>
<td>0.84 ± 1.06</td>
<td>0.91 ± 0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> n = 33</td>
<td>(4.91)</td>
<td>(6.51)</td>
<td>(70.84)</td>
<td>(60.42)</td>
<td>(8.78)</td>
<td>(8.87)</td>
<td>(0.52)</td>
<td>(0.68)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0091270010396710">
<p>Results are expressed as mean ± standard deviation. Numbers within parentheses represent the median values. AUC, area under the curve (time concentration); 5-FU, 5-fluorouracil; 5-FDHU, 5-fluoro-5,6-dihydrouracil.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0091270010396710">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Plots of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU; A) and its metabolite 5-fluoro-5,6-dihydrouracil (5-FDHU; B), 5 and 45 minutes after drug administration on day 1 (D1) and day 5 (D5) of the first chemotherapy cycle. The differences between paired sampling time points for both 5-FU and its metabolite were found to be statistically significant, as assessed by the Wilcoxon paired test. Symbols and bars, median and interquartile range values.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The best structural model for population pharmacokinetic analysis was a 2-compartment model with linear elimination (model 3, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0091270010396710">Table III</xref>). Results of the final model showed large interpatient variability, especially in terms of intercompartmental clearance and volume of peripheral compartment, which were poorly informative, as judged by the high values of shrinkage (&gt; 70%). The exploratory analysis of all covariates, both continuous (age, weight, and creatinine clearance) and categorical (sex), led to the high reduction in objective function value (model 10, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0091270010396710">Table III</xref>), which was further reduced when interoccasion variability on clearance and the effect of weight on central compartment volume (V1) were considered (model 28, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0091270010396710">Table III</xref>). With these characteristics, the estimated interoccasion variability of drug clearance accounted for −15%, and this effect was estimated to be significant by the Wald test (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .046), hence confirming the pharmacokinetic results obtained with the LSA On the contrary, although the effect of weight on V1 was not significant (Wald test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; .05), it ameliorated the performance of the final model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0091270010396710">Table III</xref>). Furthermore, the decrease in drug clearance was confirmed when plasma concentrations of 5-FU were analyzed by the same model but on 2 different occasions. In fact, when covariates and the effect of weight on V1 were considered, the reduction of 5-FU clearance from day 1 to day 5 accounted for 18%.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Table III</label>
<caption>
<p>Base and Covariate Model Building</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Model</th>
<th align="center">Description</th>
<th align="center">OFV</th>
<th align="center">ΔOFV*</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Interindividual variability on CL, V1 with first-order elimination</td>
<td>1612</td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>As model 1 but zero-order elimination</td>
<td>1637</td>
<td>+25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Interindividual variability on CL, V1, intercompartmental clearance, V2, with first-order elimination</td>
<td>1290</td>
<td>−322</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>As model 3 but zero-order elimination</td>
<td>1763</td>
<td>+473</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>As model 3 but add sex, age, weight, creatinine clearance</td>
<td>1166</td>
<td>−124</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td>As model 10 but add effect of interoccasion variability on CL</td>
<td>1063</td>
<td>−103</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td>As model 23 but add effect of weight on V1</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>−63</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0091270010396710">
<p>OFV, objective function value; ΔOFV, change of OFV from the previous model; CL, clearance; V1 and V2, volume of central and peripheral compartment, respectively.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Finally, the best model for 5-FDHU was a 1- compartment model with linear elimination and first-order production of the metabolite. When covariates were added and the interoccasion variability evaluated, metabolite formation was significantly influenced by the occasion (<italic>P</italic> = .0015 Wald test), with a 20% reduction in absorption constant (0.13 ± 0.10 vs 0.11 ± 0.08 h<sup>−1</sup> on the first and fifth day, respectively).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0091270010396710">
<title>Pharmacokinetics and Treatment Tolerability</title>
<p>Approximately 1 in 4 patients experienced severe toxicities after the first treatment cycle (grade ≥ 3 CTC-NCI), which was correlated with a significantly lower 5-FU clearance value on day 1 compared to those who tolerated the treatment well (grade ≤ 2 CTC-NCI; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0091270010396710">Table IV</xref>). Both groups reported an approximate decrease of 15% in 5-FU clearance from day 1 to 5, but this difference was only significant for the moderate toxicity group. Based on receiver operating characteristic analysis, the clearance AUC values of days 1 and 5 were estimated to be 0.753 and 0.819, respectively, with cutoff values of 74 and 60 L/h/m<sup>2</sup> having a better likelihood ratio and sensitivity (&gt; 80%) to predict toxicities.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Table IV</label>
<caption>
<p>Pharmacokinetic Parameters of 5-FU and 5-FDHU According to Treatment Tolerability on Day 1 and Day 5 of the First Chemotherapy Cycle</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="4">5-FU</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">5-FDHU</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">5-FU:5-FDHU</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">AUC (hxmg/L)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Clearance (L/h/m<sup>2</sup>)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">AUC (hxmg/L)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">AUC Ratio</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Toxicity</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Grade ≤ 2</td>
<td>7.48 ± 9.61</td>
<td>6.84 ± 6.69</td>
<td>79.08 ± 31.80</td>
<td>66.61 ± 20.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0091270010396710">*</xref></td>
<td>11.44 ± 8.06</td>
<td>10.13 ± 3.86</td>
<td>0.68 ± 0.94</td>
<td>0.71 ± 0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (n = 60)</td>
<td>(4.80)</td>
<td>(5.62)</td>
<td>(78.33)</td>
<td>(66.61)</td>
<td>(8.60)</td>
<td>(8.81)</td>
<td>(0.46)</td>
<td>(0.58)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0091270010396710">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>ns</td>
<td>ns</td>
<td>.040</td>
<td>.002</td>
<td>ns</td>
<td>ns</td>
<td>ns</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade ≥ 3</td>
<td>10.13 ± 10.62</td>
<td>11.59 ± 14.27</td>
<td>62.66 ± 28.37</td>
<td>50.27 ± 15.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0091270010396710">**</xref></td>
<td>10.61 ± 4.10</td>
<td>10.01 ± 3.23</td>
<td>0.68 ± 0.45</td>
<td>1.38 ± 2.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (n = 21)</td>
<td>(6.43)</td>
<td>(7.77)</td>
<td>(66.10)</td>
<td>(66.10)</td>
<td>(10.34)</td>
<td>(9.61)</td>
<td>(0.56)</td>
<td>(0.84)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0091270010396710">
<p>Grades per common toxicity criteria–National Cancer Institute. Results expressed as mean ± standard deviation. Numbers within parentheses represent the median values. AUC, area under the curve (time concentration); 5-FU, 5-fluorouracil; 5-FDHU, 5-fluoro-5,6-dihydrouracil.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0091270010396710">
<label>a</label>
<p>Paired <italic>t</italic> test; grade ≤ 2 vs grade ≥ 3 toxicities.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0091270010396710">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> = .0072 (day 1 vs day 5; paired <italic>t</italic> test).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-0091270010396710">
<label>**</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> = .077 (day 1 vs day 5; paired <italic>t</italic> test)</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Twelve patients did not complete the planned 6 cycles of adjuvant treatment and were excluded from further analysis because of insufficient follow-up for late toxicity reporting. The 5-FU clearance values of day 1 were significant for the remaining 69 patients who completed the treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0091270010396710">Table V</xref>). In particular, patients who experienced a grade ≤ 2 CTC-NCI toxicity and those who suffered from severe adverse reactions had significantly different mean clearance values on days 1 and 5. Interestingly, receiver operating characteristic analysis for cycles 2 through 6 showed similar curve areas (0.789 and 0.723 on days 1 and 5, respectively) to those reported for the first chemotherapy cycle, although 5-FU clearance cutoff values had to be increased to 80 and 65 L/h/m<sup>2</sup> to achieve the same sensitivity (&gt; 80%)</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0091270010396710" position="float">
<label>Table V</label>
<caption>
<p>5-FU Clearance (L/h/m<sup>2</sup>) According to Treatment Tolerability on Day 1 and Day 5 of Cycles 2 Through 6 of Chemotherapy</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0091270010396710" xlink:href="10.1177_0091270010396710-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Toxicity</th>
<th align="center">Day 1</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0091270010396710">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Day 5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Grade ≤ 2 (n = 38)</td>
<td>82.91 ± 33.93 (81.89)</td>
<td>.029<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0091270010396710">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>69.16 ± 20.29 (66.61)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>P</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn13-0091270010396710">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>.039<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0091270010396710">d</xref></sup></td>
<td/>
<td>.032<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0091270010396710">d</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade ≥ 3 (n = 31)</td>
<td>66.23 ± 31.33 (66.41)</td>
<td>ns<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0091270010396710">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>58.96 ± 17.64 (62.04)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn10-0091270010396710">
<p>Grades per common toxicity criteria–National Cancer Institute. Results expressed as mean ± standard deviation. Numbers within parentheses represent the median. 5-FU, 5-fluorouracil.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn11-0091270010396710">
<label>a</label>
<p>Day 1 vs day 5.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn12-0091270010396710">
<label>b</label>
<p>Paired <italic>t</italic> test.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn13-0091270010396710">
<label>c</label>
<p>Grade ≤ 2 vs grade ≥ 3 toxicities.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn14-0091270010396710">
<label>d</label>
<p>Unpaired <italic>t</italic> test.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0091270010396710" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study aimed to evaluate the influence of 5-FU on its own pharmacokinetics in CRC patients undergoing adjuvant chemotherapy and to correlate this with treatment tolerability. Previous studies have demonstrated an association between the pharmacokinetic characteristics of 5-FU and 5-FDHU and treatment tolerability in CRC patients given both adjuvant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0091270010396710">14</xref></sup> or first-line chemotherapy,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0091270010396710">19</xref></sup> underscoring the clinical role of phenotyping patients through the measurement of drug levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0091270010396710">20</xref></sup> The pharmacokinetic approach to identify patients at high risk of developing severe or life-threatening toxicities has been extensively studied through the administration of a test dose<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0091270010396710">7</xref></sup> or by monitoring 5-FU plasma levels during continuous infusion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0091270010396710">19</xref></sup> In the present study, patients who experienced severe first cycle toxicities had 5-FU clearance values significantly lower than those who tolerated the treatment well, confirming the importance of pharmacokinetic profiling. Twelve patients abandoned chemotherapy before completing the sixth cycle, either because of severe toxicities or because of refusal despite the good tolerability experienced. For the remaining 69 patients, there was a significant association between 5-FU clearance and treatment tolerability, irrespective of the treatment cycle considered.</p>
<p>The present study aimed to evaluate the possible influence of 5-FU administration on drug pharmacokinetics, with a mechanism of action based on the incorporation of its activated metabolites within RNA, leading us to hypothesize that the drug could impair its own metabolism due to the inactivation of DPD activity. From day 1 to day 5, there was a significant reduction in clearance, approximately 15%, and this result was confirmed by a population pharmacokinetic analysis evaluating the effect of interoccasion variability on drug clearance. This reduction was present in all patients, irrespective of whether they experienced moderate or severe toxicities, suggesting that whatever the 5-FU clearance on day 1, the drug can impair its own pharmacokinetics. This was also true for all subsequent treatment cycles, with results showing the same group differences (ie, day 1 vs day 5 dose, grade ≤ 2 vs grade ≥ 3), although mean values were higher than those obtained for first-cycle tolerability. For instance, severe first-cycle toxicities were associated with mean day 5 clearance values of 50 L/h/m<sup>2</sup>, but this increased to 59 L/h/m<sup>2</sup> for late toxicities, which in turn required a dose reduction in 12 out of 31 patients. These results suggest that patients with higher day 1 and 5 clearance values have a lower risk of severe toxicities, not only after the first cycle, but also throughout the entire chemotherapy course. Although the limits and factors (ie, the wide interpatient variability) affected the data as suggested by the pharmacokinetic population modeling, receiver operating characteristic analysis confirmed the present hypothesis, showing that clearance cutoff values increased by 5 to 6 L/h/m<sup>2</sup> when late toxicities were taken into account. Therefore, the present results suggest that some patients— specifically, those who tolerate the first cycle well but are at risk of late severe toxicities—may be identified on the basis of drug clearance values at the end of the first cycle of chemotherapy, thereby opening up the possibility to prevent severe adverse drug reactions. Finally, 5-FDHU AUC values decreased from day 1 to day 5, further confirming the drug’s influence on its own metabolism, even if this difference was not statistically significant, probably because of the large interpatient variation caused by multiple yet undefined factors. However, it is worth noting that previous studies support results of the present work. In fact, in a former study, McLeod and colleagues demonstrated that in patients receiving 5-FU according to the de Gramont schedule, DPD activity in peripheral blood mononuclear cells was significantly lower at the end of treatment; they hypothesized that the mechanism “may involve alterations in mRNA translation and/or conformation as a result of incorporation of a fraudulent fluorinated uracil moiety.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0091270010396710">21</xref></sup> This hypothesis was further supported by Kashima and coworkers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0091270010396710">22</xref></sup> and demonstrated by Matsusaka et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0091270010396710">23</xref></sup> who observed the incorporation of 5-FU into RNA, especially when the drug was administered following a schedule (320 mg/m<sup>2</sup> as a short 10-minute intravenous infusion for 5 consecutive days) similar to that investigated in our study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0091270010396710">23</xref></sup> Finally, identical results were obtained by Hoshino and coworkers 2 years later.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0091270010396710">24</xref></sup> Therefore, all these results suggest that 5-FU inhibition of DPD activity is likely based on an alteration of <italic>DPYD</italic> gene expression and, hence, protein synthesis.</p>
<p>Active areas of research include prevention of severe toxicities and optimization of drug doses. However, the availability of different drug administration schedules and the lack of well-defined therapeutic ranges remain a major hurdle to the complete achievement of these goals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0091270010396710">25</xref></sup> To overcome these problems, combination approaches have been proposed, such as pharmacogenetics and patient phenotyping (ie, DPD activity measurement, 5-FU test dose, plasma U:UH<sub>2</sub> ratio measurement).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0091270010396710">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0091270010396710">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>Finally, although the data presented in this study report on a chemotherapy schedule less frequently used in clinical practice, the present work provides evidence that fluoropyrimidines are capable of interfering with their own metabolism and, hence, their tolerability and this approach may be applied to other treatment schedules (ie, continuous infusions).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0091270010396710">25</xref></sup></p>
<p>In conclusion, the present study demonstrated that 5-FU administration is associated with a significant reduction in its own clearance, whose values at the start and end of the first chemotherapy cycle are associated with treatment tolerability throughout the entire adjuvant chemotherapy course.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>We thank Dr Ian Seymour for help with editing the manuscript.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Financial disclosure: None declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0091270010396710">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2002</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0091270010396710">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hind</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tappenden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tumur</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The use of irinotecan, oxaliplatin and raltitrexed for the treatment of advanced colorectal cancer: systematic review and economic evaluation</article-title>. <source>Health Technol Assess</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>iii</fpage>-<lpage>ix</lpage>, <fpage>xi</fpage>-<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0091270010396710">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sowa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Continuous infusion of 5-fluorouracil with versus without low-dose, consecutive administration of cisplatin in advanced colorectal cancer: a prospective randomized phase II study</article-title>. <source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0091270010396710">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danesi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between plasma concentrations of 5-fluorouracil and 5-fluoro-5,6-dihydrouracil and toxicity of 5-fluorouracil infusions in cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>588</fpage>-<lpage>593</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0091270010396710">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Oral uracil-tegafur plus leucovorin versus fluorouracil bolus plus leucovorin for advanced colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of five randomized controlled trials [published online ahead of print December 28, 2009]</article-title>. <source>Colorectal Dis</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0091270010396710">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rask</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koru-Sengul</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dhesy-Thind</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Generalizability of toxicity data from oncology clinical trials to clinical practice: toxicity of irinotecan-based regimens in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Curr Oncol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0091270010396710">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bocci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barbara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vannozzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A pharmacokinetic-based test to prevent severe 5-fluorouracil toxicity</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0091270010396710">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ciccolini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A rapid and inexpensive method for anticipating severe toxicity to fluorouracil and fluorouracil-based chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>678</fpage>-<lpage>685</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0091270010396710">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boisdron-Celle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Remaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>5-Fluorouracil-related severe toxicity: a comparison of different methods for the pretherapeutic detection of dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase deficiency</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>249</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0091270010396710">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Low-dose cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil in combination can repress increased gene expression of cellular resistance determinants to themselves</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>2620</fpage>-<lpage>2628</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0091270010396710">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brabender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Downregulation of TS, DPD, ERCC1, GST-Pi, EGFR, and HER2 gene expression after neoadjuvant three-modality treatment in patients with esophageal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>200</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0091270010396710">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aschele</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sobrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faderan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bertino</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Novel mechanism(s) of resistance to 5-fluorouracil in human colon cancer (HCT-8) sublines following exposure to two different clinically relevant dose schedules</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1855</fpage>-<lpage>1864</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0091270010396710">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aschele</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Debernardis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bandelloni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Thymidylate synthase protein expression in colorectal cancer metastases predicts for clinical outcome to leucovorin-modulated bolus or infusional 5-fluorouracil but not methotrexate-modulated bolus 5-fluorouracil</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1882</fpage>-<lpage>1892</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0091270010396710">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vannozzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danesi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of 5-fluorouracil on dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase activity in colorectal cancer patients</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings from the 93rd annual meeting of the American Association for Cancer Research</conf-name>; <conf-date>April 6-10, 2002</conf-date>; <conf-loc>San Francisco, CA</conf-loc>; <comment>Abstract 1053</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0091270010396710">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danesi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vannozzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Limited sampling model for the analysis of 5-fluorouracil pharmacokinetics in adjuvant chemotherapy for colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0091270010396710">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danesi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ciofi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Improved analysis of 5-fluorouracil and 5,6-dihydro-5-fluorouracil by HPLC with diode array detection for determination of cellular dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase activity and pharmacokinetic profiling</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>362</fpage>-<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0091270010396710">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gibiansky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Population pharmacokinetics of eltrombopag in healthy subjects and patients with chronic idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura [published online ahead of print July 27, 2010]</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharmacol</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0091270010396710">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tarning</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGready</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindergardh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Population pharmacokinetics of lumefantrine in pregnant women treated with artemether-lumefantrine for uncomplicated <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> malaria</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>3837</fpage>-<lpage>3846</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0091270010396710">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gamelin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Individual fluorouracil dose adjustment based on pharmacokinetic follow-up compared with conventional dosage: results of a multicenter randomized trial of patients with metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2099</fpage>-<lpage>2105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0091270010396710">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salamone</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetically guided dose adjustment of 5-fluorouracil: a rational approach to improving therapeutic outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>1543</fpage>-<lpage>1552</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0091270010396710">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sludden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lock</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawksworth</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Autoregulation of 5-fluorouracil metabolism</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1623</fpage>-<lpage>1627</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0091270010396710">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kashima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of 5-fluorouracil and epidermal growth factor on cell growth and dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase regulation in human uterine cervical carcinoma SKG-IIIb cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>821</fpage>-<lpage>825</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0091270010396710">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsusaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagareda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does cisplatin (CDDP) function as a modulator of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) antitumor action? A study based on a clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0091270010396710">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shirakusa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects on DNA and RNA after the administration of two different schedules of 5-fluorouracil in colorectal cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>-<lpage>652</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0091270010396710">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ploylearmsaeng</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuhr</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How may anticancer chemotherapy with fluorouracil be individualised?</article-title> <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>-<lpage>592</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0091270010396710">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bocci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barbara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics, a main actor in a many-sided approach to severe 5-FU toxicity prediction</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0091270010396710">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Del Re</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Schaik</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase polymorphisms and fluoropyrimidine toxicity: ready for routine clinical application within personalized medicine?</article-title> <source>EPMA J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>