<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NSQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnsq</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nurs Sci Q</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nursing Science Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0894-3184</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7409</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0894318413477145</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0894318413477145</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Columns</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Theoretical Concerns</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Living Quality</article-title>
<subtitle>A Humanbecoming Phenomenon</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>Rosemarie Rizzo</given-names></name>
<degrees>RN; PhD; FAAN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0894318413477145">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0894318413477145"><label>1</label>Distinguished Professor Emeritus, Loyola University Chicago</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0894318413477145">Sandra Schmidt Bunkers, RN, PhD, FAAN, Professor of Nursing, South Dakota State University, 1119 Plum Creek Road, Sioux Falls, SD 57105 Email: <email>tsbunkers@sio.midco.net</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>111</fpage>
<lpage>115</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The purpose of this article is to set forth the humanbecoming paradigm and the phenomenon living quality, which better expresses the notion of quality of life from this paradigmatic perspective. The three inherent core knowings of living quality are described and explained in light of the community change concepts. Living quality with sciencing and living the art of humanbecoming are also discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>community change concepts</kwd>
<kwd>humanbecoming</kwd>
<kwd>humanbecoming paradigm</kwd>
<kwd>living quality</kwd>
<kwd>Parse</kwd>
<kwd>quality of life</kwd>
<kwd>sciencing</kwd>
<kwd>silence</kwd>
<kwd>wisdom</kwd>
<kwd>witness</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The term quality of life is ubiquitous; many scholars from various disciplines write about the importance of it. The literature is rife with information that focuses on attributes, variables, and categories, and ways to measure and enhance physical, psychological, social, and spiritual well-being. The ontology guiding this notion of quality of life posits the human as a biopsychosocialspiritual being, and the research studies are generally quantitative and related to functional status, satisfaction, and role performance in persons with various disease conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0894318413477145">Bowling &amp; Gabriel, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0894318413477145">Chopra &amp; Kamal, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0894318413477145">Dimsdale &amp; Baum, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0894318413477145">Dorfman, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0894318413477145">Franzen-Dahlin &amp; Laska, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0894318413477145">Hu, Summers, Turnbull, &amp; Zuna, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0894318413477145">Lin, Yen, &amp; Fetzer, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0894318413477145">Malott &amp; McAiney, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0894318413477145">Pan &amp; Tsai, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0894318413477145">Samuel, Rillotta, &amp; Brown, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0894318413477145">Shin &amp; Shin, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0894318413477145">Turner, 1993</xref>). Only some qualitative nursing research studies and conceptualizations related to the importance of quality of life focus on direct information in the language of the individual (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0894318413477145">Davis &amp; Cannava, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0894318413477145">Fisher &amp; Mitchell, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0894318413477145">Mitchell &amp; Jonas-Simpson, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0894318413477145">Parse, 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0894318413477145">1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0894318413477145">1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0894318413477145">1994b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0894318413477145">1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0894318413477145">1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0894318413477145">1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0894318413477145">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0894318413477145">2007a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0894318413477145">2007b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0894318413477145">Pilkington &amp; Mitchell, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0894318413477145">Robinson, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0894318413477145">Smith, 1990</xref>; and others).</p>
<p>The construct <italic>quality of life</italic> is linguistically static; it refers to a once-and-for-all designation arrived at through the use of digital instruments designed to ascertain an individual’s overall health status. The instruments do not discover a personal description of quality of life in the individual’s own words. The instruments yield a snapshot of a moment that does not reflect the human as a whole-in-motion. The whole-in-motion refers to the everchanging moments that arise with the living experiences of being human.</p>
<p>In 1994 Parse wrote that from a humanbecoming perspective only the individual living the life can personally describe quality of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0894318413477145">Parse, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0894318413477145">1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0894318413477145">1994b</xref>). Since <italic>qual</italic> means whatness or core, who could better describe the whatness of a life but the individual? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0894318413477145">Parse (1994b)</xref> said, “Quality of life as the incarnation of lived experiences is the indivisible human’s view on living moment to moment as the changing health patterns of shifting perspectives weave the fabric of life through the human-universe connectedness” (p. 17). The purpose of this article is to posit a reconceptualization of <italic>quality of life</italic> as <italic>living quality.</italic></p>
<p>The change to <italic>living quality</italic> better expresses the notion that quality or whatness is everchanging and cannot be measured by labels that reflect only a moment in time. Furthermore, this change is logical in light of the evolution of humanbecoming as a unique paradigm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0894318413477145">Figure 1</xref>). A paradigm shift adds a totally new view to a discipline; it does not just reflect a change within the traditional system but, rather, is a transformation of all significant concepts (like quality of life) that changes the structure of the whole. The humanbecoming paradigm is just such a transformation; it deviates significantly from the totality and simultaneity paradigms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0894318413477145">Parse, 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0894318413477145">1998</xref>). It arose with the introduction of the meaning of <italic>humanbecoming</italic> as one word and <italic>humanuniverse</italic> as one word; with the specification of the foregrounding <italic>postulates</italic> (illimitability, paradox, freedom, and mystery); with the new conceptualization, <italic>becoming visible-invisible becoming of the emerging now</italic>; and with the epistemological change to universal <italic>living</italic> experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0894318413477145">Parse, 2007b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0894318413477145">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0894318413477145">2012</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0894318413477145" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Paradigms of the discipline of nursing.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0894318413477145-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The change to one word for humanbecoming and humanuniverse makes explicit the idea of indivisibility. The foregrounding postulates permeate all of the principles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0894318413477145">Figure 2</xref>), specifying the inherent unbounded knowings, contextually construed liberation, pattern preferences, and the unexplainable of humanbecoming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0894318413477145">Parse, 2007b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0894318413477145">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0894318413477145">2012</xref>). The new conceptualization, becoming visible-invisible becoming of the emerging now (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0894318413477145">Parse, 2012</xref>), clarifies the idea of all-at-onceness, which is the whatness that humans are living. “Becoming visible-invisible becoming is the living moment that brings to the fore the idea that meaning changes with each unfolding living experience incarnating remembering-prospecting all-at-once” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0894318413477145">Parse, 2012</xref>, p. 44).The epistemological change from universal lived to universal living experience clarifies that the personal description of an experience encompasses all-at-once remembering-prospecting as it is appearing in the now moment. This change distinguishes the humanbecoming methods from all other qualitative methods of inquiry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0894318413477145">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0894318413477145">Figure 2</xref>). These aforementioned changes forecast a new paradigm, since the ideas remove humanbecoming from the confines of the metaparadigm and other paradigms in nursing. It is a natural consequence of paradigm evolution, then, to conceptualize anew key constructs, like quality of life.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0894318413477145" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Humanbecoming assumptions, postulates, principles, concepts, and paradoxes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0894318413477145-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section1-0894318413477145">
<title>Living Quality</title>
<p><italic>Living quality</italic> refers to the individual’s core whatness, the stuff of a life. What is the whatness? It is the living community that each individual august presence is—the humanuniverse cocreation with predecessors, contemporaries, and successors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0894318413477145">Parse, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0894318413477145">1994b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0894318413477145">1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0894318413477145">1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0894318413477145">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0894318413477145">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0894318413477145">2007a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0894318413477145">2007b</xref>). This means that humans are the cocreated histories of who they are becoming at the moment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0894318413477145">Parse, 2003</xref>). The histories are all of the humanuniverse experiences that individuals are living as community. Individuals are continually writing their personal biographies for which nothing is foreclosed, when considering the humanbecoming postulates: illimitability, paradox, freedom, and mystery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0894318413477145">Parse, 2007b</xref>). There is only the indivisible, unpredictable, everchanging moment-to-moment moving-initiating, anchoring-shifting, and pondering-shaping, cocreating living quality as the core whatness in the emerging now of everyday situations. Moving-initiating, anchoring-shifting, and pondering-shaping are ways of living quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0894318413477145">Parse, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0894318413477145">2003</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0894318413477145">
<title>Core Knowings of Living Quality</title>
<p>Living quality has three inherent core knowings, fortifying wisdom, discerning witness, and penetrating silence. The construct <italic>living quality</italic> with its three inherent core knowings (fortifying wisdom, discerning witness, and penetrating silence), then, is the ongoing incarnating of moment-to-moment indivisible, unpredictable, everchanging meaning arising with the becoming visible-invisible becoming of the emerging now. The core knowings are lived with moving-initiating, anchoring-shifting, and pondering-shaping. Inherent core knowings comprise the whatness of the human breathing forth the uniqueness of living quality.</p>
<sec id="section3-0894318413477145">
<title>Fortifying Wisdom</title>
<p><italic>Fortifying wisdom</italic> is invigorating sagacity shown with the individual as community cocreating what is important in the moment. The individual as community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0894318413477145">Parse, 2003</xref>) is living a chosen quality while removing barriers and initiating anew in the day-to-day. Fortifying wisdom dwells with the individual’s explicit-tacit knowings, as the individual is moving and at once initiating ways to strengthen personal value priorities. In living the explicit-tacit knowings of the core whatness, meanings change moment to moment and are shown in the individual’s unfolding speech, silence, movement, and stillness.</p>
<p>The whatness of the emerging now surfaces as the individual with wisdom is earthing and unearthing personal knowings, as living with diverse currents offers opportunities and at once restrictions for moments of buoyancy in the mist of ambiguity. For the individual, living quality is fraught with the intensity of calm-turbulent rhythms that invite vigilance as the shifting winds of the unexpected cocreate different familiar-unfamiliar patterns. Individuals with their inherent fortifying wisdom cocreate their quality as they forge onward with persistently propelling while navigating the sure-unsure pressures of everydayness. Living quality is shown with and without words revealing and at once concealing the meaning of the moment. It is the individual’s wisdom that inspires, pushes, and configures patterns that fortify the climbing, immersing, drifting, soaring, and swingshifting as ways of moving on with what is the becoming visible-invisible becoming of the emerging now. The patterns of fortifying wisdom resolutely affirm the stuff of living that is the individual’s quality at the moment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0894318413477145">
<title>Discerning Witness</title>
<p><italic>Discerning witness</italic> is cautiously attending to and distancing from that which enables and limits opportunities in choosing the whatness of personal living. It is with the anchoring and at once shifting that the individual as community lives a chosen quality with persisting-diversifying. Witnessing with others, ideas, objects, and events is a way of incarnating an individual’s valued projects. Engagement with these projects cocreates living quality at the moment, identifying that which is irreplaceable about the individual. What is irreplaceable about an individual is shown in valued projects and relationships; it is how the individual is continually coming to be known. Discerning witness is transforming as the individual’s contextually construed choices cocreate the living of preferred patterns that emerge with unbounded unexplainable knowings.</p>
<p>An individual chooses ways of living that mean quality in delighting in and at once giving up cherished somethings; thus discerning witness is shown with savoring the treasured and often sacrificing the desired. The way that individuals describe living quality with and without words shows a reverence for what is significant and reveals and at once conceals personal value priorities. With the individual’s discerning, what is highly valued is anchored in tradition with conforming, yet not-conforming as the certainty-uncertainty of the emerging now illuminates the familiar-unfamiliar in new light. The individual is always choosing, and even with the ever-present discerning, the choosings are without explicitly knowing all of the consequences. Discerning witness moves individuals at every unfolding moment in anchoring with persisting amid shifting with diversifying in cautiously attending with the everchanging. With discerning witness the individual as community is living a chosen quality with what comes up with the becoming visible-invisible becoming of the emerging now.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0894318413477145">
<title>Penetrating Silence</title>
<p><italic>Penetrating silence</italic> is piercing quiet in solemn stillness. It is the perfect intimacy of the unutterable that permeates the whatness of being. In the depth of being the echoes of stillness penetrate the reality of the moment. Penetrating silence incarnates the pondering and at once shaping of living quality. With pondering-shaping the individual as community is living a chosen quality while contemplating and at once configuring anew in poised quietude.</p>
<p>Living quality emerges with ruminating with illimitable options as the penetrating silence of explicit-tacit knowings arises with the possibles surfacing in the emerging now. It is the meaning of the moment as the individual composes value priorities in dialoguing with and listening to others. The individual’s quality is cocreated with others, ideas, objects, and events that enable and limit choices, while revealing and concealing who the individual is becoming. Living quality as described by individuals is their truth for the moment that incarnates all choosings as shown in their patterns of speech, silence, movement, and stillness. In the depth of penetrating silence is the inevitable embracing of the whatness of living. The unutterable of the illimitable spawns <italic>there―with</italic> the silence where the awesomeness of becoming penetrates living quality.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0894318413477145">
<title>Living Quality: Sciencing and Living the Art of Humanbecoming</title>
<p>With the perspective of the humanbecoming paradigm the conceptualization <italic>living quality</italic> is set forth here as a guide to sciencing and living the art of humanbecoming. In <italic>sciencing</italic> to discover structures of living quality, the researcher selects phenomena arising from the inherent core knowings (fortifying wisdom, discerning witness, and penetrating silence). The phenomena include universal living experiences such as feeling strong, feeling unsure, doing the right thing, choosing to be silent, creating something new, being vigilant, being cautious, being surprised, trusting another, sacrificing something important, feeling delighted, respecting another, making a critical decision, feeling sad, suffering, feeling contented, feeling alone, and many others.</p>
<p>When <italic>living the art</italic> of humanbecoming, nurses and other health professionals who wish to know about the living quality of a person, the key question is <italic>what is important to you now</italic>? This question honors the august presence of the person and incarnates the questioner’s own humanbecoming value priorities, which include respecting that the person knows the way and not labeling or criticizing the person’s choices but, rather, bearing witness as the person cocreates becoming.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0894318413477145">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The humanbecoming paradigm posited here as a contribution to the ongoing evolution of nursing knowledge, guides sciencing, living the art, teaching-learning, and leading-following. The change from quality of life to the construct <italic>living quality</italic> flows from the humanbecoming paradigm and expands the horizon of thinking to embrace the idea that the whatness of a human life is individual—indivisible, unpredictable, everchanging. It exposes the idea that the becoming visible-invisible becoming of the emerging now <italic>is</italic> the whatness or quality that the human is living at the moment with the inherent core knowings of fortifying wisdom, discerning witness, and penetrating silence.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowling</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Lay theories of quality of life in older age</article-title>. <source>Ageing &amp; Society</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>827</fpage>-<lpage>848</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A systematic review of quality of life instruments in long-term breast cancer survivors</article-title>. <source>Health and Quality of Life Outcomes</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannava</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The meaning of retirement for communally-living retired performing artists</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dimsdale</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>1995</year>). <source>Quality of life in behavioral medicine research</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dorfman</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Health conditions and perceived quality of life in retirement</article-title>. <source>Health and Social Work</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>192</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Patients’ views of quality of life: Transforming the knowledge base of nursing</article-title>. <source>Clinical Nurse Specialist</source>, <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Franzen-Dahlin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laska</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Gender differences in quality of life after stroke and TIA: A cross-sectional survey of out-patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Nursing</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2386</fpage>-<lpage>2391</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zuna</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The quantitative measurement of family quality of life: A review of available instruments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>1098</fpage>-<lpage>1114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P.-C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fetzer</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Quality of life in elders living alone in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Nursing</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1610</fpage>-<lpage>1617</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Malott</surname><given-names>O. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAiney</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Improving quality of life for residents with dementia</article-title>. <source>Long Term Care</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jonas-Simpson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Quality of life: Exploring the client’s perspective</source>. Unpublished manuscript, <publisher-name>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y.-F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Quality of life in colorectal cancer patients with diarrhea after surgery: A longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Nursing</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2357</fpage>-<lpage>2366</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>Man-living-health: A theory of nursing</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>Nursing science: Major paradigms, theories, and critiques</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Health: A personal commitment</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Human becoming: Parse’s theory of nursing</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994a</year>). <article-title>Laughing and health: A study using Parse’s research method</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994b</year>). <article-title>Quality of life: Sciencing and living the art of human becoming</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>1995</year>). <source>Illuminations: The human becoming theory in practice and research</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National League for Nursing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Quality of life for persons living with Alzheimer’s disease: The human becoming perspective</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The human becoming school of thought: A perspective for nurses and other health professionals</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Community: An alternative view</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Qualitative inquiry: The path of sciencing</source>. <publisher-loc>Sudbury, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Bartlett</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Community: A human becoming perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Sudbury, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Bartlett</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007a</year>). <article-title>A human becoming perspective on quality of life</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007b</year>). <article-title>The humanbecoming school of thought in 2050</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>308</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Human dignity: A humanbecoming ethical phenomenon</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parse</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>New humanbecoming conceptualizations and the humanbecoming community model: Expansions with sciencing and living the art</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pilkington</surname><given-names>F. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Quality of life for women living with a gynecologic cancer</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Iron horse: Lou Gehrig in his time</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rillotta</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The development of family quality of life concepts and measures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Measurement of quality of life in menopausal women: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Western Journal of Nursing Research</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>475</fpage>-<lpage>503</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Struggling through a difficult time for unemployed persons</article-title>. <source>Nursing Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0894318413477145">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Activity nursing and the changes in the quality of life of elderly patients: A semi-quantitative study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1727</fpage>-<lpage>1733</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>