<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546513488518</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546513488518</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Knee</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>23</subject>
<subject>40</subject>
<subject>42</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Comparative Study of Meniscectomy and Nonoperative Treatment for Degenerative Horizontal Tears of the Medial Meniscus</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>Ji-Hyeon</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546513488518">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Seon</surname><given-names>Jong-Keun</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546513488518">†</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546513488518">‡</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Eun-Kyoo</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546513488518">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Jun-Ik</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546513488518">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Min-Cheol</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546513488518">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Keun-Bae</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546513488518">§</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Hyoung-Yeon</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546513488518">§</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546513488518"><label>*</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Gwangju Hyundae Hospital, Gwangju, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546513488518"><label>†</label>Center for Joint Disease, Chonnam National University Hwasun Hospital, Jeonnam, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0363546513488518"><label>§</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Chonnam National University Hospital, Gwangju, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0363546513488518">Investigation performed at the Center for Joint Disease, Chonnam National University Hwasun Hospital, Jeonnam, Korea</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546513488518"><label>‡</label>Jong-Keun Seon, MD, PhD, Center for Joint Disease, Chonnam National University Hwasun Hospital, 322 Seoyang-ro, Hwasun-eup, Hwasun-gun, Jeonnam, 519-763, Korea (e-mail: <email>seonbell@chonnam.ac.kr</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>1565</fpage>
<lpage>1570</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0363546513488518">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>It is still debated whether a degenerative horizontal tear of the medial meniscus should be treated with surgery.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546513488518">
<title>Hypothesis:</title>
<p>The clinical outcomes of arthroscopic meniscectomy will be better than those of nonoperative treatment for a degenerative horizontal tear of the medial meniscus.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546513488518">
<title>Study Design:</title>
<p>Randomized controlled trial; Level of evidence, 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546513488518">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>A total of 102 patients with knee pain and a degenerative horizontal tear of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus on magnetic resonance imaging were included in this study between January 2007 and July 2009. The study included 81 female and 21 male patients with an average age of 53.8 years (range, 43-62 years). Fifty patients underwent arthroscopic meniscectomy (meniscectomy group), and 52 patients underwent nonoperative treatment with strengthening exercises (nonoperative group). Functional outcomes were compared using a visual analog scale (VAS) for pain, Lysholm knee score, Tegner activity scale, and patient subjective knee pain and satisfaction. Radiological evaluations were performed using the Kellgren-Lawrence classification to evaluate osteoarthritic changes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546513488518">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>In terms of clinical outcomes, meniscectomy did not provide better functional improvement than nonoperative treatment. At the final follow-up, the average VAS scores were 1.8 (range, 1-5) in the meniscectomy group and 1.7 (range, 1-4) in the nonoperative group (<italic>P</italic> = .675). The average Lysholm knee scores at 2-year follow-up were 83.2 (range, 52-100) and 84.3 (range, 58-100) in the meniscectomy and nonoperative groups, respectively (<italic>P</italic> = .237). In addition, the average Tegner activity scale and subjective satisfaction scores were not significantly different between the 2 groups. Although most patients initially had intense knee pain with mechanical symptoms, both groups reported a relief in knee pain, improved knee function, and a high level of satisfaction with treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 for all values). Two patients in the meniscectomy group and 3 in the nonoperative group with Kellgren-Lawrence grade 1 progressed to grade 2 at the 2-year follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546513488518">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>There were no significant differences between arthroscopic meniscectomy and nonoperative management with strengthening exercises in terms of relief in knee pain, improved knee function, or increased satisfaction in patients after 2 years of follow-up.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>medial meniscus</kwd>
<kwd>degenerative horizontal tear</kwd>
<kwd>arthroscopic meniscectomy</kwd>
<kwd>nonoperative treatment</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Horizontal tears of the meniscus are known as degenerative tears and are more common in late middle age.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546513488518">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546513488518">6</xref></sup> The posterior horn is relatively immobile compared with other parts of the medial meniscus, and it is vulnerable to tears.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0363546513488518">35</xref></sup> Therefore, horizontal tears of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus are the most typical and basic components of degenerative tears in the meniscus. They usually begin at the inner margin of the meniscus and extend toward the periphery, producing 2 leaves: 1 superior and 1 inferior. Deciding how and when to manage such tears is difficult because of the surgical requirement for resection when the tear extends deep into the capsule and the high rate of revision surgery related to residual symptoms after partial meniscectomy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0363546513488518">31</xref></sup> Moreover, resection inevitably leads to consequences such as subtotal or total meniscectomy, which causes osteoarthritis (OA) because of its effect on the weightbearing regions of articular cartilage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546513488518">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546513488518">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>According to previous studies, early OA development is more likely to occur after meniscectomy than after nonoperative treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546513488518">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0363546513488518">29</xref></sup> However, there is often a poor correlation between objective data and subjective complaints, making studies on outcomes difficult to perform.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546513488518">19</xref></sup> In addition, few comparative studies have been reported for degenerative horizontal tears in the medial meniscus in a prospective study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546513488518">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546513488518">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>The purpose of the present investigation was to compare the clinical results of arthroscopic meniscectomy and nonoperative treatment for degenerative horizontal tears in the posterior horn of the medial meniscus. Our hypothesis was that the clinical outcomes of arthroscopic meniscectomy would be better than those of nonoperative treatment for a degenerative horizontal tear of the medial meniscus.</p>
<sec id="section7-0363546513488518" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section8-0363546513488518">
<title>Patients</title>
<p>The study protocol was approved by the institutional review board of our institution (CNUHHIRB 2006-32). Patients with a degenerative horizontal tear of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), who were referred to the Center for Joint Disease at our institution between January 2007 and July 2009 for the treatment of nontraumatic knee pain, were asked to participate in this study. The inclusion criteria included daily knee pain on the medial side with mechanical symptoms affecting daily living activities despite management at a primary clinic during the previous month. The exclusion criteria included a history of definite trauma, previous knee surgery, ligament deficiency, systemic arthritis, and osteonecrosis. In addition, patients showing a marked degenerative change with grade ≥2, according to the Kellgren-Lawrence classification,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546513488518">18</xref></sup> were excluded. Of the 162 eligible patients, 108 agreed to participate. Subsequent treatment was decided by randomization using a closed-envelope technique and dividing the participants into 2 different groups. At the 2-year follow-up, 4 patients in the meniscectomy group and 2 patients in the nonoperative group had dropped out (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546513488518">Figure 1</xref>). There were 81 women and 21 men, and the average age was 56.8 years (range, 43-62 years). Each participant provided written informed consent. Patient demographics and preoperative status of the knee are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546513488518">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>CONSORT flow diagram.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline Characteristics of Patients<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546513488518"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546513488518" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Meniscectomy Group (n = 50)</th>
<th align="left">Nonoperative Group (n = 52)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Sex, male/female, n</td>
<td align="center">9/41</td>
<td align="center">12/40</td>
<td>.666</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at surgery, y</td>
<td>54.9 ± 10.3</td>
<td>57.6 ± 11.0</td>
<td>.083</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Body mass index</td>
<td>25.0 ± 2.5</td>
<td>26.4 ± 1.9</td>
<td>.338</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mechanical axis<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0363546513488518"><italic>b</italic></xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.9 ± 1.3</td>
<td>−1.1 ± 1.4</td>
<td>.358</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maximal flexion, deg</td>
<td>139 ± 6.9</td>
<td>141 ± 10.3</td>
<td>.227</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VAS score</td>
<td>5.2 ± 1.8</td>
<td>4.9 ± 1.5</td>
<td>.366</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lysholm score</td>
<td>64.0 ± 11.2</td>
<td>65.2 ± 10.8</td>
<td>.275</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546513488518">
<label>a</label>
<p>Values are expressed as mean ± standard deviation unless otherwise indicated. VAS, visual analog scale.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0363546513488518">
<label>b</label>
<p>A negative number represents varus deformity.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0363546513488518">
<title>Management of the Nonoperative Group</title>
<p>The mean symptom duration of patients who underwent nonoperative management was 8.2 months (range, 2-81 months). All patients in the nonoperative group were prescribed drugs, such as analgesics, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), or muscle relaxants, depending on clinical symptoms for the first 2 weeks. In addition, they underwent scheduled physical exercise to improve muscle strength, endurance, and flexibility for 60 minutes per session, 3 times weekly, for 3 weeks under the supervision of a physical therapist. After an early, intensive, supervised rehabilitation program to strengthen muscles during the first 3 weeks, all patients were provided with a home exercise program, which they conducted unsupervised for 8 weeks. The home exercise program consisted of daily isometric and isotonic muscle exercises (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0363546513488518">Table 2</xref>). Patients were instructed to perform the exercises with some strain but almost pain free and not adversely influencing the affected knee.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Home Exercise Program</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0363546513488518" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Times per Week</th>
<th align="left">Exercise</th>
<th align="left">Frequency (3 Times per Day)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0-8</td>
<td>Stretching of knee extensors and flexors</td>
<td>1 min/muscle group</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0-8</td>
<td>Knee extension in sitting position</td>
<td>3 × 10 repetitions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0-8</td>
<td>Knee flexion in sitting position</td>
<td>3 × 10 repetitions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0-8</td>
<td>Stationary bicycling</td>
<td>Gradual increase every 15 min</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5-8</td>
<td>Half squats with &lt;45° of flexion with weights</td>
<td>3 × 10 repetitions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5-8</td>
<td>Squats with full flexion with weights</td>
<td>3 × 10 repetitions</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546513488518">
<title>Management of the Meniscectomy Group</title>
<p>Arthroscopic meniscectomy was performed on patients at an average of 8.4 months (range, 6 weeks to 123 months) after the onset of symptoms. Surgery was carried out by a single experienced orthopaedic surgeon, using a 5.5-mm, 30° arthroscope and a pressure-controlled irrigation system. The procedure in each case was limited to resection with limited debridement of the articular surface lesion. Patients who underwent additional procedures, such as curettage, abrasion arthroplasty, or subchondral drilling for any articular lesions, were excluded from this study (n = 3) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546513488518">Figure 1</xref>). No patient underwent total meniscectomy or peripheral meniscal repair. All patients were discharged on the day after surgery. Subsequently, patients were permitted to use co-interventions, such as analgesics or NSAIDs, within 2 weeks. All patients were then provided with a home exercise program, which was conducted unsupervised, using the same protocol as the nonoperative group for 8 weeks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546513488518">
<title>Assessments</title>
<p>Magnetic resonance imaging was used to visualize cartilage injuries at the femoral distal or tibial medial condyles of lesion sides before the surgery, and teleoroentgenography was used to measure the preoperative mechanical axes in the lower extremities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546513488518">12</xref></sup> Clinical results were evaluated with a visual analog scale (VAS) for pain, which consisted of a horizontal line that was 10 cm in length, based on symptoms (defined as pain related to specific activities, such as stair climbing, squatting, and standing up and sitting down); the Lysholm knee score<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0363546513488518">21</xref></sup>; and the Tegner activity scale.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0363546513488518">34</xref></sup> Degrees of relief from pain, according to the VAS, were categorized as “complete relief” (0 or 1 point), “improved” (&gt;2-point decrease), or “persistent” (changes within 2 points); patient subjective satisfaction with management, based on knee joint condition and degree of interference with everyday life, was rated as “very satisfied” (treatment met patient expectations), “satisfied” (treatment helped, and patient would undergo this treatment option), or “dissatisfied” (patient was the same or worse than before). Osteoarthritic changes, observed by roentgenography (anteroposterior, lateral, and Merchant views), were graded using the Kellgren-Lawrence classification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546513488518">18</xref></sup> Patients with grade ≥2 arthritis (definite osteophytes or definite narrowing of the joint space on plain radiography) with clear osteophytes were defined as having OA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546513488518">Figure 2</xref>). Clinical outcome measures and physical examinations were conducted by independent authors (J.-I.C. and M.-C.K.) not involved in the treatment at 3 months, 1 year, and 2 years in the outpatient consulting room.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Kellgren-Lawrence grade 2: definite osteophytes and definite narrowing of the joint space.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0363546513488518">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>An a priori power analysis was performed. The sample size was calculated based on the data obtained from the 30 cases in an earlier series of this study at our institution. The end point was the Lysholm knee score. As was observed in 30 patients, the standard deviation was approximately 18. Given that we wanted to test the difference in the minimal clinical relevance of 10 between the 2 groups with 80% power and a significance level of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05, these values were estimated with 54 patients in each group. The Student <italic>t</italic> test was used to analyze the numeric data and the χ<sup>2</sup> test to analyze the nonnumeric data. The analysis was performed with SPSS software (SPSS for Windows v 18.0, SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois), and significance was accepted at the 95% level.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0363546513488518" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The main symptoms before management were pain at a high flexion (94 patients, 92%) and tenderness at the posteromedial joint line (86 patients, 84%). At the 2-year follow-up, the average VAS scores were 1.8 (range, 1-5) and 1.7 (range, 1-4) in the meniscectomy and nonoperative groups, respectively, which were not significantly different (<italic>P</italic> = .675) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0363546513488518">Figure 3</xref>). In the meniscectomy group, symptom improvement, according to the mean VAS score after surgery, had continued for 6 months, and in the nonoperative group, the symptoms remained longer than in the meniscectomy group after starting management. Knee pain with mechanical symptoms in the meniscectomy and nonoperative groups was completely relieved in 34 and 35 patients, improved in 13 and 12 patients, and persisted in 3 and 5 patients, respectively, at the 2-year follow-up, and no significant difference was observed between the 2 groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0363546513488518">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mean changes in visual analog scale scores during follow-up examinations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table3-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Pain Relief Ratings at 2-Year Follow-up<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0363546513488518"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0363546513488518" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Rating</th>
<th align="center">Meniscectomy Group (n = 50)</th>
<th align="center">Nonoperative Group (n = 52)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Complete</td>
<td>34 (68)</td>
<td>35 (67)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Improved</td>
<td>13 (26)</td>
<td>12 (23)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Persistent</td>
<td>3 (6)</td>
<td>5 (10)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0363546513488518">
<label>a</label>
<p>Values are expressed as n (%). Statistical analysis between the 2 groups: <italic>P</italic> = .652.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the meniscectomy group, 18 were very satisfied, 28 were satisfied, and 4 were dissatisfied with surgery at the 2-year follow-up, and in the nonoperative group, 17 patients were very satisfied, 29 were satisfied, and 6 were dissatisfied (<italic>P</italic> = .357) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0363546513488518">Figure 4</xref>). The average Lysholm knee scores were 83.2 (range, 52-100) and 84.3 (range, 58-100) at the 2-year follow-up in the meniscectomy and nonoperative groups, respectively, which were also not significantly different (<italic>P</italic> = .237). The Lysholm knee scores had improved when evaluated at the follow-up relative to before treatment in both groups, and the only significant intergroup difference was observed at 3 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0363546513488518">Figure 5</xref>). Similarly, the average Tegner activity scale scores had been restored at the 2-year follow-up from 4.2 (range, 0-6) to 5.1 (range, 0-8) in the meniscectomy group and from 4.1 (range, 0-6) to 4.9 (range, 0-8) in the nonoperative group (<italic>P</italic> = .522). According to the Kellgren-Lawrence classification, 2 patients in the meniscectomy group (aged 59 and 62 years) and 3 in the nonoperative group (aged 57, 67, and 74 years) showed OA progression by &gt;1 grade over the study period (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0363546513488518">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Patient satisfaction rates after 2 years of follow-up.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mean changes in Lysholm knee scores after follow-up examinations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table4-0363546513488518" position="float">
<label>Table 4</label>
<caption>
<p>Kellgren-Lawrence Grade for Osteoarthritis at the Initial Visit and 2-Year Follow-up</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0363546513488518" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513488518-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Initial Visit<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0363546513488518"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">2-Year Follow-up<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0363546513488518"><italic>b</italic></xref></sup></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Kellgren-Lawrence Grade</th>
<th align="center">Meniscectomy Group</th>
<th align="center">Non-operative Group</th>
<th align="center">Meniscectomy Group</th>
<th align="center">Non-operative Group</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0363546513488518">
<label>a</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> = .482.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0363546513488518">
<label>b</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> = .440.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0363546513488518" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Horizontal meniscal tears occur frequently and may be asymptomatic.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546513488518">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546513488518">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546513488518">26</xref></sup> This tear type can give rise to a flap tear but is usually mechanically stable. Although traditionally medial meniscal tears have been treated by arthroscopic meniscectomy, there is no scientific evidence to support its efficacy for degenerative changes, which include horizontal tears of the medial meniscus. Hence, we evaluated the effect of partial meniscectomy and nonoperative management in patients with degenerative medial meniscal tears. In this study, an arthroscopic procedure for degenerative horizontal tears in the posterior horn of the medial meniscus did not provide superior outcomes when compared with nonoperative management. The only time point at which the meniscectomy group had a significantly higher Lysholm knee score was after 3 months. Roos et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0363546513488518">30</xref></sup> reported that arthroscopic partial meniscectomy, as the only intervention, showed improvements after 3 months. This finding was similar to that of the present study in which the mean Lysholm knee scores significantly improved at only 3 months postoperatively. At the 2-year follow-up, no significant difference between the 2 groups was observed. However, in a previous study by Desai and Ackroyd,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546513488518">5</xref></sup> the prevalence of degenerative meniscal tears was 60% in elderly patients who were analyzed postmortem<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0363546513488518">27</xref></sup>; thus, arthroscopic resection of degenerative lesions of menisci was considered to be of little value in the long term. On the basis of the analysis conducted in this study, we can only assume that resection of a degenerative horizontal tear in the posterior horn of the medial meniscus would have an outcome similar to that of nonoperative management. These results might be because a horizontal tear generally does not disrupt the functional continuity of the circumferential fibers, and the meniscal functions were largely preserved.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513488518">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546513488518">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>In addition, we would like to examine whether arthroscopic surgery is better for knee pain with mechanical symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546513488518">2</xref></sup> The VAS, pain relief, and patient satisfaction for subjective symptoms were assessed in this study, but no significant differences were observed between the 2 groups. The possible explanation of the lack of significant difference may be that the symptoms, including mechanical pain of patients with degenerative horizontal tears, can improve with time regardless of treatment modality. Christoforakis et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546513488518">4</xref></sup> reported that complex and horizontal tears are associated with more severe cartilage degeneration than other types of meniscal tears. In addition, Bolano and Grana<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546513488518">3</xref></sup> reported that patients with horizontal cleavage, degenerative, or complex tears were significantly more likely to report unsatisfactory results (44%) than patients with bucket-handle, flap, or radial tears (3%) (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) after arthroscopic partial meniscectomy. However, Higuchi et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546513488518">15</xref></sup> reported no significant difference in functional results between horizontal, bucket-handle, and complex tears. Matsusue and Thomson<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546513488518">22</xref></sup> found no significant difference in patient outcomes between degenerative and nondegenerative tears, with 79% and 88% reporting excellent or good results, respectively (<italic>P</italic> = .517).</p>
<p>Although there are often poor correlations between objective data and subjective complaints, making studies on outcomes difficult to perform,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546513488518">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546513488518">19</xref></sup> there is a prevailing concern that the meniscus-deficient knee is at risk for the development of premature chondral damage that leads to an accelerated and severe course of knee OA. Englund et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546513488518">8</xref></sup> reported that degenerative tears are significantly more associated with symptomatic OA than are acute tears. In that study, radiographic OA was also seen at a significantly higher rate (29%) in the operative patient’s contralateral knee (<italic>P</italic> = .039) when compared with the control group (9%). In the current study, the OA score of 5 patients (5%) increased by &gt;1 grade, based on the Kellgren-Lawrence classification,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546513488518">18</xref></sup> with our smaller incidence possibly reflecting the 2-year follow-up duration and limited exclusion criteria (Kellgren-Lawrence grade ≥2). Furthermore, many studies showed that increasing age predisposed the patient to have radiographic signs of OA at follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546513488518">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546513488518">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0363546513488518">28</xref></sup> Even if the relationship between age and the incidence of OA was not evaluated in the present study because of the short follow-up duration for the development of OA, the mean age of these patients was 59.6 years, which was greater than the mean age (56.8 years) of all patients.</p>
<p>The present study aimed to compare the modalities used to treat nontraumatic horizontal tears of the medial meniscus. In the nonoperative group, after 3 weeks of supervised exercise, patients exercised at home while unsupervised for 8 weeks. The majority of previous scientific publications have examined only rehabilitation after arthroscopic surgery, which was performed in this study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546513488518">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0363546513488518">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0363546513488518">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0363546513488518">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0363546513488518">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0363546513488518">36</xref></sup> Herrlin et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546513488518">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546513488518">14</xref></sup> reported not only great improvements in the 2 groups but also showed no differences in clinical outcomes, as in the current study. After critically reviewing clinical trials, Goodwin and Morrissey<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546513488518">10</xref></sup> failed to find sufficient evidence to support the use of physical therapy after arthroscopic surgery with respect to functional improvements, and they recommended a home exercise program. In another study, Jokl et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546513488518">16</xref></sup> concluded that a well-planned, unsupervised home exercise rehabilitation program can produce results as good as a supervised physical therapy program. Therefore, in the present study, we used a supervised exercise program, followed by a relatively longer home exercise program, to improve compliance and reduce costs.</p>
<p>The 2 groups were highly comparable, which means that the internal validity of the study was high. The risk that a prognostic variable influenced the treatment results in the 2 groups was very low. Although all patients in the meniscectomy group were not prescribed supervised physical exercise, it probably would not affect the outcomes of the 2-year follow-up. However, the other major limitation of this study is that the clinical results were obtained using questionnaires to measure parameters of pain, swelling, and various activities of daily living or with an available knee scoring system (only checked by the Lysholm knee score, not the others), and objective evaluations such as MRI and strength testing using an isokinetic device were not performed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0363546513488518">33</xref></sup> In addition, there were some drop-outs of patients (4 in the meniscectomy group and 2 in the nonoperative group), and patients were not evaluated over an extended period of time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0363546513488518" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Horizontal tears of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus of the knee joint are mainly related to degenerative changes, and as the present study shows, partial meniscectomy and nonoperative management both provide satisfactory clinical results. However, we found that arthroscopic meniscectomy for the treatment of a degenerative horizontal tear of the medial meniscus did not provide any significant advantage, relative to nonoperative management with strengthening exercises, in terms of the relief of knee pain, improved knee function, or increased satisfaction of patients after 2 years.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>Presented at the 38th annual meeting of the AOSSM, Baltimore, Maryland, July 2012.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared that they have no conflicts of interest in the authorship and publication of this contribution.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546513488518">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baratz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mengato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal tears: the effect of meniscectomy and of repair on intraarticular contact areas and stress in the human knee. A preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>270</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546513488518">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radial tears of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546513488518">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bolano</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grana</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Isolated arthroscopic partial meniscectomy: functional radiographic evaluation at five years</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>432</fpage>-<lpage>437</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546513488518">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christoforakis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanchez-Ballester</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is there an association between articular cartilage changes and degenerative meniscus tears?</article-title> <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1366</fpage>-<lpage>1369</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546513488518">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ackroyd</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Resection of degenerate menisci: is it useful?</article-title> <source>Knee</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546513488518">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal tear: a feature of osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop Scand Suppl</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>312</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>, backcover.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546513488518">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for symptomatic knee osteoarthritis fifteen to twenty-two years after meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2811</fpage>-<lpage>2819</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546513488518">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paradowski</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of radiographic hand osteoarthritis with radiographic knee osteoarthritis after meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>469</fpage>-<lpage>475</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546513488518">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Felson</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naimark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Castelli</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meenan</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The prevalence of knee osteoarthritis in the elderly: the Framingham Osteoarthritis Study</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>914</fpage>-<lpage>918</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546513488518">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical therapy after arthroscopic partial meniscectomy: is it effective?</article-title> <source>Exerc Sport Sci Rev</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546513488518">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Southall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of supervised physical therapy in the early period after arthroscopic partial meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Phys Ther</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>520</fpage>-<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546513488518">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Habata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohgushi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tamai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Axial alignment of the lower limb in patients with isolated meniscal tear</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sci</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546513488518">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herrlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wange</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weidenhielm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic or conservative treatment of degenerative medial meniscal tears: a prospective randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>393</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546513488518">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herrlin</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wange</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lapidus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weidenhielm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is arthroscopic surgery beneficial in treating non-traumatic, degenerative medial meniscal tears? A five year follow-up</article-title> [published online March 23, 2012]. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-012-1960-3</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546513488518">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shirakura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terauchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takagishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting long-term results after arthroscopic partial meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>377</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0363546513488518">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jokl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stull</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Independent home versus supervised rehabilitation following arthroscopic knee surgery: a prospective randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>298</fpage>-<lpage>305</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0363546513488518">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Learmonth</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Direct measurement of hoop strains in the intact and torn human medial meniscus</article-title>. <source>Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon)</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0363546513488518">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kellgren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiological assessment of osteo-arthrosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. <year>1957</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>494</fpage>-<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0363546513488518">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lethbridge-Cejku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Reichle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of radiographic features of osteoarthritis of the knee with knee pain: data from the Baltimore Longitudinal Study of Aging</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0363546513488518">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Knee ligament injury, surgery and osteoarthrosis: truth or consequences?</article-title> <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>605</fpage>-<lpage>609</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0363546513488518">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lysholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillquist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of knee ligament surgery results with special emphasis on use of a scoring scale</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0363546513488518">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsusue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic partial medial meniscectomy in patients over 40 years old: a 5- to 11-year follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0363546513488518">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St-Pierre</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recovery of muscle strength following arthroscopic meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0363546513488518">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amis</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The consequences of meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1549</fpage>-<lpage>1556</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0363546513488518">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moffet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malouin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Early and intensive physiotherapy accelerates recovery postarthroscopic meniscectomy: results of a randomized controlled study</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>426</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0363546513488518">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lesions of the menisci: autopsy incidence in adults less than fifty-five years old</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>480</fpage>-<lpage>483</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0363546513488518">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamblen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The pathology of the degenerate meniscus lesion</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1975</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>186</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0363546513488518">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ostenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ekdahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term outcome of meniscectomy: symptoms, function, and performance tests in patients with or without radiographic osteoarthritis compared to matched controls</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>316</fpage>-<lpage>324</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0363546513488518">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adalberth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Osteoarthritis of the knee after injury to the anterior cruciate ligament or meniscus: the influence of time and age</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0363546513488518">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lauren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adalberth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Knee osteoarthritis after meniscectomy: prevalence of radiographic changes after twenty-one years, compared with matched controls</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>-<lpage>693</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0363546513488518">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spahn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic revisions in failed meniscal surgery</article-title>. <source>Int Orthop</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>378</fpage>-<lpage>381</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0363546513488518">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>St-Pierre</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rehabilitation following arthroscopic meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0363546513488518">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>St-Pierre</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laforest</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Isokinetic rehabilitation after arthroscopic meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0363546513488518">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tegner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lysholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rating systems in the evaluation of knee ligament injuries</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0363546513488518">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vedi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tennant</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spouse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gedroyc</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal movement: an in-vivo study using dynamic MRI</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0363546513488518">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vervest</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schambergen</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Bie</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bulstra</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of physiotherapy after meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>360</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>