<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Sch Nurs</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Journal of School Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1059-8405</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1546-8364</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059840511431459</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1059840511431459</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An Intervention to Increase High School Students’ Compliance With Carrying Auto-Injectable Epinephrine</article-title>
<subtitle>A MASNRN Study</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Spina</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer L.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN, MSN, NCSN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1059840511431459">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1059840511431459"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McIntyre</surname>
<given-names>C. Lynne</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1059840511431459">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pulcini</surname>
<given-names>Joyce A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, PNP-BC, FAAN, FAANP</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1059840511431459">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1059840511431459">Nurse Educator, Massachusetts General Hospital/Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Boston, Boston, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1059840511431459">Director of Evaluation and Planning, DotWell, Dorchester, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1059840511431459">Associate Professor, Connell School of Nursing, Boston College, Boston, MA, USA Note: All authors are members of the MASNRN (Massachusetts School Nurse Research Network) Oversight Board</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1059840511431459">Jennifer L. Spina, Massachusetts General Hospital/Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Boston, 22 Maplewood Road, Lynn, MA 01904, USA Email: <email>jenniferspina@comcast.net</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1059840511431459">
<p>
<bold>Jennifer L. Spina</bold>, RN, MSN, NCSN, is a Nurse Educator, Massachusetts General Hospital/Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Boston, Boston, MA, USA.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1059840511431459">
<p>
<bold>C. Lynne McIntyre,</bold> RN, PhD, is a Director of Evaluation and Planning, DotWell, Dorchester, MA, USA.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1059840511431459">
<p>
<bold>Joyce A. Pulcini</bold>, PhD, PNP-BC, FAAN, FAANP, is an Associate Professor, Connell School of Nursing, Boston College, Boston, MA, USA.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>230</fpage>
<lpage>237</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">National Association of School Nurses</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Adolescents with life-threatening allergies are at a greater risk for a fatal anaphylactic event since only about half of them carry unexpired epinephrine available for emergency use. The aim of this study was to test the effectiveness of school nurse interventions that consisted of either routine or periodic checks during the school year for the availability of unexpired auto-injectable epinephrine. Seventy-seven students from 11 Massachusetts high schools participated in this study. Descriptive and chi-square (χ<sup>2</sup>) statistics as well as the Fisher’s exact test were used to analyze data. Findings suggest that while periodic checks for the availability of epinephrine throughout the school year do not increase the likelihood that students will have epinephrine available, those students who do carry their epinephrine are more likely to have unexpired medication with periodic reminders during the school year.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>allergies</kwd>
<kwd>adolescents</kwd>
<kwd>evidence-based practice</kwd>
<kwd>epinephrine</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1059840511431459">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Food allergy has become a significant public health issue and poses several challenging issues for schools.  Based on the 2007 National Health Interview Study, approximately 3 million children under the age of 18 years (3.9%) reported having a food allergy during the past 12 months. During the period from 1997 to 2007, the prevalence of reported food allergies in this same age group increased to 18% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1059840511431459">Branum &amp; Lucas, 2009</xref>). A recently published survey found that 1 (7.7%) in 13 children  in the United States have at least one food allergy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1059840511431459">Gupta et al., 2011</xref>); 25% of children in this survey were allergic to peanuts, 21% to milk, and 17% to shellfish. Among Department of Public Health grant-funded schools in Massachusetts, the rate of epinephrine prescriptions increased from 7.2 per 1,000 students in the 2000–2001 school year to 18.8 per 1,000 students in the 2008–2009 school year (Massachusetts Department of Public Health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1059840511431459">MADPH], 2010</xref>).  Food allergy has been identified as the leading cause of anaphylaxis in children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1059840511431459">Braganza et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1059840511431459">de Silva, Mehr, Tey, &amp; Tang, 2008</xref>) and a study of food-allergic children determined that approximately one (18%) in five  can be expected to have a reaction in school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1059840511431459">Nowak-Wegzyn, Connover-Walker, &amp; Wood, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Guidelines for the management of students with life-threatening allergies in the school setting, including management of anaphylaxis, have been developed by several states as well as professional organizations, including the National Association of School Nurses. Epinephrine has been identified as the drug of choice for the treatment of anaphylaxis (American Academy of Asthma, Allergy, and Immunology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1059840511431459">AAAAI], 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1059840511431459">National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1059840511431459">Sicherer, Mahr, Section on Allergy &amp; Immunology, 2010</xref>) and prompt administration has been shown to reduce morbidity and mortality associated with life-threatening allergic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511431459">Sampson, Mendelson, &amp; Rosen, 1992</xref>). This requires that epinephrine be readily available for immediate use in the event of an allergic reaction.</p>
<p>An estimated 2.3% of adolescents have a food allergy<sup> </sup>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1059840511431459">Pereira et al., 2005</xref>), and research has shown that adolescents or young adults are at higher risk for fatal food-allergic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1059840511431459">Bock, Munoz-Furlong, &amp; Sampson, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511431459">Sampson et al., 1992</xref>). During the period from September 2001 to July 2005, more than half of the 386 reports of epinephrine administration for a life-threatening allergic reaction in Massachusetts schools involved middle or high school students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1059840511431459">McIntyre, Sheetz, Franks, Gapinski, &amp; Gorak, 2006</xref>). Older students with diagnosed life-threatening allergies are allowed to carry auto-injectable epinephrine in the school setting if it has been determined that they are able to self-administer the medication responsibly and certain other conditions are met (National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1059840511431459">NHLBI], 2005</xref>). Unfortunately, students who are authorized to self-carry their epinephrine do not always have their medication available when it is needed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1059840511431459">Bartley, Marchitto, Kosiorowski, &amp; Boulden, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059840511431459">Ben-Shosha, et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1059840511431459">Sampson, Munoz-Furlong, and Sicherer (2006</xref>) found that only 61% of adolescents and young adults reported carrying self-injectable epinephrine with them at all times. In addition, 54% admitted to purposefully ingesting a potentially unsafe food and 42% reported that they would eat food labeled as “may contain an allergen to which they were allergic.” Those who were most likely to engage in risky behavior were also more likely to report feelings of being “different.” In a qualitative study involving 17 adolescents with food hypersensitivity, the theme of “striving to normalize” was identified (Marklund, Wilde-Larsson, Ahlstedt, &amp; Nordstrom<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1059840511431459">, 2007</xref>). The need to normalize may contribute to adolescents’ engagement in some forms of risk taking, such as knowingly ingesting an allergen, in an effort to avoid being different.</p>
<p>Previous research studies support the fact that the adolescent with a life-threatening allergy is at more risk for a fatal reaction as is demonstrated by the model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1059840511431459">Figure 1</xref>. Adolescence is typified by a decrease in parental supervision since parents are not physically with the adolescent as much as when the child was younger. This period marks the developing of self-autonomy for the adolescents; beginning to understand who they are and make decisions on their own. Those with a life-threatening allergy often have greater responsibility for making decisions about their allergies and frequently are engaged in social situations with friends or others who do not provide a support structure for appropriately managing life-threatening allergies. Not wanting to be different and the fear of social isolation increase the probability of engaging in behaviors that put adolescents at risk for anaphylactic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1059840511431459">Sampson, Munoz-Furlong, &amp; Sicherer, 2006</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Why adolescents are at more risk for fatal anaphylactic reactions?</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig1-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In 2008, a survey was conducted in Massachusetts high schools to determine the number of students with life-threatening allergies who carried unexpired auto-injectable epinephrine with them at school. Two hundred and seventy-four surveys were mailed to school nurses in Massachusetts high schools with enrollments of 500 students or more; 54 surveys were returned for a response rate of 19.7%. Although the response rate for this survey was lower than desired, all regions of the state were represented and the total school enrollment included in the sample was greater than 65,000 students. A limitation could have been that the survey was mailed to responders. The survey asked school nurses to indicate how many students with life-threatening allergies in their school (a) had a prescription on file for epinephrine, (b) were authorized to carry the medication in school, (c) presented the medication when asked by the school nurse, and (d) had epinephrine that was unexpired. Of the 878 students with life-threatening allergies who were authorized to self-carry auto-injectable epinephrine, only 509 (58%) had the device with them and 418 (47.6%) had unexpired epinephrine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1059840511431459">Crowe, Spina, McIntyre, Pulcini, &amp; Friedman, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Education in the management of life-threatening allergies, particularly in the use of epinephrine, was found to be lacking in several studies. In one study of 101 families, only 49% of parents/teens reported that their physician had demonstrated correct use of the auto-injectable epinephrine device and only 32% of the families were able to correctly demonstrate the use of the device. Among providers in the study, only 18% of attending pediatricians and 36% of pediatric residents were able to correctly demonstrate the use of auto-injectable epinephrine. Although 86% of parents/teens reported that they routinely carried auto-injectable epinephrine with them at all times, only 71% had the device with them at the time of the visit and only 55% had epinephrine that was unexpired (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1059840511431459">Sicherer, Forman, &amp; Noone, 2000</xref>). The effectiveness of a multidisciplinary team consisting of a pediatric allergist, clinical nurse specialist, and dietician to teach families how to avoid allergens and manage allergic reactions was evaluated with the families of 62 children referred for food allergies. Findings indicated that after a single visit to the clinic, there was significant improvement in knowledge of how to avoid allergens and respond to allergic reactions (including appropriate use of auto-injectable epinephrine) as well as a significant reduction in allergic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1059840511431459">Kapoor et al., 2004</xref>). Risk-taking behavior seen in adolescents may be partially related to a lack of knowledge on potential consequences of both exposure to allergens and/or prompt and appropriate treatment of an allergic reaction.</p>
<p>The risk-taking practice of not having epinephrine available increases the likelihood of a severe or fatal reaction, and it has been suggested that a system for periodically checking the availability of students’ auto-injectable epinephrine be implemented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1059840511431459">McIntyre, Sheetz, Carroll, &amp; Young, 2005</xref>). In addition, it is imperative that all adolescents have sufficient knowledge and skill regarding how to manage their life-threatening allergy.</p>
<p>The aim of this study was to test the effectiveness of an intervention designed to increase the likelihood that high school students will carry unexpired auto-injectable epinephrine with them at all times while in school. Specifically, it was hypothesized that students who received an educational intervention and periodic checks by the school nurse throughout the school year would be more likely to have their auto-injectable epinephrine available for emergency use than students who only received the educational intervention and a routine check for auto-injectable epinephrine by the school nurse at the beginning of the school year.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1059840511431459">
<title>Design</title>
<p>This study used a quasi-experimental design. The high schools that participated in this study were randomly assigned to either the control or intervention group by individually selecting the names of the participating schools from a box for each study group. Convenience sampling was used to select both the high schools and the participating students in each school. Nurses from participating schools were required to obtain written authorization from their school principal and/or school Institutional Review Board (IRB) approval if required. IRB approval for the study was obtained from the Boston College IRB. The Boston College IRB was provided with all necessary forms: written principal authorization, parental consent, and student assent. Nurses from the participating schools were also required to complete the Collaborative Institutional Training Initiative training on the responsible conduct of human subject research.</p>
<p>The study was built upon a preliminary descriptive study that was conducted in February 2008, with 54 public high school nurses in the state of Massachusetts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1059840511431459">Crowe et al., 2009</xref>). Data from the study established a baseline by determining the proportion of students in the surveyed public high schools in Massachusetts, who were authorized to self-carry auto-injectable epinephrine and actually had unexpired epinephrine with them when questioned by the school nurse.</p>
<sec id="section3-1059840511431459">
<title>Recruitment of Participating Schools</title>
<p>The current study was implemented during the 2008–2009 school year. Nurses from participant schools also took part in the initial descriptive study as described above and were members of the Massachusetts School Nurse Research Network (MASNRN), a network of more than 100 school nurses across Massachusetts, who have expressed interest in becoming involved in research projects related to school health. The 44 MASNRN nurses working in public high schools, who participated in the initial descriptive study in February 2008, were invited to participate in the current study if they had at least three students in their school who met the inclusion criteria. Inclusion criteria for study participants consisted of (a) a diagnosis of life-threatening allergy, (b) having a prescription for auto-injectable epinephrine, and (c) authorization to carry and self-administer epinephrine. Students who had bee/insect sting allergies were excluded from the study. The rationale for this exclusion was that these students may only carry their auto-injectable epinephrine seasonally which may have affected the results of this school year long study. Study schools were then randomly assigned to either an intervention or a control group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1059840511431459">
<title>Sample and Setting</title>
<p>The goal for sample size was 102 students: 51 students in each group, intervention and control that would be distributed over at least 10 schools. The sample size was based on a power analysis for a one-tailed hypothesis with α set at .05, a medium effect size of 0.5, and a power of 0.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1059840511431459">Lipsey, 1990</xref>). It was anticipated that each school nurse would be able to recruit at least 10 students with a life-threatening allergy who were authorized to carrying their epinephrine in each of the participating schools. This number was based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059840511431459">Massachusetts 2006–2007</xref> school-year data which had an epinephrine prescription rate of 15 per 1,000 students in a sample of 532,476 students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059840511431459">MADPH, 2008</xref>). Not all of the participating school nurses were able to recruit 10 students. This study was limited in the inability to recruit enough subjects to achieve a power analysis of 80%. The study team also found it difficult to recruit school nurses as many expressed that they did not have the time to commit to the study.</p>
<p>The study sample consisted of 11 schools with a total of 77 students. There were six schools in the intervention group with 45 students and five schools in the control group with 32 students. The participating schools were fairly well represented across the state with five from the Boston Metrowest area, two from the Northeast region, two from the Southeast region, and two from the Central region. There were no schools represented from the Western region of the state.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1059840511431459">
<title>Study Procedures</title>
<p>School nurses received training on study procedures at the beginning of the school year to assure fidelity of the intervention. A training manual was provided and the standardized data collection instruments. This training was 2 hr in length which included specific instruction on purpose of the study, obtaining consent for participation in research studies with children, and documentation on the standardized data collection instrument. Data collection instruments were developed for both the control and the intervention groups, which were to be used by the school nurses to record interventions and results. School nurses were given the opportunity to ask questions during this training. The research coordinator for this study maintained contact with school nurses at various intervals throughout the study via telephone and e-mail.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the school year (2008–2009), students in both groups were asked to show the school nurse their auto-injectable epinephrine. Each student also received a brief standardized educational intervention that consisted of the following:</p>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Importance of having the auto-injectable epinephrine with them at all times and methods or devices for carrying the auto-injectable epinephrine at various activities.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Relevance of the expiration date of the auto-injectable epinephrine and the need to check for the expiration date on a regular basis.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Correct storage and assessment of the auto-injectable epinephrine for damage that could interfere with medication viability.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Symptoms for which they would administer the auto-injectable epinephrine.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Demonstration of correct administration of the auto-injectable epinephrine.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Procedure to be followed if they self-administered auto-injectable epinephrine.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Importance of notifying individuals such as school personnel, people at activities outside of school and all friends of their potentially life-threatening allergy.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>The design of this standardized education tool was specific for the needs of the adolescent with life-threatening allergies. The education took place at the first session for both study groups, using the DVD, brochure, or both. School nurses were given the choice on the method of delivery (i.e., either individually or in a group) and which standardized education tool, the DVD, brochure, and/or both, they would use with study participants. The rationale for this decision made by the study team was that not all schools may have the same resources available and could have restrictions on the amount of time they may remove students from class. Most students received the education in a group setting using the DVD, supplemented with the brochure. Study participants completed a survey evaluating the DVD/brochure. The vast majority (98%) reported that these materials were organized and easy to understand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1059840511431459">Barnard &amp; Aries, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The research coordinator oversaw all study activities and monitored compliance with the study protocol. Students in the intervention schools were subsequently asked to show the school nurse their auto-injectable epinephrine at four specified times throughout the school year, one of which was at the end of the school year as seen by the time line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059840511431459">Figure 2</xref>. The times for periodic checks were preset prior to the beginning of the study. The research coordinator contacted the school nurses via telephone and e-mail to remind them that it was time for them to check students for their auto-injectable epinephrine. Participants were not aware of when school nurses would be checking for their auto-injectable epinephrine. School nurses called study participants to the nurse’s office and then asked to view their epinephrine. The school nurse documented whether or not the students had auto-injectable epinephrine available and if so, whether or not the epinephrine was expired.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Time line of periodic versus routine checks to be completed by school nurses.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig2-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>After the initial check for unexpired auto-injectable epinephrine at the beginning of the school year, students in the control schools were only asked to show the school nurse their auto-injectable epinephrine again at the end of the school year with no additional checks throughout the school year.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1059840511431459">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Data were entered into statistical package for the social sciences (SPSS for Windows, Rel. 11.0.1. 2001. Chicago: SPSS) and analyzed using descriptive statistics, chi-square (χ<sup>2</sup>) and Fisher’s exact test. In using the chi-square (χ<sup>2</sup>) and Fisher’s exact test for analyzing the data, the <italic>p</italic> value was set at .05 for data to be statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1059840511431459">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics were used to determine the characteristics of the study sample including gender, age, grade, and allergy characteristics. Among all study participants, 51% were female (52% in the intervention group and 50% in the control group). The average age of students in the both the intervention and the control group was 15 years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059840511431459">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Ages of study participants (<italic>n </italic>= 71). <italic>Note.</italic> Missing data for six subjects.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig3-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Allergy characteristics of study participants were reported on the data collection form used by the school nurses. Ninety-two percent (<italic>n</italic> = 71) of students reported having a food allergy and out of this reported number, 44% (<italic>n </italic>= 31) of students were further classified as having a peanut/nut allergy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1059840511431459">Figure 4</xref>). Sixty percent (<italic>n</italic> = 46) of the total sample reported having a history of anaphylaxis and of these, 43% (<italic>n</italic> = 20) reported having an anaphylactic reaction sometime during the last 3 years. Half of those students who reported that they had had an anaphylactic reaction in the past 3 years also had received epinephrine. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1059840511431459">Figure 5</xref> compares the percentage of students in the intervention and control groups with a previous history of anaphylaxis. During the study period, five students reported that they had an anaphylactic reaction that was treated by epinephrine.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>History of an anaphylactic reaction and/or administration of epinephrine in the past 3 years.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig5-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Classification of allergies: food (<italic>n</italic> = 71) and peanut/nut (<italic>n</italic> = 31).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig4-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The intervention and control groups were further analyzed to determine whether there was a difference in (a) the initial and final checks by the school nurse with respect to the availability of epinephrine and (b) whether the epinephrine was unexpired at the time of the check. The chi-square (χ<sup>2</sup>) statistic was used to determine whether the groups were significantly different in the proportion of students having epinephrine available for use. Significance was set at the level of <italic>p</italic>
<underline> </underline>≤ .05. No significant differences were found between the intervention and control groups in the proportion of students who had epinephrine available during the initial check (χ<sup>2</sup> = 1.63, <italic>df</italic> = 1, <italic>p</italic> = .2) or the final check at the end of the study (χ<sup>2</sup> = 1.73, <italic>df </italic>= 1, <italic>p</italic> = .189; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1059840511431459">Table 1</xref>). The Fisher’s exact test was used to interpret the significance in differences for the proportion of students with unexpired epinephrine in both groups while accounting for small sample properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059840511431459">Fisher, 1973</xref>). In the intervention group, all participants who had unexpired epinephrine during the first check continued to have current epinephrine, while one person with expired epinephrine on the first check had acquired current epinephrine during the final check (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). For the control group, of the 21 participants who reported having unexpired epinephrine during the first check, 5 participants had expired epinephrine during the final check, while one person who had expired epinephrine during the first check had current epinephrine during the final check (<italic>p</italic> = 1.0; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1059840511431459">Table 2</xref>). These findings suggest that while periodic checks for the availability of epinephrine throughout the school year do not increase the likelihood that students will have epinephrine available, those students who do carry their epinephrine are more likely to have unexpired medication.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Availability of Epinephrine (<italic>N</italic> = 73)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">
</th>
<th colspan="2">Initial Epinephrine Check</th>
<th colspan="2">Final Epinephrine Check</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Students With Epinephrine </th>
<th>Students Without Epinephrine </th>
<th>Students With Epinephrine</th>
<th>Students Without Epinephrine</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Intervention group</td>
<td>28 </td>
<td>16</td>
<td>27 </td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Control group</td>
<td>22 </td>
<td>7</td>
<td>22 </td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1059840511431459" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Unexpired Epinephrine (<italic>N</italic> = 47<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1059840511431459">a</xref></sup>)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1059840511431459" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511431459-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">
</th>
<th colspan="2">Initial Epinephrine Check</th>
<th colspan="2">Final Epinephrine Check</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Students With Unexpired Epinephrine </th>
<th>Students With Expired Epinephrine </th>
<th>Students With Unexpired Epinephrine </th>
<th>Students With Expired Epinephrine</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Intervention group</td>
<td>21 </td>
<td>4</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Control group</td>
<td>21 </td>
<td>1</td>
<td>17 </td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1059840511431459">
<p>
<italic>Note.</italic> <sup>a</sup>Includes only those students for whom data on expiration was available at both measurement periods.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1059840511431459">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Previous research has revealed that those with life-threatening allergies are at greater risk for anaphylaxis when there is a delay and/or a failure to use epinephrine. These delays and/or failure to use epinephrine can be attributed to the fact that anaphylactic reactions occur more often away from home and those with allergies may not have their epinephrine on them for emergency use when it is needed. Adolescents are particularly at a higher risk for a fatal anaphylactic reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511431459">Sampson et al., 1992</xref>). The adolescent spends a significant portion of the day at school in academics or afterschool-related activities. School nurses understand the importance of not only educating those students with life-threatening allergies but also identifying evidence-based strategies to ensure that they have unexpired epinephrine available for use in an emergency.</p>
<p>In this study, our aim was to test the effectiveness of an intervention designed to increase the likelihood that high school students with food allergies will carry unexpired auto-injectable epinephrine with them at all times while in school. This study found that there was no difference in the control and intervention groups when examining the proportion of students who had their epinephrine available for use on the initial or final check by the school nurse. Our hypothesis that students who had four additional checks for epinephrine would be more likely to have epinephrine available for use than those students who only received a routine check at the beginning of the school year was not supported by the findings. For those students who did have epinephrine available at the end of the school year, however, the intervention group actually had a slight decrease in the number of students with expired epinephrine, whereas the control group had an increase in the number of students with expired epinephrine. It is possible that the periodic checks were an effective reminder for students to check the expiration date and obtain new medication when needed. This finding needs to be validated with a larger sample of students.</p>
<p>Overall, 65% of the adolescents (62% in the intervention group and 68% in the control group) had epinephrine available for emergency use when asked by the school nurse. These results are consistent with previous study findings by the Food Allergy Anaphylaxis Network in which only 61% of adolescents reported always carrying their epinephrine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1059840511431459">Sampson et al., 2006</xref>). The rate is slightly higher than the rate reported by the 2008 Massachusetts High School Survey, in which 58% of students authorized to carry epinephrine had it on their person when asked randomly by the school nurse. Likewise, the rate of students with unexpired epinephrine available was 53% compared to 48% in the 2008 Massachusetts High School Survey. It is possible that these modest increases could be attributed to the educational intervention provided to students at the beginning of the school year. </p>
<p>Due to small numbers in the groups, we were not able to analyze the different types of educational interventions but treated them all the same. This could be a limitation of the study and might be accounted for in future studies. Also, it would have been difficult to attribute any changes in the availability of epinephrine to the implementation of multiple checks for epinephrine throughout the school year versus the implementation of a standardized educational program at the beginning of the school year. Due to the life-threatening nature of anaphylaxis, a decision was made by the research team to make the educational intervention available to both the control and the intervention group to ensure the safety of students. The education may have had an impact on increasing the likelihood that students would carry epinephrine that was independent of the periodic checks. Other limitations of this study included the small sample size and the use of convenience samples in selecting schools and study participants.</p>
<p>The adolescent with life-threatening allergies is at greater risk for a fatal anaphylactic event. Data from this study as well as other studies show that only about half of those adolescents with a life-threatening allergy tend to carry unexpired epinephrine available for emergency use. This study leaves us with many questions. Further research is needed to identify evidence-based practices that address the safety issue of adolescents with life-threatening allergies.</p>
<p>Qualitative studies that explore adolescents’ perspective on obstacles to carrying epinephrine and their recommendations for improving compliance would be an appropriate first step. In one such study that interviewed 18 adolescents with food allergies, participants reported that the devices were not convenient to carry and they would be more likely to carry them if they were smaller. Adolescents also admitted that they frequently just forgot to carry their devices or would only carry them when they perceived a significant risk of being exposed to an allergen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059840511431459">Monks et al., 2010</xref>). Further studies need to be conducted to validate these findings and further explore adolescents’ recommendations for improving compliance with carrying epinephrine. Understanding more fully the many factors that influence adolescents’ decisions to carry epinephrine is important. For example, does the adolescent who has never had an anaphylactic reaction fail to place importance on carrying the epinephrine, when other treatment methods have worked in previous allergic reactions?</p>
<p>A potential explanation for the failure of this intervention to improve the likelihood that adolescents with life-threatening allergies would carry epinephrine is the fact that the checks were done at random. Perhaps, students would have been more likely to have epinephrine available if there were a structured process in place that required students to report to the health office on a regular basis, for example, monthly, to check for the availability of unexpired epinephrine. Future studies should test this hypothesis.</p>
<p>Examining the characteristics of students who carry epinephrine versus those that do not may provide valuable information in understanding factors that influence adolescents’ decision to have epinephrine available. Also, more research is needed to determine parents’ level of understanding regarding the management of their child with life-threatening allergies and the specific obstacles they face in ensuring their child’s safety. Another important avenue for research is the use of technology such as smart phones or text messaging to remind students to carry their epinephrine. Future studies which control for extenuating factors such as income, previous anaphylaxis, family barriers, cost may identify potential barriers for obtaining unexpired epinephrine. Further qualitative studies involving adolescents with life-threatening allergies and their families should be conducted to identify socioeconomic factors that may impact the availability of having unexpired epinephrine. For example, is the cost of the epinephrine too high for some families? Do barriers exist for a family in ensuring that prescriptions are filled and picked up?</p>
<p>This research study begins an important course of study to determine effective ways to prevent life-threatening anaphylaxis in adolescents and to promote safer habits in carrying of this important medication.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors would like to acknowledge Deborah L. Barnard, RN, MEd, and Susan Aries, RN, BSN, for the research and development of the educational intervention used in this study: <italic>Allergies, Anaphylaxis and Epinephrine, Education Program for High School Students.</italic> They would also like to acknowledge the following 11 MASNRN school nurses for their efforts in conducting this study in their respective schools: Mary Beth Brow, RN, MSN, NCSN; Peggy Coleman, RN, MSN, CAGS; Doreen Crowe, RN, BSN Med; Patricia Emmons, RN, BSN, NCSN; Susan Lofquist, RN; Paula L. Mueller, RN, MSN, NCSN; Mary Patch, RN; Lois Pencinger, RN, BSN, NCSN Med; Patricia O’Hara Rok, RN, NCSN, MA; Nancy Thorsen, RN; and Karen Trevenen, RN.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn4-1059840511431459">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn5-1059840511431459">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The author(s) received a NASN (National Association of School Nurses) Research Award to conduct this research study.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr2-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">American Academy of Allergy, Asthma, and Immunology; American College of Allergy, Asthma and Immunology; Joint Council of Allergy, Asthma and Immunology; Joint Task Force on Practice Parameters</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The diagnosis and management of anaphylaxis: An updated practice parameter</article-title>. <source>Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology</source>, <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>S483</fpage>–<lpage>S523</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barnard</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aries</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Allergies, anaphylaxis and epinephrine education program for students</source>. <publisher-name>Podium presentation at NASN Annual Meeting</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bartley</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marchitto</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kosiorowski</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boulden</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Anaphylaxis—Is your school ready?</article-title> <source>NASN Newsletter</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ben-Shosha</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kagan</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Primeau</surname>
<given-names>M. N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alizadehfar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verreault</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J. W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clarke</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Availability of epinephrine at school in children with peanut allergy</article-title>. <source>Annals of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bock</surname>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Munoz-Furlong</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sampson</surname>
<given-names>H. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Fatalities due to anaphylactic reactions to foods</article-title>. <source>Journal Allergy &amp; Clinical Immunology</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Braganza</surname>
<given-names>S. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Acworth</surname>
<given-names>J. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McKinnon</surname>
<given-names>D. R. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peake</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>A. F. T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Pediatric emergency department anaphylaxis: Different patterns from adults</article-title>. <source>Archives of Diseases in Children</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Branum</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lukacs</surname>
<given-names>S. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Food allergy among children in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>124</volume>, <fpage>1549</fpage>–<lpage>1555</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Crowe</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spina</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McIntyre</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pulcini</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>June 2009</year>). <source>High school students’ compliance with carrying auto-injectable epinephrine</source>. <publisher-name>Poster session presented at the annual meeting of the National Association of School Nurses</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Silva</surname>
<given-names>I. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mehr</surname>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tey</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>M. L. K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Pediatric anaphylaxis: A 5 year retrospective review</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>1071</fpage>–<lpage>1076</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>R. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <source>Statistical methods and scientific inference</source> (<edition>3rd ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hafner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease</collab> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of food allergy in the United States: Report of the NIAID-sponsored expert panel</article-title>. <source>Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology</source>,<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>S1</fpage>–<lpage>S58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Springston</surname>
<given-names>E. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Warrier</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pongracic</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holl</surname>
<given-names>J. L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The prevalence, severity and distribution of childhood food allergy in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <comment>128, e9-17.</comment> </citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kapoor</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bynoe</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gaughan</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Habibi</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Influence of a multidisciplinary pediatric allergy clinic on parental knowledge and rate of subsequent allergic reactions</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lipsey</surname>
<given-names>M. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Design sensitivity</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marklund</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilde-Larsson</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahlstedt</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nordstrom</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Adolescents’ experiences of being food-hypersensitive: A qualitative study</article-title>. <source>BMC Nursing</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6955/6/8">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6955/6/8</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McIntyre</surname>
<given-names>C. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sheetz</surname>
<given-names>A. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>C. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>M. C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The administration of epinephrine for life-threatening allergies in the school setting</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>1134</fpage>–<lpage>1140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McIntyre</surname>
<given-names>C. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sheetz</surname>
<given-names>A. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Franks</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gapinski</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gorak</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>July 2006</year>). <source>Epinephrine administration in schools</source>. <publisher-name>Poster session presented at the annual meeting of the National Association of School Nurses</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Massachusetts Department of Public Health, Bureau of Family and Community Health, Statistics and Evaluation</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <source>The Essential School Health Program Data Report 2006-2007 School Year</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MADPH</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Massachusetts Department of Public Health, Bureau of Family and Community Health, Statistics and Evaluation</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>The Essential School Health Program Data Report 2008-2009 School Year</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MADPH</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Monks</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gowland</surname>
<given-names>M. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacKenzie</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erlewyn-Lajeunesse</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lucas</surname>
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>How do teenagers manage their food allergies?</article-title> <source>Clinical &amp; Experimental Allergy</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1533</fpage>–<lpage>1540</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, National Institute of Health/Department of Health and Human Services</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). When should students with asthma or allergies carry and self-administer emergency medications at school? <comment>Retrieved June 8, 2007, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/prof/lung/asthma/emer_med.htm">http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/prof/lung/asthma/emer_med.htm</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nowak-Wegzyn</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Connover-Walker</surname>
<given-names>M. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>R. A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Food-allergic reactions in schools and preschools</article-title>. <source>Archives of Pediatrics and Adolescent Medicine</source>, <volume>155</volume>, <fpage>790</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Venter</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grundy</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clayton</surname>
<given-names>C. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arshad</surname>
<given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dean</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of sensitization to food allergens, reported adverse reaction to foods, food avoidance, and food hypersensitivity among teenagers</article-title>. <source>Journal Allergy &amp; Clinical Immunology</source>, <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>884</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sampson</surname>
<given-names>H. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mendelson</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>J. P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Fatal and near-fatal anaphylactic reactions to food in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>The New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>237</volume>, <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sampson</surname>
<given-names>H. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Munoz-Furlong</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sicherer</surname>
<given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Risk-taking and coping strategies of adolescents and young adults with food allergy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>1440</fpage>–<lpage>1445</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sicherer</surname>
<given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Forman</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Noone</surname>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Use assessment of self-administered epinephrine among food-allergic children and pediatricians</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1059840511431459">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sicherer</surname>
<given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mahr</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, &amp; <collab collab-type="author">Section on Allergy and Immunology</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Management of Food Allergy in the School Setting</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>126</volume>, <fpage>1232</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>