<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LUP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splup</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lupus</journal-id>
<journal-title>Lupus</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0961-2033</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0962</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0961203311433917</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0961203311433917</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A case of lupus erythematosus profundus with multiple arc-shaped erythematous plaques on the scalp and a review of the literature</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Tsuzaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0961203311433917"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0961203311433917">Department of Dermatology, Tokyo Women's Medical University, Japan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0961203311433917">Satoko Tsuzaka, MD, Department of Dermatology, Tokyo Women's Medical University, 8-1 Kawada-cho, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 162-8666 Japan Email: <email>phsyd699@yahoo.co.jp</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>662</fpage>
<lpage>665</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012. Reprints and permissions: http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A 26-year-old Japanese female presented to us with a 2-year history of multiple arc-shaped erythematous lesions on her scalp and the right side of her forehead. Histopathological examination of two of the lesions showed lobular and septal panniculitis with deposits of IgG in the basement membrane zone. We diagnosed the case as lupus erythematosus profundus, and successfully treated her with 20 mg/day prednisolone. To our knowledge, there has been only one previously reported case of lupus erythematosus profundus with annular-shaped erythematous lesions and six cases with linear configuration.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Arc-shaped erythema</kwd>
<kwd>Blaschko’s line</kwd>
<kwd>linear erythema</kwd>
<kwd>lupus erythematosus profundus</kwd>
<kwd>scalp</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0961203311433917" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Lupus erythematosus profundus (LEP), which was named by Irang in 1940,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0961203311433917">1</xref></sup> was first described as subcutaneous nodules in lupus erythematosus (LE) by Kaposi in 1883. Irang stressed that LEP was a distinct clinical entity of chronic LE and the diagnosis could be made only by histopathological examination.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0961203311433917">1</xref></sup> Clinically, the disease usually appears with chronic, erythematous tender subcutaneous nodules or plaques. The histological findings reveal deep dermal and subcutaneous lymphocytic infiltrates, panniculitis. LEP presenting with arc- or annular-shaped lesions is very rare, and only one case has been previously reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0961203311433917">2</xref></sup> Here, we report another case of LEP with erythematous lesions presenting in an arc-shaped configuration.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-0961203311433917" sec-type="cases"><title>Case report</title>
<p>A 26-year-old Japanese female presented to us in August 2007 with a 2-year history of multiple erythematous plaques on her scalp. A physical examination revealed an arc-shaped indurated erythema on the right side of her forehead, and multiple arc-shaped erythematous plaques with hair loss on her scalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0961203311433917">Figure 1</xref>). She had no other symptoms, such as fever, arthralgia or general fatigue, and had no signs of Sjögren syndrome. Laboratory examinations disclosed normal blood cell counts, urine test, complements, and no liver or renal dysfunctions. LE test, anti-double-stranded DNA antibody, anti-single-stranded DNA antibody, anti-Sm antibody and anti-La (SS-B) antibody were negative. Antinuclear antibody (ANA, titer 1:1280, speckled pattern) and anti-Ro (SS-A) antibody (12.3 IU/ml) were positive. Ophthalmological and otolaryngological examinations revealed no specific findings for Sjögren syndrome. Histopathological examination of two lesions on her scalp and the right side of her forehead showed perivascular lymphocytic infiltrations in the dermis, and lobular and septal panniculitis with prominent lymphocytic infiltrations without liquefaction degeneration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0961203311433917">Figure 2(a)</xref>).
<fig id="fig1-0961203311433917" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Patient on presentation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311433917-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig2-0961203311433917" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(a) Lobular and septal panniculitis with prominent lymphocytic infiltrations (b) Alcian blue staining revealing the accumulation of acid mucopolysaccharides in the dermis and in the subcutaneous tissue.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311433917-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Stromal mucin deposition is one of the common histological characteristics of LE including LEP. Alcian blue staining, which is designed to show mucin deposition as blue to bluish green, revealed the accumulation of acid mucopolysaccharides in the dermis and in the subcutaneous tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0961203311433917">Figure 2(b)</xref>). Direct immunofluorescence examination of the biopsy specimens showed granular deposits of IgG in the basement membrane zone. Based on those clinical and histological features, we diagnosed the patient as LEP.</p>
<p>The inflammation of LEP is too deep, in the adipose tissue, to treat with topical steroids effectively. Therefore, a systemic treatment is appropriate in LEP cases of the scalp to avoid formation of scarring and alopecia. Although oral hydrochloroquine is beneficial for LEP, it is not covered by insurance in Japan. For these reasons, treatment with oral prednisolone at 20 mg/day was initiated in August 2007. Significant improvement was observed within 2 weeks, and most erythematous lesions and the hair loss disappeared without scar formation within 4 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0961203311433917">Figure 3</xref>). We reduced the dose of prednisolone gradually, and discontinued it in July 2009. So far, there has been no recurrence.
<fig id="fig3-0961203311433917" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Clinical features at 4 months after treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311433917-fig3.tif"/></fig></p></sec>
<sec id="sec3-0961203311433917" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>LEP is a variant of LE that primarily affects subcutaneous fat. Nearly all cases of LEP have indurated erythematous plaques and nodules, and occasionally there are ulcers, which usually involve the face, proximal extremities, trunk and buttocks. Lesions may be tender and painful and they frequently heal with depressed skin atrophy. The histological features show a lobular panniculitis with dense infiltrations of lymphocytes, plasma cells and histiocytes. In some cases, mucinous changes and foci of calcifications are seen.</p>
<p>To diagnose a case as LEP, there are several differential diagnoses, such as Jessner’s lymphocytic infiltration of the skin, lupus tumidus and annular erythema associated with LE. Jessner’s lymphocytic infiltration of the skin is characterized by demarcated infiltrated red plaques. Lupus tumidus is known as the dermal form of LE without surface changes, which shows indurated plaques without erythema and atrophy of the surface. Annular erythema has been associated with LE and/or Sjögren syndrome which is positive for anti-Ro(SS-A) and anti-La(SS-B) antibodies. Although the clinical features of those diseases are similar to LEP, the histological findings, which show inflammation of the dermis mainly, are different from those of LEP, which is associated with panniculitis.</p>
<p>There has been only one case with annular or arc-shaped erythematous lesions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0961203311433917">2</xref></sup> and six cases with linear LEP,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0961203311433917">3</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311433917">7</xref></sup> among about 300 reports of LEP in the literature since 1983 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0961203311433917">Table 1</xref>). In those eight reported cases (including our case) the scalp was involved in four cases, the forehead and the arm in three cases each, and the axilla, the lower extremity and the breast in one case each. It has been pointed out that cases of linear cutaneous LE, which is a variant of discoid lupus erythematosus (DLE), often follow Blaschko’s lines.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0961203311433917">8</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0961203311433917">10</xref></sup> Referring to LEP, Nagai et al. reported a case with linear LEP on the scalp following the lines of Blaschko.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311433917">6</xref></sup> In that case, they described one of the two linear lesions on the scalp as an arch-shaped lesion, which curved gently. Linear lesions of LEP might follow Blaschko’s lines and show linear, annular or arc-shaped configurations depending on the area involved, although the exact pattern of Blaschko’s lines on the head and neck is not known<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961203311433917">11</xref></sup> and the mechanism by which these lesions follow the lines of Blaschko is currently unclear.
<table-wrap id="table1-0961203311433917" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of LEP with linear, annular, and arc-shaped configurations</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0961203311433917" xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311433917-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>No.</th>
<th>Report</th>
<th>Age</th>
<th>Sex</th>
<th>Localization</th>
<th>Clinical configuration</th>
<th>Interval from onset to treatment</th>
<th>Treatment(dose)</th>
<th>Prognosis</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Tada et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0961203311433917">3</xref></sup></td>
<td>9</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>left lower extremity</td>
<td>linear</td>
<td>6 months</td>
<td>topical corticosteroid</td>
<td>decrease of nodules</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Innocenzi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0961203311433917">4</xref></sup></td>
<td>17</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>breast, right arm</td>
<td>linear</td>
<td>3 years</td>
<td>uncertain</td>
<td>uncertain</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Tamada et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0961203311433917">5</xref></sup></td>
<td>19</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>arm</td>
<td>linear</td>
<td>1 year</td>
<td>intralesional injection of steroid</td>
<td>decrease of indurated lesions</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>Nagai et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311433917">6</xref></sup></td>
<td>10</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>scalp, forehead</td>
<td>linear</td>
<td>2 months</td>
<td>topical corticosteroid</td>
<td>improvement but alopecia remained</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Marzano et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311433917">7</xref></sup></td>
<td>21</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>scalp, forehead</td>
<td>linear</td>
<td>A few months</td>
<td>intralesional injection of steroid</td>
<td>no change</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Marzano et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311433917">7</xref></sup></td>
<td>32</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>right arm</td>
<td>linear</td>
<td>3 years</td>
<td>m-PSL*(32 mg/day), hydrochloroquine (200 mg/day)</td>
<td>Improvement with depressions</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>Bacanli et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0961203311433917">2</xref></sup></td>
<td>16</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>scalp, left axilla</td>
<td>annular</td>
<td>2 years</td>
<td>Hydrochloroquine (200 mg/day)</td>
<td>significant improvement</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>Our case</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>scalp, forehead</td>
<td>arc-shaped</td>
<td>2 years</td>
<td>PSL**(20 mg/day)</td>
<td>complete improvement without alopecia or depressions</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0961203311433917"><p>m-PSL*: methylprednisolone.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0961203311433917"><p>PSL**: prednisolone.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Regarding the eight reported cases of LEP with linear, arc-shaped or annular configurations, they were initially treated with oral hydrochloroquine, topical or oral corticosteroids, or intralesional injection of steroids 2 months to 3 years after the onset of the skin eruptions. In the three cases with scalp lesions other than our case, one case had no response to an intralesional injection of steroid, the alopecia of another case remained after topical corticosteroid treatment, and another case had significant improvement following oral hydrochloroquine. It is remarkable that our case resulted in complete remission without any scar formation or alopecia. We think that sufficient control of the inflammation by the oral corticosteroid was responsible for this successful result, and that treatment of LEP should be started at an early inflammatory stage to avoid after effects, skin depressions and alopecia, especially for lesions on the scalp.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec4-0961203311433917"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-0961203311433917"><title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p></sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0961203311433917"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lupus erythematosus profundus</article-title>. <source>Arch Dermatol Syphilol</source> <year>1940</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0961203311433917"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bacanli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciftcioglu</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alpsoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case of lupus erythematosus profundus with unusual manifestations</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0961203311433917"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear lupus erythematosus profundus in a child</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>871</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0961203311433917"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Innocenzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pranteda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Giombini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Silipo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottoni</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear lupus erythematosus profundus in an adolescent</article-title>. <source>Eur J Dermatol</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0961203311433917"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Arisawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear lupus erythematosus profundus in a young man</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0961203311433917"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear lupus erythematosus profundus</article-title>. <source>Eur J Dermatol</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0961203311433917"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marzano</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alessi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sclerodermic linear lupus panniculitis: Report of two cases</article-title>. <source>Dermatology</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>210</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0961203311433917"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyachi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear cutaneous lupus erythematosus following the lines of Blaschko</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0961203311433917"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear childhood discoid lupus erythematosus following the lines of Blaschko: A case report with a review of the linear manifestations of lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0961203311433917"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>K-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>K-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linear cutaneous lupus erythematosus in the lines of Blaschko</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>396</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0961203311433917"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Happle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Assim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The lines of Blaschko on the head and neck</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>