<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Preventive Cardiology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2047-4873</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2047-4881</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1741826711424494</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1741826711424494</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original scientific papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effects of additional blood pressure and lipid measurements on the prediction of cardiovascular risk</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>Katy</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1741826711424494"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayen</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>McGeechan</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>Bruce</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>Les</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1741826711424494">University of Sydney, NSW, Australia.</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1741826711424494">Katy Bell, Screening and Test Evaluation Program (STEP), School of Public Health, Building A27, University of Sydney, NSW 2006, Australia Email: <email>katy.bell@sydney.edu.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1474</fpage>
<lpage>1485</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The European Society of Cardiology 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">European Society of Cardiology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background:</bold> Current guidelines recommend that decisions to start preventative therapy for cardiovascular disease (CVD) should be based on absolute risk; however, current risk equations are based on single measurements of risk factors. We aimed to assess whether two measurements of blood pressure and lipids improves the prediction of cardiovascular risk compared to one measurement.</p>
<p><bold>Methods and results:</bold> We used sex-specific Cox proportional hazards models to evaluate the risk of first CVD event in 2385 participants of the Framingham Offspring Study attending both the second and third visits. We estimated the effects on risk prediction of using the average of two measurements of blood pressure, total cholesterol, and HDL cholesterol compared to using one measurement of the risk factors. We found that these risk factors were each markedly more predictive of CVD when the average of two measurements was used rather than one measurement and age was less predictive of CVD. There were small improvements in the overall model fit, discrimination, and calibration. Reclassification also showed small improvements across the risk spectrum (net reclassification information, NRI, for women 3.0%, 95% CI −0.9 to 24.8%; NRI for men 4.0%, 95% CI −2.2 to 14.1%) and possibly greater improvements for intermediate-risk individuals (NRI for women 32.3%, 95% CI −21.9 to 46.8%; NRI for men 16.0%, 95% CI −3.3 to 43%).</p>
<p><bold>Conclusions:</bold> Averaging two measurements of blood pressure and lipids results in marked increases in the predictiveness of these risk factors and smaller improvements in the overall prediction of cardiovascular risk including reclassification.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Blood pressure</kwd>
<kwd>cardiovascular diseases</kwd>
<kwd>cholesterol</kwd>
<kwd>reproducibility of results</kwd>
<kwd>risk assessment</kwd>
<kwd>risk factors</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1741826711424494" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Increasingly, clinical guidelines recommend that the decision to start therapy to lower blood pressure (BP) or cholesterol be based on the individual's overall absolute risk of a cardiovascular disease (CVD) event.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711424494">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741826711424494">4</xref></sup> Cardiovascular risk prediction scores such as the Framingham equation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711424494">5</xref></sup> assess an individual's absolute risk using multiple risk factors, including cholesterol, BP, smoking history, and diabetes, and demographic variables such as sex and age. Risk scores provide a more accurate prediction of future CVD events than single risk factors considered alone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1741826711424494">6</xref></sup> However, there is considerable room for improvement in the prediction of risk of cardiovascular disease. With currently available risk prediction scores, over 50% of CVD events in a 10-year period among asymptomatic adults will occur among individuals identified as low risk.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1741826711424494">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Single risk factors like BP and cholesterol show substantial variation within an individual over time.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711424494">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711424494">9</xref></sup> Some of this variability is due to true long-term changes in the risk factor, because of the natural history of the disease or the effects of treatment. There is also ‘measurement variability’ due to both short-term biological fluctuations in the risk factors and measurement error inherent in the monitoring test. Better cardiovascular prediction may be achieved by making multiple measurements of cholesterol and BP,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1741826711424494">10</xref></sup> rather than the single measurements used by current risk prediction tools.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711424494">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1741826711424494">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1741826711424494">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>Multiple measurements may be of benefit for a number of reasons. By averaging the measurements taken over the short term, a more accurate estimation of an individual's true risk factor level is possible, with an increase in the predictive power of the risk factor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1741826711424494">13</xref></sup> Though not the focus of the current study, estimation of time trend is possible over a longer period which may also be of predictive value.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1741826711424494">14</xref></sup> Finally, the level of variability in the risk factor itself is increasingly recognized as an important risk factor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1741826711424494">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1741826711424494">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>The objective of this study was to assess whether a decrease in measurement variability with the use of two measurements of cholesterol and BP taken over the short term improves the prediction of cardiovascular risk compared to the usual practice of using just one measurement of these risk factors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1741826711424494" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec3-1741826711424494"><title>Study design and sample</title>
<p>Data were obtained on participants from the Framingham Offspring Study (FOS) who were included in the analysis that resulted in the 2008 Framingham risk equation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711424494">5</xref></sup> Participants were eligible if they attended the first or third examination cycles of the FOS and were free from CVD, aged 30–74 years of age, and had non-missing data on covariates used in the 2008 risk equation.</p>
<p>As there was an 8-year interval between the first and second visits of the FOS, we restricted our analysis to participants with data available on BP and lipids from both the second visit (1980–83) and third visit (1984–87), which resulted in a study sample of 2835 participants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1741826711424494"><title>Measurement of risk factors</title>
<p>For BP and lipid measurements, we used values from both the second and third visits. For all other risk factors we used values from the third visit. Blood pressure measurements were made on the left arm of the seated participants with a mercury-column sphygmomanometer and an appropriately sized cuff; the average of two physician-obtained measures constituted the examination BP. Serum total and HDL cholesterol levels were determined with standardized enzymatic methods. Cigarette smoking status was ascertained by self-report. Diabetes was defined as fasting glucose ≥126 mg/dl or use of insulin or oral hypoglycaemic medications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1741826711424494">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>We classified patients as receiving BP-lowering treatment according to their reported treatment at visit 3 (as ascertained by the physician examiner at the heart study and based on self-report). Of the 2835 patients, 2355 were not taking BP-lowering treatment at either visit 2 or 3, approximately 206 patients were taking treatment at visit 3 who were not taking treatment at visit 2, 30 patients were not taking treatment at visit 3 who were taking treatment at visit 2, and 214 patients were taking treatment at both visit 2 and visit 3. Of the 2835 patients, 2807 were not taking lipid-lowering treatment at either visit 2 or 3, 11 patients were taking treatment at visit 3 who were not taking treatment at visit 2, nine patients were not taking treatment at visit 3 who were taking treatment at visit 2, and eight patients were taking treatment at both visit 2 and visit 3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1741826711424494"><title>Follow up and outcome events</title>
<p>All study participants were under continuous surveillance for the development of CVD events and death. CVD was defined as a composite of CHD (coronary death, myocardial infarction, coronary insufficiency, and angina), cerebrovascular events (including ischaemic stroke, haemorrhagic stroke, and transient ischaemic attack), peripheral artery disease (intermittent claudication), and heart failure. Information about CVD events on follow up was obtained from medical histories, physical examinations at the study clinic, hospitalization records, and communication with personal physicians. All suspected new events were reviewed by a panel of three experienced investigators who evaluated all pertinent medical records. A separate review committee that included a neurologist adjudicated cerebrovascular events, and a heart study neurologist examined most participants with suspected stroke.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711424494">5</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1741826711424494"><title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>We first used measurements of risk factors from the third visit to build comparison models for assessing subsequent models. In agreement with the previous analysis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711424494">5</xref></sup> we built separate Cox proportional hazard models for men (<italic>n</italic> = 1351) and women (<italic>n</italic> = 1484) using a maximum of 12-year follow up and with a log transformation applied to all continuous predictors. Further details of the estimation of hazard ratios are given in the supplementary online material.</p>
<p>Next, we built models that included the average of measurements of BP and lipids from the second and third visits and compared regression coefficients between the two sets of models. To investigate whether variability in BP and lipids predicted CVD risk, we also built models that included change in risk factor levels both instead of, and as well as, the average of risk factor levels.</p>
<p>We assessed any improvements in both the discrimination (c-statistic, the equivalent of area under the receiver operating curve) and calibration (Hosmer–Lemeshow statistic) of models containing the averaged measurements. Further details of the estimation of the Hosmer–Lemeshow calibration plots are given in the supplementary online material. We also examined reclassification that arose from using the averaged measurements through net reclassification information (NRI). Because nested models are required for estimating reclassification, the ‘averaged’ models were fitted with both measurement occasions as separate variables rather than an average of the two. Thresholds of 10% and 20% 10-year risk of CVD were used to calculate the NRI. Programs modified for survival analysis with incomplete follow up were used to calculate each of these measures. Plots of calibration and reclassification were constructed to aid interpretation of the results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1741826711424494">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1741826711424494">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Finally, we assessed the extent to which differences between the original and preceding clinic visits could be attributable to measurement error, rather than real change. We compared the distributions of the measurements made at the second and third visits and calculated the mean, standard deviation, and coefficient of variation for change between the two measurements. We also compared Cox models that used either measurements from the second visit or measurements from the third visit to assess any change in regression coefficients that might suggest real change in risk factor levels between the two visits.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1741826711424494" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>The risk factor characteristics of men and women in our sample at the baseline examinations are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1741826711424494">Table 1</xref>. In our middle-aged sample, mean levels of serum total cholesterol and the prevalence of cigarette smoking were similar among men and women. Men had higher mean levels of systolic BP and lower mean serum HDL cholesterol than women and were more likely to have diabetes and to use BP-lowering treatment. The median length of follow up was 12 years for both men and women.
<table-wrap id="table1-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary statistics for risk factors at visit 3</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1741826711424494" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Characteristic</th>
<th>Women (<italic>n</italic> = 1484)</th>
<th>Men (<italic>n</italic> = 1351)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td>48.3 ± 9.4</td>
<td>48.6 ± 9.5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Total cholesterol (mg/dl)</td>
<td>211.1 ± 42.5</td>
<td>211.9 ± 38.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>HDL cholesterol (mg/dl)</td>
<td>57.2 ± 14.9</td>
<td>44.9 ± 11.8</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Systolic BP (mmHg)</td>
<td>121.3 ± 17.4</td>
<td>125.8 ± 15.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>BP treatment</td>
<td>177 (11.9)</td>
<td>193 (14.3)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Smoking</td>
<td>421 (28.4)</td>
<td>357 (26.4)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes</td>
<td>54 (3.6)</td>
<td>89 (6.6)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Subsequent CVD events</td>
<td>77 (5.2)</td>
<td>207 (15.3)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1741826711424494"><p>Values are mean±SD or <italic>n</italic> (%). BP, blood pressure; CVD, cardiovascular disease; HDL, high-density lipoprotein.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<sec id="sec8-1741826711424494"><title>Estimates of effect of risk factors</title>
<p>The multivariable-adjusted regression coefficients and hazard ratios for risk factors on the log scale are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1741826711424494">Table 2</xref>, and hazard ratios for risk factors on the natural scale are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1741826711424494">Table 3</xref>. Inclusion of the average of risk factor levels resulted in greater predictive ability for BP and total cholesterol in both men and women. This was especially noticeable for systolic BP in women and men and total cholesterol in women, with approximate doubling of hazard ratios for the averaged models on the log scale. On the natural scale, hazard ratios for 50% greater levels of BP or total cholesterol were approximately one-fifth to one-third higher for the averaged models compared to the single measurement models. For example, when using the average of two measurements, a man on antihypertensive treatment with a systolic BP of 195 mmHg has a 2.76 times higher risk of disease compared to a man on antihypertensive treatment with a systolic BP 130 mmHg. Using one measurement, a man on antihypertensive treatment with a systolic BP of 195 mmHg has only a 2.05 times higher risk of disease compared to a man on antihypertensive treatment with a systolic BP 130 mmHg.
<table-wrap id="table2-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Regression coefficients and hazard ratios on the log scale</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1741826711424494" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="3">Log variable</th>
<th colspan="4">Number of measurement of SBP, total cholesterol, and HDL cholesterol<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th colspan="2">One<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Two<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>β</th>
<th>HR (95% CI)</th>
<th>β</th>
<th>HR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Women (<italic>n</italic> = 1484, events = 77)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>3.21 (0.68–15.22)</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>1.98 (0.40–9.91)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Total cholesterol</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>9.04 (2.69–30.35)</td>
<td>2.96</td>
<td>19.28 (5.03–73.89)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> HDL cholesterol</td>
<td>−0.08</td>
<td>0.92 (0.40–2.14)</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>0.75 (0.30–1.85)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if not treated</td>
<td>2.56</td>
<td>12.97 (1.94–86.7)</td>
<td>3.06</td>
<td>21.24 (2.19–205.56)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if treated</td>
<td>2.72</td>
<td>15.20 (2.34–98.94)</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>24.36 (2.63–226.15)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Smoking</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.60 (0.98–2.61)</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>1.66 (1.02–2.72)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>1.32 (0.62–2.81)</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>1.19 (0.56–2.53)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Men (<italic>n</italic> = 1351, events = 207)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>23.72 (9.60–58.60)</td>
<td>2.97</td>
<td>19.57 (7.89–48.50)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Total cholesterol</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>2.60 (1.19–5.67)</td>
<td>1.19</td>
<td>3.28 (1.36–7.90)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> HDL cholesterol</td>
<td>−0.81</td>
<td>0.45 (0.26–0.77)</td>
<td>−1.00</td>
<td>0.37 (0.20–0.67)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if not treated</td>
<td>1.71</td>
<td>5.55 (1.64–18.78)</td>
<td>2.46</td>
<td>11.69 (2.87–47.71)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if treated</td>
<td>1.77</td>
<td>5.89 (1.77–19.67)</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>12.23 (3.07–48.82)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Smoking</td>
<td>0.67</td>
<td>1.95 (1.45–2.62)</td>
<td>0.68</td>
<td>1.98 (1.47–2.67)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>2.48 (1.73–3.56)</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>2.39 (1.67–3.43)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1741826711424494"><p>HDL, high-density lipoprotein; HR, hazard ratio; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Hazard ratios on the natural scale</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1741826711424494" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Variable</th>
<th colspan="2">25% greater<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">50% greater<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>One measurement</th>
<th>Two measurements</th>
<th>One measurement</th>
<th>Two measurements</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Women (<italic>n</italic> = 1484, events = 77)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>1.30</td>
<td>1.17</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>1.32</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Total cholesterol</td>
<td>1.63</td>
<td>1.94</td>
<td>2.44</td>
<td>3.32</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> HDL cholesterol</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.97</td>
<td>0.89</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if not treated</td>
<td>1.77</td>
<td>1.98</td>
<td>2.82</td>
<td>3.46</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if treated</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>2.04</td>
<td>3.01</td>
<td>3.65</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Smoking</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>1.66</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.32</td>
<td>1.19</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Men (<italic>n</italic> = 1351, events = 207)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>2.03</td>
<td>1.94</td>
<td>3.62</td>
<td>3.33</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Total cholesterol</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>1.30</td>
<td>1.47</td>
<td>1.62</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> HDL cholesterol</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.67</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if not treated</td>
<td>1.46</td>
<td>1.73</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.71</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP if treated</td>
<td>1.48</td>
<td>1.75</td>
<td>2.05</td>
<td>2.76</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Smoking</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.95</td>
<td>1.98</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>2.48</td>
<td>2.39</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1741826711424494"><p>Percentage increment is for each continuous variable where all other variables remain constant. For interpretation of percentage increase, please see Results, Estimates of effect of risk factors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Age was substantially less predictive in the averaged models, while smoking and diabetes remained largely unchanged (the small decrease in predictiveness for diabetes may be explained by the hazard of diabetes being partly mediated through its effects on BP and lipids). For example, using one measurement of lipids and BP, a 60-year-old woman has a 1.60 times higher risk of disease compared to a 40-year-old woman. Using the average of two measurements of lipids and BP a 60-year-old woman has only a 1.32 times higher risk of disease compared to a 40-year-old woman.</p>
<p>Within-person change in risk factor levels was, on the whole, not statistically significant when added instead of, or in addition to, variables based on the average of risk factors (data not shown). The one exception to this was change in HDL cholesterol, which was of borderline significance when added to the averaged model for women (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03), but not significant when added to the model for men (<italic>p</italic> = 0.64).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1741826711424494"><title>Overall model performance</title>
<p>A statistical comparison of overall model performance is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1741826711424494">Table 4</xref>. There were modest improvements in each of: overall model fit, discrimination, calibration, and NRI. The modestly improved calibration is apparent in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1741826711424494">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1741826711424494">2</xref> where data points from the averaged models align more closely to the identity line (where observed risk = predicted risk) than do the non-averaged models.
<fig id="fig1-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Hosmer–Lemeshow calibration plots for women, showing observed and predicted 10-year risk in models using single measurements and the average of two measurements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig2-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Hosmer–Lemeshow calibration plots for men, showing observed and predicted 10-year risk in models using single measurements and the average of two measurements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table4-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Comparison of models</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1741826711424494" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="3">Model</th>
<th rowspan="3">Overall model fit</th>
<th rowspan="3">Discrimination (c-statistic)</th>
<th rowspan="3">Calibration (Hosmer– Lemeshow <italic>p</italic>-value)</th>
<th rowspan="3">Reclassification (NRI)</th>
<th colspan="6">Change across risk threshold (<italic>n</italic>, %)<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th colspan="3">No cardiovascular disease<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Cardiovascular disease<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Downgraded</th>
<th>No change</th>
<th>Upgraded</th>
<th>Downgraded</th>
<th>No change</th>
<th>Upgraded</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="11">Women</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> One measurement</td>
<td>1035.5</td>
<td>0.778</td>
<td>0.29</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean of two measurements</td>
<td>1028.8</td>
<td>0.781</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>35 (2.5)</td>
<td>1350 (94.7)</td>
<td>41 (2.9)</td>
<td>4 (6.9)</td>
<td>43 (74.1)</td>
<td>11 (19.0)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11">Men</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> One measurement</td>
<td>2756.5</td>
<td>0.756</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean of two measurements</td>
<td>2747.4</td>
<td>0.766</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>86 (7.3)</td>
<td>1049 (88.5)</td>
<td>50 (4.2)</td>
<td>10 (6.0)</td>
<td>139 (83.7)</td>
<td>17 (10.2)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1741826711424494"><p>NRI, net reclassification information.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1741826711424494"><title>Reclassification</title>
<p>The effects of reclassification are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1741826711424494">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1741826711424494">4</xref> and detailed results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1741826711424494">Table 5</xref>. Among patients across the risk spectrum, NRI was 3.0% (95% CI −0.9% to 24.8%) for women and 4.0% (95% CI −2.2% to 14.1%) for men. There was slightly more downgrading of risk for non-cases and slightly more upgrading of risk for cases in the averaged models compared to non-averaged models. Amongst women who did not have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 1426), 35 (2.5%) were downgraded across a risk threshold, 1350 (94.7%) were unchanged, and 41 (2.9%) were upgraded. Amongst women who did have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 58), four (6.9%) were downgraded, 43 (74.1%) were unchanged, and 11 (19.0%) were upgraded. Amongst men who did not have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 1185), 86 (7.3%) were downgraded across a risk threshold, 1049 (88.5%) were unchanged, and 50 (4.2%) were upgraded. Amongst men who had an event (<italic>n</italic> = 166), 10 (6.0%) were downgraded across a risk threshold, 139 (83.7%) were unchanged, and 17 (10.2%) were upgraded.
<fig id="fig3-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Reclassification plots for women, showing 10-year risk (a) without cardiovascular disease and (b) with cardiovascular disease.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig4-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Reclassification plots for men, showing 10-year risk (a) without cardiovascular disease and (b) with cardiovascular disease.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table5-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Reclassification of 10-year cardiovascular risk when average of two measurements is used</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1741826711424494" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-table5.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Model with average of two measurements</th>
<th colspan="4">Model with single measurement<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>&lt;10%</th>
<th>10–20%</th>
<th>&gt;20%</th>
<th>Total</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Women</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> No CVD</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &lt;10%</td>
<td>1293</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>2↓</td>
<td>1322</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  10–20%</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>6↓</td>
<td>79</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &gt;20%</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>11↑</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>25</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  Total</td>
<td>1323</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>1426</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> CVD</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &lt;10%</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>36</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  10–20%</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>12</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &gt;20%</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6↑</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>10</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  Total</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>58</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Men</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> No CVD</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &lt;10%</td>
<td>664</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>719</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  10–20%</td>
<td>25↑</td>
<td>240</td>
<td>31↓</td>
<td>296</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &gt;20%</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>25↑</td>
<td>145</td>
<td>170</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  Total</td>
<td>689</td>
<td>320</td>
<td>176</td>
<td>1185</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> CVD</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &lt;10%</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>35</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  10–20%</td>
<td>6↑</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>3↓</td>
<td>52</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  &gt;20%</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>11↑</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>79</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>  Total</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>166</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1741826711424494"><p>Data is for 10-year risk of cardiovascular disease, and number of events is smaller than incidence over full duration of follow up presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1741826711424494">Table 1</xref>. ↓/↑Reclassification down or up across the treatment threshold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>We performed additional analyses restricted to individuals classified as intermediate risk of cardiovascular disease on the basis of single measurements of BP and lipids (10-year predicted risk 10–20%). Among individuals at intermediate risk, the NRI was 32.3% (95% CI −21.9% to 46.8%) for women and 16.0% (95% CI −3.3% to 43.0%) for men. Among women at intermediate-risk who did not have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 81), 27 (33%) were downgraded across a risk threshold, 43 (53%) were unchanged, and 11 (14%) were upgraded. Amongst intermediate-risk women who did have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 17), four (24%) were downgraded, seven (41%) were unchanged, and six (35%) were upgraded. Among intermediate-risk men who did not have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 320), 55 (17%) were downgraded across a risk threshold, 240 (75%) were unchanged, and 25 (8%) were upgraded. Among intermediate-risk men who did have an event (<italic>n</italic> = 61), 7 (11%) were downgraded across a risk threshold, 43 (70%) were unchanged, and 11 (18%) were upgraded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1741826711424494"><title>Comparison of measurement occasions</title>
<p>For each of the BP and cholesterol parameters, the mean level of the two measurements, mean change between them, and standard deviation and coefficient of variation of the changes are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1741826711424494">Table 6</xref>. Over the 4-year period there were small increases in each of these parameters for both women and men. Apart from the small shift in the mean, distributions for the parameters were similar for the second and third visits. Regression coefficients were also similar using values from the second visit compared with the third visit.
<table-wrap id="table6-1741826711424494" position="float"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>Variation in blood pressure and cholesterol change over 4 years</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1741826711424494" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711424494-table6.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Risk factor</th>
<th rowspan="2">Mean at visit 2</th>
<th rowspan="2">Mean at visit 3</th>
<th colspan="2">Change<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Mean ± SD</th>
<th>CV (%)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Women</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP (mmHg)</td>
<td>118.1</td>
<td>121.3</td>
<td>3.1 ± 12.7</td>
<td>7.5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Total cholesterol (mg/dl)</td>
<td>200.6</td>
<td>211.1</td>
<td>10.4 ± 27.6</td>
<td>9.5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> HDL (mg/dl)</td>
<td>54.4</td>
<td>57.2</td>
<td>2.8 ± 9.9</td>
<td>12.5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Men</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SBP (mmHg)</td>
<td>125.2</td>
<td>125.8</td>
<td>0.6 ± 11.6</td>
<td>6.5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Total cholesterol (mg/dl)</td>
<td>204.9</td>
<td>211.9</td>
<td>6.9 ± 25.6</td>
<td>9.4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> HDL (mg/dl)</td>
<td>43.1</td>
<td>44.9</td>
<td>1.8 ± 8.5</td>
<td>13.6</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn8-1741826711424494"><p>Difference between means and mean change may differ slightly due to rounding.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-1741826711424494"><p>CV, coefficient of variation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1741826711424494" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>We found that additional measurement of BP and cholesterol had a considerable impact on estimates of how individual risk factors predict cardiovascular disease, with an increase in the predictiveness of systolic BP (for both untreated individuals and those on BP-lowering therapy), total cholesterol, and HDL cholesterol. This increase in predictiveness was at the expense of a decrease in the predictiveness of age, suggesting that age may act in part as a proxy for the other risk factors that are usually less precisely measured. In contrast, the predictiveness of diabetes and smoking were largely unaffected by additional measurements of BP and cholesterol.</p>
<p>Although there were changes in the predictiveness of individual risk factors, the impact of additional measurements of BP and cholesterol on overall model fit, calibration, and discrimination was small. Nevertheless, there were some improvements in reclassification with the use of two measurements of the risk factors, using risk thresholds of &lt;10% (low risk, longer interval before re-test), 10–20% (intermediate risk, shorter interval before re-test), and &gt;20% (high risk, treat). More individuals of both sexes who ultimately developed disease were upgraded in their risk assessment compared to those who did not develop disease. Preventative treatment would have been appropriately started in an additional 17 individuals (six women and 11 men, 7.6%) and inappropriately stopped in three individuals (no women and three men, 1.3%) if two measurements of the risk factors had been used instead of one (these numbers reflect movements across the 20% risk threshold). Slightly more men and slightly fewer women who did not develop disease were downgraded in their risk assessment compared to those who did develop disease. Preventative treatment would have been appropriately stopped in 39 individuals (eight women and 31 men, 1.5%) and inappropriately started in 36 individuals (11 women and 25 men, 1.4%). Overall these findings suggest that the use risk equations based on two measurements of BP and cholesterol will result in small improvements in risk estimation for both men and women, with improved allocation of treatment to those who will benefit most.</p>
<p>The improvements in classification were especially noticeable among intermediate-risk individuals (although confidence intervals were large given the smaller number of women and men in this risk group). Patients at intermediate risk of an event are perhaps those for whom there is most uncertainty about the need for therapy and who may therefore benefit most from the improved decision making that results from repeat measurement of risk factors. Because the improvements were most marked in the intermediate-risk group, an alternative to re-measurement of BP and lipids in all individuals may be to restrict re-measurement to those individuals who are at intermediate risk of disease on the basis of single measurement of risk factors. Or alternatively, re-measurement might be done in the subset of patients with most potential to shift across the treatment threshold (e.g. those at 15–25% risk).</p>
<p>Although even small shifts in estimated risk with a new risk equation may have substantial implications for the individual when they are near the treatment or testing thresholds, larger shifts in risk are probably needed for the new equation to make a noticeable difference from a population health perspective. For example, treating some individuals who have a true 10-year risk just under 20% (single measurement risk equation) rather than the same number of individuals with a true risk just over 20% (average of two measurements risk equation) may not make a large difference to the absolute risk reduction and number of vascular events prevented. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1741826711424494">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1741826711424494">2</xref> show that, although many of the shifts in risk are only a few percentages, there are a number of individuals who appear to have quite large shifts in risk, including two women without disease who were reclassified from &gt;20% risk (one measurement) to &lt;10% risk (two measurements). Thus it appears that using the average of two measurements rather than one may not only have an effect on treatment decisions at the individual level, but also result in more effective treatment at the population level.</p>
<p>The improvements in overall model performance (overall model fit, discrimination, calibration, and correct reclassification) were at least as great as a number of novel risk factors which have received considerable attention including highly sensitive C-reactive protein and pro-B-type natriuretic peptide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1741826711424494">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1741826711424494">21</xref></sup> Recent evidence suggests Coronary Artery Calcium Score on computed tomography may outperform these other novel markers in the prediction of coronary artery disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1741826711424494">22</xref></sup> However concerns regarding the safety,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1741826711424494">23</xref></sup> expense,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1741826711424494">24</xref></sup> and expertise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1741826711424494">25</xref></sup> needed for this investigation may limit its use. Re-measurement of BP and lipids has the advantages over these other newer tests of being cheap and easy to implement and having minimal side effects. The other newer tests may have incremental value in addition to re-measurement, but we recommend that the introduction of these tests only be considered once measurement of traditional risk factors has been optimized.</p>
<p>The interval between re-measurement in the Framingham Offspring Study was 4 years, much longer than most clinicians would wait to re-measure risk factors before deciding on an individual's overall risk and the need for treatment and/or close follow up. During the 4-year interval, a small proportion of patients started or stopped BP- and lipid-lowering treatment. Although there is likely to be some real change in risk factor levels over this time frame, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1741826711424494">Table 6</xref> suggests that this is small in comparison to differences due to background measurement variability. The mean changes in systolic BP were small, and estimates of the standard deviation and coefficient of variation of change were not much larger than other estimates for short-term changes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1741826711424494">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1741826711424494">28</xref></sup> Although the mean changes were relatively greater for total and HDL cholesterol, they were still modest and estimates of the coefficient of variation of change were not much larger than other estimates for short-term change.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711424494">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1741826711424494">29</xref></sup> We therefore believe our findings may be largely applicable to repeat measurements made over a few weeks or months.</p>
<p>We were unable to demonstrate convincing effects of within-person change in BP or lipids on the risk of cardiovascular disease. This may be because the effects of within-person variability (at least in BP) are more likely to be detected if more than two measurements of the risk factors are used. A recent study which examined the effects of within-person variation in systolic BP for the prediction of stroke and other cardiovascular disease found that, although within-person variation was at least as strong a predictor as individuals’ mean levels, at least six or more readings were needed for estimates to reach statistical significance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1741826711424494">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>Finally, a related issue not explored in this paper is whether it is advantageous to use the average of multiple measurements of risk factors in the existing Framingham equation (which was constructed using single measurements). Anecdotal reports suggest that this may be a common clinical practice, reinforced by practice guidelines that suggest multiple measurements be made before starting treatment.<sup>30–32</sup> Further research is needed to explore the implications of applying risk equations constructed on the basis of single measurements of risk factors to the average of multiple measurements made on an individual.</p>
<p>The results of our study have important implications for practice. First, evidence of increased predictiveness of modifiable risk factors at the expense of age suggests greater potential for prevention of vascular disease burden than might otherwise be thought possible. Likewise, the improvements in overall risk prediction, although small, would be of benefit when applied at the population level. So too, the improvements resulting from reclassification across risk thresholds, which would result in allocation of interventions to those most likely to benefit.</p>
<p>In conclusion, averaging two measurements of systolic BP, total cholesterol, and HDL cholesterol results in marked increases in the predictiveness of these risk factors and smaller improvements in the overall prediction of cardiovascular risk including reclassification. These findings suggest new risk equations based on multiple measurements of these risk factors will be of clinical benefit in the identification and treatment of individuals at high risk of cardiovascular disease.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The Framingham Heart Study (FHS) and the Framingham Offspring Study (FOS) are conducted and supported by the NHLBI in collaboration with the FHS and FOS Study Investigators. This manuscript was prepared using a limited access dataset obtained from the NHLBI and does not necessarily reflect the opinions or views of the FHS, FOS, or the NHLBI. We thank Professor Paul Glasziou for his helpful comments on the presentation of the results.</p></ack>
<sec id="sec13-1741826711424494"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by the Australian National Health and Medical Research Council (grant number 402764).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1741826711424494"><title>Ethical approval</title>
<p>This project was approved by the University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee on 26 May 2009 (reference number 05-2009/11855).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-1741826711424494"><title>Disclosures</title>
<p>None. The funding body had no role in design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1741826711424494"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>National Vascular Disease Prevention Alliance. Guidelines for the assessment of absolute cardiovascular disease risk. 2009</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1741826711424494"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>New Zealand Guideline Group. <italic>The assessment and management of cardiovascular risk</italic>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.nzgg.org.nz">www.nzgg.org.nz</ext-link> [2003, consulted March 2009]</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1741826711424494"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Task Force</collab>. <article-title>European guidelines on cardiovascular disease prevention in clinical practice: executive summary</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehab</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>Supplement 2</issue>): <fpage>E1</fpage>–<lpage>E40</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1741826711424494"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Joint British Societies</collab>. <article-title>JBS 2: Joint British Societies’ guidelines on prevention of cardiovascular disease in clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Heart</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>91</volume>(<issue>Suppl V</issue>): <fpage>v1</fpage>–<lpage>v52</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1741826711424494"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Agostino</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pencina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Massaro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>General cardiovascular risk profile for use in primary care The Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>117</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>753</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1741826711424494"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment with drugs to lower blood pressure and blood cholesterol based on an individual's absolute cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>365</volume>(<issue>9457</issue>): <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1741826711424494"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>KJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Macaskill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of randomized trials to decide when to monitor response to new treatment</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>336</volume>(<issue>7640</issue>): <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1741826711424494"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>KJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Macaskill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mixed models showed no need for initial response monitoring after starting anti-hypertensive therapy</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>62</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>650</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1741826711424494"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Heritier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Simes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>the LIPID Study Investigators.. Monitoring cholesterol levels: measurement error or true change?</article-title> <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>148</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>656</fpage>–<lpage>661</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1741826711424494"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Twomey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wierzbicki</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy of cardiovascular risk estimation for primary prevention in patients without diabetes</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Risk</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1741826711424494"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hippisley-Cox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinogradova</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Derivation and validation of QRISK, a new cardiovascular disease risk score for the United Kingdom: prospective open cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>335</volume>(<issue>7611</issue>): <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1741826711424494"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tunstall-Pedoe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sign Group on Risk Estimation. Adding social deprivation and family history to cardiovascular risk assessment: the ASSIGN score from the Scottish Heart Health Extended Cohort (SHHEC)</article-title>. <source>Heart</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>93</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1741826711424494"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacMahon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorlie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Blood pressure, stroke, and coronary heart disease: Part 1, prolonged differences in blood pressure: prospective observational studies corrected for the regression dilution bias</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>335</volume>(<issue>8692</issue>): <fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>774</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1741826711424494"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Massaro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PWF</given-names></name><name><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antecedent blood pressure and risk of cardiovascular disease.The Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>105</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1741826711424494"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Limitations of the usual blood-pressure hypothesis and importance of variability, instability, and episodic hypertension</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>375</volume>(<issue>9718</issue>): <fpage>938</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1741826711424494"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlöf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic significance of visit-to-visit variability, maximum systolic blood pressure, and episodic hypertension</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>375</volume>(<issue>9718</issue>): <fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1741826711424494"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cupples</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Agostino</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Section 34: some risk factors related to the annual incidence of cardiovascular disease and death in pooled repeated biennial measurements</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kannel</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Framingham Heart Study: 30 year follow-up</source>, <publisher-loc>Bethesda</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name>, <year>1987</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1741826711424494"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGeechan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Macaskill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing new biomarkers and predictive models for use in clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>168</volume>(<issue>21</issue>): <fpage>2304</fpage>–<lpage>2310</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1741826711424494"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGeechan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Macaskill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BEK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of incident stroke events based on retinal vessel caliber: a systematic review and individual-participant meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>170</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1332</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1741826711424494"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melander</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton-Cheh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Almegren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Novel and conventional biomarkers for prediction of incident cardiovascular events in the community</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>302</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1741826711424494"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pencina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Selhub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Agostino</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>C-Reactive Protein and reclassification of cardiovascular risk in the Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1741826711424494"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polonsky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bild</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerci</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Coronary Artery Calcium Score and risk classification for coronary heart disease prediction</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>303</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>1610</fpage>–<lpage>1616</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1741826711424494"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Einstein</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Coronary Artery Calcification Screening. Estimated radiation dose and cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>169</volume>(<issue>13</issue>): <fpage>1188</fpage>–<lpage>1194</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1741826711424494"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The things to come of SHAPE: cost and effectiveness of cardiovascular prevention</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>99</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1741826711424494"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzoulaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>What makes a good predictor?: The evidence applied to Coronary Artery Calcium Score</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>303</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>1646</fpage>–<lpage>1647</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1741826711424494"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring blood pressure: the importance of understanding variation</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Hipertens</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1741826711424494"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keenan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long term monitoring in patients receiving treatment to lower blood pressure: analysis of data from placebo controlled randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>338</volume>: <fpage>b1492</fpage>–<lpage>b1492</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1741826711424494"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>KJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Macaskill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Monitoring initial response to angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor based regimens: an individual patient data meta-analysis from randomised placebo controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1741826711424494"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimbo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lipid re-screening: what is the best measure and interval?</article-title> <source>Heart</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>448</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1741826711424494"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>National Heart Foundation of Australia (National Blood Pressure and Vascular Disease Advisory Committee). Guide to management of hypertension 2008. Updated August 2009. Web version. 2009</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1741826711424494"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Chobanian AV, Bakris GR, Black HL, Cushman WC, Green LA, Izzo Jr JL, Jones DW, Materson BJ, Oparil S, Wright Jr JT, Roccella EJ, the National High Blood Pressure Education Program Coordinating Committee. Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure. <italic>Hypertension</italic> 2003; 42(6): 1206–1252</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1741826711424494"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Task Force for the Management of Arterial Hypertension of the ESH and of the ESC. 2007 Guidelines for the Management of Arterial Hypertension. <italic>Journal of Hypertension</italic> 2007; 25(9): 1105–1187</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>