<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ICS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spics</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Cultural Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1367-8779</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-356X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1367877912452484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1367877912452484</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Amsterdam – New York: Transnational photographic exchange in the era of globalization</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1367877912452484">University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1367877912452484">Christoph Lindner, ASCA, University of Amsterdam, Spuistraat 210, 1012 VT, The Netherlands. Email: <email>c.p.lindner@uva.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>16</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>151</fpage>
<lpage>168</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article examines the impact of globalization on the urban imaginary in relation to two recent photography exhibitions – one held in Amsterdam and the other in New York City – which were designed as transatlantic mirror events to celebrate the 400-year anniversary of the Dutch ‘discovery’ of Manhattan. Registering a long history of transnational exchange between the two cities, the exhibitions invited a group of New York artists to photograph Amsterdam and a group of Dutch artists to photograph New York. Both exhibitions claimed that seeing the city from these outsider perspectives enabled new and surprising photographs capable of challenging established images of both cities. Interrogating this claim, the article analyses individual artworks and artists, the marketing and staging strategies of the exhibitions, and the urban branding campaigns with which the events were associated.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>cities</kwd>
<kwd>globalization</kwd>
<kwd>photography</kwd>
<kwd>urban branding</kwd>
<kwd>visual culture</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1367877912452484">
<title>New Amsterdam</title>
<p>This article is about globalization and cities. It is also about art and tourism. Addressing these two sets of concerns in relation to Amsterdam and, in a more indirect way, New York City, the aim is to examine some of the ways in which contemporary photographic practices register the impact of globalization on the ‘urban imaginary’, a concept adapted from spatial thinking in urban studies and philosophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1367877912452484">Lefebvre, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1367877912452484">Lynch, 1960</xref>) to describe the interpretive frameworks through which we perceive, imagine and give meaning to our urban environments. This interest in photography and contemporary reshapings of the urban imaginary is connected to a broader concern with the role that transnational exchange can play in both resisting and reinforcing dominant, globalized images of contemporary city spaces.</p>
<p>In theoretical and methodological terms, the following discussion is indebted to two key studies of urban postmodernity, both of which belong to a much larger body of critical work concerned with the phenomenon of the global city. The first study is Edward Soja’s <italic>Postmetropolis</italic>, in which he argues via Henri Lefebvre for an understanding of the urban imaginary as a ‘situated and city-centric consciousness’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1367877912452484">Soja, 2000</xref>: 324), and in which he develops the term ‘postmetropolis’ to describe the future-oriented urbanism of our late-capitalist age of globalization. For Soja, the postmetropolis can take on many forms, from the fractal city to the simcity, and from the cosmopolis to the exopolis, but what these forms have in common is that they represent the product of intensified globalization processes.</p>
<p>The second study to which this article is indebted is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1367877912452484">Andreas Huyssen’s (2008)</xref> edited collection <italic>Other Cities, Other Worlds: Urban Imaginaries in a Globalizing World</italic>, which brings together new work from the fields of literature, film, art, architecture and cultural theory to examine non-Western cities through the prism of globalization. This book is important because it explicitly sets out to learn more about the deep histories and current developments of cities too often overlooked in Western academic discussions about globalization, such as Istanbul, Johannesburg, Mumbai and São Paolo. The book is also important because of the overall argument it makes about the urban imaginary: namely, that it is ‘a cognitive and somatic image’ that has become ‘an embodied material fact’ and ‘thus part of any city’s reality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1367877912452484">Huyssen, 2008</xref>: 3).</p>
<p>Although Soja and Huyssen are not quoted further here, it is important to acknowledge how their work shapes this article’s understanding of the cultural dynamic of global cities. Specifically, it is an understanding informed by Huyssen’s claim that the urban imaginary has an embedded material existence, and by Soja’s notion that, in today’s world, this city-centric consciousness is rooted in the lived experience of the postmetropolis and its new organizations of urban space. Photography, I argue, is one place where both the postmetropolitan condition and the interpretive frameworks through which we give this condition meaning coalesce.</p>
<p>With these ideas in mind, this article focuses on a 2009 art exhibition commissioned by the Amsterdam city government. Titled ‘NY Perspectives’, the exhibition featured a small group of contemporary New York artists who were invited to photograph Amsterdam to mark the 400th anniversary of Henry Hudson’s ‘discovery’ of Manhattan, an event that has always had a strong resonance in the Dutch national imagination because Hudson, although English by nationality, was working for the Dutch East India Company when he drifted into New York Bay in 1609, some 85 years after Giovanni de Verrazano.</p>
<p>One of the main ideas behind the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition was to celebrate the long history of transnational exchange that has existed between the cities of Amsterdam and New York, a history dating all the way back to New York’s origins as a 17th-century Dutch trading post, and to the transatlantic flow of people, money and goods that this early colonial enterprise set in motion. Indeed, with this last point in mind, it is worth stressing that the early modern settlement of New Amsterdam, alongside other New World outposts of this era, marked a significant moment not just in the history of European colonialism, but also in the larger history of globalization. The techno-informational space of flows that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1367877912452484">Manuel Castells (1989)</xref> has identified as enabling our contemporary network society may not yet have been in existence, but New Amsterdam was a contingent site of rapid urbanization produced by, and organized around, the transnational circulation of capital and labour, which is a feature that, in its more extreme and intensified forms, has come to be associated 400 years later by thinkers like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1367877912452484">Saskia Sassen (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1367877912452484">David Harvey (2006)</xref> with the late-capitalist, de-nationalizing phenomenon of the global city.</p>
<p>Another key idea behind the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition in Amsterdam was to create a reciprocal event – a kind of mirroring effect – with another exhibition that took place almost simultaneously in New York in the same year. Titled ‘Dutch Seen’ and hosted by the Museum of the City of New York in 2009, this other exhibition invited a group of Dutch photographers to offer a portrait of contemporary New York. This reciprocity was far from coincidental. FOAM, the Amsterdam Photography Museum, was involved in organizing both exhibitions together with the Museum of the City of New York (for ‘Dutch Seen’) and the City of Amsterdam Archives (for ‘NY Perspectives’). Further, both exhibitions were timed to coincide with the quadra-centennial celebrations being carried out in both cities, which involved a transatlantic program of cultural events promoted by the NY400 initiative.</p>
<p>NY400 was a Dutch government-funded PR operation stressing the ‘shared histories’ of New York City and the Netherlands in the form of highly sensational touristic encounters with a cultural twist. In New York, these events included ‘Dutch Ice-skating in the Big Apple’, ‘Taste New Amsterdam’, ‘New Amsterdam Bike Slam’, and the hip and exclusive-sounding ‘NY400 After Party’. Back in the Netherlands, events included New York-themed concerts, parties and performances in locations across the country, as well as the Amsterdam-based ‘Yankees Come Back Festival’, ‘American Breakfast Lectures’ (involving pancakes and politics) and ‘Hyphen-Nation’, a so-called ‘cool-politics’ youth event on immigration and diversity. These contextual details are relevant because the Amsterdam and New York photography exhibitions were caught up in this broader transnational marketing campaign. The campaign, in turn, was directly connected to the tourist industries of Amsterdam and New York, and sought to plug both cities into a global matrix of branded city spaces.</p>
<p>For example, the fact that NY400 events held in the US were also promoted in the Netherlands via Amsterdam’s main tourist portal, the ‘I Amsterdam’ website, comments on the campaign’s transnational aspirations and influences. First, the ‘I Amsterdam’ marketing campaign (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1367877912452484">Figure 1</xref>), which is Amsterdam’s official vehicle for promoting the city to international visitors, deliberately draws on the aesthetics and semantics of the ‘I Heart NY’ phenomenon, which has its origins in a New York State marketing campaign from the late 1970s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1367877912452484">Holcomb, 1999</xref>). The use of English rather than Dutch further indicates the international orientation of the ‘I Amsterdam’ slogan. Finally, the words themselves work as an explicit invitation for the visitor to occupy a subject position in relation to the city. The heart of ‘I Heart New York’ is replaced with the ‘Am’ – that is, with the declaration of urban subjectivity – of ‘I Amsterdam.’</p>
<fig id="fig1-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The ‘I Amsterdam’ slogan-sculpture at Museumplein</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the City of Amsterdam.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>In an interesting twist, a local resident group launched a counter-campaign several years ago called ‘Ai! Amsterdam.’ The counter-campaign makes even more transparent the intertextual, intercultural resonances with the ‘I Heart New York’ phenomenon, while at the same time highlighting the tension involved in Amsterdam’s city-branding efforts between, on the one hand, the desire of the city government to construct Amsterdam as an urban playground and ossified museum city (a sort of Las Vegas meets Venice), and, on the other hand, the desire of many residents to reclaim the city and its cultural institutions from the grip of international tourism.</p>
<p>The heart in the ‘Ai! Amsterdam’ logo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1367877912452484">Figure 2</xref>) is obviously an import from New York, and it is used in much the same way to express personal connection and emotional investment in the city. Further, the linguistic re-orientation of the English sound ‘I’ to the Dutch sound ‘Ai’, which means ‘ouch’, transforms the assertion of self into an exclamation of pain. As this language play suggests, the goal of the counter-campaign is to re-appropriate the city, while at the same time giving voice to the discomfort caused to many residents by what they see as Amsterdam’s excessive touristic orientation. Reconciling these two attitudes towards the city – one that invites global access and one that resists it – is something that has longed preoccupied Amsterdam’s city government (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1367877912452484">Nijman, 1999</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The ‘Ai! Amsterdam’ counter-campaign</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of Mac an Bhreithiún.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p>For example, the city’s recent move to clean up the Red Light District by performing something of a Times Square Disneyfication on this space of decriminalized drugs and prostitution is a case in point, and connects to a broader, ongoing trend in the Netherlands to reduce and more tightly restrict Red Light tourism. This development highlights some of the contradictions involved in Amsterdam’s double tourist identity as sin-city and art-city. Since around 2007, the city government has become increasingly involved in buying out brothel owners in the Red Light District and transforming the buildings into galleries and workspaces for artists and fashion designers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1367877912452484">Reed, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1367877912452484">Thomasson, 2007</xref>). Parallel to this development has been a related effort to integrate more upscale, family-friendly dining and retail opportunities into the sidewalk mix of seedy coffee shops, fastfood joints, erotic supermarkets, nightclubs and brothels. The idea is not to get rid of the sex and drug trades, but to temper their dominance of the streetscape with other, more marketable and more palatable forms of edginess: in this case, the trend-driven edginess brought by artists, designers, restaurateurs and boutiquists. The city’s simultaneous effort to create new social housing in the Red Light District also connects to this development, and signals an ambition to integrate more residents back into this space of extreme pleasure tourism.</p>
<p>The experiment is ongoing and it has not been a smooth process, with artists and designers in particular complaining that the city is using them to sell just another, cleaner and more mainstream version of the Red Light District (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1367877912452484">‘Redlight art Amsterdam’, n.d.</xref>). But the broader attempt to re-theme the Red Light District is more significant here, because it not only brings into focus the contradictory images of the city that have been promoted and maintained by the tourist and city-branding industries, but also highlights the difficulties posed in trying to reconcile those images. Ultimately, however, the re-theming of the Red Light District, much like the Disneyfication of Times Square over the last two decades, has less to do with making social improvements than it does with ensuring the growth and sustainability of mass tourism and consumption – a well-established international pattern identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1367877912452484">Sharon Zukin (2010)</xref> in her recent work on gentrification and the transformation of ‘authentic’ urban places.</p>
<p>Before moving back to the topic of transnational photographic exchange, which is this article’s primary concern, it is necessary to make one final point about Amsterdam’s city-marketing that relates directly to the photographs examined next. The reason is that the ‘I Amsterdam’ campaign functioned as the larger framework within which the NY400 programme of events operated in the Dutch capital. The NY400 programme in turn provided the context and the stimulus for the ‘Dutch Seen’ and ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibitions. This is why it is interesting that, on both sides of the Atlantic, so much of the NY400 programme was aimed at selling – even creating – a sense of otherworldliness in the familiar, everyday city.</p>
<p>In this case, the effect of otherworldliness was achieved – however superficially – by playing up the residual Dutchness of New York, as suggested by event names like ‘Taste New Amsterdam’ and ‘New Amsterdam Bike Slam’; and the latent New Yorkness of Amsterdam, as suggested by NY400’s advertising poster for its ‘New York Nights’ initiative which promised to transform nighttime Amsterdam into an after-hours Big Apple (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1367877912452484">Figure 3</xref>). What makes this dynamic of otherworldliness significant is that the same idea – the idea of creating a de-familiarizing encounter with the familiar city or what we might otherwise call an encounter with the ‘urban uncanny’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1367877912452484">Lindner, 2009</xref>) – informs both of the photography exhibitions discussed next, where the emphasis on de-familiarizing urban images, especially in the Amsterdam photographs, ultimately plays to the aesthetic and commercial needs of the tourist and city-branding industries.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>NY Nights advertising poster</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of Jarr Geerligs and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://postersinamsterdam.com">postersinamsterdam.com</ext-link></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig3.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1367877912452484">
<title>Dutch seen</title>
<p>Guest-curated by Kathy Ryan, director of photography for the <italic>New York Times Magazine</italic>, and co-organized by Amsterdam’s FOAM museum and the Museum of the City of New York, ‘Dutch Seen’ presented the work of 13 contemporary Dutch photographers who were asked to rediscover New York through the lens of the classical tradition of Dutch Golden Age painting, a period of artistic blossoming in the Netherlands most closely associated with painters such as Rembrandt and Vermeer, and loosely corresponding historically to the founding of New Amsterdam.</p>
<p>The show’s sub-title ‘New York Rediscovered’ is therefore significant. At one level, it signals the historical circularity of the Dutch presence in New York. At another level, however, it comments obliquely on the deep familiarity of the city, not only in the American visual imagination but also in the lives and work of these Dutch photographers, many of whom already had strong professional ties to New York, and all of whom were well versed in the city’s rich and extended photographic history. This helps to explain why the emphasis in the ‘Dutch Seen’ exhibition was not on newness, but instead on the newly de-familiarized.</p>
<p>Of the photographers featured in the show, Hendrik Kerstens perhaps best captures this dual concern with rediscovery and de-familiarization, especially in his engagement with the painting–photography nexus. In a series of portraits of his teenage daughter, Kerstens mimics the realist portraiture of the Dutch masters, referencing such paintings as Vermeer’s <italic>The Milkmaid</italic> (c. 1657–8) and Rembrandt’s <italic>An Oriental</italic> (1635), only now reinterpreted through the medium of photography and incorporating trivial, everyday objects from contemporary New York life. The objects are whimsically placed on the subject’s head and include a cloth napkin from a restaurant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1367877912452484">Figure 4</xref>), a plastic shopping bag and bubble-wrap. The shape and arrangement of these elements are designed to evoke 17th-century fashion and aesthetics, reinforcing the photographs’ intermedial links with Dutch Golden Age painting. At the same time, however, the choice of objects, which in the complete series also includes toilet paper, towels and a lamp shade, humorously undermines the generic pretensions of formal portraiture, gesturing in the process at the plasticity and inauthenticity of contemporary 21st-century life.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Hendrik Kerstens, <italic>Bag</italic>, 2008</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist. © Hendrik Kerstens. <email>info@nunc-contemporary.be</email></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<p>New York itself, however, is largely absent in explicit ways from Kerstens’ work, with the exception of one photograph which features his daughter wearing a Yankees cap. Yet even this connection to the city is tenuous, since the Yankees cap has become such a ubiquitous consumer accessory around the world that very little of its original geographic and cultural ties to New York remain. What is perhaps more interesting about this image is the way that it refigures Vermeer’s work. Vermeer’s early modern girl with a pearl earring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1367877912452484">Figure 5</xref>), an image which has itself become an object of commodification and remediation worldwide, becomes Kerstens’ globalized girl with a baseball cap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1367877912452484">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Johannes Vermeer, <italic>Girl with a Pearl Earring</italic>, c. 1665</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of Royal Cabinet of Paintings, Maritshuis, The Hague.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 6</label>
<caption>
<p>Hendrik Kerstens, <italic>Bump</italic>, 2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist. © Hendrik Kerstens. <email>info@nunc-contemporary.be</email></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<p>An artist who engages in a much more direct and explicit way with New York is Jaap Scheeren, best known for his surrealist nature photography. In his photo <italic>Gantry Plaza State Park</italic> (2009), the historical Dutch preoccupation with natural landscape is redirected at the urban environment, replicating a familiar and distancing visual perspective on Manhattan from across the water in Queens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1367877912452484">Figure 7</xref>). What makes the cityscape photo more than just another tourist snapshot is the incongruous, hovering presence of seemingly empty fur coats, whose silhouettes parallel the undulating lines of the urban skyline in the distance behind them.</p>
<fig id="fig7-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Jaap Scheeren, <italic>Gantry Plaza State Park</italic>, 2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<p>The coats bring Dutch colonial history into the frame by referencing the fur trade that sustained the colonial enterprise on Manhattan in the early years of European settlement. As Scheeren explains, the photograph ‘bend[s] time, bringing the present to the past and the past to the present’ (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1367877912452484">Wender, 2010</xref>), staging a confrontation between New York’s natural history and its contemporary urban present. In such a reading of the image, the dead animal pelts could be seen as alluding to the violent, profit-driven de-naturalization of Manhattan.</p>
<p>In the work of Wijnanda Deroo, the genre of the Dutch interior provides inspiration for a series of interior photographs of popular New York restaurants and eateries. Here, the murky everyday world of taverns, flophouses, gambling dens and domestic quarters so familiar in 17th-century realism is replaced by the lurid consumer spectacle of New York’s dining scene, as illustrated in Deroo’s photograph of the 42nd street Papaya Dog (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1367877912452484">Figure 8</xref>), where the overabundance of signs in the over-vivid yellow space creates an excess of visual stimulation.</p>
<fig id="fig8-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Wijnanda Deroo, <italic>Papaya Dog</italic>, 2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<p>A crucial difference between Deroo’s interiors and those of 17th-century Dutch painting is the total absence of human subjects in Deroo’s work. The urban consumer spaces depicted in her photos are ones normally filled with people, spaces designed for human activity and interaction. By presenting them in this strangely depopulated state, Deroo is able to refocus attention on details of décor, architecture and design, while simultaneously creating, to put this in terms of the uncanny, a sense of homeliness uprooted.</p>
<p>As these works by Kerstens, Scheeren and Deroo suggest, the Dutch artists featured in the exhibition do not, as a group, produce a new vision of New York. As one reviewer commented, ‘you won’t discover much here about New York – or photography – that you didn’t know beforehand’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1367877912452484">Schwendener, 2009</xref>). Instead, what the exhibition offers, as a consequence of mixing Dutch aesthetic traditions into a photographic rediscovery of New York, is a newly defamiliarized vision of a deeply familiar city.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1367877912452484">
<title>NY perspectives</title>
<p>The theme of de-familiarization was similarly present in the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition in Amsterdam. Held at the Amsterdam City Archives Building, ‘NY Perspectives’ reversed the transatlantic gaze of ‘Dutch Seen’ by inviting a portrait of Amsterdam seen through the eyes of four New York photographers: Gus Powell, Carl Wooley, Richard Rothman and Joshua Lutz. Despite the reciprocal nature of this project, there are a few significant differences with the exhibition in New York. Unlike the Dutch artists visiting New York, the American artists visiting Amsterdam were encountering the city for the first time, and were partly selected because of their unfamiliarity with the city. Also, compared to New York, Amsterdam is far less established in the global urban imaginary, so that its place and meaning in visual culture is not nearly so developed. In such terms, the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition can be understood as partly being a response to Amsterdam’s underexposure in international photography, which is a feature of the city that stands out even more when compared to New York’s relative overexposure.</p>
<p>The task given to the selected artists flown over to Amsterdam for a short four-week period was to produce work capable of de-familiarizing established images of the city. The result, or so the exhibition claimed, was that this outsider perspective on Amsterdam enabled new and surprising perspectives on four key aspects of the city which the photographers were invited to thematize in their work: the street, the night, the water and the outskirts. This claim is what the following analysis seeks to interrogate, beginning with the theme of the street.</p>
<p><italic>Voetganger</italic> is the Dutch word for pedestrian and means, literally, ‘foot-goer’. In a series of photos titled <italic>Voetganger</italic>, Gus Powell, who specializes in street photography, embraces the pedestrian in the full, double sense of the word as meaning both ordinary and foot traveller. His photos are taken as he walks the streets and public spaces of Amsterdam. They mostly depict city residents travelling on foot as they go about their everyday lives. In these photos, Powell deliberately seeks out ordinary experiences and sights in the city, such as the image of a woman walking alone through the Amsterdam Arena entertainment complex on the outskirts of the city (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1367877912452484">Figure 9</xref>). In this photograph, the design of the space – the faceless architecture and reflective materials – combined with the film poster advertising the latest 007 blockbuster, render the site indistinguishable from countless exurban zones of leisure and consumption, whether in Europe, Asia or North America. The specificity of Amsterdam is all but invisible, with the exception of the Dutch text on the film poster, so that what the photo registers is less Amsterdam and more the homogenizing effects of the global metropolitan condition.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Gus Powell, <italic>Amsterdam: No. 0267</italic>, 2008. From the series: Voetganger</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig9.tif"/></fig>
<p>When viewed alongside other photos in the series, however, Amsterdam does register in a subtle but important way through the inclusion of reflective windows. Alongside the theme of the pedestrian, the recurrence of windows and reflections is what links Powell’s various street scenes, whether in the blurred monumentalism of central station seen in the passing reflection of a tram window, or the semi-transparent glass façade of a shoe shop. This preoccupation with reflections is connected to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1367877912452484">Powell’s (2008)</xref> purposefully clichéd impression of Amsterdam as a city whose architecture of transparency mirrors the openness of Dutch society. In his work, window reflections enable him to explore this idea while playing with distinctions between inside and outside, public and private, individual and communal. The result is an oblique urban portrait in which the city frequently figures as a ghostly, immaterial presence pushed to the borders of perception.</p>
<p>Moving from streetscape to waterscape, Richard Rothman’s photographs engage with one of Amsterdam’s most enduring features: its canals, which have historically served as the city’s arteries of commerce and mobility, and which, through the pressures of water management and urban development, continue even today to exert a strong influence on the life of the city. Rothman’s black and white photographs draw on the conventions of landscape photography and reveal the lingering presence of the natural in the heart of the urban environment. The trees dominating the photographs screen the city, which can now only be glimpsed in elusive fragments in the space between branches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1367877912452484">Figure 10</xref>). Rothman’s waterscapes represent a dream-like re-naturalization of the city in which the organic now overgrows the urban.</p>
<fig id="fig10-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Richard Rothman, <italic>Hortusplantsoen</italic>, 2008</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig10.tif"/></fig>
<p>Roaming the outskirts of Amsterdam, Joshua Lutz explores Dutch suburbia and the contact zones between the city and the country. Many of his photographs register the influence of American culture, capturing the incongruous, haphazard presence of Americana in Dutch suburban living: a vintage Cadillac in the driveway of a middle-class subdivision; a wooden Indian on the balcony of a boathouse; or an oversized, metallicized Hummer parked on the side of a road (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-1367877912452484">Figure 11</xref>). These objects all belong to another world, and in some cases to another time, but they are all strangely, even uncomfortably, present in these Dutch scenes. This is particularly true of the Hummer, which in the Dutch context represents a manifestation of suburban paranoia and securitarian ideology – a product of the same militarization of urban space that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1367877912452484">Mike Davis (1990)</xref> has long associated with Fortress LA, but which is only now emerging in similar ways in the Netherlands.</p>
<fig id="fig11-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 11.</label>
<caption>
<p>Joshua Lutz, <italic>Hummer</italic>, 2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig11.tif"/></fig>
<p>Other photographs in the series are concerned with transient or liminal spaces on the margins of the city, such as improvised dwellings in a vacant field, a wall of dingy signs in a parking lot, or a highway underpass plastered with event posters no-one will stop to read (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-1367877912452484">Figure 12</xref>). These non-places, or <italic>non-lieux</italic> as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1367877912452484">Marc Augé (1995)</xref> would call them, emerge in Lutz’s work as expressions of the failures of contemporary peri-urbanism. They are under-defined places where the proximity and influence of the city become an obstacle to, rather than a vehicle for meaningful contact and exchange.</p>
<fig id="fig12-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 12.</label>
<caption>
<p>Joshua Lutz, <italic>NYED</italic>, 2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig12.tif"/></fig>
<p>The last photographer featured in the exhibition is Carl Wooley, whose series <italic>Amsterdam Night</italic> brings a long-standing interest in nocturnal photography to bear on the unfamiliar terrain of late-night Amsterdam. In particular, Wooley averts his lens from the over-lit, over-crowded, and over-determined spaces of Amsterdam’s nocturnal hot spots, such as the Red Light District or Rembrandtplein. Instead, he prefers to seek out ignored and inconspicuous spaces, such as the entrance to a back-street car-wash (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1367877912452484">Figure 13</xref>), a staircase leading into an apartment-block, the wet concrete expanse of a parking garage, or the waterside esplanade of a ferry dock.</p>
<fig id="fig13-1367877912452484" position="float">
<label>Figure 13.</label>
<caption>
<p>Carl Wooley, <italic>Wasplaats</italic>, 2008</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Courtesy of the artist.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1367877912452484-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<p>Reminiscent of <italic>film noir</italic> aesthetics and sharing the melancholy mood of Edward Hopper’s urban paintings, Wooley’s nocturnal scenes are illuminated by harsh, artificial street lighting that contrasts against the surrounding darkness. More significant is the total absence of human subjects in the majority of the images. Like the de-populated New York restaurants in Wijnanda Deroo’s work, which are perhaps similarly haunted by Hopper’s spectral influence, Wooley’s after-hours Amsterdam is strangely empty, quiet and still: devoid of human presence and caught in a state of suspended animation.</p>
<p>Looking at these various Amsterdam photographs together, it becomes clear that certain themes run through their outsider views of Amsterdam. From Gus Powell’s pedestrians to Joshua Lutz’s edgelands, and from Richard Rothman’s waterscapes to Carl Wooley’s empty nights, the vision of the city that emerges is one marked by estrangement. Here, Amsterdam emerges as a space of the ordinary, the isolated, and the unspectacular. And yet, this image – which runs counter to the dominant, globalized image of the city as a site of spectacle, experiment and excess – is nonetheless in tune with the needs of the tourist and city-branding industries, not despite its estranging treatment of Amsterdam, but because of it.</p>
<p>At one level, the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition feeds into a larger cultural/commercial dynamic in which, as Dennis Judd and Susan Fainstein argue in <italic>The Tourist City</italic>, ‘cities are sold just like any other consumer product … and each city tries to project itself as a uniquely wonderful place to visit, where an unceasing flow of events constantly unfolds’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1367877912452484">Judd and Fainstein, 1999</xref>: 4). The ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition itself, quite apart from its contents, was part of such an unceasing flow of events. It functioned as one of a series of events within the NY400 celebrations designed to stimulate interest in the city of Amsterdam and the Netherlands more broadly. It became yet another stop on the tourist loop between the Rijksmuseum and the Red Light District.</p>
<p>At the level of content, the exhibition also connects to this same dynamic of city-marketing, but in a more roundabout way, in the sense that it is becoming increasingly common, and indeed necessary, to incorporate counter-images of the city into urban branding practices as a way of both extending and refreshing the tourist appeal of cities. In particular, the last few decades have seen a growing demand worldwide for so-called alternative, underground, or authentic encounters with destination-cities. For many tourists, going beyond or behind the dominant, globalized image of a city has become an experience to seek out and consume, even if that experience is just as contrived, superficial or inauthentic.</p>
<p>It is important to stress, however, that, from the perspective of Amsterdam residents and others who are well acquainted with the everyday city, the ‘NY Perspective’ photographs do not immediately constitute ‘counter-images’ of the city, but represent instead instances of the quotidian and the commonplace which, through the photographic effects of aesthetic stilling and emptying, are made newly strange. Yet, within the urban imaginary of what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1367877912452484">John Urry (2002)</xref> has called the tourist gaze, the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition did offer an alternative, thematized vision of Amsterdam in relation to the mainstream tourist image of the city as a commercialized centre of sex, drugs and Golden Age art, even if such an image only operates at the level of outsider cliché and stereotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1367877912452484">Deben et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1367877912452484">Musterd and Salet, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1367877912452484">Nijman, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1367877912452484">Oudenampsen, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>There is a twist, however, because it is precisely this otherworldly vision of Amsterdam – the familiar city made newly strange – that was being exploited by the city government to promotional ends through the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition. After all, the city government commissioned the show in the first place, guiding the artists away from the standard tourist locations, and supplying them with the themes of street, water, night and outskirts, around which they organized their work. The fact that the exhibition was then heavily promoted via the ‘I Amsterdam’ web-portal completes the circle, suggesting that this experiment in transnational photographic exchange, like the mirror-event in New York, was not just about urban aesthetics. It was also about urban branding.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1367877912452484">
<title>Urban skimming</title>
<p>In closing it is worth commenting on how the Amsterdam and New York photographs connect to a broader cultural practice and photographic trend that can be described as ‘urban skimming’. To explain the concept of urban skimming, it is first necessary to respond to a recent essay about the ‘NY Perspectives’ exhibition. In an article titled ‘Amsterdam drift’, art historian Rachel Esner suggests that the show’s photographers demonstrate that, like Walter Benjamin wandering the dying space of the Parisian arcades, the outsider can succeed in grasping ‘the secrets of a city, secrets usually reserved for its inhabitants alone’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1367877912452484">Esner, 2009</xref>). She goes on to argue that what enables the artists to gain these insights, despite being new to Amsterdam, is the way they approach the city, which she likens to the psycho-geographical practice of the <italic>dérive</italic> – the technique of aimless drifting developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1367877912452484">Guy Debord (1955)</xref> and the Situationists in the mid 1950s to counteract the spatial controls of the capitalist city.</p>
<p>Esner is right to highlight a strong element of drifting in the working practice of the New York photographers exploring Amsterdam. This drifting registers in the images themselves, where there are frequently qualities of spontaneity and transience, as well as a deliberate turn away from urban spectacle. However, Esner is less convincing when she claims that these American photographers, let loose in Amsterdam, succeed in revealing secrets of the city. A more accurate way of characterizing the photographers’ treatment of Amsterdam might be to say that their work in fact represents a strategically superficial engagement with the urban environment – an engagement specifically designed <italic>not</italic> to bring depth of analysis, but instead to record new impressions. This approach is what constitutes urban skimming.</p>
<p>The concept of urban skimming is not mine, however. Rather, it is adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1367877912452484">Shirley Jordan (2009)</xref>, who uses it in passing in an essay about globalization and the poetics of scale in urban photography. Writing about the French photographer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1367877912452484">Raymond Depardon (2007)</xref>, Jordan attaches particular importance to his book project <italic>Villes/Cities/Städte</italic>, in which Depardon visited 12 major cities across the world, spending only three days in each one, taking improvised and impressionistic photographs. Depardon’s idea was precisely not to engage substantively with the cities he visited, but instead to pursue fleeting encounters with them in order to document his first impressions in unspoiled form. Responding to these photographic impressions, Jordan suggests that, ‘a new trope – that of “urban skimming” – might be posited to describe this project whose images express a brief, superficial relationship to the city’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1367877912452484">2009</xref>: 149). For Jordan, this trope of urban skimming represents a photographic expression of the new transnational culture of hyper-mobility that globalization has made possible.</p>
<p>Although Jordan only uses the concept briefly in relation to this particular example, urban skimming describes much more than Depardon’s project. It also describes a broader, growing trend in contemporary urban photography, including the overall approach adopted by the photographers featured in the New York and Amsterdam exhibitions, where the experience of the global city, particularly in the case of Amsterdam, is distinguished by fleeting, glancing and even gliding encounters. What the practice of urban skimming therefore reveals is not so much new insight into cities themselves, but rather new insight into the <italic>way</italic> we are increasingly experiencing and perceiving cities in the era of globalization, a development that has seen cities emerge in the urban imaginary as ever-more homogeneous, interchangeable and aesthetically standardized spaces of transit.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding statement</label>
<p>The research and images for the New York section of this article were initially enabled by a grant from the Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes><fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other"><p>For making images available for publication in this article, I am grateful to the City of Amsterdam Marketing Department, Mauritshuis Museum and Nunc Contemporary, as well as to the following photographers: Mac an Bhreithiún, Wijnanda Deroo, Jarr Geerligs, Hendrik Kerstens, Joshua Lutz, Gus Powell, Richard Rothman, Jaap Scheeren and Carl Wooley.</p></fn>
</fn-group></notes>
<bio>
<p><bold>Christoph Lindner</bold> is Professor of Media and Culture and Director of the Amsterdam School for Cultural Analysis at the University of Amsterdam. His book publications include <italic>Paris–Amsterdam Underground</italic> (2013) and <italic>Globalization, Violence, and the Visual Culture of Cities</italic> (2010).</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Augé</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Non-Places: Introduction to an Anthropology of Supermodernity</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castells</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>The Informational City: Information Technology, Economic Restructuring, and the Urban Regional Process</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>City of Quartz: Excavating the Future of Los Angeles</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Deben</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heinemeijer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Vaart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2007</year>) <source>Understanding Amsterdam: Essays in Economic Vitality, City Life and Urban Form</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Spinhuis</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Debord</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>‘Introduction à une critique de géographie urbaine’</article-title>, <source>Les Levres Nues</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Depardon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Villes/Cities/Städte</source>. <publisher-loc>Göttingen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Steidl</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Amsterdam drift</article-title>. In: <source>FOAM Album 09</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FOAM Fotografie Museum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Spaces of Global Capitalism: Towards a Theory of Uneven Geographical Development</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holcomb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Marketing cities for tourism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fainstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Tourist City</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>, pp. pp. <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huyssen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Other Cities, Other Worlds: Urban Imaginaries in a Globalizing World</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The poetics of scale in urban photography</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Globalization, Violence, and the Visual Culture of Cities</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fainstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Global forces, local strategies, and urban tourism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fainstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Tourist City</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>The Production of Space</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Nicholson-Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>London undead: screening/branding the empty city</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kofman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Branding Cities: Cosmopolitanism, Parochialism, and Social Change</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1960</year>) <source>The Image of the City</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Musterd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salet</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2003</year>) <source>Amsterdam Human Capital</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nijman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cultural globalization and the identity of place: the reconstruction of Amsterdam</article-title>. <source>Ecumene</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oudenampsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Back to the future of the creative city</article-title>. <source>Variant</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Artist’s statement. NY Perspectives</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nyperspectives.com/guspowell/gallery/#gus">http://www.nyperspectives.com/guspowell/gallery/#gus</ext-link> (available at <access-date>8 July 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>‘Redlight art Amsterdam’</article-title> (<year>n.d.</year>) Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.redlightartamsterdam.com/">http://www.redlightartamsterdam.com/</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 18 October 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Amsterdam Plans Cannabis Clean-Up</article-title>’, BBC News, 29 January. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/newsbeat/hi/the_p_word/newsid_7857000/7857533.stm">http://news.bbc.co.uk/newsbeat/hi/the_p_word/newsid_7857000/7857533.stm</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 18 October 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sassen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Global City: New York, London, Tokyo</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwendener</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Photographic links to Golden Age of Dutch painting</article-title>. <source>New York Times</source>, <day>6</day> <month>August</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/07/arts/design/07photos.html?scp=1&amp;sq=Schwendener&amp;st=cse">http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/07/arts/design/07photos.html?scp=1&amp;sq=Schwendener&amp;st=cse</ext-link> (<access-date>consulted 8 July 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Soja</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Postmetropolis: Critical Studies of Cities and Regions</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomasson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Amsterdam to clean up “red light” district</article-title>. <publisher-name>Reuters</publisher-name>, <day>7</day> <month>December</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/12/17/us-dutch-prostitution-idUSEIC76462920071217">http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/12/17/us-dutch-prostitution-idUSEIC76462920071217</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 18 October 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Urry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Tourist Gaze</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Frames from fiction: Top Ten from the fiction file</article-title>. <source>New Yorker</source>, <day>16</day> <month>December</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/photobooth/2010/12/fiction-ten.html">http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/photobooth/2010/12/fiction-ten.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 8 July 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1367877912452484">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zukin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The Naked City: The Death and Life of Authentic Urban Places</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>