<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Discourse Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1461-4456</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7080</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1461445612467254</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1461445612467254</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Sigrid Norris, <italic>Identity in (Inter)action: Introducing Multimodal (Inter)action Analysis</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1461445612467254">School of Journalism and Communication, The University of Queensland, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>805</fpage>
<lpage>806</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>Sigrid</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Identity in (Inter)action: Introducing Multimodal (Inter)action Analysis</source>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>De Gruyter Mouton</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>; <page-count count="xviii"/> + <page-count count="298"/> pp., <price>€69.95/US$89.95</price> (hbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>Identity in (Inter)action: Introducing Multimodal (Inter)action Analysis</italic> adds to the burgeoning literature on identity in social science, using ethnographic research to undertake multimodal discourse analysis in order to illustrate the practices of identity production in the lives of two German women. The author employs a form of discourse analysis introduced in Norris’s earlier work, <italic>Analyzing Multimodal Interaction: A Methodological Framework</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1461445612467254">2004</xref>), which investigates human action as mediated action, be it by talk, gesture or the embodied world. This new book applies the theory of ‘modal density’ and the notion of layers of discourse (immediate, continuous and general) to the identity production of these two women. This work reflexively argues that a multimodal framework is necessary to describe identity production and that features of identity production describe a multimodal framework (p. 4).</p>
<p>Chapter 1 introduces the reader to the methods of analysis and basic assumptions Norris uses throughout the book. This chapter uses multimodal analysis to illustrate the main argument that discourse analysis ought to consider a wider field of human action than simply talk. Norris introduces a new multimodal transcription system which relies on frame captures overlaid with text.</p>
<p>Chapter 2 outlines the theoretical framework behind multimodal (inter)action analysis and sets out the concepts of <italic>actions, mediational means, sites of engagement</italic> and the <italic>foreground–background continuum.</italic> Norris presents a definition of <italic>actions</italic> derived from cultural studies as a social object constructed with <italic>mediational-means</italic> (e.g. bodily, gestural, vocalization resources) situated within the Goffman-like <italic>site of engagement</italic> (with the key addition of ‘higher-level’ action). This chapter also introduces modal density as the <italic>foreground–background continuum</italic> – essentially the psychological idea of ‘salience’, this time for interactional theory, a concept reminiscent of Goffman’s frontstage– backstage (references to which were absent).</p>
<p>After discussing data collection in Chapter 3, Chapters 4 and 5 describe ‘modal density’, or the way in which varying levels of intensity and complexity bring the action into the foreground or background of the actor’s awareness. Chapter 5 adds the notion of ‘horizontal’ identity production and discusses the way in which higher and lower level actions are situated relative to each other in interaction. This chapter elaborates the ideas of modal density with evidence based on the use of multiple identities performed at the same time, at various levels of modal density.</p>
<p>Chapter 6, moving away from the multimodal data, investigates differing levels of discourse and their relationship to identity production. Norris identifies three levels of discourse which roughly correspond to ‘societal’, ‘situated social network’ and ‘the here and now’. Unlike the previous chapters, her analysis here employs the entire ethnography and draws heavily on cultural context. She argues that there is a tension at each level of discourse between agency and constraint in the production of identity. This chapter sat awkwardly in the book, seemingly unrelated to multimodality or the theories described.</p>
<p>Chapter 7 is for me the main payoff of the book. Norris illustrates the way in which various multimodal resources are employed to enact higher- and lower-level action at various modal densities. She highlights how such resources are employed to signal shifts in structure of discourse, coordinating various levels of action, with a stronger focus on the ways in which the features that were described are used to accomplish actions in talk.</p>
<p>Chapter 8 provides a brief exploration of how identities may change or be perceived to change by actors. Norris describes the way in which the ‘whole’ person is produced through nation, family, friends and biography. A brief conclusion to the book rounds this chapter off.</p>
<p>This book provides a well-articulated set of theoretical constructs for discourse analysts interested in the various features of identity production in talk. Stepping away from some of the earlier work in the field, this work seeks to establish a new method of discourse analysis in its own right under the rubric <italic>Multimodal Interaction Analysis.</italic> Also, those used to a more linguistic/gestural focus in multimodal research may find the sociological focus of the book useful to supplement their own analyses as Norris seamlessly weaves Bourdieu, Gadamer and Foucault into this otherwise linguistic discourse analysis. Norris deploys complex ideas from these authors in an easy-to-read way throughout the work. Linguists looking to add a social side to their work would do well with this book.</p>
<p>Overall, the theoretical propositions in this work are straightforward; however, throughout the book, analysis suffers from ‘mere description’ (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1461445612467254">Antaki et al., 2003</xref>), simply ‘spotting’ the features/theoretical concepts propounded earlier in the work. I would have liked a more convincing analysis that conclusively illustrated the operation of these concepts as they are employed for other actions in talk, or conversely that some other part of talk is used to achieve these theoretical constructs. This work sets up the theory well and falls unfortunately short with the analysis – with more focus in the analysis throughout the book on how particular (multimodal) resources are used to structure and enact these theoretical ideas (as was done so well in Chapter 7), this work would have provided more convincing support for the elaborate theory Norris has presented.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1461445612467254">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Antaki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Billig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Discourse analysis means doing analysis: A critique of six analytic shortcomings</article-title>. <source>Discourse Analysis Online</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1461445612467254">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Analyzing Multimodal Interaction: A Methodological Framework</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>