<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DIJ</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdij</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Drug Information Journal</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0092-8615</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092861512438748</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0092861512438748</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Companion Diagnostics</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Decision Making for a Companion Diagnostic in an Oncology Clinical Development Program</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kaiser</surname>
                  <given-names>Lee</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092861512438748">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0092861512438748"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Becker</surname>
                  <given-names>Claus</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD, MBA</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0092861512438748">2</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0092861512438748">*</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kukreti</surname>
                  <given-names>Sharad</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD, MBA</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0092861512438748">2</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Fine</surname>
                  <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0092861512438748">3</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="aff1-0092861512438748">
            <label>1</label>Statistical Methods and Research, Genentech Inc, South San Francisco, CA, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff2-0092861512438748">
            <label>2</label>Pipeline and Portfolio Planning, Genentech Inc, South San Francisco, CA, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff3-0092861512438748">
            <label>3</label>Exploratory Clinical Development, Oncology, Genentech Inc, South San Francisco, CA, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff4-0092861512438748">
            <sup>*</sup>Current affiliation: Vertex Pharmaceuticals Inc, Cambridge, Massachusetts</aff>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="corresp1-0092861512438748">Lee Kaiser, Genentech Inc, 1 DNA Way, MS 452a, South San Francisco, CA 94080 Email: <email xlink:type="simple">lkaiser@gene.com</email>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2012</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>46</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <fpage>294</fpage>
         <lpage>302</lpage>
         <history>
            <date date-type="received">
               <day>15</day>
               <month>9</month>
               <year>2010</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="accepted">
               <day>11</day>
               <month>1</month>
               <year>2011</year>
            </date>
         </history>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="society">Drug Information Association</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <abstract>
            <p>The decision to incorporate the specific evaluation of a candidate companion diagnostic (CDx) in a clinical development plan (CDP) is often difficult and is exacerbated by the lack of relevant decision tools. In this article, we discuss a novel method to assess the probability of technical success (PTS) of a CDP that adequately evaluates a CDx compared with a CDP that doesn’t. We propose splitting the PTS into subjective (biological uncertainty) and quantitative (clinical uncertainty) components, assessing each separately, and then combining them in a decision theoretical manner to obtain an overall success probability of a CDP with and without a CDx.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>personalized medicine</kwd>
            <kwd>expected net present value</kwd>
            <kwd>portfolio management</kwd>
            <kwd>probability of technical success</kwd>
            <kwd>R&amp;D management</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="section1-0092861512438748">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Personalized medicine frequently is described as central to the commercial success of novel medicines and to the societal goal of managing the cost and improving the quality of health care.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0092861512438748">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0092861512438748">2</xref>
            </sup> Despite this, and perhaps because of the long cycle times in drug development, there are few examples of successful personalized medicines, and these are concentrated in oncology, where companion predictive diagnostics (CDx) help match patients to a specific therapy.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0092861512438748">3</xref>
            </sup>
         </p>
         <p>Although oncology therapeutics are still typically developed in patients based on the histological characteristics of their tumor, it is becoming more common for these therapeutics to be developed in subsets of patients whose tumors have a certain molecular characteristic. Examples of this include her-2 positivity for trastuzumab in breast cancer<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0092861512438748">4</xref>
            </sup> and activating BRAF mutations for a RAF inhibitor in melanoma.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0092861512438748">5</xref>
            </sup>
         </p>
         <p>The decision to design the clinical development plan (CDP) to adequately evaluate a patient subset is typically based on the strength of hypotheses about biological characteristic of the disease, the mechanism of action of the new molecular entity (NME), and the candidate CDx, as well as on commercial considerations. Because these hypotheses were strong for trastuzumab, the clinical trials supporting its approval were limited to patients testing positive with the corresponding assay. In other cases, there may be greater uncertainty that a specific assay will identify patients who differentially benefit from the NME, with consequent uncertainty whether the CDP should include a robust evaluation of this candidate predictive diagnostic through specific study designs and primary objectives.</p>
         <p>We describe an approach to this issue that uses the portfolio management concept of the probability of technical success (PTS), which quantifies a development program’s risks. Portfolio management is commonly applied in the biopharmaceutical industry to manage the complex drug development decisions required to balance costs, risks, timing, option generation, revenue, and fit with corporate strategy.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0092861512438748">6</xref>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0092861512438748"/>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0092861512438748"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0092861512438748">9</xref>
            </sup> Our approach provides a systematic framework for the evaluation of a CDx development program relative to an “all-comers” (AC) development program.</p>
         <p>Although there are adequate tools to assess the impact of a CDx on revenue and development costs and timelines,<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0092861512438748">10</xref>
            </sup> a consistent framework for assessing PTS has not been described. In particular, both the strength of the CDx hypothesis and the details of the CDPs are key to estimating PTS. However, incorporating these considerations into decision making is generally not intuitive. The key contributions of our approach are the following.</p>
         <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
               <p>The explicit calculation of CDP PTS based on 2 clearly distinct components: (1) the objective statistical features of the candidate CDPs and (2) the inherently subjective assessment of the true benefit of the NME and the strength of the CDx hypothesis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
               <p>A straightforward method to capture this subjective assessment of the CDx hypothesis and incorporate it into the PTS calculation</p>
            </list-item>
         </list>
         <p>We describe the approach in general and demonstrate the calculations for time-to-event trial end points like progression-free survival (PFS).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section2-0092861512438748">
         <title>Candidate Clinical Development Plans</title>
         <p>To address the CDx question for an oncology NME, we evaluate 2 CDP options:</p>
         <list list-type="order">
            <list-item>
               <p>An AC CDP in which the potential companion diagnostic is included at most in exploratory analyses. The CDP starts with a randomized phase 2 trial of the NME versus a control that if positive based on predefined criteria will be followed by a randomized phase 3 trial of the NME versus a control. A submission for regulatory approval follows a positive phase 3 trial. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
               <p>A CDx CDP in which the randomized phase 2 trial of the NME versus a control is stratified by patient CDx status. Predefined criteria are used to evaluate the results of this trial in CDx-positive patients and in all patients and determine whether the randomized phase 3 trial of the NME versus control is stratified on CDx status or performed in all patients without regard to their CDx status. A stratified phase 3 trial has individual primary hypotheses about the treatment effect in CDx-positive patients and in all patients. A submission for regulatory approval follows a positive stratified phase 3 trial<bold>:</bold> depending on trial results the submission could request approval in all patients or only in CDx-positive patients. The phase 3 trial in all patients without regard to their CDx status is as in the AC CDP.</p>
            </list-item>
         </list>
         <p>For both plans, we assume that studies through phase 1 are similar, with the plans diverging at the start of phase 2. We also assume that a diagnostic test is available and there is no additional project risk associated with the development of a marketable test.</p>
         <p>With the CDPs specified, the PTS can be determined through consideration of what we call biological uncertainty and clinical uncertainty (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0092861512438748">Figure 1</xref>). </p>
         <fig id="fig1-0092861512438748" position="float">
            <label>Figure 1.</label>
            <caption>
               <p>Estimation of PTS through the disaggregation of biological and clinical uncertainty. AC, all-comers; CDx, companion diagnostic; NME, new molecular entity; PTS, probability of technical success.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="fig1-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-fig1.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
         </fig>
         <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
               <p>Biological uncertainty is the uncertainty about the true effectiveness of the NME and the effect of patient selection via the CDx. In our approach, this uncertainty is quantified by the project team through the specification of potential treatment effect values in CDx-positive and CDx-negative patients along with subjective probabilities for each scenario.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
               <p>Clinical uncertainty is the probability of trial outcomes on the assumption that specific treatment effect values hold. These probabilities are determined precisely through statistical calculations or rigorous simulations.</p>
            </list-item>
         </list>
         <p>An important distinction is that clinical uncertainty can be determined objectively, whereas the biological uncertainty cannot. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section3-0092861512438748">
         <title>Biological Uncertainty Assessment</title>
         <p>Biological uncertainty is the unavoidable uncertainty prior to obtaining clinical data regarding an NME’s efficacy in the target patient populations. This includes uncertainty regarding the NME’s ability to inhibit its target and whether the target is biologically active in the disease process, the strength and relevance of results in animal models, clinical trial results with related molecules, the ability of a candidate CDx to identify patients with differential benefit from the NME, and so on. This uncertainty cannot be determined objectively and can only be determined from the subjective assessment of knowledgeable individuals. There is a large literature on eliciting expert opinion: see Kynn<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0092861512438748">11</xref>
            </sup> for an overview and recommendations. A key feature of our approach is that the contribution of subjective components to estimates of PTS is transparent.</p>
         <p>In general, probabilities could be assigned to many potential levels of NME efficacy in all patients and likewise in CDx-positive and CDx-negative patients. However, we simplify the problem through the consideration of 3 mutually exclusive target product profiles (TPPs) for the NME. We illustrate with PFS as the end point and treatment benefit quantified through the estimated PFS hazard ratio (HR). </p>
         <list list-type="simple">
            <list-item>
               <p>
                  <italic>Null TPP</italic>
                  <bold>:</bold> There is no improvement in efficacy of the NME relative to control in either CDx-positive or CDx-negative patients. With a PFS efficacy end point, the null TPP specifies that the true HR between the treatment arms is 1.0 in both CDx-positive and CDx-negative patients.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
               <p>
                  <italic>CDx+ TPP</italic>
                  <bold>:</bold> The NME has a specified level of efficacy in CDx-positive patients, with little or no activity in CDx-negative patients. For example, the PFS HR is 0.5 in CDx-positive patients and 1.0 in CDx-negative patients.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
               <p>
                  <italic>AC TPP</italic>
                  <bold>:</bold> The NME has a specified level of efficacy in all patients, regardless of their CDx status, such as a PFS HR of 0.65 in both CDx-positive and CDx-negative patients. </p>
            </list-item>
         </list>
         <p>As these TPPs are mutually exclusive and represent all possible states, the subjective probabilities assigned to them must add to 1. Also, there is conceptually no need for the extent of efficacy specified in the CDx+ TPP to be tied in any way to the level of efficacy specified in the AC TPP. In the discussion, we address the simplification to 3 TPPs and also address the use of other phase 2 and phase 3 trial end points. </p>
         <p>Industry benchmarks can be used to guide the biological uncertainty assessment. Estimates of the chance that an oncology NME entering phase 2 achieves regulatory approval range from 10% to 35%.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0092861512438748">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0092861512438748">13</xref>
            </sup> Generally, the biological uncertainty assessment should result in calculated PTS values in or near this range, unless there is a clear reason for this not to be the case with the particular NME.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section4-0092861512438748">
         <title>Clinical Uncertainty Determination</title>
         <p>Clinical uncertainty is the probability, determined either explicitly or through simulation, of clinical trial outcomes on the assumption that a given TPP describes the NME’s true treatment effect. </p>
         <p>With the example of the PFS end point, the clinical trial outcomes are functions of the estimated PFS hazard ratios for the 2 subgroups, HˆR<sub>–</sub> and HˆR<sub>+</sub>, which have distributions that are well approximated by a log-normal distribution. The estimated log hazard ratio in all patients, log(HˆR<sub>AC</sub>), is approximately a linear combination of log(HˆR<sub>–</sub>) and log(HˆR<sub>+</sub>) and is also approximately normally distributed. See the Appendix for details.</p>
         <p>As an example of a clinical uncertainty calculation, suppose the AC TPP states that the PFS HR is 0.65, the randomized phase 2 trial is analyzed once 50 PFS events have occurred, and phase 3 will be started if HˆR<sub>AC</sub> ≤ 0.79. Through use of the usual log-normal approximation to the distribution of HˆR<sub>AC</sub> (see Appendix), the probability of starting phase 3 is</p>
         <disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0092861512438748">
            <mml:math id="mml-disp1-0092861512438748" overflow="scroll">
               <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Φ</mml:mi>
               <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                     <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi>
                     <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi>
                     <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi>
                     <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mrow>
               </mml:mrow>
               <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                     <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">.79</mml:mn>
                     <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">−</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi>
                     <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi>
                     <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi>
                     <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mrow>
               </mml:mrow>
               <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                     <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">.65</mml:mn>
                     <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
                     <mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">}</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mrow>
               </mml:mrow>
               <mml:mo stretchy="false">√</mml:mo>
               <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                     <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">50</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mrow>
                           <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">=</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn>
                     </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mrow>
                     <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn mathvariant="normal">.75</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="normal" stretchy="false">,</mml:mo>
                     </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
               </mml:mrow>
            </mml:math>
            <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-eq1.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
         </disp-formula>
         <p>where Φ is the standard normal cumulative distribution function. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section5-0092861512438748">
         <title>Calculation of PTS and Expected Net Present Value</title>
         <p>With the biological and clinical uncertainty defined above, the PTS is simply the probability-weighted average across all 3 TPPs of the probability of successful clinical outcomes for each TPP. With assumptions about clinical trial costs, time to launch, and the anticipated revenue stream from a marketed drug, the expected (or PTS-adjusted) net present value (NPV) of the drug development plan can be calculated.</p>
         <p>Trusheim et al<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0092861512438748">14</xref>
            </sup> describe revenue stream considerations of a drug with a companion diagnostic and note that actual revenues might be higher even though potential patient numbers are reduced. Although the addition of a CDx option to the marketing scenarios adds complexity, it doesn’t change the basic approach to estimating revenue streams, and the calculation of expected NPV for each CDP is performed as usual.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section6-0092861512438748">
         <title>Example</title>
         <sec id="section7-0092861512438748">
            <title>Candidate CDPs</title>
            <p>We specify 2 candidate CDPs, complete with decision rules based on PFS for moving to the next phases of each plan. Clearly, other end points could be used, along with other decision criteria. We use PFS because it is a common oncology trial end point.</p>
            <p>The AC CDP is outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0092861512438748">Figure 2</xref>. The values of e<sub>2,AC</sub> and HR<sub>2,crit</sub> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0092861512438748">Figure 2</xref> that define the “go to phase 3” decision are selected to ensure satisfactory type I error rate and study power. The number of patients enrolled, n<sub>2,AC</sub>, is selected to target a trial analysis time.</p>
            <fig id="fig2-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Figure 2.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Specification of the all-comers development plan trials and associated decision criteria. PFS, progression-free survival; PTS, probability of technical success.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="fig2-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-fig2.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>As in phase 2, the power of the phase 3 trial is determined by appropriate choice of e<sub>3,AC</sub>. A greater degree of statistical significance than 2.5% may be necessary for a single-study submission, but this is readily handled.</p>
            <p>The CDx CDP is outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0092861512438748">Figure 3</xref>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0092861512438748">Table 1</xref> contains the decision rules for the initiation and design of phase 3 based on phase 2 results. Roughly, phase 3 is stratified if the phase 2 strength of evidence of a PFS effect in CDx-positive patients is at least as good as the evidence for an effect in all patients<bold>;</bold> otherwise, phase 3 and submission criteria will be as in the AC CDP. </p>
            <fig id="fig3-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Figure 3.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Specification of the CDx development plan trials and associated decision criteria. CDx, companion diagnostic; PFS, progression-free survival; PTS, probability of technical success.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="fig3-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-fig3.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <table-wrap id="table1-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Table 1.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Decision matrix for the determination of phase 3 initiation and design based on phase 2 outcome in the CDx development plan.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="table1-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-table1.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
               <table>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="2">PFS Result in All-comers</th>
                        <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">PFS Result in CDx-Positive Patients</th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HˆR<sub>2,+</sub> ≤ HR<sub>2,+,crit2</sub>
                        </th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR<sub>2,+,crit2</sub> &lt; HˆR<sub>2,+</sub> ≤ HR<sub>2,+,crit</sub>
                        </th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR<sub>2,+,crit</sub> &lt; HˆR<sub>2,+</sub>
                        </th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub> &lt; HˆR<sub>2,AC</sub>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stratified phase 3</td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stop</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR<sub>2,AC,crit2</sub> &lt; HˆR<sub>2,AC</sub> ≤ HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub>
                        </td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HˆR<sub>2,AC</sub> ≤ HR<sub>2,AC,crit2</sub>
                        </td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
</td>
                        <td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nonstratified phase 3</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
               <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="table-fn1-0092861512438748">
                     <p>We choose HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub> and HR<sub>2,+,crit</sub> to maintain a given type I error rate for phase 2. HR<sub>2,AC,crit2</sub> and HR<sub>2,+,crit2</sub> are chosen to represent a greater level of evidence for the PFS effects. In our examples we set these cutoffs at one-half the significance level of the HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub> and HR<sub>2,+,crit</sub> cutoffs themselves. For example, if HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub> is a 15% 1-sided cutoff for the null hypothesis that HR<sub>AC</sub> = 1 and there are 50 PFS events in the analysis, then HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub> = 0.75 and HR<sub>2,AC,crit2</sub> = 0.67. Abbreviations: CDx, companion diagnostic; AC, all-comers; PFS, progression-free survival; HR, hazard ratio.</p>
                  </fn>
               </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>The phase 2 and the stratified phase 3 studies each have 2 primary analyses—one based on the estimated PFS HR in all patients and the other in CDx-positive patients. To control the overall type I error rate in each study, the significance level is split between these 2 analyses.<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0092861512438748">15</xref>
               </sup> A Pocock-type interim analysis approach, which we use in the example below, results in an equal division.<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0092861512438748">16</xref>
               </sup> For example, with 50% of the total phase 3 PFS events occurring in CDx-positive patients, the significance level for each of the 2 analyses is 1.47%. Other divisions are easily obtained with available software.<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0092861512438748">17</xref>
               </sup>
            </p>
            <p>The stratified phase 2 trial is analyzed once e<sub>2,CDx</sub> events have occurred in all patients. As with the AC plan, e<sub>2,CDx</sub> and the critical values HR<sub>2,AC,crit</sub> and HR<sub>2,+,crit</sub> are chosen to achieve reasonable type I error rate and study power. The number of patients to enroll influences the expected time of trial analysis.</p>
            <p>For the stratified phase 3 study, analyses are conducted once e<sub>3,CDx</sub> PFS events have occurred among all patients, with this number of events chosen to achieve the desired power of the study. A submission to regulatory authorities will occur with positive efficacy results and adequate safety results as follows.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
               <list-item>
                  <p>The submission will be for all patients if the estimated HR in all patients, HˆR<sub>3,AC</sub>, is statistically significant and the estimated HR in CDx-positive patients, HˆR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>+</sub>, is not statistically significant.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>The submission will be for CDx-positive patients if HˆR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>+</sub> is statistically significant and HˆR<sub>3,AC</sub> is not.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>If HˆR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>+</sub> and HˆR<sub>3,AC</sub> are both statistically significant and HˆR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>–</sub> ≤ HR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>–,crit</sub> then submit for regulatory approval in all patients. Here, HˆR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>–</sub> is the estimated PFS hazard ratio in CDx-negative patients and HR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>–,crit</sub> is a specified constant, for example, 0.75. If the HˆR<sub>3,</sub>
                     <sub>–</sub> criterion is not met, then submit for regulatory approval in CDx-positive patients.</p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>This criterion on HˆR<sub>3,–</sub> is added to ensure that a positive result in all patients is not driven by a very strong result in CDx-positive patients and a weak result in CDx-negative patients. </p>
            <p>For each CDP, there is a probability of regulatory approval assigned to the submissions. The probabilities could be different depending on the route to the submission or on the actual results of the phase 3 trial but are taken to be equal to 0.9, as is commonly assumed.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="section8-0092861512438748">
            <title>Calculation of PTS</title>
            <p>Our example is of an NME with either no efficacy, good efficacy in all patients, or very good efficacy only in CDx-positive patients, with a relatively greater subjective probability assigned to the CDx TPP than the AC TPP. The TPPs and subjective probabilities are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0092861512438748">Table 2</xref>. Furthermore, the prevalence of CDx positivity is 30%, with CDx positivity also prognostic for a poorer outcome<bold>:</bold> median PFS is 7 months in CDx-negative control patients and 4 months in CDx-positive control patients.</p>
            <table-wrap id="table2-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Table 2.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Efficacy assessments for CDx-negative and CDx-positive patients in the candidate TPPs.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="table2-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-table2.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
               <table>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Null TPP</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">All-comers TPP</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDx TPP</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">True PFS HR in CDx-negative patients</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">True PFS HR in CDx-positive patients</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subjective probability </td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
               <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="table-fn2-0092861512438748">
                     <p>Abbreviations: CDx, companion diagnostic; TPP, target product profile; PFS, progression-free survival; HR, hazard ratio.</p>
                  </fn>
               </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>The phase 2 trials in each CDP randomize 100 patients, with analyses once 76 PFS events are observed. With a 1-sided type I error rate of 20%, the AC phase 2 study has power of 80% under the AC TPP. The phase 3 trials in the plans each randomize 472 patients, with analyses once 283 PFS events are observed. With a 1-sided type I error rate of 2.5%, the AC phase 3 study has 90% power under the AC TPP.</p>
            <p>
               <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0092861512438748">Figure 4</xref> contains the decision tree for the AC CDP, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0092861512438748">Figure 5</xref> contains the decision tree for the CDx CDP. In this case the probability of regulatory approval following an AC CDP is approximately 20%. This probability is substantially increased to approximately 35% with the CDx CDP, comprising a 24% probability for CDx labeling and 11% probability of approval in all patients.</p>
            <fig id="fig4-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Figure 4.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Decision tree and associated probabilities for the all-comers development plan for the biological uncertainty assessment in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0092861512438748">Table 2</xref>. *The approval probability given the TPP is the product of the phase 3 go probability, the submission probability, and a constant 0.9 submission approval probability. Abbreviations: CDx, companion diagnostic; AC, all-comers; TPP, target product profile; PTS, probability of technical success.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="fig4-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-fig4.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="fig5-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Figure 5.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Decision tree and associated probabilities for the CDx development plan for the biological uncertainty assessment in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0092861512438748">Table 2</xref>. *The approval probability given the TPP is the product of the phase 3 go probability, the submission probability, and a constant 0.9 submission approval probability. Abbreviations: CDx, companion diagnostic; AC, all-comers; TPP, target product profile; PTS, probability of technical success.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="fig5-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-fig5.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
         </sec>
         <sec id="section9-0092861512438748">
            <title>PTS With Other Subjective Probabilities</title>
            <p>For the same CDP details, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0092861512438748">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0092861512438748">5</xref> can be used to determine CDP PTS values with different subjective probabilities assigned to the 3 TPPs, because the clinical uncertainty values are unchanged. Such PTS values are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0092861512438748">Table 3</xref> for 2 biological uncertainty scenarios that represent (1) equal belief in the CDx TPP as the AC TPP and (2) belief that the NME is much less likely to have differential benefit in CDx-positive patients. For reference, the table includes the original PTS results. Finally, the subjective probability of the AC TPP that leads to equal total PTS values between the CDPs is also included. </p>
            <table-wrap id="table3-0092861512438748" position="float">
               <label>Table 3.</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>PTS of the AC and CDx development plans as a function of the subjective probability of the TPPs.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic alt-version="no" alternate-form-of="table3-0092861512438748" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0092861512438748-table3.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
               <table>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Subjective Probability</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="2">AC Development Plan PTS</th>
                        <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">CDx Development Plan</th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AC TPP</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDx TPP</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AC PTS</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDx PTS</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total PTS</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
               <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="table-fn3-0092861512438748">
                     <p>Abbreviations: PTS, probability of technical success; AC, all-comers; CDx, companion diagnostic; TPP, target product profile.</p>
                  </fn>
               </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>Perhaps surprisingly, the PTS of the CDx CDP is equal to that of the AC CDP even when the AC TPP is considered 6 times as likely as the CDx TPP. Essentially, from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0092861512438748">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0092861512438748">5</xref>, although a PTS price is paid, from 0.65 to 0.59, in pursuing a CDx CDP when the AC TPP is true, it is not as great as the PTS price paid, from 0.57 to 0.23, in pursuing an AC CDP when the CDx TPP is true. </p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="section10-0092861512438748">
            <title>Use of These Calculations for Decision Making</title>
            <p>In the previous subsection, we set clinical trial sizes equal between the 2 CDPs to minimize differences in development timelines, which minimizes timing in the consideration of expected NPV. With similar revenue streams whether the NME approval is for a given effectiveness in all patients or for an improved level of effectiveness in CDx-positive patients, the choice between CDPs can be made on the comparison of the PTS values themselves. We recommend this approach as a first screen for whether an AC or CDx CDP is clearly preferred.</p>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section11-0092861512438748">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>Our approach is intended to aid in the difficult decision of whether to incorporate a candidate CDx into the clinical development of an NME. It can be applied to a range of clinical development scenarios and provides a clear framework for describing key assumptions and how they affect PTS estimates. In describing the framework and the examples, we chose specific details, including clinical trial designs and criteria for moving from one phase of development to the next; these specific choices should not be viewed as prescriptions or recommendations. </p>
         <p>We focused on the CDP of the NME but recognize that parallel development is required for the diagnostic<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0092861512438748">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0092861512438748">19</xref>
            </sup> where candidate biomarkers move through assay optimization to formal validation that meets US Food and Drug Administration requirements for clinical tests. The risks underlying CDx development can be readily factored into the PTS calculations through a decrease in the CDx launch probability in the CDx CDP. </p>
         <p>Furthermore, the NME’s effectiveness in CDx-positive patients is influenced by how accurately the biomarker assay determines the true positive or negative status of patients’ tumors. This was not explicitly included in our examples but can be easily incorporated. If the efficacy specified in the CDx TPP in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0092861512438748">Table 1</xref> is for a perfect assay, the specificity and sensitivity of the diagnostic test influence the prevalence of a positive test result and the target PFS HRs in a straightforward manner. </p>
         <p>Our assessment considered only program failure owing to poor efficacy results. The inclusion of failure for safety reasons would generally involve a multiplication of the efficacy PTS by a factor constant between CDPs, so the relative comparison of PTS and the expected NPV between plans would be unchanged. </p>
         <p>We used PFS as the phase 2 efficacy end point, but a CDx CDP with response rate as the efficacy end point is also feasible.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0092861512438748">20</xref>
            </sup> For some oncology indications, regulatory approval can be obtained with positive PFS results in a phase 3 trial. However, regulatory approval would be more likely with positive overall survival results, and the calculations we developed for PFS apply directly to overall survival. </p>
         <p>In our examples, we used equal sample sizes between the AC and CDx CDPs to allow a direct comparison of PTS between the plans. However, the necessity of a fresh tumor tissue sample for the CDx assay might reduce the enrollment rate of eligible patients into the study, which would affect the timing of trial results in the CDx plan. To make timelines equal between the 2 development programs, one could compare the CDx CDP to an AC plan that has correspondingly larger trials, which would raise the PTS of the AC CDP.</p>
         <p>We kept the prevalence of a positive biomarker constant in our examples, although this is clearly not a requirement. An attractive feature of our approach is that the effect of different levels of biomarker prevalence and treatment effect within the CDx-positive patients can easily be evaluated.</p>
         <p>In our examples, we used equal significance levels for the statistical tests on the estimated HRs for the AC and CDx hypotheses in the stratified designs; however, other divisions could improve PTS of the CDx plan. For example, if there is greater prior belief in the CDx TPP, then the PTS is generally improved by giving a greater share of the type I error rate to the CDx hypothesis. </p>
         <p>We’ve recommended the specification of just 1 AC TPP and 1 CDx TPP, but multiple AC TPPs and CDx TPPs could be specified along with their subjective probabilities. The clinical uncertainty calculations would be determined for each TPP and the PTS of each CDP determined as before. We think this extra effort is not worthwhile: as long as the 1 AC TPP used is near the “average” of the multiple AC TPPs, and likewise for the CDx TPPs, the resulting PTS values will be similar. Loosely, we are approximating the expectation of a function with the function evaluated at the expectation. </p>
         <p>Finally, the approach we describe could easily be used to help make decisions between any 2 CDPs regardless of whether a CDx hypothesis is involved. The approach could also be used to compare the PTS and timing of results of the more traditional CDx CDP used here in the examples to an adaptive phase 2/3 design as described, for example, in Brannath et al.<sup>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0092861512438748">21</xref>
            </sup>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section12-0092861512438748">
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>Drug development is complex, and it is even more so when a potential companion diagnostic is considered, especially when the biological characteristics of the pairing of the companion diagnostic and NME are not completely compelling. We’ve shown how PTS can be determined in the oncology setting to guide decisions regarding candidate CDPs. We’ve illustrated that even when there’s relatively little prior belief in the ability of the CDx to identify patients differentially responsive to the NME, program PTS can be increased by designing stratified trials with primary objectives that include the estimation of treatment effect in CDx-positive patients. This is not an argument that all trials should be stratified on some candidate biomarker, because assay performance, willingness of patients to agree to necessary sample collection, proposed differential efficacy in CDx-positive patients, and other factors will influence the PTS results. </p>
         <p>AC and CDx CDPs have different study designs and analyses. For appropriate comparison of the plans, it is essential to divide the CDP PTS determinations into subjective aspects and those that vary objectively with the clinical trial design and analysis. Expert opinion can be brought to bear on the subjective aspects, and trial designers can optimize trial designs to ensure that PTS values are rigorously determined and maximized within the constraints of the plans. With this, PTS values can be confidently compared between CDPs to inform decision making.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <app-group>
         <app id="app1-0092861512438748">
            <title>Appendix. <bold>Approximate Joint Distribution of log(HˆR<sub>AC</sub>) and log(HˆR<sub>+</sub>)</bold>
            </title>
            <p>In a 2-arm parallel group study with <italic>n</italic> patients per arm and <italic>d</italic> PFS events in total, the log of the estimated PFS hazard ratio HˆR as determined from a proportional hazards regression model is approximately normally distributed with a mean of log(HR) and a variance of 4/d.<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0092861512438748">22</xref>
               </sup> With patients grouped into 2 strata on the basis of the CDx test result, and ρ equal to the fraction of these patients who are CDx positive, let d<sub>+</sub> and d<sub>–</sub> denote the number of PFS events that occur in CDx-positive and CDx-negative patients, respectively. Also, let f = d<sub>+</sub>/d and let HˆR<sub>+</sub> and HˆR<sub>–</sub> be the corresponding estimated hazard ratios in the 2 subgroups. Finally, let HˆR<sub>AC</sub> denote the estimated hazard ratio in all patients in the study ignoring CDx status. Then, applying an argument similar to that in Reboussin et al,<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092861512438748">23</xref>
               </sup>
            </p>
            <p>log(HˆR<sub>AC</sub>) ≈ (1 – f) log(HˆR<sub>–</sub>) + f log(HˆR<sub>+</sub>)    (A1)</p>
            <p>and the approximate normality of log(HˆR<sub>AC</sub>) follows from the approximate normality of log(HˆR<sub>–</sub>) and log(HˆR<sub>+</sub>). If CDx status is prognostic for patient outcome, then approximation A1 is somewhat biased away from zero.<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0092861512438748">24</xref>
               </sup>
            </p>
            <p>All that is needed to apply A1 is an approximation for f. One possibility is ρ, the fraction of CDx-positive patients in the study, although this can be a poor approximation when CDx status is prognostic for patient outcome. A better option is to assume specific distributions for PFS times in the 4 CDx-by-treatment combinations and determine the expected value of f through simulation or numerical determinations.</p>
            <p>For the clinical uncertainty calculations in the phase 2 to phase 3 transition in the CDx CDP, the joint distribution of log(HˆR<sub>2,AC</sub>) and log(HˆR<sub>2,+</sub>) is bivariate normal with means and variances as before. The covariance of log(HˆR<sub>2,AC</sub>) and log(HˆR<sub>2,+</sub>) is easily determined from approximation A1 to be 4d<sup>-1</sup>, and the correlation is simply f. The necessary probabilities can be obtained from functions of bivariate normal quadrant probabilities available in most statistical software packages.</p>
            <p>For the clinical uncertainty calculations in the phase 3 to submission transition in the CDx CDP, the probability of a CDx submission when both HˆR<sub>3,AC</sub> and HˆR<sub>3,+</sub> are statistically significant involves HˆR<sub>3,–</sub> and is readily determined with numerical integration. </p>
         </app>
      </app-group>
      <fn-group>
         <fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-0092861512438748">
            <p>The authors declared the following potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: All authors were employees of Genentech Inc at the time this manuscript was developed.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-0092861512438748">
            <p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="bibr1-0092861512438748">
            <label>1</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Woodcock</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>The prospects for “personalized medicine” in drug development and drug therapy</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr2-0092861512438748">
            <label>2</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schilsky</surname>
                     <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Personalized medicine in oncology: the future is now</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr3-0092861512438748">
            <label>3</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fine</surname>
                     <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Amler</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Predictive biomarkers in the development of oncology drugs: a therapeutic industry perspective</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr4-0092861512438748">
            <label>4</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Slamon</surname>
                     <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Leyland-Jones</surname>
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Shak</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Use of chemotherapy plus a monoclonal antibody against HER2 for metastatic breast cancer that overexpresses HER2</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>344</volume>:<fpage>783</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr5-0092861512438748">
            <label>5</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Flaherty</surname>
                     <given-names>KT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Puzanov</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kim</surname>
                     <given-names>KB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of mutated, activated BRAF in metastatic melanoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>363</volume>:<fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>819</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr6-0092861512438748">
            <label>6</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bode-Greuel</surname>
                     <given-names>KM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Greuel</surname>
                     <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Determining the value of drug development candidates and technology platforms</article-title>. <source>J Commer Biotechnol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr7-0092861512438748">
            <label>7</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Steven</surname>
                     <given-names>SE</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Focused portfolio measures to support decision making throughout the pipeline</article-title>. <source>Drug Inf J</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr8-0092861512438748">
            <label>8</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rosati</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Decision analysis and drug development portfolio management: uncovering the real options value of your projects</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr9-0092861512438748">
            <label>9</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kaiser</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Helterbrand</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Barron</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Accounting for interim analyses in the assessment of program expected net present value</article-title>. <source>Drug Inf J</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr10-0092861512438748">
            <label>10</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Roth</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Keeling</surname>
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Smart</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Driving personalized medicine: capturing maximum net present value and optimal return on investment</article-title>. <source>Per Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr11-0092861512438748">
            <label>11</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kynn</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>The “heuristics and biases” bias in expert elicitation</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc Ser A</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>171</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr12-0092861512438748">
            <label>12</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kola</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Landis</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Can the pharmaceutical industry reduce attrition rates?</article-title> 
               <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr13-0092861512438748">
            <label>13</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>DiMasi</surname>
                     <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Grabowski</surname>
                     <given-names>HG</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Economics of new oncology drug development</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr14-0092861512438748">
            <label>14</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Trusheim</surname>
                     <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Berndt</surname>
                     <given-names>ER</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Douglas</surname>
                     <given-names>FL</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Stratified medicine: strategic and economic implications of combining drugs and clinical biomarkers</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr15-0092861512438748">
            <label>15</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Koch</surname>
                     <given-names>GG</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Discussion of “p-value adjustments for subgroup analyses.”</article-title> 
               <source>J Biopharm Stat</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr16-0092861512438748">
            <label>16</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lan</surname>
                     <given-names>KKG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>DeMets</surname>
                     <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Discrete sequential boundaries for clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>663</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr17-0092861512438748">
            <label>17</label>
            <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
               <collab collab-type="author" xlink:type="simple">Statistical Programs for Clinical Trials: ld98.exe</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/landemets/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/landemets/</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed February 14, 2012</comment>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr18-0092861512438748">
            <label>18</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rifai</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gillette</surname>
                     <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Carr</surname>
                     <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Protein biomarker discovery and validation: the long and uncertain path to clinical utility</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr19-0092861512438748">
            <label>19</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Phillips</surname>
                     <given-names>KA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Van Bebber</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Issa</surname>
                     <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostics and biomarker development: priming the pipeline</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage>. </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr20-0092861512438748">
            <label>20</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jones</surname>
                     <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Holmgren</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>An adaptive Simon two-stage design for phase 2 studies of targeted therapies</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Trials</source>. <year>2007</year>:<volume>28</volume>;<fpage>654</fpage>–<lpage>661</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr21-0092861512438748">
            <label>21</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brannath</surname>
                     <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zuber</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Branson</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Confirmatory adaptive designs with Bayesian decision tools for a targeted therapy in oncology</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1445</fpage>–<lpage>1463</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr22-0092861512438748">
            <label>22</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schoenfeld</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>The asymptotic properties of nonparametric tests for comparing survival distributions</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr23-0092861512438748">
            <label>23</label>
            <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Reboussin</surname>
                     <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>DeMets</surname>
                     <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kim</surname>
                     <given-names>KM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lan</surname>
                     <given-names>KKG</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Programs for computing group sequential boundaries using the Lan-DeMets method, Version 2</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/landemets/simple.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/landemets/simple.html</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed February 14, 2012</comment>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr24-0092861512438748">
            <label>24</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schmoor</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schumacher</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Effects of covariate omission and categorization when analysing randomized trials with the Cox model</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. <year>1997</year>:<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>