<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="meeting-report" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AAF</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaaf</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Adoption &amp; Fostering</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0308-5759</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1740-469X</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0308575913478784</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0308575913478784</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Legal notes</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Northern Ireland</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>37</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <fpage>87</fpage>
         <lpage>92</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="society">British Association for Adoption &amp; Fostering</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sec1-0308575913478784">
         <title>Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission’s Application: an application by the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission for Judicial Review (compatibility of the Adoption Order (NI) 1987 with the ECHR)</title>
         <sec id="sec2-0308575913478784">
            <title/>
            <p>The High Court QB (Judicial Review) Belfast Treacy J</p>
            <p>Delivered 18 October 2012</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec3-0308575913478784">
            <title>Application</title>
            <p>This case concerned an application from the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission (NIHRC) challenging Articles 14 and 15 of the Adoption (Northern Ireland) Order 1987 (‘the 1987 Order’) on the grounds that the eligibility criteria for adoption are unjustifiably discriminatory in breach of Articles 8 and 14 of the European Convention on Human Rights (ECHR). The central issue was that the NIHRC does not consider that unmarried couples should be barred from applying to adopt: the present eligibility criteria acts as a bar to unmarried couples and those who have entered into a civil partnership from even being considered as potential adopters; and it is ‘gravely concerned’ that Northern Ireland (NI) remains out of step with the rest of the UK.</p>
            <p>The absence of guidance to clarify the law is challenged, in the wake of the decision in <italic>Re P,</italic>
               <sup>
                  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0308575913478784">1</xref>
               </sup> for unmarried couples hoping to apply to adopt in NI. In the absence of a suitable individual or couple, the NIHRC has taken this judicial review itself and provided contextualisation through the affidavit evidence of C. C is a lesbian who is considering adopting with her partner, with whom she would also like to enter a civil partnership. If she does the latter, she will not be able to apply to adopt in any circumstances, either as an individual or as a couple.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec4-0308575913478784">
            <title>Factual background</title>
            <p>On 18 June 2008 the House of Lords delivered its judgment in <italic>Re P</italic>. Reversing the Court of Appeal in NI to reject, the House granted a declaration that it is unlawful for the High Court in NI to reject the applicants for adoption as prospective adoptive parents on the ground only that they are not married. In April 2010 the proposed Adoption and Children Bill (which it was assumed would deal with the issues raised in <italic>Re P</italic>) was indefinitely postponed and the Commission considered that it had no option but to challenge the prevailing status quo through these proceedings.</p>
            <p>Simultaneous to the above correspondences, C contacted the NIHRC following her experiences with various adoption agencies from which she had discovered that: ‘not only could my partner and I not even apply to be considered for adoption as a couple, but that should we enter a civil partnership, neither of us can ever adopt, either as a couple or as individuals’. C then decided to support the NIHRC application.</p>
            <p>Three other issues form part of the factual basis of this application. First is the 2006 consultation paper, ‘Adopting the Future’, which raised many of the issues at the centre of this application. Second is the question of guidance. After these proceedings were initiated, the Department issued a document and advice to deal with the issues raised in relation to <italic>Re P</italic>. This was confined to a recommendation that unmarried couples seek legal advice before applying to adopt. Finally, there is the issue of the amendment to Article 15 of the 1987 Order by section 203(4) of the Civil Partnership Act 2004 (‘the 2004 Act’) resulting in the total exclusion of a civil partner from adopting. As Baroness Hale said, with their lordships Walker, Hope and Lord Mance concurring:<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0308575913478784">2</xref>
               </sup> ‘This must have been a mistake. It means that registered civil partners have been totally excluded from adopting.’ However, as Treacy J commented:<disp-quote>
                  <p>‘In fact the Department now make the case that the total exclusion of registered civil partners from adopting was not a mistake but intended in order to clarify the fact that those in a civil partnership could not be considered single (just as those in marriage cannot be considered to be single) and was intended to “hold the ring” until the proposed new adoption legislation came into force.’</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec5-0308575913478784">
            <title>Arguments: the substantive issue</title>
            <sec id="sec6-0308575913478784">
               <title>The applicant</title>
               <p>The NIHRC argues that the current criteria concerning the eligibility to apply to adopt are discriminatory in as far as they apply to unmarried couples who (whether same or opposite sex) are free to apply to adopt in England, Wales and Scotland. The applicant identifies three outworkings of the 1987 Order which, it is argued, breach the Article 8 ECHR rights, in conjunction with Article 14 ECHR, of unmarried couples. These are: the failure to implement <italic>Re P</italic> has led to legal and practical uncertainty about the eligibility status of unmarried couples; unmarried couples may not adopt as couples; and no individual in a same-sex relationship may adopt if they have entered into a civil partnership.</p>
               <p>Further, the applicant submits that: the Department has failed to implement the judgment in <italic>Re P</italic> despite the finding there that Article 14 of the 1987 Order was incompatible with Articles 8 and 14 ECHR; while the Executive has responsibility for social policy in implementing responses to social issues, it may not act in an unjustifiably discriminatory manner and contends that Article 8 ECHR in conjunction with Article 14 ECHR is engaged; and that the respondent has failed to show that the discriminatory approach evidenced in Articles 14 and 15 of the 1987 Order is necessary or rationally connected to the averred legitimate end, which is the best interests of the child.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec7-0308575913478784">
               <title>The respondents</title>
               <p>The Department argues in response that there is no right to adopt on the grounds that: the eligibility criteria in Articles 14 and 15 of the 1987 Order represent the democratically accountable judgment of the Department in relation to what best protects the best interests of children; they have a duty to act cautiously in delivering the aims expressed in Article 9 of the 1987 Order; Article 8 ECHR is not engaged, as that Article protects only <italic>de facto</italic> and not <italic>de jure</italic> family life; the desire to adopt or found a family is not a relevant consideration in the adoption process. It is further argued by the respondent that the range of options available under the 1995 Children’s Order in relation to Residence Orders, Joint Responsibility Orders and Parental Responsibility Orders renders the practical reality convention compliant.</p>
            </sec>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec8-0308575913478784">
            <title>Re P</title>
            <sec id="sec9-0308575913478784">
               <title>The facts</title>
               <p>The applicants in <italic>Re P</italic> were an unmarried couple seeking to adopt the biological child of the female partner in the relationship. The couple had been together since before the child was born (over 11 years) but were prevented from applying to adopt as a couple by Article 14 of the 1987 Order. The court recognised that the operation of Article 14 to exclude unmarried couples from being eligible to adopt effected a breach of Articles 8–14. A declaration, that the pair were entitled to apply to adopt as a couple, was issued.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec10-0308575913478784">
               <title>Summary of the key points in the judgment</title>
               <p>Lord Hoffman confirmed that being unmarried was a status protected by Article 14 ECHR and the other Law Lords concurred with this view. He considered that the difference in treatment between unmarried and married couples as evidenced by Article 14 of the 1987 Order was not justified, noting that the effect of Article 14 is to exclude unmarried couples from being considered to adopt together, regardless of their other qualities. This means that if it is demonstrably in the best interests of a child to be adopted by a couple who are not married, a court would be forced to take a course of action that is not in the best interests of the child – ie to prevent that child from being jointly adopted by the couple in question<sup>
                     <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0308575913478784">3</xref>
                  </sup>– which would defeat the purpose of the order as expressed at Article 9. Ultimately, Lord Hoffman found that it was unlawful to reject the applicants as prospective adoptive parents on the sole ground of being unmarried.</p>
               <p>Lord Hope agreed that it was not justified to discriminate between married and unmarried couples with regard to their eligibility to apply to adopt.<sup>
                     <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0308575913478784">4</xref>
                  </sup> He acknowledged that just because the law had changed in the rest of the UK, it by no means followed that it should be changed in NI too, nor that it should be changed by judicial decision rather than by the Assembly. Like Lord Hoffman he cited with approval the decision of the South African Constitutional Court in the case of <italic>Du Toit and Vos</italic>, stating that it is consistent with authority in Scotland.<sup>
                     <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0308575913478784">5</xref>
                  </sup>
               </p>
               <p>Baroness Hale turned to the particular duty of the court in a democracy to safeguard the rights of even unpopular minorities against unjustified discrimination:<disp-quote>
                     <p>My Lords, I accept that there are differences between the cultural traditions of Northern Ireland and of Great Britain which should be taken into account in deciding whether this difference in treatment can be justified … adherence to traditional family values is more widespread in Northern Ireland … as is religious belief. But the legal traditions are the same as those in England and Wales … It is, as Lord Hope has pointed out, a particular duty of the courts in a democracy to safeguard the rights of even unpopular minorities against unjustified discrimination: therein lies the balance between majority rule and the human rights of all<sup>
                           <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0308575913478784">6</xref>
                        </sup> … I agree that a blanket ban on all joint adoptions by unmarried couples can no longer be justified.</p>
                  </disp-quote>
               </p>
               <p>Lord Mance expressed the view that the legislation was unjustifiably discriminatory on any objective assessment and cannot be reconciled with the respect for private and family life protected by Article 8 read with Article 14. He noted:<disp-quote>
                     <p>Objections to joint adoption by an unmarried couple face the problem that adoption by either one of such a couple is anyway permissible. Objections to cohabitation focus on the wrong point … I share the view of Baroness Hale of Richmond that cultural differences between Northern Ireland and Great Britain cannot justify a diametrically opposite approach to the possibility of adoption by an unmarried opposite sex couple in a child's interests.</p>
                  </disp-quote>
               </p>
               <p>Treacy J drew attention to the fact that several of the judges also noted that the enactment of the 2004 Act had the effect of excluding civil partners entirely from being considered to adopt, either individually or as a couple, and all failed to see any justification for this. He pointed out that each member of the House of Lords agreed on the substantive point that it was not justifiable to discriminate between married and unmarried couples in relation to their eligibility to apply to adopt jointly.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec11-0308575913478784">
               <title>Similarities and differences between the present issue and the issue in Re P</title>
               <p>Treacy J summarised by noting that at its core, the issues were the same in that they concern the justification for the difference in treatment between unmarried couples (same and opposite sex and including members of a civil partnership) and married couples and that, therefore, the reasoning in <italic>Re P</italic> is directly applicable.</p>
            </sec>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec12-0308575913478784">
            <title>Discussion: substantive issues</title>
            <p>Treacy J considered that two things were clear: there is no right to adopt, either in convention law or domestic law; and the sole purpose of adoption is to advance and promote the welfare of the child by providing a safe and secure environment in which she or he can grow to adulthood. However, while there is no right to adopt, statute has created a legal opportunity in the form of the right to apply to adopt. That right or opportunity falls squarely within the ambit of Article 8 and the state is enjoined by Article 14 to secure the enjoyment of the right without discrimination on any prohibited ground. He stressed that:<disp-quote>
                  <p>the justification for retaining the current eligibility criteria when considered from the point of view of a child’s right to be adopted has been demolished by the judgment in <italic>Re P </italic>… it is clear that the difference in treatment cannot be justified on any grounds and unmarried couples are suffering an ongoing breach of their Article 8 rights read together with Article 14, by the continued denial to them of the legal opportunity to apply to adopt jointly which is available to those who enjoy the status of being married.</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <sec id="sec13-0308575913478784">
               <title>The effect on those in a civil partnership</title>
               <p>Treacy J was of the view that the difference in treatment of persons in a civil partnership affected by Articles 14 and 15 as amended is even more deleterious:<disp-quote>
                     <p>Not only do they suffer the same discrimination that unmarried opposite sex couples experience when applying to adopt jointly, they also suffer unjustifiable discriminatory treatment when compared against individual members of an opposite sex couple who can apply to adopt as an individual. This is quite irrational and plainly unlawful.</p>
                  </disp-quote>
               </p>
               <p>He noted in <italic>Re P</italic> that the security of marriage remains a relevant consideration when assessing the suitability of a couple as prospective adopters. The 2004 Act was intended to give same-sex couples similar legal rights as those which accrue in a marriage. The present legislation essentially entails that a gay or lesbian person must choose between being eligible to adopt, or affirming their relationship in public via a civil partnership ceremony. Therefore, Articles 8–14 were clearly engaged on all of the above grounds.</p>
            </sec>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec14-0308575913478784">
            <title>Summary of the substantive issue</title>
            <p>Noting that the respondent avers that the current eligibility criteria serve the best interests of the child, Treacy J stated that he could find no rational basis for this contention. Excluding persons from the whole adoption process on the sole basis of their relationship status can only serve to narrow the pool of potential adopters, which cannot be in the best interests of children for the reasons identified in <italic>Re P</italic>. Further, the arguments in relation to the alternatives available under the relevant orders hold no weight. It cannot be in the best interests of a child to deny that child the full benefits of having two fully legal adoptive parents.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec15-0308575913478784" sec-type="conclusions">
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            <p>Pointing out that ‘adopting a child is no small undertaking’, Treacy J noted that this is even more so nowadays when the profile of children who need adoptive families has changed dramatically. Looked after children who require permanent adoptive homes tend to be older and often have special needs. They also often retain some links with their biological families. A loving, permanent, stable home is infinitely preferable to growing up in care. The potential benefit to a child adopted in such circumstances is immeasurable. As well as a huge benefit to the child, these adopters also provide an invaluable service to the state. No relationship is perfect and while there are benefits to an adopted child in entering a relationship where a web of legal rights exists between the parents, that web is no guarantee of a lifelong, stable, committed relationship. The most important consideration is that decisions are made in the best interests of the child. Issues relating to the sexual orientation, lifestyle, race, religion or other characteristics of the parties involved must of course be taken into account as part of the circumstances. But they cannot be allowed to prevail over what is in the best interests of the child.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec16-0308575913478784">
            <title>Held</title>
            <p>Application for judicial review allowed.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec17-0308575913478784">
            <title>Postscript</title>
            <p>Following a remedies hearing on 26 October, the court declared as follows:
<list id="list1-0308575913478784" list-type="simple">
                  <list-item>
                     <p>(a) Notwithstanding Articles 14 and 15 of the Adoption (Northern Ireland) Order 1987 it does not prevent couples who are not married, or in a Civil Partnership, from applying to adopt a child pursuant to the terms of that Order. All individuals and couples, regardless of marriage status or sexual orientation are eligible to be considered as an adoptive parent(s);</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <p>(b) Any guidance published by the Respondent must accord with the declaration at (a) above.</p>
                  </list-item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sec18-0308575913478784" sec-type="conclusions">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>Five years will soon have passed since the House of Lords declared it unlawful for the High Court in NI to reject applications from prospective adoptive parents on the sole ground that they are not married. Before and after that decision, several members of the NI judiciary have also shared views similar to the above good sense expressed by their lordships. It is now long past time for the Department to issue revised legislation that addresses the serious deficits in NI adoption law; deficits that result in children remaining in care because they are denied the opportunity of adoption.  On that point, it is not possible to let pass without comment Treacy J’s remark that ‘a loving, permanent, stable home is infinitely preferable to growing up in care’. Given that for most children in care, the growing up is something they do in the home of foster parents, it does a disservice to such carers (however inadvertently) to imply that their home is any less ‘loving, permanent, stable’ than that provided by adopters. In some cases they are one and the same, as children are often adopted by their foster parents. In other cases, there are good reasons why it is better for a child to grow up in the care of long-term foster parents rather than start again with adopters. While the choice must always turn on the best interests of the child concerned, it can only be beneficial if the number and range of available adopters are increased.</p>
         </sec>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <notes>
         <title>Notes</title>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1-0308575913478784">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>[2008] UKHL 38; [2009] 1 AC 173</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2-0308575913478784">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Ibid at para 101.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3-0308575913478784">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Citing with approval the decision of the South African Constitutional Court in <italic>Du Toit and Vos v Minister for Welfare and Population Development</italic> (2002) 13 BHRC 187, at paras 21–22, where the prospective adoptive parents were a same-sex couple.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4-0308575913478784">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Referring to <italic>EB v France</italic> [2008] Application No 43546/02.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5-0308575913478784">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Citing <italic>T, Petitioner</italic> 1997 SLT 724, 732B-C.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6-0308575913478784">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Citing <italic>Ghaidan v Godin-Mendoza</italic> [2004] UKHL 30, [2004] 2 AC 557, at para 132.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
      <bio xlink:type="simple">
         <p>
            <bold>Kerry O'Halloran</bold>, lawyer, social worker and Adjust Professor at the Centre of Philanthropy and Non-profit Studies, QUT, Brisbane, Australia, prepared these notes.</p>
      </bio>
   </back>
</article>