<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PWM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppwm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Public Works Management &amp; Policy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1087-724X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7549</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1087724X12462831</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1087724X12462831</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Degradation Modeling of Polyurea Pavement Markings</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Sitzabee</surname><given-names>William E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1087724X12462831">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>Edward D.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>Austin W.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1087724X12462831"><label>1</label>Cornell University, Ithaca, ID, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1087724X12462831"><label>2</label>Air Force Institute of Technology, OH, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1087724X12462831">William E. Sitzabee, Cornell University, 113 Barton Hall, Ithaca, ID 14850, USA. Email: <email>wes228@cornell.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>199</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Polyurea is a long life, quick-curing material used in pavement markings and a material of interest to the North Carolina Department of Transportation. This article presents a performance model and the characteristics of polyurea pavement markings in North Carolina by using Ordinary Least Squares models. The performance-based models provide pavement marking managers with tools to better allocate limited manpower and resources to optimize budgets while maintaining newly proposed pavement marking retroreflectivity levels of service. This research constructed performance models for polyurea pavement markings based on the independent variables of time, initial retroreflectivity, lateral line location, and annual average daily traffic. Using the models generated by this research, pavement marking managers can predict the remaining life of a given pavement marking to maintain a standard level of service. A key finding of this article is that the type of glass bead used in the marking significantly affects polyurea pavement marking degradation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>pavement marking</kwd>
<kwd>pavement management</kwd>
<kwd>asset management</kwd>
<kwd>degradation</kwd>
<kwd>traffic control devices</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1087724X12462831" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>State Departments of Transportation (DOTs) across the nation are engaged in a perpetual cycle of removal and replacement of pavement markings. Pavement markings, specifically the retroreflectivity (R<sub>L</sub>) of the markings, are important in keeping the safety of public road system at acceptable performance levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1087724X12462831">Sasidharan, Vishesh, &amp; Donnell, 2009</xref>). In 1993, the U.S. Congress directed the U.S. Secretary of Transportation to revise the Manual of Uniform Traffic Control Devices (MUTCD) to include minimum standards for pavement marking retroreflectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1087724X12462831">U.S. Congress, 1993</xref>). In April 2010, these minimum standards were proposed for adoption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1087724X12462831">Federal Highway Administration, 2010</xref>). To meet and keep these minimum standards, a proper management plan must be in place by which this cycle of removal and replacement is made most effective; both cost-wise and safety-wise. The backbone of many such management plans are performance models, which are used to predict the current state and life cycle of pavement markings.</p>
<p>Degradation models are the basis of performance modeling and critical to predicting the life cycles of various types of pavement marking retroreflectivity levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1087724X12462831">Rasdorf, Hummer, Harris, &amp; Sitzabee, 2009</xref>). Knowing when a particular marking material is likely to fall below the proposed minimum accepted retroreflectivity standard will allow DOTs to create a plan to replace that material at the proper time. Without degradation models, it is simply a subjective approach as to when a given marking needs to be replaced. The purpose of this article is to present the results of Ordinary Least Square degradation modeling of polyurea pavement markings. The resulting model provides additional tools for asset managers and pavement marking managers to use in their development of pavement marking management plans and allocation of limited resources as well as manpower. Keep in mind anyone who is managing pavement markings with an interest in keeping the cost down and extending the life of the material is an asset manager and can benefit from implementing performance-based modeling into their marking strategies. According to the Federal Highway Administration, an asset manager is anyone who uses a strategic approach to manage a physical infrastructure asset using cost-effective solutions based on sound engineering and business practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1087724X12462831">Cambridge Systematics Inc., 2002</xref>). In this case, an asset manager is anyone who would implement a performance-based model to manage pavement marking infrastructure systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1087724X12462831">
<title>Objective and Scope</title>
<p>Degradation models currently exist for a variety of pavement marking materials to include waterborne paint, epoxy, and thermoplastic pavement markings, which make up the majority of pavement markings nationwide; however, these degradation models vary based on marking type, geographic location, and marking manufacturer, to name a few (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1087724X12462831">Sarasua, Clark, &amp; Davis, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">Sitzabee, Hummer, &amp; Rasdorf, 2009</xref>). Polyurea is a common pavement marking material; yet it does not currently have acceptable degradation models that can accurately predict its life cycle. As a result, this research focuses on the use of polyurea data collected throughout North Carolina.</p>
<p>Polyurea is the fourth most common material used in North Carolina, after waterborne paint, thermoplastics, and epoxy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">Sitzabee et al., 2009</xref>). This research considers data collected in North Carolina over a period of 5 years on one of the largest state-maintained road systems. Specifically, this research formulates a service life degradation model for polyurea by considering the following variables:</p>
<list id="list1-1087724X12462831" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Annual average daily traffic (AADT);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Type of glass bead used (standard bead or highly reflective elements);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Time;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Initial retroreflectivity value;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lateral line location.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1087724X12462831">
<title>Background</title>
<p>The underlying reason for constructing degradation models is to have better understanding of material performance when developing asset management plans and allocating limited resources as well as manpower. Each year, DOTs spend millions of dollars in pavement marking expenditures and due to proposed national standards, expenditures are with an expected increase of 64 million US dollars, as a result of the proposed national standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1087724X12462831">Hawkins, Lupes, Schertz, Satterfield, &amp; Carlson, 2010</xref>). Not only is the cost of marking materials included in that price, but thousands of man-hours must also be paid in the execution of management plans; and this material cost does not include the intangible cost of worker safety. DOTs also consider the potential for worker injury or equipment destruction when considering the full cost of pavement marking application and maintenance. With a better understanding of the life cycle of a given marking material, both monetary and intangible costs can be minimized while maximizing retroreflectivity performance and effectively utilizing limited resources.</p>
<sec id="section4-1087724X12462831">
<title>Retroreflectivity</title>
<p>Retroreflectivity is the key indicator of pavement marking performance. It is “the amount of light returned back to a driver from a vehicle’s headlights as it is reflected from the pavement marking” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">Sitzabee et al., 2009</xref>, pp. 191). When pavement markings are placed, glass beads are mixed into the marking and protrude from the surface of the marking allowing light to pass through the bead. The light then refracts, bounces off the marking, and reflects the color of the marking back to the driver. The value of the intensity of the reflection is measured in millicandelas per meter squared of luminance (mcd/m<sup>2</sup>/lux) and is known as the retroreflectivity value. This value is typically represented by the abbreviation R<sub>L</sub>.</p>
<p>ASTM standard E1710-05 specifies the entrance angle of the light to be 88.76 degrees, measured from a reference axis perpendicular to the pavement surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1087724X12462831">American Society of Testing and Materials [ASTM], 2005</xref>). The observation angle is specified to be 1.05 degrees from the pavement. These specifications are based on the headlight being positioned 0.65 m above the pavement and an eye height of 1.2 m above the pavement. The eye position height is based on the vertical distance traveled by the light over a horizontal distance of 30 m from the reflection point and an angle of 1.05 degrees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1087724X12462831">ASTM, 2005</xref>). All measurements taken by the retroreflectometer used in this research were calibrated to this standard of 30 m geometry.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1087724X12462831">
<title>Previous Research</title>
<p>Over 83% of pavement markings in use today on the nation’s roadways are comprised of paints and thermoplastics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1087724X12462831">Migletz &amp; Graham, 2002</xref>). DOTs typically apply paint to secondary roads with a low traffic volume while thermoplastics are used mainly on primary roads. However, polyurea is also used along with several other types of markings, such as preformed plastics, epoxy, and polyester for high volume roads. Polyurea is significantly more expensive than thermoplastic or paint and cures faster; therefore it is typically used in specific applications such as concrete bridge decks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1087724X12462831">NCDOT, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Research on pavement marking retroreflectivity has been ongoing since the mid-1980s. Early studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1087724X12462831">Lee et al. (1999)</xref> demonstrate that markings degrade in a linear fashion, but the resulting models possessed a poor fit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">Sitzabee et al., 2009</xref>). While the majority of literature reviewed was based on linear regression modeling, other methods were used as well such as logarithmic and Linear Mixed Effects Modeling (LMEM; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1087724X12462831">Abboud &amp; Bowman, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1087724X12462831">Hummer, Rasdorf, &amp; Zhang, 2011</xref>). The simplicity of linear regression is what makes it a proven modeling technique; however, linear regression may not always produce the most predictive model.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1087724X12462831">Table 1</xref> highlights studies that date back to 1999 and represent a significant sample of a large body of knowledge on modeling pavement marking retroreflectivity degradation. Each of these studies, representing key research for the last decade, evaluates retroreflectivity degradation and identifies key variables, which impact and significantly describe R<sub>L</sub> performance over time. These studies provide the foundation for the methodology used in this study of polyurea pavement markings.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1087724X12462831" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Literature.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1087724X12462831" xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Year</th>
<th align="center">Authors</th>
<th align="center">Model type</th>
<th align="center"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center">Marking material</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1087724X12462831">1999</xref></td>
<td>Lee et al.</td>
<td>Linear</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>Thermoplastic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1087724X12462831">2001</xref></td>
<td>Migletz et al.</td>
<td>Linear</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>Durable</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1087724X12462831">2002</xref></td>
<td>Abboud and Bowman</td>
<td>Logarithmic</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1087724X12462831">2003</xref></td>
<td>Sarasua et al.</td>
<td>Complex curve with a Linear region</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>Thermoplastics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1087724X12462831">2004</xref></td>
<td>Kopf</td>
<td>Linear</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>Paint, Thermo</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Fitch</td>
<td>Logarithmic</td>
<td>.53-.86</td>
<td>Polyurea</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">2009</xref></td>
<td>Sitzabee et al.</td>
<td>Linear</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>Thermoplastic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1087724X12462831">2011</xref></td>
<td>Hummer et al.</td>
<td>Mixed effects</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>Paint</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1087724X12462831">Migletz, Graham, Harwood, and Bauer (2001)</xref> compiled a pavement marking synthesis, which summarized a great deal of the literature on pavement markings. However, very little performance modeling had been accomplished by then. Current literature has focused more on performance modeling and shows several factors influence pavement marking retroreflectivity values and degradation rates. Factors such as age, material type, color, surface type, snow plowing, and annual average daily traffic (AADT) have all been considered in modeling pavement marking performance.</p>
<p>Marking age is the predominate factor in pavement marking degradation with most studies showing retroreflectivity linearly associated with age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1087724X12462831">Lee et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1087724X12462831">Sarasua, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1087724X12462831">Bahar, Masiliah, Erwin, &amp; Tan, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1087724X12462831">Kopf, 2004</xref>). Other studies proposed using nonlinear modeling such as an exponential or logarithmic transformation to estimate retroreflectivity according to age of pavement marking after installation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1087724X12462831">Andrady, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1087724X12462831">Perrin, Martin, &amp; Hansen, 2001</xref>). For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1087724X12462831">Karwa and Donnell (2011)</xref> proposed a nonlinear model to estimate retroreflectivity according to initial retroreflectivity, the age of the markings, traffic flow, pavement marking type, and route location information. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1087724X12462831">Hummer et al. (2011)</xref> showed the usefulness of a Linear Mixed Effects Model for retroreflectivity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1087724X12462831">Craig, Sitzabee, Rasdorf, and Hummer (2007)</xref> showed that white and yellow markings achieve different levels of retroreflectivity with white generally measuring higher than yellow markings. Additionally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1087724X12462831">Craig et al. (2007)</xref> proved that line location laterally across the road segment was a key variable that significantly impacts degradation. Traffic volume has been a controversial factor with some studies showing that AADT is a factor while others show it is not. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">Sitzabee et al. (2009)</xref> showed that traffic volumes (AADT) affect markings while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1087724X12462831">Abboud and Bowman (2002)</xref> suggested that vehicle exposure (time × AADT) replaces time or traffic volume alone. With retroreflectivity depending on glass beads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1087724X12462831">Zhang &amp; Wu, 2006</xref>), it would seem that more studies would have evaluated the impact of beads on degradation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1087724X12462831">
<title>Why Polyurea?</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1087724X12462831">Migletz and Graham (2002)</xref> list the 16 most common materials used across the United States and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1087724X12462831">Sitzabee et al. (2009)</xref> highlighted the four most common materials used in North Carolina as waterborne paint, thermoplastics, epoxy, and polyurea. Currently pavement markings in North Carolina consist of 60% paint and 35% thermoplastic. Polyurea currently comprises a small percentage of pavement markings in North Carolina; nevertheless, research into its attributes is still warranted. Polyurea is used only in specific applications, all of which experience high volumes of traffic. The North Carolina Department of Transportation (NCDOT) has implemented a policy to replace epoxy with polyurea due to its quick curing time; this policy will significantly increase its usage and is important for two reasons. First, the high volume of vehicle passes over a marking causes that marking to wear at an accelerated pace. Second, when restriping is required in these areas, significant traffic delays are caused by closing lanes for the restriping operations. Additional concerns are raised due to construction crews being exposed to high volumes of traffic. Development of a performance model describing and predicting polyurea characteristics creates a tool, which pavement marking managers can use to better plan when and where polyurea pavement markings should be used.</p>
<p>Additionally, polyurea is considered a low profile marking material when compared to thermoplastic. NCDOT specifies polyurea to be 20 mils thick while thermoplastics are specified to be 90 to120 mils thick (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1087724X12462831">NCDOT, 2006</xref>). Because of its thinner profile, polyurea is used in areas with high snowplow exposure as well as areas with limited access such as bridge decks. Its thin profile allows snow plows to pass without damaging the marking and all other traffic to pass with minimal impact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1087724X12462831">Sasidharan et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1087724X12462831">
<title>Need for Performance Models</title>
<p>With the nationwide cost of pavement markings exceeding two billion dollars annually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1087724X12462831">Hawkins et al., 2010</xref>), it has become necessary to build performance models for each pavement-marking material. An asset manager, who, in this case, is anyone who manages pavement markings, can use performance models to create more effective asset management programs, which could easily reduce annual budgets. Furthermore, with federal minimum standards for retroreflectivity pending (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1087724X12462831">FHWA, 2009</xref>), it is even more critical that DOTs have better asset management tools to assist in managing pavement-marking programs. Knowing when a particular pavement marking is going to fail is critical to optimizing DOT pavement-marking budgets. Without performance models, decisions on when to replace a given marking is based on best guess and rules of thumb, which are not scientific and do not maximize service lives of pavement markings. This research specifically benefits anyone who plans, programs, schedules, or executes pavement-marking operations. These can include all levels of transportation asset managers such as district engineers; federal, state, and local maintenance crews; and public administrators.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1087724X12462831">
<title>Data Collection</title>
<p>The retroreflectivity data for this study were collected over a 5-year period for approximately 30,000 miles of roads (multilane highways to two-lane roads) at initial installation and then again at 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months after installation via a modified Laserlux mobile retroreflectometer (model LLR5) mounted on a Chevrolet Suburban. The initial R<sub>L</sub> values were measured within 30 days of installation, but the researchers did not possess data that indicate the installation dates of the pavement markings. Mobile retroreflectometers are especially effective for collecting large volumes of data because they can be used at highway speeds. This allows the technician to remain safely inside the vehicle and collect a large amount of data in a short period of time. For a data collection effort of this magnitude, a handheld retroreflectometer simply would be too time-consuming to be practical.</p>
<p>The LLR5 uses the standard 30-m geometry as required by ASTM E 1710-97 and averages the R<sub>L</sub> readings at every 10th of a mile increments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1087724X12462831">ASTM, 2005</xref>). As a result of the equipment averaging the reading every 10th of a mile, the researchers were not able to conduct repeated measures from year to year to determine a temporal correlation. The units were recorded in mcd/m<sup>2</sup>/lux by an onboard computer to eliminate user error when entering data. The resulting data set contained 1,142 entries.</p>
<p>Vehicle-mounted retroreflectometers are safe and accurate, but they are not without error. To minimize this error, a rigorous calibration process was adhered to for the duration of the data collection. Prior to every trip, the unit was calibrated against a known test bed of pavement markings at the NCDOT maintenance facility. This test bed R<sub>L</sub> value was established with a handheld LTL2000 retroreflectometer. Each time the LLR5 was calibrated against the test bed, adjustments were made to account for suspension changes, tire pressure, and ambient light. Additionally, the LTL2000 was taken into the field on each trip and used to verify the calibration of the mobile unit each time any conditions changed in the field such as amount of daylight or weather conditions.</p>
<p>The data used in this study were collected by an independent contractor and originally intended for quality assurance purposes. Since regression analysis wasn’t the primary focus of the data collection, there were some limitations to the analysis of these data. However, after extensive data mining, the resulting reduced data set was found to be of high quality for use in linear modeling. The data mining process largely consisted of separating polyurea data from a larger data set that included all types of markings in North Carolina. Additionally, the researchers removed extraneous information from the database such as the names of the technicians collecting the data, street names, and phone number, to name a few. The most significant removal of information was the deletion of retroreflectivity values equal to zero mcd/m<sup>2</sup>/lux. These values represent a data collection error, which was confirmed with the data collectors. Even though the resulting data set was significantly smaller than the original, the information contained therein could immediately be used for modeling purposes. Many possible variables were contained in the data set, but only variables meeting the customary 0.05 significance level were included in a least-squares analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1087724X12462831" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>This study used the method of Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) or linear least squares to estimate the unknown parameters in the model. The method of OLS aims to predict a response variable, <italic>y</italic>, from a set of explanatory variables, <italic>x</italic>. OLS accomplishes this by minimizing the Sum of Squared Errors (SSE), which is the sum of the squared residuals (the difference between the <italic>y</italic>s and the predicted values, <italic>Ŷ</italic>s). OLS investigates for a mathematical association and not necessarily a cause and effect relationship. The overall model that OLS develops is statistically accessed via an <italic>F</italic>-test that tests for any statistical significance between <italic>y</italic> and any of the <italic>x</italic> predictors. The level of significance for this test is 0.05, the customary Type I error for hypothesis tests. For the OLS model to have statistical inferential validity, the model residuals must be normally distributed, display homoscedasticity, and be serially uncorrelated. These assumptions are checked and tested for with respect to the OLS model presented in this article.</p>
<p>Specifically this section presents the development of the OLS regression model for predicting the retroreflectivity level (R<sub>L</sub>) value of polyurea. Initially, attempts were made to have R<sub>L</sub> as the dependent variable; however, the customary OLS assumptions of normality and homoscedasticity of model residuals did not hold for such a model. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1087724X12462831">Figure 1</xref> illustrates this heteroscedasticity (nonconstant variance) of model residuals. These residuals resulted from a preliminary OLS model of regressing R<sub>L</sub> onto AADT (average number of vehicles per day on a given roadway), bead type (standard bead or highly reflective elements), time (in months from 6 months to 60 months), initial retroreflectivity level (IRL), and lateral line location (center or edge).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1087724X12462831" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Scatterplot of model residuals (R<sub>L</sub> Residual) by (R<sub>L</sub> Predicted).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>To partially remedy this heteroscedasticity issue the dependent variable was changed to the ratio of R<sub>L</sub> to IRL. Second, individual regression models were developed for each range of AADT before incorporating all the models into one macro OLS model. It was discovered that besides R<sub>L</sub> causing issues with heteroscedasticity of model residuals, the average amount of vehicles traveling on a road also contributed to this nonconstancy of variance. The type of variables and the magnitude effect of those variables greatly change depending on the AADT range. This latter finding is discussed in more detail in the conclusion section.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1087724X12462831" sec-type="results">
<title>Analysis and Results</title>
<p>The modeling database consisted of 1,142 points of which only one point was excluded. This point was removed because of an inordinate decline in retroreflectivity from an IRL of 999 to a R<sub>L</sub> of 408 in 6 months. This calculated decline of approximately 60% in a relatively short span of time indicated a problem with marking application and not with polyurea itself. From this modeling database of 1,141 points, the dependent variable of R<sub>L</sub> to IRL was calculated. AADT was also broken into 10 traffic volume categories (average number of vehicles passing on that roadway a day) based on the similarities of independent variables that proved predictive for that range. By allowing the OLS model to incorporate certain ranges of AADT, the model would look to only those data points within that particular range to model the ratio of R<sub>L</sub> to IRL for that AADT range.</p>
<p>For all AADT ranges, the independent variables presented proved very statistically significant. With the exception of one independent variable (and its <italic>p</italic> value was .0003), all the explanatory variables had a <italic>p</italic> value &lt; .0001. (Note: even the intercepts proved to be significant with the smallest <italic>p</italic> value being .002.) To verify the modeling building process, all-subsets stepwise regression analysis was conducted post hoc and no other simple statistical trends were discovered to override what is presented. All analysis to include linear regressions was performed using the JMP<sup>®</sup> statistical software.</p>
<p>Before listing the explanatory variables for each AADT range, it is noted that the decay rate of the polyurea proved to be highly predictive for nearly all of the ranges (this variable is called ‘Time Adj Decay’ in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> with an associated <italic>p</italic> value of .0001 or lower). The decay rate of R<sub>L</sub> does not follow a linear trend; in fact it appears more of an exponential decay and changes depending on bead type. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1087724X12462831">Figure 2</xref> highlights these decay rates. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equation (1)</xref> shows the mathematical equation for the decay rate for standard beads, while <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">Equation (2)</xref> shows the mathematical equation for the highly reflective beads. Both equations are only applicable for up to 60 months, to coincide with the time range of the database. Both equations are nonlinear in nature and Microsoft’s Solver<sup>®</sup> was used to estimate the decay parameters using the method of maximum likelihood.</p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-1087724X12462831">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Standard Bead</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>486</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>139</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>9</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831" xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-1087724X12462831">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Highly Reflective Bead</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>836</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>191</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>25</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831" xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1087724X12462831" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Predictive Explanatory Variables for Each Range of AADT.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1087724X12462831" xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">AADT band (Vehicles per day)</th>
<th align="center">Variable name</th>
<th align="center">Parameter estimate</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>&lt;2,000</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−176.21</td>
<td>0.0020</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&lt;2,000</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.68</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&lt;2,000</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2,000-5,000</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>162.64</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2,000-5,000</td>
<td>Center line</td>
<td>−123.22</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2,000-5,000</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5,800-7,800</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−718.74</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5,800-7,800</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5,800-7,800</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>1.66</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5,800-7,800</td>
<td>Standard bead</td>
<td>298.85</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8,200-9,800</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>986.06</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8,200-9,800</td>
<td>Time (months)</td>
<td>−2.05</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8,200-9,800</td>
<td>AADT</td>
<td>−0.078</td>
<td>0.0003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10,000-11,000</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−979.89</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10,000-11,000</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>2.49</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10,000-11,000</td>
<td>Standard bead</td>
<td>408.03</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10,000-11,000</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14,000-29,000</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−664.18</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14,000-29,000</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>1.78</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14,000-29,000</td>
<td>Standard bead</td>
<td>352.49</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14,000-29,000</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30,000-38,000</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−1602.78</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30,000-38,000</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30,000-38,000</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>1.56</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30,000-38,000</td>
<td>AADT</td>
<td>0.027</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30,000-38,000</td>
<td>Standard bead</td>
<td>283.15</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30,000-38,000</td>
<td>Snow plowed</td>
<td>67.94</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45,000-79,000</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−311.99</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45,000-79,000</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45,000-79,000</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45,000-79,000</td>
<td>Standard bead</td>
<td>178.94</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>83,500-89,500</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−991.75</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>83,500-89,500</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>1.94</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>83,500-89,500</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100.5K-116K</td>
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>−714.49</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100.5K-116K</td>
<td>Time adj decay</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100.5K-116K</td>
<td>Standard bead</td>
<td>409.47</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100.5K-116K</td>
<td>Initial RL</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-1087724X12462831" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Retroreflectivity level (R<sub>L</sub>) decay rates for polyurea.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> next presents the predictive explanatory variables for each range of AADT in the model database. The variables listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> are defined as follows: Initial R<sub>L</sub>(mcd/m<sup>2</sup>/lux) is the initial retroreflectivity level at time of application, while Time Adj Decay is the decay function described in either <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equations (1)</xref> or (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>) depending on which bead (standard bead or highly reflective) is being used for R<sub>L</sub> prediction. Center Line, Standard Bead, and Snow Plowed represent dummy variables (dichotomous variables) wherein these explanatory variables assume a “1” if the prediction is for either middle of the road, standard bead, or snow plowed application, and zero otherwise. AADT represents the annual average daily traffic for that particular AADT range (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> for the applicable range).</p>
<p>With respect to interpreting the estimated OLS parameter estimates for each AADT band, none of them are directly interpretable except for IRL. This is because the decay function presented in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equations (1)</xref> or (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>) depends on bead type used for that roadway. That is, one cannot hold the explanatory variable Standard Bead constant while varying the decay function of time (the variable Time Adj Decay in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref>) and vice versa because both of these variables are related via the nonlinear functions in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equations (1)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>). In addition, the intercept estimate also is changing, which in turn makes any explanatory variable that adjusts the baseline, that is, Snowplowed, not interpretable. Since IRL is never involved with changing the baseline or involved with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equations (1)</xref> or (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>) and is a continuous measure, it is the only explanatory variable whose parameter estimate is directly interpretable. Those parameter estimates are all positive, which is in the direction one would expect.</p>
<p>The main utility of the parameter estimates in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> comes from knowing which values to use, within the applicable AADT range, and then applying them to the macro OLS model to get an estimated R<sub>L</sub>. For the most part, the parameter estimates in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> modify the decay functions as shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equations (1)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1087724X12462831">2</xref>) by altering the rate of degradation or the horizontal asymptote. But more importantly than that, the parameter estimates show the great variability between them as one looks at the AADT ranges. In other words, the fact the same explanatory variables are not appearing in each AADT as well as having the same magnitude sign illustrates aflux in variability caused by AADT. For had AADT not played a significant role in model building, one would expect the parameter estimates to be reasonably close to one another from one AADT block to another. As an example of this variability, the intercept estimates range from −1602.28 to 986.6, and the parameter estimates for the decay functions (the Time Adj. Decay variable in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref>) varies from 0.6 to 2.49, which for a nonlinear function represents a wide range.</p>
<p>In terms of model application, one would first find the applicable AADT range within <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref> and use the associated parameter estimates from within that interval to arrive at the initial predictive response of R<sub>LAADT</sub>. After which, one would then apply <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1087724X12462831">Equation (3)</xref></p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1087724X12462831">
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-1087724X12462831">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>LADDT</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>87</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>Initial</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
<mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>09</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-1087724X12462831" xlink:href="10.1177_1087724X12462831-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p>to arrive at the OLS estimate of R<sub>L</sub>. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1087724X12462831">Equation (3)</xref> represents the overall macro OLS model and has an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value of .64. This model passes the residual assumptions of normality via the Shapiro-Wilk test and homoscedasticity via the Breusch-Pagan test. Both pass at the customary 0.05 level of significance. A possible negative aspect of using this model is that one would need to know the Initial R<sub>L</sub>. Given there are usual minimum R<sub>L</sub> standards required for a contractor or worker to adhere to when initially applying the polyurea, this minimum could be used as the IRL.</p>
<p>With respect to an application of the OLS model, suppose one wished to predict the R<sub>L</sub> of a road painted with polyurea (standard bead) 2 years into the future that has an AADT of 50,000 and an initial IRL of 400. One would then arrive at the following RL<sub>AADT</sub> estimate using <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1087724X12462831">Table 2</xref>: 289.54 = −311.99 + 0.54 * 400 + 0.93 * 222.14 + 178.94, where 222.14 is obtained from the decay function shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1087724X12462831">Equation (1)</xref> for standard bead and time equal to 24 months. Plugging 289.54 into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1087724X12462831">Equation (3)</xref> along with an Initial R<sub>L</sub> of 400, one arrives at the R<sub>L</sub> estimate of 287.9.</p>
<p>This example illustrates two key points from the analysis: One, a fallback estimate of R<sub>L</sub> via the decay functions shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1087724X12462831">Figure 1</xref> is given for roadways whose AADT does not appear within the intervals modeled (can be somewhat considered the unconditional R<sub>L</sub> estimate); using the decay functions themselves results in an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value of .45 for predicting R<sub>L</sub>. Second, AADT plays a major role in determining R<sub>L</sub> in the sense that for different ranges some explanatory variables appear predictive while others do not. And even for the key drivers of Initial R<sub>L</sub>, bead type, and decay rate over time, their effects change from range to range (as mentioned earlier). The analysis suggests that AADT may or may not be deemed predictive for other studies depending on the AADT range being considered for a study on a micro scale. For larger or macro studies, AADT appears to be a major driver in determining R<sub>L</sub>. Consistent with the literature, this study shows that AADT is significant and pavement managers need to consider the effects of AADT on pavement markings, but is often hidden in the function of time because of the selective application of material by pavement marking managers.</p>
<p>Lastly, both the Mean Absolute Percentage Error (MAPE) and the Median Absolute Percentage Error (MdAPE) were used to descriptively determine the accuracy of the OLS model developed and shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1087724X12462831">Equation (3)</xref>. All 1,141 data points were used to determine these descriptive measures. Overall, the MAPE and MdAPE scores consisted of 17% and 12%, respectively. Considering no other polyurea regression models were found in the literature, these numbers now serve as a baseline for others to compare.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1087724X12462831" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>With no real model for polyurea presented in the reviewed literature, the results of this study are significant and can be considered the baseline for future research for this material. Furthermore, this study proved unique by highlighting that the physical characteristics of polyurea and its decay rate are different from paint and thermoplastic and that the material can be successfully modeled as an exponential function. Recall that the majority of the previous studies presented in this article show that paint and thermoplastic pavement markings degrade in a linear fashion.</p>
<p>A significant finding of this study is the impact of AADT on pavement marking degradation. We clarify why AADT proves significant in some studies and not significant in others. The proposed models reflect what the literature has been stating and show the inconsistency in AADT, which does affect degradation. However, the lack of consistency in the literature is more likely a result of management application policies and not the actual impact of traffic volume. For example, some studies show AADT as predictive and others have not. If a study only looked at a narrow band of AADT it is very possible AADT didn’t show up as being predictive, since the key variables within that range didn’t change much. However, as the AADT range was further expanded to perhaps “encroach” on another band that we identified then some key variables would suddenly appear while others dropped out. This shifting in and out of predictor variables reflects AADT being a conditional variable and hence key driver in determining R<sub>L</sub>. Future studies need to consider the selective application of materials when determining the impact of AADT on performance.</p>
<p>Finally, this study shows the tremendous variability with polyurea, especially with the highly reflective beads, which seems to come from the initial installation of material. High variability is consistent with the literature and one of the frustrations performance modelers have been dealing with for over a decade. This finding would suggest a need for the industry to develop more stringent controls on installation specifications, which would ultimately result in better degradation rates and consistent performance of pavement marking materials such as polyurea. Overall, these performance-based degradation models serve to predict the remaining service life of a given polyurea pavement marking to allow pavement marking managers to better allocate limited manpower and resources while providing a standard level of service for retroreflectivity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1087724X12462831">
<title>Future Research</title>
<p>The significant finding produced by this study is the impact of bead type on degradation. While highly reflective elements produce pavement markings with much higher initial R<sub>L</sub> values, the decay rate is substantially greater than standard bead degradation. However, based on the models, at the 60-month mark pavement markings containing highly reflective elements produce almost twice the retroreflectance than those containing standard beads.</p>
<p>It is recommended that future research collect data specific to highly reflective elements. Advancements in understanding the performance characteristics of highly reflective elements have the potential to significantly impact the effectiveness of pavement marking performance models. Future studies should collect data pertaining to pavement markings with highly reflective elements, recording at a minimum the same variables used in this study. It is recommended that the collection effort continue for at least 8 years to improve on the current model presented in this article.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>William E. Sitzabee</bold>, PhD, PE, is a professor of Aerospace Studies at Cornell University. His research interests include infrastructure systems, asset management, geographical information systems, leadership and management.</p>
<p><bold>Edward D. White</bold> is an associate professor of Statistics at the Air Force Institute of Technology. His research interests include Design of Experiments, Biostatistics, Growth Curves, Linear and Nonlinear regression, Categorical Data Analysis, Log-Linear Models, Statistical Simulation, and Response Surface Modeling.</p>
<p><bold>Austin W. Dowling</bold>, MS, is a cost analyst for the B-2 program with the Aeronautical Systems Center. His educational background and his research interests focus on simulation and statistical modeling.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abboud</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Cost-and longevity-based scheduling of paint and thermoplastic striping</source> (Transportation Research Record 1794). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>TRB, National Research Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Society of Testing and Materials</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>Standard test method for measurement of retroreflective pavement marking materials with CEN-prescribed geometry using a portable retroreflectometer</source> (E 1710-05: Annual book of ASTM standards). <publisher-loc>West Conshohoken, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andrady</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Pavement marking materials: Assessing environmentally-friendly performance</source> (NCHRP Report 392). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transportation Research Board</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bahar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masiliah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Pavement marking materials and markers: Testing the relationship between retroreflectivity and safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transportation Research Board</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Cambridge Systematics, Inc</collab>. (<year>2002</year>). <source>Phase I Report Task 1 of 3: Synthesis of asset management practice</source> (NCHRP Project 20-24[11]). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transportation Research Board</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sitzabee</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rasdorf</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hummer</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Statistical validation of the effect of lateral line location on pavement marking retroreflectivity degradation</article-title>. <source>Public Works Management and Policy</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Federal Highway Administration</collab>. (<year>2010</year>, <month>April</month> <day>22</day>). <source>Proposed Revision 1 of the 2009 MUTCD—Maintaining minimum retroreflectivity of longitudinal pavement markings</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mutcd.fhwa.dot.gov">http://mutcd.fhwa.dot.gov</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Federal Highway Administration</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Manual of Uniform Traffic Control Devices</source>, <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lupes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schertz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Satterfield</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Revised assessment of economic impacts of implementing minimum levels of pavement marking retroreflectivity</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Federal Highway Administration, Office of Safety</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hummer</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rasdorf</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Linear mixed effects models for paint pavement marking retroreflectivity data</article-title>. <source>Journal of Transportation Engineering</source>, <volume>137</volume>, <fpage>705</fpage>-<lpage>716</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karwa</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donnell</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Predicting pavement marking retroreflectivity using artificial neural networks: Exploratory analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Transportation Engineering</source>, <volume>137</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kopf</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Reflectivity of pavement markings: Analysis of retroreflectivity degradation curves</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Washington State Transportation Center (TRAC)</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.-T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maleck</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Pavement marking material evaluation study in Michigan</article-title>. <source>Institute of Transportation Engineers ITE Journal</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>44</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Migletz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>NCHRP Synthesis 306 long-term pavement marking practices</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transportation Research Board</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Migletz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Service life of durable pavement markings</source> (Transportation Research Board 80th Annual Meeting Preprint CD-ROM). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transportation Research Board, National Research Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>North Carolina Department of Transportation</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>2006 NCDOT Pavement Marking Rodeo</source> (North Carolina Department of Transportation). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Federal Highway Administration</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>, <month>January</month>). <source>A comparative analysis of pavement marking materials</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the 2001 Transportation Research Board Annual Meeting</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Washington, DC</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rasdorf</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hummer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sitzabee</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>IT Issues for the management of high-quantity low-cost assets</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computing and Civil Engineering</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sarasua</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Evaluation of interstate pavement marking retroreflectivity</source> (Report No. FHWA-SC-03-01). <publisher-name>Report to South Carolina Department of Transportation</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>South Carolina</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sasidharan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vishesh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donnell</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Use of pavement marking degradation models to develop a pavement marking management plan</article-title>. <source>Public Works Management and Policy</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sitzabee</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hummer</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rasdorf</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Pavement marking degradation modeling and analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Infrastructure Systems</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>U.S. Congress</collab>. (<year>1993</year>). <source>United States Department of Transportation and Related Agency Appropriation Act</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1087724X12462831">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Methodologies to predict service lives of pavement marking materials</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Transportation Research Forum</source>, <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>