<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjrn</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Research in Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1744-9871</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1744-988X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1744987112458880</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1744987112458880</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Guest editorial: Science, technology, innovation and research: the ultimate conundrum?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1744987112458880"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1744987112458880">Organisational and Workforce Development Director, National Institute for Health Research, Clinical Research Network, Leeds, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1744987112458880">Susan Hamer, Organisational and Workforce Development Director, National Institute for Health Research, Clinical Research Network, Fairbairn House, 71-75 Clarendon Road, Leeds LS2 9PH, UK Email: <email>susan.hamer@nihr.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>516</fpage>
<lpage>518</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I was recently working with a group of researchers who are in the field of nursing informatics; it was an international group who have only recently been brought together. The researchers came from a broad range of discipline backgrounds and not all of us were nurses. There were computer scientists, psychologists and informaticians; as a consequence the conversation was broad and interweaved. However, what did emerge was a real tension in the group between the need to provide policy makers and purchasers of health services with the evidence they need now to support real-time decisions and the time it takes for researchers to develop, design, set up and undertake a robust programme of research. This was graphically displayed when we started to talk about the evidence in the field of telehealth. These technologies are currently very fashionable. There are a lot of companies actively seeking to sell their goods into an expanding market place. Everyone would appear to see some aspect of telehealth as a solution to some aspect of health need, but look again at the evidence base for this and we know so little. This, however, has not stopped the UK committing itself to putting 3 million people into interventions in the next few years.</p>
<p>As a recent public launch of the campaign notes: ‘“3millionlives” is about transforming service delivery for people with long-term conditions, and/or social care needs, by utilising telehealth and telecare within health and social care services, enabling millions of people to receive the significant benefits evidenced in the UK’s Whole System Demonstrator trials; the largest randomised control trial of telecare and telehealth in the world’ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.3millionlives.co.uk">http://www.3millionlives.co.uk</ext-link>).</p>
<p>All this sounds very reassuring but really from a low base it is not difficult to be the largest randomised telecare control trial. We have not really asked how these technologies should be deployed. Which aspects of these technologies add value to patient outcomes and not just cost reduction? Does seeing someone using a visual link as well as speaking to them really make a big enough difference to justify the cost? Do you leave a telehealth system in for 2 weeks, 2 months, a year or a life time? We just do not know, yet their impact on aspects of clinical practice is huge and nurses are absolutely in that care setting. We seem to be in a world where somehow technology innovation is automatically a good thing with few questions asked, and yet if we viewed the same activities as a clinical intervention there would be a different view. This is symptomatic of a wider challenge for the research community.</p>
<p>The growth and interest in life sciences and the development of clinical research is a key platform for many countries and a strong theme throughout Europe. Politicians are placing a strong emphasis on research and development and linking this directly to innovation and productivity. Typical of many governments a recent strategy for UK life sciences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1744987112458880">BIS, 2011</xref>) articulates an ambitious vision: ‘The UK will become the global hub for life sciences in the future providing an unrivalled ecosystem that brings together business, researchers, clinicians and patients to translate discovery into clinical use for medical innovation within the NHS’.</p>
<p>All looks fine until you examine the evidence. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1744987112458880">Tilford and Whyte (2011)</xref> note, there is now significant research which shows that only a small part of productivity growth in Europe is related to R&amp;D spend in a country. Crucially it is the diffusion of technology that results in organisational change which is a driver to productivity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1744987112458880">Tilford and Whyte (2011)</xref> also make the point that most important future innovations will be made by companies that are not yet in existence. So paradoxically a government supporting existing established industries stifles the very growth they need. This then is the challenge as innovation is by its very processes unpredictable, disruptive and creates insecurities.</p>
<p>Additionally as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1744987112458880">Christensen (2009)</xref> notes: ‘When a disruptive technology enabler emerges, the leaders in the industry disparage and discourage it because, with its orientation towards simplicity and accessibility, the disruption just isn’t capable of solving the complicated problems that define the world in which the leading experts work. Always the technological enablers of disruption are successfully deployed against the industries simplest problems first’ (p. xlvii).</p>
<p>Those actors in the system who have the most to lose in terms of power and status can repeatedly resist proposed changes; the consequence is a low innovation culture.</p>
<p>It is important to see that as a research community we are no different in our own reaction to innovation and change, and I believe that we too are slow to see innovation in methodologies, as those with an established view of how things ought to be are able to keep and reinforce the existing system. I am no exception; I have sat on funding committees, developed specifications, edited journals and essentially controlled the rewards. So how do we stay fresh and open to other views?</p>
<p>As I noted earlier in my reference to telehealth research, 5 years to carry out research on technologies that change in 1 year is not going to work. There are also signs of frustrations from patients themselves with how research is being done. We are seeing the emergence of trends such as crowd sourced health research studies whereby participants have begun to organise their own research studies through their health social networks and health collaboration communities for the purpose of self-experimentation and product development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1744987112458880">Swan, 2012</xref>). As co participants on the research journey patients expect access to their own data and to use it for their own purposes which may be beyond that envisaged by the researcher. This is an example of innovation but it can feel destructive to our way of doing things.</p>
<p>As a community we do need to develop our own capacity for the strategic leadership of innovation. It will be about diversity and collaboration in our approaches to problem-solving. Perhaps being braver in our challenge to rules and regulations, can we simplify our processes, work on higher levels of trust, be more flexible and responsive and let technology support the straightforward and the ordinary. Can we think about adoption and diffusion from day 1 and make sure our processes are transparent and visible, so we gift our understanding along the way not just at the end? Do we allocate time and resources for innovative ‘out the box’ thinking in our daily work?</p>
<p>As researchers we are often tasked with taking the long-term view. By definition we are working in the unknown where answers do not exist. That does not, however, exempt us from the same commitment to using science, technology and innovation to support the growth of our own disciplines and our own skills in a more purposeful way.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1744987112458880"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>BIS Department for Business Innovation and Skills (2011) Strategy for UK Life Sciences: Office for Like Sciences UK</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1744987112458880"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Innovator’s Prescription</source> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1744987112458880"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Crowd sourced health research studies: an important emerging complement to clinical trials in the public health research ecosystem</article-title>. <source>Journal of Medical Internet Research</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>e46</fpage>–<lpage>e46</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1744987112458880"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tilford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Innovation. How Europe Can Take Off</source> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre for European Reform (CER)</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>