<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjag</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Applied Gerontology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0733-4648</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4523</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0733464813481562</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0733464813481562</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On the Success of the Successful Aging Paradigm</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Cosco</surname><given-names>Theodore D.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0733464813481562">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Stephan</surname><given-names>Blossom C.M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0733464813481562">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Brayne</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0733464813481562">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0733464813481562"><label>1</label>University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0733464813481562"><label>2</label>Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0733464813481562">Theodore D. Cosco, Cambridge Institute of Public Health, Department of Public Health &amp; Primary Care, University of Cambridge, Forvie Site, Robinson Way, Cambridge, CB2 0SR. Email: <email>tdc33@medschl.cam.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>275</fpage>
<lpage>276</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Southern Gerontological Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In “Aging Populations’ Everyday Life Perspectives on Healthy Aging: New Insights for Policy and Strategies at the Local Level,” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0733464813481562">Naaldenberg, Vaandrager, and Leeuwis (2012)</xref> examine lay perspectives of the healthy aging concept, highlighting the many and varied ways in which laypersons experience aging well. However, laypersons are not the only group subject to the many and varied conceptualizations of aging well; researchers have been wrestling with naming conventions and operationalization issues for decades.</p>
<p>The ease of labelling the presence of disease stands in stark contrast to the ambiguity of labelling positive states of aging. Within the medical field, specific diagnostic criteria are routinely applied within established protocols leading to determination of the presence or absence of disease. There are obviously exceptions to the rule, but the overarching ability with which a state of disease or illness is described usually has a well-established pedigree. Conversely, when dealing with positive states of aging, current naming conventions used by researchers are ambiguous at best and contradictory at worst. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0733464813481562">Naaldenberg et al. (2012)</xref> acknowledge that healthy aging, their term of choice, is “used alongside related concepts such as active aging, positive aging, and successful aging” (p. 712). Lack of consensus definitions, generalizability, and practical applications for these terms inhibits research.</p>
<p>Definitions of aging well can vary dramatically, from quantitative biomedical models to subjective single-item measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0733464813481562">Bowling &amp; Dieppe, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0733464813481562">Depp &amp; Jeste, 2006</xref>). These terms have been used synonymously with, as complimentary processes to, and as constituent components of each other. The subjectivity in defining positive states of aging is cause for concern; this lack of consensus is both confusing and inhibitive, severely impeding cross-study comparison. For researchers, producing results relevant only within the context of the original study is an inefficient use of resources and a detriment to collaborative, cross-cultural, and intergenerational studies.</p>
<p>The connotations of each aging term (e.g. successful aging, healthy aging, robust aging, productive aging, active aging, positive aging, and optimal aging), are often broadened and/or retrofitted for the purposes at hand. Definitions researchers have used to describe positive states of aging have, as a result, digressed from the original meanings of these terms. Taking a step away from these niche definitions and examining the original denotations of these terms provides a more straightforward approach to their practical application.</p>
<p>The development of standardized definitions of positive states of aging will be integral to conducting cross-study comparisons of aging well. Although the development of consensus definitions of these terms may not be imminent, taking a more parsimonious approach to their utilization by taking a step back to the original denotations of these terms may be a collective step in the right direction.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0733464813481562">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowling</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dieppe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>What is successful ageing and who should define it?</article-title> <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>331</volume>(<issue>7531</issue>), <fpage>1548</fpage>-<lpage>1551</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0733464813481562">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Depp</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeste</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Definitions and predictors of successful aging: a comprehensive review of larger quantitative studies</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.JGP.0000192501.03069.bc</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0733464813481562">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Naaldenberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaandrager</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leeuwis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Aging populations’ everyday life perspectives on healthy aging: New insights for policy and strategies at the local level</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Gerontology</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>-<lpage>733</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>