<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptso</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Teach Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Teaching Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0092-055X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-862X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092055X11420393</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0092055X11420393</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Film Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Tapped</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0092055X11420393">Loyola University Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>88</fpage>
<lpage>90</lpage>
<product>
<source>Tapped</source>. <person-group person-group-type="director">
<name><surname>Soechtig</surname><given-names>Stephanie</given-names></name>
</person-group>, director. <publisher-loc>Oley, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bullfrog Films</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>. <comment>75 minutes</comment>. <price>$295.00</price>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>Tapped</italic> examines the bottled water industry in the United States, touching on many sociological concepts related to the environment, consumption, science, and health. Covering controversies such as the use of public water sources by bottling companies, pollution from plastic bottles, and the health dangers of plastics, <italic>Tapped</italic> openly challenges the commodification of water and the industry’s claims of safety and purity. Through interviews with citizens, journalists, activists, scientists, and two industry public relations representatives, the film provides a commodity chain analysis that exposes the social and environmental relations of production. Additionally, viewers hear the story of how bottled water became ubiquitous. The high production quality of the film is evident in the editing, splicing interview footage with striking images of tanker trucks barreling through small New England towns, automated bottling lines, polluted water bodies, television commercials and print advertisements, and scrolling microfiche-like newspaper headlines.</p>
<p><italic>Tapped</italic> begins with the story of Nestlé’s water mining operation in the small town of Fryeburg, Maine. Without having to notify residents or ask public officials, Nestlé, the largest food processing company in the world, began mapping the water table and clandestinely buying parcels of land to dig wells and pump water. By directly tapping into the same source from which the town of Fryeburg gets its water, Nestlé avoids paying for the water yet makes a profit of nearly $6 per gallon. The film follows the town’s struggle to set limits on Nestlé’s pumping and recuperate lost revenue through bottled water taxes, all of which the company resists with its extensive legal resources. Even during times of water shortage for the city, Nestlé continues pumping water unimpeded. Similar stories of Coca-Cola in Marietta, Georgia, and PepsiCo in Durham, North Carolina, document cities’ inability to effectively regulate the bottling companies during severe drought. The first part of the film comes to a close with positive images of protestors and activist organizing and a brief look at communities’ victories temporarily halting bottling companies and the ensuing legal battles.</p>
<p>The focus then turns to the history of bottled water consumption, connecting it to the development of cheap clear plastic in 1989, which made the transport of individual units of water convenient. The industry exploded when Coke and Pepsi decided to enter the market as soda sales declined. This led to hundreds of millions of dollars used to advertise the health and beauty effects of water, contributing to an $11.5 billion industry in 2007. Here, the film does well in pointing out the hypocrisy of the industry claiming that their product is safe and pure (implying that tap water is not), while bottled water is almost completely unregulated and untested, even though its plastic packaging can leach toxins, endocrine disruptors, and carcinogens.</p>
<p>The rest of <italic>Tapped</italic> examines the environmental and health impacts of plastic bottle production and disposal. The documentary focuses on environmental justice struggles in a neighborhood suffering negative health effects from pollution emitted from an oil refinery that produces the primary ingredient in plastic beverage containers, polyethylene terephthalate (PET or PETE). An interview with a former scientist with the Environmental Protection Agency highlights the reactive nature of the agency, because it cannot enter into a community and test air quality until residents formally complain and demand testing. The theme of government agencies is then carried over to the reliance of consumers on the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to protect them and regulate industry. However, the FDA only regulates interstate commerce, and 60 percent to 70 percent of bottled water is produced and purchased in the same state. Instead, the FDA requires that producers conduct their own tests but does not mandate that they report their results. To highlight the danger of the loose regulatory process, the film looks at bisphenol A (BPA), a hormone-disrupting chemical contained in PET plastics that is linked to many diseases, even at extremely low levels. By this time in the documentary, when a scientist states that BPA “is going to dismantle the entire regulatory process,” one has to wonder what regulatory process he is speaking of.</p>
<p>From there, the documentary turns to the failures of recycling and the amount of plastic bottles that end up in landfills, incinerated, or washed out to sea. Images of the Pacific garbage patch and its negative consequences for marine life drive home the point that there is no nature “untouched” by humans. Up until this point, the filmmaker has stressed the importance of not buying bottled water; however, in concluding the documentary, interviewees encourage active political participation to create change. As the credits roll, viewers are urged to demand from legislators that the public water infrastructure be repaired and insist that bottled water industries find an alternative to plastic, among other policies.</p>
<p><italic>Tapped</italic> is well researched and well argued and presents information in an easy-to-consume manner. More important, the film avoids the pitfalls of helplessness or partisanship that students may come away with from other documentaries detailing environmental crises. Instead, the film provides practical ways for students to confront these issues. Additionally, protestors and activists are portrayed as effective and rational, unlike in the mainstream media. Overall, the film does an excellent job of connecting environmental issues and politics.</p>
<p>The run time of 1 hour and 15 minutes lends itself well to being viewed during a longer class period, or the film can be broken up into sections (commodification, consumption, and consequences) and watched over multiple class meetings. Many assignments and in-class activities would resonate with the film, including tragedy-of-the-commons games and commodity chain analysis explorations. Screenings of the film have inspired rallies, boycotts, and proposed bans of bottled water in cities and schools throughout the United States. Looking at these examples may inspire ideas for projects outside of class that emphasize environmental citizenship and community involvement.</p>
<p><italic>Tapped</italic> will be most beneficial in an undergraduate environmental sociology course. The film details many important sociological concepts without using a sociological vocabulary. Conveniently, this leaves plenty of room for discussion. Potential discussion topics include lifecycle and commodity chain analysis, environmental justice, and consumption. With more advanced undergraduate students, instructors can discuss neoliberalism and the social organization of knowledge. The privatization of a public good and the externalization of the costs of production in terms of pollution all exemplify central tenets of neoliberalism. With regard to knowledge, the BPA controversy provides an opportunity to introduce the precautionary principle and undone science. Indeed, the film has many examples of epistemological modernization in terms of citizen science and environmentalists employing scientists to do research. Finally, the movie can provide a good backdrop for examining the debate between mainstream environmental sociology and ecological modernization theory over the effectiveness of reform and regulation.</p>
<p><italic>Tapped</italic> is sure to resonate with many of today’s undergraduate students, who partook in the phenomenon of bottled water as a status symbol while they were in high school.</p>
</body>
</article>