<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjpp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Pharmacy Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0897-1900</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1531-1937</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0897190012451930</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0897190012451930</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Professional Reading Habits of Pharmacists Attending 2 Educational Seminars in New York City</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Nathan</surname>
<given-names>Joseph P.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MS, PharmD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0897190012451930"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0897190012451930">1</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grossman</surname>
<given-names>Sara</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PharmD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0897190012451930">1</xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0897190012451930">
<label>1</label>International Drug Information Center, Arnold &amp; Marie Schwartz College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences, Long Island University, Brooklyn, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0897190012451930">Joseph P. Nathan, International Drug Information Center, Arnold &amp; Marie Schwartz College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences, Long Island University, 75 DeKalb Avenue, Room HS509, Brooklyn, NY 11201, USA Email: <email>Joseph.nathan@liu.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>600</fpage>
<lpage>605</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec>
<title>Purpose:</title>
<p>Data regarding the professional reading habits of pharmacists in the United States are lacking. The purpose of this pilot study was to investigate whether pharmacists read professional publications and assess other aspects of their professional reading habits.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>In December 2010, surveys were distributed to pharmacists participating in 2 educational seminars in New York City. The main outcome measures were percentages of pharmacists who read regularly (at least monthly), specific publications read, and the perceived value and impact of reading.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results:</title>
<p>A total of 184 pharmacists were surveyed. Of the 122 (66%) respondents, 112 (92%) reported reading professional publications regularly. Of these, 97 (87%) indicated the titles read, with the 4 publications reported most frequently being Drug Topics (n = 73; 75%), Pharmacy Times (n = 67; 69%), US Pharmacist (n = 60; 62%), and Pharmacist’s Letter (n = 48; 49%). All 122 respondents indicated that reading positively impacted their practice, and 121 (99%) reported that reading was important.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>The value of reading professional publications was recognized by surveyed pharmacists; this likely contributed to the high reading rate reported in this study.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>pharmacist</kwd>
<kwd>reading habits</kwd>
<kwd>professional publications</kwd>
<kwd>journals</kwd>
<kwd>life-long learning</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0897190012451930">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Because of the dynamic nature of the health care field, the concept of life-long learning is of utmost importance for health care professionals. To ensure that professionals maintain competency in their discipline, jurisdictions commonly require that members of the profession participate in formal continuing education (CE) activities. In recent years, as with other professions, there has been an increased interest in nurturing life-long learning among pharmacists using a continuing professional development (CPD) model. This model has been implemented in a number of countries and is being explored in some states in the US.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0897190012451930">1</xref></sup> CPD has been defined as “a self-directed, ongoing, systematic and outcomes-focused approach to learning and professional development”.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0897190012451930">1</xref></sup> This approach recognizes that life-long learning can be achieved via a variety of professional activities and places the impetus on the individual to understand, reflect on, and document the contribution of various activities that he/she participated in to his/her continuous professional growth. Examples of CPD activities include participating in CE programs, answering drug information questions, participating in journal club, and ward rounding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0897190012451930">2</xref></sup> A learning activity integral to most, if not all, professions is reading professional literature. Reading on a regular basis is important, not only because it keeps the reader up-to-date with changes affecting the profession but also because it exposes the reader to opinions, philosophies, arguments, theories, book reviews, advice, and even employment opportunities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0897190012451930">3</xref></sup> Despite the importance of this learning activity, a search of MEDLINE (1947-December 2010), International Pharmaceutical Abstracts (1970-December 2010), and Google Scholar (accessed December 2010), using various combinations of the terms “pharmacist*”, “read,” “reading”, “habits”, “subscribe”, “pharmacy”, “journal”, “magazine”, “publication”, “up to date”, and “keeping current” did not identify relevant articles describing the professional reading habits of pharmacists in the US.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0897190012451930">
<title>Objectives</title>
<p>The purpose of this pilot study was to investigate whether pharmacists routinely read professional publications and to assess other aspects of their professional reading habits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0897190012451930" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>In December 2010, cover letters and surveys were distributed to pharmacists participating in 2 live educational seminars which took place in Queens and Brooklyn, New York and were conducted by the Arnold &amp; Marie Schwartz College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences, Long Island University. One seminar topic was an update on pharmacy law and the other was a pharmacist immunization certificate program; both programs provided CE credit to attendees. The survey instrument was developed by the investigators and tested on a pharmacist who provided feedback. The instrument included questions concerning the participants’ demographics (ie, practice setting, years in practice, professional title [RPh vs PharmD], and gender), and inquired as to whether pharmacy or medical publications were read on a regular basis. For the purpose of this survey, a “publication” was defined as a journal, magazine, and/or a newsletter, while a “regular basis” was defined as at least monthly. Respondents who indicated that they did not read professional publications regularly were asked to provide the reason/reasons for same. For those who reported reading regularly, the instrument requested that the respondent indicate the title/titles of the publication/publications read and inquired as to how the publication/publications was/were available (personal subscription, at/through practice site, or through organization membership), and how the publication/publications was/were accessed (in print or online). Furthermore, for these respondents, the survey also included a question about whether they thought that reading professional publications positively impacted their practice. All participants were asked whether they believed that it was important for pharmacists to read professional publications. In addition, they were asked to indicate other methods utilized to keep up with information on therapeutics.</p>
<p>Data were collected and analyzed using an Excel spreadsheet (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington). Descriptive statistics were used to report the frequencies of the responses. The study was granted an exempt status by the institutional review board of Long Island University.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0897190012451930">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section5-0897190012451930">
<title>Demographics</title>
<p>A total of 184 pharmacists participated in the 2 educational seminars, all of whom received a cover letter and survey. Of these, 122 (66%) surveys were returned. The respondents’ primary practice sites were independently owned community pharmacy (n = 55; 45%), chain pharmacy (n = 31; 25%), hospital (n = 19; 16%), academia (n = 4; 3%), and others (n = 15; 12%), such as long-term care, compounding, and industry. Notably, despite being asked to indicate their primary practice setting (ie, where they practice more than 50% of the time), 2 respondents provided 2 practice settings as their primary practice settings. Sixty-seven (55%) respondents reported being licensed for more than 20 years, 10 (8%) were licensed for 16 to 20 years, 14 (11%) were licensed for 11 to 15 years, 18 (15%) were licensed for 6 to 10 years, and 13 (11%) were licensed for 5 years or less. Ninety-five (78%) respondents used RPh as their professional title, while 27 (22%) used the title PharmD. Seventy (58%) of the 121 respondents to the question about gender were male.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0897190012451930">
<title>Reading Habits</title>
<p>When asked whether they read pharmacy or medical publications regularly, 112 (92%) of the respondents reported that they did. Among the 10 (8%) who reported that they did not read, reasons for not reading included obtaining sufficient information from other sources (n = 5; 50%), time constraints (n = 4; 40%), cost, and publications being difficult to understand (n = 2; 20% for each). Of those who reported that they read professional publications, 97 (87%) indicated the titles read. The 4 titles reported most frequently included Drug Topics (n = 73; 75%), Pharmacy Times (n = 67; 69%), US Pharmacist (n = 60; 62%), and Pharmacist’s Letter (n = 48; 49%). A list of the titles read and their reporting frequencies is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0897190012451930">Table 1</xref>. Eighty-two (73%) of the 112 respondents who reported reading publications regularly indicated how the publications were available to them. The 3 most commonly reported responses were at/through practice site (n = 30; 37%), both at/through practice site and personal subscription (n = 23; 28%), and personal subscription (n = 20; 24%). Sixty-nine (62%) respondents indicated the manner by which they accessed the publications. Of these, 50 (72%) reported reading publications in print, 3 (4%) reported reading them online, and 16 (23%) reported reading publications both in print and online.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0897190012451930" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Professional Publications Read by Pharmacists on a Regular Basis (n = 97)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0897190012451930" xlink:href="10.1177_0897190012451930-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Title</th>
<th>No. (%) reporting</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Drug Topics</td>
<td>73 (75)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pharmacy Times</td>
<td>67 (69)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>US Pharmacist</td>
<td>60 (62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pharmacist’s Letter</td>
<td>48 (49)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A professional organization’s newsletter</td>
<td>12 (12)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>American Journal of Health-System Pharmacists</td>
<td>10 (10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hospital Pharmacy</td>
<td>10 (10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Journal of the American Pharmacists Association</td>
<td>9 (9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Consultant Pharmacist</td>
<td>8 (8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A hospital newsletter</td>
<td>7 (7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Journal of Pharmacy Practice</td>
<td>6 (6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New England Journal of Medicine</td>
<td>6 (6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Annals of Pharmacotherapy</td>
<td>5 (5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Journal of the American Medical Association</td>
<td>4 (4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Medical Letter</td>
<td>4 (4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pharmacotherapy</td>
<td>3 (3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rx Consultant</td>
<td>2 (2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes Care</td>
<td>1 (1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>International Journal of Pharmaceutical Compounding</td>
<td>1 (1)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0897190012451930">
<title>Perceived Value of Reading and Other Methods of Keeping Up</title>
<p>Of the 122 respondents to the survey, 121 (99%) reported that they believed that it was important for pharmacists to read professional publications. This number includes 9 of the 10 respondents who reported not reading professional publications. The 112 respondents who reported reading professional publications were asked whether they thought that it positively impacted their practice. One hundred and eleven participants (99%) responded to this question, and all (100%) reported that they believed that reading positively impacted their practice. Of the 122 survey participants, 118 (97%) responded to the question concerning other methods of keeping up-to-date, aside from reading professional publications and completing CE requirements. The most frequently reported activity was attending professional in-service programs (n = 65; 55%). Other recurring methods of keeping up included attending professional meetings (n = 26; 22%) and subscribing to list serves (n = 20; 17%). Twenty-eight (24%) respondents did not utilize other methods of keeping up with knowledge about drug therapy.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0897190012451930">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Keeping up with published professional literature is of great importance for practicing pharmacists. Reading such publications exposes readers to a wide range of topics that may affect their practice and contribute to their professional growth. The availability of a variety of publications catering to different aspects of the profession allows pharmacists to select and read publications that suit their needs. Beyond their professional obligations, pharmacists maintain a legal obligation to stay abreast of current knowledge by completing state CE requirements. The Accreditation Council on Pharmaceutical Education (ACPE) states that the intended purpose of CE is to “support the continuing development of pharmacists and/or pharmacy technicians to maintain and enhance their competence”.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0897190012451930">4</xref></sup> Although pharmacy publications often contain articles that are accredited by ACPE to provide the reader with CE credits upon completion of a posttest, the overall practice of reading professional publications is generally not a recognized form of fulfilling state CE requirements. The purpose of this study was to assess whether pharmacists recognize their professional obligations to being a life-long learner and implement this recognition by reading professional publications.</p>
<p>In this study, over 90% of respondents reported reading professional publications at least on a monthly basis. All but 1 respondent indicated that they felt that reading was important. Moreover, all respondents who read professional publications reported that they felt that reading positively impacted their practice. Although representing a small number of respondents, the most commonly reported reason for not reading professional publications was that sufficient information was obtained from other sources. Nevertheless, as suggested previously, professional publications offer a multitude of benefits.</p>
<p>Although time constraints did not generally prevent pharmacists from reading professional publications, it may play a role in the overall reading habits of pharmacists. Pharmacists were asked to report whether they read professional publications on a regular basis, defined as at least monthly, however, they were not asked for the number of hours spent reading. In an article describing a national survey of medical internists,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0897190012451930">5</xref></sup> Saint et al reported that the internists spent an average of 4.4 hours per week reading medical journals. The authors of the aforementioned report also noted that in prior studies, physicians reportedly devoted approximately 3 to 6 hours weekly reading medical publications. Although allotting time to reading may be difficult, a similar time commitment by pharmacists may be necessary for staying up-to-date.</p>
<p>One may hypothesize that the cost of subscriptions may deter pharmacists from routinely reading professional publications. It should be noted, however, that several publications, such as Drug Topics, Pharmacy Times, US Pharmacist, and Hospital Pharmacy, are available free to qualified subscribers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0897190012451930">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0897190012451930"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0897190012451930"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0897190012451930">9</xref></sup> while others are provided to members of professional organizations or employees of a company/institution. Accordingly, in this study, the cost of subscriptions did not appear to deter pharmacists from reading professional publications but may have contributed to the findings regarding the most commonly read publications. The 3 most commonly read publications were Drug Topics, Pharmacy Times, and US Pharmacist; all publications that are available free of charge to qualifying pharmacists. The fourth most commonly read publication, Pharmacist’s Letter, requires a paid subscription of $115 annually.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0897190012451930">10</xref></sup> Furthermore, these 4 publications tend to provide short, easy-to-read reviews on topics relevant to any practicing pharmacist. Few respondents reported reading other journals, including journals that we consider to be premier journals. One possible explanation is that certain types of articles published in these journals, for example, research reports, are generally not as practical for community pharmacists, which comprised 70% of our sample.</p>
<p>This study found that nearly three-fourths of respondents read publications in print only. Notwithstanding that personal preference may play a role in the decision to read a print or electronic publication, this finding may be a reflection of the demographics of the survey respondents, as 63% of the respondents reported being licensed for more than 15 years. Nonetheless, it illustrates the need for journal publishers to continue offering publications in print to satisfy different reading preferences. We do suspect that younger pharmacists are more likely to utilize computer technology in general, and thus also more likely to read publications online.</p>
<sec id="section9-0897190012451930">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>There are several limitations to this study. First, it included a small, convenience sample of pharmacists attending live seminars in 2 boroughs of New York City (NYC). Likewise, as is the case with survey research, it is possible that the reading habits of the nonresponders differed from that reported by the participating pharmacists. Additionally, the sample was skewed toward pharmacists who have been licensed for a relatively long time and toward those practicing in a community pharmacy setting. Thus, we cannot conclude that a survey of “younger” pharmacists and of those practicing in other settings would yield similar results. Notably, however, according to the US Government’s Bureau of Labor Statistics, in 2008, approximately 65% of US pharmacists worked in a community setting. This figure is similar to that reported in this study, in which 70% of respondents practiced in a community setting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0897190012451930">11</xref></sup> Another limitation to this study is that it did not investigate the amount of time that pharmacists spent reading professional publications. Furthermore, the survey’s definition of “reading” was broad and did not differentiate between scanning and reading or the types of articles read. Obtaining that information can be useful in gauging the extent to which pharmacists are involved in this activity. Finally, we were unable to identify a validated survey instrument and thus, we developed an instrument that was pretested to a limited extent. Nonetheless, we believe that this pilot study offers a glimpse into the reading habits of pharmacists and provides a platform for future research.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0897190012451930">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this survey of pharmacists conducted in 2 boroughs of NYC, 92% reported reading professional publications at least on a monthly basis. All respondents who read professional publications indicated that they felt that reading positively impacted their practice and almost all reported that they believed that it was important. Thus, it appears that the value of reading professional publications was recognized by the surveyed pharmacists; this likely contributed to the high reading rate reported in this study. Although conducted in a limited sample, this study provides a framework for further research involving a large, random sample of pharmacists to evaluate other aspects of their professional reading habits, including the extent to which pharmacists read professional publications and whether demographics influences reading habits. Further research in this area should also examine the factors influencing the choice of publications and specific articles that pharmacists opt to read.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0897190012451930">
<title>Appendix A</title>
<p>December 2010</p>
<p>Dear Colleague:</p>
<p>As it is for many professions, mandatory participation in continuing education activities (CE) is one method of ensuring that pharmacists keep abreast of changes within the profession. While literature about the utilization of CE programs as a means of keeping up with ongoing changes is available, little is published about the professional reading habits of pharmacists. As such, our intent is to conduct a survey to assess the reading habits of pharmacists and to ultimately publish the information collected.</p>
<p>We would greatly appreciate it if you could take a few minutes to anonymously answer the survey questions. Please note that completing the survey is voluntary. If you choose to complete the survey, kindly tear off and keep this cover sheet and return the survey to us at the end of the program. The information provided will be handled in a confidential manner and if published, it will be presented in the aggregate.</p>
<p>If you have any questions, you may contact me by telephone at: –––––––– or via e-mail at: joseph.nathan@liu.edu. Thank you for your assistance.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Joseph P. Nathan, M.S., Pharm.D.</p>
<p>Associate Professor of Pharmacy Practice</p>
<p>Arnold &amp; Marie Schwartz College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences</p>
<p>Long Island University</p>
<sec id="section11-0897190012451930">
<title>Survey Questions</title>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Please indicate the type of practice setting in which you practice most (&gt;50%) of the time:<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Chain pharmacy</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Independently-owned community pharmacy</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Hospital</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Academia</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Other:___________________________</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>How many years have you been licensed as a pharmacist in the US?<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ <underline>&lt;</underline> 5 years</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ 6-10 years</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ 11-15 years</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ 16-20 years</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ &gt; 20 years</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>What is your professional title? (Please select one option only.)<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ R.Ph.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Pharm.D.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Please indicate your gender:<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Male</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Female</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Do you read a pharmacy or medical publication on a regular (at least monthly) basis for the purpose of keeping up with drug therapy? Examples of pharmacy or medical publications include professional journals, magazines, or newsletters.<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Yes</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ No</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<bold>
<italic>If you answered</italic>
<italic>“No</italic>
<italic>” to question #5, please skip to question #10.</italic>
</bold>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>In the table presented below, please select all of the publications that you read on a regular basis. For each of the publications selected, please include the manner in which the publication is available to you. Additionally, please note whether you read the print or online version of the publication. If a particular publication is not listed, please add the complete title in the space provided in the section entitled “Other”.
<table-wrap id="table2-0897190012451930" position="float">
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0897190012451930" xlink:href="10.1177_0897190012451930-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">Publication</th>
<th rowspan="2">Please √ if read on a regular basis</th>
<th colspan="3">How available?</th>
<th colspan="2">How accessed?</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Personal subscription</th>
<th>Available at/through practice site</th>
<th>Available as part of membership of an organization</th>
<th>In print</th>
<th>Online</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>American Journal of Health-System Pharmacists</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Annals of Pharmacotherapy</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Consultant Pharmacist</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drug Topics</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hospital Pharmacy</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Journal of Pharmacy Practice</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Journal of the American Medical Association</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Journal of the American Pharmacists Association</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pharmacist’s Letter</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pharmacotherapy</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pharmacy Times</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Medical Letter</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The New England Journal of Medicine</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>US Pharmacist</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A newsletter published by your hospital</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A professional organization’s newsletter</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<bold>Other: Please list below</bold>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Do you think that reading professional publications positively impacts your practice?<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Yes</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ No</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Overall, do you think it is important for pharmacists to read professional publications?<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Yes</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ No</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>In addition to reading professional publications and completing CE requirements, what other method(s) of keeping up with drug therapy do you utilize?<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Attending professional in-service programs</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Attending professional meetings (e.g., ASHP Midyear Clinical Meeting)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Subscribing to a list-serve</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Other:________________________</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ None (I do not utilize other methods of keeping up with drug therapy.)</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<bold>
<italic>Thank you for completing the survey. Please stop here and return the survey to us.</italic>
</bold> <bold>
<italic>The remaining questions are reserved for those that answered</italic>
<italic>“</italic>
<italic>No</italic>
<italic>”</italic>
</bold> <bold>
<italic>to question #5.</italic>
</bold>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>What is/are the reason(s) that you do not read pharmacy or medical publications? (Please select all that apply.)<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ I do not see a value in reading these publications.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ I obtain sufficient information from other sources.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Publications are typically difficult to understand.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Subscriptions are too expensive.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Time constraints prevent me from reading these publications.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Other:___________________________</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Overall, do you think it is important for pharmacists to read professional publications?<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Yes</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ No</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>In addition to completing CE requirements, what other method(s) of keeping up with drug therapy do you utilize?<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>___ Attending professional in-service programs</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Attending professional meetings (e.g., ASHP Midyear Clinical Meeting)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Subscribing to a list-serve</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ Other:___________________________</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>___ None (I do not utilize other methods of keeping up with drug therapy.)</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<bold>
<italic>Thank you for completing the survey.</italic>
</bold>
</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0897190012451930"><label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>An abstract of this research was accepted for presentation at the American Pharmacists Association 2012 Annual Meeting and Exposition in New Orleans, LA, in March 2012.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-0897190012451930"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-0897190012451930"><label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0897190012451930">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education</collab>. <source>Continuing Professional Development (CPD)</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.acpe-accredit.org/ceproviders/CPD.asp">www.acpe-accredit.org/ceproviders/CPD.asp</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed January 4, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0897190012451930">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dopp</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moulton</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rouse</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <source>Continuing Professional Development CPD 101. CPD: A Reason to Learn; CPD: A Way to Learn</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.acpe-accredit.org/pdf/CPD_101_Handouts.pdf">www.acpe-accredit.org/pdf/CPD_101_Handouts.pdf</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed January 4, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0897190012451930">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gehlbach</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Interpreting the Medical Literature</source>. <edition>5th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Companies, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0897190012451930">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education</collab>. <source>CPE Standards—Updated Policies &amp; Procedures</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.acpe-accredit.org/pdf/CPE_Policies%20_Procedures.pdf">www.acpe-accredit.org/pdf/CPE_Policies%20_Procedures.pdf</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed February 11, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0897190012451930">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saint</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Christakis</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saha</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Journal reading habits of internists</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>884</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0897190012451930">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Drug Topics website</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drugtopics.modernmedicine.com">http://drugtopics.modernmedicine.com</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed February 15, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0897190012451930">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Pharmacy Times website</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.pharmacytimes.com/subscribe">www.pharmacytimes.com/subscribe</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed</comment> <comment>February 15, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0897190012451930">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">US Pharmacist website</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.job-sub.halldata.com/site/JOB000287UPland/init.do?&amp;PK">www.job-sub.halldata.com/site/JOB000287UPland/init.do?&amp;PK</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed</comment> <comment>February 15, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0897190012451930">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Thomas Land Publishers Incorporated website</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.thomasland.com/hospitalpharmacy.html">www.thomasland.com/hospitalpharmacy.html</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed</comment> <comment>February 23, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0897190012451930">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Pharmacist’s Letter website</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pharmacistsletter.therapeuticresearch.com/pl/AboutServices.aspx?cs=FACULTY&amp;s=PL">http://pharmacistsletter.therapeuticresearch.com/pl/AboutServices.aspx?cs=FACULTY&amp;s=PL</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed February 23, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0897190012451930">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">United States Department of Labor</collab>. <comment>Bureau of Labor Statistics</comment>. <source>Occupational Outlook Handbook</source>. <year>2010-11</year> ed. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos079.htm">http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos079.htm</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed December 14, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>