<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwmr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Waste Manag Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Waste Management &amp; Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-242X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-3669</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734242X11403798</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734242X11403798</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On site domestic organic waste treatment through vermitechnology using indigenous earthworm species</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rajpal</surname><given-names>Ankur</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11403798">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>Renu</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11403798">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sasi</surname><given-names>Salin Kumar</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11403798">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0734242X11403798">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0734242X11403798"><label>1</label>Department of Civil Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee (IITR), Roorkee, India</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0734242X11403798"><label>2</label>Department of Zoology and Environmental Sciences, G.K.V. Haridwar, Uttarakhand, India</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0734242X11403798">Ankur Rajpal, C/O Renu Bhargava, Department of Civil Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee, Roorkee-247667, India Email: <email>ankur.envt@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>266</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>14</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Solid Waste Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In India the exotic epigeic species, <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic> is mostly used for vermicomposting. The introduction of exotic species into local bio system may affect the indigenous earthworm species population. A comparative study between exotic species (<italic>Eisenia fetida</italic>) and indigenous species <italic>Perionyx sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>Perionyx excavates</italic> was performed to determine the potential of indigenous species of the area <italic>vis-à-vis</italic> the exotic species for composting of domestic organic waste blended with cattle manure. The results of the study show a significant reduction in initial C/N ratio from 55 to 13 for <italic>P. excavates</italic> and 15 for <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> of the ready product which was within the agronomic acceptable limit ( &lt; 20). The total organic matter reduced by 50% and pH also reduced to be nearer to neutral, but there was an increase in total nitrogen to 102% and total phosphorus increased from the initial concentration of 7.62 g kg<sup>−1</sup> up to 13.2 g kg<sup>−1</sup>. Overall, by employing above indigenous species, domestic organic waste can be directly converted into high-quality hygienic stable fertilizer (vermicompost) which is rich in nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium and free from pathogens.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd><italic>Perionyx excavatus</italic></kwd>
<kwd><italic>Perionyx sansibaricus</italic></kwd>
<kwd><italic>Eisenia fetida</italic></kwd>
<kwd>vermicomposting</kwd>
<kwd>composting</kwd>
<kwd>domestic organic waste</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0734242X11403798" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Vermitechnology application has been proposed globally as an appropriate alternative for the safe, hygienic and cost-effective disposal of the organic fraction of municipal solid waste (MSW) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X11403798">Gajalakshmi et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0734242X11403798">Gupta and Garg, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0734242X11403798">Suthar, 2008a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X11403798">Suthar and Singh, 2008 a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0734242X11403798">b</xref>). Vermitechnology utilizes earthworms in an eco-biotechnological process that transforms energy rich organic substances into stabilized humus-like product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X11403798">Benitez et al., 2000</xref>). The large quantity of MSW produced in modern society, has become a serious environmental, social and economic problem. Domestic solid waste such as fruit and vegetable residues (FVW) constitute a source of nuisance in municipal landfills because of their high biodegradability. In India, FVW constitute about 5.6 million tons annually and currently these waste materials are disposed of by dumping on the outskirts of cities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X11403798">Arvanitoyannis et al., 2008</xref>). The problem is magnified due to lack of adequate infrastructure for segregation, collection, transportation and disposal of MSW. There are various shortcomings in the existing practice followed for the management of solid waste (domestic waste); these pertain mainly to inadequate manpower, financial resources and machinery required to perform various activity. However, vermitechnology can be used as a potential resource for transformation from expensive disposal to stabilized product for agricultural and soil conditioning.</p>
<p>Vermitechnology is a process of bio-oxidation and stabilization of organic material involving the joint action of earthworms and micro-organisms. Although microbes are involved in the biodegradation of organic matter, earthworms are the important drivers of the process, conditioning the substrate and altering biological activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X11403798">Adi and Noor, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0734242X11403798">Sharma et al., 2005</xref>). During the process of vermicomposting the earthworms act as the carriers of micro-organism, they feed on the organic matter and convert them into stable castings (ejected matter), which are rich in plant nutrients such as nitrogen, phosphorous and potassium.</p>
<p>In India the exotic epigeic species, <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic> (Savigny) and <italic>Eisenia euginae</italic> (Kinberg) have been identified as potential candidates to decompose organic waste materials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X11403798">Khwairakpam and Bhargava, 2009b</xref>). The introduction of foreign species into local biosystem has been justified by a few scientists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X11403798">Lavelle et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0734242X11403798">Murphy, 1993</xref>), but the introduction has been considered unnecessary and undesirable and leads to confrontation between the indigenous and foreign species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0734242X11403798">Ismail, 1995</xref>; Kaviraj et al., 2003).The composting potential of a few indigenous species such as <italic>Perionyx excavatus</italic>, <italic>Lampito mauritti</italic>, <italic>Dichogaster bolaui</italic>, <italic>Amynthas morrisi</italic>, <italic>Drawida willsi</italic> and <italic>Perionyx sansibaricus</italic> is well established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X11403798">Gajalakshmi et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X11403798">Suthar and Singh, 2008 a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0734242X11403798">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X11403798">Tripathi and Bhardwaj, 2004</xref>). With this in view the present study was undertaken to investigate the potential of indigenous species in the vermicomposting of domestic waste in order to help to solve waste management problems by minimizing the waste handling by the local authorities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0734242X11403798" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0734242X11403798">
<title>Collection and culturing of earthworms</title>
<p>In the present study exotic earthworms <italic>E. fetida</italic> were randomly picked up from the laboratory of Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee (IITR) for experimentation, where it has been cultured for the last 6 years. However, indigenous earthworm species <italic>P. excavatus</italic> was collected from a drain in IITR and <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> was collected from a village and both were identified before use. All three earthworm species were cultured in the environmental engineering laboratory of IITR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0734242X11403798">
<title>Substrate for experiment</title>
<p>Domestic waste was procured from campus residences and the student canteen of IITR. The non-biodegradable items such as plastic, rubber, polythene bags, wood, cardboard and glass were separated through hand sorting from the collected domestic waste. The domestic waste blended with cattle dung, having the initial characteristics of pH 8.62 ± 0.2; EC 0.25 ± 0.015 (S m<sup>−1</sup>); total organic carbon (TOC) 54.13 ± 4.3 (%); TN 0.99 ± 0.5 (%); C/N 54.67  ± 2.3; NH<sub>4</sub>-N 0.15  ± 3.1 (%), TP 7.62  ± 0.45 (g kg<sup>−1</sup>), C/P 71.32  ± 1.1, K 1.8  ± 1.9 (%), Na 0.45  ± 2.9 (%) was used as the substrate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0734242X11403798">
<title>Experimental set-up</title>
<p>The reactors were kept in a dark room in which the temperature was maintained at 25  ± 3°C, which is the optimum temperature range for all the three species (Tripathi and Bhardwaj, 2003). The experiments were conducted for 45days in rectangular plastic containers of 5 L capacity. The containers were punched with pin holes at the bottom for aeration and leaching of extra water. The experiments were conducted in quadrate, the first three sets having <italic>P. excavates</italic> (T<sub>1</sub>), <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> (T<sub>2</sub>), and <italic>E. fetida</italic> (T<sub>3</sub>) and the last set acting as the control (without any earthworms) (T<sub>4</sub>). Ten centimetres of bedding was provided in all the containers using matured vermicompost to provide the initial favourable condition for the earthworms. Forty grams ( ∼ 130–150 in number) of the experimental species of worms having clitellated were inoculated in the bedding of all containers except the control. One kilogram of domestic waste was amended with cattle manure in a 4 : 1 ratio to provide a favourable condition for earthworms and was kept for 2 weeks prior to the experimentation for thermal stabilization and then added to each of the reactors. The quantity of waste to be added to each container was decided, based on the literature reports that the earthworms can consume the food equal to half of their body weight per day under favourable conditions (Haimi and Huhta, 1986; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X11403798">Khwairakpam and Bhargava, 2009a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X11403798">b</xref>). The moisture level was maintained at about 60–70% throughout the study by periodic sprinkling of an adequate quantity of tap (potable) water. To prevent moisture loss, the reactors were covered with bags prepared by jute fibers at the top.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0734242X11403798">
<title>Compost analysis</title>
<p>The homogenized wet samples of the feedstock were collected on 0, 15th, 30th and 45th day from each experimental reactor and analyzed. The zero day sample refers to the substrate taken out before earthworm inoculation. (1 : 10 w/v waste: water extract) total coliforms (TC), faecal streptococci (FS) and faecal coliforms (FC) were measured by inoculation of culture in tubes having Lauryl tryptose broth, Azide dextrose broth and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> medium, respectively, using the most probable number (MPN) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0734242X11403798">APHA, 1995</xref>), and the rest sub-samples were oven dried at 110°C, ground in a stainless steel blender, passed through a 0.2 mm sieve and stored until further analysis. Each sub-sample was analysed for the following parameters: pH using a pH meter and electrical conductivity (EC) using a conductivity meter (1 : 10 w/v waste : water extract), total organic carbon (TOC) determined by Shimadzu (TOC-Vcsn) solid sample module (SSM-5000 A), total nitrogen (TN) using the Kjeldahl method, ammoniacal nitrogen (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N) and nitrate nitrogen (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>-N) using KCl extraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0734242X11403798">Tiquia and Tam, 2000</xref>). Total potassium (TK), chemical oxygen demand (COD) and biochemical oxygen demand (BOD) were analyzed by spectrophotometry. In addition the temperature of the composting bed was monitored on a daily basis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0734242X11403798">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>All the reported data are the mean of four replicates. One way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to determine any significant difference among the parameters analysed. Where asignificant difference was observed, individual means were tested using the Fisher’s Least Significance Difference test (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0734242X11403798" sec-type="results|discussion">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="section9-0734242X11403798">
<title>pH</title>
<p>The pH reduced in all of the reactors, the maximum reduction was observed for T<sub>3</sub> where the pH reduced from 8.62 to 7.03 and the minimum reduction was observed in the control where the pH reduced nominally to 8.2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X11403798">Table 1</xref>). A higher reduction in pH in T<sub>3</sub> was observed because of the higher rate of breakdown of organic matter in this reactor. In the case of T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>2</sub> the pH had reduced to 7.28 and 7.42, respectively. The decreasing trend of pH was prominent for T<sub>1</sub>, T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>3</sub> during the first 30 days of vermicomposting. In the last 15 days the reduction was nominal. However, for the control reaction the reduction was uniform throughout the period of vermicomposting. The result was in accordance with the finding reported previously by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0734242X11403798">Atiyeh et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X11403798">Gunadi et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0734242X11403798">Mitchell, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X11403798">Ndegwa and Thompson, 2000</xref>). The lowering of pH in the final product was due to the generation of CO<sub>2</sub> and organic acids produced during microbial metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11403798">Elvira et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X11403798">Haimi and Hutha, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X11403798">Hartenstein and Hartenstein, 1981</xref>). There was a significant variation in pH on the 45th day of sampling (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for all the reactors.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida</italic> inoculation on pH, e. conductivity (EC) and TOC</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors/earthworm species</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">pH</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">EC (S m<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">TOC (%)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub> (<italic>P. excavatus</italic>)</td>
<td>8.5a</td>
<td>7.9a</td>
<td>7.3a</td>
<td>0.26b</td>
<td>0.27ac</td>
<td>0.27bc</td>
<td>42.7a</td>
<td>35.1a</td>
<td>27a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub> (<italic>P. sansibaricus</italic>)</td>
<td>8.5a</td>
<td>7.9a</td>
<td>7.4a</td>
<td>0.27b</td>
<td>0.27ac</td>
<td>0.27bc</td>
<td>42.2ab</td>
<td>39.7c</td>
<td>30.3abc</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub> (<italic>E. fetida</italic>)</td>
<td>8.5a</td>
<td>7.6b</td>
<td>7.03ab</td>
<td>0.26b</td>
<td>0.27a</td>
<td>0.28ab</td>
<td>45.9b</td>
<td>37.9ab</td>
<td>28.4ab</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>4</sub> (without earthworm)</td>
<td>8.5b</td>
<td>8.4bc</td>
<td>8.2abc</td>
<td>0.25b</td>
<td>0.26abc</td>
<td>0.26c</td>
<td>51.4ab</td>
<td>45.9ac</td>
<td>41.8bc</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0734242X11403798">
<p>Data with the same letter within the same column do not differ significantly at the 5% level according to the Fisher’s Least Significant Difference test.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0734242X11403798">
<title>Electrical conductivity</title>
<p>A gradual increase in EC was observed in all reactors during the process of vermicomposting. The maximum increase was observed in EC values of reactor T<sub>3</sub> (0.28 S/m) as compared to control (0.26 S/m), T<sub>1</sub> (0.27 S/m) and T<sub>2</sub> (0.27 S/m) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X11403798">Table 1</xref>). These observations are supported by the findings of other authors who have reported an increase in EC during the course of vermicomposting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0734242X11403798">Garg et al., 2006</xref>). The increase of EC is attributed to the loss of organic matter and release of different mineral salts in available forms (such as phosphate, ammonium, potassium, etc) which means the mineralization/decomposition of the organic matter is responsible for the increase in EC. This is supported by the findings of the other researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X11403798">Huang et al., 2004</xref>). No significant variation was observed in EC on the 45th day in all the reactors (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0734242X11403798">
<title>Total organic carbon</title>
<p>The TOC reduced during the process of vermicomposting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X11403798">Figure 1</xref>). A large fraction of TOC was lost due to the oxidation of biodegradable organic carbon to CO<sub>2</sub> and consumption of available carbon as an energy source by earthworms and micro-organisms. The maximum reduction was observed for T<sub>1</sub> from 541.28 to 270.36 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (50%) and the minimum reduction was observed in the case of controls, which had shown a reduction of 22% during the period of composting (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X11403798">Table 1</xref>). The observed results are supported by the findings of other authors who have reported 20 to 45% loss of carbon as CO<sub>2</sub> during vermicomposting of municipal or industrial waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11403798">Elvira et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0734242X11403798">Kaviraj and Sharma, 2003</xref>). TOC varied significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the 15th and 30th day but showed insignificant variation on the 45th day of sampling (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>TOC profile during vermicomposting.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0734242X11403798">
<title>Total nitrogen, nitrogen (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) and nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>)</title>
<p>The maximum increase of 113% in TN was observed for reactor T<sub>3</sub> as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0734242X11403798">Table 2</xref>. The minimum increase of 17% was observed for control. For T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>1</sub> the increase was in the order of 102 and 108%, respectively, which is comparable to the performance of reactor T<sub>3</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X11403798">Figure 2</xref>). The reduction in organic carbon due to substrate utilization by microbes and earthworms, and water loss by evaporation and mineralization of organic matter might have led to a relative increase in nitrogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0734242X11403798">Viel et al., 1987</xref>). However, in general the final content of nitrogen in vermicomposting is dependent on initial nitrogen present in the waste and the extent of decomposition. Earthworm activity enriches the nitrogen profile of the vermicompost through microbial-mediated nitrogen transformation, addition of mucus and nitrogenous waste secreted by earthworms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X11403798">Khwairakpam and Bhargava, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0734242X11403798">Suthar, 2009 a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0734242X11403798">b</xref>). A decrease in NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N was observed with a corresponding increase in NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>-N at the end of the vermicomposting process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0734242X11403798">Suthar, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0734242X11403798">2009 b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0734242X11403798">Suthar and Singh, 2008 a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0734242X11403798">b</xref>). However, there was no relation observed between both forms of nitrogen. The difference between various forms of nitrogen would be due to immobilization and de-nitrification. TN showed a significant variation (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) on the 30th and 45th day for all the reactors.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida</italic> inoculation on nitrogen</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">TN (%)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">NH<sub>4</sub><sup>−</sup>N-(%)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>N-(%)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>1.3ab</td>
<td>1.6bc</td>
<td>2.07c</td>
<td>0.11b</td>
<td>0.1a</td>
<td>0.09abc</td>
<td>0.01a</td>
<td>0.02ab</td>
<td>0.07ab</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>1.17a</td>
<td>1.53b</td>
<td>2.01ab</td>
<td>0.12ab</td>
<td>0.1a</td>
<td>0.09b</td>
<td>0.02ab</td>
<td>0.03abc</td>
<td>0.07ac</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub></td>
<td>1.37b</td>
<td>1.86ab</td>
<td>2.12ab</td>
<td>0.1ab</td>
<td>0.09bc</td>
<td>0.08ac</td>
<td>0.02ab</td>
<td>0.05ab</td>
<td>0.08a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>4</sub></td>
<td>1.02a</td>
<td>1.06b</td>
<td>1.17ab</td>
<td>0.12b</td>
<td>0.11c</td>
<td>0.1abc</td>
<td>0.01a</td>
<td>0.01a</td>
<td>0.02a</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0734242X11403798">
<p>Data with the same letter within the same column do not differ significantly at the 5% level according to the Fisher’s Least Significant Difference test.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>TN profile during vermicomposting.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0734242X11403798">
<title>Total phosphorous</title>
<p>Total phosphorous increased during the vermicomposting process because of the mineralization of the organic matter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X11403798">Figure 3</xref>). The initial value was 7.62 g kg<sup>−1</sup> and this subsequently increased during vermicomposting to 13.2 g kg<sup>−1</sup> for T<sub>1</sub>, and to 11.3, 13.5 and 8.52 g kg<sup>−1</sup> for T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub>, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0734242X11403798">Table 3</xref>). The maximum increase of about 1.77 times the initial value was observed in T<sub>3</sub>. The increase in TP during vermicomposting was due to mineralization and mobilization of phosphorus by the bacterial and faecal phosphates activity of earthworms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X11403798">Edwards et al., 1972</xref>). An increase of 25% in TP of paper waste sludge after worm activity was found by some authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0734242X11403798">Satchell et al., 1984</xref>). The difference in TP content was significant in all the reactors on all the sampling days (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida</italic> inoculation on TP and potassium</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">TP (%)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">K (%)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>0.78a</td>
<td>0.94b</td>
<td>1.32ab</td>
<td>1.96a</td>
<td>1.98a</td>
<td>2.06a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>0.79ab</td>
<td>0.92abc</td>
<td>1.13abc</td>
<td>1.86b</td>
<td>1.93ab</td>
<td>1.98a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub></td>
<td>0.86a</td>
<td>0.98ab</td>
<td>1.35ab</td>
<td>1.96a</td>
<td>2.08b</td>
<td>2.08b</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>4</sub></td>
<td>0.78ab</td>
<td>0.81ab</td>
<td>0.85ab</td>
<td>1.86a</td>
<td>1.89b</td>
<td>1.93ab</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0734242X11403798">
<p>Data with the same letter within the same column do not differ significantly at the 5% level according to the Fisher’s Least Significant Difference test.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig3-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>TP profile during vermicomposting.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0734242X11403798">
<title>C/N and C/P ratios</title>
<p>The role of organic carbon and inorganic nitrogen for cell synthesis, growth, and metabolism is important in all living organisms. The C/N and C/P ratios are important because plants cannot assimilate mineral N and P unless these ratios are of the order of 20 : 1 and 15 : 1, respectively or less (Khwairakpam and Bhargava, 2008; Tripathi and Bhardwaj, 2003). The decrease in C/N ratio over time is due to increase in the earthworm population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X11403798">Ndegwa and Thompson, 2000</xref>), which led to rapid decrease in the organic carbon due to enhanced oxidation of the organic matter. The release of part of the carbon as carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) in the process of respiration, production of mucus and N excrements, increases levels of N and lowers the C/N ratios (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X11403798">Khwairakpam and Bhargava, 2009</xref>). To provide proper nutrition for earthworms during vermicomposting, carbon and nitrogen must be present in the substrates at the correct ratio (45–60). The usual practice is to arbitrarily add either a rich nitrogenous material, or a rich carbonaceous material to the feed substrate, depending on the situation, to correct C-to-N imbalance. The initial C/N and C/P value of the substrate were 55 and 71 respectively. C/N subsequently reduced during vermicomposting to 13 for T<sub>1</sub>, 15 for T<sub>2</sub>, 13 for T<sub>3</sub> and 36 for T<sub>4</sub> as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0734242X11403798">Figure 4</xref>. Similar to C/N, a gradual reduction in C/P was observed in all the reactors during the process. The decrease observed was 20 for T<sub>1</sub>, 26 for T<sub>2</sub>, 21 for T<sub>3</sub> and 49 for T<sub>4</sub> (control) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X11403798">Figure 5</xref>). In both the cases the minimum reduction was observed in the case of the control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0734242X11403798">Table 4</xref>). The performance of both indigenous earthworm species was comparable with that of other exotic earthworm species. The differences in both C/N and C/P content in the final product obtained from the different reactors were significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for all of the reactors on all the sampling days.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>C/N profile during vermicomposting.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>C/P profile during vermicomposting.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table4-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida</italic> inoculation on C/N and C/P ratio</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">C/N ratio</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">C/P ratio</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>33</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>36</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub></td>
<td>34</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>4</sub></td>
<td>50</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>49</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0734242X11403798">
<p>All data represent average of four replicates.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0734242X11403798">
<title>Macro-nutrients (potassium, sodium, calcium)</title>
<p>The initial concentration of potassium in the substrate was 13.6 g kg<sup>−1</sup> and this subsequently increased for all reactors during the process of vermicomposting. The maximum increase was observed in reactor T<sub>3</sub>, in which the concentration after vermicomposting was 19.72 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (45% increase) and the minimum increase was observed in the case of the control, in which the potassium increase was 16.6 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (22% increase) as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0734242X11403798">Table 3</xref>. The performance of T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub> was comparable, as T<sub>1</sub> has shown an increase of 18.5 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (36% increase). In the case of vermicomposting the enhanced number of micro flora present in the gut of earthworms plays an important role in this process resulting in increased potassium over the control (Kaviraj et al., 2003). There was significant variation (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for all the reactors on all the sampling days.</p>
<p>The initial concentration of Na in the substrate was 6.6 g kg<sup>−1</sup> and this increased during vermicomposting in all reactors except for the control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X11403798">Table 5</xref>). The maximum increase was observed in T<sub>3</sub> and was 8.7 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (32% increase) and the minimum increase was observed in T<sub>2</sub> and was 7.4 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (12% increase). The increase for T<sub>1</sub> was 8.2 g kg<sup>−1</sup> (24% increase). There was significant variation (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in all the reactors on all of the sampling days.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida</italic> inoculation on sodium and calcium</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Na (%)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Ca (%)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>0.37ab</td>
<td>0.25abc</td>
<td>0.22abc</td>
<td>2.76ab</td>
<td>2.91ab</td>
<td>3.01a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>0.42ab</td>
<td>0.37abc</td>
<td>0.28abc</td>
<td>2.58ab</td>
<td>2.72ab</td>
<td>2.76ab</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub></td>
<td>0.3b</td>
<td>0.22abc</td>
<td>0.18abc</td>
<td>2.88ab</td>
<td>2.96ab</td>
<td>3.04ab</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>4</sub></td>
<td>0.44a</td>
<td>0.39ab</td>
<td>0.36ab</td>
<td>2.55ab</td>
<td>2.61ab</td>
<td>2.71ab</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0734242X11403798">
<label>a</label>
<p>Data with the same letter within the same column do not differ significantly at the 5% level according to the Fisher’s Least Significant Difference test.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The initial concentration of Ca was 5.6 g kg<sup>−1</sup>, which subsequently increased to 6.8, 6.7, 7.2 and 6.3 g kg<sup>−1</sup> for T<sub>1</sub>, T<sub>2</sub>, T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub>, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X11403798">Table 5</xref>). There was no significant variation for Ca on all the sampling days.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0734242X11403798">
<title>Coliforms and fecal streptococci</title>
<p>This parameter is important from the view point of application of compost in the field. The number of coliforms reduced in all of the reactors during vermicomposting as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0734242X11403798">Table 6</xref>. The initial value for total coliforms (TC) was 2.4 × 10<sup>9</sup>: In T<sub>1</sub>, T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>3</sub> 7 log reductions were observed for TC in vermicompost; however, for control only a 2 log reduction was observed. The initial fecal coliforms (FC) count was 4.3 × 10<sup>6</sup>, which subsequently reduced to 24 for T<sub>1</sub>, 36 for T<sub>2</sub>, 43 for T<sub>3</sub> at the 45th day, however for the control only 2 log reduction was observed. The source of fecal coliforms in the substrate was the cattle manure, as no fecal coliforms were found in the domestic waste. The initial value for fecal streptococci (FS) was 9.3 × 10<sup>7</sup>, which reduced by 5 log during vermicomposting in reactor T<sub>1</sub>, T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>. For T<sub>4</sub>, only a 2 log reduction was observed. The presence of coliform bacteria is often used as an indicator of overall sanitary quality of the compost. For compost hygiene, the recommended FC and FS densities are 5 × 10<sup>2</sup> and 5 × 10<sup>3</sup> MPN g<sup>−1</sup>, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0734242X11403798">Vuorinen and Saharinen, 1997</xref>). These results show that the pathogen stabilization potential of the indigenous species of earthworm (<italic>P. excavates</italic> and <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic>) is comparable with that of the exotic species (<italic>E. fetida</italic>) within 45 days. The coliform count varied significantly for all the reactors (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida</italic> inoculation on coliforms and streptococci</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">TC (MPN g<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">FC (MPN g<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">FS (MPN g<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
<th align="left">15 days</th>
<th align="left">30 days</th>
<th align="left">45 days</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>7</sup>  ± 300</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>5</sup> ± 197</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 20</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 500</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 356</td>
<td>Nil</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 700</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>3</sup>  ± 240</td>
<td>240  ± 21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>7</sup>  ± 600</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>4</sup>  ± 200</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 18</td>
<td>4.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 879</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 398</td>
<td>Nil</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 900</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 230</td>
<td>903  ± 34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub></td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>7</sup>  ± 650</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 189</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 14</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 700</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>2</sup>  ± 167</td>
<td>Nil</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 600</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>3</sup>  ± 197</td>
<td>24  ± 15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>4</sub></td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>8</sup>  ± 290</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>7</sup>  ± 545</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 198</td>
<td>4.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 345</td>
<td>9.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 300</td>
<td>9.3 x 10<sup>4</sup>  ± 170</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>7</sup>  ± 650</td>
<td>2.4 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 213</td>
<td>1.5 × 10<sup>5</sup>  ± 195</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0734242X11403798">
<p>All data represent average of four replicates.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0734242X11403798">
<title>Earthworms biomass</title>
<p>The change in worm biomass in all the reactors during the vermicomposting period is depicted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-0734242X11403798">Table 7</xref>. No mortality was observed in any reactor during the vermicomposting period. The vermicompost was dark brown (towards blackish) in colour and homogeneous after 45 days of earthworm activity. At the end of the 45 days, the earthworm biomass increased slowly in all the reactors. The increase in weight of earthworm biomass during the composting period varied between 27.5 and 47.5%. The maximum increase was observed in T<sub>3</sub> and the value was 47.5%. However in T<sub>1</sub> the increase observed was 14.3% and in T<sub>2</sub> the increase observed was only 9.98%. The biomass increase in <italic>E. fetida</italic> was found to be a maximum, but in comparison the amount of juveniles were more in the indigenous species. This may be because the activity of the native worms is delayed in the beginning or the adaptation process is slow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X11403798">Garg, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X11403798">Khwairakpam, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0734242X11403798">Tripathi and Bhardwaj, 2004</xref>). The adaptability of <italic>E. fetida</italic> is a well known fact.</p>
<table-wrap id="table7-0734242X11403798" position="float">
<label>Table 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Growth and reproduction of <italic>P. excavatus</italic>, <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>E. fetida.</italic>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-0734242X11403798" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11403798-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Reactors</th>
<th align="left">Earthworms</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Mean weight of earthworms (g)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Number of earthworms</th>
<th align="left">Earthworm weight gain (%)</th>
<th align="left">Earthworm number gain (%)</th>
<th align="left">Number of cocoons (worms/day)</th>
<th align="left">Number of juveniles hatched/100 g of vermicompost</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">Initial</th>
<th align="left">Final</th>
<th align="left">Initial</th>
<th align="left">Final</th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>1</sub></td>
<td><italic>P. excavatus</italic></td>
<td>40</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>158</td>
<td>32.5</td>
<td>43.6</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>2</sub></td>
<td><italic>P. sansibaricus</italic></td>
<td>40</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>151</td>
<td>27.5</td>
<td>43.7</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>T<sub>3</sub></td>
<td><italic>E. fetida</italic></td>
<td>40</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>155</td>
<td>47.5</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0734242X11403798">
<p>All data represent average of four replicates.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0734242X11403798" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Waste management in vegetable production is a tough problem, and its optimum solution must look for local factors that need to be taken into account. Vermicomposting could be answer to this difficulty. Unfortunately, the vermicomposting process is limited in use because the users have to purchase the earthworms in the beginning and if they are lost for some reason then they have to be purchased again and thus more expenditure is needed. This constraint can be removed by use of indigenous earthworms.</p>
<p>In addition, <italic>E. fetida</italic> is well known to be a more tolerant species, hence after continuous application of the vermicompost produced using <italic>E. fetida</italic> the local earthworm species will vanish from that area.</p>
<p>This study was performed to investigate the efficacy of indigenous species in comparison with <italic>E. fetida</italic> for the composting of domestic waste. From the study it is concluded that the performance of the indigenous species of earthworms (<italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>P. excavates</italic>) is comparable with that of the exotic species (<italic>E. fetida</italic>). This study also revealed that the exotic species degraded the organic matter faster in comparison with the indigenous species but <italic>P. sansibaricus</italic> and <italic>P. excavates</italic> produced a quality of compost which was comparable with that produced from <italic>E. fetida</italic>; that is, the C/N ratio was below 20 with a minor difference in N P K values. The process of stabilization takes about 30 days for completion and maturation takes place in another 10–15 days later. Hence these species can be successfully used for on-site treatment of domestic organic waste.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors would like to express thanks to Uttarakhand Council of Science and Technology (UCOST) for their Financial assistance.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Waste recycling: Utilization of coffee grounds and kitchen waste in vermicomposting</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1030</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Public Health Association (APHA)</collab> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater</source>, <edition>17th edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>APHA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arvanitoyannis</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varzakas</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Vegetable waste treatment: Comparison and critical presentation of methodologies</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Atiyeh</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Changes in biochemical properties of cow manure during processing by earthworms (<italic>Eisenia andrei</italic> Bouche) and the effects on seedling growth</article-title>. <source>Pedobiologia</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benitez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elvira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masciandaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceccanti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Enzyme activities as indicators of the stabilization of sewage sludge composting with <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic></article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>C A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lofty</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>Biology of Earthworms</source>. <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elvira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sampedro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benitez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Vermicomposting of sludges from paper mill and dairy industries with <italic>Eisenia andrei</italic>: a pilot scale study</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gajalakshmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramasamy</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Potential of two epigeic and two anecic earthworm species in vermicomposting of water hyacinth</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gajalakshmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramasamy</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Vermicomposting of different forms of water hyacinth by earthworm <italic>Eudrilus eugeniae</italic>, Kinberg</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Performance Evaluation of Native and Exotic Species of Earthworm for Agrohorticulture Waste Management</source>. <comment>Unpublished doctoral thesis</comment>, <publisher-name>Department of Civil Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dilbaghi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Vermiconversion of wastewater sludge from textile mill mixed with anaerobically digested biogas plant slurry employing <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic></article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gunadi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The effect of multiple applications of different organic wastes on the growth, fecundity and survival of <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic></article-title>. <source>Pedobiologia</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Stabilization of primary sewage sludge during vermicomposting</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haimi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hutha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Capacity of various organic residues to support adequate earthworm biomass for vermicomposting</article-title>. <source>Biology and Fertility of Soil</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartenstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartenstein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Physicochemical changes effected in activated sludge by the earthworms <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Environmental Quality</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JWC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>QT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagar</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Effect of C/N on composting of pig manure with sawdust</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>813</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Earthworms in soil fertility management</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Thampan</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Organic Agriculture</source>. <publisher-name>Peekay Tree Crops Development Foundation</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>Cochin, India</publisher-loc>, <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaviraj</surname></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Municipal solid waste management through vermicomposting employing exotic and local species of earthworms</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khwairakpam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Integrated Waste Management through Vermitechnology</source>. <comment>Unpublished doctoral thesis</comment>, <publisher-name>Department of Civil Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>Roorkee, India</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khwairakpam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009a</year>) <article-title>Vermitechnology for sewage sludge recycling</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>948</fpage>–<lpage>954</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khwairakpam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009b</year>) <article-title>Bioconversion of filter mud using vermicomposting employing two exotic and one local earthworm species</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>5846</fpage>–<lpage>5852</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavelle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barois</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaidi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Management of earthworm population in agro-ecosystem</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Charholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berystrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds). <source>A Possible Way to Maintain Soil Quality and Ecology of Arabie Land</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>, <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Production of <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic> and vermicompost from feedlot cattle manure</article-title>. <source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>766</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Earthworms in Australia</source>. <publisher-loc>Victoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hyland House Publishing Pty Ltd</publisher-name>, <fpage>112</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ndegwa</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Effect of C-to-N ratio on vermicomposting of biosolids</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Satchell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Phosphate activity in earthworm faeces</article-title>. <source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Satya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasudevan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>, (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>Potentially of earthworms for waste management and in other uses – a review</article-title>. <source>The Journal of American Science</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008a</year>) <article-title>Bioconversion of post harvest crop residues and cattle shed manure into value-added products using earthworm <italic>Eudrilus eugeniae</italic> Kinberg</article-title>. <source>Ecological Engineering</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009a</year>) <article-title>Vermicomposting of vegetable market solid waste using <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic>: impact of bulking material on earthworm growth and decomposition rate</article-title>. <source>Ecological Engineering</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>914</fpage>–<lpage>920</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009b</year>) <article-title>Growth and fecundity of earthworms (Oligochaeta): <italic>Perionyx excavatus</italic> and <italic>Perionyx sansibaricusin</italic> cattle waste solid</article-title>. <source>Environmentalist</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008a</year>) <article-title>Vermicomposting of domestic waste by using two epigeic earthworms (<italic>Perionyx excavatus</italic> and <italic>Perionyx sansibaricus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Environmental Science and Technology</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008b</year>) <article-title>Feasibility of vermicomposting in biostabilization sludge from a distillery industry</article-title>. <source>Science of the Total Environment</source> <volume>394</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tiquia</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>NFY</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Fate of nitrogen during composting of chicken litter</article-title>. <source>Environmental Pollution</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Decomposition of kitchen waste amended with cow manure using epigeic species (<italic>Eisenia fetida</italic>) and an anecic species (<italic>Lampito mauritii</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Viel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sayag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Optimisation of agricultural, industrial waste management through in-vessel composting</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>de Bertoldi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Compost: Production, Quality and Use</source>. <publisher-loc>Harlow, Essex</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Applied Science</publisher-name>, <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0734242X11403798">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vuorinen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saharinen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Evolution of microbiological and chemical parameters during manure and straw co-composting in a drum composting system</article-title>. <source>Agriculture, Ecosystem &amp; Environment</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>