<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcmc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Crime, Media, Culture: An International Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1741-6590</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-6604</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1741659011435404</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1741659011435404</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Flashback: Drugs and Dealing in the Golden Age of the London Rave Scene</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Winlow</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>Rowland</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1741659011435404">University of Winchester, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: York Deviancy Conference 2011</issue-title>
<fpage>236</fpage>
<lpage>240</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Flashback: Drugs and Dealing in the Golden Age of the London Rave Scene</source>, <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>; <page-count count="192"/> pp. ISBN <isbn>9781843927914</isbn>, <price>£45.00</price> (hbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It is less common these days to come across research monographs based upon classical participant observation in the tradition established by Whyte’s <italic>Street Corner Society</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741659011435404">1943</xref>). The privations associated with this research strategy and the pressure to produce research outputs within ever-shortening time frames mean that it is too often a problematic choice for both new and established researchers. And yet, as Whyte explains, it was only when he took the decision to <italic>live</italic> among the communities of Cornerville that he began to really understand how the social networks, including those sustaining a variety of illegal activities, actually worked. Jennifer Ward did not choose to actually live with the drug users and drug dealers that she studied during a five-year period of ethnographic field work between 1993 and 1998, reported in this book, but in a sense she did join their communities in London on the rave club scene. Like Whyte, she organizes much of her ethnographic material around detailed accounts of the lives of a small number of characters active on the scene at that time; like Whyte, one of her principal theoretical interests relates to the dynamics of closed and open social networks, and like Whyte she provides a rather poignant account of the ‘later lives’ of these characters, following the completion of the field work, as they age through their twenties and into their thirties or, in some cases, forties.</p>
<p>The title of the book foregrounds the claim that the mid-1990s was an exceptional period – a ‘golden age’ – for the London rave and clubbing scene. This could be interpreted in two ways: first, as a quantitative claim about the volume of ‘recreational drugs’ consumed during this period, or second, as a description of the vibrancy of rave culture during this period. It is certainly true that in the decade following the period of the field work official data suggests a modest but significant decline in the quantity of recreational drugs such as ecstasy and cocaine, consumed by young people, as more embraced the pleasures of alcohol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1741659011435404">Measham and Brain, 2005</xref>). The suggestion that the 1990s was a distinctive period because of the centrality of these recreational drugs to the culture of young people has been made elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1741659011435404">Hammersley, Khan and Ditton, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741659011435404">Measham, Aldridge and Parker, 2001</xref>). However, the approach taken in this book is distinctive because, rather than focusing upon quantitative measures of the extent of recreational drug use or the subcultural identities and meanings associated with that consumption, the focus here is upon the business end of the process: ‘the income generation and economic activity’ associated with the drug dealing that underpinned this ‘golden age’ (p. 2). Ultimately, through ethnography Ward seeks to uncover ‘the organisational features of drug selling and purchasing in different settings and social arenas’ and ‘emphasises the enterprise and entrepreneurship that underpinned this activity’ (p. 2). In other words, while many rave culture participants were enthusiastic consumers of recreational drugs, they were also keen to capitalize on the money-making opportunities afforded by this culture.</p>
<p>Following earlier studies of ‘hard’ drug distribution, the theoretical framework develops a neo-Weberian approach which distinguishes open from closed drug markets. Open markets afford access to all comers based upon fixed-site locations; closed markets are more exclusive, operating across locations but through closed social networks of friends and acquaintances. But Ward’s ethnographic research prompts her to describe rave drug markets of the 1990s as ‘semi-open’ systems because, while much of the drug distribution operated through friendship networks, at the same time, nightclubs provided open marketplaces where ‘anyone, providing they didn’t look like an undercover police officer could purchase’(p. 5). The central argument emerging from the ethnography rests upon this analysis of the distribution systems in operation. It is these that foster the entrepreneurial culture which becomes the focus for the research: the ‘enterprise and entrepreneurship, friendship and functionality’ to be found within the urban setting of the London club scene in the 1990s (p. 5). Ward argues that the rave culture generated a variety of economic opportunities, illegal and legal, for the more enterprising rave culture participants who could spot ways to make money through the expanding night-time leisure economy. These ‘leisure entrepreneurs’ might prosper through running nightclubs, working as DJs, promoting illegal events, and, of course, distributing recreational drugs.</p>
<p>The theme of ‘crime as work’ is not new; its roots can certainly be traced as far back as the structural sociology of Robert Merton in the 1940s, the critical arguments of the New Criminology in the 1970s and more recently in the numerous studies of organized crime and the security industries. However, Ward’s study is particularly valuable in drawing our attention to the routine blurring of the boundaries between legitimate and illegal enterprise inherent in the everyday lives of these participants in the rave and club scene of the 1990s. She locates her work in the tradition of urban sociology and the study of the impact that urban localities have upon the quality of social relationships. Just as Tonnies and Simmel identified looser, more anonymous and functional relationships in the city, so Ward suggests that the entrepreneurial relationships of the rave scene were facilitated not only by the size of London night-time leisure markets but also by their fleeting and transitory nature. It was their looseness that afforded opportunities to the more fleet-footed ‘leisure entrepreneurs’. But these were not just economic relationships but also social relationships or ‘friendships’, and this prompts Ward to question the nature of ‘friendship’ in these contexts. The subjects of her study operated with the shifting, fluid identities and flexible social skills of the actors to be found in Giddens’ account of late-modern society (p. 6). The ‘friends’ that sustained the chains of drug distribution might include personal acquaintances of long standing, regular customers whose primary purpose was simply to purchase, and ‘friends of friends’ encountered for the first time on a particular night.</p>
<p>It is this picture of the social and economic relationships underpinning the London rave scene that explains Ward’s inclination to move beyond the accounts offered by subcultural theory. Rave culture here is more pluralistic and inclusive; participants come from a variety of backgrounds; neither social class, nor ethnicity, appears to be a primary determinant of cultural participation. Most importantly, for Ward, her subjects demonstrated an entrepreneurial agency that she is tempted to attribute to the influence of Thatcherism (p. 17) and one cannot dispute the point that her subjects, growing up in the 1980s, were the first subjects, or perhaps victims, of the Thatcherite project of moral re-regulation that unfolded through the decade that preceded the 1990s. While some have sought to explain subcultures, including rave and club cultures, as expressions of social protest, Ward is drawn to the enterprise and entrepreneurial energy that characterized rave culture during this period. These subjects, according to Ward, were not victims resisting the oppressive structures of neoliberal capitalism but rather active agents choosing to combine their drug styles with opportunistic strategies to make a living through their pharmaceutical hobbies. Some of these hobbies grew into thriving and successful businesses.</p>
<p>Chapter one sets the scene and places the study in the context of previous work on drug consumption and the emergence of the rave and dance cultures. Chapter two demonstrates one of the great advantages of the ethnographic approach in providing a succinct but rich account of the locations within which the research occurred. These ranged from small DJ bars, larger organized, commercial dance venues, ‘moving parties’ (one-off, exclusive events, usually at small venues) and more anarchic and illegal, free ‘thrash’ events, organized through word of mouth. At Lush, for example, a small venue running club nights, Ward describes a cold, dank, empty space to be found under some railway arches in South London, a location that could only be attractive to those eager to evade the more sustained regulatory surveillance to be found at larger, more physically comfortable venues. Each location is assessed in terms of its physical environment and its ‘drug selling and security’ arrangements. At Lush, it is not surprising to find that, while individual consumption of drugs was tolerated, more systematic dealing was strongly discouraged by the venue’s security team because it threatened the position of the club owner as the monopoly supplier of the recreational drugs required to make the venue tolerable (p. 41).This is the kind of detail that can probably only be secured through ethnographic research.</p>
<p>Chapter three introduces the main ‘characters’, the subjects that provide the narratives upon which the study is based. One of the advantages of a five-year-longitudinal study is that it can track changes in drug styles or consumption patterns through the experiences of the subjects. Ward started the study as a drugs agency worker and it is through this role that she meets her subjects, including six main contacts and five distinct friendship groups associated with each of them. Through her participation with these friendship groups, she tells the story of a number of distinct drug styles, from the heavy and uncontrolled poly-drug use of Joe and his friends involved in the anarchic thrash events, the slightly more discriminating but nonetheless pretty heavy consumption patterns of the Australian expatriates, the moderate but sustained drug use of the older participants, and more casual patterns among other groups. Through these accounts the study charts the shift in drug fashions from ecstasy to cocaine as the price of the latter drops and the growing tendency to combine cocaine and amphetamines with alcohol during the later phase of the fieldwork.</p>
<p>The next two chapters concern the patterns of drug trading to be found within clubs (chapter four) and through social networks existing independently of the club scene (chapter five). Drug trading within clubs and public venues brings obvious risks but Ward provides an interesting account of the risk assessment and risk management strategies employed by traders. What becomes clear is the tacit acknowledgement on the part of even the more mainstream operators that the success of a dance night depends upon the plentiful supply of drugs. A commercially successful club needs its drug traders as much as an impromptu thrash event. Ward distinguishes ‘resident dealers’ who operate in arrangement with club managements from ‘club dealers’ who operate independently, but also notes that ‘opportunistic sellers’ may operate in more sporadic ways. Significantly, she notes that those most prepared to take the greatest risks of selling in public places were those from ‘low socio-economic and marginalised backgrounds . . . restricted to unskilled, poorly paid work’ (p. 91). In the following chapter (five), Ward describes the activities of the ‘social network dealers’ who operated mainly through friends and friends of friends, rather than in open public locations. These characters were less likely to regard themselves as ‘dealers’ despite the high volumes of drugs and money circulating. Typically they have drifted into drug trading as their own consumption has opened up increasing opportunities to supply friends and social networks. Nevertheless, despite the haphazard way in which these careers often begin, Ward emphasizes that these friendship groups are simultaneously both social and highly networked economic distribution systems (p. 106).</p>
<p>Pen portraits are provided of the main characters in the tradition of Whyte. Good social ethnography begins to function almost as a novel in that our curiosity is aroused about the eventual outcomes for its subjects and the final chapter (chapter eight) acknowledges this. The reader is tempted to wonder whether Ward rather glosses over the health and behavioural problems that some of her characters are likely to experience in the future, or indeed were already reporting during the study. She is anxious to emphasize that in the main her subjects were able to manage their drug styles and to combine them with paid work, including professional careers and full-time university study (p. 67). This is in accord with the theoretical framework within which her data is organized, the shifting and flexible identities of the late-modern world, but the reader cannot help but also notice the references to alcohol-related pancreatitis, mental health issues, relationship breakdowns and difficulties at work. And it is here that perhaps some greater consideration of social structure might have been warranted. Ward convincingly demonstrates through the richness of the detail of her field work the variety of backgrounds of her subjects, from semi-skilled office workers to professionals and medical students. At this point, differences in material and cultural resources are not particularly important in determining the drug styles and cultural patterns of her subjects. But, on the other hand, in her very illuminating account of the struggles experienced by those seeking to find a way out from lives dependent upon drug dealing as well as drug consumption, it is those with the most in the way of material and cultural resources that seem to be most successful in navigating their escape routes. The City professionals and medical students had sufficient material resources to evade the danger of falling back into dealing; those without such opportunities appeared to be more likely to slide back into dealing in the absence of alternative sources of income. Ward notes these differences in outcome, and also includes a thoughtful chapter on the opportunities for women in a world still sometimes understood to be highly gendered, but she is not inclined to elaborate the discussion in terms of how these characters negotiated the social structures that in important respects did still allocate possibilities and constraints through patterns of systemic inequality.</p>
<p>This is a fine study and the investment in ethnographic research over a period of five years in the field yields a rich dividend in data and valuable insight. The theoretical framework employed relates the data to other contemporary approaches to recreational drug consumption in thoughtful and illuminating ways. The energy generated through the adoption of Thatcherite entrepreneurial values is evaluated very well and, as Ward suggests, there are important insights to be gained from examining the ‘business end’ of the dance and rave phenomenon. There is some comfort in finding that the great Thatcherite project of re-moralization produced the vibrancy of rave as well as the greed of the City. One disappointment is the absence of any discussion of the methodology employed. It would have been very interesting to find out a little more about the practical and ethical issues associated with the field work but sadly one suspects that, in contrast to Whyte’s day, publishers now rarely tolerate extended methodological discussions.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1741659011435404">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giddens</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Modernity and Self-Identity: Self and Society in the Late Modern Age</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1741659011435404">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammersley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ditton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Ecstasy and the Rise of the Chemical Generation</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1741659011435404">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Measham</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brain</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>‘Binge’ drinking, British alcohol policy and the new culture of intoxication</article-title>. <source>Crime Media Culture</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1741659011435404">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Measham</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Dancing on Drugs: Risk, Health and Hedonism in the British Club Scene</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Association Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1741659011435404">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1943</year>) <source>Street Corner Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>