<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcrw</journal-id>
<journal-title>Community College Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0091-5521</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1940-2325</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0091552112454914</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0091552112454914</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Stability of Educational Expectations Among Baccalaureate Aspirants Beginning at Community Colleges</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xueli</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0091552112454914">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0091552112454914"><label>1</label>University of Wisconsin–Madison, Madison, WI, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0091552112454914">Xueli Wang, Assistant Professor, Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Analysis, University of Wisconsin–Madison, 270-H Education Building, 1000 Bascom Mall, Madison, WI 53706, USA Email: <email>xwang273@wisc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>300</fpage>
<lpage>319</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">North Carolina State University</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Using data from the Education Longitudinal Study of 2002, this study explored factors that predict stability of educational expectations among baccalaureate aspirants beginning at community colleges. Based on a nationally representative sample of baccalaureate-aspiring high school seniors of 2004 who entered community colleges as their first postsecondary institutions, this study tested a logistic regression model and found that among precollege characteristics, students’ SES and perceived importance of getting a good education were positively related to the likelihood of retaining baccalaureate expectations 2 years after high school graduation. Among postsecondary predictors, the likelihood of students’ persistence in baccalaureate expectations was positively influenced by interaction with faculty members outside of class and studying in school libraries, but was negatively associated with having reading remediation, receiving financial aid, and being married. These findings have implications for community colleges in providing effective educational practices to help students move forward toward their degree goals.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>bachelor’s degrees</kwd>
<kwd>educational aspirations</kwd>
<kwd>first-time students</kwd>
<kwd>longitudinal studies</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0091552112454914" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>For most high school graduates, participation in postsecondary education represents one of the most viable pathways to economic and social success. In particular, completing more postsecondary education, such as attaining a bachelor’s degree, not only improves earning capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0091552112454914">Pascarella &amp; Terenzini, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0091552112454914">2005</xref>), but also leads to greater social and economic benefits for society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0091552112454914">Swail, 2004</xref>). Given the returns of postsecondary participation and completion, it is not surprising that empirical efforts in higher education research have largely focused on finding the plethora of factors that lead to successful completion of a postsecondary credential, particularly a baccalaureate degree.</p>
<p>With rising college tuitions, community colleges increasingly serve as the entry point into higher education for many socioeconomically disadvantaged students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0091552112454914">Wang, 2012</xref>). Moreover, for many of these students, access to community colleges represents an alternative route to the bachelor’s degree or higher: A large number of students enter community colleges with the hope of transferring to a 4-year institution to complete a baccalaureate degree. For example, it is estimated that among the high school graduates of 1992 who first enrolled in public 2-year colleges, nearly two thirds were seeking a bachelor’s degree or above (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0091552112454914">Hoachlander, Sikora, Horn, &amp; Carroll, 2003</xref>). Based on more recent national data, the proportion of baccalaureate aspirants at community colleges is close to four-fifths (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0091552112454914">Bailey &amp; Morest, 2006</xref>). However, although community colleges have helped promote access to postsecondary education among underprivileged students over the past century, access does not guarantee persistence and completion in congruence with students’ educational expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0091552112454914">Heller, 1997</xref>). For baccalaureate aspirants starting at community colleges, persisting in their educational expectations is what really matters in completing a baccalaureate degree.</p>
<p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0091552112454914">Rubinson (1986)</xref> argued, although social class plays a major role in student achievement and attainment levels, “[t]here is little formal stratification in the U.S. national system, compared with other countries where formal rules stratify schooling into different status streams” (p. 521). In this sense, students’ educational expectations are not structurally determined or constrained, and the transfer function of community colleges has long been understood to promote educational upward mobility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0091552112454914">Laanan, 2001</xref>). On the other hand, there has been a perennial debate about whether community colleges function as a democratizing force in higher education or as a mechanism that perpetuates social inequality and results in a “cooling out” of students’ baccalaureate dreams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0091552112454914">Dougherty, 1994</xref>). However, this debate has not yet produced much systematic, longitudinal examination of the relationship between the community college experiences of baccalaureate-aspiring students and the stability of their educational expectations.</p>
<p>Indeed, educational expectations are one of the most critical predictors of educational attainment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0091552112454914">Allen, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0091552112454914">Astin, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0091552112454914">Carter, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0091552112454914">Duncan, Featherman, &amp; Duncan, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0091552112454914">Epps, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0091552112454914">Pascarella &amp; Terenzini, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0091552112454914">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0091552112454914">Sewell, Haller, &amp; Ohlendorf, 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0091552112454914">Sewell, Haller, &amp; Portes, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0091552112454914">Sewell, Hauser, &amp; Wolf, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0091552112454914">Teachman, 1987</xref>). Exerting both direct and indirect effects on educational attainment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0091552112454914">McCormick, 1997</xref>), students’ commitment to their educational expectations and goals is a central element in models of postsecondary persistence and attainment (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0091552112454914">Pascarella &amp; Chapman, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0091552112454914">Tinto, 1975</xref>). The pivotal role of educational expectations in shaping attainment thus warrants particular empirical focus in its own right. Although factors influencing educational expectations or their stability have received considerable attention, most of the interest is at the secondary level, and research that addresses college students has predominantly concerned those beginning at 4-year institutions. Not enough focus has been placed on community college students, especially baccalaureate-aspiring high school graduates who attend community colleges as their first postsecondary institutions.</p>
<p>This study explores factors predicting the stability of educational expectations among recent baccalaureate-aspiring high school graduates attending community colleges as their first postsecondary schools. This study is important in several aspects. First, focusing on community college students, the study moves beyond prior research on educational expectations that has largely concentrated on high school students or students attending 4-year institutions. In addition, as baccalaureate-aspiring students increasingly seek entry into the postsecondary world through community colleges, what influences these students to hold on to their baccalaureate dreams or to lower their expectations needs to be better understood. Toward that end, this study conceptualizes various individual and college factors underlying the stability of these students’ educational expectations. In particular, this study gives attention to the effect of students’ first-year experiences at community colleges on the stability of baccalaureate expectations. The results of this study not only add to the literature on community college students’ educational expectations and associated factors, but also are relevant for educators of community colleges in understanding the relationships between student characteristics, community college practices, and stability of educational expectations. This knowledge will help design programs and services to assist students in fulfilling their educational expectations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0091552112454914">
<title>Review of the Literature</title>
<p>The following includes a review of the literature on community college students’ educational expectations. The review also highlights several important theoretical perspectives on educational expectations and aspirations, and it provides the conceptual underpinning that guides this study. Although two distinct constructs, <italic>educational expectations</italic> and <italic>educational aspirations</italic> are often used interchangeably in the literature. Educational expectations refer to what students think will happen in terms of their educational attainment when taking into account external constraints (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0091552112454914">Museus &amp; Hendel, 2005</xref>), and educational aspirations refer to how far students hope to advance in their education in the absence of external constraints (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0091552112454914">Hauser &amp; Anderson, 1991</xref>). Meanwhile, educational aspirations and their underlying social constraints are central components of students’ educational expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0091552112454914">Museus, Harper, &amp; Nichols, 2010</xref>), thus making these two constructs often indistinguishable. This review of the literature addresses both aspirations and expectations and, for the most part, uses <italic>educational expectations</italic> for the sake of consistency.</p>
<sec id="section3-0091552112454914">
<title>Community College Students’ Educational Expectations</title>
<p>Since its inception in the early years of the 20th century, the community college sector has expanded dramatically to become a comprehensive and multifaceted postsecondary educational system, serving an increasing number of students with diverse backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0091552112454914">Cohen &amp; Brawer, 2008</xref>). Although commended for democratizing higher education and helping students achieve realistic academic and occupational goals, community colleges are also often criticized for serving as a device that perpetuates social inequality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0091552112454914">Dougherty, 1994</xref>). The major argument in support of this criticism has been that attending community colleges has an adverse effect on student educational expectations by diverting students from baccalaureate-granting institutions and eventually from completing a bachelor’s degree. In his seminal paper, “The ‘Cooling-Out’ Function in Higher Education,” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0091552112454914">Burton Clark (1960)</xref> maintained that junior colleges channeled students whose academic expectations were deemed exceeding their abilities out of transfer programs and into terminal degree programs; he termed this the <italic>cooling-out process</italic>.</p>
<p>A small number of studies have explicitly examined how community college attendance affects students’ educational expectations. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0091552112454914">Pascarella, Edison, Nora, Hagedorn, and Terenzini (1998)</xref> studied students attending 18 four-year institutions and five community colleges and found that after 2 years of college, baccalaureate aspirants attending community colleges were 20% to 30% more likely than their 4-year counterparts to have reduced their baccalaureate expectations. Similar findings were revealed in other studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0091552112454914">Carter, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0091552112454914">McCormick, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0091552112454914">1997</xref>). In particular, based on the High School and Beyond study of seniors graduating in 1980, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0091552112454914">McCormick (1997)</xref> found that among students beginning at community colleges, the odds of reporting baccalaureate expectations after 2 years were 40% lower than students starting at 4-year institutions and about 60% lower after 4 years. Using 4-year institutions as a comparison group, these earlier studies point to the same level of disadvantage in regard to degree expectations experienced by students attending community colleges compared to their counterparts who begin at 4-year institutions. In this way, these studies seem to support the cooling-out argument on the relationship between attending community colleges and changes in educational expectations.</p>
<p>However, a change of reference point may present the issue of educational expectations within a broader context. Instead of focusing narrowly on the contrast between students at 2-year and 4-year colleges, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0091552112454914">Swanson (2002)</xref> used data from the High School and Beyond Study (HS&amp;B:80) and the Beginning Postsecondary Student Survey (BPS:90/94) to compare four postsecondary enrollment patterns: not enrolled, enrolled in a less-than–2-year institution, enrolled in a community college, and enrolled in a 4-year institution. Swanson found that attending community colleges seemed to “warm” educational expectations compared to not enrolling in postsecondary schools or attending a vocational or proprietary institution, although this effect was not as strong as that of attending 4-year institutions. This pattern has been confirmed by at least two recent studies. For example, based on a sample of predominantly low-income, mainly African American high school graduates, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0091552112454914">Alexander, Bozick, and Entwisle (2008)</xref> found that community college students did not experience a significant decrease in expectations once in college compared to other students. Taking into account background factors, community college attendance was associated more with increased educational expectations. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0091552112454914">Leigh and Gill (2004)</xref> found that attending community colleges led to a substantial increase in educational expectations of students, controlling for student family backgrounds and race and ethnicity.</p>
<p>Although these studies have generated a rich literature with reference to the impact of levels of institutions (2-year vs. 4-year, for example) on educational expectations, still very little is known in regard to how internal workings of these institutions influence educational expectations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0091552112454914">Pascarella and Terenzini (2005)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0091552112454914">Swanson (2002)</xref> all argued that research should move beyond the generic institutional traits and examine in detail what affects changes in educational expectations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0091552112454914">Pascarella (1984)</xref> also pointed out that in order to adequately assess the institutional influence on students’ educational expectations, it may be necessary to focus on differences among students’ actual experiences as well as the intensity and scope of their involvement during college.</p>
<p>As one of the scant examples of research examining factors related to educational expectations of community college students, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0091552112454914">Laanan (2003)</xref> investigated the relationship between internal and external factors and the educational expectations of 2-year college students upon postsecondary entrance; he found that a number of demographic variables, high school academic experiences, and personal goals were associated with educational expectations. Although this represents an important step toward understanding what influences community college students’ educational expectations, more empirical research is needed in addressing the various factors that undergird the stability of students’ educational expectations over time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0091552112454914">
<title>Theoretical Perspectives on Educational Expectations</title>
<p>Multiple theoretical frameworks are instrumental in studying the development of educational expectations. One of the most prominent is the status attainment model (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0091552112454914">Barr &amp; Dreeben, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0091552112454914">Sewell et al., 1970</xref>). According to the status attainment model, socioeconomic status (SES) is strongly and positively related to educational expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0091552112454914">Barr &amp; Dreeben, 1983</xref>). Specifically, family income, parental social status and education, as well as the provision of academic experiences largely shape educational expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0091552112454914">Mau, 1995</xref>). Because the process of transmitting socioeconomic advantage (or disadvantage) from generation to generation is longitudinal, it is reasonable to assume that the status attainment model not only helps in understanding educational expectations measured at one point in time, but may also shed light on studying stability of educational expectations over time.</p>
<p>Social capital (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0091552112454914">Coleman, 1988</xref>) represents another viable theoretical lens for studying educational expectations. According to the social capital theory, students receive information, values, and expectations for education through interpersonal relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0091552112454914">Coleman, 1988</xref>), and these interpersonal networks provide useful resources in a variety of social contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0091552112454914">Tierney &amp; Venegas, 2006</xref>). Although the status attainment model largely emphasizes student socioeconomic background, social capital development considered in the postsecondary context may add more explanatory power to studies of educational expectations by adding the influences of postsecondary socialization sources (such as faculty members and academic advisors) on the stability of students’ educational expectations.</p>
<p>Although both the status attainment model and social capital theory have received a large amount of empirical validation in studies of secondary students’ educational expectations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0091552112454914">Domina, Conley, &amp; Farkas, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0091552112454914">Jencks, Crouse, &amp; Mueser, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0091552112454914">Sewell et al., 1970</xref>), these two theoretical perspectives are not without their limitations when applied to the study of educational expectations at the postsecondary level. One such limitation is that they both neglect the importance of other influences, such as the behaviors of students as more independent young adults and their exposure to more diverse educational practices in postsecondary education. Part of this limitation can be addressed by utilizing the social cognitive career theory. Rooted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0091552112454914">Bandura’s (1986)</xref> general social cognitive theory, the social cognitive career theory underscores the interrelationship among individual, environmental, and behavioral variables that are assumed to affect academic and career development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0091552112454914">Lent &amp; Brown, 2006</xref>). The emphasis of social cognitive career theory on the relationship between outcome expectations and environmental supports and barriers is particularly relevant for understanding influences on the stability of students’ educational expectations: After baccalaureate aspirants begin their college career at community colleges, they will negotiate a set of academic, social, financial, and personal demands. The outcome of this transition process may present either barriers or supports, thus impacting students’ persistence in their academic goals.</p>
<p>Most of the studies that employ one or more of these theoretical perspectives in examining educational expectations focus on students at the secondary level. Very few studies have looked at community college students who aspire to a bachelor’s degree or higher, determining how their baccalaureate expectations are affected by various precollege and college characteristics and experiences. Given that educational expectations are not stable and change over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0091552112454914">Ingels, Curtin, Kaufman, Alt, &amp; Chen, 2002</xref>) and that community colleges increasingly serve as an alternative route to the bachelor’s degree, it is pivotal to understand what affects the stability of educational expectations among baccalaureate aspirants beginning at community colleges.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0091552112454914">
<title>Conceptual Framework</title>
<p>This study’s conceptual framework is informed by existing literature and previously discussed conceptual lenses. The stability of the educational expectations of baccalaureate-aspiring community college entrants is presumed to be influenced by theoretically grounded precollege and postsecondary factors, including students’ experiences at community colleges. Among precollege variables are the students’ sociodemographic background and the perceived importance of getting a good education. As students transition into postsecondary education, the framework necessarily includes postsecondary experiences and relevant aspects of family life and employment. Characteristics and experiences in all these domains are posited to influence baccalaureate aspirants to sustain their educational expectations or to lower their expectations to less than a bachelor’s degree.</p>
<p>Guided by the conceptual framework, this study analyzes a nationally representative sample of over 2,000 baccalaureate-aspiring high school graduates who attended community colleges as their first postsecondary institutions. The study answers the following research question: How do baccalaureate-aspiring students’ precollege characteristics, experiences at community colleges, and external demands affect the stability of their educational expectations 2 years after high school graduation?</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0091552112454914" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section7-0091552112454914">
<title>Data Source and Sample</title>
<p>This study is based on data from the first and second follow-up of the Education Longitudinal Study of 2002 (ELS:2002), which was designed to study the transition of young people from high school into postsecondary education and the workplace. ELS:2002 started with a nationally representative cohort of high school sophomores. The sample was then augmented in the 2004 first follow-up study to represent high school seniors. In 2006, roughly 2 years after high school, the second follow-up study collected data about access to postsecondary institutions, students’ choices of enrollment, and other aspects of their college experience. Educational expectations were measured in both the 2004 and 2006 waves of data collection in the ELS study.</p>
<p>The study reported in this article focuses on the spring 2004 high school seniors who participated in the second follow-up interview in 2006 and who had enrolled in a community college as their first postsecondary institution within 2 years of high school graduation. Of approximately 12,500 members of the 2004 senior cohort who responded to the second follow-up interview, about 3,400 students attended community colleges as their first true postsecondary institutions. Given the purpose of this study, I retained roughly 2,100 community college entrants who, when they were high school seniors, indicated that they expected to earn a bachelor’s degree or above. All analyses were weighted using the appropriate panel weight (F2F1WT) and therefore generalize to the population of spring 2004 high school graduates who began postsecondary education at a community college and who expected to earn a bachelor’s degree or above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0091552112454914">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>Because this study is interested in what influences baccalaureate-aspiring students to hold on to their baccalaureate degree goals after enrolling in community colleges, the dependent variable, stability of educational expectations, is a binary variable coded 1 if in 2006 the student still expected to earn a bachelor’s degree or above and 0 if the student’s expectations had been reduced to less than a bachelor’s degree. This variable was derived from the survey item pertaining to students’ educational expectations measured in 2006, 2 years after high school graduation.</p>
<p>Guided by the conceptual framework, this study includes independent variables in the following areas: sociodemographic background, perceived importance of education, student experiences at community college, and external demands. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0091552112454914">Table 1</xref> provides a detailed description of each variable.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0091552112454914" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Variable Definitions and Descriptive Statistics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0091552112454914" xlink:href="10.1177_0091552112454914-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Mean (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center">Definition</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Stability of educational expectation</td>
<td>.813 (.391)</td>
<td>Binary variable measuring stability of educational expectations: 1 = <italic>educational expectations remaining baccalaureate and above</italic>; 0 = <italic>educational expectations reduced to less than a bachelor’s degree</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female</td>
<td>.560 (.496)</td>
<td>Binary variable: 1 = <italic>female</italic>, 0 = <italic>male</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Race/ethnicity</td>
<td/>
<td>A series of dummy variables with White as the reference category</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>.120 (.325)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>.081 (.272)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian</td>
<td>.116 (.320)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>.092 (.289)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Socioeconomic status</td>
<td>2.58 (1.056)</td>
<td>First follow-up measure of socioeconomic status: 1 = <italic>lowest quartile</italic>, 2 = <italic>second quartile</italic>, 3 = <italic>third quartile</italic>, 4 = <italic>highest quartile</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perceived importance of getting a good education</td>
<td>2.92 (.290)</td>
<td>A single-item construct that measures students’ perceived importance of education: 1 = <italic>not important</italic>, 2 = <italic>somewhat important</italic>, 3 = <italic>very important</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interaction with faculty members</td>
<td>1.92 (.677)</td>
<td>Talk with faculty about academic matters outside of class: 1 = <italic>never</italic>, 2 = <italic>sometimes</italic>, 3 = <italic>often</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interaction with advisors</td>
<td>1.96 (.685)</td>
<td>Meet with advisor about academic plans: 1 = <italic>never</italic>, 2 = <italic>sometimes</italic>, 3 = <italic>often</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Study at school libraries</td>
<td>2.08 (.752)</td>
<td>Work on coursework at school library: 1 = <italic>never</italic>, 2 = <italic>sometimes</italic>, 3 = <italic>often</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social involvement</td>
<td>1.44 (.678)</td>
<td>Participate in extracurricular activities: 1 = <italic>never</italic>, 2 = <italic>sometimes</italic>, 3 = <italic>often</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reading remediation</td>
<td>.26 (.426)</td>
<td>Took remedial course to improve reading skills: 1 = <italic>yes</italic>, 0 = <italic>no</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Writing remediation</td>
<td>.29 (.456)</td>
<td>Took remedial course to improve writing skills: 1 = <italic>yes</italic>, 0 = <italic>no</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Math remediation</td>
<td>.39 (.487)</td>
<td>Took remedial course to improve math skills: 1 = <italic>yes</italic>, 0 = <italic>no</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Enrollment intensity</td>
<td>.752 (.432)</td>
<td>Intensity of enrollment at community colleges: 1 = <italic>full-time</italic>, 0 = <italic>less than full-time</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Financial aid receipt</td>
<td>.425 (.494)</td>
<td>Whether offered financial aid during the 1st year at community colleges: 1 = <italic>yes</italic>, 0 = <italic>no</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Marital status</td>
<td>.03 (.179)</td>
<td>Whether the respondent is married: 1 = <italic>yes</italic>, 0 = <italic>no</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Parental status</td>
<td>.09 (.280)</td>
<td>Whether the respondent has child or children: 1 = <italic>yes</italic>, 0 = <italic>no</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hours of work</td>
<td>9.862 (12.393)</td>
<td>Number of hours the respondent worked per week during the first two years of college</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0091552112454914">
<p>Note: Statistics are based on the restricted-use data from the first and second follow-up studies of ELS:2002.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0091552112454914">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>I chose binomial logistic regression to explore the research question because it is the appropriate form of regression analysis, given the dichotomous nature of this study’s dependent variable. Logistic regression can handle predictor variables that are categorical, ordinal, or continuous, as in the present study. The full logistic regression model can be expressed as follows:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0091552112454914">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0091552112454914">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>log</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext>
<mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext>
<mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0091552112454914" xlink:href="10.1177_0091552112454914-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where φ<sub>i</sub> is the log odds of expecting to earn at least a bachelor’s degree in 2006, and P<sub>i</sub> is the probability of this binomial outcome (1 = persisted in baccalaureate expectations). In this model, <italic>D</italic><sub>i</sub> is a vector of precollege sociodemographic characteristics, <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> is a vector of postsecondary variables during community colleges, and <italic>E</italic><sub>i</sub> is a vector of environmental variables that measure external demands. The α term is a constant, and βs are regression coefficients.</p>
<p>In addition to regression coefficients, I reported odds ratios for significant effects, facilitating the interpretation of the results. Odds ratios provide an alternative method of describing the impact of a particular predictor on the outcome in terms of odds. An odds ratio of one implies that the predictor has no effect on the odds of the outcome occurring. Odds ratios greater than one indicate that the odds of the outcome occurring tend to increase as the predictor increases by one unit. Conversely, when odds ratios are less than one, they indicate that the odds of the outcome occurring tend to decrease as the predictor increases by one unit, holding all other variables constant. Furthermore, in order to more intuitively compare the relative effects of odds ratios greater than one to those less than one, I followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0091552112454914">DesJardins (2001)</xref> and reported the inverse odds ratios for statistically significant, negatively related coefficients. An inverse odds ratio is obtained by taking the inverse of the normally produced odds ratio when estimated coefficients are negative. In addition, the reference group should be reversed when interpreting an inverse odds ratio.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0091552112454914">
<title>Missing Data and Adjustment for Design Effects</title>
<p>As inherent with survey research, the ELS:2002 study is characterized with missing data due to survey item nonresponse. To handle missing data, I employed multiple imputation techniques to generate five different data sets with imputed values. Compared to listwise deletion, multiple imputation has the advantage of retaining cases with incomplete information while also accounting for the uncertainty intrinsic in imputing missing values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0091552112454914">Rubin, 1987</xref>). I estimated the logistic regression model using Stata’s survey commands that adjust for the complex survey design effects associated with ELS:2002. Subcommands in Stata can average the logistic regression coefficients and standard errors from analyses across the five imputed data sets.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0091552112454914">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>The primary limitation of this study is that it draws on data from a study that followed students only two years after high school (2004-2006). This relatively brief time window of ELS:2002 limits the study’s ability to fully explore the long-term development of educational expectations and the lasting impact of their various underlying precollege and community college factors. Another limitation of the study is that given its emphasis on baccalaureate aspirants who resort to community colleges as an alternative route to their degree goals, only recent high school graduates who aspired to earn a bachelor’s degree when they were high school seniors were included in the study. Also, because ELS:2002 is a longitudinal study of a particular high school cohort, it does not include older students who attend community colleges and who may also expect to earn a bachelor’s degree eventually. These restrictions prohibit the researcher from making claims of generalizability to the population of all community college entrants. In addition, several independent variables used in the study (e.g., interaction with faculty, interaction with advisors, and social involvement) are based on single survey items due to the fact that ELS:2002 does not contain multiple survey items measuring each of these constructs. Although these available single items represent proxies for several important aspects of community college students’ academic experience, future research may benefit from using instruments that employ multiple items measuring these complex constructs in a valid and reliable way. Despite these limitations, ELS:2002 is an appropriate data set for this study given its focus on the transition from high school to postsecondary education, the longitudinal measures of educational expectations, and the rich information on student precollege characteristics and first-year experiences at community colleges.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0091552112454914" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion of the Findings</title>
<p>Using a set of theoretically grounded predictor variables, I estimated a logistic regression model to predict the stability of educational expectations in 2006 (holding onto educational expectations of at least a bachelor’s degree versus expecting less than a bachelor’s degree) among baccalaureate aspirants entering community colleges. Weighted descriptive statistics of the outcome variable suggest that among the high school graduates of 2004 entering community colleges with the expectation of earning at least a bachelor’s degree, 81.3% held on to their original expectations 2 years later, while 18.7% lowered their educational expectations to less than a bachelor’s degree. Considering that the sample consists of baccalaureate aspirants only, the high percentage of students expecting a bachelor’s degree 2 years later is not surprising, because prior educational expectations are one of the strongest predictors of subsequent educational expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0091552112454914">Camburn, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0091552112454914">Carter, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0091552112454914">Pascarella &amp; Terenzini, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0091552112454914">2005</xref>). However, roughly one fifth of the initial baccalaureate aspirants did experience a decrease of their educational expectations. In the following sections, I explain this variation based on the logistic regression results. (For detailed information on the logistic regression analysis results, refer to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0091552112454914">Table 2</xref>.)</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0091552112454914" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression Parameter Estimates: Stability of Baccalaureate Expectations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0091552112454914" xlink:href="10.1177_0091552112454914-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Independent variables</th>
<th align="center"><italic>b</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">Odds ratio</th>
<th align="center">Inverse odds ratio</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Precollege</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>–.184</td>
<td>.140</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>.142</td>
<td>.213</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>.195</td>
<td>.236</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian</td>
<td>.356</td>
<td>.252</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>.178</td>
<td>.275</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> SES</td>
<td>.232<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">***</xref></td>
<td>.068</td>
<td>1.262</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Perceived importance of education</td>
<td>.499<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">**</xref></td>
<td>.215</td>
<td>1.647</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Postsecondary</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Interaction with faculty members</td>
<td>.175<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">*</xref></td>
<td>.094</td>
<td>1.192</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Interaction with advisors</td>
<td>.132</td>
<td>.106</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Study at school libraries</td>
<td>.162<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">*</xref></td>
<td>.094</td>
<td>1.175</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Social involvement</td>
<td>–.039</td>
<td>.101</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Reading remediation</td>
<td>–.371<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">*</xref></td>
<td>.212</td>
<td>.690</td>
<td>1.449</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Writing remediation</td>
<td>.104</td>
<td>.217</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Math remediation</td>
<td>–.200</td>
<td>.164</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Enrollment intensity</td>
<td>–.016</td>
<td>.154</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Financial aid receipt</td>
<td>–.251<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">**</xref></td>
<td>.127</td>
<td>.778</td>
<td>1.285</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">External demands</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Marital status</td>
<td>–1.006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0091552112454914">***</xref></td>
<td>.371</td>
<td>.366</td>
<td>2.732</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Parental status</td>
<td>.377</td>
<td>.274</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hours of work</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>.005</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0091552112454914">
<p>Note: Results are based on the restricted-use data from the first and second follow-up studies of ELS:2002.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0091552112454914">
<p>Odds ratios are reported only for statistically significant coefficients. Inverse odds ratios are reported only for statistically significant coefficients with negative values.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0091552112454914">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0091552112454914">Table 2</xref>, two precollege variables were significantly related to whether students held steady with their original baccalaureate expectations: SES and perceived importance of getting a good education. Specifically, controlling for other independent variables in the model, students with higher socioeconomic status had higher odds of persisting in their expectations than students with lower socioeconomic status. For every one quartile increase in SES, the odds that the student retained the original expectation increased by 26.2%, when other variables in the model were held constant. The odds of remaining a baccalaureate expectant increased by 64.7% as students attached more importance to getting a good education. It should be noted that in ELS:2002, SES is a composite measure that took into account parental education, occupation, and income. This finding resonates with existing literature that indicates that educational expectations are affected by family income and parental education (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0091552112454914">Cheng &amp; Starks, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0091552112454914">Lowman &amp; Elliott, 2010</xref>). This relationship between SES and stability of expectations can also be explained by the status attainment model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0091552112454914">Sewell et al., 1969</xref>) that highlights the intergenerational transmission of socioeconomic status reflected in educational expectations. Despite their baccalaureate dreams, students from lower socioeconomic backgrounds entering community colleges had higher odds of lowering their degree expectations than their counterparts from families of more favorable socioeconomic status. Other demographic variables in the model, namely gender and race/ethnicity, however, exerted no significant effects on the stability of students’ educational expectations. The relationship between SES and educational expectations pinpoints the fact that although community colleges have opened the door to high school graduates aspiring to earn a bachelor’s degree or above, sorting based on class within community colleges still seems to negatively affect students from more disadvantaged social backgrounds, regardless of gender and race/ethnicity and in spite of students’ initial aspirations to advance beyond a community college education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0091552112454914">Wang, 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>The relationship between perceived importance of getting a good education and the probability of retaining original educational expectations indicates that students who attach great importance to education are more likely to hold on to their long-term educational goals than those who do not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0091552112454914">Wang, 2009</xref>). This relationship can be explained by expectancy-value theory that stipulates that the subjective value individuals attach to an activity, along with their perceived probability of success, largely influences their persistence in the activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0091552112454914">Bandura, 1997</xref>). The results from this study reiterate the importance of value: Those students who value education may be more motivated to follow their ultimate educational goal (a bachelor’s degree or higher). Consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0091552112454914">Wang (2009)</xref>, this finding may suggest that those 12th-grade baccalaureate aspirants with a stronger intrinsic value attached to getting a good education may sustain a stronger commitment toward a bachelor’s degree while attending community colleges.</p>
<p>Four variables measuring community college experiences emerged as significant predictors of stability of baccalaureate expectations: interaction with faculty members outside of class for academic matters, studying at school libraries, reading remediation, and receipt of financial aid. Controlling for other predictors in the model, the more frequently students talked with faculty members about academic matters outside of class, the more likely they held on to their baccalaureate expectations. For each 1-point increase on the student-faculty interaction scale (ranging from 1 to 3, with higher scores reflecting more frequent interaction), the odds that students persisted in their expectations were estimated to increase by 19.2%. Although numerous studies have shown that student-faculty interaction leads to positive educational experiences and promotes desirable educational outcomes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0091552112454914">Kuh &amp; Hu, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0091552112454914">Pascarella &amp; Terenzini, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0091552112454914">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0091552112454914">Reason, Terenzini, &amp; Domingo, 2007</xref>), most of the research in this vein has focused on students attending 4-year institutions. On the other hand, the limited literature on community college students reveals generally low levels of interaction between students and faculty members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0091552112454914">Chang, 2005</xref>). Given the fact that community colleges are predominately commuter campuses and that the percentage of part-time faculty members at community colleges has reached an average of 70% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0091552112454914">Jaeger, 2008</xref>), it is not surprising that student-faculty interactions are limited and that most of these interactions occur in the classroom. This study shows that when interaction with faculty members does occur outside of the classroom, it proves beneficial for community college students, helping them to persist in their baccalaureate expectations. It should be noted that the population of this study consists of recent high school graduates who aspire to earn a bachelor’s degree. This pattern of student-faculty interaction outside of the classroom might not hold true among nontraditional-age students attending community colleges with different educational and professional goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0091552112454914">Dougherty &amp; Kienzl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0091552112454914">Peter &amp; Forrest Cataldi, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The findings also indicate that the frequency of studying in a school library was positively related to the stability of community college students’ baccalaureate expectations. The odds of being committed to baccalaureate expectations increased by 17.5% for a 1-point increase on the scale that measured studying at school libraries. Limited prior research has suggested that student use of school libraries often indicates high levels of student engagement in other important educationally valuable activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0091552112454914">Laird &amp; Kuh, 2005</xref>). A community college student who spends more time studying in the library may well be engaged in various other aspects of his or her college experience and stand a greater chance of persisting in his or her degree expectations. In addition, because library use is also related to the quality of academic experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0091552112454914">Kuh &amp; Gonyea, 2003</xref>), students who study in the library more frequently are likely to have a high-quality academic experience that reinforces their expectations to receive a bachelor’s degree.</p>
<p>Taking remedial courses in reading was negatively associated with the likelihood of persisting in educational expectations. Students who had remediation in reading were only .690 times as likely to remain baccalaureate expectants compared to students who did not take remedial courses in reading. In other words, students who had remediation in reading were significantly less likely to retain their educational expectations compared to their counterparts who did not have remediation in reading. For students beginning at community colleges, taking remediation in reading suggests low reading competency. The importance of college-level reading in college success has been highlighted by previous research, suggesting that the leading predictor of dropping out of college is the need for remedial reading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0091552112454914">National Center for Education Statistics, 2004</xref>). Community college students who are underprepared for college-level reading and therefore need reading remediation may struggle with reading assignments in key subjects such as math, science, and English. As a result, they may become less confident in their baccalaureate plans and lower their educational expectations.</p>
<p>For students receiving financial aid, the odds that they retained their educational expectations was .778 times that for students who did not receive financial aid. Put in a different way, students who received financial aid were less likely to persist in their educational expectations than students who did not receive financial aid. It should be noted that the negative effect of financial aid on stability of expectations may have more complex implications than suggesting that financial aid is ineffective in helping community college students sustain their baccalaureate expectations. Typically, students who are eligible to receive financial aid are low-income, disadvantaged students. Because financial aid eligibility and receipt of aid are unlikely to be independent of factors that also influence college persistence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0091552112454914">Alon, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0091552112454914">DesJardins, Ahlburg, &amp; McCall, 2006</xref>), it may be that factors associated with receiving financial aid, such as low SES, instead of financial aid itself, are at work in negatively affecting the stability of educational expectations.</p>
<p>Students who were married were less likely to retain their baccalaureate expectations compared to students who were not married. Previous research shows that although social support from families and friends improves adjustment to college, support from students’ spouses is not associated with improved college adjustment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0091552112454914">Meehan &amp; Negy, 2003</xref>). Research on college persistence suggests that a number of environmental pull factors, including family responsibilities, will pull students away from the college environment and affect students’ tenacity to continue with their education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0091552112454914">Nora &amp; Wedham, 1991</xref>). Married community college students may experience more pull factors that result from their multiple relationship dimensions and have more difficulties adjusting to the demands of postsecondary education relative to unmarried students, thus lowering their educational expectations.</p>
<sec id="section13-0091552112454914">
<title>Implications and Conclusions</title>
<p>This study focuses on community college entrants who aspire to a bachelor’s degree or higher, a student subpopulation largely neglected in the research literature. Previous research on the educational outcomes of community college students tends to focus on a comparison between students who begin at community colleges and those who attend 4-year institutions. The studies in this stream have consistently proved the relatively lower attainment of community college attendees from various approaches. The very knowledge of the fact that community college students fare less well than their 4-year counterparts represents the mere first step toward solving the problems surrounding this educational inequity. It is high time for empirical research in higher education to shift focus from the between-group differences to within-group variations among community college students to uncover the mechanisms that underlie their educational success. By placing the emphasis on the within-group differences among baccalaureate-aspiring community college students, researchers can develop a more adequate understanding of factors that may help reduce this educational inequity that has been well documented in existing literature. Focusing on baccalaureate aspirants who access postsecondary education through community colleges, this study centers on the bachelor’s degree-seeking community college beginners and examines within this group various factors related to the stability of their educational expectations. The results of this study show that baccalaureate aspirants who are least likely to persist in their educational expectations are those from disadvantaged socioeconomic backgrounds as well as those who attached less importance to getting a good education, spent less time interacting with faculty members and studying in school libraries, took reading remediation, received financial aid, and were married.</p>
<p>These findings are useful information for community colleges in providing effective educational practices to help students move toward their degree goals. For example, the positive relationship between student-faculty interaction outside of class and stability of educational expectations pinpoints the importance of improving practice that allows community college faculty members—who are at the heart of community colleges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0091552112454914">McArthur, 2005</xref>)—to fully explore their potential to contribute to student success. Also, the positive relationship between library use and stability of expectations is consistent with another empirical study that highlights the vital supporting role of school libraries in helping the institution achieve its academic mission and helping the institution’s students achieve their educational success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0091552112454914">Kuh &amp; Gonyea, 2003</xref>). This finding therefore justifies the importance of focusing institutional expenditures on libraries and other academic supports that have been shown to have strong positive correlations with student engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0091552112454914">Pike, Smart, Kuh, &amp; Hayek, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Although several models of educational attainment have incorporated various factors that might shape student outcomes, it is particularly important to expand on these models in an effort to develop an understanding of how motivational attributes affect individual students. Relevant motivational variables are especially critical for the student population under discussion: community college beginners who seek a bachelor’s degree, but who do not begin their postsecondary education at a baccalaureate-degree-granting institution. The findings suggest that perceived importance of getting a good education is a close correlate to the stability of baccalaureate expectations among community college students. It will be important for future research to focus on other pertinent motivational attributes in understanding community college student outcomes. Equally important, research aimed at identifying effective measures that help cultivate positive motivational beliefs among students may well inform educational policy and practice.</p>
<p>This study provides additional empirical evidence suggesting a negative relationship between reading remediation and the stability of baccalaureate-aspiring community college students’ educational expectations. Based on national data, this study provides an assessment of the aggregated predictive value of remediation in reading. This global indication, however, might not be very significant when researching and assessing the effect of reading remediation at the level of individual institutions. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0091552112454914">Wang (2009)</xref> pointed out, with continued diversification of the community college student body and emergence of new remedial practices, researchers should focus on identifying effective models for implementing and assessing remedial education.</p>
<p>Much more research is needed to investigate how educational practices could help community college students achieve their long-term educational goals. In a time when community colleges are facing increasing public scrutiny while being challenged by resources and funding retrenchment, these institutions need to have an adequate understanding of their students in a changing environment that will profoundly affect their future. Educational policies and programs that effectively meet student expectations are of greatest importance and value to them. The development and selection of such policies and programs should be based on a sound knowledge of their students’ educational expectations as well as factors underlying these expectations.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Xueli Wang</bold> is an assistant professor in the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Analysis at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Her current research deals with several issues pertaining to community colleges and their students, including baccalaureate aspirations, participation in STEM fields of study, educational pathways, as well as the role of community colleges in STEM education.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bozick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Entwisle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Warming up, cooling out, or holding steady? Persistence and change in educational expectations after high school</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The color of success: African-American college student outcomes at predominantly White and historically Black public colleges and universities</article-title>. <source>Harvard Education Review</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The influence of financial aid in leveling group differences in graduating from elite institutions</article-title>. <source>Economics of Education Review</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>296</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Astin</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>What matters in college: Four critical years revisited</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morest</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Introduction</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morest</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Defending the community college equity agenda</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Social foundations of thought and action: A social cognitive theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Self-efficacy: The exercise of control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Freeman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dreeben</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>How schools work</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Camburn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>College completion among students from high schools located in large metropolitan areas</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Education</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>551</fpage>-<lpage>569</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The impact of institutional choice and environments on African American and White students’ degree expectations</article-title>. <source>Research in Higher Education</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>A dream deferred? Examining the degree aspirations of African American and White college students</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>RoutledgeFalmer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>College students’ degree aspirations: A theoretical model and literature review with a focus on African-American and Latino students</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Higher education: Handbook of theory and research</source> (Vol. <volume>17</volume>, pp. <fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>171</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Agathon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Faculty-student interaction at the community college</article-title>. <source>Research in Higher Education</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>769</fpage>-<lpage>802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Starks</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in the effects of significant others on students’ educational expectations</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1960</year>). <article-title>The cooling-out function in higher education</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>569</fpage>-<lpage>576</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brawer</surname><given-names>F. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The American community college</source> (<edition>5th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Social capital in the creation of human capital</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DesJardins</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>, <season>Fall</season>). <source>A comment on interpreting odds-ratios when logistic regression coefficients are negative</source> (<comment>Association for Institutional Research Professional File, No. 81</comment>). <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://airweb3.org/airpubs/81.pdf">http://airweb3.org/airpubs/81.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DesJardins</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahlburg</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An integrated model of application, admission, enrollment, and financial aid</article-title>. <source>Journal of Higher Education</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Domina</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The link between educational expectations and effort in the college-for-all era</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>The contradictory college: The conflicting origins, impacts and futures of the community college</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kienzl</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>It’s not enough to get through the open door: Inequalities by social background in transfer from community colleges to four-year colleges</article-title>. <source>Teachers College Record</source>, <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>452</fpage>-<lpage>487</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Featherman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>). <source>Socioeconomic background and achievement</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Seminar Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Epps</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Race, class, and educational opportunity: Trends in the sociology of education</article-title>. <source>Sociological Forum</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>-<lpage>608</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Post-high school plans and aspirations of Black and White high school seniors: 1976-86</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Student price response in higher education: An update to Leslie and Brinkman</article-title>. <source>Journal of Higher Education</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>624</fpage>-<lpage>659</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoachlander</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Community college students: Goals, academic preparation, and outcomes</source> (<comment>NCES 2003-164</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingels</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Coming of age in the 1990’s: The eighth-grade class of 1988 12 years later</source> (<comment>NCES 2002-321</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Contingent faculty and student outcomes</article-title>. <source>Academe</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jencks</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crouse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mueser</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>The Wisconsin model of status attainment: A national replication with improved measures of ability and aspiration</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuh</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonyea</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The role of the academic library in promoting student engagement in learning</article-title>. <source>College and Research Libraries</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>256</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuh</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The effects of student-faculty interaction in the 1990s</article-title>. <source>Review of Higher Education</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laanan</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Editor’s notes</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Laanan</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Transfer students: Trends and issues</source> (<comment>New Directions for Community Colleges, No. 114, pp. 1-3</comment>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laanan</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Degree aspirations of two-year college students</article-title>. <source>Community College Journal of Research and Practice</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>T. F. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuh.</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Student experiences with information technology and their relationship to other aspects of student engagement</article-title>. <source>Research in Higher Education</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leigh</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The effect of community colleges on changing students’ educational aspirations</article-title>. <source>Economics of Education Review</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lent</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Integrating person and situation perspectives on work satisfaction: A social-cognitive view</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>236</fpage>-<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowman</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A multilevel model of educational expectations of secondary school students in the United States</article-title>. <source>Social Psychology of Education</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Educational planning and academic achievement of middle school students: A racial and cultural comparison</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling and Development</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>518</fpage>-<lpage>526</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Faculty-based advising: An important factor in community college retention</article-title>. <source>Community College Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<conf-date>1990, November</conf-date>). <article-title>Mobility of educational expectations: The effect of community colleges</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the Association for the Study of Higher Education</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Portland, OR</conf-loc>. (<comment>ERIC Document Reproduction Service No. ED326132</comment>)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<conf-date>1997, November</conf-date>). <article-title>Changes in educational aspirations after high school: The role of postsecondary attendance and context</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the Association for the Study of Higher Education</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Albuquerque, NM</conf-loc>. (<comment>ERIC Document Reproduction Service No. ED415808</comment>)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meehan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Negy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Undergraduate students’ adaptation to college: Does being married make a difference?</article-title> <source>Journal of College Student Development</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>670</fpage>-<lpage>690</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Museus</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in the formation of postsecondary educational expectations: A structural model</article-title>. <source>Teachers College Record</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>811</fpage>-<lpage>842</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Museus</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hendel</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Test scores, self-efficacy, and the educational plans of first-year college students</article-title>. <source>Higher Education in Review</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Center for Education Statistics</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <source>The condition of education 2004, indicator 18: Remediation and degree completion</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nora</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wedham</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<conf-date>1991, April</conf-date>). <article-title>Off-campus experiences: The pull factors affecting freshman-year attrition on a commuter campus</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Chicago, IL</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascarella</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>College environmental influence on students’ educational aspirations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Higher Education</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>751</fpage>-<lpage>771</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascarella</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>A multi-institutional, path analytic validation of Tinto’s model of college withdrawal</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pascarella</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edison</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nora</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagedorn</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terenzini</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Does work inhibit cognitive development during college?</article-title> <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascarella</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terenzini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>How college affects students</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascarella</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terenzini</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>How college affects students: Vol. 2. A third decade of research</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forrest Cataldi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The road less traveled? Students who enroll in multiple institutions</source> (<comment>NCES 2005-157</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuh</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayek</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Educational expenditures and student engagement: When does money matter?</article-title> <source>Research in Higher Education</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>-<lpage>872</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reason</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terenzni</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Developing social and personal competence in the first year of college</article-title>. <source>Review of Higher Education</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>Multiple imputation for nonresponse in surveys</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rubinson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Class formation, politics, and institutions: Schooling in the United States</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>-<lpage>548</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>A. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohlendorf</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>The educational and early occupational status attainment process: Replication and revision</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1014</fpage>-<lpage>1027</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>A. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <article-title>The educational and early occupational attainment process</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>82</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Sex, schooling and occupational status</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>551</fpage>-<lpage>583</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swail</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>The art of student retention: A handbook for practitioners and administrators</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Education Policy Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Cooling-out and warming-up: The role of the postsecondary institutional environment in managing ambitions</source>. <comment>Unpublished manuscript</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teachman</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Family background, educational resources and educational attainment</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>548</fpage>-<lpage>557</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tierney</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venegas</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Fictive kin and social capital: The role of peer groups in applying and paying for college</article-title>. <source>American Behavioral Scientist</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1687</fpage>-<lpage>1702</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tinto</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Dropout from higher education: A theoretical synthesis of recent research</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Baccalaureate attainment and college persistence of community college transfer students at four-year institutions</article-title>. <source>Research in Higher Education</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>570</fpage>-<lpage>588</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0091552112454914">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Factors contributing to the upward transfer of baccalaureate aspirants beginning at community colleges</article-title>. <source>Journal of Higher Education</source>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>