<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjrp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Reinforced Plastics and Composites</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0731-6844</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-7964</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0731684412444652</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0731684412444652</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Optimizing processing parameters of pin-assisted-melt impregnation of fiber-reinforced plastics by numerical simulation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Rong-guo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412444652">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0731684412444652"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Fan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412444652">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Li-feng</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412444652">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Ge</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0731684412444652">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Wei-cheng</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412444652">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0731684412444652"><label>1</label>Center for Composite Materials and Structures, Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0731684412444652"><label>2</label>School of Mathematical Sciences, Peking University, Beijing, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0731684412444652">Rong-guo Wang, Center for Composite Materials and Structures, Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China Email: <email>wangrongguo@hit.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>731</fpage>
<lpage>737</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In this paper, we report a new method to predict the pin-assisted-melt impregnation of a fiber bundle to a high-viscosity resin. An analytical model is established based on pulling a single fiber over a pin located in a melt pool. The impregnation depth is studied as a function of diameter of the pin, the line speed of the fiber, the viscosity of the resin, the pre-tension on the fiber, and the width of the fiber bundle. The results show that the level of impregnation is highly dependent on the fiber width, but insensitive to the line speed of the fiber, the pre-tension and the pin diameter, in accord with the previous reported experimental result.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Impregnation</kwd>
<kwd>high viscous resin</kwd>
<kwd>fiber bundle</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0731684412444652" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Fabric-reinforced plastic composites, with the structure of fibers, especially long fibers, embedded in polymer matrix, are widely used as mechanical parts due to their superior mechanical properties, such as high strength, high elastic modulus, and light weight. In order to achieve these properties, many factors need to be taken into consideration, including the material factors such as the properties of polymer matrix and fibers as well as the interface adhesion between them, and the process factors such as impregnation, fiber orientation, and fiber wear. Among all the fabrication processes, fiber impregnation is the first step and one of the most important steps, especially for fiber winding and fiber prepreg. This process is widely used to produce large structures with high performance. Generally, impregnation is carried out by pulling fiber roving over cylindrical pins in a pool of resin with a low viscosity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0731684412444652">1–3</xref></sup> In recent years, advanced resins with a viscosity 2–3 orders of magnitude higher than that of the traditional resins found more and more applications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0731684412444652">4</xref></sup> However, with this highly viscous and glutinous resin, it is a big challenge to achieve a complete and homogenous impregnation of a large number of slender fibers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0731684412444652">5</xref></sup> To circumvent this problem, a significant amount of research has been done to study the impregnation of high viscous resins and fiber roving. Per Nygard presented a pin chamber impregnation method based on a series of impregnation experiments and pointed out that the radial slot impregnation method gave the best overall impregnation efficiency compared to other methods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0731684412444652">6</xref></sup> Chandler showed that there was a dry contact area on the pin in the process of impregnation for the pin chamber impregnation method.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0731684412444652">7</xref></sup> Gaymans studied the effect of the diameter of the pin, fiber tension, pulling speed, and the melt viscosity on the impregnation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412444652">8</xref></sup> Till now, most work in this field focus on the experiments, while very little attention is paid to theoretical analysis.</p>
<p>In this paper, a flow model of a pin-assisted-melt impregnation was not only developed to describe the fluxion between the fiber roving and the pin but also to analyze the influence of the processing parameters on the impregnation efficiency.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-0731684412444652"><title>Model for impregnation process</title>
<p>For a pin-assisted-melt impregnation process, fiber roving is pulled over a cylindrical pin in a pool of resin, as show in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0731684412444652">Figure 1</xref>. It is generally accepted that the impregnation process can be divided into four regions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684412444652">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0731684412444652">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0731684412444652">9</xref></sup> In Region I, the movement of the fiber roving drags resin into the narrow gap between the fiber and the pin. The gap could be further divided into two parts—Region II and Region III. In Region II, pressure is built up by the resin dragged in from Region I, resulting in impregnation and some leakage of the resin from the gap to the surrounding pool. Both these processes lead to a reduction of the thickness of the gap, resulting in a wedge shape. The point where the gap thickness vanishes is defined as dry contact, which also separates Region II from Region III. In Region III, the fiber monofilaments are physically in contact with the pin surface, causing little impregnation because of lacking resin. Finally, In Region IV, the fiber roving is pulled away from the pin. It is interesting to note that the impregnation process primarily takes place in the wedge-shaped region, which will be taken into consideration in the following model in detail.
<fig id="fig1-0731684412444652" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic of a pin-assisted-melt impregnation setup.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In the wedge-shaped region, the melt flow is relatively slow, and the viscous force is very high, so the pseudoplastic behavior of the melt is negligible, and the melt can be simplified as a Newton fluid. Generally, the impregnation is driven by capillary action and applied pressure. In this case, the capillary action is neglected due to the high viscosity of the melt. This assumption is supported by the experimental results reported by Gaymans.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412444652">8</xref></sup> Based on the assumptions mentioned above, we build a model for impregnation process, derive several process parameters, and analyze their influence on the impregnation.</p>
<sec id="sec3-0731684412444652"><title>Impregnation pressure</title>
<p>For a pin, the tension on a fiber roving is composed of several parts: the pre-tension, the viscous shear stresses from fluid, and the friction between glass monoﬁlaments and pin surface.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684412444652">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0731684412444652">9</xref></sup> In the wedge-shaped region, the fiber roving and the pin are not physically contacted, so the friction can be ignored. And the shear stress is also negligible due to Bates’s study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684412444652">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0731684412444652">3</xref></sup> As a result, the tension on a fiber is approximately equal to the pre-tension. The pressure of the melt is equal to the vertical component of the tension force which is perpendicular to the liquid surface and given by the lap lace’ law,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412444652">8</xref></sup> as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0731684412444652"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>T</italic> is the fiber pre-tension, <italic>P</italic> is the melt pressure, <italic>P</italic><sub>in</sub> is the vertical component of the tension force, and <italic>R</italic> is the pin diameter.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-0731684412444652"><title>Flow in the wedge-shaped region</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684412444652">Figure 2</xref> shows the wedge-shaped region, with <italic>L</italic>, <italic>w</italic>, and <italic>H</italic> representing its length, width, and height, respectively. Here <italic>w</italic> is equal to the fiber width. The resin flow in the wedge-shaped region can be characterized by three velocities: <italic>u</italic><sub>tow</sub>, the velocity of the fluid flowing into the wedge-shaped region; <italic>u</italic><sub>impregnation</sub>, impregnation velocity; <italic>u</italic><sub>pressure</sub>, the leakage velocity from the sides of the wedge-shaped region due to the pressure gradient along the resin flow direction. According to Bates’ work, the gap thickness is far less than the gap length,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684412444652">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0731684412444652">9</xref></sup> so <italic>u</italic><sub>impregnation</sub> can be approximately regarded as parallel to the <italic>z</italic> direction. Noted that the thickness of the gap is very small, and the melt viscosity is very high, we can assume that the Reynolds Number of the fluid is very low, thus the fluid behavior could be expressed by N-S equation. It is further assumed that the entrance effect in the inlet of the gap could be negligible and the gap thickness is far less than the gap length, the fluid could be assumed as a pressure flow between two parallel plates along <italic>y</italic> direction and expressed as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0731684412444652"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
in which <italic>P</italic> is the melt pressure, η is the resin viscosity, and
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0731684412444652"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
<fig id="fig2-0731684412444652" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The flow direction of the resin in the wedge-shaped area.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The volume flow <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub> along <italic>y</italic> direction is calculated by integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0731684412444652">equation (4)</xref> in the wedge-shaped region and written as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0731684412444652"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>h</italic> and <italic>w</italic> are the thickness and the width of the wedge-shaped area, respectively.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-0731684412444652"><title>Thickness of the wedge shaped area</title>
<p>Working from first principles, Blok<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0731684412444652">10</xref></sup> has shown that a flexible impermeable tape in contact with a rotating cylinder covered with lubricating oil will cause the oil to form a film gap with constant thickness between tape and cylinder, and this constant thickness was given as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0731684412444652"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>T</italic> is the tape tension, <italic>w</italic> is the tape width, η is the oil viscosity, <italic>U</italic> is the relative tape/cylinder speed and <italic>R</italic> is the cylinder radius. For the pin-assisted impregnation, Chandler proposes that the thickness of the wedge-shaped region has an initial value, <italic>H</italic>, as given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0731684412444652">equation (1)</xref>, keeps reducing along the <italic>x</italic> direction and eventually drops to a constant value which is comparable to the monoﬁlament diameter, at the “dry contact” point. For simplicity, we assume that the thickness drops linearly along <italic>x</italic> direction and is expressed as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0731684412444652"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>h</italic> and <italic>L</italic> are the thickness and the total length of the wedge-shaped region at the position <italic>x</italic>.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-0731684412444652"><title>Impregnation depth</title>
<p>According to the previous research,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684412444652">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412444652">8</xref></sup> the rate of the molten polymer that penetrates the ﬁbers is the most important factor in the melt-impregnation process. The rate of penetration of a fluid into the fibers structure has been described by Darcy’s law<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0731684412444652">11</xref></sup> as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0731684412444652"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
where Δ <italic>P/Z</italic>  is the pressure drop over penetration depth <italic>Z</italic>, <italic>u</italic><sub>impregnation</sub> is the impregnation velocity, <italic>K</italic> is the permeability coefficient of the fiber structure, which can be calculated from the Carman-Kozeny equation:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0731684412444652">12</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0731684412444652"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>D<sub>f</sub></italic> is the diameter of the fiber, <italic>e</italic> is the porosity, and <italic>k</italic> is a constant related to polymer viscosity, ﬁber structure, and ﬁber type, written as:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0731684412444652">12</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0731684412444652"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>By integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0731684412444652">equation (6)</xref>, we can get
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0731684412444652"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>Here <italic>t</italic> = <italic>x</italic>/<italic>U</italic>, then we get
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-0731684412444652"><label>(11)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
the melt is dragged into the gap by the fiber roving, causing a volume flow along <italic>x</italic> direction, which is expressed as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0731684412444652"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
in an arbitrary small volume between <italic>x</italic> and <italic>x</italic> + <italic>dx</italic>, the net volume flow is zero, and this can be written as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0731684412444652"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p><xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0731684412444652">Equations (4)</xref>, (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11-0731684412444652">11</xref>), (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula12-0731684412444652">12</xref>), and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0731684412444652">13</xref>) can be combined to yield the following differential equation for tension build-up on an individual differential element:</p>
<p>Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0731684412444652">equations (4)</xref>, (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11-0731684412444652">11</xref>), and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula12-0731684412444652">12</xref>) into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0731684412444652">equation (13)</xref>, we get
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0731684412444652"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>Integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0731684412444652">equation (13)</xref> yields
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-0731684412444652"><label>(15)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>The total depth of the impregnation at the point of “dry contact” can be acquired by substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-0731684412444652">equation (10)</xref> into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0731684412444652">equation (15)</xref> and expressed as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula16-0731684412444652"><label>(16)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq16.tif"/></disp-formula></p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec7-0731684412444652"><title>Numerical simulation results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0731684412444652">Equations (1)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0731684412444652">15</xref>) show that the impregnation depth is determined by many factors, including the permeability coefficient of the fiber structure, the width of the fiber bundle, the pin diameter, the line speed of the fiber, the fiber pre-tension, and the melt viscosity. Among these factors, the permeability coefficient of the fiber structure and the melt viscosity can be regarded as constants for a Newton fluid with negligible capillary action as we assumed, according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-0731684412444652">equations (7)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0731684412444652">8</xref>). Therefore, in the following section, we will mainly discuss the influence of other impregnation parameters.</p>
<p>In order to quantitatively study the influence of the line speed of fiber, an example of impregnating a 2400TEX glass fiber roving through a high-viscosity melt is used. Here, the melt viscosity is assumed to be 80 Pa.s, the width of fiber bundle is 4 mm, the pre-tension is 8 N, the permeability coefficient of the fiber structure is 4.3 × 10<sup>−10</sup> m<sup>2</sup>, the pin diameter is 30 mm, and the pin roving contact angle is 180°. These parameters are used for the calculation below unless otherwise specified.</p>
<sec id="sec8-0731684412444652"><title>Pre-tension on the fiber</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0731684412444652">Figure 3</xref> shows the depth of impregnation calculated as a function of the line speed of the fiber at different pre-tension values of 2 N, 4 N, 6 N, and 8 N. We notice that, for a single curve, such as the 2 N one, the depth of the impregnation increases sharply in the small speed region, reaches a maximum at about 0.237 mm, and decreases with the further increase of the speed.
<fig id="fig3-0731684412444652" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Impregnation depth as a function of the line speed of fiber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The inset shows the peak position for different pre-tension value. This trend can be explained by the flow of the melt. Here, two factors affect the impregnation process, the amount of the melt and the impregnation duration. With the increase of the line speed of the fiber, the amount of the melt flowing into the wedge region increases, while the duration of impregnation process keeps decreasing. For a small line speed of the fiber, the melt factor dominates, and the wedge-shaped region tends to vanish, resulting in a stagnated impregnation due to insufficient melt. On the contrary, for a large speed, the duration of impregnation play a more important role, and the contact area is limited by the pin roving contact angle. As a result, the impregnation depth is also small. In between these two cases, for a medium speed, a maximum value of impregnation depth exists.</p>
<p>With the increase of the fiber tension, the peak position of the impregnation depth increases, while the largest impregnation depth is almost unchanged. This indicates that the impregnation depth does not depend on the pre-tension in accord with the experimental result reported by Gaymans.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412444652">8</xref></sup> From <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0731684412444652">equation (15)</xref>, we note that the maximum value of impregnation depth is only determined by the permeability coefficient of the fiber structure and the width of a fiber bundle. With the increase of the fiber pre-tension, the pressure perpendicular to the fiber increases, causing an enhancement of the impregnation process, but the pressure also gives rise to the pressure flow along y direction and shorten the length of the wedge-shaped area, so finally the maximum value of the impregnation depth remains unchanged.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec9-0731684412444652"><title>Pin diameter</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412444652">Figure 4</xref> shows the influence of different pin diameters on the impregnation depth. The calculation is done by using different pin diameters of 30 mm, 60 mm, 90 mm, and 120 mm, while fixing other parameters to values mentioned above. With the increase of the pin diameter, the maximum impregnation depth is unchanged, but the peak position moves toward larger line speed of the fiber. This indicates that the maximum impregnation depth does not depend on the pin diameter in accord with the experimental results reported by Gaymans.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412444652">8</xref></sup> With the increase of the pin diameter, the length of the wedge-shaped area increases, while the pressure in the polymer film decreases. These two factors counteract with each other, keeping the maximum value of the impregnation depth a constant value.
<fig id="fig4-0731684412444652" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Impregnation depth as a function of the pin diameter. The inset shows the peak position for different pin diameter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-fig4.tif"/></fig></p></sec>
<sec id="sec10-0731684412444652"><title>Fiber bundle width</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412444652">Figure 5</xref> shows the influence of different width of fiber bundle on the maximum value of the impregnation depth. Here, the widths of fiber bundles used are 4 mm, 6 mm, 8, mm, and 10 mm. The result shows that the fiber bundle width plays an important role in the pin-assisted melt impregnation. The maximum value of impregnation depth increases as the width gets bigger. With the increase of the width, the flow path of the pressure along y direction gets longer, and this blocks the leakage of melt from the wedge-shaped region. As a result, more melt is involved in the impregnation process. Besides, for a real fiber bundle, the cross-section area is a constant value, so increasing width would reduce the thickness of the fiber bundle, in turn, the needed impregnation depth reduced at the same time. So increasing the width of the fiber bundle is a more effective way to improve the impregnation.
<fig id="fig5-0731684412444652" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The width of a fiber bundle as a function of the fiber bundle widths. The inset shows the peak position and the peak height for different fiber bundle widths.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The discussion above is only based on an ideal condition. For a real case, the length of the wedge-shaped region is also limited by the pin roving contact angle θ, in turn limiting the largest impregnation depth. There exists a maximum value for the length of wedge. When the real length exceeds this limit, a leakage of melt tends to occur at the end of the contact area, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0731684412444652">equation (15)</xref> will no longer hold. In this case, the depth of impregnation tends to get smaller, because of the extra loss of the melt, which can be described as an increase of the leakage volume flow. So the line speed of the fiber should match with the following conditions simultaneously,
<disp-formula id="disp-formula17-0731684412444652"><label>(16)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412444652-eq17.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p><xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula16-0731684412444652">Equation (16)</xref> limits the maximum length of the wedge-shaped region, and when the speed of fibre bundle reaches a limitation, at which the the dry contact point reaches the edge of the pin, and Region III vanishes. If the line speed of the fiber gets even faster, the melt will leak not only from the side but also from the flow front, so the depth of impregnation will reduce rapidly. In this case, the model built in this paper would no longer hold. So an optimization calculation on the fiber bundle width is necessary for practical application.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec11-0731684412444652"><title>Multiple pins</title>
<p>The amount of polymer that can be impregnated with one pin is limited as we have seen above. Several pins are often used to increase the impregnation. With one pin, the degree of impregnation is low for the bundle, and the model’s assumptions in this paper were not changed for multiple pins, so this model is still effect. According to the model in this paper, the pre-tension and the pin diameter of every pin has changed, which has been studied by Bate,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0731684412444652">3</xref></sup> thus, the impregnation depth of every pin could be calculated and the total depth of multiple pins is the summation.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec12-0731684412444652" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This paper studied the process of pin-assisted-melt impregnation of fiber-reinforced plastics, and a model was developed to estimate the depth of the impregnation when the fiber roving is pulled symmetrically over a stable pin. Many factors were taken into consideration, including the pin diameter, the line speed of the fiber, the fiber bundle width, fiber pre-tension, polymer viscosity, and the permeability coefficient of the fiber structure in the wedge-shaped region. The result shows that the maximum impregnation depth is not related to the fiber pre-tension and the pin diameter but highly depends on the fiber bundle width. This result has been satisfactorily corroborated by experiment.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec13-0731684412444652"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec>
<ack><title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>This project is supported by the Center for Composite Materials and Structures of Harbin Institute of Technology.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0731684412444652"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henninger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thermoplastic filament winding with online-impregnation. Part A: process technology and operating efficiency</article-title>. <source>Compos: Part A</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1479</fpage>–<lpage>1486</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0731684412444652"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pulling tension monitoring during the melt impregnation of glass roving</article-title>. <source>Polym Compos</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0731684412444652"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendallb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pressure build-up during melt impregnation</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0731684412444652"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Charrier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of process parameters on melt impregnation of glass roving</article-title>. <source>J Thermoplast Compos Mater</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0731684412444652"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Lutz A and Harmia T. Impregnation techniques for fiber bundles or tows, In: Karger-Kocsis J (ed.,). <italic>Polypropylene: an A–Z reference</italic>. Dordrecht: Kluwer, 1999, pp. 301–306</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0731684412444652"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Xian G, Hongting P and Xiaosu Y. Parametric optimisation of pin-assisted-melt impregnation of glass fiber/polypropylene by Taguchi Method. <italic>J Compos Mater</italic> 2006; 40(23): 2087–2097</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0731684412444652"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nygard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>C-G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Continuous glass fiber–polypropylene composites made by melt impregnation: influence of processing method</article-title>. <source>J Thermoplast Compos Mater</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0731684412444652"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bijsterbosch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaymans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impregnation of glass rovings with a polyamide melt. Part 1: impregnation bath</article-title>. <source>Compos Manuf</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0731684412444652"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A model for the continuous impregnation of fiber tows in resin baths with pins</article-title>. <source>Plast Rubber Compos Process Applicat</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0731684412444652"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Blok H and van Rossum JJ. The foil bearing—a new departure in hydrodynamic lubrication. <italic>Lubrication Eng</italic> 1953; 9: 316–320</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0731684412444652"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaymans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wevers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impregnation of a glass fiber roving with a polypropylene melt in a pin assisted process</article-title>. <source>Compos Part A: Appl Sci Manuf</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>5–6</issue>): <fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0731684412444652"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iannace</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolais</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of processing conditions on the impregnation of glass fibre mat in extrusion/calendering and film stacking operations</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>2217</fpage>–<lpage>2222</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>