<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SAP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsap</journal-id>
<journal-title>South African Journal of Psychology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0081-2463</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0081246313478509</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0081246313478509</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorials</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial: South African psychology makes history</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ngcobo</surname><given-names>Humphrey SB</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0081246313478509">President of the Psychological Society of South Africa, South Africa</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0081246313478509">Humphrey SB Ngcobo, Psychological Society of South Africa, PO Box 989, Houghton, 2041, South Africa. Email: <email>drsiphiwe@medis.co.za</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>7</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Psychological Society of South Africa</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The past year has seen the occurrence of a few significant events in the science and profession of psychology that will have immeasurable positive impact on the future trajectory of African psychology generally and South African psychology in particular.</p>
<p>A year ago an international jury appointed by the International Union of Psychological Science (IUPsyS) decided to confer the Inaugural IUPsyS ‘Achievement Against the Odds Award’ to Saths Cooper. Comprising over 80 national members and 20 affiliates, IUPsyS is dedicated to ‘the development, representation and advancement of psychology as a basic and applied science nationally, regionally, and internationally’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0081246313478509">IUPsyS, 2012</xref>). The jury pointed out that Cooper is a key figure in South African psychology who has invested heavily in moving the discipline forward in the international arena following the dark years of Apartheid. They noted further that:
<disp-quote>
<p>The struggle for an emancipatory and just psychology in South Africa closely mirrors the struggles and achievements of Saths Cooper himself. Through his belief in and pursuit of social justice, as well as his abiding commitment towards the attainment of equality, human rights and health, he has succeeded in making significant contributions to psychology in South Africa. Despite considerable personal hardship and risk, including imprisonment, Saths Cooper facilitated the resilience of psychology in South Africa, and is actively continuing in his efforts to bring African psychology into the fold of international psychology and to enhance the wider internationalization of psychology as a science and profession. He continues to encourage and build the capacity of young psychology scholars and professionals to take up leadership in local, national and global contexts. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0081246313478509">IUPsyS, 2013</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>According to IUPsyS,
<disp-quote>
<p>Dr Cooper is recognised as one of the key psychology leaders to have restored credibility to South African psychology, after years of isolation brought about by psychology’s historical association with the system of Apartheid. His undergraduate studies were abruptly ended in 1969 when he was rusticated from the University College, Durban for his unwavering opposition to the creation of an ethnic university that would grant its own degrees. He was put under house arrest and jailed for a total of nine years. This included a term of over five years on Robben Island Prison (in the same cell-block as former President Mandela, Govan Mbeki and Walter Sisulu) for his non-violent student and community development activities. He was refused permission to study. After release from Robben Island prison in December 1982, he was able to continue his studies, despite reservations from those who considered that his political background or his imprisonment made him unsuitable. In 1998, he was declared a ‘victim of gross human rights violations’ by South Africa’s Truth and Reconciliation Commission. He has received a number of honours for his services to psychology, including a Medal for Services to International Psychology from IUPsyS (2008), fellowship of the National Academy of Psychology, India (2007), Paul Harris Fellow (Rotary International, 2003) and the Golden Peacock Achiever Award for Political and Intellectual Leadership and Academic Excellence, Indian Academy of South Africa (2003). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0081246313478509">IUPsyS, 2013</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Cooper has been in the leadership of the Psychological Society of South Africa (PsySSA) from its inception, as the inaugural President, and he was elected as its first Fellow in September 2002.</p>
<p>The most successful International Congress of Psychology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0081246313478509">ICP, 2012</xref>) was hosted by South Africa from 22 to 27 July. This was the first time an ICP was held on African soil in the 123 years of this quadrennial flagship event in international psychology. Almost 6000 delegates from 103 countries converged at Cape Town for an exciting and comprehensive scientific programme that included 30 parallel sessions daily, including seven parallel sessions of invited speakers from across the world. In terms of quality, the range of topics covered, the capable organisation, and the sheer hospitality evidenced by South African psychologists and students, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0081246313478509">ICP 2012</xref> set new benchmarks. It is noteworthy that South Africa succeeded in ensuring that after the September 2011 PsySSA Congress, there was no other psychology conference held on the continent in the 10 months preceding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0081246313478509">ICP 2012</xref> and for a year after. Most African and South African psychology associations fully supported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0081246313478509">ICP 2012</xref>, with many being co-hosts. The <italic>Cape Town Declaration</italic> announcing the creation of the Pan African Psychology Union will also strengthen psychology’s last frontier, and provide the opportunity for the world to benefit from the extant humanism that abounds in Africa, despite the ravages of socio-political history, and afford a novel horizon for psychology’s future growth and development in South Africa, the continent, and the world.</p>
<p>The landslide election of Saths Cooper as President of IUPsyS for a 4-year term (beating the eminent Chinese and Australian candidates) and the unanimous appointment of Ann Watts as IUPsyS Secretary General is an affirmation that South African psychology has emerged from its chequered past as a vibrant science and profession that the world acknowledges. Saths Cooper was the first sub-Saharan African to be elected onto the IUPsyS Executive Committee in 2000, serving as its Vice President from 2004. Ann Watts was elected onto the IUPsyS Executive Committee in 2008, appointed Deputy Secretary General in 2010, and was also appointed President-Elect of the International Neuropsychology Society in January 2013. These important appointments are an unprecedented acclaim for the ability and vision of South Africans to lead pre-eminent psychological organisations globally.</p>
<p>This issue of the <italic>South African Journal of Psychology</italic> (<italic>SAJP</italic>) is also historic. The <italic>SAJP</italic> is 43 years old, but if its predecessors – especially <italic>Psychologia Africana</italic> and the <italic>South African Psychologist –</italic> are taken into account, it is well over half a century old! During this time, it has seen many changes and has had illustrious editors, albeit most were, understandably, either open or closet supporters of the erstwhile Apartheid dispensation. Since the formation of PsySSA (on 21 January 1994), successive editors have been Linda Richter, Lionel Nicholas, Cheryl de la Rey, Norman Duncan, Martin Terre Blanche, and Kobus Maree, each bringing innovation, taking the <italic>SAJP</italic> to new heights and adding to its academic and scientific impact and quality. The <italic>SAJP</italic> is the foremost scientific psychology publication in Africa and is one of the major South African academic journals.</p>
<p>Beginning with this issue, the <italic>SAJP</italic> will, for the first time, be externally published. The process to enable this important milestone took a few years of deliberation within the PsySSA Council until unanimity was achieved a couple of years ago. The PsySSA leadership could easily have relied on having achieved a majority when the idea was first mooted of having the <italic>SAJP</italic> published externally, but the leadership’s deeply held commitment to ensuring full consensus and enabling full and further discussion – cherishing the minority view expressed – allowed for complete ownership of the decision. Only when this position was achieved were concrete steps taken to announce a request for proposals. This transparent consensual approach has been a <italic>leit motif</italic> of PsySSA decision-making processes under significant Black and female presidents, who have strenuously upheld divergence of opinion.</p>
<p>Two international psychology publishers were shortlisted (local publishers remained surprisingly reticent) and interviewed during the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0081246313478509">ICP 2012</xref> in Cape Town last July. After much negotiation, SAGE was engaged to publish the <italic>SAJP</italic> for 5 years. The <italic>SAJP</italic> will be fully electronic and free to PsySSA members, who will enjoy electronic access to numerous psychology titles published by SAGE. Members and others can continue to enjoy subscribing to the printed version.</p>
<p>All of us can anticipate an exciting period ahead for the <italic>SAJP</italic> under the SAGE imprint, coming in the wake of the most successful ICP ever held and the significant accession of leading South African psychologists to world psychology organisations, all of which augur well for the future of psychology in our country and our continent. Warm wishes are extended to the editor Anthony Pillay and his team for a successful and progressive chapter in the life of the <italic>SAJP</italic>.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0081246313478509">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>International Congress of Psychology (ICP) 2012</collab>. (<year>2012</year>). <source>30th International congress of psychology programme</source>. <publisher-loc>Cape Town, South Africa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0081246313478509">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>International Union of Psychological Science (IUPsyS)</collab>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Statues</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iupsys.net/images/archive/statutes/statutes2012.pdf">http://www.iupsys.net/images/archive/statutes/statutes2012.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0081246313478509">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>International Union of Psychological Science (IUPsyS)</collab>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Winner: Achievement against the odds award</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iupsys.net/index.php/component/content/article/302/26980-winner-achievement-against-the-odds-award">http://www.iupsys.net/index.php/component/content/article/302/26980-winner-achievement-against-the-odds-award</ext-link></citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>