<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJT</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spijt</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Toxicol</journal-id><journal-title>International Journal of Toxicology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1091-5818</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1092-874X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1091581812442688</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1091581812442688</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Malathion/Oxon and Lead Acetate Increase Gene Expression and Protein Levels of Transient Receptor Potential Canonical Channel Subunits TRPC1 and TRPC4 in Rat Endothelial Cells of the Blood–Brain Barrier</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balbuena</surname><given-names>Pergentino</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1091581812442688">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1091581812442688">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rzigalinski</surname><given-names>Beverly A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1091581812442688">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ehrich</surname><given-names>Marion</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1091581812442688">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1091581812442688"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1091581812442688"><label>1</label>Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-1091581812442688"><label>2</label>The Edward Via Virginia College of Osteopathic Medicine, Blacksburg, VA, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1091581812442688">Marion Ehrich, Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine, 1 Duck Pond Drive, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg VA 24061, USA Email <email>marion@vt.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">American College of Toxicology</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>This study examined the effects of malathion and lead on transient receptor potential canonical channel TRPC1/TRPC4 channels in rat brain endothelial cells as a mechanism to explain previously noted blood–brain barrier (BBB) permeability induced by these compounds. Lead, malathion, malaoxon and combinations of these were assessed for protein levels and gene expression of TRPC1/C4 at 2, 4, 8, 16, and 24 hours after exposure. Changes in intracellular free calcium dynamics were also assessed. Compounds increased TRPC1 and TRPC4 protein levels as well as gene expression within 4 hours after exposure. Basal levels of intracellular free calcium were also elevated. Increases in gene and protein expression may be associated with an increase in the numbers of TRP channels, and the increases in intracellular calcium may be associated with activation of such channels. Therefore, upregulation and activation of the TRPC1/TRPC4 may be a mechanism by which these neurotoxicants affect BBB permeability.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>BBB</kwd><kwd>TRPC1</kwd><kwd>TRPC4</kwd><kwd>permeability</kwd><kwd>lead</kwd><kwd>malathion</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="section1-1091581812442688"><title>Introduction</title><p>Endothelial cells of the blood–brain barrier (BBB) regulate transport between the brain and the blood systemic circulation. This regulation is critical for homeostasis in the central nervous system (CNS) and is responsible for the restriction of paracellular ion transport in the BBB.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1091581812442688">1</xref></sup> Increases in cytoplasmic free calcium by depletion of intracellular calcium stores are associated with increases in permeability that result in disruption of BBB integrity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1091581812442688">2</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1091581812442688">3</xref></sup> Disruption of BBB integrity has also been associated with increases in intracellular free calcium in endothelial cells initiated by transient receptor potential canonical channel (TPRC) activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1091581812442688">3</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1091581812442688">4</xref></sup> The disruption of integrity and the increases in permeability of the BBB are associated with several pathological conditions such as ischemic stroke,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1091581812442688">5</xref></sup> traumatic brain injury,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1091581812442688">6</xref></sup> multiple sclerosis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1091581812442688">7</xref></sup> and Alzheimer disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1091581812442688">8</xref></sup></p><p>Lead poisoning is still a worldwide concern. Environmental lead poisoning, which was epidemic in the nineteenth century, resurged in the 1920s when tetraethyl lead began to be added to gasoline.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1091581812442688">9</xref></sup> Although less than that in the past, environmental exposures still occur. Lead toxicity is accompanied by damage to cell membranes, allowing it to bind to proteins in soft tissues of the organs affected. Lead toxicity has been associated with altered liver, kidney, lung, cardiovascular, immune, bone, and CNS functions. At high concentrations, lead also disrupts the cerebral capillary endothelial cells forming the BBB, causing extensive cerebral hemorrhage and the extravascular distribution of proteins.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1091581812442688">10</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1091581812442688">11</xref></sup> Lead is also capable of entering cells through store-operated calcium channels and through transient receptor potential canonical channels (TRPCs).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1091581812442688">12</xref></sup></p><p>Malathion is in many cases the organophosphorus (OP) compound of choice in pest control of crops and households.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1091581812442688">13</xref></sup> Insecticidal efficacy of OP compounds resides in their capability to inhibit degradation of the neurotransmitter acetylcholine via inhibition of acetylcholinesterase (AChE). The same mechanism is associated with OP toxicities in humans. OP compounds can disrupt BBB permeability in vitro,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1091581812442688">15</xref></sup> and malathion decreased the levels of tight junction proteins in endothelial cells of the BBB.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1091581812442688">16</xref></sup> Nevertheless, mechanisms by which OPs disrupt tight junction proteins and therefore increase BBB permeability were not described in these reports. Also unknown is whether additive effects of lead and OP compounds on BBB permeability occur because both affect a similar mechanism.</p><p>Transient receptor potential canonical channels (TRPCs) are composed of a family of several isoforms (TRPC1 through TRPC7). These isoforms, when configuring the channel, arrange into 6 transmembrane subunits that can assemble into both homomeric and heteromeric complexes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1091581812442688">17</xref></sup> The TRPCs have been associated with the regulation of endothelial cell permeability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1091581812442688">18</xref></sup> Specifically, the TRPC1 and TRPC4 subunits form heteromeric channels in endothelial cells of the BBB and therefore may be involved in BBB permeability mechanisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1091581812442688">19</xref></sup> In normal cell function, the TRPC1 and <italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic> subunits may be coupled to capacitative calcium influx. Furthermore, the <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> subunits show similarity to voltage-gated calcium channels, although they lack the set of positively charged residues that confer voltage sensitivity to most voltage-gated ion channels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1091581812442688">17</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1091581812442688">20</xref></sup></p><p>Previous work in our laboratory established that lead and malathion alone, and even more in combination, decreased transendothelial electrical resistance in an in vitro model of the BBB at noncytotoxic concentrations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup> This disruption in permeability is caused in part by reducing tight junction protein levels,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1091581812442688">16</xref></sup> but the mechanism (or mechanisms) by which this damage is induced still remains to be elucidated. The present study examined the effects of these 2 neurotoxic substances on <italic><italic>TRPCs</italic></italic> by utilizing rat brain endothelial cells (RBE4s) of the BBB. We hypothesized that <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> and/or <italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic> may be associated with the mechanism through which lead and malathion affect the BBB. We assessed gene expression and protein levels of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> subunits in endothelial cells of the BBB following exposure to lead and malathion at concentrations that alone and together did not affect cell viability but were able to decrease BBB barrier function. We also assessed changes in levels of intracellular free calcium in response to treatments with lead and malathion up to 24 hours after exposure. Since lead and organophosphates are associated with variations in intracellular free calcium concentrations in different cell systems,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1091581812442688">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1091581812442688"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1091581812442688">23</xref></sup> the <italic><italic>TRPCs</italic></italic> are good candidates to explore as contributors to disruption of the BBB.</p></sec><sec id="section2-1091581812442688" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="section3-1091581812442688"><title>Chemicals</title><p>Malathion of 94% purity was donated by the American Cyanamid Company, agricultural division (Princeton, New Jersey). Malaoxon 98.2% pure was obtained from Chem Services Inc (West Chester, Pennsylvania); it was used to determine the need for having an active esterase inhibitor in order to observe changes in the levels of <italic><italic>TRPCs</italic></italic>. Lead acetate, Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, NaCl, trizma base, triton X-100, glycine, SDS, tween-20, deoxycholate, fura-2 AM (acetoxymethyl ester), and DMS were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, Inc (St Louis, Missouri). Blocking buffer was purchased from LI-COR Biotechnology (Lincoln, Nebraska). Thapsigargin (an inhibitor of sarcoplasmic endoplasmic calcium ATPase pumps) was purchased from Calbiochem (San Diego, California).</p></sec><sec id="section4-1091581812442688"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>The rat brain microvascular endothelial cell line RBE4 was donated by the laboratory of Dr M Aschner, Vanderbilt University. Cells for Western blots and real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) were cultured in 100 mm × 20 mm polystyrene tissue-culture-treated dishes (Sigma-Aldrich) at a concentration of 1.5 ×10<sup>5</sup> cells per culture dish; cells utilized for calcium measurements were cultured in 6-well tissue-culture-treated plates (Sigma-Aldrich). Cells in both the dishes and the plates were left to reach 100% confluency. RBE4 cultures were cultured in 44.5% minimum essential medium (MEM), 44.5% Ham F10 with glycine, 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), and 1% of a penicillin/streptomycin/amphotericin B solution and kept at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. All the cell culture media and reagents utilized in cell culture procedures were obtained from Mediatech Inc (Manassas, Virginia), unless otherwise noted. After 3 to 4 days of incubation, the cells were treated with astrocyte conditioned medium (ACM) and incubated for an additional 2 days in order to induce the presence of tight junctions on the endothelial cells. ACM has been associated with induction of BBB-specific characteristics such as tight junctions in several cell lines.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1091581812442688">24</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1091581812442688">25</xref></sup> After the incubation with the ACM, cells were treated with the neurotoxicants.</p></sec><sec id="section5-1091581812442688"><title>Treatments</title><p>Cells were treated with combinations and compounds alone at different times and concentrations. Treatment groups include lead acetate at 10<sup>−5</sup> M (Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M) and 10<sup>−6</sup> M, malathion 10<sup>−5</sup> M (Mal10<sup>−5</sup> M), malaoxon 10<sup>−6</sup> M (M×10<sup>−6</sup> M), and combinations of both neurotoxicants (Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M + Mal10<sup>−5</sup> M, Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M + M×10<sup>−6</sup> M, Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M + Mal10<sup>−5</sup> M, and Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M + M×10<sup>−5</sup> M). Cells were treated for 2, 4, 8, 16, and 24 hours. Viability was unaffected after exposure of BBB cells to these concentrations for these periods of time.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="section6-1091581812442688"><title>Western Blot Assessment</title><p>RBE4 cells were washed in 5 mL ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) of pH 7.4 and then lysed for 10 minutes with an ice-cold lysis buffer solution containing 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM trizma base, 0.5% v/v triton X-100, and 0.5% w/v deoxycholate. Lysates were centrifuged at 16 000<italic>g</italic> for 5 minutes and resuspended in 700 µL of ice-cold PBS. Lysates were processed immediately for protein determination; sample concentrations were adjusted to 1 mg/mL and stored at −20°C. Proteins were separated by electrophoresis in 4% to 15% Tris-HCl 1.0 mm pre-casted gels (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, California) and then transferred to a 0.45 µm pure nitrocellulose membrane by electroblotting. Membranes were blocked for 1 hour at room temperature with Odyssey blocking buffer (LI-COR Biotechnology) and then incubated for 1 hour with polyclonal antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, California) for <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic>, <italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic>, and anti-β-actin (as a normalizing control) at 1:200 dilutions. Membranes were washed 5 times (5 minutes each) with a solution of PBS pH 7.4 and 0.1% tween-20 and then incubated for 1 hour with IRDye 700DX conjugated affinity purified anti-rabbit immunoglobulin G ([IgG] donkey) and IRDye 800CW conjugated affinity purified anti-goat IgG (donkey) secondary antibodies (Rockland, Gilbertsville, Pennsylvania) at 1:5000 dilutions. Membranes were washed and then analyzed by near-infrared (NIR) fluorescence detection methods with the Odyssey Infrared Imaging System. Results were expressed as relative band fluorescence in pixels.</p></sec><sec id="section7-1091581812442688"><title>Total RNA Extraction and Reverse Transcription/Complementary DNA Synthesis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted utilizing the Total RNA purification RNeasy kit from Qiagen (Valencia, California). Briefly, cells were lysed with lysis buffer applied directly on the cell culture dishes after washing them with ice-cold PBS; lysates were then homogenized with 70% ethanol utilizing a blunt 20-gauge needle (0.9 mm diameter), and pipetted into RNeasy spin columns and centrifuged. Samples were treated with DNase I in order to digest any genomic DNA that may have been present in the samples and then washed again in the columns. RNA was then eluted directly from the columns with 30 µL of RNase-free water. Concentrations of total RNA were determined for samples with an Eppendorf UV/Vis bioPhotometer analysis system (Hamburg, Germany), and then RNAs were stored at −80°C. Reverse transcription synthesis was carried out utilizing the reverse transcription system from Promega (Madison, Wisconsin) processing 1 µg of total RNA per reaction. Briefly, total RNA was incubated at 70°C for 10 minutes and placed on ice. Reactions were prepared at the following concentrations: 50 ng/µL of total RNA, 50 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10× reverse transcription buffer (100 mM Tris-HCl of pH 9.0 at 25°C; 500 mM KCl; 1% TritonX-100), 1 mM each dNTP mixture, 1 unit/µL recombinant RNasin ribonuclease inhibitor, 50 units/µg avian myeloblastosis virus (AMV) reverse transcriptase (high concentration), and 0.5 µg of random primers per microgram RNA with nuclease-free water to a total volume of 20 µL per reaction. Reactions were incubated at room temperature for 10 minutes and then at 42°C for 15 minutes before they were heated at 95°C for 5 minutes. After cooling, complementary DNA (cDNA) reactions were stored at −20°C until used.</p></sec><sec id="section8-1091581812442688"><title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title><p><italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic> real-time oligonucleotide primers for <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> and <italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic> and β-actin (as an internal normalizing control) were designed with the Beacon Designer 7.6 software (Premier Biosoft International, Palo Alto, California) as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1091581812442688">Table 1</xref>. Primers were designed to be compatible with the SYBR Green PCR assays avoiding significant cross homologies and preventing secondary structures that can interfere with SYBR Green primer extension. Primers were synthesized by Invitrogen and then concentrations of each primer were standardized to 30 µM concentrations. Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) amplifications were carried out utilizing an iCycler iQ optical system (Bio-Rad). The PCR reaction mix was generated by adding 12.5 µL of SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad) with 0.25 µL of each primer (forward/reverse), 1 µL of cDNA template, and RNA-free water to a total of 25 µL per reaction. The relative quantification of gene expression was attained utilizing the comparative C<sub>T</sub> method.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1091581812442688">26</xref></sup></p><table-wrap id="table1-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic> Oligonucleotide Primer Sequences Used in the Real-Time PCR Assessments<sup>a</sup></p></caption><graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1091581812442688" xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-table1.tif"/><table><thead><tr><th>Gene</th><th>Accession Number</th><th>Primer/Forward</th><th>Primer/Reverse</th><th align="center">Product Length (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>TRPC1</td><td>NM_053558</td><td>5’-AGGTGAAGGAGGAGAACACCTTG-3’</td><td>5’-CCATAAGTTTCTGACAACCGTAGTCC-3’</td><td>101</td></tr><tr><td>TRPC4</td><td>AF421364</td><td>5’-AATTACTCGTCAACAGGCGGC-3’</td><td>5’-CACCACCACCTTCTCCGACTT-3’</td><td>179</td></tr><tr><td>β-actin</td><td>NM_053558</td><td>5’-TATCGGCAATGAGCGGTTCC-3’</td><td>5’-GTGTTGGCATAGAGGTCTTTACG-3’</td><td>144</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-1091581812442688"><p>Abbreviations: PCR, polymerase chain reaction; TRPC, transient receptor potential canonical channel; bp, base pair.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn2-1091581812442688"><p><sup>a</sup> All the primers were synthesized by Invitrogen (Carlsbad, California).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section9-1091581812442688"><title>Intracellular Free Calcium Analysis</title><p>Intracellular free calcium was determined microspectrophotometrically as we have previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1091581812442688">27</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1091581812442688">28</xref></sup> Briefly, RBE4 cells were seeded in six-well tissue-culture-treated plates and after confluency was reached, cells were treated with ACM and incubated for an additional 2 days in order to induce the presence of tight junctions on the endothelial cells. Cells were then treated with neurotoxicants lead acetate and malathion/oxon for 2 and 4 hours. These concentrations had been previously demonstrated not to affect cell viability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup> After treatment with the neurotoxicants, cells were washed twice with Dulbecco PBS and then incubated for 1 hour with 5 µM Fura-2AM in Dulbecco PBS of pH 7.4 supplemented with 1 mM glucose and 1% fatty acid–free bovine serum albumin (FAF-BSA). After incubation, cells were washed twice with supplemented Dulbecco PBS and analyzed. Intracellular free calcium was determined with a Ratiomaster microspectrophotometery system (Photon Technologies International, South Brunswick, New Jersey). Excitation light was provided by a Xenon Arc lamp coupled to a scanning monochrometer that alternated excitation light between 340 and 380 nm. Band pass was set at ±2 nm. Excitation light was delivered to the cells via fiber optics through the epifluorescence port of a Zeiss Axioscop II coupled to a 40× water immersion lens. Emission was measured at 510 nm via microphotometer. The entire system for data collection was computer driven. Intracellular free calcium was calculated as previously described using a correction for intracellular viscosity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1091581812442688">29</xref></sup> The concentration of intracellular Fura-2 within the cells was routinely monitored at the isobestic wavelength to assure that dye leakage did not occur after toxicant treatment. Additionally, the excitation/emission spectra of loaded cells was scanned prior to the experiment. Fura-2 spectra from toxicant-exposed cells was similar to that of control cells, indicating that chemical chelation or alteration of Fura-2 by any toxicant remaining in the cells did not occur.</p></sec><sec id="section10-1091581812442688"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All results are expressed as means ± standard error of the mean (SEM) of 3 or more individual assays. Multiple comparisons were performed by utilizing 1-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by Dunnett's test for comparison of treatments with the control, and by Tukey's test for comparison among treatments. Data were analyzed by GraphPad Prism 4 (GraphPad software, San Diego, California); <italic>P</italic> values less than.05 were considered to be significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section11-1091581812442688"><title>Results</title><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1091581812442688">Figure 1</xref>, the levels of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> protein increased considerably at the 4-hour period for all treatments. When endothelial cells of the BBB were exposed to the treatments for this time period, the combinations of neurotoxicants and malaoxon alone considerably increased protein levels (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Levels of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> protein were still high at 8 hours after exposure except for the two concentrations of lead alone. However at 16 hours, only the Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M + Mal10<sup>−5</sup> M combination maintained <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> protein levels above those of control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1091581812442688">Figure 1</xref>). In general, combinations of lead and malathion induced higher levels of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> protein at the 4- and 8-hour periods (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01); this is indicative of the presence of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> channels in the membrane of cells. Levels of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic> </italic>protein at 24 hours resemble those at 2 hours. The 24-hour treatments with the organophosphates alone and their combinations with lead were significant when compared with the control (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), however, these levels are not significant when compared to the increases measured early in the experiment (2 hours).</p><fig id="fig1-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Transient receptor potential canonical channel (TRPC1) protein levels in response to treatment. Levels increased for the 4-hour period, with the combinations elevating the levels of TRPC1 protein more than the compounds alone (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) except for Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M. At 8 hours, only the combinations and the organophosphates maintain the increased levels of protein (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). Pb indicates lead; Mx, malaoxon; Mal = malathion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-fig1.tif"/></fig><p>The results for experiments determining <italic><italic>TRPC4</italic> </italic>protein levels showed time-related differences when compared with the levels of <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic> </italic>protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1091581812442688">Figure 2</xref>). There were marked increases in <italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic> protein levels at 2 and 4 hours but not at 8 hours. In contrast, <italic><italic>TRPC1</italic></italic> still showed increases at 8 hours. With the exception of Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M and its combination with Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M, <italic><italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic></italic> protein levels increased at 2 hours for all treatments (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). However, after 4 hours of treatment, only the Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), Mal10<sup>−5</sup> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), and Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M + Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) maintained increased levels of <italic><italic><italic>TRPC4</italic></italic></italic> protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1091581812442688">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Transient receptor potential canonical channel (TRPC4) protein levels in response to treatment. Protein levels increased at the 2-hour period for both compounds alone and combinations (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), with the exception of the lowest concentration of lead and the Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M + Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M combination. At 8 and 16 hours combinations decreased protein levels (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), a trend that continued to the 24-hour period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-fig2.tif"/></fig><p>Increases in gene expression for <italic>TRPC1</italic>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1091581812442688">Figure 3A</xref>, were noted in cells exposed to both organophosphates and the highest concentration of lead alone at 4 hours (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). At 8 hours, however, only the organophosphates were still showing a 2-fold increase in <italic>TPRC1</italic> gene expression. Combinations of neurotoxicants significantly increased <italic>TRPC1</italic> gene expression at 4 hours with <italic>P</italic> values less than .01 for all treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1091581812442688">Figure 3B</xref>). Furthermore, at 24 hours, the gene expression was still upregulated for all combination treatments except for Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M + Mal10<sup>−5</sup> M.</p><fig id="fig3-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>A, Transient receptor potential canonical channel (<italic>TRPC1</italic>) response to neurotoxicants alone. Gene expression was increased significantly for all the compounds at the 4-hour period (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), especially for malaoxon (Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). B, <italic>TRPC1</italic> response to combinations of neurotoxicants. Gene expression significantly increased at the at the 4-hour period for all the combinations (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). The expression of the gene was still above the control levels at 24 hours (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), with the exception of the Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M + Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M combination.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-fig3.tif"/></fig><p>The pattern of <italic>TRPC4</italic> gene expression differed from that of <italic>TRPC1</italic>. For example, the response to treatments with neurotoxicants alone was increased significantly earlier, with effects seen at 2 and 4 hours (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) except for the lowest lead (Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M) concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1091581812442688">Figure 4A</xref>). Increases in <italic>TRPC4</italic> gene expression occurred after exposure to both the lead and the organophosphates alone at 24 hours. In contrast to this increased gene expression in cells that were exposed to single neurotoxicants, no combinations of neurotoxicants significantly increased <italic>TRPC4</italic> gene expression at 16 and 24 hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1091581812442688">Figure 4B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>A, Transient receptor potential canonical channel (<italic>TRPC4</italic>) response to neurotoxicants alone. Gene expression was increased by all the compounds alone at 2 hours and especially at 4 hours (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). The exception was Pb10<sup>−6</sup> M which decreased gene expression at 2 hour (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). At 24 hours, however, all compounds were noted to increase <italic>TRPC4 </italic><italic/>expression when compared to controls (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). B, <italic>TRPC4</italic> response to combinations of neurotoxicants. Combinations of neurotoxicants increased <italic>TRPC4</italic> gene expression at 2 hours (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), with the exception of Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M + Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M. At 16 and 24 hours, however, combinations significantly decreased <italic>TRPC4</italic> gene expression (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). Pb10<sup>−5</sup> M + Mx 10<sup>−6</sup> M decreased gene expression at all times (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-fig4.tif"/></fig><p>Protein and gene expression of <italic>TR</italic><italic>PC1</italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> were elevated by treatment with lead and malathion. The <italic>TRPC1</italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> may be associated with store-operated intracellular calcium-signaling pathways. Therefore, we examined the effects of lead and malathion on basal and thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium 2 and 4 hours after treatments. Thapsigargin depletes intracellular calcium stores via a slow leakage and activates subsequent calcium influx through store-operated channels, which are believed to be related to <italic>TRPC</italic>. Hence, its use gives an approximate picture of the total flux through the capacitative or store-operated calcium influx pathway. Since <italic>TRPC1</italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> may be associated with store-controlled calcium entry, we hypothesized that the altered protein and gene expression of <italic>TRPC1</italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> after toxicant treatment would alter the dynamics of store-operated calcium entry as evidenced with thapsigargin treatment.</p><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1091581812442688">Figure 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1091581812442688">2</xref>-hour treatment with lead increased the basal (unstimulated) intracellular free calcium by 30% to 38% at the 10<sup>−5</sup> M and 10<sup>−6</sup> M concentrations. Malathion 10<sup>−5</sup> M increased basal intracellular free calcium in a similar manner (35%-50%). After a 2-hour treatment with 10<sup>−5</sup> M and 10<sup>−6</sup> M lead or malathion 10<sup>−5</sup>M, the thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium elevation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1091581812442688">Figure 5B</xref>) was higher when compared with the increases in basal intracellular free calcium shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1091581812442688">Figure 5A</xref> (2-fold increase <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1091581812442688">Figure 5A</xref> vs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1091581812442688">B</xref>). Nevertheless, when increases in the treatments are compared with control for just the thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium, there are no statistically significant differences among groups.</p><fig id="fig5-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A, Effect of lead (Pb) and malathion (Mal) on basal intracellular free calcium in rat brain endothelial cells (RBE4s) after 2 hours of exposure. Asterisks (*) indicate values statistically different from untreated control cells, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01. B, Effect of lead and malathion on thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium in rat brain endothelial cells (RBE4s) after 2 hours of exposure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-fig5.tif"/></fig><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1091581812442688">Figure 6</xref> shows basal (6A) and thapsigargin-stimulated (6B) increases in intracellular free calcium after a 4-hour exposure to lead or malathion. Basal levels of intracellular free calcium were significantly elevated by both lead and malathion compared to control levels (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) at 4 hours, although comparisons of increases among treatments with each other were not statistically significant. At 4 hours, the levels of thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium increased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) when compared with those of unstimulated (basal) intracellular free calcium for the same time period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1091581812442688">Figure 6A</xref> vs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1091581812442688">B</xref>). Furthermore, treatments with both concentrations of lead and malathion increased the calcium levels for all groups when compared with the controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1091581812442688">Figure 6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1091581812442688">B</xref>). When calcium level increases among treatments were compared, only the thapsigargin-stimulated group showed a dose–response increase among treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1091581812442688">Figure 6B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6-1091581812442688" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>A, Basal intracellular free calcium in rat brain endothelial cells (RBE4s) following 4 hours of exposure to lead (Pb) and malathion. Asterisks (*) indicate values significantly different from untreated control cells, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01. B, Effect of lead (Pb) and malathion (Mal) on thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium in rat brain endothelial cells (RBE4s) after 4 hours of exposure. Asterisks (*) indicate significant differences when compared to untreated controls, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1091581812442688-fig6.tif"/></fig><p>Increases in basal and thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium declined to levels similar to untreated controls after 8 hours of treatment, suggesting the observed effects may be early events in the toxicological pathway that results in failure of BBB integrity. Although malaoxon and combinations of the neurotoxicants were assessed, no further changes in intracellular free calcium were noted.</p></sec><sec id="section12-1091581812442688"><title>Discussion</title><p>The <italic>TRPCs</italic> are associated with permeability in endothelial cells of the BBB.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1091581812442688">3</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1091581812442688">20</xref></sup> Activation of these channels may be associated with increases in intracellular free calcium originating from depletion of calcium from stores of the endoplasmic reticulum followed by subsequent influx of extracellular calcium.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1091581812442688">2</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1091581812442688">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1091581812442688">30</xref></sup> In turn, these increases in intracellular free calcium may be associated with endothelial cell permeability,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1091581812442688">3</xref></sup> which can cause BBB disruption. Our results noted a marked increase in protein levels of <italic>TPRC1</italic> measured by Western blot, which is in accordance with the increases in <italic>TRPC1</italic> gene expression measured by real-time PCR. The increases in <italic>TRPC1</italic> protein and gene expression denote increased presence of <italic>TRPCs</italic> in the cell membranes especially at 4 hours. However, this does not signify activation of such channels. Actual activation of these channels is followed by increases in intracellular free calcium, which may in turn activate several calcium-dependent pathways. For example, increases in calcium can activate proteases such as metalloproteinases that are associated with tight junction proteolysis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1091581812442688">31</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1091581812442688">32</xref></sup> inducing in the process increases in permeability of the BBB.</p><p>The results of the present study indicate that neurotoxicants lead and malathion considerably increase <italic>TRPC1</italic> levels, which may induce increases in <italic>TRPCs</italic> in cell membranes. Because intracellular free calcium rises as well, we propose that the elevation in basal intracellular free calcium after lead and malathion exposure may be due to upregulated <italic>TRPC1</italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> basal activity or dysregulation of <italic>TRPC1</italic>-/<italic>TRPC4</italic>-associated channels. Furthermore, it is possible that activation and/or increase in <italic>TRPCs</italic> may be at least one of the mechanisms by which these neurotoxicants increase the BBB permeability noted in our previous work.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup> The increases in basal and thapsigargin-stimulated intracellular free calcium declined to normal levels after 8 hours of treatment, suggesting the observed effects may be early events in the toxicological pathway that results in the failure of BBB integrity. Furthermore, combinations of lead and malathion produced no further changes in intracellular free calcium, compared to that produced by each toxicant individually (data not shown), suggesting the effects were not additive.</p><p>The <italic>TRPC4</italic> protein levels were increased by the treatments with the neurotoxicants alone; however, no clear additive effects of combinations were seen. This was substantiated with the measurements of gene expression by real-time PCR. These results suggest the need for further studies to determine whether these compounds might compete for the same mechanism of action during the early stages of mixture treatments. Further studies are needed to clarify the nature of the effects seen here with lead and malathion. Decreases in <italic>TRPC4</italic> levels would indicate smaller quantity of <italic>TRPCs</italic> in the membrane of RBE4 cells if the <italic>TRPC4</italic> subunit could form homomeric channels; however, in most cases <italic>TRPC4</italic> subunits associate with <italic>TRPC1</italic> subunits to form functional heteromeric channels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1091581812442688">17</xref></sup> The percentage of each subunit present in heteromeric channels, however, has not yet been reported. The <italic>TRPC1</italic> also has been demonstrated to form homomeric channels, but its functionality is decreased.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1091581812442688">33</xref></sup> The differences and ratios of the heteromeric channels or even the presence of homomeric channels for both <italic>TRPC1</italic> and <italic>TRPC4</italic> may be a factor in the differences noted in increases of the <italic>TRPC1</italic> levels at 4 hours but at 2 hours for <italic>TRPC4</italic>. Therefore, identification of the number of subunits in each channel in a mixed population of <italic>TRPC1</italic>/<italic>TRPC4</italic> heteromeric channels would allow us to assess whether the variation in protein levels for both subunits could modify increases in permeability on the BBB induced by lead and malathion.</p><p>In previous studies in our laboratory with a BBB system that allowed polarity, the RBE4 cells on the luminal side of the model sequestered considerably less lead compared to another model constructed with bovine brain endothelial cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup> This may be relevant in assessing the <italic>TRPC1</italic> and <italic>TRPC4</italic> protein levels in RBE4 cells since lead affects kinases that modulate expression and activation of <italic>TRPCs</italic>. Moreover, Sukumar and Beech reported activation of <italic>TRPC5</italic> channels at micromolar concentrations of lead.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1091581812442688">34</xref></sup> Since the RBE4s utilized in this experiment are the same utilized in our BBB system mentioned above, we can expect similar results utilizing this BBB system with an apical and a basolateral side. Furthermore, the increases in <italic>TRPCs</italic> noted in this work and their association with increases in endothelial permeability are in agreement with previous work from our laboratory, which demonstrated that these neurotoxicants increased BBB permeability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1091581812442688">14</xref></sup> and decreased tight junction proteins in the endothelial cells forming the luminal layer of the BBB.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1091581812442688">16</xref></sup></p><p>The present study noted early increases in the levels of protein and in gene expression for <italic>TRPC1</italic> and <italic>TRPC4</italic>, as well as increases in intracellular free calcium in response to treatments with lead and malathion. This agrees with most reported studies, although some authors reported no effect of lead on basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1091581812442688">35</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1091581812442688">36</xref></sup> Nevertheless, the early increases in gene expression and protein levels of the <italic>TRPC</italic> subunits and the increases in intracellular free calcium in the endothelial cells of the rat BBB (RBE4 cells) reported in this work suggest that these increases are a component of the mechanism by which lead and malathion contribute to changes in BBB permeability and, therefore, damage tight junction structures.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1091581812442688"><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1091581812442688"><p>This research was funded by Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1091581812442688"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The blood-brain barrier/neurovascular unit in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-1091581812442688"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cioffi</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of endothelial cell barrier function by store-operated calcium entry</article-title>. <source>Microcirculation</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-1091581812442688"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiruppathi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmmed</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Calcium signaling, TRP channels, and endothelial permeability</article-title>. <source>Micro Inf Health</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>692</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-1091581812442688"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gias</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name><surname>Asrar</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional role of TRPC channels in the regulation of endothelial permeability</article-title>. <source>Arch-Eur J Physiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>451</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-1091581812442688"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouns</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Dyen</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The complexity of neurobiological processes in acute schemic stroke</article-title>. <source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>482</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-1091581812442688"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lotocki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccari JP de</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alterations in blood-brain barrier permeability to large molecules and leukocyte accumulation after traumatic brain injury: effects of post-traumatic hypothermia</article-title>. <source>J Neurotrauma</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1123</fpage>–<lpage>1134</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-1091581812442688"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McQuaid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunnea</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of blood-brain barrier on glial cell function in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>pt 1</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-1091581812442688"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farral</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McGurn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardlaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Blood-brain barrier permeability in Alzheimer’s disease: a case-control MRI study</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-1091581812442688"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lead poisoning in a historical perspective</article-title>. <source>Am J Ind Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-1091581812442688"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Asbury</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of lead encephalopathy: uptake of lead and reaction of brain capillaries</article-title>. <source>Archs of Neurol</source>. <year>1974</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-1091581812442688"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early lead exposure increases the leakage of the blood-cerebrospinal fluid barrier <italic>in-vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Human Expertl Toxicol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-1091581812442688"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerper</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinkle</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lead uptake in brain capillary endothelial cells: activation by calcium store depletion</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-1091581812442688"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><collab collab-type="author">Environmental Protection Agency</collab>. <year>2000-2001</year>. <article-title>Pesticide market estimates. Pesticide industry sales webpage</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/oppbead1/pestsales/01pestsales/usage2001_3.htm#3_8">http://www.epa.gov/oppbead1/pestsales/01pestsales/usage2001_3.htm#3_8</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed May 13, 2010</comment>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-1091581812442688"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balbuena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnin-Bissel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of two blood-brain barrier <italic>in vitro</italic> systems: cytotoxicity and transfer assessments of malathion/oxon and lead acetate</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-1091581812442688"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parran</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chlorpyrifos alters functional integrity and structure of an <italic>in vitro</italic> BBB model: co-cultures of bovine endothelial cells and neonatal rat astrocytes</article-title>. <source>Neurotox</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>, <fpage>291</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-1091581812442688"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balbuena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessments of tight junction proteins occludin, claudin 5 and scaffold proteins ZO1 and ZO2 in endothelial cells of the rat blood-brain barrier: cellular responses to neurotoxicants malathion and lead acetate</article-title>. <source>Neurotox</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-1091581812442688"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Owsianik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilius</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TRP channels: an overview</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3-4</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-1091581812442688"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiruppathi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmmed</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ca2<sup>+</sup> signaling, TRP channels, and endothelial permeability</article-title>. <source>Microcirculation</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-1091581812442688"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antoniotti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pla</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Barral</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalabrino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Munaron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovisolo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interaction between TRPC channel subunits in endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>J Recept Sig Transd</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-1091581812442688"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physiology, phylogeny, and functions of the TRP superfamily of cation channels</article-title>. <source>Sci STKE Re1</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2001</volume>(<issue>90</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-1091581812442688"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuh</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lein</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckles</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jett</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-cholinesterase mechanisms of chlorpyrifos neurotoxicity: altered phosphorylation of CA<sup>2+</sup>/ cAMP response element binding protein in cultured neurons</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-1091581812442688"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schanne</surname><given-names>FAX</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lead-induced rise in intracellular free calcium is mediated trough activation of protein kinase C in osteoblastic bone cells</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>1360</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-1091581812442688"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence that lead acts as a calcium substitute in second messenger metabolism</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2-3</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-1091581812442688"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omidi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Barar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadian</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidari</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbleton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization and astrocytic modulation of system L transporters in brain microvasculature endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Biochem Funct</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-1091581812442688"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Astrocyte-endothelial interactions and blood-brain barrier permeability</article-title>. <source>J Anat</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>200</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-1091581812442688"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the C<sub>T</sub> method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-1091581812442688"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rzigalinski</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Falck</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Calcium influx factor: further evidence it is 5,6-epoxyeicosatrienoic acid</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>274</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-1091581812442688"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rzigalinski</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Traumatic injury of cortical neurons causes changes in intracellular calcium stores and capacitative calcium influx</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>276</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1800</fpage>–<lpage>1807</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-1091581812442688"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grynkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poenie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new generation of calcium indicators with greatly improved fluorescence</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>260</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>3440</fpage>–<lpage>3450</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-1091581812442688"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Putney</surname><given-names>JW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>. <article-title>Store-operated calcium channels</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>810</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-1091581812442688"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wachtel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Occludin proteolysis and increased permeability in endothelial cells through tyrosine phosphatase inhibition</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>pt 23</issue>):<fpage>4347</fpage>–<lpage>4356</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-1091581812442688"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasche</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita-Fujimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Massengale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawase</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early appearance of activated matrix metalloproteinase-9 and blood-brain barrier disruption in mice after focal cerebral ischemia and reperfusion</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>842</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-1091581812442688"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chasan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The multimeric structure of polycystin-2 (TRPP2): structural-functional correlates of homo- and hetero-multimers with <italic>TRPC1</italic></article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1238</fpage>–<lpage>1251</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-1091581812442688"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sukumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Beech</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stimulation of <italic>TRPC5</italic> cationic channels by low micromolar concentrations of lead ions (Pb2+)</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>393</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-1091581812442688"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomsig</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Suszkiw</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pb2(+)-induced secretion from bovine chromaffin cells: fura-2 as a probe for Pb2+</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>259</volume>(<issue>5 pt 1</issue>):<fpage>C762</fpage>–<lpage>C768</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-1091581812442688"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westerink</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijverberg</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ca(2+)-independent vesicular catecholamine release in PC12 cells by nanomolar concentrations of Pb(2+)</article-title>. <source>J Neurochem</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>861</fpage>–<lpage>873</lpage>.</citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>