<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HFS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphfs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Human Factors: The Journal of Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0018-7208</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1547-8181</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0018720812456870</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0018720812456870</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special Section: Keynote Addresses From the 18th Triennial Congress of the International Ergonomics Association</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Inculcating the Ergonomic Culture in Developing Countries</article-title>
<subtitle>National Healthy Schoolbag Initiative in Sri Lanka</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>Marcelo</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Jayaratne</surname><given-names>Kapila</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0018720812456870">Family Health Bureau, Ministry of Health, Colombo, Sri Lanka</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0018720812456870">Kapila Jayaratne, Family Health Bureau, Ministry of Health, 613/1 Nihathamani, Embaraluwa (South), Weliveriya 11710, Sri Lanka; e-mail: <email>kapjay613@gmail.com</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>54</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<issue-title>Special Section: Keynote Addresses From the 18th Triennial Congress of the International Ergonomics Association</issue-title>
<fpage>908</fpage>
<lpage>924</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>5</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012, Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0018720812456870">
<title>Objective:</title>
<p>The aim of this article is to describe a survey on ergonomic factors of classroom environments of school children, their influence on health, and use of research outcomes to launch a healthy schoolbag initiative.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0018720812456870">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Ergonomics have not yet well penetrated relevant fields in industrially developing countries, such as Sri Lanka. One of the crucial parameters of the school environment is ergonomics. Available evidence suggests ergonomic mismatches in classroom settings. Good practice examples in child ergonomic interventions are few in resource-poor contexts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0018720812456870">
<title>Method:</title>
<p>A school-based cross-sectional study was conducted in a district in Sri Lanka with a sample of 1,607 children in Grades 6 to 8 with the use of a stratified multistage cluster sampling method.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0018720812456870">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Many children did experience discomfort related to substandard seating arrangements in the classroom. A significant proportion had to turn their necks to see the blackboard. For many children, seating locations were not changed. There were widespread incompatibilities of classroom furniture with anthropometric dimensions of children. A majority of children perceived discomfort contributed by mismatched classroom furniture. Carriage of school materials was not healthy. Deficiencies were noted in weight, model, ergonomic features, and carrying behavior of bags. Children experienced several negative effects, in part attributable to mismatched ergonomic factors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0018720812456870">
<title>Application:</title>
<p>The schoolbag was considered a priority issue. Findings were disseminated to stakeholders and to media. Solutions were contemplated on bag weight reduction, healthy schoolbag introduction, and behavior change in a collaborative initiative with the Education Ministry. Political, administrative, and business stakeholders were successfully engaged to inculcate an ergonomic culture in an industrially developing country.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>backpack</kwd>
<kwd>school environment</kwd>
<kwd>school ergonomics</kwd>
<kwd>ergonomics for children</kwd>
<kwd>school health promotion</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-0018720812456870" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Sri Lanka is an industrially developing country on the Indian subcontinent. The country profile boasts better health indices, on par with industrially developed countries, with low maternal and infant mortality ratios. Key welfare measures adopted in the country are the free health and education systems catering to the entire population of nearly 20 million.</p>
<sec id="section7-0018720812456870">
<title>Ergonomics</title>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0018720812456870">Dul et al. (2012)</xref>,
<disp-quote>
<p>ergonomics (or human factors) is the scientific discipline concerned with the understanding of the interactions among humans and other elements of a system, and the profession that applies theoretical principles, data and methods to design in order to optimize well-being and overall performance. (p. 378)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Furthermore, to achieve goals of the discipline, “practitioners of ergonomics, ergonomists, contribute to the planning, design, implementation, evaluation, redesign and continuous improvement of tasks, jobs, products, technologies, processes, organizations, environments and systems in order to make them compatible with the needs, abilities and limitations of people” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0018720812456870">Dul et al., 2012</xref>, p. 379). Matched ergonomic arrangement at any place of work is essential for better human performance. Traditionally, ergonomics was focused on factories, offices, and similar adult environments. In keeping pace with advances in human development, ergonomics also goes beyond conventional boundaries. The use of ergonomics is relevant in every type and size of workplace.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0018720812456870">
<title>School and Ergonomics</title>
<p>The school is the largest workplace of all. Children are the “workers” there. School constitutes an important environment for the child where “productivity” in terms of attainment of expected educational levels is of prime importance to the child, the family, and the country as a whole. School is an efficient setting for the promotion of health of children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0018720812456870">World Health Organization, 1996</xref>). The need for design improvements of learning environments to benefit learning has already been recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0018720812456870">Smith, 2007</xref>). The Sri Lankan government spends 78 billion rupees (or 2.8% of the gross domestic product) for provision of education to a total of 4 million children in government schools each year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0018720812456870">Central Bank of Sri Lanka, 2006</xref>). A substantial proportion of children in the country benefits from this system. These children spend a considerable amount of time during the day in a school environment. One of the crucial parameters of the environment is the ergonomics, which plays an important role in influencing the health of school children. Therefore, the school is no exception to the introduction of ergonomics. It should be stressed that children are not smaller models of adults.</p>
<p>Many studies conducted in other regions of the world have shown that several parameters related to students in a school environment are not ergonomically suitable and pose negative health effects. These studies showed that classroom furniture and seating arrangements, position of the blackboard and the surroundings (lighting, sound, and vibration), and schoolbags and carriage of schoolbooks were not optimal for an adolescent. The same studies suggested that arrangements in classrooms were not designed or suited to the anthropometric dimensions of the students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0018720812456870">Cheung &amp; Wong, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0018720812456870">Gouvali &amp; Boudolos, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0018720812456870">Grimmer &amp; Williams, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0018720812456870">Milanese &amp; Grimmer, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0018720812456870">Oates, Evans, &amp; Hedge, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0018720812456870">Panagiotopoulou, Christoulas, Papanckolaou, &amp; Mandroukas, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0018720812456870">Parcells, Stommel, &amp; Hubbard, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0018720812456870">Troussier, Davoine, Gaudemaris, Fauconnier, &amp; Phelip, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0018720812456870">Viry, Creveuil, &amp; Marcelli, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Musculoskeletal pain, general tiredness, postural changes (lateral deviation of the spine, shoulder level shift), psychological manifestations, and poor educational performance have been identified as key negative effects of mismatched ergonomics in the classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0018720812456870">Gunzburg et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0018720812456870">Harreby et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0018720812456870">Negrini, Carabalona, &amp; Sibila, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0018720812456870">Szpalski, Gunzburg, Balagué, Nordin, &amp; Mélot, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0018720812456870">Viry et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>There was growing public concern in Sri Lanka about the classroom environment, especially in regard to schoolbags, that is, the weight of the bag and the behavior of the users. There were several newspaper articles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0018720812456870">Arambewela, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0018720812456870">Gunathilaka, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0018720812456870">Jayakody, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0018720812456870">Jayalath, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0018720812456870">Jayarathna, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0018720812456870">Jayasinghe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0018720812456870">Prashan, 2009</xref>) and electronic media programs appearing on the issue. One article even described carriage of schoolbags by children as similar to “an adult carrying a cement bag over the back” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0018720812456870">Gunathilaka, 2009</xref>). Previous studies have shown biomechanical evidence on load carriage and/or backpack and possible negative health outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0018720812456870">Chow, Li, Lai, &amp; Pope, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0018720812456870">Korovessis, Koureas, &amp; Papazisis, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0018720812456870">Özgül et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0018720812456870">Rodriguez-Oviedo et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0018720812456870">Singh &amp; Koh, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0018720812456870">
<title>The Need</title>
<p>Ergonomic risks in school environments and their impact have not been methodically evaluated in a Sri Lankan context and not even in the South Asian region. Feasible solutions are available to mitigate ergonomic risks. However, until recently, focus on ergonomic risks to schoolchildren was minimal even at international levels. Many developed countries have contemplated both micro- and macroergonomic preventive strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0018720812456870">Legg, 2007</xref>). The aim of this study was to provide basic data to promote professional and public awareness of ergonomics related to schoolchildren and to apply ergonomics in all educational environments. After evidence is generated or substantiated, formulation of solutions that are possible with financial, technical, and administrative constraints in school environments may be identified, implemented, and evaluated.</p>
<p>The initiative will be described in two sections: Phase 1, the research project, and Phase 2, follow-up and getting research into practice, including the challenges and the way forward—the initiative per se.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0018720812456870">
<title>Phase 1: Survey</title>
<sec id="section11-0018720812456870">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>The research project was conducted to determine ergonomic factors of the classroom environment and their relationship to musculoskeletal pain and selected physical attributes of school children 11 to 13 years of age with a view to provide ergonomic solutions with consideration of local contexts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0018720812456870">
<title>Method</title>
<p>A school-based cross-sectional study was conducted in a representative district of Sri Lanka, Gampaha, a semiurban district with a population varied in socioeconomic, cultural, and ethnic characteristics. A wide range of all types of schools according to the classification of schools by the Ministry of Education is available within the same district.</p>
<p>The study process involved the following:</p>
<list id="list1-0018720812456870" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Assessment of distribution of ergonomic and other contributory factors</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Assessment of musculoskeletal pain prevalence and potential consequences of mismatched ergonomics</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Determination of the association between selected ergonomic factors and potential consequences of mismatched ergonomics and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Formulation of feasible solutions</p></list-item>
</list>
<sec id="section13-0018720812456870">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>The study population consisted of schoolchildren in Grades 6, 7, and 8 (11- to 13-year-olds) in the district of Gampaha in Sri Lanka. Children in this age group can be considered to be in early adolescence. Early adolescence signifies the commencement of the second growth spurt, when children gain remarkable increments in weight, height, and skeletal mass. They were considered capable of participating in a study of this nature and would comply sufficiently with measurements involving anthropometry, physical attributes, and postural displacements. On the other hand, children in Grades 6 to 8 remain in school settings for another 5 to 7 years, enabling adequate time to focus on preventive strategies based on the findings of the study.</p>
<p>The Ministry of Education in Sri Lanka classifies schools with four types (1 AB, 1 C, 2, 3) depending on the resources (buildings, teachers, other facilities) available in schools. Type 1 AB has more and Type 3 fewer resources. Since there were only seven Type 3 schools in the entire district of Gampaha, that type was not considered for sampling.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0018720812456870">
<title>Sampling</title>
<p>A sample of 1,607 schoolchildren was selected from 55 clusters with use of a stratified multistage cluster sampling method. A class was considered a cluster. Stratification was based on sector (urban or rural), type of school, and grade (6, 7, or 8).</p>
<list id="list2-0018720812456870" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Stage 1: Schools were classified as urban or rural on the basis of their location in a municipal council area (urban) and in the “Pradeshiya sabha” area (rural). The Ministry of Education also adopts the same basis for the urban-rural classification of schools. A proportionate number of clusters was allocated to each sector (urban and rural) according to the size of the population.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Stage 2: A proportionate number of clusters was allocated to each school type (1 AB, 1 C, and 2) in each sector proportionate to the size of the population.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Stage 3: A proportionate number of clusters was allocated to each grade (6, 7, and 8) in each school type in each sector according to total student population in each grade.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0018720812456870">Figure 1</xref> schematically depicts the aforementioned process (Stages 1 through 3).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Stages of allocation of clusters.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0018720812456870">
<title>Data-collecting instruments</title>
<p>A pretested questionnaire was used to collect basic information and details on other variables related to ergonomic factors, confounders, and negative effects. We measured objective evaluation of musculoskeletal pain with the Adolescent Musculoskeletal Pain Assessment Tool (AMPAT; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0018720812456870">Figure 2</xref>) and ensured validity by conducting a separate validation study. The tool thus developed showed a satisfactory level of judgmental, construct, convergent, and discriminant validities and an acceptable level of internal consistency (Cronbach’s alpha = .773). AMPAT was included in the main questionnaire.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Adolescent Musculoskeletal Pain Assessment Tool.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Although the questionnaire was self-administered, uniform interviewer guidance was provided to participants because of the complexity of the questionnaire, relatively younger age group of participants, and the results of the pilot study.</p>
<p>Distances to the blackboard and measurements of chairs (seat and backrest), desks, popliteal height, and buttock-popliteal length were taken. Height and sitting height of children, body weight, total weight, and weight of contents of the bag were measured. Shoulder-level shift and lateral deviation of the spine were measured with an OSI Scoliometer and Sabia’s Scoliometer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0018720812456870">
<title>Data collection team</title>
<p>The principal investigator (PI) was able to gain hands-on experience in child ergonomics at the International Ergonomic Association’s 16th World Congress held in Maastricht, Netherlands. This experience was in addition to the special training that was acquired with an ergonomist in Sri Lanka.</p>
<p>There were two data collection teams under the supervision of the PI, each headed by a field investigator (FI). Each team consisted of one assistant field investigator (AFI) and four field assistants (FA): one public health inspector (PHI), one public health nursing sister (PHNS), and two public health midwives (PHM).</p>
<p>FIs and AFIs were female preintern medical officers. They have gained adequate training and experience working in the field and conducting epidemiological research. FAs were selected from the public health staff of the Medical Officer of Health (MOH) offices of Gampaha district. One PHI, one PHNS, and two PHMs were selected from each MOH area in which selected schools were located.</p>
<p>All interviewers and data collectors were uniformly trained on administering the questionnaire and taking measurements with practical sessions. All of them collected data according to the same guidelines. All the data collectors were subjected to adequate supervision by the PI during the study process. Data collectors were blind on absence or presence of musculoskeletal pain among the participants at the time of taking measurements.</p>
<p>Reliability of information on selected variables of the questionnaire and selected physical measurements was checked, and interobserver reliability expressed as Pearson’s correlation coefficient between the PI and other field investigators was calculated. The level of agreement was &gt;0.7 for all subjective items of the questionnaire and physical measurements, representing good reliability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0018720812456870">
<title>Ethical aspects</title>
<p>Ethical clearance was obtained from the Ethical Review Committee of the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Colombo. Informed consent was obtained from parents and the schoolchildren prior to participation in the study. Children were allowed to refuse to participate if they wished at any time during the study. Respondents were assured of confidentiality of the details they provided through a numerical coding system for the questionnaire identification. All measurements were made with maximum privacy with least discomfort to the child. Results of the measurements were made available to the child and/or parents whenever indicated, and the child was referred for appropriate health care if any abnormality was detected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0018720812456870">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The software EpiData was used for data entry and exported to SPSS for statistical analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0018720812456870">
<title>Univariate analysis</title>
<p>To study the relationship between contributory factors and the presence of recurrent musculoskeletal pain, we completed an unmatched case-control study. A large number of contributory factors have been studied in previous work. The importance of contributory factors from a public health point of view depends on the extent to which such factors are modifiable to affect the outcome in a positive manner. On the basis of the opinion of the experts, relative risks (odds ratios [ORs]) that would have sufficient biological or public health importance were decided and sample sizes were calculated to achieve a minimum sample size of 534.</p>
<p>In the prevalence study, students with four categories of pain were identified: no pain, acute pain, one-time pain, and recurrent pain. We compared students identified as having recurrent pain (cases, <italic>n</italic> = 463) with children identified as having no pain (controls, <italic>n</italic> = 463) to find relative risks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0018720812456870">
<title>Multivariate analysis</title>
<p>We carried out a multivariate analysis to determine the best predictors of recurrent musculoskeletal pain when contributory factors are considered simultaneously. Variables considered in the univariate analysis, irrespective of whether they showed any significance, were entered into the multivariate models to establish factors that were independently associated. To test the association of recurrent musculoskeletal pain with its contributory factors, we applied a logistic regression model using a forward stepwise method. The dependent variable was coded as 0 and 1 for controls and cases, respectively. All independent factors (contributory factors) identified as predictors or risk factors by previous researchers were included as categorical variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0018720812456870">Table 1</xref>). Inclusion of variables, at each step, was based on the likelihood ratio test at 10% level of significance. Probability was fixed for entry at .05 and removed at .1 significance level.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Table 1:</label>
<caption><p>Variables Included in Univariate and Multivariate Analyses</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0018720812456870" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Contributory Factor = 1</th>
<th align="center">Reference = 0</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Female gender</td>
<td>Male gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Urban sector</td>
<td>Rural sector</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Underweight</td>
<td>Not underweight</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Obesity</td>
<td>Not obese</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Walking to school</td>
<td>Other modes of traveling</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Multiple modes of traveling</td>
<td>Single mode of traveling</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Backpack bag model</td>
<td>Other bag models</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Both-shoulders style of backpack carriage</td>
<td>Other styles of backpack carriage</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Noncompliance with timetable</td>
<td>Compliance with timetable</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Self-carriage of the bag always</td>
<td>Carriage of the bag by others</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unchanging location of seating</td>
<td>Changing location of seating</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seated on a chair with backrest without hand rests</td>
<td>Seated on other models of chair</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Backrest used</td>
<td>Backrest not used</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seated with an individual desk</td>
<td>Seated with a common desk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Engaged in sports and related activities</td>
<td>Not engaged in sports and related activities</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Engaged in tiresome sports activities</td>
<td>Not engaged in tiresome sports activities</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Television watching more than 1 hr</td>
<td>Television watching less than 1 hr</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Engaged in tuition</td>
<td>Not engaged in tuition</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleeping on a bed with a mattress</td>
<td>Sleeping on a place other than a bed with a mattress</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Presence of severe general tiredness</td>
<td>Other categories of general tiredness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Presence of functional disability</td>
<td>No presence of functional disability</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Abnormal total difficulties score</td>
<td>Normal total difficulties score</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Knowledge of a person with musculoskeletal pain</td>
<td>No knowledge of a person with musculoskeletal pain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bag weight &gt;10% body weight</td>
<td>Bag weight &lt;10% body weight</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bag weight &gt;15% body weight</td>
<td>Bag weight &lt;15% body weight</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mismatched seat depth with buttock-popliteal length</td>
<td>Matched seat depth with buttock-popliteal length</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mismatched seat height with popliteal height</td>
<td>Matched seat height with popliteal height</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mismatched legroom height with popliteal height</td>
<td>Matched legroom height with popliteal height</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The model produces logistic regression coefficients and ORs for each of the independent variables in the model.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0018720812456870">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section22-0018720812456870">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>The study included 52% male and 48% female students from urban (31.7%) and rural (68.3%) schools belonging to three classification types; 1 AB (48%), 1 C (30.7%), and 2 (21.2%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0018720812456870">
<title>Seating location</title>
<p>The mean of this distance to the blackboard was 398.04 cm with a mean angle 30.71°. A proportion of 76.7% students turned their heads less than 45°, and 23.3% had to turn more than 45° to see the center of the blackboard. For many children (25.5%), seating locations were not changed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0018720812456870">
<title>School furniture</title>
<p>A majority (95.6%) of the students sat on a chair with a backrest but no hand rests, and 2.1% sat on a common bench. For more than 99% of the students, the seats were made of wood and not cushioned. A backrest was present in 97.7% of seats. Most (52.8%) of the students used the backrest sometimes only.</p>
<p>A higher proportion (78.3%) of the students were provided with an individual desk, and 21.7% were given a common desk. Desks for a majority (98.1%) of students were made of wood. Desk surface was horizontal for 84.9% and sloped for 15.1% of students. A footrest was present in 81.6% desks.</p>
<p>A mismatch of desk-chair combination occurs if the buttock-popliteal length is &lt;80% or &gt;95% of seat depth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0018720812456870">Parcells et al., 1999</xref>). The buttock-popliteal length of the children was not complying with the seat depth for a total of 87.3% children.</p>
<p>A mismatch of popliteal height and seat height exists if the seat height is either &gt;95% or &lt;88% of the popliteal height (shoe sole thickness was included in popliteal height). This measurement allows for popliteal clearance of between 5% and 12% of popliteal height (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0018720812456870">Parcells et al., 1999</xref>). A majority (79.8%) of seats did not comply with this requirement.</p>
<p>The legroom height of the desk should be more than the space rendered by popliteal height + 200 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0018720812456870">Pheasant, 1991</xref>). Such a mismatch was observed in 1,226 (76.3%) desks and chairs provided to the study population.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0018720812456870">
<title>Carriage of school material</title>
<p>Bags of different models are used by schoolchildren to carry books and amenities. These models include backpacks, shoulder bags, trolley bags, and suitcases. Carrying school material in hand without a bag was specified as “hand carriage.” A majority (79.6%) used backpacks to carry their books and amenities to the school. A proportion of 17.9% used shoulder bags. Use of other models was fairly low (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0018720812456870">Table 2</xref>). Nearly 97% of children carried the bag themselves.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Table 2:</label>
<caption><p>Details on Selected Aspects of Carriage of School Material</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0018720812456870" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="center">Frequency</th>
<th align="center">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Bag model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hand carriage</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Backpack</td>
<td>1279</td>
<td>79.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Shoulder bag</td>
<td>288</td>
<td>17.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Trolley bag</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Suitcase</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>2.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Total</td>
<td>1,607</td>
<td>100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Person who carried the bag</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Always by the child</td>
<td>1,557</td>
<td>96.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sometimes by others</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Always by others</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Total</td>
<td>1,607</td>
<td>100.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The internationally accepted healthy bag model for school children is a backpack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0018720812456870">Goodgold, 2005</xref>). Children using a backpack model (<italic>n</italic> = 1,279) were assessed for recommended features: two contoured and padded shoulder straps, movability of straps, a waist belt, and multiple compartments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0018720812456870">Goodgold, 2005</xref>). Students should use both shoulder straps and tighten the waist belt.</p>
<p>Of the backpacks observed, 89.6% of backpacks were not compartmentalized, 99.4% had movable straps, and 91.6% had padded shoulder straps. A waist belt was present in 29.5% backpacks, and only 30.5% of students used it. A majority (97.1%) of the students carried the backpack on both shoulders, and only 2.9% carried the backpack in other styles.</p>
<p>A school classroom should have proper and safe storage facilities for students to keep school materials. None of the classrooms studied had such storage facilities for students.</p>
<p>The mean weight of the schoolbag was 3.72 kg (<italic>SD</italic> = 1.05; range = 0.45 to 8.30). Mean schoolbag weight as a proportion of body weight was 11.04% (<italic>SD</italic> = 3.88; range = 1.27 to 29.28). The current internationally recommended cutoff for the weight of the schoolbag as a percentage of the total body weight is 10% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0018720812456870">Chia &amp; Wong, 2002</xref>). A bag weighing more than the international cutoff was carried by 57.9% of children. Textbooks accounted for an average of 36.7% of the total weight of the bag; other books, 30.4%; and nonbook items, 17.7%. Most (96.9%) students always carried their schoolbag by themselves (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0018720812456870">Table 2</xref>). Mean carrying distance of the bag was 3.87 km (<italic>SD</italic> = 4.68; range = 0.1 to 40.0), and mean carrying time was 24.07 min (<italic>SD</italic> = 15.8; range = 0.0 to 90.0).</p>
<p>The evidence on bag weight as a fraction of body weight in many countries is often greater than the accepted limits. For example, nearly 50% of Saudi children carried backpacks weighing more than 10% of their weight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0018720812456870">Al-Hazzaa, 2006</xref>), and 35% of Italian schoolchildren carried more than 30% of their bodyweight at least once a week (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0018720812456870">Negrini et al., 1999</xref>). Bag weight as a proportion of body weight is 13.2% in New Zealand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0018720812456870">Whittfield &amp; Legg, 1999</xref>) and 12% to 13% in the United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0018720812456870">National Back Pain Association, 1997</xref>). Singapore adopts a limit of 12% of body weight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0018720812456870">Chia &amp; Wong, 2002</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0018720812456870">
<title>Negative effects</title>
<p>Almost three quarters (72%) of the children reported that they perceived at least some level of discomfort having to carry school material, and 62% of students reported a moderate to severe level of general tiredness at the end of school sessions.</p>
<p>Musculoskeletal pain among children was categorized into three groups according to the recall period and frequency of occurrence. The <italic>acute pain</italic> category includes children who reported musculoskeletal pain only during the last 2 weeks. During the period from commencement of academic year to 2 weeks prior to the time of the study, children who experienced pain only once during this period were included in the <italic>one-time pain</italic> category, and those who experienced recurrent episodes of pain during the same period were categorized as <italic>recurrent pain</italic>.</p>
<p>The prevalence of recurrent musculoskeletal pain among the study group was highest (35.9%), and acute-pain and one-time-pain groups showed a prevalence of 19.0% and 16.2%, respectively. Nearly 29% of students had no musculoskeletal pain. This finding meant that a larger proportion (71.2%) of children reported any musculoskeletal pain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0018720812456870">Table 3</xref>). Knees (28.8%), lower back (26.5%), and shoulders (23.2%) were the most common locations where musculoskeletal pain occurred in the children. A proportion of 63%, nearly two thirds of the study population, located pain in more than two anatomical points (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0018720812456870">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Table 3:</label>
<caption><p>Prevalence of Musculoskeletal Pain According to Pain Categories</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0018720812456870" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Pain Category</th>
<th align="center">Population Size (<italic>n</italic>)</th>
<th align="center">Prevalence Estimate (%)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% Confidence Interval</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>No pain</td>
<td>463</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>[26.7, 31.0]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Acute pain</td>
<td>306</td>
<td>19.0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>[17.2, 21.0]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One-time pain</td>
<td>261</td>
<td>16.2</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>[14.5, 18.1]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recurrent pain</td>
<td>577</td>
<td>35.9</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>[33.6, 38.3]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>1607</td>
<td>100.0</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Table 4:</label>
<caption><p>Prevalence of Musculoskeletal Pain in Anatomical Sites</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0018720812456870" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Anatomical Site</th>
<th align="center">Population Size (<italic>n</italic>)</th>
<th align="center">Prevalence Estimate (%)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% Confidence Interval</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Knees</td>
<td>463</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>[26.7, 31.1]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lower back</td>
<td>392</td>
<td>24.4</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>[22.4, 26.5]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Shoulders</td>
<td>373</td>
<td>23.2</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>[21.2, 25.3]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ankles/feet</td>
<td>279</td>
<td>17.4</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>[15.6, 19.3]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neck</td>
<td>242</td>
<td>15.1</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>[13.4, 16.9]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Upper back</td>
<td>177</td>
<td>11.0</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>[9.6, 12.6]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Elbows</td>
<td>123</td>
<td>7.7</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>[6.5, 9.1]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wrists/hands</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>7.0</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>[5.9, 8.4]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hips/thigh</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>[3.6, 5.7]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Although many children reported that pain had no effect at all, a significant proportion, more than 50%, reported at least a little effect on either school attendance or academic performance.</p>
<p>In the univariate analysis, of the variables considered, female gender (OR = 1.52), urban-sector school (OR = 1.66), presence of severe general tiredness (OR = 2.99), abnormal total difficulties score (OR = 2.02), knowledge of a person with musculoskeletal pain (OR = 1.97), and mismatched seat depth with buttock-popliteal length of chair (OR = 1.59) were related to a high risk for having recurrent musculoskeletal pain. Shoulder backpack carriage (OR = 0.06), proper use of waist belt (OR = 0.57), use of backrest (OR = 0.55), and sleeping on a bed with a mattress (OR = 0.79) lowered the risk of having such pain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0018720812456870">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Table 5:</label>
<caption><p>Correlates of Recurrent Musculoskeletal Pain (Unadjusted)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0018720812456870" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Contributory Factor</th>
<th align="center">OR [95% CI]</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Female gender</td>
<td>1.52 [1.17, 1.97]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Urban sector</td>
<td>1.66 [1.25, 2.21]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Severe general tiredness</td>
<td>2.99 [2.10, 4.24]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Abnormal psychiatric status</td>
<td>2.02 [1.41, 2.89]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Knowledge of a person with musculoskeletal pain</td>
<td>1.97 [1.51, 2.56]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mismatched seat depth with buttock-popliteal length</td>
<td>1.59 [1.07, 2.36]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Both-shoulders backpack carriage</td>
<td>0.06 [0.03, 0.12]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Proper use of waist belt</td>
<td>0.57 [0.34, 0.98]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Use of backrest</td>
<td>0.55 [0.37, 0.81]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleeping on a bed with a mattress</td>
<td>0.79 [0.56, 1.11]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0018720812456870">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. OR = odds ratio; CI = confidence interval.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the regression model, only eight variables were found to be significant correlates of recurrent musculoskeletal pain. Even then, one ergonomic factor, mismatched seat depth with buttock-popliteal length of chair, posed 1.65 times the risk of recurrent musculoskeletal pain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0018720812456870">Table 6</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Table 6:</label>
<caption><p>Correlates of Recurrent Musculoskeletal Pain (Adjusted)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0018720812456870" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Predictor Variable</th>
<th align="center">Exp β (OR)</th>
<th align="center">95% Confidence Interval</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Urban sector</td>
<td>1.633</td>
<td>[1.198, 2.226]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female gender</td>
<td>1.427</td>
<td>[1.078, 1.890]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleeping on a bed with a mattress</td>
<td>0.669</td>
<td>[0.463, 0.967]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Presence of severe general tiredness</td>
<td>2.323</td>
<td>[1.603, 3.365]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Presence of functional disability</td>
<td>2.153</td>
<td>[1.624, 2.855]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Abnormal psychiatric status</td>
<td>1.722</td>
<td>[1.167, 2.541]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Knowledge of a person with musculoskeletal pain</td>
<td>1.762</td>
<td>[1.332, 2.330]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mismatched seat depth with buttock-popliteal length</td>
<td>1.646</td>
<td>[1.070, 2.532]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0018720812456870">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. OR = odds ratio.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0018720812456870">
<title>Major Findings of the Survey</title>
<p>With the findings of our study we concluded the following:</p>
<list id="list3-0018720812456870" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Many children did experience discomfort related to substandard seating arrangements in the classroom. A significant proportion had to turn their necks to see the blackboard. For many children, seating locations were not changed.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>There were widespread incompatibilities of classroom furniture with anthropometric dimensions of children.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A majority of children perceived discomfort contributed by mismatched classroom furniture.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>There were several deficiencies with regard to carriage of schoolbags. Deficiencies were noted in weight (almost 58% of children carried a bag weighing more than the international cutoff of 10%), model (nearly 20% did not use a healthy model), ergonomic features (not compartmentalized in 90%, no waist belt in 70.5%), and the carrying behavior of bags (only 30.5% used the waist belt).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Children experienced several negative effects, especially musculoskeletal pain, in part attributable to mismatched ergonomic factors.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Despite the existence of many deficiencies in ergonomic parameters, only a few parameters became significant as causing negative effects on children. We must also take into consideration that the capacity of the adolescents to withstand the stresses of an ergonomic mismatch is dependent on a range of other factors in adolescence. These include differences in musculoskeletal maturation, psychosocial influence of self-reporting in this group, and influence of extra-academic activities. Ergonomic mismatches were widespread. Therefore, the students may show a habitual adjustment to furniture size, perhaps reflecting compensatory mechanisms despite the existence of ergonomic incompatibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0018720812456870">Milanese &amp; Grimmer, 2004</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0018720812456870">
<title>Phase 2: Intervention</title>
<p>The study revealed the need for major improvements in several ergonomic parameters within the classrooms. We considered it important to translate research findings into action. We adopted three strategies: dissemination of research findings, provision of feasible solutions, and advocacy.</p>
<sec id="section29-0018720812456870">
<title>Dissemination of Research Findings</title>
<p>We shared our research outcomes and recommendations with the Ministry of Education and other relevant stakeholders and had a joint media seminar with them to spread the information to the general public. Several articles were published in print media highlighting the gravity of the issue.</p>
<p>We disseminated the research findings also at international conferences to share and update good practice evidence in an attempt to obtain constructive inputs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0018720812456870">
<title>Provision of Feasible Solutions</title>
<p>Research findings necessitated identification of priority areas and formulation of feasible solutions to improve the current status. As mentioned earlier, there are about 4 million government schoolchildren in nearly 9,400 in Sri Lanka schools. Change of classroom furniture may require substantial financial cost as well as a complex process. Taking into account several factors, including feasibility of implementation and acceptability by the schoolchildren and their parents, we decided that issues related to schoolbags should be a priority area for intervention.</p>
<p>Solutions were contemplated on strategies for bag weight reduction, introduction of a model healthy bag, and bag behavior changes.</p>
<sec id="section31-0018720812456870">
<title>Strategies for bag weight reduction</title>
<p>In Sri Lanka, the Ministry of Education is responsible for the state-sector schools, which cater to about 95% of the school-going population. There is a well-organized administrative structure that facilitates implementation of programs at the school level. Thus, sharing of research outcomes and recommendations with the Ministry of Education stimulated the consideration of strategies to lower the weight of books that have to be carried in the schoolbag, for example, splitting textbooks into several volumes and recommending only 80-page writing exercise books.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-0018720812456870">
<title>Introduction of a model schoolbag</title>
<p>The need for modeling a healthy schoolbag was imperative. Available evidence on methods children adopt to carry their books and amenities to school shows that of the load-carrying models, hand carriage causes the maximum and backpack (rucksack) causes the minimum physiological distress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0018720812456870">Malhotra &amp; Sengupta, 1965</xref>). Backpack is the healthiest schoolbag model for load carriage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0018720812456870">Goodgold, 2005</xref>). Inputs were obtained from the International Ergonomic Association and from consultations with experts. Healthy bags designed in other countries were also studied. A healthy schoolbag was modeled by the principal investigator according to ergonomic standards and on the basis of principles of biomechanics. This sample bag was locally manufactured and was based on an ergonomically designed healthy bag approved by the Australian Chiropractic Association.</p>
<p>Key features of a “healthy schoolbag” were as follows:</p>
<list id="list4-0018720812456870" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Rectangular shape with rounded edges to accommodate elongated textbooks and to minimize rolling of edges of textbooks provided free by the government</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Two compartments to facilitate putting heavier books closer to the body and the center of gravity and to minimize relative movement of contents of bag when the child is walking and running</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Minimum additional space: Single front space for the lunchbox and two specific pockets in both sides for the water bottle and pencil box</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Wide and cushioned shoulder straps to minimize pressure on nerves and vessels of the shoulder and to provide additional comfort</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Waist belt to transmit the weight of the bag to the hip region</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Movable buckles in shoulder straps and waist belts to facilitate fixing the bag snugly to the body</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Well-padded back wall to provide comfort to the back of the chest of the child with the loaded bag</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The Sri Lanka Standards Institute was consulted for physical quality assurance. The sample bag was evaluated by experts, teachers, and children. Recommendations on the healthy schoolbag and implementation strategies were sent to the Ministry of Education.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-0018720812456870">
<title>Implementation of healthy schoolbag campaign</title>
<p>The National Schoolbag Regulatory Committee was established to monitor implementation of the healthy schoolbag campaign. Following successive meetings, based on opinions of textile engineers, bag manufacturers, and ergonomists, several modifications were made in the model bag and the implementation strategies. These include the following: (a) Ministry of Education to be considered the implementation agency, (b) Ministry of Health and Sri Lanka Standards Institute to provide technical guidance, (c) national standards on schoolbags to be formulated, (d) backpacks to be introduced in the market in different colors and with pictures to cater to children choices, (e) many physical quality parameters (cushion thickness, stitching, buckle specification, waist belt location, smaller hanging loop, etc.) to be added, and (f) surveillance mechanism to be set up to monitor compliance by bag manufacturers.</p>
<p>Bag manufacturers were registered by the Ministry of Education and were educated on the healthy bag concept, ergonomic features, implications of features, and technical know-how in the manufacturing process. Registered manufacturers were requested to make a sample healthy bag to be evaluated for quality assurance. Sample bags from bag manufacturers were evaluated by the regulatory committee, and bags that complied with healthy standards were awarded a healthy bag logo certified by the Ministry of Education (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0018720812456870">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Healthy schoolbag logo.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The National Healthy Schoolbag Initiative was launched at the commencement of the academic year in January 2011 as a joint project of the Ministries of Health and Education. Schoolbags in five sizes were introduced to the market by registered bag manufacturers from all throughout the country. The secretary of the Ministry of Education issued a circualr with input from the health sector. The circular specified all the aspects of implementation, including the roles of principal, class teacher, parents, and children; healthy schoolbag specifications; and instructions on how to choose and wear the bag.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section34-0018720812456870">
<title>Behavior changes</title>
<p>What is important is not only the healthy bag with ergonomic features but also the correct bag behavior. Behavior changes necessitate multiple approaches. Children, parents, and teachers should be educated through different strategies. A chapter on schoolbag and ergonomic behavior in the Grade 8 science textbook was written by the principal investigator. A leaflet providing information on correct selection, ergonomic features, and proper bag behavior was prepared and distributed to all the schools by the Ministry of Education, and also it was mandatory to include the same in all the healthy schoolbags approved by the Ministry of Education. Information leaflets in vivid forms were designed and released to the media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0018720812456870">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Health education leaflets.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-0018720812456870">
<title>Media explosion</title>
<p>We adopted what we call “a media explosion strategy” to disseminate information quickly and deeply. We used both print and electronic media. Numerous televison programs, prime-time newscasts, newspaper headlines, articles in women’s magazines, and e-mail communications showed the depth of the penetration of our media strategy. One newspaper article branded the bag “<italic>dosthara mahaththayage poth malla</italic>” in Sinhala, meaning “Doctor’s schoolbag” depicting the warm and respectful welcome of the new intervention by the general public. It even appeared in cartoons.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section36-0018720812456870">
<title>Awareness campaigns</title>
<p>Doctors, including first-contact phsicians, public health workers, and peripheral health administrators, were made aware of the initiative and their role. Information was included in the Sri Lanka Medical Association newsletter. Several community awareness campaigns were conducted at educational exhibitions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section37-0018720812456870">
<title>Advocacy</title>
<p>Advocacy of policy makers, ministers, administrative officers, health program managers, and health care professionals in both health and education sectors played a crucial role. Both Ministers of Health and Education were updated on the project.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section38-0018720812456870">
<title>Challenges and the Way Forward</title>
<p>Naturally, a multidisciplinary project of this nature would have to face a multitutde of challenges. However, even if the problems faced are of lesser magnitude, sharing such experiences will enlighten prospective workers who would contemplate similar strategies.</p>
<sec id="section39-0018720812456870">
<title>Commercial</title>
<p>Schoolbag manufacture in Sri Lanka is largely a home-based industry. The schoolbag market in the country is dominated by a few bag manufacturing companies who purchase all homemade bags and redistribute them throughout the country. Some bag manufacturing companies, without registering or complying with standards, tagged a fake logo in one of their bag models and marketed it at a higher price. This problem was dealt with successfully, and such companies withdrew the substandard bags. Some “registered” bag manufacturers deliberately raised the prices of their bags, implying that they were of high quality. Few principals of schools negotiated with local registered bag manufacturers for commercial gains, which resulted in higher prices of healthy bags. These problems were highlighted by certain media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0018720812456870">Figure 5</xref>). Discussions were held with bag manufacturers’ associations to rectify the situation. They agreed to continue bag production at a reasonable price.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0018720812456870" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Media reaction.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0018720812456870-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section40-0018720812456870">
<title>General public</title>
<p>Education, from the primary to tertiary, is totally free in Sri Lanka. Not only all the textbooks but even school uniforms are provided by the government to all schoolchildren. With the issue of a circular on the implementation of healthy schoolbags by the Ministry of Education, the media with vested interests created a public outcry that the government should provide these bags free to all children.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section41-0018720812456870">
<title>Customer satisfaction</title>
<p>Although the introduced model allows room for diverse outputs of schoolbags, a rigid specification of features of healthy bags was not liked by users (schoolchildren) as well as producers (bag manufacturers). There was specific concern about the rectangular shape, which was included to cater to the Ministry of Education’s requirement to safeguard free textbooks from rolling and damaging their edges.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section42-0018720812456870">
<title>Political</title>
<p>The opposition political parties and trade unions in the education sector, waiting for an issue, tried to capitalize on the issue. According to a news item on a local radio station, one extreme political party issued a statement accusing the government of “pickpocketing” 200 rupees from each bag bought by the schoolchildren. Steps were taken to make the minister of education, minister of health, and secretary to his excellency, the president, to streamline and sustain the project. Positive outcomes were achieved.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section43-0018720812456870">
<title>Professional</title>
<p>This aspect is important: how to deal with our professional colleagues. There were issues with regard to ownership of the campaign between the two ministries as well as among the personalities involved within the ministries. The writer pioneered the project on his personal interest and not as an official obligation. However, with his lead role and commitment, many issues could be settled.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section44-0018720812456870">
<title>Media</title>
<p>Media played a dual role in the campaign by promoting and penetrating the concept among the general public and also by highlighting the deficiencies. Some media were biased, highlighting only negative aspects. However, with concerted efforts, media are right on track in promoting healthy schoolbag to the nation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section45-0018720812456870">
<title>Administrative</title>
<p>The National Schoolbag Regulatory Committee lacked administrative power. The interest shown by different members was based on their agenda and the stake or the credit they expected to achieve through this project. Discussions are under way to coordinate fragmented approaches of the Ministry of Education, the Ministry of Health, and the Sri Lanka Standards Institute led by the author. The National Schoolbag Regulatory Committee will be strengthened to monitor the implementation of the national healthy schoolbag campaign. The Sri Lanka Medical Association, the apex body in the medical profession in Sri Lanka, has already indicated a green light to make the doctor community aware of ergonomics in relevant specialities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section46-0018720812456870">
<title>Legal</title>
<p>In addition, we are developing a specific standard for schoolbags in consultation with the Sri Lanka Standards Institute. The draft was distributed for public comments and is in the final stage of implementation. When Sri Lanka Standards Institute standards are in force, it provides a legal framework for manufacturing schoolbags in Sri Lanka.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section47-0018720812456870">
<title>Financial</title>
<p>There were no specific finances allocated to the project except for the funds received for the research work. The sustainability of a campaign of this magnitude will depend on a strong background of funding. Negotiations are under way with international nongovernmental organizations on funding opportunities.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section48-0018720812456870">
<title>Outcome</title>
<p>We looked at the findings of this study at a collective level to plan and implement ergonomic interventions with overall positive effect. Findings of this study and follow-up activities highlight that the ergonomic parameters related to the classroom could be improved through simple changes. Nearly 4 million schoolchildren will be the beneficiaries of this project.</p>
<p>We could change the thinking of an entire nation. We could popularize the word <italic>ergonomics</italic> across many categories: rural folk, media, professionals, and politicians. In addition to promoting a healthy school environment for the child, we attempted to inculcate an ergonomic culture in a country where industrial development is likely to take an important place in the development scenario.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka is seen as a model developing country. Several international monetary agencies are using the Sri Lankan capacity built as “South-South training models” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0018720812456870">Yumkella, 2010</xref>). In such contexts of technology transfer, introduction of ergonomics at both macro- and microlevels will undoubtedly contribute to economic and human development. With an initial attempt of this nature, ergonomic concepts could be expanded in other areas also.</p>
<sec id="section49-0018720812456870">
<title>Recognition</title>
<p>This project was well received by the general public. There were numerous appreciations in the media. The author was invited to the prestigious SLMA Oration 2010, the highest recognition for medical research, awarded by the Sri Lanka Medical Association.</p>
<p>Going forward, most importantly, there needs to be a continuous focus on awareness programs on healthy schoolbags and proper behavior changes. This good practice needs to be disseminated globally, since the problem is similar throughout the world.</p>
<p>The challenge for the future is to improve all aspects of ergonomics in the classroom environment for all schoolchildren throughout the world. We consider this only as a beginning.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section50-0018720812456870">
<title>Key Points</title>
<list id="list5-0018720812456870" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Schoolchildren in Sri Lanka experienced several negative effects, especially musculoskeletal pain, in part attributable to widespread incompatibilities in ergonomic arrangements in the school educational environment.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>There were many deficiencies in carriage of school material. Deficiencies were noted in weight, model, ergonomic features, and the carrying behavior of bags.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The schoolbag issue was considered a priority area, and an ergonomic bag was modeled and introduced at the national level to benefit 4 million schoolchildren.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>This study represents an inspiring story of inculcating ergonomics in an industrially developing country engaging with health, education, political, and business stakeholders to adopt ergonomics interventions in school educational envioronments.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The assistance given by the following individuals to make this project a success is greatly appreciated: Dulitha N. Fernando (supervisor of the research project and member of the Faculty of Medicine, University of Colombo), Saman Jayanetti (cosupervisor of the research project and consultant rheumatologist, Lady Ridgeway Children’s Hospital), Rohini Ranwala (consultant anesthetist, National Hospital of Sri Lanka), Nelli Rajaratne (program officer of school health, Family Health Bureau), Vineetha Karunaratne (director of maternal and child health, Family Health Bureau), the late Cherryl Bennet (ergonomist and pioneer in school ergonomics, International Ergonomic Association), Chris McIntyre (ergonomist, Canada), Karen Jacobs (cochair, International Ergonomic Association, ECEE), David Caple (past president, International Ergonomic Association), and Leon Straker (School of Physiotherapy, Faculty of Health Sciences, Curtin University, Australia). This work was funded by the School Health Unit of the Family Health Bureau, Ministry of Health, under the Health Sector Development Project of World Bank.</p>
</ack>
<bio>
<p>Kapila Jayaratne is a medical doctor specializing in public health and child health. He holds master’s (2004) and doctorate degrees (2007) in community medicine from the University of Colombo, Sri Lanka, and had postdoctoral training at the University of Melbourne in Australia. He currently works as the national program manager for maternal and child mortality and morbidity surveillance at the Family Health Bureau of the Ministry of Health of Sri Lanka. He has conducted several epidemiological studies on the health of school-age children and pregnant mothers. He has presented more than 35 papers at international academic forums and authored several articles in addition to disseminating in both print and electronic media. He has always attempted to translate research findings into action. He strives to expand ergonomics in industrially developing countries.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Al-Hazzaa</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>School backpack: How much load do Saudi school boys carry on their shoulders?</article-title> <source>Saudi Medical Journal</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1567</fpage>–<lpage>1571</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arambewela</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>, <month>September</month> <day>2</day>). <article-title>School bags on students’ health warrants serious attention</article-title>. <source>Daily News</source>, p.<fpage>17</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Central Bank of Sri Lanka</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Annual report of Central Bank of Sri Lanka</source>. <publisher-loc>Colombo, Sri Lanka</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>J. W. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T. K. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Anthropometric evaluation for primary school furniture design</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Small backs need minding</article-title>. <source>ACHPER Australian Healthy Lifestyles Journal</source>, <volume>49</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>), <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>, <fpage>25</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>D. H. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effect of load carriage on spinal compression</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dul</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carayon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falzon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marras</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname> . . . van der Doelen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A strategy for human factors/ergonomics: Developing the discipline and profession</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodgold</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Backpack intelligence: Implementation of a backpack safety program with fifth grade students</article-title>. <source>Orthopaedic Practice</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gouvali</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boudolos</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Match between school furniture dimensions and children’s anthropometry</article-title>. <source>Applied Ergonomics</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>773</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grimmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Gender-age environmental associates of adolescent low back pain</article-title>. <source>Applied Ergonomics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gunathilaka</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>April</month> <day>26</day>). <article-title>Pasal poth begaya daruwanta bara wediyi</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Schoolbags are heavy for children</trans-title>]. <source>Lakbima</source>, p. <fpage>25</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gunzburg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balague</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szpalski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duyck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mélot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Low back pain in a population of school children</article-title>. <source>European Spine Journal</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harreby</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nygaard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jessen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Storr-Paulsen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname> . . . Laegaard</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Risk factors for low back pain in a cohort of 1389 Danish school children: an epidemiologic study</article-title>. <source>European Spine Journal</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jayakody</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>July</month> <day>27</day>). <article-title>School bag: A threat to students’ health?</article-title> <source>Daily Mirror</source>, p.<fpage>1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jayalath</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>August</month> <day>31</day>). <article-title>Beri bara kare thiyan akurata yana ape lamayi</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Children going to school with heavy weight on back</trans-title>]. <source>Dinamina</source>, p. <fpage>6</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jayarathna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>July</month> <day>26</day>). <article-title>Pasal begaya barayi</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Schoolbag is heavy</trans-title>]. <source>Silumina</source>, p. <fpage>4</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jayasinghe</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>, <month>August</month> <day>10</day>). <article-title>Bara wediyi: Apata konde amaruwa</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Heavy weight: We have got back pain</trans-title>]. <source>Silumina</source>, p.<fpage>35</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Korovessis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koureas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papazisis</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Correlation between backpack weight and way of carrying, sagittal and frontal spinal curvatures, athletic activity, and dorsal and low back pain in schoolchildren and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Spinal Disorders &amp; Techniques</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Legg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Ergonomics in schools</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1523</fpage>–<lpage>1529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <article-title>Carrying of schoolbags by children</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Milanese</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grimmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>School furniture and the user population: An anthropometric perspective</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>National Back Pain Association</collab>. (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>NBPA school bag survey ’97: Findings and recommendations</article-title>. <source>NBPA Newsletter–Talkback</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Negrini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carabalona</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sibila</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Backpack as a daily load for schoolchildren</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>354</volume>, <year>1974</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oates</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>An anthropometric and postural risk assessment of children’s school computer work environments</article-title>. <source>Computers in the Schools</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Özgül</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akalan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuchimov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uygur</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temelli</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polat</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>During asymmetrical backpack loading: Is unloaded side of body segments truly unloaded?</article-title> <source>Journal of Biomechanics</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Panagiotopoulou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christoulas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papanckolaou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandroukas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Classroom furniture dimensions and anthropometric measures in primary school</article-title>. <source>Applied Ergonomics</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parcells</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stommel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Mismatch of classroom furniture and student body dimensions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adolescent Health</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pheasant</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>The ergonomics of seating: Work and health</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McMillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prashan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>November</month> <day>30</day>). <article-title>Doo daruwanta bara adu poth mallak</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Lighter schoolbag for our kids</trans-title>]. <source>Nawaliya</source>, p. <fpage>12</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Oviedo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruano-Ravina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perez-Rios</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>F. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gomez-Fernandez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandez-Alonso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname> . . . Turiso</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>School children’s backpacks, back pain and back pathologies</article-title>. <source>Archives of Disease in Childhood</source>. Advance online publication.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effects of backpack load position on spatiotemporal parameters and trunk forward lean</article-title>. <source>Gait &amp; Posture</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The ergonomics of learning: Educational design and learning performance</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1530</fpage>–<lpage>1546</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Szpalski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gunzburg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balagué</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mélot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A 2-year prospective longitudinal study on low back pain in primary school children</article-title>. <source>European Spine Journal</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Troussier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davoine</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaudemaris</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phelip</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). Back pain in schoolchildren: A study among <year>1178</year> pupils. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Rehabilitation Medicine</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Viry</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Creveuil</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Nonspecific back pain in children: A search for associated factors in 14 year old schoolchildren</article-title>. <source>Revue du Rhumatisme</source> (<edition>English</edition> ed.), <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whittfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Legg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<conf-date>1999, November</conf-date>). <source>Schoolbag weight and musculoskeletal symptoms in New Zealand secondary schools</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the 9th Conference of the New Zealand Ergonomics Society</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Christchurch, New Zealand</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>. (<year>1996</year>). <source>Promoting health through schools: A summary and recommendations of WHO’s Expert Committee on Comprehensive School Health Education and Promotion</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0018720812456870">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yumkella</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Sri Lanka model developing country, but challenges in industrial, export sectors remain, says UNIDO Director-General</article-title>. <source>News &amp; Events–UNIDO</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unido.org/index.php?id=7881&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=482&amp;cHash=2d60c61346">http://www.unido.org/index.php?id=7881&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=482&amp;cHash=2d60c61346</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>