<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OPP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spopp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Oncol Pharm Pract</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Oncology Pharmacy Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-1552</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-092X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078155212451196</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078155212451196</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Determination of exposure of dispensary drug preparers to cyclophosphamide by passive sampling and liquid chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wakui</surname><given-names>Nobuyuki</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1078155212451196">Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, Japan; Department of Pharmacy, Kawasaki Municipal Kawasaki Hospital, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ookubo</surname><given-names>Tetuo</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1078155212451196">Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>Yusuke</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1078155212451196">Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Rie</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff4-1078155212451196">Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitui</surname><given-names>Miyuki</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff5-1078155212451196">Department of Pharmacy, Kawasaki Municipal Kawasaki Hospital, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>Yuichi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff6-1078155212451196">Department of Pharmacy, Kawasaki Municipal Kawasaki Hospital, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Koichi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff7-1078155212451196">Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>Hiroyuki</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1078155212451196"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff8-1078155212451196">Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078155212451196">Hiroyuki Nakazawa, Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hoshi University, 2-4-41 Ebara, Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo 142-8501, Japan. Email: <email>drhironakazawa@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Objectives:</bold> To determine cyclophosphamide exposure to preparers during tablet crushing and subsequent handling by analyzing indoor air collected using a high-performance volatile organic compounds-solvent desorption (VOC-SD) passive air sampler.</p>
<p><bold>Methods:</bold> The passive sampler was taped to the mask over the mouth of the preparer and indoor air was collected during crushing and preparation of cyclophosphamide tablets (Endoxan®). After collection, the carbon molecular sieve adsorbent of the passive sampler was placed in a centrifuge tube, and 1 mL of carbon disulfide was used to elute cyclophosphamide from the adsorbent. Liquid–liquid extraction with 1 mL of water was performed, and the aqueous phase was used as the test solution. Cyclophosphamide concentration was determined by liquid chromatography with ultraviolet and tandem mass spectrometry detection.</p>
<p><bold>Results:</bold> Cyclophosphamide concentration was detected in the range of 7.6–157.7 ng/sampler. Our results showed that low-level exposure occurred near the mouth of the preparer, which could present risks for long-term exposure, especially if combined with multiple toxic drug exposures.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> The anticancer drug monitoring methodology described here is a simple exposure assessment that can be used to ensure the safety of hospital pharmacy tablet preparers. Furthermore, since the anticancer drug exposure risk is very high for preparers, preparation should be in hood or with face mask.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cyclophosphamide</kwd>
<kwd>anticancer drugs</kwd>
<kwd>passive air sampler</kwd>
<kwd>liquid chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1078155212451196" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Many anticancer drugs used in cancer chemotherapy are cytotoxic, mutagenic and teratogenic, and carcinogenic side-effects are known to occur frequently in treated patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078155212451196">1</xref></sup> These side-effects have also been reported in cases of secondary carcinogenesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078155212451196">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212451196">3</xref></sup> The guidelines of the International Agency for Research on Cancer of the World Health Organization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078155212451196">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078155212451196">5</xref></sup> have classified many anticancer drugs according to their carcinogenicity into Group 1 (carcinogenic to humans) and Group 2 (high risk of carcinogenicity to humans).</p>
<p>Medical professionals who work with anticancer drugs, such as doctors, pharmacists and nurses, are at a high risk of exposure from multiple sources, including direct inhalation of aerosolized particles during preparation, adherence of particulates to the skin and eyes, and ingestion from food touched with contaminated hands.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078155212451196">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078155212451196">7</xref></sup> For this reason, Australia, Canada, Norway, Sweden, Britain, USA and other developed countries have created guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1078155212451196">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1078155212451196"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1078155212451196"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1078155212451196"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1078155212451196"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1078155212451196"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1078155212451196"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1078155212451196">15</xref></sup> for anticancer drug handling. In Japan, under the supervision of the Japanese Society of Hospital Pharmacists the publication ‘Japan Guidelines for Clinical Evaluation of Anticancer Drugs’ (Japan Oncology Guidelines),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1078155212451196">16</xref></sup> a revision of the ‘Guidelines for Anticancer Treatment in Hospitals,’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1078155212451196">17</xref></sup> was created in 2005 and provided to healthcare workers exposed to anticancer drugs. Based on these guidelines, mixing of anticancer drugs for injections is now commonly performed in safety cabinets, and anticancer drug preparation now requires adequate measures for prevention of exposure, such as wearing caps, masks, goggles, gowns and gloves. Although there are industrial safety and health laws in Japan for the safety of workers, labor regulations for anticancer drug handling in hospitals are still insufficient.</p>
<p>Cyclophosphamide (CPA) is frequently used as an anticancer drug. CPA vaporization phenomena have been reported,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1078155212451196">18</xref></sup> and exposure can occur from splashing during preparation even at room temperature. In addition to contamination due to intravenous injections and residual liquid drops during anticancer drug replacement at bedside, there is a concern that contamination of hospital wards may occur from leakage of urine during treatment of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1078155212451196">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Yoshida et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1078155212451196">20</xref></sup> reported that 11 ng/day of CPA was detected in the urine of anticancer drug preparers. They also detected one or more anticancer drugs on the door knobs and floors of control room entrances, boxes carried into the control room, wagons for dispensing injectables, wagon injection syringes adjusted for audit, dispensing units, floors of staff toilets and dining tables, desks and beds used by staff.</p>
<p>To understand the extent of anticancer drug contamination, we examined the presence of anticancer drugs throughout hospital rooms in a hospital pharmacy. Previously, numerous anticancer drug exposure studies analyzed swabs samples from safety cabinets and dispensing units,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1078155212451196">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1078155212451196"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1078155212451196"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1078155212451196">23</xref></sup> but real-time assessment related to exposure of individual preparers to anticancer drugs has not been reported. Therefore, the accuracy of previous studies involving exposure of healthcare workers to anticancer drugs is debatable. In addition, CPA, methotrexate, and 5-fluorouracil (CMF) chemotherapy is often used for treating breast cancer. CPA is administered daily over 2 weeks in the form of oral Endoxan® tablets in the chemotherapy regimen. In the case of breast cancer patients with difficulty swallowing tablets, crushed tablet preparations made in Japan are often administered as powders because Endoxan® tablets cannot be prepared as suspensions. Therefore, the risk of exposure to scattered and/or volatile CPA has been a concern for health care workers who perform preparation and administration.</p>
<p>In this study, we measured the concentrations of CPA collected from air. In clinical practice, it is difficult to use generic active samplers for collection of airborne chemicals because of the difficulty in equipment installation and related problems such as sampling noise. On the other hand, passive samplers are easy to carry and provide a simple method for sample collection. In this study, passive samplers were used to collect indoor air to measure exposure of individual preparers to airborne contaminants. High-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) with ultraviolet detection (LC-UV) together with LC and tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) was performed to identify and measure the concentrations of airborne contaminants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1078155212451196" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec3-1078155212451196"><title>Materials and reagents</title>
<p>CPA, CPA-d<sub>4</sub> (internal standard), carbon disulfide (&gt;98%), hexane (&gt;95%), diethyl ether (&gt;98%) and HPLC grade methanol and acetonitrile were obtained from Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd. (Osaka, Japan). Toluene (&gt;99%) was obtained from Kanto Chemical Co., Inc. (Tokyo, Japan). Volatile organic compounds-solvent desorption (VOC-SD) passive air samplers were manufactured by Sigma-Aldrich Japan K.K (Tokyo, Japan). Face mask with ear loops (3-ply) was purchased from Shanghai Dochem Industries Co., Ltd. (London, England). HPLC grade water was produced using the Milli-Q water purification system (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). The nylon membrane filter (0.2 µm, 13 mm) was purchased from Nihon Pall Ltd. (Tokyo, Japan).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1078155212451196"><title>Preparation of CPA standard solution</title>
<p>The CPA standard stock solution was prepared by dissolving 1000 µg/mL of CPA in acetonitrile. The standard stock was appropriately diluted with Milli-Q water to give standard solutions for the LC-UV calibration curve in the concentration range of 0.01–500 µg/mL and for the LC-MS/MS calibration curve in the concentration range of 0.01–300 ng/mL. CPA-d<sub>4</sub> stock solution was prepared by dissolving 10 µg/mL CPA-d<sub>4</sub> in acetonitrile and diluting it with Milli-Q water to obtain a 1 µg/mL standard solution.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1078155212451196"><title>Sample preparation and equipment</title>
<p>A commercially available porcelain mortar (15 cm in diameter) and pestle (12.5 cm in length) was used for grinding and mixing of drug tablets. An automatic powder packaging machine in a fully automatic machine rotating division system (YS-93WR-type SY; Yuyama Co., Ltd., Osaka, Japan) was used. Masks worn by the preparers were manufactured by Hogy Medical Co., Ltd. (Tokyo, Japan). Nanospace SI-2 3001 (Shiseido Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) was used for LC-UV. An Agilent Technologies 1100 Series LC (pump: Agilent 1100 G1312A, autosampler: Agilent 1100 G1316A; Agilent Technologies Inc., CA, USA) connected to an API4000™ tandem mass spectrometer (AB Sciex K.K, Tokyo, Japan) was used for LC-MS/MS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1078155212451196"><title>LC-UV and LC-MS/MS measurement conditions</title>
<p>The LC-UV analytical column was an Inertsil ODS-3 (4.6 × 150 mm<sup>2</sup>, 5 -µm i.d.) manufactured by GL Sciences Inc. (Tokyo, Japan), and the column oven was set at 40°C. The mobile phase was water:acetonitrile, 77:23 (v/v), flow rate was 0.7 mL/min, and injection volume was 20 µL. The UV detection wavelength was set at 205 nm. The analytical column used for LC-MS/MS was an L-column 2 ODS (2.1 × 150 mm<sup>2</sup>, 5 -µm i.d.) from GL Sciences Inc., and the column oven was set at 40°C. The mobile phase was water:acetonitrile, 70:30 (v/v), flow rate was 0.2 mL/min, and injection volume was 10 µL. Positive-ion electrospray ionization with multiple reaction monitoring (MRM) was used. MRM was performed to simultaneously monitor ions with CPA (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 261 → 140) and CPA-d<sub>4</sub> (internal standard: <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 265 → 140). The ionization voltage was 5500 V.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1078155212451196"><title>CPA sampling and extraction using the passive sampler</title>
<p>Crushing of dispensed Endoxan® tablets (Shionogi &amp; Co., Ltd., Osaka, Japan) for patients who needed CMF therapy was performed by five pharmacists according to the prescription (prescription example: Endoxan® tablet, one tablet once, twice a day, 7 days of administration).</p>
<p>After the preparer put on a lab coat, rubber gloves and mask, the passive sampler was fixed on the surface of the mask with cellophane tape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1078155212451196">Figure 1</xref>). The Endoxan® tablets were powdered by crushing, and then the automatic powder packaging machine located approximately 1.4 m from the preparation table was used to package the powder, and sampling was stopped by removing the passive sampler. The sampling time varied among the preparers, but was approximately 20 min. CPA recovery from the passive sampler was performed as follows. The adsorbent of the passive sampler was removed and placed in a test tube containing 10 µL of CPA-d<sub>4</sub> and 1 mL of carbon disulfide and allowed to stand for 5 min. Next, the adsorbent was removed from the carbon disulfide and placed in 1 mL of water. After stirring well, liquid–liquid extraction was performed. The solvent was then centrifuged at 3000 r/min for 5 min at 4°C. The test solution was obtained by collecting the aqueous phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1078155212451196">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig id="fig1-1078155212451196" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Fixed position of the passive sampler on the mask.</p>
<p>The passive sampler was fixed on the surface of the mask with cellophane tape.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451196-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-1078155212451196" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Flowchart of analysis of CPA adsorbed to the passive sampler.</p>
<p>CPA: cyclophosphamide; LC-UV: liquid chromatography with ultraviolet detection; LC-MS/MS: liquid chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry.</p>
<p>To measure CPA, 1 mL of carbon disulfide was used to desorb CPA from the carbon molecular sieve. Next, liquid–liquid extraction was performed with 1 mL of water. The obtained aqueous sample was measured by LC-UV and LC-MS/MS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451196-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1078155212451196" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec9-1078155212451196"><title>Validation of the CPA analytical method</title>
<p>The CPA standard was measured by LC-UV and LC-MS/MS. Good chromatographic peaks were obtained for both methods. In the LC-UV method, the limit of detection (LOD, signal to noise ratio = 3) was 0.01 µg/mL and limit of quantitation (LOQ, signal to noise ratio &gt; 10) was 0.05 µg/mL. Furthermore, in the LC-MS/MS method, LOD was 0.005 ng/mL and LOQ was 0.01 ng/mL. Good calibration curves were obtained for LC-UV and LC-MS/MS methods; the correlation coefficient <italic>r</italic> = 0.992 in the concentration range of 0.05–500 µg/mL for LC-UV, and <italic>r</italic> = 0.999 in the concentration range of 0.01–300 ng/mL for LC-MS/MS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1078155212451196"><title>CPA extraction from the passive sampler</title>
<p>As the CPA exposure risk was very high for the experimenter, a simple CPA extraction method for the passive sampler was used. A high-performance VOC-SD passive air sampler was used because of the ease in sampling and extraction and its high precision. Also, when the use of an indoor air suction pump for collection is not possible, a passive sampler can be used. The VOC-SD passive air sampler is capable of sampling volatile organic compounds such as limonene and pinene from indoor air. Although Supleco, Inc. suggested carbon disulfide as the desorption solvent, its application to a reversed-phase analytical column was found to be difficult. Instead, a liquid–liquid extraction (water, acetonitrile and methanol) which could be applied to the LC column was used. Good LC chromatograms were obtained using only water. Therefore, water was used as the liquid–liquid extraction solvent. In addition to carbon disulfide, diethyl ether, toluene, and hexane were also examined to select an optimum desorption solvent (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Good recovery of CPA (near 100%) was obtained when carbon disulfide was used as the desorption solvent and when water was used in liquid–liquid extraction of CPA.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1078155212451196"><title>Study of CPA desorption time</title>
<p>We studied CPA desorption time from the adsorbent using carbon disulfide.</p>
<p>After adding a fixed amount of CPA to the carbon molecular sieve adsorbent of the passive sampler, the adsorbent was allowed to stand for 1 h. Next, the optimum desorption time was calculated by adding carbon disulfide to the adsorbent for 0, 5, 10, 30, 60 and 90 min. Desorption was found to occur immediately (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1078155212451196">Figure 3</xref>), and desorption time was observed to be 5 min.
<fig id="fig3-1078155212451196" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Time profile of CPA extractability from the carbon molecular sieve.</p>
<p>CPA: cyclophosphamide.</p>
<p>The optimum desorption time was observed to be 5 min by adding carbon disulfide to the adsorbent for 0, 5, 10, 30, 60 and 90 min.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451196-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1078155212451196"><title>CPA exposure from tablet crushing and preparation</title>
<p>Sampling by the passive sampler was performed during tablet crushing with a mortar and pestle and packaging using the automatic powder packaging machine. The passive sampler was taped to the surface of the preparer’s mask to assess human CPA exposure. This operation was performed by 5 preparers, and the samples obtained (<italic>n</italic> = 5) were analyzed. Because the LC-UV values were close to LOD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1078155212451196">Figure 4</xref>), quantification was performed by LC-MS/MS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1078155212451196">Figure 5</xref>). The detected concentrations of CPA were in the range of 7.6–157.7 ng/sampler (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1078155212451196">Table 1</xref>).
<fig id="fig4-1078155212451196" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>UV chromatogram of CPA in an air sample collected by passive sampling.</p>
<p>CPA: cyclophosphamide.</p>
<p>Analytical conditions: column, Inertsil ODS-3 (4.6 × 150 mm<sup>2</sup>, 5-µm i.d.); column oven, 40°C; mobile phase, water: acetonitrile = 77:23 (v/v); flow rate, 0.7 mL/min; injection volume, 20 µL; UV detection wavelength, 205 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451196-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-1078155212451196" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Multiple reaction monitoring chromatogram of CPA in an air sample collected by passive sampling.</p>
<p>CPA: cyclophosphamide.</p>
<p>Analytical conditions: column, L-column 2 ODS (2.1 × 150 mm<sup>2</sup>, 5-µm i.d.); column oven, 40°C; mobile phase, water: acetonitrile = 70:30 (v/v); flow rate, 0.2 mL/min; injection volume, 10 µL; monitored ions (ESA-Positive), CPA (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 261→140), CPA-d<sub>4</sub> (internal standard: <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 265 → 140); ionization voltage, 5500 V.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451196-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-1078155212451196" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Detection of CPA from the passive sampler by using LC-MS/MS.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1078155212451196" xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451196-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Sample no.</th>
<th>CPA (ng/sampler)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>61.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>7.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>37.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>157.7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1078155212451196"><p>CPA: cyclophosphamide; LC-MS/MS: liquid chromatography and tandem mass spectrometry.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1078155212451196" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, a passive sampler was used to sample CPA near the mouth of the preparer during crushing of Endoxan® tablets and preparing them for packaging using the automated equipment. We assumed that in the process of crushing Endoxan® tablets CPA would always be dispersed in the air as small particles, which would present a high risk of exposure for the preparer. Our results showed that a passive sampler used in conjunction with the developed sampling and analysis methods allowed simple determination of CPA exposure for staff involved in preparation of the drug and may be generally applicable for detection of other anticancer drugs at preparation sites.</p>
<p>This method has been evaluated only for exposure near the mouth, and thus, is not applicable for determining the total CPA exposure of humans. However, real per capita exposures can be presumed to be even higher than the levels detected by using this method.</p>
<p>In this study, it was difficult to evaluate the potential toxicity of CPA to humans because concentrations of CPA were very low (7.6–157.7 ng/sampler). However, chronic toxicity studies in rats involving intraperitoneal administration of 1.8 mg/kg/day of CPA for 6 months showed no changes in general condition, body weight and food consumption, even if leukopenia and increase in bladder mucous membranes were observed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1078155212451196">24</xref></sup> Because anticancer drugs are cytotoxic and mutagenic, it is necessary to prevent human exposure to even small amounts. In addition to CPA, many other anticancer drugs are used in medical practice, and healthcare workers may be chronically exposed to multiple drugs. Considering this, prevention of exposures to even trace amounts of hazardous drugs, such as those encountered during the procedures described in this investigation, is important.</p>
<p>Currently, in many hospitals in Japan, anticancer drugs are prepared in accordance with the ‘Japan Guidelines for Clinical Evaluation of Anticancer Drugs’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1078155212451196">16</xref></sup> under supervision of the Japanese Society of Hospital Pharmacists. To reduce exposures to anticancer drugs, closed systems such as the PhaSeal® system are used for injectable anticancer drug preparation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1078155212451196">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1078155212451196">26</xref></sup> However, there are no closed systems for oral anticancer drug preparation. Our results show that there is a risk of exposure when following certain preparation procedures for these drugs.</p>
<p>Considering that one or more anticancer drugs have been detected from the floors of staff toilets and dining tables, desks and beds used by staff, as reported by Yoshida et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1078155212451196">20</xref></sup> and because powdered medicines always present a risk of volatility and scattering, there is a need to develop a manual for preparation and a closed preparation system for oral medicines. In addition, it is necessary and important to verify the exposure status of health care workers to anticancer drugs, such as CPA, in many hospitals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1078155212451196" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The anticancer drug monitoring methodology described here is a simple exposure assessment that can be used to ensure the safety of hospital pharmacy tablet preparers. Furthermore, since the anticancer drug exposure risk is very high for preparers, preparation should be in hood or with face mask.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec15-1078155212451196"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078155212451196"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>McDiarmid</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preventing occupational exposures to antineoplastic drugs in health care settings</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078155212451196"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stellman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoloth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer chemotherapeutic agents as occupational hazards</article-title>. <source>Cancer Invest</source> <year>1986</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078155212451196"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorsa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemminki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vainio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occupational exposure to anticancer drugs-potential and real hazards</article-title>. <source>Mutation Res</source> <year>1985</year>; <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078155212451196"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>IARC.<italic> IARC monographs on the evaluation of carcinogenic risks to humans. Some antineoplastic and immunosuppressive agents</italic>. Lyon: International Agency for Research on Cancer, vol. 26, 1981, p.411</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078155212451196"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>IARC. <italic>IARC monographs on the evaluation of carcinogenic risks to humans. Pharmaceutical drugs</italic>. Lyon: International Agency for Research on Cancer, vol. 50, 1990</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078155212451196"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Problems of cytotoxicity drug mainly based on antineoplastic tumor medicine</article-title>. <source>J Jpn Med Waste Res</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078155212451196"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krstev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Perunicic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidakovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Work practice and some adverse health effects in nurses handling antineoplastic drugs</article-title>. <source>Med Lav</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1078155212451196"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>The Society of Hospital Pharmacists of Australia</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines for safe handling of cytotoxic drugs in pharmacy departments and hospital wards</article-title>. <source>Hospital Pharm</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1078155212451196"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Canadian Society of Hospital Pharmacists</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines for the handling of hazardous pharmaceuticals</article-title>. <source>Can J Hosp Pharm</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1078155212451196"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Working Party Report: Guidelines for handling of cytotoxic drugs. <italic>Pharm J</italic> 1983; 230</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1078155212451196"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>ASHP technical assistance bulletin on handling cytotoxic drugs in hospitals. <italic>Am J Hosp Pharm</italic> 1985; 42: 131–137</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1078155212451196"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Directorate of Labour Inspection</collab>. <source>Guidelines concerning the handling of cytostatic agents</source> , <publisher-loc>Oslo, Norway</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Directorate of Labour Inspection</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1078155212451196"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hakansson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Landersjo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Instructions for handling and administering of cytostatics</source> , <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Social Welfare Board</publisher-name>, <year>1978</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1078155212451196"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Health and Safety Executive (U.K.). Precautions for the safe handling of cytotoxic drugs. <italic>Guidance Note MS</italic> 1984; 21</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1078155212451196"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>NIOSH Alert. Preventing occupational exposures to antineoplastic and other hazardous drugs in health caresettings 2004. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health, DHHS (NIOSH) Publication No 2004–2165</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1078155212451196"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Kouganzai tyousei manyuaru<italic> (in Japanese)</italic></source> , <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jiho</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1078155212451196"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Japanese Society of Hospital Pharmacists</collab>. <source>Kou akusei syuyou yakuzai no innai toriatukai sisin<italic> (in Japanese)</italic></source> , <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Japanese Society of Hospital Pharmacists</publisher-name>, <year>1991</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1078155212451196"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiffmeyer</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kube</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Opiolka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vapour pressures, evaporation behaviour and airborne concentrations of hazardous drugs: implications for occupational safety</article-title>. <source>Pharm J</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1078155212451196"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genotoxic risks to nurses from contamination of the work environment with antineoplastic drugs in Japan</article-title>. <source>J Occup Health</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1078155212451196"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between occupational exposure levels of antineoplastic drugs and work environment in five hospitals in Japan</article-title>. <source>J Oncol Pharm Pract</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1078155212451196"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessink</surname><given-names>PJM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surface contamination with antineoplastic agents in six cancer treatment centers in Canada and the United States</article-title>. <source>Am J Health-Syst Pharm</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1427</fpage>–<lpage>1432</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1078155212451196"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of a closed system device to reduce occupational contamination and exposure to antineoplastic drugs in the hospital work environment</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1078155212451196"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bing</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of surface contamination with cyclophosphamide and fluorouracil using a closed-system drug transfer device versus standard preparation techniques</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1736</fpage>–<lpage>1744</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1078155212451196"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ifosphamide (Z4942) no rat ni okeru a mansei narabini mansei dokusei siken (in Japanese)</article-title>. <source>Kiso To Rinsyo</source> <year>1982</year>; <volume>16(2)</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1078155212451196"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Slawson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgenson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Using a closed-system protective device to reduce personnel exposure to antineoplastic agents</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2314</fpage>–<lpage>2320</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1078155212451196"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessink</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of a closed-system device in containing surface contamination with cyclophosphamide and ifosfamide in an i.v</article-title>. <source>admixture area. <italic>Am J Health Syst Pharm</italic></source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>