<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ANT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spant</journal-id>
<journal-title>Anthropological Theory</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1463-4996</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2641</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1463499612436457</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1463499612436457</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Introduction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Reyna</surname><given-names>Stephen P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1463499612436457"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1463499612436457">University of Manchester, UK, and Max Planck Institute of Social Anthropology, Haale, Germany</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1463499612436457">Stephen P Reyna, Max Planck Institute of Social Anthropology, Haale, Germany Email: <email>Stephen.Reyna@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>SPECIAL ISSUE: NEUROANTHROPOLOGY</issue-title>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>4</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It is a liminal time in anthropology when a number of its practitioners imagine new futures. The articles that comprise this issue of <italic>Anthropological Theory</italic> consider one imminent future by exploring certain implications for the discipline if the investigation of the brain is integrated into the project of understanding human being.</p>
<p>Anthropology <italic>is</italic> the study of human being, realities of humanity. Three actualities stand out: humans have brains; they have experiences; and they have cultures. Juan Domínguez explores a phenomenological future for anthropology. He argues for a <italic>cultural neurophenomenology</italic> to account for relationships between the three actualities. This phenomenology would be ‘a theory of the experiential and neurobiological aspects of cultural activity’, one that expressed a ‘neural theory of culture and a cultural theory of the brain’. Stephen Reyna investigates a hermeneutic future for the discipline. His article sets neuroanthropology in a broader context. First, it outlines a particular approach to the study of human being, that of <italic>critical structural realism</italic>. Then, it shows how Boasian anthropology exhibited the elements of critical structural realism and how, when neuroscience is added to its accomplishments, a new, <italic>neo-Boasian</italic> anthropology emerges. Reyna employs neuroscience to answer the question: what is interpretation? Specifically, he hypothesizes that <italic>cultural neurohermeneutic systems</italic> interpret antecedent events connecting them with subsequent actions.</p>
<p>Novel intellectual approaches are of especial consequence if they fortify other, existing approaches. Robert Turner, the originator of several important neuroimaging techniques, indicates the relevance of neuroanthropology to cognitive neuroscience. He argues that humans exhibit cultural variability, which cognitive neuroscience tends to ignore. So, to attain greater scientific validity, he suggests how it might incorporate anthropological insights regarding cross-cultural variations into an ethnopsychology. Charles Whitehead demonstrates neuroanthropology’s utility for the study of human evolution. He argues that ‘collective deceptions’ from Western ideology have subverted research into the human brain and, then, shows how more anthropologically relevant research can resolve some of the resulting problems. He formulates a concept of <italic>the culture-ready brain</italic> and uses it as part of a <italic>play and display</italic> hypothesis of hominid brain expansion, which seems consistent with recent fossil and archaeological findings.</p>
<p>Andreas Roepstorff and Chris Frith, an anthropologist and cognitive neuroscientist research team of some distinction, comment on the four articles. In so doing, they explicate experimental procedures that could operate as a methodological base of neuroanthropology. Additionally, they point to a Bayesian interpretation of the (neuro)hermeneutic circle, the role of synchronized high arousal in group cohesion, and neural implementations of cultural dimensions of the self.</p>
<p>The articles in this issue suggest a bright neuroanthropological future for two reasons. First, they are respectful of existing traditions that have proved their worth in the struggle to know human being, though – at the same time – they seek to build upon those traditions. Neuroanthropology promises a neurophenomenology and neurohermeneutics in a neo-Boasianism. Second, they promise to assist in the solution of conundrums in widely different areas – ranging from cognitive neuroscience to hominid evolution to group cohesion to the self.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Stephen P Reyna</bold> (PhD Columbia University 1972) is currently at the Conflict and Integration Working Group of the Max Planck Institute of Social Anthropology. His publications deal with social theory, power, culture and the brain, and Africa.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>