<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppig</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part G: Journal of Aerospace Engineering</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4100</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-3025</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954410011417346</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954410011417346</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effect of interlayer slip on the damping of layered and welded aluminium beams</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954410011417346">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>B K</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954410011417346">Department of Mechanical Engineering, National Institute of Technology, Rourkela, India</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954410011417346">Department of Mechanical Engineering, National Institute of Technology, Jagda, Rourkela 769008, India. email: <email>bhagatmech@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>898</fpage>
<lpage>911</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Authors 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Damping is a complex phenomenon, which acts in the form of absorption and dissipation of energy in the vibrating systems. Joints are inherently present in all most all assembled structures that contribute significantly to the slip damping. The joints fabricated by welding contribute to the damping mechanism in assembled structures. In this study, the relationship between the dynamic slip and damping capacity has been theoretically investigated considering the higher modes of vibration of the welded aluminium cantilever beams. The damping ratios of these structures are determined using forced vibration test method. It has been confirmed through the comparison of theoretical and experimental results that the damping capacity of a jointed cantilever beams can be well estimated using the proposed method.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>slip damping</kwd>
<kwd>tack welded joint</kwd>
<kwd>amplitude</kwd>
<kwd>frequency</kwd>
<kwd>in-plane bending stress</kwd>
<kwd>dynamic loading</kwd>
<kwd>aluminium beams</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954410011417346"><title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>Many structures that find wide applications in aerospace and automotive industries are assembled by welded connections. Usually, such structures possess low structural damping, necessitating incorporation of additional measures to improve their damping characteristics. One of the techniques used for this purpose is fabricating these structures in layers by means of joints, which provide adequate means of energy dissipation. Aluminium being lighter is one of the potential materials for such structures and it becomes imperative to understand the damping mechanism and quantify the same for successful design of the assembled structures in order to enhance their useful life. This has become important in the present global scenario because of continuous research and heavy investments in those industries.</p>
<p>An important feature of built-up structures is the existence of many mechanical joints that connect structural components, which lead to the existence of slip interfaces. Welded joints are such fasteners and have a great potential for reducing the vibration levels of fabricated structures. In such cases, when the dynamic load is increased or decreased within a threshold range, slip along the frictional joint interfaces occurs locally at the joints. This situation is called micro-slip, where slip along the interface is localized in the slip region while the rest of the interface is in the stick region. When the vertical load reaches beyond the threshold range, slip along the entire interfaces takes place which is being referred as macro-slip. While both micro and macro-slips cause energy dissipation providing the dominant damping mechanism in a built-up structure, the latter is generally avoided as it leads to structural damage of the joints. On the other hand, micro-slip provides a good level of energy dissipation without causing damage to the joints. Damping due to micro-slip is generally promoted in structural joint designs as it plays an important role in reducing the amplitude of structural vibrations, thereby increasing the fatigue life of the structures.</p>
<p>The mechanism of damping in assembled structures has received considerable interest by various investigators. Friction damping at slip interfaces has been the subject of many studies and is still a subject of current investigation [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954410011417346">1</xref></bold>–<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954410011417346">3</xref></bold>]. In an earlier attempt, the theory of structural damping in a built-up beam has been investigated by Goodman and Klumpp [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954410011417346">4</xref></bold>] considering two identical beams pressed together with uniform pressure, forming a composite cantilever beam. When the beam was loaded with shear force at the free end, frictional slip was induced at the interfaces, causing energy dissipation. They developed a formula for determining the amount of energy dissipation per loading cycle under plane stress conditions.</p>
<p>Pian [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954410011417346">5</xref></bold>] considered a cantilever beam with reinforcing spar caps subjected to a vertical shear load at the free end. The reinforcing caps have been attached to the beam by rivets, generating pressure along the beam–spar interfaces. The sliding motion between the cap and the beam has been resisted by pressure-dependent friction at the interfaces. The damping behaviour of the built-up beam in bending has been investigated analytically in terms of an elastic beam theory. Energy loss per cycle of static loading has been evaluated and compared with experimental measurements.</p>
<p>Another classical work has been carried out by Metherell and Diller [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954410011417346">6</xref></bold>]; they investigated the damping behaviour of a lap-shear joint subjected to a uniform clamping pressure. The authors derived expressions for the load–deflection relationship, the energy dissipation per cycle, and the instantaneous rate of energy dissipation.</p>
<p>The early studies of frictional slip, energy loss, and damping properties of built-up structures with mechanical joints have been reviewed vividly by Goodman [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011417346">7</xref></bold>] and Ungar [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0954410011417346">8</xref></bold>]. Following the work of Goodman [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011417346">7</xref></bold>], researchers such as Masuko <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954410011417346">9</xref></bold>], Nishiwaki <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954410011417346">10</xref></bold>], and Motosh [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954410011417346">11</xref></bold>] studied the damping capacity of layered and jointed structures assuming uniform intensity of pressure distribution at the interfaces. However, their work is limited to the layered and jointed structures with static loads.</p>
<p>Further, Masuko <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954410011417346">9</xref></bold>], Nanda and Behera [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954410011417346">12</xref></bold>] examined the interfacial slip damping in layered bolted structures and developed a theoretical expression for the pressure distribution at the interfaces of a bolted joint by curve fitting the earlier data reported by Ziada and Abd [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954410011417346">13</xref></bold>]. They further extended their work by developing a generalized mathematical expression for the logarithmic damping decrement of such structures with multiple interfaces. Nanda and Behera [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954410011417346">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954410011417346">15</xref></bold>] and Nanda [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954410011417346">16</xref></bold>] further studied the distribution pattern of the interface pressure as well as the damping capacity of layered and jointed structures by carrying out numerical analysis and performed experiments to ascertain the effects of number of layers, diameter of bolts, and use of washers on the damping characteristics. However, their study is limited to the static loading without considering the effect of in-plane bending stresses on the dynamic slip and damping capacity.</p>
<p>The effect of non-uniform interface pressure distribution on the mechanism of slip damping for layered beams has also been examined recently by Damisa <italic>etal</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954410011417346">17</xref></bold>], limiting their analysis to static loads and linear profiles of interface pressure distribution. However, Olunloyo <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0954410011417346">18</xref></bold>] have considered other forms of interfacial pressure distributions such as polynomial and hyperbolic and observed large difference in the results compared to the work of Damisa <italic>etal</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954410011417346">17</xref></bold>]. Although all these researchers considered the in-plane distribution of bending stresses but their analysis is limited to the structures subjected to static loads.</p>
<p>Although a lot of work has been carried out on the damping capacity of bolted and riveted structures, but a little amount of work has been reported on the mechanism of damping in layered and jointed welded structures. The study of slip damping in welded structures is very vital for achieving maximum vibration attenuation in automotive and aerospace industries, where these structures are extensively used. Masuko <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954410011417346">9</xref></bold>] and Nishiwaki <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954410011417346">10</xref></bold>] have established that the welded steel structures can be used in machine tool structures as a substitute for monolithic cast iron material to compensate for damping. The use of welded steel structures furtherbecomes economical in saving the materials for heavy machine tools. Aoki [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0954410011417346">19</xref></bold>] studied the effect of welding on dynamic characteristics of welded cantilever beam structures and established that the damping ratio increases when welding is used for the fabrication of the structures.</p>
<p>More recent works in this area include Vitelleschi and Schmidt [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0954410011417346">20</xref></bold>] considering the effects of surface finish, Beards and Williams [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0954410011417346">21</xref></bold>] on rotational slip, Jezequel [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0954410011417346">22</xref></bold>] on a plate-theory analysis, Groper [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0954410011417346">23</xref></bold>] on micro- and macro-slips in bolted joints, Wettergren [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0954410011417346">24</xref></bold>] and Csaba [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954410011417346">25</xref></bold>] on the role of micro-slip in generating damping and reducing the dynamic instability of turbine generators.</p>
<p>In this study, attempt has been made to investigate the mechanism of slip damping in layered and welded aluminium beams. The mathematical analysis has been carried out, considering the in-plane bending stresses, which has been neglected by the earlier researchers. The analysis carried out by the earlier researchers is limited to the structures subjected to static loads. In this study, dynamic analysis has been done to investigate the effect of various types of loading on the slip damping of welded structures. The study of slip damping of welded structures is very vital for automotive and aerospace industries, where the jointed welded structures are predominantly used. The present investigation focuses on the influence of interface pressure distribution, relative dynamic slip, and kinematic coefficient of friction on the damping capacity of welded aluminium cantilever beams subjected to dynamic conditions. The energy approach of evaluation of loss factor has been presented to study the effect of various parameters on the damping capacity of such structures. Moreover, extensive experiments have been conducted on a number of specimens to authenticate the numerical results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954410011417346"><title>2 THEORETICAL ANALYSIS</title>
<sec id="sec3-0954410011417346"><title>2.1 Static analysis</title>
<p>The two-layered and tack-welded cantilever beam model with overall thickness 2<italic>h</italic>, width <italic>b</italic>, and length<italic>l</italic>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011417346">Fig. 1</xref>(a) is considered to find out the damping capacity. The loading consists of uniformly distributed pressure at the interfaces due to the contact between two flat bodies, and a concentrated static load <italic>P</italic> is applied at the free end, <italic>x</italic> = <italic>l</italic>. Each of the two halves of thickness <italic>h</italic> is considered separately with the loading, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011417346">Fig. 1</xref>(b). The continuity of stress and vertical displacement <italic>v</italic> is imposed at the interfaces. At some finite value of <italic>P</italic>, the shear stress at the interfaces will reach the critical value for slip <inline-formula id="ilm1-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>xy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <italic>µ</italic> and <italic>p</italic> are the kinematic co-efficient friction and interface pressure, respectively. Additional force due to excitation will produce a relative displacement <inline-formula id="ilm2-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the interfaces.
<fig id="fig1-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(a) Two layered tack welded cantilever beam model and (b) two halves of the beam depicting load and co-ordinates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<sec id="sec4-0954410011417346"><title>2.1.1 Interface pressure distribution</title>
<p>In the present analysis, the welded beams are considered to be in contact with each other because of perfect flatness and same condition of flatness is maintained under excitation due to welding. Since perfect contact is maintained under both the static and dynamic conditions, the pressure at the interfaces is assumed to be uniform. The contact pressure for flat surfaces with rounded corners has been found out by Ciavarella <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954410011417346">26</xref></bold>], which shows a non-uniform distribution pattern at the interfaces. Contrary to this, the pressure distribution at the interfaces of flat surfaces is uniform owing to the contact of the upper layer over the lower one, as established byJohnson [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954410011417346">27</xref></bold>] and Giannakopoulos <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954410011417346">28</xref></bold>]. Therefore, the pressure distribution due to contact of two flat bodies, as given by Johnson [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954410011417346">27</xref></bold>] and Giannakopoulos <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954410011417346">28</xref></bold>], has been considered and the same is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0954410011417346"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>P</italic> and <italic>b</italic> are the normal load per unit length and width of the beam, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954410011417346"><title>2.1.2 Analysis of static response</title>
<p>The resultant moment at the centroid of each laminate, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011417346">Fig. 1</xref>(b), is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0954410011417346"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
where the subscripts 1 and 2 refer to the upper andlower laminates, respectively.</p>
<p>Invoking the relation between bending momentand curvature, as derived by Warburton [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0954410011417346">29</xref></bold>], one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0954410011417346"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>E</italic> is the modulus of elasticity.</p>
<p>Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0954410011417346">expression (3)</xref> in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0954410011417346">2</xref>, the following expression is obtained
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0954410011417346"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="ilm3-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>bh</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>bh</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the moment of inertia of the cross-section of the beam.</p>
<p>Integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0954410011417346">expression (4)</xref> once, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0954410011417346"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> is the integration constant and evaluated tobe zero substituting the boundary condition, <inline-formula id="ilm4-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>dv</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>dx</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954410011417346">expression (5)</xref>.</p>
<p>Further, integration of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954410011417346">expression (5)</xref> yields
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0954410011417346"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
where the integration constant, <inline-formula id="ilm5-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> since <inline-formula id="ilm6-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>Substituting the value of <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0954410011417346">expression (6)</xref> and simplifying, the static deflection mode shape expression is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0954410011417346"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
The two-dimensional (2D) parameters <italic>Q</italic> and <italic>R</italic> are defined as presented below
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8a-0954410011417346"><label>(8a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq8a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8b-0954410011417346"><label>(8b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq8b.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8a-0954410011417346">expressions (8a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8b-0954410011417346">8b</xref> in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-0954410011417346">7</xref>) and simplifying, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0954410011417346"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954410011417346"><title>2.1.3 Evaluation of relative slip</title>
<p>The displacement at any axial position <italic>x</italic> and <inline-formula id="ilm7-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∓</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10a-0954410011417346"><label>(10a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq10a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10b-0954410011417346"><label>(10b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq10b.tif"/></disp-formula>
These displacements are produced by the resultant axial force <inline-formula id="ilm8-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and moment <inline-formula id="ilm9-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math9-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, about the centroid of each half of the beam, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011417346">Fig. 1</xref>(b).</p>
<p>Here, <italic>v</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>v</italic><sub>2</sub> are the vertical deflections, <italic>E</italic> the modulus of elasticity, and <inline-formula id="ilm10-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math10-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the in-plane bending stresses. It is assumed that the continuity equation prevails, i.e. <inline-formula id="ilm11-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math11-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>From the equilibrium of force, the in-plane bending stresses in the upper and lower laminates are computed as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11a-0954410011417346"><label>(11a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq11a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11b-0954410011417346"><label>(11b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq11b.tif"/></disp-formula>
Combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0954410011417346">expressions (9)</xref> to (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11a-0954410011417346">11</xref>) and simplifying, the relative slip displacement at the interfaces is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0954410011417346"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
Slip will occur only if <inline-formula id="ilm12-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math12-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&gt;P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext/><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mtext>Q</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mtext/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>Here, <italic>P<sub>c</sub></italic> is the critical static load applied at the tip of the welded cantilever beams.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954410011417346"><title>2.2 Dynamic analysis</title>
<p>For the forced vibration of a cantilever beam, the static analysis has been extended to include distributed inertia forces and examine their effect on the mode shape, slip distribution, and energy dissipation due to slip. The analysis developed here follows the static analysis developed in the preceding sections for the beam, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011417346">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<sec id="sec8-0954410011417346"><title>2.2.1 Analysis of dynamic response</title>
<p>The forced vibration of the beam produced by a time-dependent displacement at the unsupported end has been considered such that
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0954410011417346"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
Following Timoshenko [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0954410011417346">30</xref></bold>], the dynamic displacement is composed of two parts
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0954410011417346"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
where
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-0954410011417346"><label>(15)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula>
The term in the bracket represents the static mode function and satisfies the end conditions
<disp-formula id="disp-formula16-0954410011417346"><label>(16)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq16.tif"/></disp-formula>
but not the dynamic equilibrium equation
<disp-formula id="disp-formula17-0954410011417346"><label>(17)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq17.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>EI</italic> and <italic>ρ</italic> are the flexural rigidity and density ofthe beam, respectively.</p>
<p>The displacement <inline-formula id="ilm13-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math13-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> produces the dynamic loads as given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula18-0954410011417346"><label>(18)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq18.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>A</italic> is the cross-sectional area of the beam.</p>
<p>Moreover, the displacement (<italic>v</italic><sub>II</sub>)representing vibrations produced by the force function (18) is expressed as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula19-0954410011417346"><label>(19)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq19.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="ilm14-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math14-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="ilm15-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math15-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the modal and time-dependent functions, respectively.</p>
<p><italic>v</italic><sub>II</sub> must satisfy the end conditions as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula20-0954410011417346"><label>(20)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq20.tif"/></disp-formula>
<inline-formula id="ilm16-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math16-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the solutions of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula17-0954410011417346">expression (17)</xref> and satisfies the end condition (20). Thus, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula21-0954410011417346"><label>(21)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq21.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>k<sub>i</sub></italic> are the roots of the following expression
<disp-formula id="disp-formula22-0954410011417346"><label>(22)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq22.tif"/></disp-formula>
The total displacement is then given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula23-0954410011417346"><label>(23)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq23.tif"/></disp-formula>
Applying the principle of virtual work, Timoshenko [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0954410011417346">30</xref></bold>] has shown that the time-dependent functions <inline-formula id="ilm17-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math17-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> must satisfy the differential equation
<disp-formula id="disp-formula24-0954410011417346"><label>(24)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq24.tif"/></disp-formula>
where the superscript dots denote differentiation with respect to time. The coefficients <italic>b<sub>i</sub></italic> are obtained by expanding the force function (18) in a series of the normal functions, <italic>X<sub>i</sub></italic>. Thus
<disp-formula id="disp-formula25-0954410011417346"><label>(25)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq25.tif"/></disp-formula>
and the coefficients <italic>b<sub>i</sub></italic> are obtained from the following expression
<disp-formula id="disp-formula26-0954410011417346"><label>(26)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq26.tif"/></disp-formula>
Integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula26-0954410011417346">expression (26)</xref>, <italic>b<sub>i</sub></italic> is finally given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula27-0954410011417346"><label>(27)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq27.tif"/></disp-formula>
The general solution of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula24-0954410011417346">expression (24)</xref> is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula28-0954410011417346"><label>(28)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq28.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="ilm18-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math18-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>EI</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Constants <italic>A<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>B<sub>i</sub></italic> are evaluated from the initial conditions
<disp-formula id="disp-formula29a-0954410011417346"><label>(29a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq29a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula29b-0954410011417346"><label>(29b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq29b.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula23-0954410011417346">expression (23)</xref> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula29a-0954410011417346">expression (29)</xref>, <italic>U</italic> and <italic>V</italic> are given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula30a-0954410011417346"><label>(30a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq30a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula30b-0954410011417346"><label>(30b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq30b.tif"/></disp-formula>
Moreover
<disp-formula id="disp-formula31-0954410011417346"><label>(31)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq31.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula31-0954410011417346">expression (31)</xref> in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula30a-0954410011417346">30</xref>) and simplifying, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula32a-0954410011417346"><label>(32a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq32a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula32b-0954410011417346"><label>(32b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq32b.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substituting the initial conditions <italic>U</italic> = <italic>V</italic> = 0, the constants <italic>A<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>B<sub>i</sub></italic> are evaluated as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula33a-0954410011417346"><label>(33a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq33a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula33b-0954410011417346"><label>(33b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq33b.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substitution of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula28-0954410011417346">expressions (28)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula33a-0954410011417346">33</xref>) in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula23-0954410011417346">23</xref>) yields
<disp-formula id="disp-formula34-0954410011417346"><label>(34)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq34.tif"/></disp-formula>
Integrating and simplifying <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula34-0954410011417346">expression (34)</xref>, the transverse deflection is finally found to be
<disp-formula id="disp-formula35-0954410011417346"><label>(35)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq35.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954410011417346"><title>2.2.2 Evaluation of dynamic slip</title>
<p>The relative slip at the interfaces under dynamic condition is evaluated by combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10a-0954410011417346">expressions (10)</xref>, (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11a-0954410011417346">11</xref>), and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula35-0954410011417346">35</xref>). The relative slip at the interfaces is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula36-0954410011417346"><label>(36)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq36.tif"/></disp-formula>
Utilizing the expression for mode shape as given by (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula35-0954410011417346">35</xref>) in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula36-0954410011417346">36</xref>), the relative slip is modified as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula37-0954410011417346"><label>(37)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq37.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0954410011417346"><title>2.2.3 Analysis of energy dissipated</title>
<p>The energy is dissipated due to friction and relative dynamic slip at the interfaces. For completely reversed loading, the product of the shear force, <italic>μp</italic> and the relative displacement, <italic>Δu</italic> integrated over the length of the beam, which is found to be equal to one-fourth of the energy dissipated in a complete cycle.</p>
<p>Thus, energy dissipation per cycle, as established by Goodman and Klumpp [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954410011417346">4</xref></bold>], is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula38-0954410011417346"><label>(38)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq38.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> are the displacements in the <italic>x</italic>-direction of points on the adjacent faces of the upper and lower half beams, respectively.</p>
<p>Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">expression (37)</xref> in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula38-0954410011417346">38</xref>), the energy dissipation per cycle is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula39-0954410011417346"><label>(39)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq39.tif"/></disp-formula>
Rearranging <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula39-0954410011417346">expression (39)</xref>, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula40-0954410011417346"><label>(40)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq40.tif"/></disp-formula>
Modifying <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula40-0954410011417346">expression (40)</xref>, one has
<disp-formula id="disp-formula41-0954410011417346"><label>(41)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq41.tif"/></disp-formula>
Integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula41-0954410011417346">expression (41)</xref>, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula42-0954410011417346"><label>(42)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq42.tif"/></disp-formula>
Simplifying <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula42-0954410011417346">expression (42)</xref>, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula43-0954410011417346"><label>(43)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq43.tif"/></disp-formula>
Rearranging <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula43-0954410011417346">expression (43)</xref>, one gets
<disp-formula id="disp-formula44-0954410011417346"><label>(44)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq44.tif"/></disp-formula>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula44-0954410011417346">Expression (44)</xref> is modified substituting 2D parameters <italic>Q</italic> and <italic>R</italic> as given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8a-0954410011417346">expressions (8a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8b-0954410011417346">8b</xref>) and the same is given as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula45-0954410011417346"><label>(45)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq45.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0954410011417346"><title>2.2.4 Evaluation of loss factor</title>
<p>In vibration problems, it is most convenient to express the dissipative properties of the system in terms of non-dimensional quantities such as the damping ratio <italic>ψ</italic> and loss factor <italic>η<sub>s</sub></italic>, defined by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula46a-0954410011417346"><label>(46a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq46a.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula46b-0954410011417346"><label>(46b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq46b.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>E<sub>ne</sub></italic> is the maximum strain energy stored in the system.</p>
<p>The maximum strain energy stored in the system in terms of dynamic deflection at the tip of the beam is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula47-0954410011417346"><label>(47)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq47.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula40-0954410011417346">expressions (40)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula42-0954410011417346">42</xref>) in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula41-0954410011417346">expression (41a)</xref> and simplifying, the damping ratio in terms of dynamic tip displacement is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula48-0954410011417346"><label>(48)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq48.tif"/></disp-formula>
Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula43-0954410011417346">expression (43)</xref> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula41-0954410011417346">expression (41b)</xref> and simplifying, the loss factor in terms of dynamic tip displacement is given as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula49-0954410011417346"><label>(49)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq49.tif"/></disp-formula>
This result clearly indicates that the value for <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula44-0954410011417346">expression (44)</xref> cannot be fully determined until the forcing time-dependent displacement function <inline-formula id="ilm19-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math19-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is specified. Consequently, we limit our analysis to the following cases namely</p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula50a-0954410011417346"><label>(50a)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq50a.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="ilm20-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math20-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the Heaviside function and <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> the amplitude</p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula50b-0954410011417346"><label>(50b)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-eq50b.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>where <italic>ω</italic> is the excitation frequency.</p>
<p>The dynamic response, slip, and the loss factor have been evaluated for the above two cases of <inline-formula id="ilm21-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math21-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula50a-0954410011417346">expressions (50a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula50b-0954410011417346">50b</xref>) in (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula35-0954410011417346">35</xref>), (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">37</xref>), and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula49-0954410011417346">49</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0954410011417346"><title>3 EXPERIMENTAL SET-UP AND EXPERIMENTS</title>
<sec id="sec13-0954410011417346"><title>3.1 Preparation of tack-welded aluminium specimens</title>
<p>The specimens are prepared from the stock of aluminium flats by tack welding two layers of various thicknesses and cantilever lengths. The details of the aluminium specimens used for experimentation are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954410011417346">Table 1</xref>. The welding of aluminium flats has met with great difficulties because of its ability to oxidation. The moment it is prepared and cleansed, the aluminium at once covered with aluminium oxide, which prevents the pieces from fusing together. Using a flux, however, the oxidation skin is dissolved, and a dross is simultaneously formed, which enables the metal to flow and make a perfect weld. The commercial aluminium welding method has been employed which uses an electric arc with a permanent tungsten electrode plus filler wire (with AC current). The arc has been protected by argon gas (or argon–helium gas mix) to shield the weld pool and the electrode from the surrounding atmosphere. Arc welding is easy to use and regulate; also, it attains a high temperature and provides high heat input. To ensure an acceptable weld quality, two basic factors have been considered – breaking loose and removing the oxide film, and preventing the formation of new oxide during the weld process. It is essential that proper preparations and precautions are to be undertaken before welding commences. The surfaces to be joined and the area around the weld zone have been degreased using a solvent (acetone or toluene) and a clean cloth. The area has been cleaned and completely dried as grease and moisture can form gases and cause pores in the welded joint. The metal surface has been lightly brushed in and around the weld, after degreasing, to remove surface oxides and avoid oxide inclusion in the weld. The high melting temperature (~2000 °C) surface oxides has been removed just prior to welding (at least within 3 h or less). The weld has been properly shielded with the inert gas at the correct flow rate, and of the required purity. Care has been taken that the nozzle distance does not vary from the weld point.
<table-wrap id="table1-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Details of aluminium specimens used for layered and jointed beams</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954410011417346" xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Thickness of the specimen (mm)</th>
<th>Width of the specimen (mm)</th>
<th>Number of layers</th>
<th>Cantilever length (mm)</th>
<th>Type of welding</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>40.2</td>
<td rowspan="4">2</td>
<td rowspan="4">520.6</td>
<td rowspan="4">Tack weld</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>40.2</td>
<td rowspan="4">2</td>
<td rowspan="4">560.4</td>
<td rowspan="4">Tack weld</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>40.2</td>
<td rowspan="4">2</td>
<td rowspan="4">600.6</td>
<td rowspan="4">Tack weld</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>40.2</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0954410011417346"><title>3.2 Experimentation</title>
<p>An experimental set-up, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954410011417346">Fig. 2</xref>, has been fabricated to conduct the experiments. The cantilever specimens are excited transversally by a time-dependent displacement at the free end with the aid of vibration generator. The input excitation and output vibration are sensed with vibration pick-ups and the corresponding signal is fed to a digital storage oscilloscope which is connected to the computer with vibration analyser software, i.e. Lab View of National Instruments Limited.
<fig id="fig2-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Experimental set-up</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The frequency response has been measured for the first four modes of the vibration. Frequency response functions (FRFs) were measured in the frequency interval of 400 Hz with a resolution of 0.5 Hz. The frequency response curves at different loadings are plotted on a logarithmic scale, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954410011417346">Figs 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011417346">4</xref>. The experimental loss factor is then evaluated using experimental FRF curves.
<fig id="fig3-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>FRF plot at harmonic loading for jointed and welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 600.6 × 40.2 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig4-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>FRF plot at Heaviside loading for jointed and welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 600.6 × 40.2 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0954410011417346"><title>4 RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
<p>The dynamic slip and transverse response of two-layered and tack-welded aluminium specimens have been found out numerically using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula35-0954410011417346">expressions (35)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">37</xref>). From the analysis, following inferencesare drawn as outlined below. The variation of dynamic slip and transverse response at different locations along the cantilever beam length at various excitation frequencies for Heaviside and harmonic loading have been plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011417346">Figs 5</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954410011417346">8</xref>, respectively. It is evident from the figures that the transverse response of vibration and the complementary interfacial slip increase with higher frequency ratio in the pre-resonance regime on one hand and behave conversely in the post-resonance zone. Moreover, the dynamic response and relative slip increases in the pre-resonance region with the increasing frequency and is maximum at the frequency ratio of one, i.e. at the resonant frequency.
<fig id="fig5-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Normalized slip profile at Heaviside loading with respect to the frequency ratio: (a) surface plot and (b) contour plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Normalized slip profile at harmonic loading with respect to the frequency ratio: (a) surface plot and (b) contour plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig7-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Normalized dynamic response at Heaviside loading with respect to the frequency ratio: (a)surface plot and (b) contour plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig8-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Normalized dynamic response at harmonic loading with respect to the frequency ratio: (a)surface plot and (b) contour plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The variation of energy dissipation with the initial amplitude of excitation for the layered and jointed beams of single interface has been plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954410011417346">Fig. 9</xref>. From the figure, it is apparent that the energy dissipation increases with the increase in initial amplitude of excitation. From <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula45-0954410011417346">expression (45)</xref>, it is deduced that the energy loss due to friction is directly proportional to the initial amplitude of excitation, which establishes that the energy dissipation is enhanced with increase in initial amplitude of excitation. Further, the relative slip at the interfaces is increased due to increase in initial amplitude of excitation, as shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">expression (37)</xref>, thereby enhancing the energy loss due to friction. The effect of relative slip due to dynamic loading on the energy loss is linearly proportional as the second term in the relative slip <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">expression (37)</xref> due to dynamic loading disappears on integrating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">expression (37)</xref> over the whole length of the beam.
<fig id="fig9-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Normalized energy loss versus amplitude</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig9.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The theoretical loss factor has been evaluated for various configurations and vibration conditions using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula49-0954410011417346">expressions (49)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula50a-0954410011417346">50</xref>) and these results as well as the corresponding experimental ones are plotted as solid (——) and dotted lines (...............) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011417346">Figs 10</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0954410011417346">15</xref>, respectively for comparison. It is observed that both the curves are in good agreement with a maximum variation of 11.7 per cent, which shows the authenticity of the theoretical analysis.
<fig id="fig10-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Variation of loss factor with amplitude at Heaviside loading welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 600.6 × 40.2 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig10.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011417346">Figures 10</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954410011417346">11</xref> show that the loss factor decreases with the increase in the initial amplitude of vibration at the free end of the beam model although the increase in the amplitude of vibration raises energy loss due to friction. The strain energy introduced into the system is proportional to the square of the amplitude, as given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula47-0954410011417346">expression (47)</xref>, as such increase in amplitude of excitation increases the input strain energy at a higher rate compared to the energy loss due to friction, which is linearly proportional to the initial amplitude, as given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">expression (37)</xref>, thereby reducing the damping capacity.
<fig id="fig11-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Variation of loss factor with amplitude at harmonic loading welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 560.2 × 40.2 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig11.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011417346">Figs 12</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954410011417346">13</xref>, it is concluded that the damping capacity decreases with the increase in thickness. From <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula47-0954410011417346">expression (47)</xref>, it is evident that the strain energy introduced in to the system is enhanced withthe increase in thickness. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula37-0954410011417346">Expression (37)</xref> reveals that the increase in thickness increases the relative slip, thereby raising the energy loss. Although the energy loss is enhanced with the increase in thickness, the damping capacity is reduced as the dissipation of energy is at a slower rate compared to that of the input strain energy.
<fig id="fig12-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Variation of loss factor with thickness at Heaviside loading for welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 600.6 × 40.2 mm<sup>2</sup> and amplitude = 0.1 mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig12.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig13-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Variation of loss factor with thickness at harmonic loading for welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 600.6 × 40.2 mm<sup>2</sup> and amplitude = 0.2 mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig13.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Damping capacity of the layered and welded structures increases with the increase in length, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0954410011417346">Figs 14</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0954410011417346">15</xref>. With the increase in length, the interface area is increased resulting in greater dissipation of the energy due to friction. Furthermore, with increase in the length of the jointed beam, strain energy introduced into the system is reduced as evident from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula47-0954410011417346">expression (47)</xref>. Hence, the overall effect is an increase in the damping capacity of the system.
<fig id="fig14-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Variation of loss factor with length at Heaviside loading for jointed and welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 40.2 × 4 mm<sup>2</sup> and amplitude = 0.1 mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig15-0954410011417346" position="float"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Variation of loss factor with length for jointed and welded cantilever beams of dimensions = 40.2 × 3 mm<sup>2</sup> and amplitude = 0.2 mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011417346-fig15.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0954410011417346"><title>5 CONCLUSIONS</title>
<p>The present investigation primarily discusses the various parameters affecting the damping capacity of light-weight aluminium structures that find wide applications in aerospace and automotive industries. The mechanism of interfacial slip damping based on energy approach has been studied vividly in this study. It is found from the experimentally validated numerical results that the damping capacity of welded beams can be improved substantially with use of aforesaid principle. The above design concept can be effectively used in aerospace and automotive industries, which extensively use aluminium materials with welded joints as structural members because of light weight and high damping.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954410011417346"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segalman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Observations on simulation of joint friction</article-title><year>1999</year><conf-name>Proceedings of the 1999 ASME International Design Engineering Technology Conferences, Symposium on Dynamics and vibrations of structures with mechanical joints</conf-name> <conf-date>12–15 September</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Las Vegas, Nevada</conf-loc></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954410011417346"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smallwood</surname><given-names>D. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Damping investigations of a simplified frictional shear joint</article-title><year>2000</year><conf-name>Proceedings of the 71st Shock and Vibration Symposium</conf-name> <conf-date>6–9 November</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Alexandria, Virginia</conf-loc></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954410011417346"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Heinstein, M. W. and Segalman D. J. Bending effects in the frictional energy dissipation in lap joints. Report # SAND2002-0083, Sandia National Laboratories, Albuquerque, New Mexico, 2002</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954410011417346"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klumpp</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Analysis of slip damping with reference to turbine-blade vibration</article-title>. <source>ASME J. Appl. Mech.</source>, <year>1956</year>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954410011417346"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pian</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Structural damping of a simple built-up beam with riveted joints in bending</article-title>. <source>ASME J. Appl. Mech.</source>, <year>1957</year>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954410011417346"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metherell</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diller</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Instantaneous energy dissipation rate in a lap joint—uniform clamping pressure</article-title>. <source>ASME J. Appl. Mech.</source>, <year>1968</year>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954410011417346"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ruzicka</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>A review of progress in analysis of interfacial slip damping</article-title>. <source>Structural damping</source>, <year>1959</year>, pp. <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage> (<publisher-name>ASME</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954410011417346"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungar</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The status of engineering knowledge concerning the damping of built-up structures</article-title>. <source>J.Sound Vibration</source>, <year>1973</year>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954410011417346"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masuko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Theoretical analysis for a damping ratio of jointed cantibeam</article-title>. <source>Bull. JSME</source>, <year>1973</year>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1432</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954410011417346"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiwaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>A study on damping capacity of a jointed cantilever beam (1st Report; experimental results</article-title>. <source>Bull. JSME</source>, <year>1978</year>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>524</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954410011417346"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motosh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Stress distribution in joints of bolted or riveted connections</article-title>. <source>ASME J. Engng Ind.,</source>, <year>1975</year>, <volume>97</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954410011417346"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Study on damping in layered and jointed structures with uniform pressure distribution at the interfaces</article-title>. <source>J. Sound Vibration</source>, <year>1999</year>, <volume>226</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>624</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954410011417346"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziada</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Load pressure distribution and contact areas in bolted joints</article-title>. <source>Inst. Engrs India</source>, <year>1980</year>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954410011417346"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Damping in layered and jointed structures</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Acoust. Vibration</source>, <year>2000</year>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954410011417346"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Improvement of damping capacity of structural members using layered construction</article-title><year>2000</year><conf-name>Proceedings of Seventh International Congress on Sound and vibration</conf-name> <conf-date>4–7 July</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Garmisch-Partenkirchen, Germany</conf-loc><fpage>3059</fpage>–<lpage>3066</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954410011417346"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Study of the effect of bolt diameter and washer on damping in layered and jointed structures</article-title>. <source>J. Sound Vibration</source>, <year>2006</year>, <volume>290</volume>, <fpage>1290</fpage>–<lpage>1314</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0954410011417346"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damisa</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olunloyo</surname><given-names>V. O. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osheku</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyediran</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Static analysis of slip damping with clamped laminated beams</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Sci. Res.</source>, <year>2007</year>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0954410011417346"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olunloyo</surname><given-names>V. O. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Damisa</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osheku</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyediran</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Further results on static analysis of slip damping with clamped laminated beams</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Sci. Res.</source>, <year>2007</year>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0954410011417346"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Dynamic characteristics of welded structures</article-title>. <source>Nucl. Engng Des., Elsevier</source>, <year>1996</year>, <volume>160</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0954410011417346"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vitelleschi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Damping in friction-grip bolted joints</article-title>. <source>ASCE J. Struct. Div.</source>, <year>1977</year>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>1447</fpage>–<lpage>1460</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0954410011417346"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beards</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The damping of structural vibration by rotational slip in joints</article-title>. <source>J.Sound Vibration</source>, <year>1977</year>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0954410011417346"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jezequel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Structural damping by slip in joints</article-title>. <source>ASME J. Vibration Acoust. Stress Reliabil. Des.</source>, <year>1983</year>, <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0954410011417346"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groper</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Microslip and macroslip in bolted joints</article-title>. <source>Exp. Mech.</source>, <year>1985</year>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0954410011417346"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wettergren</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Optimal design to reduce dynamic instability of a turbine generator due to microslip</article-title>. <source>J.Sound Vibration</source>, <year>1998</year>, <volume>214</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0954410011417346"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Csaba</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Forced response analysis in time and frequency domains of a tuned bladed disk with friction dampers</article-title>. <source>J. Sound Vibration</source>, <year>1998</year>, <volume>214</volume>, <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0954410011417346"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciavarella</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monno</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The influence of rounded edges on indentation by flat punch</article-title>. <source>Proc. IMechE, Part C: J. Mechanical Engineering Science</source>, <year>1998</year>, <volume>212</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0954410011417346"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name></person-group> <source>Contact mechanics</source>, <year>1985</year> (<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0954410011417346"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giannakopoulos</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindley</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenut</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Similarities of stress concentrations in contact at round punches and fatigue at notches: Implications to fretting fatigue crack initiation</article-title>. <source>Fatigue Fract. Engng Mater. Struct.</source>, <year>2000</year>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0954410011417346"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name></person-group> <source>The dynamical behaviour of structures</source>, <edition>2nd ed.</edition>, <year>1976</year>, pp.<fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage><comment>230–231</comment> (<publisher-name>Pergamon Press Ltd</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0954410011417346"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timoshenko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> <source>Vibration problems in engineering</source>, <edition>3rd edition</edition>, <year>1955</year>, pp. <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage> (<publisher-name>Van Norstrand Co. Inc</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>).</citation></ref>
</ref-list><app-group><app id="app1-0954410011417346"><title>APPENDIX</title>
<sec id="sec17-0954410011417346"><title/>
<sec id="sec18-0954410011417346"><title>Notations</title>
<p><def-list id="duolist1-0954410011417346">
<def-item><term><italic>A</italic></term><def><p>cross-sectional area of the beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>b</italic></term><def><p>width of the beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>E</italic></term><def><p>modulus of elasticity</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>E<sub>ne</sub></italic></term><def><p>maximum strain energy stored in the system</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm22-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math22-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def><p>forcing time-dependent displacement function</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub></term><def><p>amplitude</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>2<italic>h</italic></term><def><p>overall thickness of the beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm23-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math23-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def><p>Heaviside function</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>I</italic></term><def><p>moment of inertia of the cross-section of the beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>l</italic></term><def><p>length of the beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>p</italic></term><def><p>interface pressure</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P</italic></term><def><p>static load applied at the free end of the cantilever beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P<sub>c</sub></italic></term><def><p>critical static load applied at the tip of the welded cantilever beams</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub></term><def><p>displacement in the <italic>x</italic>-direction of points on the upper beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub></term><def><p>displacement in the <italic>x</italic>-direction of points on the lower beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>v</italic><sub>1</sub></term><def><p>vertical deflection of upper laminate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>v</italic><sub>2</sub></term><def><p>vertical deflection of lower laminate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm24-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math24-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def><p>modal function</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>η<sub>s</sub></italic></term><def><p>loss factor</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>µ</italic></term><def><p>kinematic coefficient of friction</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ρ</italic></term><def><p>density of the beam</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm25-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math25-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def><p>in-plane bending stress on the upper laminate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm26-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math26-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def><p>in-plane bending stress on the lower laminate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm27-0954410011417346"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math27-0954410011417346"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def><p>time-dependent function</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ψ</italic></term><def><p>damping ratio</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ω</italic></term><def><p>excitation frequency</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>