<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Contemp Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Contemporary Sociology: A Journal of Reviews</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0094-3061</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-8638</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0094306113477387b</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0094306113477387b</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Briefly Noted</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Queer Youth Suicide, Culture and Identity: Unliveable Lives?</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>291</fpage>
<lpage>291</lpage>
<product>
<source>Queer Youth Suicide, Culture and Identity: Unliveable Lives?</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cover.</surname><given-names>Rob</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>. <page-count count="172"/>pp. <price>$99.95</price> cloth. ISBN: <isbn>9781409444473</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Suicide among young people is a growing social problem. Though youth who experience suicide ideation come from a wide variety of different backgrounds, a common characteristic among young individuals who attempt suicide is a feeling of hopelessness and the inability to cope. Research indicates that among adolescents and emerging adults, queer youth, broadly defined as youth who identify as gay, lesbian, bisexual, or transgendered (GLBT), are more likely to contemplate, attempt, and successfully execute suicide. The disproportionate number of queer youth who attempt suicide has led many researchers to hypothesize what is it about “queerness” that makes these youth more at risk for suicide and how we can mediate this effect. In his book, <italic>Queer Youth Suicide, Culture and Identity: Unliveable Lives?</italic>, Rob Cover argues that it is not queerness that leads to an increased risk of suicide in GLBT youth. Rather, increased risk of suicide in queer youth can be attributed to a broader social context that embraces, upholds, and perpetuates heteronormativity. In other words, queerness as risk is culturally constructed.</p>
<p>To make his case, Cover draws heavily on the postructuralist works of Judith Butler and Michel Foucault, arguing that competing power structures create this idea of vulnerable queer youth through a variety of different mediums, including everyday language and the media. Cover effectively shows how representations of GLBT men and women in popular films and television have essentially equated being queer to being at risk for suicide. He then goes on to explain the tension between identifying as a sexual minority and the larger heteronormative culture that shames and stigmatizes queer identity. Cover supports his arguments quite well.</p>
<p>With clear and non-technical writing, this book is an appropriate read for anyone interested in youth suicide broadly speaking, and queer youth suicide in particular.</p>
</body>
</article>