<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">URO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spuro</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Clinical Urology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2051-4158</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2051-4166</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2051415812472674</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2051415812472674</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A case of delayed vesical pancreatic adenocarcinoma metastasis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Petrides</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-2051415812472674">Department of Urology, Queen Alexandra Hospital Portsmouth, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2051415812472674">N. Petrides, Department of Urology, Queen Alexandra Hospital Portsmouth, UK. Email: <email>np262@cantab.net</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>128</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>24</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>3</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© British Association of Urological Surgeons 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">British Association of Urological Surgeons</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We report the first case of a pancreatic-vesical metastasis presenting with haematuria as the initial symptom of a previously thought to be completely excised pancreatic primary four years earlier.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Metastasis</kwd>
<kwd>pancreas</kwd>
<kwd>bladder</kwd>
<kwd>vesical</kwd>
<kwd>haematuria</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-2051415812472674">
<title>Case summary</title>
<p>We report the first case of a pancreatic-vesical metastasis presenting with haematuria as the initial symptom of a previously thought to be completely excised pancreatic primary four years earlier.</p>
<p>An 80-year old woman presented for investigation of recurrent urinary tract infections and visible painless haematuria over the last five to six weeks.</p>
<p>Her past medical history included breast, endometrial and pancreatic carcinoma. The breast cancer was successfully treated by mastectomy and the endometrial cancer by hysterectomy and adjuvant radiotherapy (45 Gy). The pancreatic carcinoma was excised four years earlier (Whipple’s procedure) and post-operative adjuvant gemcitabine chemotherapy was abandoned after the first cycle because of side effects. Four years’ surveillance using cross-sectional imaging showed no evidence of recurrence.</p>
<p>Renal tract ultrasound revealed right-sided hydronephrosis thought to be secondary to a partially obstructing 9 mm ureteric stone, and flexible cystoscopy demonstrated bladder debris and a uniformly inflamed bladder wall.</p>
<p>On subsequent rigid cystoscopy, an irregular papillary mass was found in the midline on the posterior bladder wall, and this was completely resected. It was not possible to identify her right ureteric orifice.</p>
<p>Histological analysis of the resected tumour showed polypoid mucosa covered by mildly reactive urothelium with underlying fibrotic stroma. The tumour was composed of small irregular and coalescing glands lined by neoplastic cuboidal epithelium consistent with a moderate to poorly differentiated invasive adenocarcinoma. Immunohistochemical profiling confirmed a tumour consistent with metastasis from a pancreatic primary (positive to CK7, CA125 and CDX2 and negative to both oestrogen receptors and progesterone receptors).</p>
<p>A post-operative staging computed tomography (CT) scan of the chest, abdomen and pelvis showed a residual bladder posterior wall mass, no pelvic or intra-abdominal lymphadenopathy and a small (29 mm × 25 mm) previously unidentified right lung nodule. Treatment proceeded with dexamethasone and pelvic irradiation. A decision was made to postpone any further surgery for her ureteric stone until the effects of the treatment were established and the patient’s prognosis was characterised. She did not respond to active treatment; over the next few months, her condition deteriorated and a decision was made to proceed to palliation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-2051415812472674">
<title>Case discussion</title>
<p>Isolated metastatic carcinomatous vesical metastases are uncommon entities, occurring with an overall incidence of around 1%, with malignant melanoma, gastric and breast carcinoma being the most commonly reported primary sites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2051415812472674">1</xref></sup> Pancreatic adenocarcinoma vesical metastasis are very uncommon and usually present only at the late stages of the disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2051415812472674">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2051415812472674">3</xref></sup> with haematuria thought to be due to mucosal ulceration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2051415812472674">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>On review of the literature, we identified three previous reports of vesical metastasis from a pancreatic adenocarcinoma presenting with haematuria.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2051415812472674">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2051415812472674">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2051415812472674">5</xref></sup> All were in patients with widespread metastatic disease identified either at diagnosis or during follow-up.</p>
<p>This case represents the first reported case where haematuria secondary to a vesicular metastasis has presented as the first evidence of a recurrence from a previously thought to be successfully treated pancreatic adenocarcinoma. Immunohistochemistry proved essential in establishing the pathological diagnosis in the presence of multiple previously treated primary tumours. Thus unnecessary surgery was avoided and appropriate oncological treatment initiated.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2051415812472674">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fetter</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogaev</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCuskey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Carcinoma of the bladder; sites of metastases</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source> <year>1959</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>746</fpage>–<lpage>748</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2051415812472674">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Metastatic carcinoma to the bladder</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source> <year>1967</year>; <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2051415812472674">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Urinary tract involvement from pancreas carcinoma [in Japanese]</article-title>. <source>Nihon Igaku Hoshasen Gakkai Zasshi</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1102</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2051415812472674">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavelle</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An 84-year-old female with gross hematuria</article-title>. <source>Urology</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>534</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2051415812472674">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Athey</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Metastasis to the bladder from pancreatic adenocarcinoma presenting with haematuria</article-title>. <source>Urol Radiol</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>