<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546512437842</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546512437842</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>6</subject>
<subject>13</subject>
<subject>23</subject>
<subject>40</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Results of Meniscus Allograft Transplantation Using Bone Fixation</article-title>
<subtitle>110 Cases With Objective Evaluation</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jong-Min</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512437842">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Bum-Sik</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546512437842">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Keong-Hwan</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512437842">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Kyung-Ah</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546512437842">‡</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>Seong-Il</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512437842">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546512437842">§</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546512437842"><label>*</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan, Seoul, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546512437842"><label>†</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, College of Medicine, Incheon St Mary’s Hospital, Catholic University, Incheon, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0363546512437842"><label>‡</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, College of Medicine, Chungbuk National University, Cheongju, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0363546512437842">Investigation performed at the College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan, Seoul, Korea</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546512437842"><label>§</label>Seong-Il Bin, MD, Department of Orthopedic Surgery, University of Ulsan, College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, 88, Olympic-ro 43-gil, Songpa-gu, Seoul 138-736, Korea (e-mail: <email>sibin@amc.seoul.kr</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>1027</fpage>
<lpage>1034</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background</bold>: Meniscus allograft transplantation (MAT) has shown efficacy in relieving pain and improving knee joint function, but objective evaluation in a large number of patients is necessary to verify this effect.</p>
<p><bold>Hypothesis</bold>: Meniscus allograft transplantation relieves pain and improves function of the involved knee joint. Objective evaluation provides evidence of allograft integrity.</p>
<p>
<bold>Study Design</bold>: Case series; Level of evidence, 4.</p>
<p><bold>Methods</bold>: Of the 115 knees that underwent MAT from December 1996 to February 2009, 110 (95.7%) were followed up for more than 2 years and were enrolled in this study. Of these, 83 underwent lateral MAT, and 27 underwent medial MAT. Clinical outcomes were evaluated using the modified Lysholm score and Knee Society pain score. All knees underwent postoperative magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and/or second-look arthroscopy to evaluate the integrity and position of the allografts, with allograft status classified as satisfactory, fair, or poor.</p>
<p><bold>Results</bold>: At a mean follow-up of 49.4 months, clinical improvement was achieved in 104 of the 110 knees (94.5%). Mean modified Lysholm score increased from 72.7 preoperatively to 92.3 at final follow-up (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and mean preoperative Knee Society pain score increased from 32.5 to 47.7 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Of the 110 knees, 90 were evaluated by postoperative MRI alone, 2 by second-look arthroscopy alone, and 18 by both. Magnetic resonance imaging showed 12 gross tears and 6 small tears in the allograft. Mean extrusion of the allograft was 3.7 mm, and mean relative percentage of extrusion was 42.6%. Second-look arthroscopy showed 6 gross tears and 1 small flap tear. Classification by clinical outcome, MRI, and second-look arthroscopy graded 90 allografts (81.8%) as satisfactory, 8 (7.3%) as fair, and 12 (10.9%) as poor.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion</bold>: Meniscus allograft transplantation using bone fixation resulted in significant symptomatic and functional improvements. Magnetic resonance imaging or second-look arthroscopy was necessary to assess allograft status even after favorable clinical outcome. Meniscus allograft transplantation with bone fixation is considered effective for symptomatic, totally meniscectomized knees.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>menisci</kwd>
<kwd>transplantation</kwd>
<kwd>arthroscopy</kwd>
<kwd>magnetic resonance imaging</kwd>
<kwd>treatment outcome</kwd>
<kwd>objective evaluation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The meniscus is crucial for maintaining knee function including load transmission, shock absorption, decrease of contact stress, joint stability, and joint lubrication.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512437842">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512437842">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512437842">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546512437842">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512437842">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0363546512437842">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0363546512437842">23</xref></sup> Although every effort should be made to preserve as much meniscal tissue as possible when treating patients with torn menisci, preservation of sufficient meniscal tissue is not always feasible, and total or subtotal meniscectomy may be required. Human meniscus allograft transplantation (MAT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0363546512437842">25</xref></sup> is regarded as a promising approach for restoring meniscal functions, reducing knee pain during activity, and preventing rapid degeneration of articular cartilage after subtotal or total meniscectomy.</p>
<p>The continued performance of MAT has identified factors prognostic of successful and unsuccessful outcomes. For example, lyophilized allografts were found to shrink substantially after transplantation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0363546512437842">44</xref></sup> and generalized degenerative arthritis was identified as prognostic for poor allograft survival.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546512437842">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0363546512437842">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0363546512437842">39</xref></sup> However, other factors associated with benefits from this procedure, such as graft processing method, surgical technique, type of graft fixation, timing of surgery, range of tibiofemoral angle, and patient’s age, have yet to be determined. Long-term analysis of clinical outcomes, as well as objective methods, including magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or second-look arthroscopy, may be necessary to determine the factors associated with the efficacy of MAT. To date, however, few studies have applied objective evaluation methods to the entire study population to evaluate the results of MAT.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512437842">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512437842">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512437842">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512437842">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546512437842">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0363546512437842">40</xref></sup></p>
<p>We have therefore analyzed clinical outcomes and allograft survival of MAT with bone fixation using clinical scoring systems and objective evaluation methods. We hypothesized that MAT would reduce pain and improve the function of the involved knee joint.</p>
<sec id="section1-0363546512437842" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section2-0363546512437842">
<title>Patients</title>
<p>We retrospectively evaluated knees that underwent MAT in our hospital and were followed up for a minimum of 2 years. Of the 115 knees that underwent MAT from December 1996 to February 2009, 5 were lost to follow-up, with the remaining 110 knees (95.7%) enrolled in this study. All operations were performed by a single surgeon (S.I.B.). Of the 110 knees, 83 in 79 patients (54 men and 25 women) underwent lateral MAT (LMAT), and 27 in 27 patients (23 men and 4 women) underwent medial MAT (MMAT). The 4 patients who underwent bilateral LMAT did so at different times. Mean patient age at the time of MAT was 33.1 years (range, 16-57 years), and mean duration from meniscectomy to MAT was 35.8 ± 45.2 months. Associated injuries included anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) tears in 22 knees, osteochondritis dissecans in 4 knees, ACL tear with posterolateral corner injury in 1 knee, and posterior cruciate ligament (PCL) tear in 1 knee. All these associated injuries were treated surgically at the same time as MAT or during a separate operation.</p>
<p>Indications for MAT included a previous subtotal or total meniscectomy followed by persistent swelling and pain in the involved compartment during activities of daily living. Contraindications to MAT included grade III or higher generalized degenerative arthritis, uncorrected instability, axial lower extremity malalignment, skeletal immaturity, and age over 60 years. Localized grade III or IV articular cartilage degeneration confined to the area covered by the meniscus was not considered a contraindication. Each patient underwent a routine radiographic examination preoperatively and at follow-up to assess the degree of arthritis and axial alignment; these included standing anteroposterior, 45° flexion weightbearing posteroanterior, lateral, Merchant, and standing full-leg anteroposterior views. Allograft sizing was based on anteroposterior and lateral radiographs, taking magnification into account.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0363546512437842">28</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546512437842">
<title>Surgical Technique and Rehabilitation</title>
<p>The first 2 LMATs were performed utilizing cryopreserved meniscus allografts and the trough method, whereas the remaining 81 LMATs were performed using fresh-frozen allografts and the keyhole technique.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512437842">9</xref></sup> Both methods employed a common bone bridge between the anterior and posterior horns of the allograft. The first 3 MMATs were performed using cryopreserved allografts and the trough method, the following 9 MMATs were performed using fresh-frozen allografts and the keyhole technique, and the remaining 15 MMATs were performed using fresh-frozen allografts and the bone plug technique.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0363546512437842">34</xref></sup></p>
<p>For LMAT, the remnant of the lateral meniscus was trimmed arthroscopically to a 1- or 2-mm peripheral rim to achieve a fresh, bleeding, and stable bed. This was followed by a lateral parapatellar mini-arthrotomy to trim the anterior meniscal rim, create a bone tunnel, and allow later allograft passage. Under a C-arm image intensifier, we inserted a guide wire about 8 mm beneath the highest portion of the articular surface of the lateral tibial plateau, taking care not to choose a too lateral or deep point of entry. A core reamer, 10 mm in diameter, was used to create a bone tunnel without breaching the posterior cortex. The roof of the bone tunnel was removed with an osteotome, a narrow rongeur, and a pituitary rongeur to create a keyhole-shaped tunnel. After preparation of the bone tunnel, a posterolateral incision was made to expose the posterolateral joint capsule. A lateral meniscus allograft was introduced through the anterior mini-arthrotomy. Two No. 2 braided, nonabsorbable leading sutures anchored to the most posterior portion of the allograft were passed posteriorly through the posterolateral incision by pulling the previously inserted passing wires. The allograft was inserted into the keyhole slot, and the leading sutures were tied to each other just outside the capsule. Using traditional inside-out meniscal repair techniques, 8 to 10 vertically oriented 2-0 nonabsorbable sutures were placed in the middle and posterolateral part of the allograft. The anterior part of the allograft was sutured to the anterior capsule under direct visualization.</p>
<p>For MMAT, the remnant of the medial meniscus was trimmed arthroscopically to a 1- or 2-mm peripheral rim. The space between the medial wall of the intercondylar notch and the PCL was developed to allow passage of the arthroscope and the posterior bone plug of the medial meniscus allograft. If the space was too narrow, a small osteotome was used to remove osteocartilaginous fragments from the medial wall of the intercondylar notch and the medial tibial spine. After a posteromedial portal was created, an ACL tibial guide was inserted through the space while viewing from the posteromedial portal. After the native posterior horn of the medial meniscus was identified, the tip of the ACL guide was placed anatomically, and a guide wire was inserted for reaming. A 10-mm tunnel was created using a 10-mm coring reamer in antegrade fashion, and a passing wire was inserted through the posterior bone tunnel. Two No. 2 braided, nonabsorbable leading sutures were anchored to the anterior and posterior bone plugs of the allograft, and a small anteromedial arthrotomy was made for graft passage. The posterior leading suture was passed through the bone tunnel using the previously inserted passing wire. The allograft was then inserted by pulling the posterior leading suture and pushing the graft into the joint with a probe. After the anatomic placement of the posterior bone plug was ascertained, 10 to 12 vertical peripheral meniscal repairs were performed using an inside-out technique. After all peripheral repairs were completed, the position of the anterior bone tunnel was determined, and an anterior bone tunnel was created using a 10-mm coring reamer over a guide wire. Finally, 4 leading sutures were tied at the anteromedial cortex of the tibia, and all peripheral sutures were tied over the joint capsule. The superior stability and biomechanical function of the allograft were ensured by bone fixation and by placing more than 3 inside-out sutures in the inferior part of the allograft.</p>
<p>Isometric muscle strengthening exercises were begun immediately after surgery. A continuous passive motion machine was used to initiate range of motion (ROM) exercises 1 day after MAT, 0° to 60° during the first 3 weeks, up to 120° during weeks 4 to 6, and full flexion during weeks 8 to 12. Nonweightbearing walking with crutches was started the day after surgery to 3 weeks, partial weightbearing at 4 weeks, and full weightbearing walking at 7 weeks. Return to all daily activities, such as running, was allowed 6 months after surgery.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546512437842">
<title>Clinical Evaluations</title>
<p>Patients were followed up 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months after surgery and annually thereafter. Clinical improvements were assessed by physical examination, modified Lysholm scoring system,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0363546512437842">38</xref></sup> and Knee Society pain score.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512437842">14</xref></sup> Physical examinations included measurements of joint effusion, ligament stability, and ROM. Range of motion was measured with a goniometer and compared with the nonoperated side, if possible. Modified Lysholm score and Knee Society pain score before surgery and at last follow-up were compared using paired <italic>t</italic> tests, with the level of significance set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546512437842">
<title>Objective Evaluations</title>
<p>Postoperative MRI was performed in a nonweightbearing, supine position. All MRI examinations were performed using a 1.5-T magnetic resonance scanner (Magnetom Vision, Siemens Medical Systems, Erlangen, Germany) using a dedicated knee coil or a 3-T magnetic resonance scanner (Gyroscan Achieva, Philips Medical Systems, Best, the Netherlands). Proton density–weighted sagittal and coronal images were taken of each knee. All postoperative MRI results were reviewed by a single musculoskeletal radiologist with 10 years of clinical experience who was blinded to the patients’ clinical information. Joint effusion was graded as none, mild, moderate, or massive. The general shape of each allograft was determined, especially to gross volume and occurrence of shrinkage. The position of the allograft was assessed as extrusion in coronal sections, with the coronal image that showed maximal allograft extrusion selected. Extrusion was measured on a horizontal line parallel to the tibial articular surface and defined as the distance between the outer edge of the allograft and the outer edge of the tibial articular surface. Both the absolute extrusion and the relative percentage of extrusion (RPE) were measured, with RPE defined as the percentage width of the extruded allograft relative to the entire allograft width. The status of the articular cartilage in the involved compartment was determined using the International Cartilage Repair Society classification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512437842">3</xref></sup> The femoral and tibial cartilage were assessed separately, with the overall grade defined as the status of the worst area of each. The correlation between the status of the articular cartilage and each clinical score was assessed using the Spearman rank correlation test. The signal intensity within the allograft and the integration of the allograft with the joint capsule were evaluated, especially regarding degenerative changes and tearing of the allograft, with degeneration within the allograft evaluated as described by Stoller et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0363546512437842">35</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the initial cases of this series, we tried to perform second-look arthroscopy routinely. However, this was not always possible because many patients without pain were unwilling to undergo another invasive procedure. Therefore, rather than performing both MRI and second-look arthroscopy, patients were objectively evaluated by postoperative MRI alone, with second-look arthroscopy performed only when there was pain in the knee and MRI findings were positive for tears. Second-look arthroscopy, when performed, included evaluations of gross appearance, capsular healing, allograft tearing, and status of the articular cartilage. Knees with allograft tears were treated by arthroscopic shaving, partial meniscectomy, or total meniscectomy depending on the tear pattern.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546512437842">
<title>Determination of Allograft Status</title>
<p>Allograft status was based on clinical evaluation, MRI, and second-look arthroscopy, on each of which allografts were graded as satisfactory, fair, or poor (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546512437842">Table 1</xref>), with the worst grade in the 3 evaluations defined as the overall grade for that knee. Modified Lysholm scores of 80 to 100 points were defined as satisfactory, scores of 70 to 79 points as fair, and &lt;70 points as poor. The MRI results were graded by the signal intensity of the allografts, with grades of 0, 1, and 2 defined as satisfactory; grade 3 signal intensity involving ≤20% of the allograft and confined to its free, inner margin defined as fair; and grade 3 signal intensity involving &gt;20% of the allograft defined as poor. The presence of a peripheral tear of any size in the allograft corresponded to a poor grade. Second-look arthroscopy findings of stable peripheral healing of the allograft with no tears were defined as satisfactory; those with small tears limited to the inner margin of the allograft with stable peripheral healing that could be debrided with brief use of a motorized shaver were defined as fair; and those showing allografts that did not heal with the joint capsule at the periphery or gross tears necessitating meniscectomy of &gt;20% of the allograft were defined as poor.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546512437842" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Evaluation Criteria and Allograft Grades<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512437842"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546512437842" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512437842-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Grade</th>
<th align="center">MRI Evaluation (Signal Intensity)</th>
<th align="center">Second-Look Arthroscopy (Tears)</th>
<th align="center">Modified Lysholm Score</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Satisfactory</td>
<td>None, grade 1, or grade 2</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>80-100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fair</td>
<td>Grade 3 (tear) &lt;20% of allograft, confined in inner margin</td>
<td>Small degenerative tears in inner margin of allograft with stable peripheral healing</td>
<td>70-79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Poor</td>
<td>Grade 3 (tear) &gt;20% of allograft or any peripheral tear</td>
<td>Gross tears, meniscectomy &gt;20%</td>
<td>&lt;70</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546512437842">
<label>a</label>
<p>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) grading was based on the criteria of Stoller et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0363546512437842">35</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>We assessed correlation between the degree of arthrosis and overall allograft grade using the Spearman rank correlation test, with the degree of arthrosis defined as the sum of the grades of the femoral and tibial cartilage. We also assessed correlation between 2 clinical scores and the grades of MRI results using the Spearman rank correlation test. Modified Lysholm score and Knee Society pain score before surgery and at last follow-up were compared using paired <italic>t</italic> tests, with the level of significance set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0363546512437842" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section8-0363546512437842">
<title>Clinical Results</title>
<p>The mean follow-up duration was 49.4 months (range, 24-164 months). All patients showed full recovery of ROM to preoperative levels within 6 months after MAT. Symptomatic and functional improvement was noted in 104 of 110 knees (94.6%). Mean modified Lysholm score (92.3 ± 7.3 vs 72.7 ± 12.8; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and mean Knee Society pain score (47.7 ± 5.0 vs 32.5 ± 5.9; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) were significantly higher at final follow-up than preoperatively. Of the 110 knees, 104 (94.6%) showed satisfactory outcomes, 4 (3.6%) were fair, and 2 (1.8%) were poor, with each of the latter having modified Lysholm scores &lt;70 at last follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0363546512437842">
<title>Objective Results</title>
<p>Of the 110 knees, 90 (81.8%) were postoperatively evaluated by MRI alone, 2 (1.8%) by second-look arthroscopy alone, and 18 (16.4%) by both methods. Thus, 108 knees were evaluated by postoperative MRI and 20 by second-look arthroscopy. The mean duration from MAT to postoperative MRI was 28.8 months (range, 6-151 months). In some cases, magnetic susceptibility artifacts made detailed assessment difficult. However, these artifacts were usually limited to small areas, enabling us to determine the status of the allograft and articular cartilage in most knees.</p>
<p>We observed massive, moderate, and mild joint effusion in 1, 3, and 24 knees, respectively, with the other 80 showing no evidence of joint effusion. Generalized atrophy in the allograft was observed in 3 knees, atrophy in the anterior horn in 21, and atrophy in the posterior horn in 4. Swollen anterior horns were observed in 6 knees, while the remaining 74 showed allografts of almost normal volume and contour. Almost all knees showed some degree of allograft extrusion, with a mean extrusion of 3.7 ± 1.8 mm and a mean RPE of 42.6% ± 21.9%. The final status of the articular cartilage in the involved compartment is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0363546512437842">Table 2</xref>. Clinical results were not significantly correlated with the status of the articular cartilage on final MRI. We observed no correlation between modified Lysholm score and the status of the femoral (ρ = –.106; <italic>P</italic> = .276) and tibial (ρ = –.085; <italic>P</italic> = .380) cartilage of the corresponding compartment or between Knee Society pain score and the status of the femoral (ρ = –.025; <italic>P</italic> = .801) and tibial (ρ = –.091; <italic>P</italic> = .349) cartilage of the corresponding compartment.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0363546512437842" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Magnetic Resonance Imaging Determination of the Final Status of Articular Cartilage of the Involved Compartment (n = 108)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0363546512437842"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0363546512437842" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512437842-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Femoral Cartilage</th>
<th align="center">Tibial Cartilage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Grade 0</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 1</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 2</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 4</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>108</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0363546512437842">
<label>a</label>
<p>The status of articular cartilage was determined using the International Cartilage Repair Society classification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512437842">3</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Although 8 allografts showed normal signal intensity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546512437842">Figure 1</xref>), the other 100 showed varying degrees of degeneration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546512437842">Figure 2</xref>). The distribution and degree of degeneration are illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0363546512437842">Table 3</xref>. Mild degeneration was more frequently observed at the anterior horn of the allograft, whereas severe grade III degeneration occurred more frequently at the posterior horn. Tears were observed in 18 allografts, including 12 with gross tears involving &gt;20% of the allograft and 6 with small tears confined to the inner margin involving ≤20% of the allograft. The 12 gross tears included 5 degenerative, 2 radial, 2 bucket handle, 2 horizontal, and 1 flap, whereas the 6 small tears included 3 horizontal, 1 degenerative, 1 flap, and 1 radial. Second-look arthroscopy was omitted in asymptomatic patients with allograft tears. Thus, 6 patients with gross tears and 1 patient with a small tear underwent subsequent arthroscopic meniscectomy because of knee pain.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0363546512437842" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Magnetic resonance imaging of a medial meniscus allograft 8 years after transplantation showing good position, signal intensity, and healing of the allograft in (A) sagittal and (B) coronal sections.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512437842-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0363546512437842" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Magnetic resonance imaging of a lateral meniscus allograft 4 years after transplantation showing good position and healing of the allograft in (A) sagittal and (B) coronal sections. However, mild (grade I) degeneration was observed in the anterior horn of the allograft.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512437842-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table3-0363546512437842" position="float">
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution and Degree of Allograft Degeneration by Location (n = 108)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0363546512437842"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0363546512437842" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512437842-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Anterior Horn</th>
<th align="center">Midbody</th>
<th align="center">Posterior Horn</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Grade 0</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 1</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 2</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>108</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0363546512437842">
<label>a</label>
<p>Magnetic resonance imaging grading was based on the criteria of Stoller et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0363546512437842">35</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The mean duration from MAT to second-look arthroscopy in the 20 knees examined was 20.5 months (range, 9-102 months). Stable peripheral healing, normal contour, and consistency of the allograft were observed in 13 patients. In the remaining 7 knees, the allografts were more or less damaged, with 2 showing gross degenerative, 2 bucket handle, 1 deep radial, 1 gross horizontal, and 1 small flap tears. Six of these knees were treated with subtotal or partial meniscectomy removing &gt;20% of the allograft volume. The seventh knee, with a small flap tear, was treated with minimal debridement that removed ≤20% of the allograft.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546512437842">
<title>Overall Results</title>
<p>Based on our clinical and objective criteria, including modified Lysholm score and MRI and second-look arthroscopy results, 90 of the 110 knees (81.8%) were graded as satisfactory, 8 (7.3%) as fair, and 12 (10.9%) as poor (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0363546512437842">Table 4</xref>). Of 83 LMATs, 65 knees (78.3%) were graded as satisfactory, 7 (8.4%) as fair, and 11 (13.3%) as poor. Of 27 MMATs, 25 knees (92.6%) were graded as satisfactory, 1 (3.7%) as fair, and 1 (3.7%) as poor. We observed a moderate correlation between the degree of arthrosis and overall allograft grade (<italic>r</italic> = .468; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). However, we observed no correlation between modified Lysholm score and the grade of MRI results (<italic>r</italic> = .029; <italic>P</italic> = .762) or between Knee Society pain score and the grade of MRI results (<italic>r</italic> = .054; <italic>P</italic> = .581). None of these knees showed evidence of infection, arthrofibrosis, or neurovascular injury.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0363546512437842" position="float">
<label>Table 4</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of Grades in Each Category and Overall Grades of Allografts</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0363546512437842" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512437842-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Grade</th>
<th align="center">Magnetic Resonance Imaging</th>
<th align="center">Second-Look Arthroscopy</th>
<th align="center">Modified Lysholm Score</th>
<th align="center">Overall</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Satisfactory</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>104</td>
<td>90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fair</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Poor</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>110</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546512437842" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Meniscus allograft transplantation has shown favorable results in various situations, depending on allograft type, allograft fixation method, accompanied surgery, surgical indications, or timing of surgery. For example, lyophilized allografts have been reported to shrink substantially after MAT and are therefore no longer recommended.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0363546512437842">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0363546512437842">44</xref></sup> Generalized severe degenerative arthritis has been associated with allograft failure,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546512437842">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0363546512437842">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0363546512437842">39</xref></sup> although degree of degeneration of the articular cartilage was recently found to be unrelated to clinical results or graft survival according to a few studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0363546512437842">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0363546512437842">43</xref></sup> Other factors, however, remain undetermined. We focused on the type of allograft fixation because the initial stability and long-term biomechanical properties of allografts were thought to be influenced by the type of fixation, soft tissue versus bone. Biomechanical studies have shown higher contact pressure of the articular cartilage after soft tissue than after bone fixation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546512437842">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546512437842">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546512437842">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0363546512437842">27</xref></sup> Because we believed that MAT with bone fixation would result in superior clinical and functional improvements compared with soft tissue fixation, we have consistently utilized bone fixation techniques.</p>
<p>The lack of consensus regarding many variables related to MAT may be because of, at least in part, the paucity of studies utilizing objective evaluation methods. Although MAT is known to be associated with pain relief and functional improvement, objective evaluation methods are needed to compare study results. Until now, however, only a few studies have applied objective evaluation methods to the entire study population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512437842">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512437842">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512437842">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512437842">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546512437842">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0363546512437842">40</xref></sup> Magnetic resonance imaging has been used to evaluate allograft extrusion and to divide subgroups according to degeneration of the articular cartilage. We believe that analyzing the effects of MAT requires a more detailed investigation and description of the meniscus allograft itself and the adjacent cartilage. A thorough evaluation of MAT outcomes requires determining the degree and location of degeneration, extrusion, shrinkage, location, and extent of tearing in the allograft as well as the degeneration of the adjacent articular cartilage. These objective measures are necessary because MATs using different techniques and allografts have reported similar clinical results.</p>
<p>Although good MAT results have been reported using either soft tissue fixation methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512437842">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512437842">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0363546512437842">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0363546512437842">41</xref></sup> or soft tissue and bone fixation methods alternatively,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512437842">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0363546512437842">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0363546512437842">43</xref></sup> bone fixation techniques are generally preferred probably because of their theoretical advantages.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0363546512437842">‖</xref></sup> Verdonk et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0363546512437842">41</xref></sup> reported the clinical outcome of MAT using soft tissue fixation. They included 39 MMATs and 61 LMATs with a mean 7.2-year follow-up and found that the mean modified Hospital for Special Surgery pain score increased from 13.7 preoperatively to 39.4 at final follow-up and the mean function score increased from 60.1 to 88.6 at final follow-up. The cumulative graft survival rate at 10 years was 74.2% for MMAT and 69.8% for LMAT. As in most studies of MAT using soft tissue fixation, however, failure was defined by clinical judgment alone and not by objective methods such as MRI or second-look arthroscopy. Although a later study by the authors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0363546512437842">42</xref></sup> used MRI for objective evaluation, only 17 patients were evaluated, and the resolution of the MRI machine was low (1.0 T).</p>
<p>In a study of MATs using bone fixation methods,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546512437842">26</xref></sup> 39 knees (74.4%) were evaluated by MRI and 13 (33.3%) by second-look arthroscopy. After a mean follow-up of 40 months, 34 patients (89%) rated their knee conditions as improved. However, the overall failure rate was 28%, which may have been because of the adoption of very strict criteria of failure. Failure was adjudged in 3 categories: MRI, follow-up arthroscopy, and clinical evaluation, with the worst grade in each category determining the overall grade. Therefore, some MATs may have been judged as failures, despite favorable clinical outcomes, because of poor objective outcomes.</p>
<p>Another study evaluated 36 knees that underwent MAT using bone fixation with a mean follow-up of 31.4 months.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512437842">12</xref></sup> All 36 were evaluated by postoperative MRI examination and 18 (50%) by second-look arthroscopy. This study was a rare one that used objective methods of evaluation to their entire study materials. Clinical evaluation showed that 9 outcomes were excellent, 19 were good, 7 were fair, and 1 was poor. Magnetic resonance imaging showed complete meniscal healing in 26 knees (72.2%) and partial healing in the other 10 cases. In one, however, the fixation of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus allograft was lost.</p>
<p>The criteria for allograft failure have varied considerably. Most studies used only clinical criteria,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512437842">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0363546512437842">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0363546512437842">41</xref></sup> whereas others have used objective methods of evaluation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512437842">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546512437842">26</xref></sup> In several studies, failures have been defined as conversion to total knee arthroplasty or total removal of the allograft. Objective results have been better documented in patients undergoing bone than soft tissue fixation. Our findings suggest that favorable clinical outcomes should rely on sound structure and long-term benefits. Therefore, favorable clinical outcomes should be judged as failures if objective evaluation reveals substantial structural damage. We found that the failure rate was 10.9% if failure was defined as poor overall results or 18.2% if failure was defined as nonsatisfactory overall results. These findings were not inferior to previous results, despite our use of objective evaluation. Additional long-term studies, in larger numbers of patients and using objective criteria, are needed to evaluate the effects of bone and soft tissue fixation.</p>
<p>This study has several limitations. First, the average follow-up duration was not long enough to reflect long-term changes within the allograft and cartilage. Second, this was a retrospective study without a control group. However, we included a large number of knees that underwent MAT using a uniform bone fixation method, with a high follow-up rate (95.7%). Finally, our patients were evaluated not only clinically but by objective methods. Our findings therefore strongly indicate that MAT with bone fixation is effective for symptomatic, totally meniscectomized knees.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>One or more of the authors has declared the following potential conflict of interest or source of funding: This research was supported by the Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (2011-0004083 and 2011-0001045).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0363546512437842">
<label>‖</label>
<p>References <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512437842">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546512437842">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512437842">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512437842">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512437842">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512437842">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546512437842">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0363546512437842">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0363546512437842">31</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0363546512437842">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0363546512437842">36</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546512437842">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alhalki</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How three methods for fixing a medial meniscal autograft affect tibial contact mechanics</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>320</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546512437842">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baratz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mengato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal tears: the effect of meniscectomy and of repair on intraarticular contact areas and stress in the human knee. A preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>270</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546512437842">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brittberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winalski</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of cartilage injuries and repair</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>85</volume> <issue>Suppl 2</issue>:<fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546512437842">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation for unicompartmental arthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>337</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>-<lpage>171</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546512437842">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Branch</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is it important to secure the horns during lateral meniscal transplantation? A cadaveric study</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546512437842">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective evaluation of allograft meniscus transplantation: a minimum 2-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>919</fpage>-<lpage>927</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546512437842">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fairbank</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Knee joint changes after meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1948</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>664</fpage>-<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546512437842">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marberry</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Concomitant meniscal allograft transplantation and autologous chondrocyte implantation: minimum 2-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1459</fpage>-<lpage>1466</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546512437842">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goble</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Decette</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McGinty</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caspari</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poehling</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Operative Arthroscopy</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott-Raven</publisher-name>; <volume>1996</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546512437842">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gonzalez-Lucena</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pelfort</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monllau</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation without bone blocks: a 5- to 8-year follow-up of 33 patients</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1633</fpage>-<lpage>1640</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546512437842">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>KW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Sekiya</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wojtys</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results after combined medial meniscal allograft transplantation and anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: minimum 8.5-year follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546512437842">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ra</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between meniscal extrusion and various clinical findings after meniscus allograft transplantation</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2448</fpage>-<lpage>2455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546512437842">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hommen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Applegate</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Del Pizzo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscus allograft transplantation: ten-year results of cryopreserved allografts</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>388</fpage>-<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546512437842">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Insall</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rationale of the Knee Society clinical rating system</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>248</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546512437842">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fibrin clot delivery system for meniscal repair</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Relat Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0363546512437842">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation after total meniscectomy of torn discoid lateral meniscus</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1344.e1</fpage>-<lpage>1350.e1</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0363546512437842">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurosawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fukubayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Load-bearing mode of the knee joint: physical behavior of the knee joint with or without menisci</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0363546512437842">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lanzer</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Komenda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Changes in articular cartilage after meniscectomy</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>252</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0363546512437842">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LaPrade</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spiridonov</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A prospective outcomes study of meniscal allograft transplantation</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1804</fpage>-<lpage>1812</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0363546512437842">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Midterm outcomes after meniscal allograft transplantation: comparison of cases with extrusion versus without extrusion</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0363546512437842">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medial meniscal tears in anterior cruciate ligament-deficient knees: effects of posterior tibial slope on medial meniscal tear</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Relat Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0363546512437842">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torzilli</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of lateral meniscectomy on motion of the knee</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>406</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0363546512437842">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torzilli</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of medial meniscectomy on anterior-posterior motion of the knee</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>883</fpage>-<lpage>888</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0363546512437842">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amis</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effects of lateral meniscal allograft transplantation techniques on tibio-femoral contact pressures</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>553</fpage>-<lpage>560</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0363546512437842">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Milachowski</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weismeier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Homologous meniscus transplantation: experimental and clinical results</article-title>. <source>Int Orthop</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0363546512437842">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barber-Westin</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal transplantation in symptomatic patients less than fifty years old</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1392</fpage>-<lpage>1404</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0363546512437842">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paletta</surname><given-names>GA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergfeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of allograft meniscal replacement on intraarticular contact area and pressures in the human knee: a biomechanical study</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>692</fpage>-<lpage>698</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0363546512437842">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiographic sizing for meniscal transplantation</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>684</fpage>-<lpage>687</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0363546512437842">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yassir</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gundogan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation: two- to eight-year results</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>410</fpage>-<lpage>414</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0363546512437842">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodeo</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allografts: where do we stand?</article-title> <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>246</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0363546512437842">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rue</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yanke</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Busam</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNickle</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective evaluation of concurrent meniscus transplantation and articular cartilage repair: minimum 2-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1770</fpage>-<lpage>1778</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0363546512437842">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft replacement: a 1-year to 6-year experience</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>989</fpage>-<lpage>994</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0363546512437842">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sekiya</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groff</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Irrgang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harner</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical outcomes following isolated lateral meniscal allograft transplantation</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>771</fpage>-<lpage>780</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0363546512437842">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dukes</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscus replacement with bone anchors: a surgical technique</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>324</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0363546512437842">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stoller</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Magnetic Resonance Imaging in Orthopaedics and Sports Medicine</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0363546512437842">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stollsteimer</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dukes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bomboy</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation: a 1- to 5-year follow-up of 22 patients</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0363546512437842">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adelson</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pelsis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walgenbach</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turek</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term survival of concurrent meniscus allograft transplantation and repair of the articular cartilage: a prospective two- to 12-year follow-up report</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>941</fpage>-<lpage>948</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0363546512437842">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tegner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lysholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rating systems in the evaluation of knee ligament injuries</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0363546512437842">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Arkel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Human meniscal transplantation: preliminary results at 2 to 5-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>589</fpage>-<lpage>595</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0363546512437842">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Arkel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Ploeg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allografts: evaluation with magnetic resonance imaging and correlation with arthroscopy</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>517</fpage>-<lpage>521</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0363546512437842">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verdonk</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demurie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almqvist</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veys</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verbruggen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verdonk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Transplantation of viable meniscal allograft: survivorship analysis and clinical outcome of one hundred cases</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>715</fpage>-<lpage>724</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0363546512437842">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verdonk</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almqvist</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation: long-term clinical results with radiological and magnetic resonance imaging correlations</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>694</fpage>-<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0363546512437842">
<label>43.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vundelinckx</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopically assisted meniscal allograft transplantation in the knee: a medium-term subjective, clinical, and radiographical outcome evaluation</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2240</fpage>-<lpage>2247</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0363546512437842">
<label>44.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milachowski</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weismeier</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results of meniscal allograft transplantation</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>