<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">THE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spthe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Thesis Eleven</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0725-5136</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7455</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0725513612470537</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0725513612470537</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The political economy of pervasive rent-seeking</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>de Kadt</surname>
<given-names>Raphael</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0725513612470537">St Augustine College, South Africa</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0725513612470537"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Simkins</surname>
<given-names>Charles</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff2-0725513612470537">St Augustine College, South Africa</aff>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p>
<bold>Raphael de Kadt</bold> holds the Bill Lynch Chair of Political Studies at St Augustine College of South Africa. A Research fellow at the Helen Suzman Foundation, he was formerly Head of the School of Politics at UKZN. The author, co-author or editor of over 70 publications, his scholarly interests cover modernization studies, the political economy of growth and development, comparative politics, normative political theory and international relations. He was, for 20 years, Editor-in-Chief of <italic>Theoria: A Journal of Social and Political Theory</italic>. He is a member of the International Political Science Association and the American Political Science Association.</p>
<p>
<bold>Charles Simkins</bold> holds the Oppenheimer Chair of Economics at St Augustine College of South Africa, where he also serves as Vice President. He was educated at the universities of the Witwatersrand, Oxford, Natal and Princeton. His fields of study include mathematics, physics, philosophy, politics, economics and demography. He worked at the universities of Natal and Cape Town before being appointed as the Helen Suzman Professor of Political Economy at the University of the Witwatersrand (1991–2008). His research interests include political economy, social insurance, education, labour markets and public finance. His current research projects involve social insurance modelling (for the National Treasury) and mathematics and science education (for the Centre for Development and Enterprise).</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name>
<surname>Vale</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name>
<surname>Prinsloo</surname>
<given-names>Estelle H.</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0725513612470537">Raphael de Kadt, School of Commerce, Ethics and Humanities, St Augustine College, PO Box 44782, Linden 2104, South Africa. Email: <email>R.deKadt@staugustine.ac.za</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>115</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Between Adolescence and Anger: The ‘new’ South Africa nears Twenty</issue-title>
<fpage>112</fpage>
<lpage>126</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Thesis Eleven Pty, Ltd., SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article provides an account of rent-seeking in relation both to economic policies and political practices in South Africa. The article draws attention to continuities and similarities in this regard between the two distinct periods of nationalist rule from 1948 to 1994 and from 1994 to 2012. The economic dimensions that are specifically addressed are industrial policy, the labour market, state administration and tenders and service delivery and welfare. The more specifically political dimensions addressed include the electoral system, the relationship between constitutionalism and the judiciary, and the rule of law. The article highlights the dangers posed by excessive rent-seeking and especially its negative implications for redistribution, economic growth and the consolidation of democracy in a highly unequal society.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Middle-income countries</kwd>
<kwd>nationalist movements</kwd>
<kwd>political economy</kwd>
<kwd>rent-seeking</kwd>
<kwd>South Africa</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Nationalist political movements sometimes go through a revolutionary phase in which they expropriate the assets of the hated other, driving their opponents to political impotence, or exile, or even (in extreme cases) to liquidation. This has not been the path chosen by the two successive nationalist movements which have ruled South Africa since 1948. The 1948 Afrikaner National Party (NP) victory was achieved in a racially-restricted election and the African Nationalist Congress (ANC) victory in 1994 was the result of universalization of the franchise in a re-unified country. For both movements, change started from the base of the inherited state and proceeded incrementally.</p>
<p>This study explores policies and techniques of non-revolutionary nationalist rule in a middle-income country. There are grounds for comparison between measures taken by the two nationalist movements, particularly in relation to specific fields of operation, although the beneficiaries have been different. In particular, non-revolutionary nationalist movements create rents for their supporters. In turn, these rents have economic implications, since every rent has an efficiency cost and a distributive implication. They also have implications for the quality of the political system.</p>
<p>Economically, nationalist rents can arise from: (a) import substitution and elaborate industrial policy more generally and the use of state-owned enterprises, (b) affirmative action, the manipulation of the labour market, and distortion of principal-agent relationships, (c) state administration and tender practices, and (d) service provision and aspects of the welfare system. The necessity for all these measures can be put down to the multi-class nature of nationalism in a middle-income country. Nationalists have to deliver to their middle class, their working class and to a substantial under class. The composition of delivery is itself politically determined, leading to perpetual jostling within the nationalist political movement itself, with an associated instability in the heart of the system.</p>
<p>These measures connect to the political system by means of patronage or, in the discourse of contemporary South Africa, ‘cadre deployment’.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0725513612470537">2</xref>
</sup> They may require erosion of political freedom for their protection. Rents may be created by legal or illegal means. Illegally created rents are generally larger, but more risky. Quite often, legal measures may be surrounded by a penumbra of dubious legality shading into outright illegality. And any particular rent regime may be reinforced by a latent or manifest political threat of more extreme measures.</p>
<sec id="section1-0725513612470537">
<title>Industrial policy</title>
<p>South African industrialization started after the First World War, initially in difficult economic circumstances and then more rapidly after the country abandoned the gold standard at the end of 1932. It was associated with the imposition of import tariffs, often imposed at the instance of potential industrialists. The tariff system evolved into one of the most complex in the world. Import tariffs often lead to a balance of trade problem in that goods produced behind them are not competitive at world prices. Added to this was the impact of the increasing isolation of South Africa as a result of apartheid, which further constrained the balance of payments. Although controls on the flow of capital across borders were common in the Bretton Woods era, they were accentuated by emergency measures to contain capital outflows in the early 1960s.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0725513612470537">3</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The effect of this, for instance, on the motor industry can be seen clearly. Started in the 1920s, the industry was subjected to increasing local content requirements from the beginning of the 1960s, lasting through much of the remaining apartheid period. By the end of apartheid, the result of this process in industry after industry was the creation of monopolistically competitive, oligopolistic or monopoly market structures with ownership held by South African conglomerates.</p>
<p>The reintroduction of international capital mobility since 1994 has led to a considerable measure of de-conglomeration, in favour of more internationally connected, efficient and industrially specific corporations. South African Breweries has gone international as SABMiller, and Anglo American is now run from London.</p>
<p>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0725513612470537">Edwards et al. (2009</xref>: 151–81) find that there was a considerable simplification and rationalization of the South African tariff structure in the 1990s, but that progress has virtually ceased since 2000. They point out that the current preference in trade policy is for preferential agreements rather than further liberalization, designed to achieve substantial market access for manufactured and agricultural goods, and to leverage export-oriented investment, displaying what they describe as a strong mercantilist ethos among civil servants in the Department of Trade and Industry.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0725513612470537">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>More generally, South Africa has a history of trying to make industrial policy serve nationalist goals. Both sets of nationalists have wanted it to reduce poverty and unemployment among their constituencies. Editions of the <italic>South African Year Book</italic> were full of such schemes in the Depression Era. They vanished as the morning mist following rapid economic growth starting in 1933. Apartheid wanted a decentralization of industrial activity, if not to the heart of the Bantustans<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0725513612470537">5</xref>
</sup> themselves, then at least to their borders, and introduced a system of incentives and disincentives to achieve the goal, never with significant success.</p>
<p>The influence of Marxism was strong in the ANC in exile and many assumed that extensive nationalisation would follow an ANC political victory. This view was embarrassed by the collapse of communism in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. One response was to look for statist themes in the experience of Japan and the East Asian tigers, and the allure of a ‘relatively autonomous’, highly interventionist, state trade and industrial complex remains strong. Recently, indeed, a whole new set of documents have emerged and are competing for influence: the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0725513612470537">Office of the President’s (2012)</xref> <italic>National Development Plan</italic>, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612470537">Department of Trade and Industry’s (2010)</xref> <italic>Industrial Policy Action Plan,</italic> the Minister for Economic Development’s <italic>The</italic> <italic>New Growth Path: Framework </italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0725513612470537">Economic Development Department 2011</xref>), and the Congress of South African Trade Unions’ (COSATU)<italic> A Growth Path towards Full Employment </italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0725513612470537">2010</xref>) strategy. They are best read not as a blueprint for reducing unemployment and poverty but as a testimony to an enduring mentality.</p>
<p>Competition policy is a key part of industrial policy. There was a Competition Act under apartheid, but it was weakly enforced. A new Act was passed in 1998, establishing a Competition Commission and a Competition Tribunal. Both institutions have been active, investigating and adjudicating cases and establishing principles. The Act deals with the usual issues in competition policy – abuse of dominant position, collusion, mergers – but it has one important provision. Section 10(3)(b)(ii) provides that exemption to the provisions of the Act can be granted if an (uncompetitive) practice or agreement promotes the ability of firms controlled or owned by historically disadvantaged persons to become competitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0725513612470537">RSA 1998</xref>: 16).</p>
<p>It is considerably easier to meet nationalist goals in respect of employment in state-owned enterprises than in the private sector, since their governance is directly controlled by the state. This is why the privatization wave of the 1980s and 1990s had limited effects in South Africa, although there were some sales in the late 1980s and early 1990s, in anticipation of the political transition. Shares in the Iron and Steel Corporation were sold in 1989 and it has since become part of the ArcelorMittal Group. Government arms manufacturing was placed in DENEL in 1992, a company which has the South African government as its sole shareholder. TELKOM, formerly the state telecommunications agency, was partially privatized in 1991. The government has recently turned down a deal between the Korean KT Corporation and TELKOM which would have diluted the government’s and Public Investment Commission’s stake to less than 50 per cent. The Electricity Supply Commission has not been privatized in any way. During the first decade after 1994, ESKOM invested little in additional generating capacity, and has been struggling to meet demand in recent years. A crash building programme has been accompanied by rapidly increasing electricity prices.</p>
<p>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0725513612470537">Buccola and McCandlish (1999)</xref> point out that state enterprises retain de facto control of their markets long after surrendering any de jure monopoly privileges. Managers of the state firm and their supervisors in the civil service form a coherent lobbying group whose interest is to defend the enterprise from competition. For this reason privatization is subject to roll back, a tendency visible in South Africa at present.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0725513612470537">
<title>The labour market</title>
<p>On assuming office in 1924, Prime Minister Hertzog introduced racially based hiring norms into the civil service, restricting the number of black persons who could be hired per white employee. These complemented already existing measures of job reservation in the mines and the whole economic system was conditioned by unequal educational opportunity. South African whites born in 1885 received on average eight years of education; their black contemporaries received less than two. Even with this difference, there was a poor class of predominantly Afrikaner whites in the 1920s and 1930s which was subject to competition from black workers. What Afrikaner nationalism offered them was promotion to the status of a non-competing group. During the Smuts government of 1939–48, segregationist measures were rolled back to a degree,<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0725513612470537">6</xref>
</sup> and this provided mobilizational opportunities for the NP. When they were returned to power in 1948, the measures returned and were amplified. Key to the programme were: (a) segregation of the industrial relations system – black trade unions were not outlawed, but they were excluded from collective bargaining; (b) segregation in urban settlement using the Group Areas and Urban Areas Acts; (c) sharp limits on the scope and funding of black education; (d) reinforcement of existing limitations on black ownership outside the Bantustans; and (e) the attempt to put as much black employment on a migrant labour basis as possible, along with a major shift of black people out of the commercial farming areas into the Bantustans. In short, the labour market became riddled with rent – to the point where by the end of the 1960s it had started to become dysfunctional to some of the interests that had put it in place.</p>
<p>The problem was that the rapid economic growth of that decade had mopped up the last remaining white unemployment and that shortages of skilled labour had started to appear. First to go was the restrictive financing of black school education. This did not mean that the system ceased to be cheap and nasty; at the end of apartheid the learner:educator ratio in black education was still double that in the white system. Nor did it mean abandonment of control of the ideological content of black education. But it did mean rapid expansion of the number of black learners in the system. By the end of the 1970s, the segregation of the industrial relations system was undone. Repeal of influx control and the Group Areas Acts followed in the next decade. In the meantime, The Urban Foundation (formed by industrialists Harry Oppenheimer and Anton Rupert) chipped away at restrictions on black ownership in urban areas. Liberalizing tendencies were introduced into the labour market in the late apartheid period.</p>
<p>A new set of nationalists, a new set of rents. The first move was to have the principle of affirmative action written into the Constitution’s Bill of Rights. Section 9(2) states:<disp-quote>
<p>To promote the achievement of equality, legislative and other measures designed to protect or advance persons, or categories of person, disadvantaged by unfair discrimination may be taken. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0725513612470537">RSA 1996</xref>: 4)</p>
</disp-quote>Affirmative action in the labour market emerged informally immediately after the political transition. Trades between politically powerful but penniless exiles returning to govern and the business establishment were waiting to be done, as was the mutual desire to grow a black middle class. It took several years for ad hoc responses to develop into the Broad Based Black Economic Empowerment Act of 2003. This Act deals with more than just the labour market. Essentially it works by creating standards for black participation in the private sector under the following heads: equity ownership, management control, employment equity, skills development, preferential procurement, enterprise development and socio-economic development. Any firm may choose to be assessed against norms under these heads and to be assigned a Black Economic Empowerment (BEE) score. A favourable BEE score counts alongside price when state tenders are considered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0725513612470537">RSA 2003</xref>). The preferential procurement part creates backward linkages so that a firm not interested in tendering for state work itself might nonetheless want an assessment in order to supply another firm dealing directly with the state.</p>
<p>The relevance of this for the labour market lies in the management control, employment equity and skills development. Management control deals with black participation in the board and top management, employment equity with the composition of senior, middle and junior management and skills development with the extent of black participation in learning programmes. The result is that, as the South African Institute of Race Relations points out, the work environment has been re-racialized, requiring records which even apartheid at its height did not require.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0725513612470537">7</xref>
</sup> How well does this system work? Opinions differ. The system relies on accredited evaluators to produce BEE scores for firms who want them. The certificates are valid for a year. No central set of records is kept, and it is virtually impossible to construct the counterfactual of how things would be had the policy not been introduced. In a sense, the whole system, tricked out with precise regulations, may do little more than establish a general norm for black participation in the economy – which has been an economic imperative for several decades.</p>
<p>Moreover, demand-side manipulations have to interact with the supply conditions. This brings us to the mess that is contemporary South African education. Given the authoritarianism which was apartheid education, it was not surprising that progressive themes featured strongly in the early post-apartheid policy context. Rote learning was to be replaced by encouragement of learner creativity, tests and examinations by portfolios of work, competitive individualism by group work, syllabi by curriculum statements, and so forth. The trouble was that this was all to be introduced by poorly trained teachers who had neither the capacity nor the inclination to supply the necessary input. In many cases, schools did not have the necessary infrastructure either. The result was not a creative flowering but an inability to meet the most basic standards. In addition to resource problems, there is inadequate accountability in South African schools. The old inspectors were chased out of black schools in the troubles of the 1980s and have never been allowed back. Studies consistently show low time on task and low cognitive effort made by teachers and learners alike.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0725513612470537">8</xref>
</sup> Distortion of principal-agent relationships mean high consumption of leisure on the job by teachers – that, with high pay relative to GDP per capita, constitutes the rent deal for a constituency which is always important for nationalist movements. South African pupils routinely perform very badly in standardized international benchmarking tests (especially in mathematics), sometimes coming behind other less developed African countries.</p>
<p>In short, South African school education can be characterized as a low quality mass system. The General Household Survey shows that 98 per cent of children between the ages of 7 and 15 (the compulsory age range) are enrolled in schools, and that of every hundred pupils who start in Grade 1, about 94 reach Grade 9 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0725513612470537">SSA 2010</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0725513612470537">9</xref>
</sup> Drop-out rates increase sharply in the three year senior secondary school phase. Of every hundred students starting in Grade 10, fewer than 60 write the final National Senior Certificate. The National Senior Certificate classifies passing candidates as suitable for degree, diploma or certificate studies. Most degree passes proceed to university. A minority of diploma and certificate passes do, but many of the rest are catered for in private higher education. About half of those enrolling for degrees complete them and about 40 per cent of those enrolling for diplomas do the same. The filtering in senior secondary education and higher education means that those with a university qualification command high returns in the labour market and suffer markedly less unemployment than others. These are rents for a few. The system suffers from not having a larger and more critical middle class as a constituency for a more meritocratic system and as a bulwark against the removal of democratic rights.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0725513612470537">10</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0725513612470537">
<title>State administration and tenders</title>
<p>Francis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0725513612470537">Fukuyama (2011)</xref> claims that a successful modern democracy contains three components in a stable balance: efficient state administration, the rule of law, and accountable government. How does South African administration measure up to the first criterion?</p>
<p>In the early days after 1948, South African state policy was sometimes described as <italic>baasskap</italic>,<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0725513612470537">11</xref>
</sup> celebrating not only political victory but capture of key instances of state administration, with central power deployed to overrun opposition strongholds in the provinces and municipalities. Centralizing legislation was used in this battle. In particular, the administration of black affairs became a state within the state, replacing older provincial and local government authority. In all of this, it was essential to have senior civil service posts in safe sets of hands. This process was aided by the Broederbond, a secret association of influential Afrikaner nationalists who could be called on when needed. Moreover, the Broederbond was dedicated to cycling state funds through its members as far as possible.</p>
<p>Political transition, of course, ended that regime, with a graceful exit period negotiated as part of the transition package. It left a vacuum filled not by comprehensively competitive recruitment but, to a significant degree, by loyalists to the anti-apartheid cause, many of whom had prepared themselves carefully for the move between 1990 and 1994. ‘Cadre deployment’ came to describe the process which could easily surmount formal recruitment. Its legal status is far from clear and needs constitutional testing. Pre-1948 civil service practices meant that the top civil service positions were reached by internal promotion. From the 1970s onwards, the old departmental secretaries were replaced by new directors-general on fixed term contracts, who were much more sensitive to changes in political fortune and to ministerial appointments. Such a system encourages senior civil servants to move on to positions in the private sector.</p>
<p>The new system is as hostile as the old to genuine decentralization of power. The three tier system of government incorporated in the Constitution was closely negotiated, with the ANC compromising on the electoral independence of the middle tier of nine provinces. It has been restive about the issue ever since. It has had to deal with the Western Cape as an opposition province and even ANC fiefdoms at the provincial level have extracted concessions from the centre.</p>
<p>New legislation, notably the Public Finance Management Act of 1999, has modernized the normative order governing the civil service (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0725513612470537">RSA 1999</xref>). Getting the system to comply with it is another matter. The Auditor-General’s report for 2010–11 stated that the central government administration as a whole is not making progress towards the desired outcomes, with only 8 per cent of national departments receiving clean audits. The same stagnation of performance occurred in provincial government and many local authorities fail to submit accounts at all. The Auditor-General ascribes this situation to the high vacancy rate and staff acting in senior management positions. It is a situation which renders the system highly vulnerable to dubious and outright illegal practices.</p>
<p>In this context, a new class of businessman has come into existence: the ‘tenderpreneurs’, as they have come to be called. The tenderpreneur seeks to make a living from state tender awards. It does the tenderpreneur no harm to be active in ANC branches. Normatively, personal relationships and alliances should not play a part, but they often do and are intimately bound up with political relationships. More than one commentator has bemoaned the fact these relationships often define the effective content of ANC policy, making it difficult for the ANC to concentrate on policy as classically defined.</p>
<p>Two large pieces of pork have attracted particular attention. The first was the arms deal of the late 1990s designed to modernize South African defence force equipment. Arms deals the world over are notorious for their rent components, and certainly it seems that a great deal was wrong with this one.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0725513612470537">12</xref>
</sup> Legal contestation around it has gone on a long time and in 2011 President Zuma appointed a commission on inquiry into it, to stave off a possible judicial commission of inquiry. Wrangles and obfuscation have hampered the work of this commission ever since. The second is around the provision of infrastructure. The government has developed the habit of announcing ever larger sums to be spent on infrastructure over an unspecified period, by adding up the capital expenditures of all the infrastructure agencies. Sometimes these come in large chunks, such as the construction of the high-speed Gautrain between Johannesburg and Pretoria. It has recently come to light that the Canadian company who won the contract paid $35 million to a Tunisian agent as a part of its ‘capture plan’ for the contract. Middle Eastern connections featured in some of the scandals of the NP era.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0725513612470537">
<title>Service delivery and welfare</title>
<p>The ANC assumed office facing large service delivery deficits in black areas. Its manifesto for the 1994 election was premised on the Reconstruction and Development Programme and it made good on many of its early promises, such as the building of a million new homes in the first five years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0725513612470537">ANC 1994</xref>). It became clear that nearly all local governments would need more support than they could raise from local taxation. The Constitution provides that local governments are entitled to an equitable share of national revenues. Equitable share allocations started small in the late 1990s and rose dramatically between 2000 and 2010. The results are apparent in improved infrastructure, facilitating transport and access to water and electricity.</p>
<p>Income support for individuals and households has also risen. Non-contributory old age grants, disability grants, foster care grants and child dependency grants were in place under apartheid. The government added a child support grant in 1998. It started off as being available to support children under the age of seven in the poorer half of South African households. The age limit has been raised in steps from 7 to 18. About 16 million people, out of a total population of 50 million, receive a social grant.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0725513612470537">13</xref>
</sup> The government is committed to introducing a contributory social security and retirement system, as well as national health insurance, the latter to be phased in over a long period. Both will need careful design.</p>
<p>Redistribution through the fiscal system, though attended by economic inefficiencies, is not in itself rent. Rent may occur around the edges, as it does in local government expenditure. It may also occur in the social grants system if people are placed in categories for which they do not qualify. Disability grants are the most susceptible to this kind of manipulation. Understanding of rent-seeking can be extended by an analysis of South Africa’s political institutions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0725513612470537">
<title>The electoral system</title>
<p>South Africa before 1994 had a classical single member constituency electoral system. This was true even of the short-lived tricameral system for coloureds, Asians and whites with racially segregated electoral rolls between 1983 and 1994. The advent of universal franchise posed a dilemma: since voters were likely to vote along racial lines, the classical system threatened to close out minorities altogether from political representation. Proportional Representation (PR) held attractions for both the NP, inclined to think of the post-apartheid future in consociational<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0725513612470537">14</xref>
</sup> terms, and for the ANC, who did not want to see complete minority alienation from the system. Closed list proportional representation was decided upon. Political parties establish an ordered list of candidates, voters vote for parties, a cut-off point on each list is established by the electoral outcome and people above the cut-off points are returned to Parliament to represent their parties. Members of Parliament (MP) cease to be accountable to their constituencies; they owe their positions instead to party leaderships.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0725513612470537">15</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>It is possible to vary the terms of a proportional representation system, notably through the establishment of multi-member constituencies, and this was recommended by the van Zyl Slabbert Task Team.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-0725513612470537">16</xref>
</sup> The Task Team’s recommendations were not accepted. Change would require the support of party leaders who have a vested interest in the system remaining as it is and who now have very great control over MPs, weakening the power of the legislature and rendering it mediocre. Instead, the government divides the country into regions, each allocated to a Member of Parliament for their particular attention. Given the lack of real accountability, this arrangement has not amounted to much. One feature of the PR system has been to splinter the opposition. Among the racial minorities, multi-partyism is alive and well because the proportional representation system removes the incentives for consolidation.</p>
<p>Decades of single party dominance combined with the effects of the PR system on the legislature means that civil society lobbying of government is mainly directed at the executive. The personalities and standing of members of the Cabinet are more closely observed than debates in Parliament. The system of governance, along with corporatist institutions like the National Economic Development and Labour Advisory Council, with its representation of business, labour and government interests, fosters elite accommodation and its associated rent creation and allocation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0725513612470537">
<title>Constitutionalism and the judiciary</title>
<p>The NP became embroiled in fights with the courts over franchise issues in the 1950s which ended in the packing of the Supreme Court. It introduced detention without trial in the 1960s. It restricted the flow of information. It upheld the supremacy of Parliament against the courts through nearly all of its time in power. Only when the political transition was imminent did it see the advantages of constitutional rule. For its part, the ANC had suffered badly because of the virtual absence of judicial constraint on political decisions between the 1950s and 1994. This formed the basis of a shift to constitutional rule after 1994, with a Bill of Rights carefully negotiated as a chapter within the Constitution. A constitutional court was established and this has played an active role in defining the content of first-generation (civil) and second-generation (social and economic) rights.</p>
<p>At any time in a constitutional democracy tension may arise between the party in power and the judicial interpreters and enforcers of the Constitution. The ANC executive respects the decisions of the Constitutional Court, but tension has appeared in recent years. One issue is the composition of the judiciary, the ANC projecting the view that it is not really ‘our’ judiciary because ‘our’ people are not adequately represented in it. Lawyers qualify for senior judicial posts by virtue of many years’ experience, and there has been a black catch-up issue. This problem, however, diminishes steadily over time. The ‘our’ has a political as well as an ethnic dimension, however, and the Cabinet has initiated a process of review of the powers of the Constitutional Court. The review is to be carried out by research institutions and will be completed in 18 months. The Department of Justice and Constitutional Development has released a discussion document<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-0725513612470537">17</xref>
</sup> in which it is made clear that the desired outcome is the development of a ‘comprehensive programme of action to enable each branch of the state to overcome the hurdles that confront the transformation of the legal sector and society in general’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0725513612470537">2012</xref>: 28).</p>
<p>Fears about what this may mean in practice have been raised by the Protection of State Information Bill. This is designed to regulate the classification, protection and dissemination of state information and involves weighing up state interests against transparency and freedom of information. Nadine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0725513612470537">Gordimer (2012)</xref>, generally sympathetic to the ANC but also on the receiving end of apartheid censorship, has recently published sharp criticism of the proposal. COSATU is also critical, stating that ‘the Secrecy Bill is merely [part] of a much bigger and problematic effort to centralise power in the security cluster of government’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0725513612470537">COSATU 2012</xref>). Rents can be expected to multiply when they are shielded from public knowledge and debate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0725513612470537">
<title>The rule of law in practice</title>
<p>South Africa has long had a distinguished legal tradition. Its law schools are of high standard and its leading lawyers have often made international as well as national contributions. But lower down, in the magistrates’ and traditional courts, the system is poorly resourced and often works badly. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612470537">Du Preez (2012)</xref> cites a serious backlog of cases – about 210,000 in 2007 – with a steady increase in the number of prisoners awaiting trial for more than two years. He attributes the problems to poor police work, shortage of personnel and facilities and poor management of the courts, and tampering with or loss of documents. Democratic Alliance spokeswoman Debbie Schafer provides the following analysis of the outcome: the number of cases disposed of by other courts in 2010–11 was 996,320. Of these, there were verdicts in 331,045 cases with 293,673 convictions. 129,846 cases were resolved through alternative dispute resolution methods and 535,429 were removed from the rolls. The number of serious crimes reported to the police exceeded two million in the same period. So performance depends on how one counts: 89 per cent of verdicts were convictions, 29 per cent of cases brought to court resulted in convictions and fewer than 15 per cent of crime reports ended with convictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0725513612470537">Schafer 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>Unnerving, too, is the mistrust of the police by wide sections of the public. The 2008 Afrobarometer survey showed that respondents were more likely to regard the police as corrupt than any other group about which they were asked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0725513612470537">Afrobarometer 2008</xref>). Statistics South Africa’s <italic>Victims of Crime Survey</italic> in 2011 showed that over a third of South African households were not satisfied with the police, the most widespread complaints being of laziness, corruption, invisibility and early release of criminals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0725513612470537">SSA 2011</xref>). Dispiritingly, two successive commissioners of police have run into trouble with the law. Commissioner Selebi received a 15-year sentence for acceptance of bribes and perjury and Commissioner Cele is under investigation for corruption and unlawful procurement. Not surprisingly, there has been controversy over the disbanding of the Scorpions, a special investigating unit within the National Prosecuting Agency (and not under the Commissioner of Police). It helped the Scorpions not at all that they had been involved in the investigation of Jacob Zuma for fraud, corruption, money laundering and tax offences. The charges were dropped in 2009. The Supreme Court of Appeal has, however, created the possibility that they could be reinstated.</p>
<p>Defects of police performance in protecting the public has led to the growth of private security firms with functions ranging from the protection of VIPs to the securing of company premises and providing armed response protection to middle-class homes, all rents arising from the absence of a public good.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0725513612470537">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>Rents are to be found in all societies. How severe is South Africa’s situation?</p>
<p>One measure is Transparency International’s Corruption Perceptions Indicator. In 2011, South Africa was ranked 64th out of 182 countries, slightly below Turkey and slightly ahead of Italy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0725513612470537">Transparency International 2011</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-0725513612470537">18</xref>
</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0725513612470537">Transparency International (2010)</xref> also conducted a survey in southern Africa in 2010, which found that two-thirds of respondents regarded the police, and nearly half regarded political parties and Parliament, to be extremely corrupt; 43 per cent reported having paid bribes in the last 12 months to the police, 39 per cent to registry services and 20 per cent to the judiciary. Two-thirds of the bribes were paid to avoid problems with the authorities; 62 per cent of respondents felt that corruption was getting worse, against 24 per cent who felt it was getting better. However, more than 60 per cent believed that ordinary people can make a difference in the fight against corruption. South African civil society has developed resistance to the worst forms of political oppression over the years.</p>
<p>Rents may have static or dynamic effects on the economy. Static effects lower welfare; dynamic effects lower the growth rate. Rents which strike at the savings and investment mechanism are a source of particular concern. All three major ratings agencies (S &amp; P, Fitch, and Moody’s) have downgraded the outlook for the South African economy from stable to negative between November 2011 and June 2012. Fitch commented as follows:<disp-quote>
<p>The negative outlook reflects the limited progress on several long-standing structural issues that have over time caused South Africa’s economic performance to fall behind its peers. The inability to create sufficient jobs has constrained growth and kept the tax base narrow and has caused public finances to become increasingly redistributive. The resulting narrowing of fiscal space undermined a key support to South Africa’s creditworthiness. The ANC is unlikely to expropriate assets, but its entertaining of the nationalisation debate has upset investor confidence. Any move to nationalise mines would adversely affect the business climate and have immediate and negative consequences for the rating. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0725513612470537">England 2012</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote>Although there is evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0725513612470537">Drury et al. 2006</xref>) that while corruption impacts in significantly negative ways on economic growth in non-democracies it has little impact in democracies, there is little cause to be sanguine about its impact on the prospects for economic and political prosperity in South Africa. The dangerous scenario for South Africa is as follows. Dynamic rents lower the growth rate. The struggle for rent at all levels intensifies. Stagnation follows with growing radicalization in the political sphere. Ultimately, the system lurches into an experiment which would at once close down democracy and cause the economy to collapse. Difficult global economic circumstances and high levels of domestic inequality increase the risk of this scenario.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-0725513612470537">19</xref></sup> Long periods of dominant party rule have induced a cultural adaptation to rent-seeking. A long period without political alternation results in ‘rent encrustation’, and is likely to be conducive to the formation of anti-democratic preferences and sentiments on the part of incumbent office bearers who are recipients of rent. Such anti-democratic sentiments were not absent, in the South African case, from the leadership of, and among many key functionaries in, the apartheid era NP regime.</p>
<p>Defence of democracy would then require a struggle to prevent development along these lines, a new South African politics. It would have to break long-standing moulds of political behaviour. Fortunately South Africa has some entrenched democratic traditions and values which, as past contestations and progress have shown, are available to be effectively drawn on and mobilized.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0725513612470537">
<label>1.</label>
<p>‘A rent is personal benefit for which there is no corresponding counterpart value of personal productive contribution’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0725513612470537">Hillman 2009</xref>: 85). Rents may take diverse forms, not all of which are against the ‘public good’ or damaging to the ‘public interest’. Thus, there may be ‘ego rents’ which refer to the ‘private enjoyment of prestige and power’ and even ‘negative rents’ where talented, public spirited personnel earn much less in pursuing public service careers than they would earn in the private sector (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0725513612470537">Przeworski 2003</xref>: 88). Also, where rents take a form that <italic>is</italic> damaging to the country, they may be extracted through diverse means ranging from outright theft, such as in the case of President Mobutu of Zaire, to usufruct and the enjoyment of the perks of office, as was the pattern in the former Soviet Union (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0725513612470537">Przeworski 2003</xref>: 88–9). </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0725513612470537">
<label>2.</label>
<p>A ‘cadre’ in the South African context is a loyal member of the ANC, or of some part of the governing alliance, including Cosatu and/or the South African Communist Party. ‘Deployment’, euphemistically, means ‘bringing into effective action’, and entails appointing, or seconding, such a loyal member to a position of power and/or responsibility. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0725513612470537">Hoffman (2010)</xref> for one account of this phenomenon.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0725513612470537">
<label>3.</label>
<p>The 1960s controls reactivated some of the Wartime Measures of 1939.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0725513612470537">
<label>4.</label>
<p>On the relationship between mercantilism and rent see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0725513612470537">Basinger et al. (1980)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0725513612470537">
<label>5.</label>
<p>The term ‘Bantustan’ refers to territories that were allocated, under the apartheid regime, to black ‘ethnic groups’ with the intention that they should be, or become, self-governing ethnic ‘homelands’. The purpose of creating these was to exclude black South Africans from citizenship rights in the so-called ‘white’ areas.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0725513612470537">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Smuts proclaimed in 1942 that segregation had fallen on evil days.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0725513612470537">
<label>7.</label>
<p>See, for instance, <italic>The Rainbow Index 2010/2011</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0725513612470537">SAIRR 2011</xref>: 19–22).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0725513612470537">
<label>8.</label>
<p>See for instance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0725513612470537">Chisholm et al. (2005)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0725513612470537">
<label>9.</label>
<p>See the <italic>General Household Survey P0318 2010</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0725513612470537">SSA 2010</xref>); own tabulations from GHS unit record data.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0725513612470537">
<label>10.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0725513612470537">Glaeser et al. (2007</xref>: 77–99) for an account of the relationship between democracy and education.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0725513612470537">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Literally translated as ‘bossism’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0725513612470537">
<label>12.</label>
<p>The best reference is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0725513612470537">Feinstein (2007)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0725513612470537">
<label>13.</label>
<p>See the <italic>South Africa Survey</italic> published annually by the South African Institute of Race Relations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0725513612470537">(SAIRR) (various years)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0725513612470537">
<label>14.</label>
<p>A consociational arrangement is a political power-sharing deal that is struck between the leaderships of parties or movements in conflict in societies with deep ethnic, religious or linguistic divisions or cleavages. Among the ‘classical’ accounts of the phenomenon are the seminal works of Arend <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0725513612470537">Lijphart (1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0725513612470537">1977</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0725513612470537">
<label>15.</label>
<p>On this, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0725513612470537">Congleton (2011</xref>: 285–6).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-0725513612470537">
<label>16.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0725513612470537">Electoral Task Team (2003)</xref>. The task team was chaired by Frederik van Zyl Slabbert (1940–2010), a former Professor of Sociology at the University of the Witwatersrand who entered Parliament in 1974 as a member of the liberal opposition Progressive Party and who rose, subsequently, to become Leader of the Official Opposition and of the Progressive Federal Party. He left Parliament in 1986 on the grounds that the required political transition to democracy could not be achieved through Parliament. Subsequent to his departure from parliamentary politics, he played a key role in facilitating dialogue between the leaders of the ANC and leading white businessmen and politicians.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-0725513612470537">
<label>17.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0725513612470537">Department of Justice and Constitutional Development (2012)</xref> for the <italic>Discussion Document on the Transformation of the Judicial System and the Role of the Judiciary in the Developmental South African State</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-0725513612470537">
<label>18.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0725513612470537">Transparency International (2011)</xref>. It should be noted that although rent-seeking and corruption (for instance in the form of bribery) are not identical, the level of corruption in a country is a useful indirect measure of the extent of rent-seeking practices.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-0725513612470537">
<label>19.</label>
<p>On the relationship between inequality and democratic consolidation, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0725513612470537">Houle (2009)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">African National Congress (ANC)</collab> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>National election manifesto</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.anc.org.za/show.php?id=262">http://www.anc.org.za/show.php?id=262</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Afrobarometer</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Is crime dividing the rainbow nation? Fear of crime in South Africa</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idasa.org/media/uploads/outputs/files/Afrobarometer%20study%20on%20Crime%20in%20South%20Africa.pdf">http://www.idasa.org/media/uploads/outputs/files/Afrobarometer%20study%20on%20Crime%20in%20South%20Africa.pdf</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Basinger</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekelund</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tollison</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Mercantilism as a rent-seeking society</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Buchanan</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tollison</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tullock</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Towards a Theory of the Rent-seeking Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Texas</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>A &amp; M University Press</publisher-name>. </citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Buccola</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCandlish</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Rent seeking and rent dissipation in state enterprises</article-title>. <source>Review of Agricultural Economics</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>358</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chisholm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoadley</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>wa Kivulu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Educator Work Load in South Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HSRC Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Congleton</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Perfecting Parliament: Constitutional Reform, Liberalism and the Rise of Western Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU)</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>A Growth Path towards Full Employment</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://us-cdn.creamermedia.co.za/assets/articles/attachments/29577_cosatu_booklet.pdf">http://us-cdn.creamermedia.co.za/assets/articles/attachments/29577_cosatu_booklet.pdf</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU)</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <source>COSATU Submission to the NCOP on the Protection of State Information Bill (POSIB)</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pmg.org.za/report/20120329-protection-state-information-bill-public-hearings-day-3">http://www.pmg.org.za/report/20120329-protection-state-information-bill-public-hearings-day-3</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Department of Justice and Constitutional Development</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Discussion Document on the Transformation of the Judicial System and the Role of the Judiciary in the Developmental South African State</source>. <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Justice and Constitutional Development</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Department of Trade and Industry</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>2010–2011 – 2012–2013 Industrial Policy Action Plan</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.info.gov.za/view/DownloadFileAction?id=117330">http://www.info.gov.za/view/DownloadFileAction?id=117330</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Drury</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krieckhaus</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lusztig</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Corruption, democracy and economic growth</article-title>. <source>International political Science Review</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Du Preez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Justice delayed is justice denied</article-title>. <comment>F W de Klerk Foundation, 24 May. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fwdeklerk.org/cgi-bin/giga.cgi?cmd=cause_dir_news_item&amp;cause_id=2137&amp;news_id=114983&amp;cat_id=1596#.UCWj6qCbHqI">http://www.fwdeklerk.org/cgi-bin/giga.cgi?cmd=cause_dir_news_item&amp;cause_id=2137&amp;news_id=114983&amp;cat_id=1596#.UCWj6qCbHqI</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Economic Development Department</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The New Growth Path: Framework</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.economic.gov.za/publications/new-growth-path-series/125-new-growth-path-framework">http://www.economic.gov.za/publications/new-growth-path-series/125-new-growth-path-framework</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cassim</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Seventer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Trade policy in South Africa</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kahn</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kahn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kindon</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>South African Economic Policy under Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Electoral Task Team</collab> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Report of the Electoral Task Team</source>. <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Home Affairs</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>England</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fitch puts South Africa on negative</article-title>. <source>Financial Times</source>, <issue>13 January</issue>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.ft.com/beyond-brics/2012/01/13/fitch-puts-south-africa-on-negative-watch/#axzz24shGWpuT">http://blogs.ft.com/beyond-brics/2012/01/13/fitch-puts-south-africa-on-negative-watch/#axzz24shGWpuT</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feinstein</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>After the Party: A Personal and Political Journey inside the ANC</source>. <publisher-loc>Johannesburg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jonathan Ball</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fukuyama</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The Origins of Political Order: From Prehistoric Times to the French Revolution</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Profile Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glaeser</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ponzetto</surname>
<given-names>GNS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schleifer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Why does democracy need education?</article-title> <source>Journal of Economic Growth</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gordimer</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>South Africa: The new threat to freedom</article-title>. <source>New York Review of Books</source> <volume>LIX</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Public Finance and Public Policy, 2nd Edn</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoffman</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cadre deployment</article-title>. <source>The Institute for Accountability in Southern Africa</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ifaisa.org/Cadre_Deployment.html">http://www.ifaisa.org/Cadre_Deployment.html</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Houle</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Inequality and democracy: Why inequality harms consolidation but does not affect democratization</article-title>. <source>World Politics</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lijphart</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>The Politics of Accommodation</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lijphart</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <source>Democracy in Plural Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Office of the President</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <source>National Development Plan 2030. Our future – make it work</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.info.gov.za/view/DownloadFileAction?id=172297">http://www.info.gov.za/view/DownloadFileAction?id=172297</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Przeworski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>States and Markets: A Primer in Political Economy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Republic of South Africa (RSA)</collab> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Constitution of the Republic of South Africa, No. 108 of 1996, Chapter 2</article-title>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>). <publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of the President</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Republic of South Africa (RSA)</collab> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Competition Act, No. 89 of 1998</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of the President</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Republic of South Africa (RSA)</collab> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Public Finance Management Act, No. 1 of 1999</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of the President</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Republic of South Africa (RSA)</collab> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Broad-based Black Economic Empowerment Act, No. 53 of 2003</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of the President</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schafer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Criminal conviction rate: Lies, damned lies and statistics</article-title>. <source>Democratic Alliance (DA)</source>, <comment>Newsroom/press releases, 4 June. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.da.org.za/newsroom.htm?action=view-news-item&amp;id=10763">http://www.da.org.za/newsroom.htm?action=view-news-item&amp;id=10763</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">South African Institute of Race Relations (SAIRR)</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The Rainbow Index 2010/2011</source>. <publisher-loc>Johannesburg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>South African Institute of Race Relations</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">South African Institute of Race Relations (SAIRR)</collab> (<year>various years</year>) <source>South Africa Survey</source>. <publisher-loc>Johannesburg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>South African Institute of Race Relations</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Statistics South Africa (SSA)</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>General Household Survey 2010 (Revised version), Statistics Release PO318</source>. <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistics South Africa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Statistics South Africa (SSA)</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>South Africa’s Victims of Crime Survey</source>. <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistics South Africa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">The Department of Justice and Constitutional Development</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Discussion Document on the Transformation of the Judicial System and Role of the Judiciary in the Developmental South African State</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov.za/m_statements/2012/20120228_m_transformation.html">http://www.justice.gov.za/m_statements/2012/20120228_m_transformation.html</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Transparency International</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Daily lives and corruption: Public opinion in southern Africa</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.transparency.org/files/content/pressrelease/20111122_TI-S_Southern_Africa_EN.pdf">http://www.transparency.org/files/content/pressrelease/20111122_TI-S_Southern_Africa_EN.pdf</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0725513612470537">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Transparency International</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Corruption Perceptions Index 2011</source>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cpi.transparency.org/cpi2011/results/">http://cpi.transparency.org/cpi2011/results/</ext-link> <comment>(consulted August 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>