<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnas</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nasnewsletter.</journal-id>
<journal-title>NASN School Nurse</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1942-602X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1942-6038</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1942602X12437879</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1942602X12437879</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Feature Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>What Every School Nurse Needs to Know About Section 504 Eligibility</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>Cheryl Husa</given-names></name>
<degrees>MN, BSN, RN, NCSN</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1942602X12437879">School Nurse Specialist Central Valley School District Spokane Valley, WA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Galemore</surname><given-names>Cynthia A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSEd, BSN, RN, NCSN</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1942602X12437879">Editor, <italic>NASN School Nurse</italic> Director of Health Services Olathe Public Schools</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-1942602X12437879">
<p>Cheryl has been a school nurse in Central Valley School District since 1995 and also served as the lead school nurse for the district since 1997. She recently completed 10 years on the board of directors for the School Nurse Organization of Washington working her way up from committee chair for writing position statements to President.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-1942602X12437879">
<p>Cynthia is the editor of the <italic>NASN School Nurse</italic>. In addition, she serves as the director of health services supervising over 50 school nurses for Olathe Public Schools, the second-largest school district in Kansas. She is also the chair of professional standards for the Kansas School Nurse Organization.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>88</fpage>
<lpage>93</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 National Association of School Nurses</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">National Association of School Nurses</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Americans With Disabilities Amendment Act of 2008 (ADAA), effective January 1, 2009, expanded the definition of disability. These changes in turn impact which students qualify for Section 504 plans in the school setting and will no doubt strain school resources as implementation of the law progresses. Therefore, it is essential that school nurses be well versed in the changes in order to continue to perform a lead role in advocating for students with disabilities in the school setting and to assist with Section 504 compliance.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Section 504</kwd>
<kwd>accommodations</kwd>
<kwd>ADA</kwd>
<kwd>major life activities</kwd>
<kwd>eligibility</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic id="img1-1942602X12437879" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1942602X12437879-img1.tif"/>
<p>With passage of the Americans With Disabilities Amendment Act of 2008 (ADAA), Congress amended the American With Disabilities Act of 1990 (ADA) and included a conforming amendment to the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 affecting the meaning of <italic>disability</italic> in Section 504 (34 C.F.R. Part 104., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1942602X12437879">2008</xref>). The changes, along with a history of Section 504, were thoroughly reviewed with regard for the role of the school nurse in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1942602X12437879">Zirkel’s 2009</xref> article published in the <italic>Journal of School Nursing</italic>. According to Zirkel (p. 256), “Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 and it sister civil rights statute, the ADA, probably have been the most important federal laws in terms of the responsibilities of the school nurse to K-12 students.” Zirkel’s article also included a systematic discussion of the difference between the Individuals With Disabilities Education Act (IDEA), an act with provisions and funding for disabilities that specifically impact learning, Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, and the ADA. The reader is referred back to the historical article as needed to differentiate between these acts. Readers are also encouraged to review the U.S. Department of Education (DOE) <italic>Revised Frequently Asked Questions</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. DOE, 2009</xref>) that was written for the purpose of clarifying the requirements in the area of public elementary and secondary education.</p>
<p>Section 504 applies not only to public schools (known recipients of federal funding) but also to private, parochial, and postsecondary education institutions if they receive any form of federal financial assistance (e.g., IDEA services, Title 1 services, grants from the U.S. DOE, U.S. Department of Agriculture’s school hot lunch program, etc.) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. DOE, 2009</xref>). Three years have passed since the amendment, allowing time for interpretation and beginning implementation of changes. The purpose of this article is to once again underscore the changes and also to provide practical guidance for school nurse leadership related to Section 504 eligibility compliance at the local level.</p>
<sec id="section1-1942602X12437879">
<title>Expansion of Eligibility</title>
<p>Distinct from the IDEA, Section 504 expands disabilities beyond learning to other major life activities with three criteria:</p>
<list id="list1-1942602X12437879" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>a mental or physical impairment</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>that substantially limits</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>one or more of major life activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. DOE, 2009</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In the ADAA (S. 3406, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1942602X12437879">2008</xref>) the definition of <italic>major life activities</italic> was broadened to include a fairly extensive list of general life activities such as reading, concentrating, thinking, sleeping, eating, and operations of major bodily functions. The ADAA further emphasized that these activities are just examples and not a complete listing of major life activities.</p>
<p>In addition, the regulations now clearly include impairments that are episodic or in remission if they would substantially affect a major life activity when active (S. 3406, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1942602X12437879">2008</xref>). Furthermore, the ameliorative effects of mitigating measures are no longer to be considered when determining eligibility. <italic>Mitigating measures</italic>, as listed in the ADAA, include such things as medication, medical supplies, equipment or appliances, low-vision devices, prosthetics, hearing aids and cochlear implants or other implantable hearing devices, mobility devices, oxygen therapy equipment and supplies, use of assistive technology, environmental or instructional accommodations other related aids or services, learned behavior or adaptive neurological modifications, and so forth (S. 3406). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1942602X12437879">Table 1</xref> lists the original and broadened definitions for <italic>disability</italic>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1942602X12437879" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Broadening and Clarifying the Definition of Disability</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1942602X12437879" xlink:href="10.1177_1942602X12437879-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">American With Disabilities Act of 1990</th>
<th align="center">Americans With Disabilities Amendment Act of 2008</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Listing of major life activities</td>
<td valign="top">Included<break/>• seeing<break/>• hearing<break/>• speaking<break/>• walking<break/>• breathing<break/>• performing manual tasks<break/>• learning<break/>• caring for oneself<break/>• working</td>
<td valign="top">Expanded to include<break/>• reading<break/>• concentrating<break/>• thinking<break/>• sleeping<break/>• eating<break/>• and various major bodily functions including operation of the immune system, normal cell growth, digestive, bowel, bladder, neurological, brain, respiratory, circulatory, endocrine, and reproductive functions.<break/>ADAA further emphasized that this is not an exhaustive list.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Consideration of length of time of disability</td>
<td valign="top">Temporary impairment does <bold><italic>not</italic></bold> constitute a disability unless it results in substantial limitation for an extended period of time.</td>
<td valign="top">Clarified that a transitory and minor impairment (actual or expected duration of 6 months or less) <bold><italic>does not</italic></bold> constitute a disability<break/>Clarified that impairments must be considered disabilities that are <bold><italic>episodic or in remission</italic></bold> if the condition would substantially impair a major life activity when active</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Substantial limitation</td>
<td valign="top">Made on a case-by-case basis by a group of knowledgeable persons—impairment is significant and somewhat unique, rather than common-place, when compared to the average person in the general population</td>
<td valign="top">Clarifies that the eligibility determination need not entail “extensive analysis” and it be expansive rather than restrictive</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Consideration of ameliorating effects of any mitigating measures</td>
<td valign="top">Allowed to consider ameliorating effects of mitigating measures</td>
<td valign="top"><bold><italic>No longer allowed</italic></bold> to consider mitigating measures <bold><italic>except eyeglasses and contact lenses</italic></bold> (lenses that are intended to fully correct visual acuity or eliminate refractive error); the 2008 amendment provides an expansive list of mitigating measures</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1942602X12437879">
<p>Sources: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1942602X12437879">Zirkel (2009)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. Department of Education (2009)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. DOE document (2009)</xref> also clarifies that school districts do <bold><italic>not</italic></bold> develop Section 504 plans for a student who either “has a record of disability” or is “regarded as disabled”:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>In public elementary and secondary schools, unless a student actually has an impairment that substantially limits a major life activity, the mere fact that a student has a “record of” or is “regarded as” disabled is insufficient, in itself, to trigger those Section 504 protections that require the provision of a free appropriate public education. (#37)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The expansion of life activities with the addition of temporary or episodic impairments and the requirement to no longer consider mitigating factors mean that many students who previously would not have been eligible now qualify as an individual with a disability under Section 504. A common example would include a student with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder whose symptoms are fairly well regulated by medication. In the past, this student might not have been determined as eligible because of the ameliorative effects of the medication, though if receiving medication at school he or she would likely have been afforded an Individualized Healthcare Plan (IHP) developed by the school nurse. Similarly, a student with asthma and receiving medication resulting in control of symptoms would not have been considered eligible and likely also have had an IHP on file. As a result, the ADAA is expected to increase the percentage of public school students with 504 plans from the 1.2% originally cited in a study by Holler and Zirkel published in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1942602X12437879">2008</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1942602X12437879">
<title>Impact of Eligibility Changes on School Section 504 Processes</title>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Many students who previously would not have been eligible now qualify as an individual with a disability under Section 504.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>After assimilating the magnitude of the changes defining Section 504 eligibility, several questions naturally come to mind:</p>
<list id="list2-1942602X12437879" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Do students serviced under IDEA also need a 504 plan?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How is it possible to know if the impairment would substantially limit a major life activity if it were present in its full-blown state or if the mitigating factor was not in use, particularly if the mitigating measure has been in use for a long period of time?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Are there certain chronic health conditions that always warrant a 504 plan?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does an IHP suffice for the 504 plan?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How are we going to be able to manage the growing list of individuals with disabilities now seemingly eligible for 504 plans, especially in this time of shrinking school budgets?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Indeed, the questions are many and call for additional discussion.</p>
<p>With regard to a student’s being serviced by IDEA, the Individualized Education Plan (IEP) must include nursing and other school health services if they are required for the child to benefit from special education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1942602X12437879">Zirkel, 2009</xref>). Therefore, a student would <italic>not</italic> have both an IEP and a Section 504 plan, though a student with an IEP that includes specific nursing services will likely have an IHP. In essence, the student’s IEP is the school’s proof of providing Section 504 services, only under the IDEA umbrella.</p>
<p>Second, with regard to not being allowed to consider mitigating factors when determining eligibility, it is important to understand a final requirement of eligibility—“Does the student need accommodations and services to have his educational needs met as adequately as the needs of non-disabled students?” (Incorporate “relaxed” ADA standards, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1942602X12437879">2010</xref>, p. 4). A student with ADHD performing well at school or a student well controlled on asthma medications may be found technically eligible but not need a 504 plan. Students found technically eligible are afforded key protections such as the right not to be discriminated against on the basis of disability, the right to a manifestation determination review prior to a <italic>significant change in placement, and</italic> protection from excessive short-term removals. Additionally, the student can file an Office of Civil Rights complaint and has a right to a Section 504 due process hearing, periodic reevaluations (at least every 3 years, but more often depending on individual district policies to determine if a 504 plan is needed in the future), and a right to equal access of extracurricular and nonacademic services (Incorporate “relaxed” ADA standards).</p>
<p>Next, how do school nurses decide which health conditions warrant a Section 504 plan? Certain conditions like Type 1 Diabetes stand out, and interpretation may vary from state to state. For example, in the state of Washington, Carolyn Madsen, an Assistant Attorney General, and James Rich, a Washington state education administrator considered the most knowledgeable in the state about the implementation of 504 law, in the document “A Parent and Educator Guide to Free Appropriate Public Education” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1942602X12437879">Rich, 2010</xref>), have stated that all students with life-threatening health conditions require a 504 plan. Because the state of Washington actually has a legal definition of a <italic>life-threatening health condition</italic> (RCW 28A.210.320, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1942602X12437879">2006</xref>), this seems to be a logical requirement. However, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. DOE (2009)</xref> continues to endorse the position that there is no impairment that confers automatic eligibility under Section 504; rather, a medical diagnosis is one source of information to be considered among others in determining the student’s eligibility. As a further consideration, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1942602X12437879">Olathe District Schools (2011)</xref> in Olathe, Kansas, has developed a list of red flags to consider along with health conditions very likely to warrant 504 eligibility consideration (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1942602X12437879">Table 2</xref>). The considerations identified are solely to assist in identifying students who warrant further review.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1942602X12437879" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>504 Eligibility Considerations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1942602X12437879" xlink:href="10.1177_1942602X12437879-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Red Flags to Consider</th>
<th align="center">Health Conditions Very Likely to Warrant 504 Eligibility Consideration</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Frequent or excessive absences as the result of a medical condition<break/>Threats or attempts to commit suicide<break/>Visits to the school nurse on a frequent basis due to a health condition<break/>Missing excessive instructional time due to a health condition<break/>Medical reports that speak to a severe chronic or episodic health condition<break/>Inability of the student to self-monitor his or her chronic health condition symptoms<break/>The need for several staff members to be aware of the student’s health condition</td>
<td valign="top">Type 1 Diabetes<break/>Severe allergies (consider all students with history of a severe reaction or with coexisting diagnosis of asthma)<break/>Asthma (consider all students with a history of past serious episodes where immediate access to medication is of greater importance)<break/>Seizure disorder (consider all students with emergency medication order and/or history of life-threatening seizure episode)<break/>Depression (consider all student with known diagnosis and/or with past suicide attempt)<break/>Bowel/bladder disorders that benefit from bathroom privileges<break/>Impaired mobility disorders<break/>Any student with a medical diagnosis that potentially limits life expectancy</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1942602X12437879">
<p>Source: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1942602X12437879">Olathe District Schools (2011)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>To be sure, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1942602X12437879">U.S. DOE’s document (2009)</xref> points out that a variety of sources must be reviewed in the evaluation process to minimize the possibility of error. The information obtained from all such sources must be documented and all significant factors related to the student’s learning process must be considered. These sources and factors may include aptitude and achievement tests, school nurse and teacher recommendations, medical reports, current and past physical condition, social and cultural background, and adaptive behavior. The document also warns that it is unacceptable to rely on presumptions and stereotypes regarding persons with disabilities or classes of such persons.</p>
<p>Also required to determine eligibility is advanced parent notification of evaluation and a decision-making process conducted by a team of knowledgeable individuals. As stated in the U.S. DOE <italic>Frequently Asked Questions About Section 504 and the Education of Children with Disabilities</italic> (2009),</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>The Section 504 regulatory provision at 34 C.F.R.104.35 (c) (3) requires that school districts ensure that the determination that a student is eligible for special education and/or related aids and services be made by a group of persons, including persons knowledgeable about the meaning of the evaluation data and knowledgeable about the placement options. (#28).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>See the referenced document for procedures to follow if parents decline the initial evaluation.</p>
<p>School nurses spend a lot of time developing IHPs and emergency care plans (ECPs). The idea of having to develop yet another plan and attend another meeting for the same student may feel to some as if they were reinventing the wheel. However, school nurses can utilize the new ADAA requirements as an opportunity to emphasize the importance of health accommodations in a team setting. Portions of an already-created IHP and ECP will likely serve well as starting accommodations for the Section 504 plan, thus serving a dual purpose. The Section 504 accommodation plan, for students found eligible, is one of the many required documented steps in the process; thus an IHP, with or without a ECP, will not suffice for the entire Section 504 plan.</p>
<p>In summary, it is suggested that schools take the following steps to implement the changes in eligibility brought about by the ADAA:</p>
<list id="list3-1942602X12437879" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Maintain current local procedures for identifying students as eligible under Section 504 with consideration of the changes in eligibility.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Provide information regarding the changes to key players such as school principals, counselors, school nurses, and other regular members of the Section 504 evaluation team.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Amend forms to include the definitional changes for “major life activity.”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Include in the thorough consideration of eligibility the level of the student’s abilities without the use of mitigating measures, such as medication or hearing aids.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Remember to periodically review students found technically eligible but not needing a Section 504 plan initially.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Consider including a brief explanation of the changes in the mandatory “notice of evaluation parent letter.”</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Public elementary and secondary schools that receive federal funding, as mentioned at the beginning of the article, are required to meet the individual education needs of students with disabilities as adequately as they meet the needs of students without disabilities. This has also been stated as the requirement to provide a free appropriate public education to qualified students with disabilities consisting of regular or special education and related aids and services that help to <bold><italic>level the playing field</italic></bold>. Now that it has been 3 years since the ADAA of 2008, school nurses across the United States are feeling the impact of the changes in the law. Interpretations of how to implement the law continue to evolve. It is critical that school nurses stay involved so we can help ensure that all of our students with disabilities receive the education and related aids and services to which they are entitled. ■</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<comment>34 C.F.R. Part 104</comment>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Nondiscrimination on the basis of handicap in programs or activities receiving federal financial assistance</article-title>. <access-date>Retrieved May 9, 2011</access-date>, <comment>from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.ed.gov/policy/rights/reg/ocr/edlite-34cfr104.html">http://www2.ed.gov/policy/rights/reg/ocr/edlite-34cfr104.html</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zirkel</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Section 504 and public schools: A national survey concerning “Section 504-only” students</article-title>. <source>NASSP Bulletin</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<article-title>Incorporate “relaxed” ADA standards into eligibility framework</article-title>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Section 504 Compliance Advisor</source>,<volume>14</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Olathe District Schools</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Section 504 child find process for students with health concerns: Determining eligibility</source>. <publisher-loc>Olathe, KS</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Olathe District Schools</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<comment>RCW 28A.210.320</comment>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Children with life-threatening health conditions—Medication or treatment orders—Rules</source>. <access-date>Retrieved November 3, 2011</access-date>, <comment>from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.leg.wa.gov/rcw/default.aspx?cite=28A.210.320">http://apps.leg.wa.gov/rcw/default.aspx?cite=28A.210.320</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>A parent and educator guide to free appropriate public education</source>. <access-date>Retrieved August 15, 2010</access-date>, <comment>from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.k12.wa.us/HealthServices/pubdocs/504ManualFinal.pdf">http://www.k12.wa.us/HealthServices/pubdocs/504ManualFinal.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>S. 3406</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <source>Americans with disabilities act amendments act of 2008</source>. <access-date>Retrieved November 3, 2011</access-date>, <comment>from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://frwebgate.access.gpo.gov/cgibin/getdoc.cgi?dbname=110_cong_bills&amp;docid=f:s3406enr.txt.pdf">http://frwebgate.access.gpo.gov/cgibin/getdoc.cgi?dbname=110_cong_bills&amp;docid=f:s3406enr.txt.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>U.S. Department of Education, Office of Civil Rights</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Frequently asked questions about Section 504 and the education of children with disabilities</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.ed.gov/print/about/offices/list/ocr/504faq.html">http://www2.ed.gov/print/about/offices/list/ocr/504faq.html</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1942602X12437879">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zirkel</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>History and expansion of Section 504 student eligibility: Implications for school nurses</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Nursing</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>256</fpage>-<lpage>260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>