<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APY</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spapy</journal-id>
<journal-title>Australasian Psychiatry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1039-8562</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1440-1665</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1039856213479470b</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1039856213479470b</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>College Affairs</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>From the CEO</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>Andrew C.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>188</fpage>
<lpage>188</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="fig1-1039856213479470" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Andrew C. Peters</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1039856213479470b-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>It is fitting that in the College’s 50<sup>th</sup> anniversary year we will be staging an Asia-Pacific Forum at Congress. This initiative builds upon earlier work by the College and individual Fellows in developing relationships with international psychiatric colleges and associations. Recently the College also identified developing relationships with South-East Asia and South Pacific organisations as a key priority. This has been reinforced by the establishment of an International Affairs Working Group within the College.</p>
<p>A major milestone of this strategy will be achieved with the Asia-Pacific Mental Health Forum held as part of the 48<sup>th</sup> annual Congress in Sydney (26–30 May). The Forum brings together senior officers from psychiatric colleges and medical societies from more than 15 countries (India, Japan, Fiji, Myanmar, South Korea, Indonesia, Taiwan, Solomon Islands, Vietnam, China, Thailand, Cambodia, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Papua New Guinea, Vanuatu, Malaysia and Singapore) and invites them to share their views on the most urgent issues and priority areas in mental health, and for the profession of psychiatry, in their country.</p>
<p>In addition to the Asia-Pacific Mental Health Forum, another session at Congress will also focus on psychiatry in the Asia-Pacific region. Organised by the Faculty of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, this session will tackle the specific challenges facing child and adolescent psychiatry in countries such as Fiji, where 50% of the population is 21 years old or younger. Open to all Congress attendees, both forums will provide a unique opportunity to hear from our regional colleagues about the challenges they face.</p>
<p>Importantly, Congress offers the opportunity each year for members to enhance their sense of ‘fellowship’ with psychiatrists beyond their immediate colleagues. It is a positive reflection of the quality of the scientific program, as well as the ‘collegiality’, that attendance has been consistently high at each Congress, and that many members return every year. Congress is also an opportunity to promote a wider understanding of psychiatry; among the many non-psychiatrists who attend are medical students and consumers.</p>
<p>Each Congress relies upon the excellent support of Branch and organising committees. In recent years the College has continued to innovate, with the first Congress ever held in the Northern Territory in 2011, and a hugely successful international World Psychiatric Association conference in Melbourne in 2007. In particular, the success of the Darwin conference has raised the question of holding the Congress in partnership with other psychiatric colleges, or key organisations, in the Asia-Pacific region. Whilst Congress regularly travels to New Zealand, it has not been held outside Australia and New Zealand since 1989 (Honolulu). Prior to that, Congress was also held in Hong Kong (1981) and Singapore (1978). Perhaps as the College now engages further with our region we could consider staging a future conference in partnership with a neighbouring college or society.</p>
<p>As the College formally celebrates its 50<sup>th</sup> anniversary at Congress, and welcomes the new governance arrangements at the AGM on May 29, it would be fitting to have many members of the College in attendance, both to welcome in a new era, and to celebrate the successes of the last. If you only attend one College event I encourage you to join us in Sydney at Congress this year.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold>Andrew C. Peters</bold><break/>
<bold>Chief Executive Officer</bold></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>