<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spajh</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Hosp Palliat Care</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine®</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-9091</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2715</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049909111430224</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049909111430224</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Burnout and Connectedness in the Job Demands–Resources Model</article-title>
<subtitle>Studying Palliative Care Volunteers and Their Families</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>Jasmine-Yan</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>B.Psych(Hons)</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111430224">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1049909111430224"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Winefield</surname>
<given-names>Anthony H.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111430224">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xanthopoulou</surname>
<given-names>Despoina</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Metzer</surname>
<given-names>Jacques C.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111430224">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1049909111430224"><label>1</label> Centre for Applied Psychological Research, School of Psychology, University of South Australia, Australia</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1049909111430224"><label>2</label> Department of Psychology, University of Crete, Greece</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049909111430224">Jasmine-Yan Huynh, Centre for Applied Psychological Research, School of Psychology, Magill Campus, University of South Australia, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, SA 5001 Australia Email: <email>huyny003@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>462</fpage>
<lpage>475</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study examined the role of burnout and connectedness in the job demands–resources (JD-R) model among palliative care volunteers. It was hypothesized that (<italic>a</italic>) exhaustion mediates the relationship between demands and depression, and between demands and retention; (<italic>b</italic>) cynicism mediates the relationship between resources and retention; and (<italic>c)</italic> connectedness mediates the relationship between resources and retention. Hypotheses were tested in 2 separate analyses: structural equation modeling (SEM) and path analyses. The first was based on volunteer self-reports (N = 204), while the second analysis concerned matched data from volunteers and their family members (N = 99). While strong support was found for cynicism and connectedness as mediators in both types of analyses, this was not altogether the case for exhaustion. Implications of these findings for the JD-R model and volunteer organizations are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>burnout</kwd>
<kwd>job demands–resources model</kwd>
<kwd>connectedness</kwd>
<kwd>hospice palliative care</kwd>
<kwd>volunteers</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Hospice palliative care volunteers are people who provide practical, spiritual, social, and emotional support for dying clients, families, and their friends.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909111430224">1</xref>
</sup> They do this, out of their own freewill without any payment for their service. In an ageing population such as Australia, the demand for palliative care volunteers is likely to increase dramatically in the future.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</sup> According to the United Nations,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049909111430224">3</xref>
</sup> the number of older people (age 60 and over) worldwide is expected to increase from 606 million in 2000 to 1.9 billion in 2050. If there are enough volunteers to keep up with this demand, a significant contribution to the economy can be achieved. In the United Kingdom alone, the increase in volunteer numbers from 90 000 in 2003<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049909111430224">4</xref></sup> to over 100 000 in recent years<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049909111430224">5</xref>
</sup> is encouraging, but it is still questionable whether this number can be sustained or increased to meet future demands. For example, Amenta<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049909111430224">6</xref>
</sup> estimated that the total number of hospice volunteers in the United States dropped by 43% between 4 and 11 months after undertaking their volunteer role. Similar turnover rates have been reported in other volunteer studies.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049909111430224">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049909111430224">8</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Thus, it is worthwhile investing in ongoing research on volunteer health and well-being in order to promote recruitment and retention, particularly in countries such as Australia where there is a shortage of palliative care volunteers. This is an important issue not only for the health care system but also to the volunteer managers and/or coordinators who invest a lot of time, energy, and money into recruiting and training their volunteers.</p>
<p>Recently, the job demands–resources (JD-R) model<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref>
</sup> has been applied to the area of volunteer work. The JD-R model is a well-established theoretical model that provides a comprehensive assessment on how employees’ working conditions may affect their health and well-being at work. Although the model has only been well documented in the paid work literature, there is increasing evidence<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909111430224">10</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049909111430224"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111430224">12</xref>
</sup> that the model is valid to the area of volunteer work. The JD-R model is an appropriate model as it enables researchers and practitioners to examine simultaneously both negative (stress and burnout) and positive (motivation and retention) aspects of volunteer well-being. In addition, different types of demands and resources which are specific to the occupational context under study (ie, volunteers) can be examined. Moreover, recent studies<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111430224">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049909111430224">13</xref></sup>suggest that different mediators may explain the underlying psychological processes proposed by the JD-R model depending on its relevance to the type of context under study.</p>
<p>In the current study, we use the JD-R model<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref>
</sup> to examine the mediating role of exhaustion on the relationship between volunteer demands on one hand, and depression and (low) retention on the other hand. Furthermore, this study examines the mediating role of cynicism and connectedness on the relationship between volunteer resources and retention. To extend previous volunteer studies on the JD-R model, we also examine 2 new types of work characteristics that are crucial for volunteers: “conflict with paid staff” (as a volunteer demand) and “family support” (as a volunteer resource).</p>
<sec id="section1-1049909111430224">
<title>Burnout and Its Consequences</title>
<p>Although vital for the welfare community and economy, the work of hospice palliative care volunteers (being able to deal or cope with patient death rather than cure) can be difficult, challenging, and demanding.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049909111430224">14</xref>
</sup> The nature of such work is considered to be potentially stressful and has been linked to poor psychological health such as burnout.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049909111430224">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049909111430224">15</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049909111430224"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049909111430224">17</xref></sup>Like paid workers, volunteers can also be prone to burnout.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049909111430224">18</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>A popular definition of “burnout” comes from Maslach, Jackson, and Leiter<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049909111430224">19</xref></sup>who define the term as a syndrome of emotional exhaustion, cynicism (or depersonalization), and reduced personal accomplishment (or professional efficacy) which usually occurs among employees who do “people work.” <italic>Emotional exhaustion</italic> refers to the depletion or draining of mental resources and is characterized by physical, emotional, and mental tiredness. <italic>Cynicism</italic> involves having a negative, cynical attitudes, and feelings about one’s job and/or clients. Finally, lack of <italic>personal accomplishment</italic> is the tendency to evaluate one’s work negatively in which there are feelings of insufficiency and poor self-esteem.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049909111430224">20</xref>
</sup> There is accumulating evidence suggesting that emotional exhaustion and cynicism constitute the core dimensions of burnout.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049909111430224">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049909111430224">22</xref>
</sup> Thus, these two dimensions will be the focus of the present study.</p>
<p>Previous studies have shown that burnout has negative consequences for both the individual and the volunteer organization. In the present study, we focus on depression and turnover intentions as outcomes of the dimensions of burnout. These two outcomes were chosen as they have been found to be related to burnout in previous volunteer research<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909111430224">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049909111430224">23</xref>
</sup> and is currently an issue among volunteers in the palliative care context.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049909111430224">24</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1049909111430224">
<title>Connectedness and Its Consequences</title>
<p>Connectedness is a work-motivational construct that may be defined “as a positive emotional sense of wellbeing that results from an individual’s strong sense of belonging with other workers and the recipients of one’s service. It may manifest itself as a human striving for interpersonal attachments, as well as the need to be connected with one’s work and to the values of an organization.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049909111430224">25</xref>(p6)</sup> This definition consists of 4 interrelated components. The first component, <italic>other workers</italic>, refers to having a sense of belonging with one’s work group and is characterized by positive feelings of appreciation and respect. The second component, <italic>recipients</italic>, refers to a sense of being part of a relationship with one’s client (in this study, dying patients and/or their families) in which there are feelings of compassion and obligation to help those in need. The third component, <italic>task</italic> <italic>requirement</italic>, refers to a sense of connection with the required or assigned task and is characterized by feelings of enjoyment and competency in performing the work well. Finally, the fourth component, <italic>values</italic>, refers to an individual’s identification with the aims and goals of the organization whereby volunteers feel that they are being valued, appreciated, recognized and treated fairly.</p>
<p>Following from this conceptualization, the notion of belongingness can be seen as an important feature of connectedness.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049909111430224">26</xref>
</sup> The concept of connectedness is closely tied to the belongingness hypothesis outlined by Baumeister and Leary<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049909111430224">27</xref>
</sup> which includes an individual’s desire for close and intimate relationships as a fundamental human motivation. Therefore, if we apply this concept in the work context, specifically volunteer work in palliative care, it refers to volunteers’ interpersonal relationships with their work group which includes co-volunteers, palliative care staff, and clients of their help (dying patient and their families).</p>
<p>Previous studies have shown that connectedness has important implications for volunteer organizations. Not only is connectedness a positive experience in itself, but it is also related to positive outcomes and commitment to the organization. For example, Baumeister and Leary<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049909111430224">27</xref>
</sup> reported a close linkage between the need to belong and positive emotions such that the more connected an individual feels, the more likely he or she would feel happy. Moreover, Gabard<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049909111430224">28</xref>
</sup> discovered that volunteers who felt that they were not being appreciated or did not feel connected to the work group were more likely to terminate their service.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049909111430224">
<title>The JD-R Model</title>
<p>The JD-R model begins with the assumption that in any type of job (including volunteer work), the characteristics of the psychosocial work environment can be categorized into 2 broad groups: job demands and job resources.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049909111430224">29</xref>
</sup> Job demands are characteristics of the job that require sustained physical and/or psychological effort and are associated with physiological and/or psychological costs such as exhaustion. Job resources are characteristics of the job that (1) help to reduce job demands; (2) aid in achieving work goals; and (3) stimulate personal growth, learning, and development.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049909111430224">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049909111430224">30</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>A second assumption of the JD-R model is that job demands and job resources may evoke 2 relatively independent psychological processes: the <italic>health impairment</italic>process and the <italic>motivational</italic>process. These processes are each associated with a different component of burnout. While exhaustion is better explained by the former process, cynicism is explained by the latter process.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref></sup>This latter process may also be used to explain work engagement and retention.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049909111430224">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1049909111430224">31</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The health impairment process explains the development of job strain and occurs where high job demands exhaust workers’ mental and physical resources which leads to emotional exhaustion (severe fatigue) and in turn, to poor health (eg, depression) and negative organizational outcomes (eg, low retention)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref>
</sup>. Several studies have shown that specific job demands such as emotional demands and work–home conflict are strong predictors of emotional exhaustion.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049909111430224">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049909111430224">32</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049909111430224"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1049909111430224"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049909111430224"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049909111430224">36</xref>
</sup> Other studies have also found a direct link between emotional exhaustion on one hand, and depression<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049909111430224">37</xref>
</sup> and low retention<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1049909111430224">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049909111430224">39</xref>
</sup> on the other hand. Although limited, there is recent empirical support for the role of emotional exhaustion as a mediator between job demands and negative outcomes in volunteers. Lewig et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111430224">12</xref>
</sup> found in a large sample of volunteer ambulance officers that burnout mediated the relationship between job demands and health problems, and between job demands and low retention. Similarly, Cox et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909111430224">10</xref>
</sup> who studied AIDS volunteers found that exposure to high levels of job demands such as role conflict, resulted in emotional exhaustion and consequently depression. More recently, research by Huynh<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup> among different groups of emergency service volunteers showed that emotional exhaustion also explained the relationship between volunteer demands and intentions to leave the volunteer organization.</p>
<p>In the current study, we focus on 3 specific types of volunteer demands. Given that palliative care volunteers provide emotional support for the terminally ill, the most relevant and significant type of job demand is emotional demands (having to deal with emotionally demanding interactions or situations). In addition, work–home conflict is another important job demand since the stress experienced at volunteer work can interfere with one’s social and family life.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049909111430224">35</xref>
</sup> These 2 types of job demands are not limited to volunteers as they have also been extensively studied among paid workers.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049909111430224">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049909111430224">41</xref>
</sup> In order to expand the above findings, we also introduce “conflict with paid staff” as a third type of job demand that is relevant to the volunteer context. Previous qualitative studies (Hoad<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1049909111430224">42</xref>
</sup>) found that conflict with paid staff is a significant demand for volunteers, and Huynh's<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1049909111430224">53</xref></sup>study revealed that such demands may lead to resignation among volunteer members. Exploring other types of job demands will expand our current knowledge on the antecedents of volunteers’ emotional exhaustion.</p>
<p>The motivational process is the second process proposed by the JD-R model.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref>
</sup> It occurs where a lack or absence of job resources interferes with a worker’s ability to deal effectively with high job demands, thereby preventing them from achieving their work goals. This in turn leads to decreased motivation and disengagement or cynicism.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049909111430224">43</xref>
</sup> On the positive side, the presence of high job resources provides the means to achieve work-related goals and as such it stimulates personal growth and development.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049909111430224">29</xref>
</sup> This in turn may enhance feelings of connectedness and consequently motivation to continue with the organization.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111430224">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In the current study, we will focus on 4 main types of job resources. Supervisor support is one of the best known types of job resource. For palliative care volunteers, the first point of contact when something goes wrong at volunteer work is usually the volunteer coordinator and/or manager. Consider the scenario where the volunteer coordinator “mistakenly” matches a volunteer with the wrong client or the volunteer feels inadequately trained for their role. When problems arise, the volunteer may turn to their supervisor for help (eg, asking to be assigned to a different client or to receive more training in particular areas) but then, no action is undertaken to address this issue. Such action may be interpreted as “my supervisor simply does not care about me.” In these instances, it is very likely that the volunteer will feel cynical about their job. However, if the supervisor takes interest and fulfills the volunteer’s wishes (eg, matching them with the “right” client), it is likely that the volunteer will feel connected to the work group. Thus, the supervisor is considered to be a central “resource” in facilitating volunteers’ feelings of connectedness.</p>
<p>Other volunteer resources such as training and volunteer organizational support are also relevant to volunteer work. Given the sensitive nature of palliative care work, training is absolutely necessary to equip volunteers with the skills required to perform the work well.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049909111430224">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1049909111430224">45</xref>
</sup> Some volunteer studies<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1049909111430224">46</xref>
</sup> have also suggested that training can be used as a retention tool. Volunteer organizational support<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1049909111430224">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1049909111430224">48</xref>
</sup> which includes such things as reimbursement for out-of-pocket expenses can also enhance feelings of connectedness since volunteers would have the financial resources (travel, phone, and petrol expenses) to help their clients (eg, provide practical support to their clients by driving them to the hospital—transportation). Social exchange theory<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1049909111430224">49</xref></sup>may be able to explain this relationship such that when volunteer organizations are able to provide these resources, volunteers are willing to give more and thus build a stronger connection with their clients.</p>
<p>In addition to the above resources, we also included family support as a type of volunteer resource. The link between friends/family support and positive outcomes such as volunteer satisfaction, connectedness, and intentions to continue volunteering has been documented in the literature.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1049909111430224">50</xref>
</sup> It is worthwhile noting that the JD-R model does not consider other aspects outside of the work environment that may be important determinants of health-related and motivational outcomes. Given that family support is a form of social support which is based on relationships and positive interactions with others,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049909111430224">27</xref>
</sup> it is relevant to the connectedness theory. Thus, the present study attempted to expand the JD-R model by examining whether contextual resources outside of the workplace, such as receiving support from friends and family, can also help decrease cynicism, increase connectedness, and relate to retention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1049909111430224">
<title>The Present Study</title>
<p>Based on the main assumptions of the JD-R model and the analysis above, we formulate the following hypotheses (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1049909111430224">Figure 1</xref>). Emotional exhaustion mediates the positive relationship between volunteer demands (emotional demands, work–home conflict, conflict with paid staff) and depression (<italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>), and the negative relationship between volunteer demands and retention (<italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>). Cynicism mediates the positive relationship between volunteer resources (supervisor, family and organizational support, and training opportunities) and retention (<italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>). Finally, connectedness mediates the positive relationship between volunteer resources and retention (<italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1049909111430224" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The hypothesized JD-R model as applied to volunteers. JD-R indicates job demands–resources; CWP, conflict with paid staff; WHC, work-home conflict; VOS, volunteer organizational support.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049909111430224-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In the present study, we will first test the hypothesized relationships in a sample of palliative care volunteers. An additional aim of the present study is to validate our findings by going beyond single-source self-reports of job characteristics. Specifically, we will present additional analyses where observer (family) ratings of volunteer demands and resources will be matched to volunteer ratings of burnout, connectedness, depression, and retention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1049909111430224" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section6-1049909111430224">
<title>Participants and Procedure</title>
<p>The volunteer manager and/or coordinator from 18 different volunteer palliative care organizations in Australia were approached and informed about the study by the first author. After their consent, information sheets and questionnaires were sent out to the volunteers. Participants were given the option of either completing the questionnaire online or hard copy. Where possible, a reminder was sent to volunteers 2 to 3 weeks of receiving the survey. To encourage participation, participants were also given the chance to win a gift voucher.</p>
<p>As mentioned previously, a special feature of the study is that instead of measuring only self-reported demands and resources, we also collected data from family members regarding the volunteer’s work experience on these different aspects. Specifically, each volunteer was asked to pass the spouse/family member survey to just one of their family members whom they thought could comment on their volunteer work experience. Such information may substantiate or provide a certain degree of confidence (ie, external validity) in the observed relationships among the study variables. In this study, family members included the following people: spouse, sibling, adult children, relative, parent, and/or close friend. This choice was made based on the fact the not all volunteers had spouses.</p>
<p>Of the 633 questionnaires distributed, 211 were returned, yielding an initial response rate of 32%. From these, 7 were excluded due to large amounts of missing data. Therefore, only 204 survey responses were used in the present study (31% final response rate). This response rate is similar to previous research on volunteers.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049909111430224">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049909111430224">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1049909111430224">51</xref>
</sup> Their two main tasks included (1) providing emotional and social support to patients and families (eg, listening, talking, preparing biographies), and (2) providing practical support to patients such as helping them with their daily functioning (eg, eating, washing, transportation). Participants were predominantly females (N = 159, 77.9%), and their mean age was 63 years (SD = 10.78). Six participants did not disclose their gender. Participants had volunteered for an average of 6.52 years (SD = 6.61) in their volunteer organization, and their mean length of service within the volunteer workforce was 13.42 years (SD = 12.50). In their current organization, volunteers contributed an average of 4.48 hours of work per week (SD = 2.33). The majority of participants were married (62.7%) and retired (68.1%). Only a small percentage had paid employment: full-time (3%), part-time (14.1%), and casual (11.1%). Most participants had completed high school education (31.9%) or TAFE/Equivalent (32.4%). In Australia, TAFE stands for “Technical and Further Education” and includes qualifications such as graduate certificates and graduate diplomas. Unlike university education, courses undertaken at TAFE are more hands-on and practical oriented.</p>
<p>Out of the 204 volunteers who participated in the present study, only 99 surveys could be matched with their family members. Other volunteers indicated that they did not have a family member who could comment on their volunteer work experience. Seventy-eight percent of these volunteers were female and 63.4 years old on average (SD = 10.07). Sixty-one percent of family members were male and 61.5 years old on average (SD = 13.96). Although most family members were not involved in palliative care volunteering (<italic>n</italic> = 91, 91.9%), they were happy for their spouse/family member to continue work as a palliative care volunteer (n = 96, 97%). Family members included the following people: spouse (n = 70, 70.7%), close friend (n = 9, 9.1%), sibling (n = 2, 2%), mother (n = 3, 3%), adult children (n = 11, 11.1%), relative (n = 1, 1%), and de facto partner (n = 1, 1%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049909111430224">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section8-1049909111430224">
<title>Volunteer demands</title>
<p>The 3 volunteer demands included in this research were <italic>emotional demands</italic> (measured with 6 items: eg, “I have to deal with people who have unrealistic expectations”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1049909111430224">52</xref>
</sup>), <italic>conflict with paid staff</italic> was measured with 3 items that were developed on the basis of previous qualitative data on volunteers (eg, “I find it difficult to communicate with paid staff”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1049909111430224">53</xref>
</sup>), and <italic>work–home conflict</italic> (4 items: eg “The demands of volunteer work interfere with my family/home/social life”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1049909111430224">54</xref>
</sup>). The response options for all the demands subscales were ranging from 1 (<italic>strongly disagree</italic>) to 5 (<italic>strongly agree</italic>), with high scores indicating higher volunteer demands.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1049909111430224">
<title>Volunteer resources</title>
<p>The 4 volunteer resources included in the study were s<italic>upervisor/coordinator support</italic> (4 items: eg, “My supervisor/coordinator is concerned about my welfare”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1049909111430224">55</xref>
</sup>), <italic>volunteer training</italic> (5 items: eg, “The workshops and seminars, eg, monthly support groups; available to me through this organization help improve my palliative caring skills”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1049909111430224">56</xref>
</sup>), volunteer<italic> organizational support</italic> (5 items: eg, “The organization provides adequate reimbursement for my out-of-pocket expenses”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup>), and <italic>family support</italic> (4 items; eg, “My friends/family care about how I feel about my volunteer work”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1049909111430224">57</xref>
</sup>). The same response options as for the demands subscales were used.</p>
<p>
<italic>Volunteer demands and resources</italic>were further assessed by a family member who completed a short questionnaire which included the same demands and resources. However, each demand and resource was measured with a single item. For example, we asked family members to “rate how often this person has to deal with the following demands in their role as a volunteer: (1) emotional demands, (2) conflict with paid staff, and (3) volunteering work interfering with home life” and “the extent to which this person has enough of the following support and/or resources to perform effectively in their role as a palliative care volunteer: (1) support from supervisors, (2) organizational support (eg, reimbursement for out-of-pocket expenses), (3) support from family/friends and (4) training (eg, workshops/seminars) is provided to prepare them well for their volunteer position.” Family members rated the following demands and resources on a scale ranging from (1) = <italic>never</italic> to (5) = <italic>always</italic>.</p>
<p>
<italic>The Burnout</italic> dimensions were measured using the Maslach Burnout Inventory–General Survey (MBI-GS<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1049909111430224">58</xref>
</sup>). <italic>Exhaustion</italic> was measured with the respective 5-item scale with examples like “I feel emotionally drained from my (volunteer) work”; while <italic>Cynicism</italic> was measured with 4 items such as “I doubt the significance of my (volunteer) work.” Volunteers rated their answers in a scale ranging from 0 = <italic>never</italic> to 6 = <italic>everyday</italic>.</p>
<p>
<italic>Connectedness</italic> was measured using the 15-item 4-dimensional connectedness scale.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049909111430224">26</xref>
</sup> Example items include “I am appreciated by the people I work with” (other workers, 4 items), “I enjoy doing the volunteer work that I do” (task requirement, 3 items), “The volunteer organization appreciates my effort” (values, 4 items), and “I feel close to the people I am helping” (recipients, 4 items). All items are rated on a 7-point Likert-type scale ranging from 1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic> to 7 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>. High scores are indicative of high connectedness. The scale has demonstrated good reliability and validity in several research studies. For example, Huynh et al’s<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049909111430224">26</xref></sup>study examined the psychometric properties of the scale in 2 independent volunteer samples, that is volunteer ambulance workers (N = 236) and state emergency service volunteers (N = 227). They found that the scale reliabilities ranged from .88 to .90 and shared a low-to-medium correlations with other job-related variables such as organizational commitment (<italic>r</italic> = .12, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), work engagement (<italic>r</italic> = .42, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and volunteer satisfaction (<italic>r</italic> = .56, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Furthermore, confirmatory factor analyses of the scale showed that the 4-factor structure of connectedness was stable across the volunteer groups and was better than alternative 3-factor, 2-factor, and 1-factor models.</p>
<p>
<italic>Depression</italic> was measured using a 7-item scale taken from the depression anxiety stress scale.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1049909111430224">59</xref>
</sup> An example item is “I felt I wasn’t worth much as a person.” Participants were asked how much they felt this way over the past week. All items were rated on a 4-point scale ranging from (0) = <italic>did not apply to me at all</italic> to (3) = <italic>applied to me very much, or most of the time</italic>. High scores indicate depression or poor psychological health.</p>
<p>
<italic>Retention</italic> was measured using a 4-item scale by Huynh et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup> Negatively worded items (“I intend to change volunteer jobs soon” and “I often think about quitting my volunteer job”) were reversed scored so that all high scores reflect greater intent to remain in the organization. Response options ranged from 1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic> to 5 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1049909111430224">
<title>Data Analyses</title>
<p>With regard to the single-source analyses, we tested the mediation hypotheses using structural equation modeling (SEM) methods as implemented by AMOS 16.0.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1049909111430224">59</xref>
</sup> The covariance matrix was analyzed using the maximum-likelihood method. The research model, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1049909111430224">Figure 1</xref>, included 3 indicators of the latent volunteer demands variable (emotional demands, conflict with paid staff, work–home conflict), and 4 indicators of the latent volunteer resources variable (supervisor support, family support, organizational support, and volunteer training). In addition, there were 4 indicators of the latent connectedness variable (other workers, recipients, task, and values). Similar to previous studies,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049909111430224">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1049909111430224">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1049909111430224">61</xref>
</sup> single indicators were used for all other latent-mediating variables (exhaustion and cynicism) and latent outcome variables (depression and retention) to ensure a parsimonious model. For single-indicator variables, random measurement errors were corrected by setting the random error variances associated with each variable equal to the product of its variance and the quantity 1 minus its internal consistency.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1049909111430224">62</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Given the relatively small sample size in the multisource model (N = 99), we performed path analyses instead of SEM by using manifest variables for all constructs.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1049909111430224">62</xref>
</sup> The weighted factor scores of “other-rated” volunteer demands and resources, and “self-rated” connectedness were used as manifest variables given their multidimensional nature. The scores were calculated by conducting second-order principal axis factoring (PAF) analysis with Varimax rotation on the 3 volunteer demands, the 4 volunteer resources, and the 4 connectedness dimensions separately. The advantage of such scores is that the weight of each item used to create the factor score is taken into account when computing the total score (see Xanthopoulou et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1049909111430224">63</xref>
</sup>). Principal axis factoring analyses resulted in 1 volunteer demands factor (26% of explained variance), 1 volunteer resources factor (48% of explained variance), and 1 connectedness factor (56% of explained variance). Thus, the manifest “volunteer demands” variable represented the factor score of the 3 volunteer demands scales, the manifest “volunteer resources” variable represented the factor score of the 4 volunteer resources scales, and the manifest “connectedness” variable represented the factor score of the 4 connectedness subscales. For all other manifest unidimensional variables in the model, the raw scores were used.</p>
<p>In addition to the chi-square (χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</sup>) statistics, the following fit indices were used to assess the fit of the various nested models to the data: the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) and the Goodness-of-Fit Index (GFI). Three other fit indices were also chosen as they are considered to be less sensitive to sample size: the Incremental Fit Index (IFI); the Comparative Fit Index (CFI); and Non-Normed Fit Index (NNFI)—also known as the Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI). Generally, models with fit indices &gt;.90<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1049909111430224">64</xref>
</sup> and RMSEA &lt;.08 indicate an acceptable fit.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1049909111430224">65</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1049909111430224">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section12-1049909111430224">
<title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
<p>The means, standard deviations, and correlations of the study variables for the total volunteer sample are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1049909111430224">Table 1</xref>. With the exception of the correlation between family support and emotional demands, and social support and depression, all correlations were significant and in the expected direction. Furthermore, all scales exhibited acceptable reliabilities with Cronbach αs approaching or exceeding .70.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1049909111430224" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Means, Standard Deviations, Intercorrelations and Reliabilities of the Study Variables—Total Volunteer Sample (N = 204)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1049909111430224" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909111430224-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>M</th>
<th>SD</th>
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
<th>11</th>
<th>12</th>
<th>13</th>
<th>14</th>
<th>15</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 1. Emotional demands</td>
<td>2.41</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>(.69)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2. Conflict with paid staff</td>
<td>1.73</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.46<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.80)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3. Work–home conflict</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>.29<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.38<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.80)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 4. Supervisor support</td>
<td>4.50</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td>−.19<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.34<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.28<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.92)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 5. Organizational support</td>
<td>4.20</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>−.16<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.25<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.62<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.86)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 6. Training</td>
<td>4.16</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>−.18<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.35<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.37<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.66<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.72<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.87)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 7. Family support</td>
<td>4.06</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>−.16<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.23<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.28<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.36<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.39<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.85)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 8. Exhaustion</td>
<td>.91</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.45<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.34<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.40<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.30<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.40<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.82)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 9. Cynicism</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>.81</td>
<td>.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.37<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.30<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.34<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.40<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.23<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.67<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.88)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10. Other workers</td>
<td>6.24</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>−.27<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.45<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.47<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.45<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.56<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.28<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.38<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.91)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11. Task</td>
<td>6.26</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>−.13<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.17<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.42<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.33<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.43<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.24<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.34<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.58<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.76)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12. Values</td>
<td>6.21</td>
<td>.73</td>
<td>−.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.36<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.29<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.50<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.54<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.56<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.27<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.35<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.60<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.46<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.95)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13. Recipients</td>
<td>6.15</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>−.12<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.18<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.18<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.20<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.16<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.24<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.14<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.28<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.24<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.74)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14. Depression</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.30<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.20<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.17<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>−.15<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.19<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.33<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.19<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.34<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>(.78)</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15. Retention</td>
<td>4.15</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>−.23<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.38<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.46<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.43<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.18<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.44<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.56<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.30<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.17<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.43<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.25<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.12<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.68)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1049909111430224">
<p> <sup>a</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1049909111430224">
<p> <sup>b</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1049909111430224">
<p> <sup>c</sup>
<italic>P</italic>&lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The descriptive statistics for the matched sample are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1049909111430224">Table 2</xref>. Consistent with <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1049909111430224">Table 1</xref>, volunteer resources were positively related to connectedness and retention and negatively related to cynicism, whereas volunteer demands were positively related to exhaustion. However, while self-ratings of volunteer demands were also positively related to depression and negatively related to retention, this was not the case for family ratings of volunteer demands on self-reported outcomes. The majority of the scales showed good reliabilities with Cronbach αs greater than .70. However, the extremely low reliability for job demands raises strong doubts about the reliability of the family member ratings of job demands. It is noteworthy that other ratings of job demands and resources correlated significantly with self-ratings of job demands (<italic>r</italic> = .23, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) and resources (<italic>r</italic> = .47, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), respectively. These results suggest that there is some degree of inter-rater agreement among the measures used.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1049909111430224" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Means, Standard Deviations, Intercorrelations, and Reliabilities of the Study Variables—Matched Data (Self-Ratings and Other Ratings, n = 99)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1049909111430224" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909111430224-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>M</th>
<th>SD</th>
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 1. Volunteer demands (F)</td>
<td>1.96</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>(.46)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2. Volunteer resources (F)</td>
<td>4.17</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>(.78)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3. Exhaustion</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.19<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.17<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.79)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 4. Cynicism</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>.55<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.86)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 5. Other workers</td>
<td>6.26</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>−.21<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.33<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.36<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.90)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 6. Task</td>
<td>6.31</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>−.25<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.37<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.56<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.73)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 7. Values</td>
<td>6.32</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>.33<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.40<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.58<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.39<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.93)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 8. Recipients</td>
<td>6.15</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.19<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.33<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.23<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.30<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.25<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.72)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 9. Depression</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>−.21<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.43<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.39<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.21<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.13</td>
<td>−.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.19<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.78)</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10. Retention</td>
<td>4.18</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.34<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.39<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.50<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.32<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1049909111430224">c</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.52<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>.35<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1049909111430224">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>−.22<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1049909111430224">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>(.63)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1049909111430224">
<p>Abbreviation: F = Family member ratings.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1049909111430224">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-1049909111430224">
<p>
<sup>b</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1049909111430224">
<p>
<sup>c</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1049909111430224">
<title>Test of the JD-R Model</title>
<p>To test the 4 mediation hypotheses, we followed the 4-step approach outlined by Baron and Kenny.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1049909111430224">66</xref>
</sup> First, the predictor should be significantly related to the outcome. Second, the predictor must be significantly related to the mediator. Third, the mediator should be significantly related to the dependent variable. Finally, mediation is evident when the relationship between the predictor and the outcome becomes significantly weaker (partial mediation) or nonsignificant (full mediation). The significance of the mediating effects was also tested using the Sobel <italic>z</italic> test.</p>
<sec id="section14-1049909111430224">
<title>Self-reports</title>
<p>The study hypotheses were first tested using self-reports from the total volunteer sample (N = 204). In line with the first 2 prerequisites, preliminary analyses revealed that volunteer demands were significantly related to depression (γ = .39, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), retention (γ = −.63, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), and exhaustion (γ = .79, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), while volunteer resources were significantly related to retention (γ = .66, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), cynicism (<italic>γ</italic>= −.47, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and connectedness (γ = .80, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Next, exhaustion was significantly related to depression (γ = .36, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and retention (γ = −.58, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Finally, cynicism was negatively related to retention (γ = −.68, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and connectedness was positively related to retention (γ = .59, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). These results satisfy the prerequisite conditions for the mediation hypotheses.</p>
<p>To test Hypotheses 1 to 4, we compared the full mediation model (M1; volunteer demands à emotional exhaustion à depression/retention and volunteer resources à cynicism/connectedness à retention) with the partial mediation model (M2; similar to the full mediation model with additional paths from volunteer demands to depression and retention; and from volunteer resources to retention). According to Holmbeck,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1049909111430224">67</xref>
</sup> full mediation is demonstrated when the inclusion of the direct paths in the model does not significantly improve the fit of the model, and the inclusion of the mediator renders the previously significant direct effects nonsignificant. If the previously significant direct effects (after the inclusion of the mediator) are reduced but remain significant then partial mediation is demonstrated.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1049909111430224">68</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The results of SEM analyses showed that both the full mediation model (M1; χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</sup> = 163.05, <italic>df</italic> = 83, GFI = .91, RMSEA = .07, IFI = .93, CFI = .93, TLI = .91) and the partial mediation model (M2; χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</sup> = 159.26, <italic>df</italic> = 80, GFI = .91, RMSEA = .07, IFI = .93, CFI = .93, TLI = .91) fit well to the data. Further, the results of chi-square test showed that these additional paths in M2 did not significantly improve the fit of the model to the data (Δχ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</sup> (3) = 3.78, <italic>P</italic> &gt; .05, ns), which supports the full mediation hypotheses. Inspection of the parameter estimates of M2 showed that the magnitude of the direct paths was reduced and became nonsignificant. Specifically, the paths from volunteer demands to depression (γ = .09, <italic>P</italic> = .433) and retention (γ = −.12, <italic>P</italic> = .708) and from volunteer resources to retention (γ = .28, <italic>p</italic> = .152) were all nonsignificant in M2. Thus, full mediation was demonstrated. The standardized path coefficients of the final SEM model (M1) for the total volunteer sample are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1049909111430224">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1049909111430224" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of SEM analyses (standardized path coefficients) of the full JD-R model for the total volunteer sample (self-reports, N = 204). SEM, structural equation modeling; JD-R, job demands–resources; CWP, conflict with paid staff; WHC, work–home conflict; VOS, volunteer organizational support. The covariances between the error terms of the mediators have been left out for clarity. All path coefficients were significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001 except for the path from emotional exhaustion to retention which was at <italic>P</italic> = .243.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049909111430224-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The results of the SEM analyses in combination with the Sobel test suggested that (<italic>a</italic>) exhaustion fully mediated the relationship between volunteer demands and depression (<italic>z</italic> = 3.82, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) but not between volunteer demands and low retention (<italic>z</italic> = −1.15, <italic>P</italic> = .250, ns); (<italic>b</italic>) cynicism mediated the relationship between volunteer resources and retention (<italic>z</italic> = 3.18, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01); and finally (<italic>c</italic>) connectedness mediated the relationship between volunteer resources and retention (<italic>z</italic> = 4.19, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Thus, these findings provide support for Hypotheses 1, 3, and 4 by showing that volunteer demands leads to depression through their effect on emotional exhaustion and that volunteer resources foster retention through their effect on cynicism and connectedness. However, Hypothesis 2 was not supported, indicating that emotional exhaustion did not explain the relationship between volunteer demands and low retention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1049909111430224">
<title>Self-ratings and other ratings</title>
<p>In a new series of analyses, hypotheses were tested using matched data (N = 99) from the family member ratings of volunteer demands and resources, and self-ratings of burnout, connectedness, depression, and retention. Preliminary analyses revealed that while volunteer resources were positively related to retention (γ = .33, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), cynicism (γ = −.28, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), and connectedness (γ = .36, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), volunteer demands were not related to emotional exhaustion (γ = .19, <italic>P</italic> = .055), depression (γ = .14, <italic>P</italic> = .174), and retention (γ = .03, <italic>P</italic> = .804). This latter finding is not surprising if one considers the low reliability of the family member ratings of job demands. Therefore, these results reject Hypotheses 1 and 2. On this basis, we focus only on the motivational pathway of the JD-R model in the multisource model. Next, as expected volunteer resources were negatively related to cynicism (γ = −.28, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) and positively related to connectedness (γ = .36, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Finally, cynicism was negatively related to retention (γ = −.34, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and connectedness was positively related to retention (γ = .34, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). These results satisfy the prerequisite conditions for the mediation Hypotheses 3 and 4.</p>
<p>To test Hypotheses 3 and 4, we compared the full mediation model (M3; volunteer resources à cynicism/connectedness à retention) with the partial mediation model (M4; similar to the full mediation model with an additional path from volunteer resources to retention). M3 showed a good fit to the data (<italic>χ</italic>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111430224">2</xref>
</sup> = 2.12, <italic>df</italic> = 1, GFI = .99, RMSEA = .11, IFI = .99, CFI = .99, TLI = .91). M4 is a fully saturated model because every variable has a direct connection to every other variable which makes the model fit perfectly to the data. As such, it has a chi-square of 0 and perfect fit (with RMSEA = 0 and all other fit indexes equal to 1). On this basis, it does not make sense to discuss its fit or proceed with model comparisons (via a chi-square difference test). The sensible step would be to test the significance of the mediating effect with Sobel test.</p>
<p>The results of the Sobel test suggest that (<italic>a</italic>) cynicism mediated the relationship between volunteer resources and retention (<italic>z</italic> = 2.27, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05); and (<italic>b</italic>) connectedness mediated the relationship between volunteer resources and retention (<italic>z</italic> = 2.63, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Considering that the direct path from volunteer resources to retention (γ = .13, <italic>p</italic> = .143) became nonsignificant in M4, after the inclusion of the mediators, these findings suggest that cynicism and connectedness fully mediated the relationship between volunteer resources and retention. Thus, results support Hypotheses 3 and 4. The standardized path coefficients of the final full mediation path model (M3) for the multisource sample are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1049909111430224">Figure 3</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1049909111430224" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of path analyses (standardized path coefficients) of the motivational pathway of the JD-R model for the matched data (self-reports and other-ratings, <italic>n</italic>= 99). JD-R indicates job demands–resources. * <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05; ** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; *** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049909111430224-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1049909111430224">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study used the JD-R model as the theoretical framework to examine how volunteer demands and resources influence palliative care volunteers’ psychological health and retention, through their relationship with burnout (exhaustion and cynicism) and connectedness. While there was strong support for the motivational process of the JD-R model, there was only partial support for the health impairment process.</p>
<sec id="section17-1049909111430224">
<title>Theoretical Implications</title>
<p>In line with the health impairment process, emotional exhaustion mediated the relationship between volunteer demands and depression<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909111430224">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1049909111430224">69</xref>
</sup> but not between volunteer demands and low retention. These results indicate that when volunteers experience high levels of emotional demands (ie, unable to control and suppress their emotions to perform effectively), work–home conflict (ie, when volunteering work creates too much tension with their home life), and (unique to this study) conflict with paid staff (ie, in terms of lack of trust and mutual respect), it is likely that they will feel overly exhausted about their volunteer work and this, in turn, could affect their health and well-being (ie, make them feel depressed). However, the present study suggests that feeling overly exhausted does not necessarily lead to turnover among volunteers. These results are in line with Ross et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049909111430224">23</xref>
</sup> who studied burnout among AIDS volunteers. It is possible that volunteers remain with the organization despite feeling emotionally exhausted.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1049909111430224">70</xref>
</sup> Volunteers who choose to work with people who are dying (ie, palliative care) would know that such work can be emotionally exhausting and thus, it is unlikely that this is something that would determine their intentions of leaving the organization.</p>
<p>In line with the motivational process of the JD-R, cynicism and connectedness played a significant mediating role between volunteer resources and retention. A unique contribution of this study is that the results were confirmed using other ratings of volunteer resources. These findings support and expand on the findings of Ross et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049909111430224">23</xref>
</sup> who found that cynicism predicted retention among HIV/AIDS volunteers. The results of the present study suggest that (lack of) cynicism and connectedness is a prerequisite for retention in palliative care volunteers.</p>
<p>The present study advances knowledge on the JD-R model and the literature on volunteers in several ways. First, our findings are compatible with the assumption of the JD-R model<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049909111430224">29</xref>
</sup> and previous research<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049909111430224">30</xref>
</sup> by suggesting that retention is mainly determined by the availability of resources. The robustness of this finding was strongly supported by other ratings of volunteer resources and suggests that nonprofit organizations should concentrate on interventions that promote resources rather than decrease demands in the volunteer workplace.</p>
<p>Second, the finding that exhaustion and cynicism have different causes and consequences are in line with the basic assumption of the JD-R model and thus, future researchers are encouraged to study them separately<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111430224">9</xref>
</sup> rather than together as indicators of burnout<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111430224">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1049909111430224">69</xref>
</sup> in the JD-R model. One important point to note is that the relationship between exhaustion and (low) retention may not be as strong as indicated by the zero-order correlation. The relative contribution of exhaustion is less when other variables such as cynicism are taken into account. For example, in the present study, cynicism was shown to have a stronger impact on volunteer retention than exhaustion when tested together in the full SEM model. Inspection of M1 showed that the path from emotional exhaustion to retention was nonsignificant. Such explanation may not be surprising given that previous research has shown that emotional exhaustion leads to cynicism<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1049909111430224">71</xref>
</sup> which then causes negative work outcomes such as poor work performance.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049909111430224">33</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Finally, the present study also add to the current understanding of burnout and connectedness in palliative care volunteers as both of these constructs have not been examined as mediators within this population. It demonstrates “how” (rather than “whether”) resources may lead to desirable (or undesirable) outcomes for volunteers. Specifically, it indicates that when volunteers receive adequate levels of supervisor support, training, volunteer organizational support, and (unique to this study) family support, they would feel connected to (rather than feel cynical about) their volunteer work and this, in turn, increases their intention to remain with the organization (increased retention). However, a lack of these resources would de-motivate the volunteers as they would develop a cynical attitude to the volunteer work and consequently leave the organization (decreased retention).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1049909111430224">
<title>Strengths and Limitations of the Study</title>
<p>The present study had the following strengths. As the sample consisted of unpaid workers, the study adds to the limited research on volunteers. In addition, the use of a self-rating and other rating means that the results were not entirely based on a single source. However, the results need to be interpreted with caution, given that there are also several limitations to the present research.</p>
<p>The study was cross-sectional so causal inferences cannot be made. Second, it is important to note that some scales produced for paid workers may not be highly reliable among volunteer workers. For example, the emotional demands scale is a well-validated measure adapted from the Demand-Induced Strain Questionnaire (DISQ).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1049909111430224">52</xref>
</sup> Researchers using this scale have often reported a reliability of .80 or higher in their studies of paid workers<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1049909111430224">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1049909111430224">73</xref>
</sup>; but in the present volunteer study, it fell short of the minimum criterion of .70. Some volunteers specifically indicated that they did not think the item, “I have to deal with people who have unrealistic expectations” was appropriate for their case and thought that it should be reworded to “I agree to” or “I want to.” To avoid such ambiguity in the future, a “pilot” survey should be conducted to ensure that items adapted from paid workers are appropriately worded and relevant to the volunteer context under study.</p>
<p>Another reliability problem in the present study is the other ratings of job demands. The internal consistency of the 4-item scale was .46 which is much lower than the minimum criterion of .70. This low reliability may be due to the fact that each demand was measured with only 1 item. Such low reliability may explain the nonsignificant correlations between family ratings of job demands and self-ratings of exhaustion, depression, and (low) retention. In future research, it may be advisable to use the same number of items (scales) for both self-ratings and other-ratings of job demands or design measures specifically for use with families of volunteers. For example, a focus group or interview could be conducted with a few family members to capture specific stressors in which they believed to be important in the volunteer’s job. Major themes expressed in interview transcripts can then be identified to determine key job stressors. From there, items can be generated to form the other ratings scale of job demands.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1049909111430224">
<title>Practical Implications for Volunteer Organizations</title>
<p>The results of the present study have several important practical implications for the management of members of nonprofit organizations. While we do not know for certain whether exhaustion actually leads to depression in palliative care volunteers (as this was not confirmed by the multisource sample), we do know that they will continue to volunteer despite feeling emotionally drained from their work. The cognitive processes that underlie this particular behavior may be explained by the social exchange theory.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1049909111430224">49</xref>
</sup> When a volunteer gives it may be a cost to them (in terms of feeling stress and exhausted) and in return, they receive rewards (in terms of friendship, gratitude, or simply knowing that they have made a difference to other people’s lives) which makes things satisfying. In this sense, emotional exhaustion would not be severe enough to lead to depression. However, the extent to which volunteers can make a difference to other people’s lives is also dependent upon the resources that are provided to them to perform their “helping” role.</p>
<p>Motivation (cynicism and connectedness) appeared to play a prominent role in explaining the underlying psychological processes as to why volunteer turnover and retention occur. Our results revealed that individuals who enter the volunteer workforce often have goals and needs in mind, which are expected to be fulfilled when they undertake volunteer activities. Therefore, it is in the volunteer organization’s best interest to invest time into understanding and satisfying these needs. Such needs may not be met in volunteers’ paid job or when they have retired. So, what are these needs? As identified in the present study, one of these motivational needs is the need to belong or feel connected. The important practical implication here is that if volunteer organizations are able to provide volunteers with the necessary resources, volunteers would feel connected to (rather than cynical about) their volunteer job and this, in turn, would encourage them to remain with the organization. Volunteers are unlikely to suffer from financial hardship, if they choose to terminate their service, but it would probably cost them socially, such as losing friendships.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1049909111430224">74</xref>
</sup> However, if they have not been able to develop friendships (ie, feel that they belong) at their volunteer workplace then there will virtually be no costs to them from leaving the organization.</p>
<p>In order to promote connectedness and reduce cynicism in the volunteer workplace, volunteer organizations are encouraged to provide their volunteers with the following resources. First, good supervisory support—supervisors (ie, volunteer coordinator or manager) are important source of social support for volunteers. They provide structure to the volunteer work environment, provide information and feedback to their volunteers, and are able to help volunteers overcome difficulties that may arise. In addition, family members are also an important source of social support for volunteers as they can either encourage or discourage their decision to stay or leave the organization. In order to get family members to support the volunteers, supervisors could invite them to take part in training and meetings where they can obtain information about the kind of work that volunteers do and how it may affect them.</p>
<p>Third, training (including education) provided to volunteers should be “adequate” and “ongoing” so that volunteers have the updated skills and knowledge to help their clients as well as manage themselves. This will also help volunteers feel competent about performing the work well and thus, making it more enjoyable for them. When volunteers feel inadequately trained, it is unlikely that they will develop strong bonds with their clients because they may not know how to handle their clients’ emotional needs and/or be able to manage their own stresses appropriately (eg, professionally removing oneself from the difficulties and problems of the client). More importantly, when volunteers try to cope with these negative experiences at “home,” this could potentially lead to marital and/or family difficulties. As one family member indicated, sharing volunteer work experiences has led to marital problems. Finally, receiving support from the organization such as reimbursement for out-of-pocket expenses (phone and petrol) is important to volunteers.</p>
<p>The suggestions provided above are potentially useful strategies that volunteer organizations could adopt to increase volunteer well-being and retention. However, it must also be acknowledged that these strategies will not work when the reasons for leaving are beyond the control of the organization. These reasons may be related to health, age, study, or moving (relocating) interstate. In terms of moving interstate, volunteer coordinators and managers can still play an important role by encouraging individuals to continue volunteering at a different palliative care organization in the new location they are moving to. Although some researchers may suggest that turnover due to work and family commitments may be reduced by adopting the concept of corporate volunteering,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1049909111430224">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1049909111430224">76</xref>
</sup> it only applies to people who are working and not retirees. The management issues related to retired volunteers are slightly different so the main focus here is to build strong connectivity within the organization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1049909111430224">
<title>Suggestions for Future Research</title>
<p>The present study provides several important implications for future research. Presently, the application of the JD-R model from paid workers to volunteer workers appears promising. The model has been previously validated in a number of volunteer occupational groups including firefighters,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049909111430224">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup> ambulance officers,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111430224">12</xref>
</sup> state emergency service workers,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup> and AIDS workers.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909111430224">10</xref>
</sup> The present study extends this research by successfully applying the model, for the first time, to a group of volunteer palliative care workers and their families.</p>
<p>Within the volunteer context, it is important to distinguish between 2 types of volunteer motivation (1) the motivation to begin volunteering and (2) the motivation to remain a volunteer.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909111430224">1</xref>
</sup> While the need to belong or feel connected has been identified as an underlying motivation for volunteering, it is uncertain whether this is also a reason for volunteers to continue their service in the long run. In order to answer this question, future research is needed to determine whether connectedness changes over time.</p>
<p>In the present study, we included work–home conflict as an important volunteer demand. Previous research<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049909111430224">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1049909111430224">77</xref>
</sup> has also investigated the crossover effects from paid work to family and family to paid work. In addition, the conflict between volunteer work and family on burnout has also been investigated.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049909111430224">35</xref>
</sup> However, what has not been investigated is the crossover effect from paid work to volunteer work and vice versa. Like family commitments, some volunteers also have paid work commitments that can influence their decisions to stay or leave the organization.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111430224">40</xref>
</sup> Future research should simultaneously examine the interactions between paid work, volunteer work, and family demands, and how this may contribute to burnout and turnover among volunteers.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1049909111430224">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our findings make both theoretical and empirical contributions to the literature. Theoretically, they suggest a means by which the JD-R model can be further refined and extended to give a better understanding of the relationship between volunteer demands and strain as well as the relationship between volunteer resources and motivational outcomes. Specifically, they suggest that the two components (exhaustion and cynicism) of burnout should be studied separately and that connectedness (as a multidimensional construct) should be added to the model to provide further insights into the psychological processes underlying volunteer ill-health, well-being and motivation.</p>
<p>Empirically, the results add support to the generalizability of the JD-R theory to other volunteer workers—volunteer palliative care workers. Practically, the results demonstrate that both work and nonwork resources are important for promoting connectedness and reducing cynicism in the volunteer work environment. It may thus be beneficial for volunteer coordinators and managers to provide a work environment that does not only include good supervisory support, training, and organizational resources but also an environment where friends and/or families of volunteers can get involved.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors are grateful to all volunteer coordinators and managers who assisted with data collection and to the volunteers who generously took out more of their time to participate in the study.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1049909111430224">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1049909111430224">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049909111430224">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Starnes</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wymer</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Demographics, personality traits, roles, motivations, and attrition rates of hospice volunteers</article-title>. <source>J Nonprof Public Sec Market</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>72</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049909111430224">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Australia Bureau of Statistics</collab>. <source>Population by Age and Sex, Australian States and Territories</source>, <comment>No. 3201.0</comment>. <publisher-loc>Canberra, ACT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Capital Territory</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049909111430224">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Population Ageing</collab> <year>2002</year>. <source>United Nations Website</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>United Nations, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Population Division</publisher-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.un.org/esa/population/publications/ageing/Graph.pdf">http://www.un.org/esa/population/publications/ageing/Graph.pdf</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed April 14, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049909111430224">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alexandra</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Valuing the volunteers</article-title>. <source>The Times</source> <publisher-loc>London, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Times Newspapers Limited</publisher-name>. <year>2003</year>: <fpage>30</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049909111430224">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Facts and figures</collab>. <source>Help the Hospices Website</source>. <publisher-loc>London, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Help the Hospices</publisher-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.helpthehospices.org.uk/about-hospice-care/facts-figures/">http://www.helpthehospices.org.uk/about-hospice-care/facts-figures/</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed April 14, 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049909111430224">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Amenta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Death anxiety, purpose in life and duration of service in hospice volunteers</article-title>. <source>Psych Rep</source>. <year>1984</year>; <volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>984</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049909111430224">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lafer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The attrition of hospice volunteers</article-title>. <source>OMEGA</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049909111430224">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paradis</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Runnion</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Volunteer stress and burnout: issues for administrators</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Paradis</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Stress and Burnout Among Providers Caring for the Terminally III and Their Families</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Haworth Press</publisher-name>; <year>1987</year>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049909111430224">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Demerouti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nachreiner</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The job demands-resources model of burnout</article-title>. <source>J App Psych</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>86</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049909111430224">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pakenham</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A test of the job demands-resources model with HIV/AIDS volunteers</article-title>. <source>J HIV/AIDS Soc Serv</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049909111430224">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klemasz</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuckey</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Volunteer demands and resources as antecedents to burnout, engagement, and team effectiveness</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Dollard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winefield</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuckey</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winwood</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Better Work, Better Organizations, Better World: Proceedings of the 7<sup>th</sup> Industrial and Organisational Psychology Conference/1<sup>st</sup> Asia Pacific Congress on Work and Organisational Psychology; 2007 Jun 28 –July 1</source>. <comment>Adelaide</comment> <comment>, South Australia</comment>; <year>2007</year>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049909111430224">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lewig</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xanthopoulou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dollard</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Metzer</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Burnout and connectedness among Australian volunteers: a test of the job demands-resources model</article-title>. <source>J Vocat Behav</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049909111430224">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boyd</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pignata</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winefield</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gillespie</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stough</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A longitudinal test of the job demands-resources model among Australian university academics</article-title>. <source>Appl Psychol Inter Rev</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049909111430224">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hubert</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morrison</surname>
<given-names>VL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A preliminary study into stress in palliative care: optimism, self-efficacy and social support</article-title>. <source>Psychol Health Med</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049909111430224">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fletcher</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Work, Stress, Disease and Life Expectancy</source>. <publisher-loc>England, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>1991</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049909111430224">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glass</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hastings</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Stress and burnout: concerns for the hospice volunteer</article-title>. <source>Educ Gerontol</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049909111430224">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hardy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Occupational Stress. Personal and professional Approaches</source>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanley Thornes Publishers</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049909111430224">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cyr</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dowrick</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Burnout in crisisline volunteers</article-title>. <source>Adm Policy Ment Health</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049909111430224">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maslach</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leiter</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Maslach Burnout Inventory Manual</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>California, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049909111430224">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burnout</surname>
<given-names>Maslach C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A dimensional perspective</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maslach</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marek</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Professional Burnout: Recent Developments in Theory and Research</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>; <year>1993</year>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049909111430224">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buunk</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Burnout: an overview of 25 years of research and theorizing</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Schabracq</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winnubst</surname>
<given-names>JAM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Handbook of Work and Health Psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester, West Sussex</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049909111430224">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shirom</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Job related burnout: a review</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Quick</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tetrick</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Handbook of Occupational Health Psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049909111430224">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenfield</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of dropout and burnout in AIDS volunteers: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>AIDS Care</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049909111430224">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Claxton-Oldfield</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Claxton-Oldfield</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Keeping hospice palliative care volunteers on board: dealing with issues of volunteer attrition, stress, and retention</article-title>. <source>Indian J Palliat Care</source>: <year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049909111430224">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Metzer</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winefield</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Engaged or Connected? A perspective of the motivational pathway of the job demands-resources model in volunteers working for nonprofit organizations</article-title>. <source>Int J Voluntary Nonprofit Organizations</source>. <fpage>November 1, 2011 (doi: 10.1007/s11266-011-9233-1)</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1049909111430224">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>J-Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Metzer</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winefield</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Validation of the four dimensional connectedness scale in a multi-sample volunteer study: a distinct construct from work engagement and organizational commitment</article-title>. <source>Int J Voluntary Nonprofit Organizations</source>. <comment>(in press)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1049909111430224">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baumeister</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leary</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The need to belong: desire for interpersonal attachments as a fundamental human motivation</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>117</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1049909111430224">
<label>28</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gabard</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Volunteer burnout and dropout: issues in AIDS service organizations</article-title>. <source>J Health Hum Serv Adm</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1049909111430224">
<label>29</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Demerouti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The job demands-resources model: state of the art</article-title>. <source>J Manage Psychol</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1049909111430224">
<label>30</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Job demands, job resources, and their relationship with burnout and engagement: a multi-sample study</article-title>. <source>J Org Behav</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1049909111430224">
<label>31</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Llorens</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salanova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Testing the robustness of the job demands-resources model</article-title>. <source>Int J Stress Manag</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>378</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1049909111430224">
<label>32</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Demerouti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verbeke</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Using the job demands-resources model to predict burnout and performance</article-title>. <source>Hum Res Manag</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1049909111430224">
<label>33</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Emmerik</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Riet</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How job demands, resources, and burnout predict objective performance: a constructive replication</article-title>. <source>Anxiety Stress Coping</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1049909111430224">
<label>34</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brenninkmeijer</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Yperen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How to conduct research on burnout: advantages and disadvantages of a unidimensional approach to burnout</article-title>. <source>Occup Environ Med</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1049909111430224">
<label>35</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cowlishaw</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLennan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Balance between volunteer work and family roles: testing a theoretical model of work-family conflict in the volunteer emergency services</article-title>. <source>Aust J Psychol</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1049909111430224">
<label>36</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>KZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Che</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The missing link between emotional demands and exhaustion</article-title>. <source>J Manage Psychol</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>798</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1049909111430224">
<label>37</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Melamed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shirom</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Toker</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berliner</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shapira</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Burnout and the risk of cardiovascular disease: evidence, possible causal paths, and promising research directions</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>132</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1049909111430224">
<label>38</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knudsen</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ducharme</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roman</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Turnover intention and emotional exhaustion “at the top”: Adapting the job demands-resources model to leaders of addiction treatment organizations</article-title>. <source>J Occup Health Psychol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1049909111430224">
<label>39</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cropanzano</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Emotional exhaustion as a predictor of job performance and voluntary turnover</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>83</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1049909111430224">
<label>40</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>J-Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>The job demands-resources model: a multi-sample study of emotional exhaustion, work engagement and connectedness in emergency service volunteers</source> <comment>[unpublished manuscript]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Adelaide, SA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Work and Stress Research Group, University of South Australia</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1049909111430224">
<label>41</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Demerouti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dollard</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How job demands affect partners’ experience of exhaustion: integrating work-family conflict and crossover theory</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>93</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>911</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1049909111430224">
<label>42</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoad</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Volunteers in the independent hospice movement</article-title>. <source>Sociol Health Ill</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1049909111430224">
<label>43</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Demerouti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dual processes at work in a call centre: an application of the job demands-resources model</article-title>. <source>Euro J Work Org Psychol</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1049909111430224">
<label>44</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Department of Human Services</collab>. <source>Palliative Care Volunteer Survey Findings</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne, VIC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Victoria, Australia</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1049909111430224">
<label>45</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Payne</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The role of volunteers in hospice bereavement support in New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1049909111430224">
<label>46</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fahey</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sleigh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Training can be a recruitment and retention tool for emergency service volunteers</article-title>. <source>Aust J Emerg Manage</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1049909111430224">
<label>47</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lynch</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Volunteer retention and feelings of connection</article-title>. <source>E-volunteerism: The Electronic Journal of the Volunteer Community</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1049909111430224">
<label>48</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Volunteering Australia</collab>. <source>National Survey of Volunteering Issues</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne, VIC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Victoria</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1049909111430224">
<label>49</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hormans</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Social Behaviour: Its Elementary Forms</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</publisher-name>; <year>1961</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1049909111430224">
<label>50</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Omoto</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crain</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Punished for their good deeds: Stigmatization of AIDS volunteers</article-title>. <source>Am Behav Sci</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>1192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1049909111430224">
<label>51</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McLennan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Birch</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A potential crisis in wildfire emergency response capability? Australia’s volunteer firefighters</article-title>. <source>Environ Hazards</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1049909111430224">
<label>52</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Jonge</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dormann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Vegchel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <source>The DISC Questionnaire: English Version 2.0</source>. <publisher-loc>Eindhoven, the Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Eindhoven University of Technology</publisher-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jandejonge.nl/disq.html">http://www.jandejonge.nl/disq.html</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed July 14, 2008</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1049909111430224">
<label>53</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Summary of Results: Volunteer State Emergency Services</source>. <comment>(unpublished)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Adelaide, SA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Work and Stress Research Group, University of South Australia</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1049909111430224">
<label>54</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holahan</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gilbert</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interrole conflict for working women: careers versus jobs</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>. <year>1979</year>; <volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1049909111430224">
<label>55</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Karasek</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Job Content Instrument: Questionnaire and User’s Guide</source>. <comment>Rev 1.1</comment>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Southern California</publisher-name>; <year>1985</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1049909111430224">
<label>56</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Applying the Job Demands-Resources Model in Volunteer Populations</source> <comment>[Unpublished honours thesis]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Adelaide, SA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of South Australia</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1049909111430224">
<label>57</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baruch-Feldman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brondolo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ben-Dayan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sources of social support and burnout, job satisfaction, and productivity</article-title>. <source>J Occup Health Psychol</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1049909111430224">
<label>58</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leiter</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maslach</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Maslach Burnout inventory-general survey</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Maslach</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Leiter</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Maslach Burnout Inventory</source>. <publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1049909111430224">
<label>59</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arbuckle</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Amos 16.0 User’s Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SPSS, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1049909111430224">
<label>60</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Korunka</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kubicek</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoonakker</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Work engagement and burnout: testing the robustness of the job demands-resources model</article-title>. <source>J Posit Psychol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1049909111430224">
<label>61</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weigl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hornung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petru</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Glaser</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Angerer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Work engagement accumulation of task, social, personal resources: a three-wave structural equation model</article-title>. <source>J Vocat Behav</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1049909111430224">
<label>62</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Joreskog</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sorbom</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>LISREL 8: Structural Equations Modeling With the SIMPLIS Command Language</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scientific Software International</publisher-name>; <year>1993</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1049909111430224">
<label>63</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xanthopoulou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Demerouti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reciprocal relationships between job resources, personal resources, and work engagement</article-title>. <source>J Vocat Behav</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1049909111430224">
<label>64</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holye</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The structural equation modeling approach: basic concepts and fundamental issues</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Hoyle</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Structural Equation Modeling: Concepts, Issues and Applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1049909111430224">
<label>65</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>MacCallum</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sugawara</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Power analysis and determination of sample size for covariance structure modelling</article-title>. <source>Psychol Methods</source>. <year>1996</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1049909111430224">
<label>66</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kenny</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>1986</year>; <volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1049909111430224">
<label>67</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmbeck</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Toward terminological, conceptual, and statistical clarity in the study of mediators and moderators: examples from the child-clinical and pediatric psychology literatures</article-title>. <source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>65</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1049909111430224">
<label>68</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frazier</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tix</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barron</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Testing moderator and mediator effects in counselling psychology research</article-title>. <source>J Counsel Psychol</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1049909111430224">
<label>69</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hakanen</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Burnout and work engagement among teachers</article-title>. <source>J Sch Psychol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1049909111430224">
<label>70</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The role of individual, interpersonal, and organizational factors in mitigating burnout among elderly Chinese volunteers</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1049909111430224">
<label>71</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Toppinen-Tanner</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kalimo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mutanen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The process of burnout in white-collar and blue-collar jobs: eight year prospective study of exhaustion</article-title>. <source>J Organ Behav</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1049909111430224">
<label>72</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chrisopoulos</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dollard</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Winefield</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dormann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increasing the probability of finding an interaction in work stress research: a two-wave longitudinal test of the triple-match principle</article-title>. <source>J Occup Organ Psychol</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>83</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1049909111430224">
<label>73</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Jonge</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peeters</surname>
<given-names>MCW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Convergence of self-reports and co-worker reports of counterproductive work behaviour: a cross-sectional multi-source survey among health care workers</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs Stud</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1049909111430224">
<label>74</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cuskelly</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brosnan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Volunteers and employment relations issues in the not for profit sector</article-title>. <source>Aust J Volun</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1049909111430224">
<label>75</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The social case for corporate volunteering</article-title>. <source>Aust J Volun</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1049909111430224">
<label>76</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Quirk</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Corporate Volunteering: The Potential Way Forward</source>. <publisher-loc>New Zealand</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Wellington Volunteer Centre</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1049909111430224">
<label>77</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hakanen</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahola</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The job demands-resources model: a three-year cross-lagged study of burnout, depression, commitment, and work engagement</article-title>. <source>Work Stress</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>