<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Humanity &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0160-5976</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0160597611433269</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0160597611433269</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Title IX and the School Experiences of Pregnant and Mothering Students</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Erdmans</surname>
<given-names>Mary Patrice</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0160597611433269">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0160597611433269"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0160597611433269">
<label>1</label>Department of Sociology, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain, CT, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0160597611433269">Mary Patrice Erdmans, Department of Sociology, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain, CT 06050, USA Email: <email>ErdmansM@ccsu.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0160597611433269">
<p>I believe that every woman has the right to bear and raise children regardless of age, marital status, income, or educational achievement. As such, my research on adolescent mothers does not focus on ways to prevent early childbirth but how to prevent the injustices and disadvantages that shape the lives of many young parents and their children. This article evolved from a misconception that I had, as a young female athlete, that Title IX was the equal-right-to-play-sports amendment for young women. Not until I began researching the educational experiences of pregnant and mothering students did I fully understand that Title IX mandates gender equality in all aspects of education.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>50</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Association for Humanistic Sociology 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association for Humanistic Sociology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article examines why pregnant and mothering students did or did not stay in high school to see whether schools violated Title IX legislation by not providing equal educational opportunities. Examining life-story interviews conducted in 2002–2004 with 62 black, white, and Latina pregnant and mothering students in Connecticut, the author found that (1) while school policies and faculty were often hostile and unreceptive, mothers who dropped out were usually disengaged from school before pregnancy; (2) the presence or absence of school-based day care was a critical factor in school outcomes; and (3) alternative programs for pregnant and mothering students were experienced differently depending on whether students came from urban or nonurban school districts. In conclusion, the author argues that when our attention shifts from teen mothers to the problems of underfunded and overburdened schools, we are confronted with the larger systemic problems of economic and racial segregation and consequently educational inequality.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>education</kwd>
<kwd>adolescent mothers</kwd>
<kwd>Title IX</kwd>
<kwd>inequality</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>My belly was this big and I tell them I need a key because I can’t walk. My feet are swollen. They say, “Well, we need a doctor’s note proving that you are pregnant.” I opened my shirt and said, “This is not proof enough?” She said, “I’m sorry, honey. Those are the rules.” I said, “You people are real assholes.” And I would walk and break my back to the first floor, all the way to fourth floor, to go back to the third, to the basement.</p>
<p>Wanda, 16-year-old Puerto Rican mother</p>
<p>Dropped out of school during pregnancy</p>
</disp-quote>
<disp-quote>
<p>There’s a bathroom every ten thousand miles and it’s one huge maze that takes you about an hour to walk in-between classes. And if you were late then you couldn’t get into class and with being pregnant and being slow and waddling and not being able to get through people because they won’t move and you’re protecting your stomach, it was hard.</p>
<p>Donna, 17-year-old white mother</p>
<p>Enrolled in night school</p>
</disp-quote>
The corporeality of pregnancy makes high schools uncomfortable: bladders do not wait for the bell; smoke in the bathroom nauseates stomachs; climbing stairs aggravates swollen ankles; morning sickness makes it difficult to concentrate in first period history; and firm rounding tummies do not fit easily into student desks. Once children are born, sleepless nights, on-demand feeding, and child care make it even more difficult for young mothers to attend school.</p>
<p>In 2006, the birth rate for teenage mothers increased for the first time in 15 years reenergizing the campaign to prevent early childbirth (Hamilton, Martin, and Ventura 2007). One reason adolescent childbirth is considered a social problem is because of its connection with school failure. Teen mothers have low rates of high school completion and college attendance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0160597611433269">Hofferth, Reid, and Mott 2001</xref>). One-third of all teen mothers do not earn a high school diploma or a General Educational Development (GED) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0160597611433269">certificate (Perper, Peterson, and Manlove 2010</xref>), and the drop-out rate for these young mothers is three to four times higher than the national average (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0160597611433269">Kelly 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0160597611433269">Luttrell 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Politicians and policy makers use these data on school failure to rebuke young unmarried women having children. A report prepared at the request of a U.S. Senator based on data from the Alan Guttmacher Institute stated that “70 percent of teen mothers drop out of high school, making pregnancy the primary reason young women drop out early” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0160597611433269">Berglas, Brindis, and Cohen 2003</xref>:24). A fact sheet put together by the National Campaign to Prevent Teen and Unplanned Pregnancy (formed in 1996, shortly after President Clinton defined teen pregnancies as our most serious social problem) carried the headline, “Parenthood is the leading cause of school drop out among teen girls” (Teen Pregnancy and Education 2010). And the public policy firm Civic Enterprises noted in their report on school dropouts, <italic>The Silent Epidemic</italic>, that “becoming a parent was a major factor in their decision to leave school” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0160597611433269">Bridgeland, DiIulio, and Morison 2006</xref>:6)</p>
<p>Academics not funded by policy research firms are less likely to blame school failure on early childbirth. Kristin Luker writes that “the assumption that early pregnancy and childbearing <italic>cause</italic> many students to drop out of school is wrong” (1996:123-4, emphasis in original). Instead, she and numerous other scholars argue that high rates of school failure among teenage mothers are a consequence of social and economic disadvantages that precede the early births (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0160597611433269">Bickel et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0160597611433269">Bissell 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0160597611433269">Butler 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0160597611433269">Furstenberg 2007</xref>; Furstenberg, Brooks-Gunn, and Phillip 1987; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0160597611433269">Geronimus 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0160597611433269">Geronimus and Korenman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0160597611433269">Hotz, McElroy, and Sanders 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0160597611433269">Records 1993</xref>). Teen mothers are disproportionately from poor families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0160597611433269">Furstenberg 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0160597611433269">Luker 1996</xref>), and students from poor families are more likely to drop out of high school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0160597611433269">Fine 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0160597611433269">Weis, Farrar, and Petrie 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>School outcomes for young mothers are strongly influenced by their academic performances before pregnancy. Girls with low-educational expectations and poor school performance are more likely to become adolescent mothers, and after they have a child, their educational expectations often decrease further (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0160597611433269">Beutel 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0160597611433269">Corcoran 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0160597611433269">Gordon 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0160597611433269">Marini 1984</xref>). Other researchers found that school disengagement (e.g., failing grades, truancy, poor attitudes) preceded the pregnancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0160597611433269">Luker 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0160597611433269">Wasserman et al. 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0160597611433269">Yampolskaya et al. 2002</xref>), and conversely, that doing well in school lowered the risk of pregnancy and increased the chances that an unwanted pregnancy would be terminated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0160597611433269">Luster and Small 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0160597611433269">Scaramella et al. 1998</xref>). According to one study, women who had not dropped out of school before having children were as likely to graduate as women who did not have children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0160597611433269">Upchurch and McCarthy 1990</xref>). In sum, doing well in school decreases the chances for early childbirth, while doing poorly increases the chances for both early childbirth and dropping out.</p>
<sec id="section1-0160597611433269">
<title>Title IX and the Education of Pregnant and Mothering Students</title>
<p>While policy makers and politicians connect school failure to early childbirth, and social scientists connect it to preexisting economic and social disadvantage, feminist scholars and women’s advocates focus on gender discrimination in schools. For most of the twentieth century, pregnant and mothering students were treated like <italic>persona non gratis</italic> in high schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0160597611433269">Zellman 1981</xref>). Title IX of the Educational Amendments Act of 1972 made this illegal by mandating that “No person in the United States shall, on the basis of gender, be excluded from participating in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under any educational program or activity receiving federal financial assistance.” Related more specifically to the needs of pregnant and mothering students, Section 106.40.b(1) of this amendment reads:<disp-quote>
<p>A recipient [of federal funding] shall not discriminate against any student, or exclude any student from its educational program or extracurricular activity, on the basis of such student’s pregnancy, childbirth, false pregnancy, termination of pregnancy or recovery there from, unless the student requests voluntarily to participate in a separate portion of the program.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>This legislation made it illegal to force pregnant and mothering students out of regular schools and classrooms and into alternative programs. In addition, Title IX mandated that schools treat pregnancy and childbirth “under the same policies as any other temporary disability,” and that conditions related to pregnancy “were justification for a leave of absence” (106.40.b(4-5)). Any special services schools provided to disabled students, such as home tutors or transportation, must also be provided to pregnant and mothering students who need them. Moreover, students were entitled to make up assignments and tests and be reinstated without any penalties to their class status. Schools could create special programs to accommodate the needs of pregnant and mothering students, but only if enrollment was voluntary and programs did not sacrifice academic rigor nor limit students’ access to extracurricular activities.</p>
<p>Following this amendment, the rate of high school completion for teen mothers increased. In 1975 (when Title IX was effectuated), less than one-third of school-age mothers completed high school (with a diploma or GED certificate), but 10 years later more than one-half did, suggesting that changes to enrollment and reentry policies had “a substantial impact” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0160597611433269">Luker 1996</xref>:121). The quality of the school programs, however, was “uneven” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0160597611433269">Zellman 1981</xref>:104). Twenty years after this legislation, Wanda Pillow found that most educators were not aware of the protections guaranteed to pregnant and mothering students by Title IX, and that “evidence indicates that schools are falling short on this mission” of providing equal educational opportunities (2006:62). A report by the National Women’s Law Center stated: “Pregnant and parenting students’ chances of success are harmed by a lack of support from their schools, active discouragement by school personnel, outright discrimination and stigmatization, and inferior alternative programs” (2009). These continued problems prompted a 2009 bill, The Pregnant and Parenting Students Access to Education Act (H.R. 5894), designed to provide money for schools to meet the obligations of Title IX. Pillow concluded that even though pregnant and mothering students are guaranteed equal access to education, pervasive violations of Title IX “are likely the reason that pregnancy is the most cited reason given by teen girls who drop out of school and why up to half of all school-aged mothers will not complete high school” (2006:69).</p>
<p>Schools fail pregnant and mothering students in several ways. First, many schools have not addressed infrastructure problems (e.g., small desks and numerous stairs) that pregnant and mothering students face when they are attending regular classes. Schools also construct barriers by restricting access to bathroom facilities, implementing stringent absentee policies and homework and examination timetables, and not providing on-site child care or home tutors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0160597611433269">Lesko 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0160597611433269">Manlove 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0160597611433269">Pillow 2006</xref>). This “structural and social dislocation” Luttrell argues, “is coupled with a psychological dislocation that results from shaming practices and undue hostility in school settings and that require pregnant girls to cope with tainted identities” (2003:21). In fact, H.R. 5894 mentioned above, states specifically that the grants for schools are designed not only for child care and transportation but also to change the culture that stigmatizes these students.</p>
<p>A second way that schools fail pregnant and mothering students is when schools force pregnant and mothering students into alternative programs, especially if these programs are of inferior quality or limited range. Title IX states specifically that students must “voluntarily request” to attend an alternative program. And yet, in 2000, the New York Civil Liberties Union (NYCLU) found that public schools routinely denied pregnant and mothering students enrollment in a regular high school or strongly encouraged them to enroll in an alternative program. When testers, posing as pregnant students, made phone calls to enroll in schools, administrators often denied or discouraged their requests. One administrator asked the caller, “Does it bother you that you are going to show in front of the other high school students?” and then suggested she consider an alternative school. Others stressed that their school would not be making accommodations, that missing classes would be a problem, or that they could attend until “it gets bad” by which they meant the eighth month of the pregnancy (NYCLU 2000).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0160597611433269">1</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Racial minorities are more likely to be steered into these alternative programs. Wanda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0160597611433269">Pillow (2004</xref>) found that seven of the ten separate school settings she studied were a majority African American (with one school majority Latina). The white girls more often stayed in school during the early trimesters and then used home schooling/home tutoring until they returned to school after they had the child. This practice, Pillow argues, results in fewer white girls in the separate school programs, makes the white pregnancies less visible to the student body, and reinforces “the perception that ‘good girls’ and in this case ‘white girls’ are not getting pregnant.” At the same time, the separation of black and Latina students into separate schools “works discursively to mark these settings as problematic, special, and deficit while also reinforcing placement decisions that perpetuate segregated school settings” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0160597611433269">2004</xref>:131).</p>
<p>In addition to not always being voluntary, especially for racial minorities, critics argue that these programs do not provide an equal education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0160597611433269">Lesko 1995</xref>; McDade 1992; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0160597611433269">Zellman 1981</xref>). For example, the breadth of the instruction in these alternative programs is limited to the basics and does not include foreign languages, composition, advanced science, or math (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0160597611433269">Luttrell 2003</xref>). As a result, even after students are mainstreamed back into regular classrooms they are not on pace with their peers who are in college preparatory courses.</p>
<p>Another way these programs stigmatize students is through the conservative and ideological politics embedded in their curricula. Programs for pregnant and mothering students often focus on moral reform, personal responsibility, and parenting skills rather than educational instruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0160597611433269">Burdell 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0160597611433269">Lesko 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0160597611433269">Luttrell 2003</xref>; McDade 1992). They are designed for young mothers to “take responsibility” for their actions (e.g., they need an education to provide for their children) and education becomes redefined as a responsibility rather than a right. Lesko argues that this curriculum helps “teenage mothers <italic>redeem</italic> themselves, or deliver themselves from the position of their former sinful, or problematic, status” (1990:115).</p>
<p>Finally, these programs stigmatize and marginalize pregnant and mothering students by separating them from the larger student body. Deidre Kelly argues that pregnant and mothering students are “ghettoized” in alternative programs located off school grounds or in separate buildings or wings (2000:12). Patricia Burdell maintains that separatist school policies are designed to “conceal pregnant students” (1998:211). Similar to homes for unwed mothers fifty years ago, hiding pregnant and mothering students sends the message that they did something wrong and must be kept out of sight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0160597611433269">Fessler 2006</xref>). The discourses around teen pregnancy—the irresponsible girl discourse, the epidemic discourse, the out-of-control sexualized teen discourse—construct adolescent mothers as deviants, and the programs that separate them from the student body underscore this message (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0160597611433269">Kelly 2000</xref>; Lesko 1990). Wendy Luttrell maintains that it is “the ‘showing’ of the pregnancy” that is the problem (2003:18). When pregnancy is seen as something to be prevented, like a sexually transmitted disease, then it gets construed as a “disease” that other students could catch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0160597611433269">Pillow 2004</xref>). Programs for pregnant and mothering students isolate these pregnant bodies so as not to contaminate the rest of the student body.</p>
<p>While school policies, personnel, and programs continue to stigmatize young girls who get pregnant, the fathers of the babies suffer none of these hostilities. Given the fact that it is the showing of the belly that becomes the stigmatizing marker, the biological fact that men do not get pregnant makes their participation less visible (and in many cases invisible). The male students are not isolated in separate programs, they do not have physical discomforts or medical complications that interfere with course work, and they do not have to suffer moralizing faculty and demoralizing policies. Teen fathers are not seen as having a disease (though they have been defined as predators in statutory rape laws). Moreover, many young fathers deny paternity or disassociate from the mother of their child and thereby exacerbate the social discomfort many pregnant students experience. More recently, in efforts to make fathers accountable, laws have been introduced to enforce child support payments, however, this is not something that interferes with their schooling, which is the focus of this article. In schools, it is girls who are stigmatized by the early pregnancy and face barriers to education.</p>
<p>In this article, the author examines the school experiences of 62 young mothers who were attending public high schools in Connecticut when they became pregnant. She looks first at how attached the girls were to school (academically and socially) before they became pregnant, and whether school policies and personnel weakened or reinforced these attachments after they became pregnant and had a child. Second, the author analyzes the transcripts of the 14 mothers who attended alternative programs for pregnant and mothering students to examine their perceptions of and satisfaction with these programs. In general, her analysis is directed toward understanding why some adolescent mothers complete school and others do not. Was “pregnancy the primary reason” or “parenthood … the leading cause of school drop out among teen girls” as the policy reports suggest? Or did schools discriminate against pregnant and mothering students by not providing them with equal opportunities?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0160597611433269">
<title>Methodology</title>
<p>The life-story interviews were conducted with a convenience sample of first-time mothers participating in a home visitation program in Connecticut designed to support healthy parenting practices. This sample of mothers was more disadvantaged than the general population because one prerequisite for inclusion in the home visitation program was testing positive on the Revised Early Identification (REID) screen composed of 17 items related to child maltreatment (e.g., being single, unemployed, with a history of substance abuse, mental illness, or family problems). Testing positive meant having three or more of the 17 characteristics, or two or more of the characteristics if one was a history of substance abuse, psychiatric care, family problems, or depression.</p>
<sec id="section3-0160597611433269">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>The life-story interviews were conducted in 2002–2003 by a team of trained researchers (two principal investigators—myself and Timothy Black—a project director, and eight interviewers) through the Center for Social Research at the University of Hartford.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0160597611433269">2</xref>
</sup> Participants were recruited through their home visitors who explained the project and collected signed consent forms after which the research team contacted the participants directly. We assured mothers confidentiality (in this article all identifying information has been changed). We matched interviewers and interviewees by race and ethnicity and interviewed each mother twice (each interview was one-and-a-half to two hours). Most interviews took place in the mother’s home and we paid mothers 50 dollars at the completion of the second interview. The interviewers explained that the goal of the research was “to understand their lives better” in order to improve home visitation services.</p>
<p>Before the life-story interview, we had information about the mothers from the REID screen and the program’s baseline interview that covered family history, school achievement, involvement of the birth father, state assistance, medical history, current living conditions, histories of abuse, and involvement with the prison system or child welfare authorities. The life-story interview covered the following: family background, school experience, relationship history, pregnancy story, parenting experience, work history, household resources, interactions with state welfare agencies, and involvement in the home visitation program. Each section of the life-story interview began with a grand tour question (e.g., Describe what it was like growing up?) and had a series of follow-up questions and prompts. The schedule was designed to encourage mothers to tell stories rather than answer questions.</p>
<p>While the baseline interview provided information (e.g., highest grade completed), the life-story interview provided detailed descriptions that fleshed out and gave meaning to life events. For example, one mother reported on the baseline interview that the highest grade she completed was ninth grade. In the life-story interview, however, we found that she had only completed eighth grade and that she attempted ninth grade three times before she finally gave up and stopped going to school. In was only during the more in-depth interview that we understood that she was failing school before she became pregnant even though she had not officially dropped out of school until after she had a child.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0160597611433269">
<title>Analysis</title>
<p>Interview tapes were transcribed and, when necessary, translated. The two principal investigators and the project director coded and organized the transcriptions using QSR Nud*ist software, version N6. The codes ranged from concrete topics (e.g., occupation and education) to more abstract concepts (e.g., social support and school integration). We line-coded each transcript. The first 40 interviews were line-coded by two researchers who independently coded the same transcript and then met to discuss and resolve discrepancies in the coding to attain intercoder reliability. After we became more confident in our coding categories, the remaining interviews were each coded by one of the three researchers and we met as a group to discuss any vagaries or indecisions in coding.</p>
<p>Coding the transcripts led to a fragmentation of the life story as each narrative became divided into “nodes” in the QSR program. An analysis of these nodes helped identify the coexistence of life events, but they belied the narrative value of the life story which is to understand life events (such as dropping out of school) within a life history and social context (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0160597611433269">Bertaux and Kohli 1984</xref>). To analyze the biography in situ, we read each transcript a second time and wrote a summary narrative identifying the salient social processes shaping the life course.</p>
<p>The life story is a reconstruction of the past; it is not “the life” but a representation of a life, and in this study, this representation was performed for the benefit of a stranger in her house asking the teen mother to talk about her life in exchange for 50 dollars. As a performance, the stories were influenced by the age and maturity of the mother, language and cognitive ability, and personality and willingness. Some mothers were outgoing and eager story tellers while others were reticent and ambivalent.</p>
<p>During the analysis, we were cognizant of this performative element and tried to assess how our presence influenced the construction of the life story. For example, given the stigma associated with early childbearing, most mothers tried to present a counternarrative that portrayed themselves as good mothers. We expected, therefore, that they would underreport deviant and illegal behavior such as drug use that could jeopardize their right to parent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0160597611433269">
<title>Study Participants</title>
<p>In the original study, 171 first-time mothers were interviewed. This article focuses on only the 62 mothers who were attending a high school when they were pregnant. Characteristics of the sample are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0160597611433269">Table 1</xref>. All but three of the mothers received the Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women, Infants, and Children (WIC), and 93 percent were eligible for Medicaid. Less than one-half of the mothers lived in a household with a car that worked. The African Americans and Puerto Ricans most often lived in urban areas while whites lived in towns and small cities (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0160597611433269">Table 2</xref>). At the time of the interview, more than one-half of the young mothers were actively working on completing their high school education—some were enrolled in a high school, others were attending GED programs and adult education, and still others were being home schooled. Twelve of the young mothers had completed high school (and four were enrolled in college), but 13 mothers had dropped out of school at the time of the interview (though several spoke about their hopes of enrolling in a GED program at some point in the future).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0160597611433269" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Description of the Sample of Pregnant and Mothering Students (<italic>N</italic> = 62)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0160597611433269" xlink:href="10.1177_0160597611433269-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age at birth of first child (range 13–19)</td>
<td>
<italic>X</italic> = 16.2</td>
<td align="center">
<italic>X</italic> = 16.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at time of interview (range 14–24)</td>
<td>
<italic>X</italic> = 17.9</td>
<td align="center">
<italic>X</italic> = 17.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Racial/Ethnic Identity:</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Puerto Rican</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 22</td>
<td>36%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Non-Hispanic White</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 14</td>
<td>23%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 12</td>
<td>20%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mixed Racial</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 7</td>
<td>11%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0160597611433269">a</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 7</td>
<td>11%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Live in a household with a car that works</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 27</td>
<td>44%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family history of domestic violence</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 22</td>
<td>35%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim of child abuse</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 23</td>
<td>37%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mother completed high school<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0160597611433269">b</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 40</td>
<td>65%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of partner abuse</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 23</td>
<td>37%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of substance abuse</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 7</td>
<td>11%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of juvenile detention</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 13</td>
<td>21%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Was in a bilingual program</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 6</td>
<td>10%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Was in a special education program</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 3</td>
<td>5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">At the time of the interview:</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Working on diploma or GED</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 37</td>
<td>60%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Completed high school with diploma or GED</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 12</td>
<td>19%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dropped out of school</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic> = 13</td>
<td>21%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0160597611433269">
<p>
<italic>Notes</italic>: <sup>a</sup>Other racial/ethnic identities include three Latinas, two West Indians, two Asians.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0160597611433269">
<p>
<sup>b</sup>Refers to the biological mother of the teen mother, and high school completion was GED certificate or diploma.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0160597611433269" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Residence and Racial/Ethnic Identity of Young Mothers</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0160597611433269" xlink:href="10.1177_0160597611433269-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>City Size</th>
<th>Puerto Rican</th>
<th>White</th>
<th>African American</th>
<th>Mixed racial</th>
<th>Other</th>
<th>Totals</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>&gt;100,000</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50,000–100,000</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&lt;50,000</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>62</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0160597611433269">
<title>School Experiences of Pregnant and Mothering Students</title>
<p>Three patterns emerged from the analysis of their school experiences. First, some students were doing poorly in school before pregnancy and dropped out soon after they became pregnant. For them school failure was a precursor to rather than an effect of early childbirth. This was the clear case for 13 of the mothers. Second, some students experienced hostile school environments that nudged them out of regular schools and into GED programs or night school. Third, a few students experienced friendly school policies and faculty that kept them integrated into the regular school and on track with their peers. While 18 students spoke explicitly about hostile school environments and 8 mentioned negative peer reactions (with some overlap), only nine students spoke explicitly about friendly environments, mentioning personnel and policies that helped them to stay in school.</p>
<sec id="section7-0160597611433269">
<title>Discouraged Students</title>
<p>Thirteen mothers were in school when they became pregnant but had dropped out of school and were not enrolled in any school or program (GED, adult education, correspondence) at the time of the interview. The dropouts were more likely to be Puerto Rican (69 percent) and to live in large metropolitan areas (62 pecent; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0160597611433269">Table 3</xref>). Only three of them lived in a household with a car that worked, and less than half had a mother who had completed high school. The mothers of the Puerto Rican girls were all born on the island as were five of the teen mothers who dropped out of school.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0160597611433269" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Residence and Racial/Ethnic Identity of Students Who Dropped out of School during Pregnancy or after Birth</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0160597611433269" xlink:href="10.1177_0160597611433269-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>City Size</th>
<th>Puerto Rican</th>
<th>White</th>
<th>African American</th>
<th>Mixed Racial</th>
<th>Totals</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>&gt;100,000</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50,000–100,000</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&lt;50,000</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>A prominent narrative in their life stories is that pregnancy followed on the heels of school failure. While some of these young mothers talked about school environments hostile to them as pregnant and mothering students, these students already had one foot (and sometimes two feet) out the door before they became pregnant. Their stories were primarily about peer conflicts and academic failure and can be summed up by one student who said, “I hated school, I’m not gonna lie, I hated school.”</p>
<p>Spanish-speaking students quickly became discouraged learners because of inadequate bilingual programs or the absence of English as a Second Language (ESL) courses. For example, Felicia started having problems in ninth grade when her bilingual program required more English. She could no longer complete the assignments, she failed the exams, and then failed ninth grade. She became pregnant in June, returned to school to repeat ninth grade but dropped out later that year.</p>
<p>Several of the dropouts also talked about girl-on-girl conflict. Danielle was a student with a history of fighting in school, which led to several suspensions before eighth grade. She grew up in one of the poorest neighborhoods in Hartford with one of the highest rates of teen pregnancy. She had been suspended from elementary school numerous times for fighting, and after a particularly violent fight in eighth grade—at which time she was already six months pregnant—her principal suggested that she spend her last trimester home tutored. This could appear as if the principal was trying to “conceal” her pregnancy, but the suggestion also helped protect the fetus. Danielle gave birth in December, returned to school when her baby was only one month old, and was immediately enmeshed in another fight (a continuation of the previous fights). She said, “the principal told me that he was going to give me a week’s suspension, so I told him that was fine, then [laughs] I told him to keep his school that I wasn’t coming back anymore.” She kept her word. She did not return. At the time of the interview she was 20 years old, she had three children, and had not completed her GED.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0160597611433269">3</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Many of the discouraged students had histories of extreme family trauma coupled with learning disabilities that resulted in poor school performance. For example, Lilly’s academic problems were linked to emotional trauma caused by child sexual abuse. She was raped when she was 10 years old and was in a psychiatric hospital from the time she was 11 until she was 15. She also had a learning disability, as she explained:<disp-quote>
<p>I didn’t know how to read that good, so I used to get mad and I just used to throw stuff and hit my classmates. They used to laugh at me when I read so. It’s frustrating. They’ll be like some paperwork they’d give me and I wouldn’t do it because I didn’t know how to spell that good.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Other students discouraged in school before they became pregnant were Isabel who had cognitive problems and was held back a grade, and Alisha who was in and out of psychiatric institutions.</p>
<p>These adolescent mother dropouts were all marginalized in school (academically and socially) before they became pregnant. They dropped out because they were discouraged students, not because they were pregnant. Their stories point to other issues that undermined their ability to succeed including ineffective school policies regarding the education of cognitively disabled, mentally impaired, and non-English speaking students. This suggests that insufficient services for students with special needs better explain why these young women are leaving school than does having a baby. There life stories illustrate that teenage pregnancy is not an independent variable causing school dropout but more of an intervening dependent variable resulting from poverty, inequality, family instability, and underfunded and inadequate schools.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0160597611433269">
<title>Hostile School Environments</title>
<p>In several life stories, the young mothers talked about how physically uncomfortable settings, inflexible school policies, and demeaning administrators and faculty had a corrosive effect on their attachment to school. These young mothers were often moderately integrated into their high schools even if they were not high-performing students. For example, Wanda, a 16-year-old mother of twins, described herself as a good student in elementary and junior high, attached to school through sports and extracurricular activities, but as someone who struggled with the academic work in high school. “Until eighth grade I was smart, but once I hit high school and so much people around me, my head just got—I don’t know where it went.” In smaller elementary school classes, “you could raise your hand and you could say, ‘Mister, could you help me with this?’ But you can’t really do that” in larger high schools. Her pregnancy exacerbated the chilly, impersonal climate of the high school. She said: “Nobody cared. If you tell them, ‘Oh, Miss can I go to the bathroom because I feel like I got to throw up,’ they wouldn’t let you go. They would just say, ‘You have to wait until the class is over because I have a lot of things to do today.’” Her mother told her: “‘If you got to pee and they don’t let you, get up and walk out!’ And I would always do that. But this [one] time she didn’t let me go. And I just had to hold it. And once I got downstairs my stomach hurted. I had to go home.”</p>
<p>Wanda, who was quoted at the beginning of this article, also complained about having to walk up and down four flights of stairs in her large urban high school. “It was hard for me to get a key to take the elevator,” she said, “they would make a big deal out of it.” In her last month of pregnancy, medical complications kept her bedridden and then in the hospital for two weeks until she delivered. She never went back to school after the twins were born. At the time of the interview, her twins were four months old and she hoped to complete her schooling through correspondence courses but she had no intention of returning to a regular high school. It was hard enough while she was pregnant, and now with two small children, she was no longer the sort of student who would raise her hand to go to the bathroom, or “hold it” till someone gave her permission.</p>
<p>Cassandra was more defiant from the beginning<disp-quote>
<p>The teachers they was being too stupid. If I asked them, I need to use the bathroom, they was like no you can wait to the end of the [class period]. I’m like what? I used to just get up and use the bathroom. They wrote me up. I went to the office and I was like, “Hey I’m pregnant. Whenever I need to use the bathroom I'll go use the bathroom. Whenever I need to drink something I’m gonna go drink something cause none of y’all gonna tell me what I can’t do when I’m pregnant. As long as I get y’all work and all that, I be straight.”</p>
</disp-quote>
Despite her strong assertive statements, Cassandra eventually dropped out of high school and enrolled in a GED program where she was at the time of the interview.</p>
<p>In addition to the barriers created by intransigent teachers, other students talked about the uncomfortable physical structures. For example, Mary said she “couldn't deal with going to school anymore cuz it was hard walking up the stairs and walking through the halls.” Felicia, who was already a discouraged student because of language issues, had a problem getting a key to the elevator. The hallways were “full” and she had almost fallen down the stairs two or three times she said, but when she went to the office to ask for a key no one spoke Spanish so she was not sure if they understood her, nor did she ever did get a key. Donna also had a problem with, “people running into you in the hallway. Our school is unbelievably crowded.” As their stomachs expanded the desks became a problem. Trudy pointed out, “The desk was attached to the chair so I had to sit sideways [laughing].” Donna had a different strategy: “You have to sit in ‘em and scrunch down and slowly pivot to the right [laughs].” Desks that did not fit them reinforced their stigmatized identity and sent the message that they did not belong there. This was expressed poignantly by Virginia, a 15-year-old mother:<disp-quote>
<p>I wanted to be home cause I wasn’t feeling right. I was the only one pregnant at the home room in my high school. And it was stressful. I had to go up and down the stairs and sit in a chair that did not fit and they made me feel really—it would put my self-esteem down cause I couldn’t sit and people would just look at me with this big belly.</p>
</disp-quote>
Virginia had fit into school before the pregnancy. She was a cheerleader, involved in a Latin dance troupe, received good grades, and talked positively about her teachers, especially some who helped her through her pregnancy. Unfortunately, she was constantly reminded of her “big belly,” the bump of shame, when she sat in desks that did not fit her.</p>
<p>Pregnant students were also shamed by school faculty and administrators. Rosa described one particularly painful incident:<disp-quote>
<p>One time they made me change my shirt cause they said it was too tight, like that I was showing that I was pregnant. And I said, I don’t understand why that’s a problem, like why should I be ashamed of it, you know what I mean? I’m pregnant, that’s it. And my stomach wasn’t showing, so I started crying cause I was really mad. Because there was fat girls in the school, they wore tight shirts and I didn’t understand like why, just because I was pregnant, they were ashamed of it, they didn’t want people seeing that at their school.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In her case, it was the showing of pregnancy that was frowned upon and communicated to her.</p>
<p>The hostile environments and stigmatized identities marginalized these students, but many of them stayed in school through the pregnancy only to drop out after they had a child because of childcare problems. Virginia detailed the complicated and time-consuming bus travel required to get her child to a childcare provider, herself to school, to pick her child up from the provider, and then get back home. She also was worried about the fact that she was away from her child all day during the crucial bonding period. She said: “I wasn’t having any kind of affection with my son. You know, he wasn’t close with me.” Even those who had their children being cared for at home, spoke of missing their children and feeling uncomfortable when their children “went to grandma” for comfort instead of them. None of these mothers had a school-based child care center as an option.</p>
<p>Strict absentee policies also influenced school outcomes especially around the time of delivery or shortly afterward. Unless students were fortunate enough to have their children in the summer or at the end of the semester, it was difficult to miss one to two months of classes. Pamela said that just after delivery her tutors brought her tests to take at home but in one case “my teacher wanted me to go there and I was like I just had a kid. Some teachers just weren’t cooperative.” Others fell behind when their children were sick causing them to miss weeks of schools without adequate bridging programs (home tutors, flexible exam schedules) so that they were “lost” when they returned and told to restart the grade “the following semester”—leaving them further behind and disengaged from their cohort. Teachers who did not accommodate the missed classes made it difficult for pregnant students. Iris talked about this:<disp-quote>
<p>I was out of school a lot [because] it was a very bad pregnancy. Some of the teachers accepted it; some made my life very hard. They wouldn’t let me do the work. They’d say I had to have it in the day after I got there and there’d be like six classes that I’d have one night’s homework plus the last two days that I wasn’t there and it was just very hard and they didn’t seem to understand.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Iris never returned to school after she delivered and later enrolled in a night school course to earn her diploma.</p>
<p>Hostile school environments were created by uncomfortable school infrastructures, inflexible policies and teachers, morally condemning personnel, and the absence of on-site child care. Without some allowances, these students found it physically difficult to attend school. These barriers forced some students to drop out of high school and others to enroll in GED programs and night classes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0160597611433269">
<title>Accommodating School Environments</title>
<p>Just as hostile personnel and lack of child care created barriers for pregnant and mothering students, the opposite was also true. For example, Chery, born in Connecticut and raised by a “Jamaican strict” mother, got pregnant at age 16. She was shocked, “I wanted to finish high school, you know, go to college, go away to New York and go to school.” Her mother was also disappointed; she had Chery at 16 years of age, and as Chery said, they “had <italic>that </italic>conversation fifty times before I got pregnant!” Chery graduated with her class without missing even a semester of work (the baby was born in June). Her math teacher (who had also taught her mother) was an advocate for her and strongly encouraged her to stay in school as did as a school counselor who helped her. In addition, she family and community who provided child care. Her mother was actively involved in supervising her homework and interacting with school officials. At the time of the interview, her child was one year old and Chery was working as a nursing assistant and attending college part time.</p>
<p>Like Chery, teen mothers who stayed in school tended to be well integrated in school before they became pregnant, and they had institutional and familial support around child care needs. Students who stayed in school often had an advocate for them inside the school—teacher, school nurse, advisor, administrator, or counselor—who mediated between the needs of the pregnant and mothering students (to come to school late, complete assignments late, be excused for long periods, receive assignments at home) and the duties of the teacher (to teach and evaluate the students). Keisha raved about a counselor who “was so nice, really cool” because he helped her manage her classes and arranged for tutors around the time of the delivery when she was out of school for a month.</p>
<p>Adequate child care and transportation helped these mothers stay in school. An on-site child care program was the ideal situation. For example, Ivalesse had a child care program in her school, her parents helped her with child care in the evening so she could do her homework, and her family owned a car so they were able to drive her to and from school. Nita was able to return to school after her pregnancy because a bus picked up her and her child (there is a special car seat for him), and her son was in a child care program at school. These programs allowed mothers to have regular contact with their children.</p>
<p>Most important was that these mothers were not failing academically nor were they socially marginalized before they became pregnant. Having a child reinforced their plans to complete high school and, without major barriers, and with a little help, they could realize these goals.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0160597611433269">
<title>Alternative School Programs for Pregnant and Mothering Students</title>
<p>Fourteen of the students attended some alternative school or program for young parents housed in locations off the school grounds, or in a separate wing of the school building. The race and ethnicity of those attending these alternative schools reflected the racial/ethnic makeup of our sample population (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0160597611433269">Table 4</xref>). This included three white, five Puerto Rican, three African American, two biracial, and one Asian mother. Six of these mothers (all African American or Puerto Rican) lived in cities with populations over 100,000. At the time of the interview, three mothers had already completed high school and 11 were currently enrolled in school or a GED program. In 2007, there were 13 Adolescent Pregnancy Programs in Connecticut (also referred to as Teen Pregnancy Programs [TPP] and Young Parent Programs [YPP]) serving pregnant or parenting adolescents and their partners, whether they were in or out of school. These programs, introduced in the early 1990s, were designed “to prevent initial and repeat pregnancies, assure healthy birth outcomes, and promote self-sufficiency among the teen population.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0160597611433269">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0160597611433269" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Racial/Ethnic Identity of Students in Alternative Programs</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0160597611433269" xlink:href="10.1177_0160597611433269-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Total Sample Number (% of Sample)</th>
<th>Alternative Programs Number (% of Sample)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Puerto Rican</td>
<td>22 (36)</td>
<td>5 (36)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>White</td>
<td>14 (23)</td>
<td>3 (21)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>African American</td>
<td>12 (20)</td>
<td>3 (21)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mixed Racial</td>
<td>7 (11)</td>
<td>2 (14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>7 (11)</td>
<td>1 (7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>62 (100)</td>
<td>14 (100)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Many of the adolescent mothers who attended these programs spoke positively about their experiences. Roxanne said she stayed in school because “they had a Young Parents Program and so they had a small school bus that would come by and pick me up and bring me to school and bring me home.” She returned to the regular high school her senior year. At the time of the interview, she was taking Advanced Placement courses (Algebra and English 4) and planned to attend a technical 4-year college the following year.</p>
<p>Some mothers who did not like regular high school thrived in the alternative programs. First, the alternative school helped manage the stigma of having “a big belly.” Several pregnant students spoke about feeling shame or humiliation in the regular school. An alternative program shielded them from the accusatory eyes of their peers. Lark said, “I didn’t want to go to high school pregnant so I started going to YPP.” Eden said that she “didn’t really like [high school] because I didn’t like being around people.” She said she liked the alternative school because “if you needed to eat right then and there, you can eat a snack, an apple or orange in class, give you a pillow to lay down, get comfortable basically.” She also liked the routines in the alternative school that conferred adult status: “You didn’t need no parent or no guardian to sign you out of school. You sign out of school yourself and go handle your business, like if you got a WIC appointment for your milk or something like that, I would sign myself out. I didn’t have to call my grandmother. They just go by your word.” She also found that the alternative school “definitely helped you get your grades up so you won’t stay back.”</p>
<p>Rosa also liked the alternative program. “It was fun,” “the best school I ever went to.” She said, “when you are pregnant you have certain needs that they won’t tolerate in regular school. If you are sick they don’t care.” Prior to the pregnancy, she was attending a large urban high school and she had numerous conflicts with other students. As Rosa described, “the girl called me a name because of my best friend—she didn’t like her so she didn’t like me. I was just like ‘What is your problem? I don’t talk to you. Why do you have things to say about me?’ And it just erupted, a whole big thing in the middle of school.” The alternative school had none of this chaos or fighting. She stayed in the alternative program through the end of her junior year. When she was mainstreamed back into the regular high school she attended a new school in a different town. She could not bring her child with her and had to manage child care for herself. She began working “split shifts” at a fast food restaurant and a gas station while her son was cared for by her mother. “Between working and going to school,” she said, “I was just not physically capable of doing it and taking care of a child.” She quit and at the time of the interview she hoped to complete her high school education by doing course packets at home through an Adult Education program.</p>
<p>Mothers often attended YPP because they provided day care. Paloma was in the YPP for the last 3 months of her pregnancy and said, “I was doing good, but then when my baby was born I didn’t have anyone to babysit and they didn’t have an opening so I missed two months of school.” She returned as soon as space opened up and, like others, talked positively about the YPP, in particular it was small, personal, and addressed her individual needs.<disp-quote>
<p>It’s just easier for you. They have food all the time and it’s a more comfortable place to be. It’s a little house. You have to ring the door and say your name. They have daycare for your kids and there’s so few of us that we all communicate together and do everything together.</p>
</disp-quote>
Lark, a 15-year-old mother, also dropped out of school after she was mainstreamed back into a regular high school from a YPP.<disp-quote>
<p>I didn’t want to go in the high school pregnant [so] I started going to YPP. It’s the same thing like at high school but it’s just for pregnant girls. It was a smaller place so the class would be like four girls and one teacher, and you would do the same thing you was doing in the high school because I had all the same classes, all the same work. I found it easier because if I did all I had to do, then I could just go downstairs and eat, so it was easier to manage there than it was in the high school. And that school is like a house, like a three-floor house like this and downstairs is the childcare for the kids and the cafeteria, and then you walk up the stairs into the classrooms, and the third floor is like the library.</p>
<p>So I did that and after I gave birth and my daughter was like six months, they sent me back to the high school and then I just started messing up. I don’t know why. All my grades started going down. I started just slacking off for some apparent reason. I don’t know why. I felt like I couldn’t do my homework half the time cuz my daughter was a cranky baby and then she started getting sick on me a lot. She’s asthmatic and I would have to run back and forth to the hospital. That’s one of the reasons why I dropped out because they left her in the hospital for two weeks because of asthma so I would have to go to the high school and get pamphlets of homework, and I would do them, and when I go back I was like lost in-between because I wasn’t there for what was going on and then I would be late on exams that I had to do and it was just a bunch of crap so that’s hard.</p>
</disp-quote>
The alternative school worked for Lark when she was pregnant, but she had problems reentering high school after her child was born, especially because her child suffered from asthma and was in and out of the hospital.</p>
<p>Only one mother spoke negatively about her experiences in the alternative young parent program. Haylee, a white mother who gave birth to twins when she was 16 years old, was well integrated in her high school before her pregnancy. She attended the alternative program after delivering twins because it provided childcare. Because the program was located in a separate wing of the school, she said it was not as “fun” as high school where “between classes when the halls were all crowded it was exciting and I’d just see my friends and stuff.” In the regular school, Haylee said, “you could hang around with your friends in the hallways and stuff, but over at the Teen Parent Program you were like in this one room with all your books all day.” She felt isolated and stigmatized by the program. She said that she was forced to get “special permission” to attend the prom because the vice principal said that “the Teen Parent Program was not part of the school” even though it was housed in the same building.</p>
<p>Haylee was in college preparatory courses before she became pregnant. She made “high honors” her freshman year and “honors” her sophomore year. She took two years of “Honors Spanish” and she “made the Spanish National Honor Society.” She could not continue her language studies in the alternative program because “they don’t have elective classes over at the Teen Parent Program.” She also identified the instructional disparities when describing her sophomore English class at the regular high school.<disp-quote>
<p>The teacher was really strict, so a lot of people dropped that class. I stuck it out and I think I got a B+ and I’m usually an A student in English, but she had some hard stuff but that was good because it taught me a lot more about English. In the Teen Parent Program there wasn’t much English at all. Not at all. They had like grammar packets—you had to do like underline and circle stuff like prepositional phrases and just a whole bunch of crazy stuff—but the English in my sophomore year, she made us do like a research paper, and you had to do citations and things like that and it was like a five-page research paper, and I think that is what prepped me for like college. I think that’s the only thing because that’s what I remember more than any of the other stuff that I did after because the work was easy.</p>
</disp-quote>
Haylee gave birth in August, entered the TPP immediately after, and completed her junior and senior course work “packets” in one year. She said she just put her head down and “got my work done because it was boring.” She finished the TPP as quickly as possible and the following year she enrolled in a community college.</p>
<p>In general, most of the pregnant and mothering students who attended the alternative programs commented on the physical comforts, smaller classrooms, and less restrictive gatekeeping routines. For Haylee, however, the program provided an inferior education. While she did receive on-site child care—the reason she attended—she was deprived of a fuller educational experience.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0160597611433269">
<title>Discussion: Fragile Students and Fragile Schools</title>
<p>As others have found, these life-story narratives show how social and economic disadvantages contribute to school failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0160597611433269">Furstenberg 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0160597611433269">Luker 1996</xref>). Teen mothers who dropped out of school were already failing school or marginalized before pregnancy suggesting that school outcomes after pregnancy were related to school performance before pregnancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0160597611433269">Leadbeater 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0160597611433269">Upchurch and McCarthy 1990</xref>). While the added complications of having a child early can overwhelm already tenuous connections to school, the connection to school before the pregnancy is crucial. Those mothers doing well in school before the pregnancy continued to do well after having a child.</p>
<p>Students who dropped out were often from large urban school districts where a high percent of students fail, schools that Robert Balfanz refers to as “dropout factories.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0160597611433269">5</xref>
</sup> In 2007, there were 14 Connecticut schools listed as dropout factories.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0160597611433269">6</xref>
</sup> All three public high schools in Hartford were on that list, and two in Bridgeport. Nine of the eleven adolescent mothers living in Hartford dropped out of school and both of the mothers living in Bridgeport did. Hartford and Bridgeport are also the two poorest cities in Connecticut and graduation rates for these cities are no better than national graduation rates for adolescent mothers—almost one-half of students in the Hartford School District dropout and at least one-third do not have a GED certificate or a diploma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0160597611433269">Kuzyk 2003</xref>:17).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0160597611433269">7</xref>
</sup> The problems in these urban schools are extensive and influence the educational outcomes of all students, not just adolescent mothers (Eaton 2007).</p>
<p>Hostile school policies did weaken some students’ attachment to school. The complaints about physical barriers (desks, bathrooms, stairs), morally condemning personnel, inflexible absentee policies, and lack of on-site child care corroborate Wanda Pillow’s argument that adverse school policies push pregnant and mothering students out of school (2004, 2006; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0160597611433269">Burdell 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0160597611433269">Lesko 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0160597611433269">Luttrell 2003</xref>). Pushed out, several of the young mothers nonetheless worked to complete high school in night school or a GED program. Unfortunately, these programs are often less rigorous than high school, and as a result a GED certificate is perceived to be of less value than a diploma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0160597611433269">Hofferth et al. 2001</xref>). This suggests that inhospitable infrastructures, policies, and faculty that steer pregnant and mothering students out of regular school and into GED programs violate Title IX mandates to provide equal educational opportunities.</p>
<p>In contrast, several students spoke about friendly school environments that helped them stay attached to school. Particularly salient were the stories where at least one adult (e.g., Chery’s teacher) helped them and encouraged them to stay in school. They sent the young mothers the message that they belonged in school. Attachment theory suggests that when students form an attachments to adults, first at home and then at school, they are less likely to drop out (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0160597611433269">Hirschi 1969</xref>). Looking at the role of long-term mentors, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0160597611433269">Klaw, Rhodes, and Fitzgerald (2003</xref>) also found that an intervention by even one person was critical in helping adolescent African American mothers “beat the odds” academically.</p>
<p>These encouraging adults who created hospitable school environments were often the exception. Twice as many students spoke of hostile environments as those who mentioned explicitly that they received help to stay in school. This suggests that the feminist scholars are right to focus on the enduring gender discrimination that pregnant and mothering students face in school. Students were denied their legal right to make up assignments and exams, they were actively discouraged from attending the regular high school, and they were even ridiculed by faculty (e.g., Rosa was called out for “showing” her pregnancy by wearing a tight shirt). Schools continue to be hostile environments for young mothers, but not young fathers, underscoring the gender inequality that persists in the education system.</p>
<p>Regarding the forced versus voluntary nature of participation in the alternative programs, the narratives do not provide information to assess whether or not the 14 students voluntarily choose to attend the alternative programs or whether they were forced (and if child care is only provided in an alternative setting that may represent coercion). The narratives do show, however, that the alternative programs worked differently for different populations. Only one student, a white mother from a small town experienced the alternative program as isolating and the curriculum limited. In contrast, the other mothers valued the alternative programs because they provided services that their regular public high schools did not—transportation, child care, and easy access to food and bathrooms as well as more personal instruction, one-on-one attention, and counselors.</p>
<p>Do these alternative schools “isolate” or” ghettoize” pregnant and mothering students any more than their regular high schools? The urban schools in Connecticut are racially and economically segregated from the suburban schools. Rosa, describing her regular school in New Haven, said, “It was all black people, black and Puerto Rican mostly. And it was ghetto.” This also holds true for inner city schools in Bridgeport, Waterbury, and Hartford. In Hartford, over 90 percent of students in the public schools are racial minorities (minorities make up only 27 percent of the Connecticut population), and 75 percent are eligible for free and reduced lunches (in one of the wealthiest states in the nation).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0160597611433269">8</xref>
</sup> Those attending schools in large urban areas experienced de facto apartheid conditions; it was not the alternative school for pregnant and mothering students that isolated them but racial segregation.</p>
<p>The problems these young mothers face are rooted in deeper structural inequalities. This is evident in Lark’s story. She explains how she dropped out because she fell behind when the school did not accommodate her absences that resulted from the hospitalization of her child for asthma. The backdrop to her life story is the high prevalence of asthma among poor Hispanics living in urban areas in Connecticut: 48 percent of all Latino youth in Hartford had asthma in 2000, and one-half of all Hispanic households in Hartford reported that at least one family member had asthma in 2000.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0160597611433269">9</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Can we incriminate schools for not meeting the mandates of Title IX when they are not given the resources to do so? Schools in poor urban areas are inadequately funded to meet the needs of many of their students, not just pregnant and mothering students. Schools located in impoverished neighborhoods have students with more problems—like asthma rates—and yet their school districts have fewer resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0160597611433269">Kuzyk 2003</xref>:108). They do not have adequate remedial services, counseling services, art and sports programs, and bilingual classes (Eaton 2007). It is expensive to have an on-site child care program, home tutors, and buses that pick up the mother and child and bring them to school.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0160597611433269">10</xref>
</sup> When a student from a low-income neighborhood has a child, she adds stress to an already stressed system.</p>
<p>While schools without adequate funding for all students will have a difficult time accommodating students with special needs, it is important to stress that some of the mandates of Title IX do not require more funding, but simply—or perhaps not so simply—a change of attitude toward pregnant and mothering students to provide equitable school experiences for women. In some of the life stories, we continue to see the insidious gender discrimination based on misogynous construction of pregnant and mothering students as deviants? Why is it considered “indecent” to show a pregnant extended belly at school? What attitudes underscore the desire to conceal the pregnant students in alternative programs? Why do pregnant bodies not belong in student bodies? It does not cost money to provide keys to elevators, to allow students with swollen ankles to arrive a few minutes late to class, or even to allow students with morning sickness the option of being able to eat during class. The raised eyebrows, tsk-tsk dismissals, and insensitive commands to “just hold it” send these young women the message that they do not belong in the classroom, at the prom, or in the Honor Society. Schools are required, by law, to create a culture that does not stigmatize pregnant and mothering students, and without discounting the larger structural realities, the narratives of too many of the young mothers in this study suggest that they still experience hostile school environments. Even when the nastiness is perpetrated by her peers, schools have some responsibility to protect these students in the same way that they have a responsibility to take a stand against bullying.</p>
<p>In addition to the individual and organizational gender discrimination, the problems these young mothers face represent structural gender inequality. This is most evident in the case of child care—one of the most common reasons young mothers leave school. Child care in this country is woefully inadequate for most mothers—not just adolescent mothers—with problems related to accessibility, affordability, and quality of care. One recent study looking at the demands for child care in the Washington metropolitan region found that the lack and high cost of care was a problem for the majority of single working mothers (Portraits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0160597611433269">Project 2010</xref>:41). In Hartford, in 2005, there were a total of 545 day care slots available for the 4,267 children born in 2004–2005, and only eight openings reserved for the 881 children born to teenage mothers in 2004–2005.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0160597611433269">11</xref>
</sup> New Britain High School had 50 pregnant students in 2006, but there was no child care program in the high school. Moreover, the city of New Britain had only seven licensed day care slots per 100 infants and toddlers (costing on average $200 a week), and the state Care4Kids program that provided child care subsidies was already overenrolled and not accepting new participants (A Blue Print 2010). If we as a society cannot provide adequate child care, why do we expect underfunded overstressed schools to provide it? To focus on the adolescent mothers or impoverished urban schools as the source of the problem overlooks the larger structural inequalities that cry out for national solutions.</p>
<p>Studies warning against the negative consequences of early child birth distract us from looking at the problems that started long before the pregnancies, problems that are embedded in historical, institutional, and social inequalities. Violations of Title IX mandates in these school districts represent gender inequality, but this inequality is embedded within a matrix of racial and economic inequality. When our attention shifts from teenage mothers to the problems of underfunded and overburdened schools, we are confronted with the larger systemic problems of educational inequality.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The author would like to thank Timothy Black, Karen Hansen, Heili Pals, and Fiona Pearson for reviewing early versions of this article, as well as the reviewers for <italic>Humanity and Society,</italic> Crystallee Crain, Kathleen Fitzgerald, and Gina Petonito whose helpful comments made this a stronger article.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0160597611433269">
<p>Earlier versions of this article were presented at the Eastern Sociological Society meetings (2008) and the Association for Humanist Sociology meetings (2010).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn3-0160597611433269">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn4-0160597611433269">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research was funded by the Children’s Trust Fund, now a division of the Department of Social Services of the state of Connecticut.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0160597611433269">
<label>1</label>
<p>Between 1967 and 1970, the New York Department of Education opened six schools for pregnant and parenting mothers. They closed the remaining four schools in 2007. In their place, the Living for Young Families through Education (LYFE) programs provided services in 40 sites citywide (NYCLU 2009).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0160597611433269">
<label>2</label>
<p>For a full description, see Black, Erdmans, and Dickinson 2004.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0160597611433269">
<label>3</label>
<p>Of interest is that, although Danielle had lived her whole life in Connecticut, she told us her primary language was Spanish and we conducted the interview in Spanish. In school, however, she was not enrolled in bilingual courses.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0160597611433269">
<label>4</label>
<p>(http://www.dph.state.ct.us/OPPE/ch1994.html#Familyhlth, acc. 3-27-07) The programs were based in four hospitals (in Bridgeport, Meriden, Middletown, and Milford), two schools (in New Haven and New London), and seven community agencies (in Bristol, Danielson, New Britain, Norwich, Stamford, Waterbury, and Willimantic). </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0160597611433269">
<label>5</label>
<p>“Dropout factories” are schools where no more than 60 percent of freshman get to their senior year. </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0160597611433269">
<label>6</label>
<p>“14 Conn. Schools on Dropout Factory List” http://www.wfsb.com/education/14455600/detail.html, accessed November 16, 2010.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0160597611433269">
<label>7</label>
<p>Graduate rates are slippery numbers and generally any number a school district posts is underestimated.“The figure is supposed to exclude students who transfer; die; are expelled and are not receiving educational services; are sent to prison, a juvenile facility, or a mental institution; skip a grade in mid-year; or are held back as of August 29, 1998. The State Department of Education's instructions also describe how to calculate cumulative 4-year drop-out rates” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0160597611433269">Lohman 1999</xref>). </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0160597611433269">
<label>8</label>
<p>Data on the Hartford School District come from Connecticut State Department of Education in accordance with CT General Statutes 10-220<sup>©</sup>. <italic>Strategic School Profile, 2005-</italic>06. In 2002–2003 school year, 95 percent of students were eligible for free or reduced lunches; in the 2005–2006 school year, this dropped to 68 percent. The total black and Hispanic student population was 93.1 percent in the 2005–2006 school year.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0160597611433269">
<label>9</label>
<p>
<italic>High Rates of Asthma</italic> 2000. http://www.hartford.gov/HealthyHartford/Asthma/AsthmaConcern.htm accessed on January 13, 2010. </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0160597611433269">
<label>10</label>
<p>It cost over a $135,000 simply to hire three staff members for an eight slot child care center in Hartford (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0160597611433269">Mozdzer 2009</xref>). </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0160597611433269">
<label>11</label>
<p>Connecticut Registration Reports, CT Department of Public Health, Vital Records, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0160597611433269">Table 4</xref>, p. 16, 2004 and 2005. All eight slots were at the Little Owls Learning Center at Hartford Public High School (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0160597611433269">Mozdzer 2009</xref>). </p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berglas</surname>
<given-names>Nancy</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brindis</surname>
<given-names>Claire</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>Joel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Adolescent Pregnancy and Childbearing in California</source>. <publisher-loc>Sacramento</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>California Research Bureau</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bertaux</surname>
<given-names>Daniel</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kohli</surname>
<given-names>Martin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <article-title>“The Life Story Approach: A Continental View.”</article-title> <source>American Review of Sociology</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beutel</surname>
<given-names>Ann M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>“The Relationship Between Adolescent Nonmarital Childbearing and Educational Expectations: A Cohort and Period Comparison.”</article-title> <source>The Sociological Quarterly</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bickel</surname>
<given-names>Robert</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>Susan</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>Tony</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lange</surname>
<given-names>Linda</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <article-title>“Opportunity, Community, and Teen Pregnancy in an Appalachian State.”</article-title> <source>The Journal of Educational Research</source> <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bissell</surname>
<given-names>Mary</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>“Socio-Economic Outcomes of Teen Pregnancy and Parenthood: A Review of the Literature.”</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Human Sexuality</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>Timothy</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erdmans</surname>
<given-names>Mary Patrice</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dickinson</surname>
<given-names>Kristina</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Life Stories of Vulnerable Families in Connecticut: An Assessment of the Nurturing Families Network Home Visitation Program. </source>West Hartford, CT: Center for Social Research, University of Hartford.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>Blueprint for Improving the Lives of New Britain’s Young Children Birth through Third Grade</source>. <year>2010</year>. <publisher-loc>New Britain, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New Britain Early Childhood Collaborative</publisher-name>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bridgeland</surname>
<given-names>John M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DiIulio</surname>
<given-names>John J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morison</surname>
<given-names>Karen Burke</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <source>The Silent Epidemic: Perspectives of High School Drop Outs</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Civic Enterprises</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burdell</surname>
<given-names>Patricia</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>“Young Mothers as High School Students: Moving Toward a New Century.”</article-title> <source>Education and Urban Society</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Butler</surname>
<given-names>Amy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1992</year>. “<article-title>The Changing Economic Consequences of Teenage Childbearing</article-title>.” <source>Social Science Review</source> <volume>March</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Corcoran</surname>
<given-names>Jacqueline</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>“Consequences of Adolescent Pregnancy/Parenting: A Review of the Literature.”</article-title> <source>Social Work in Health Care</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eaton</surname>
<given-names>Susan</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>The Children in Room E4: American Education on Trial</source>. <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Algonquin Books of North Carolina</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fessler</surname>
<given-names>Ann</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <source>The Girls Who Went Away: The Hidden History of Women Who Surrendered Children for Adoption in the Decades Before Roe V. Wade</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fine</surname>
<given-names>Michelle</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1991</year>. <source>Framing Dropouts: Notes on the Politics of an Urban Public High School</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Furstenberg</surname>
<given-names>Frank F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <source>Destinies of the Disadvantaged: The Politics of Teenage Childbearing</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Furstenberg</surname>
<given-names>Frank F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brooks-Gunn</surname>
<given-names>Jeanne</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>S. Phillip,</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1987</year>. <source>Adolescent Mothers in Later Life</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geronimus</surname>
<given-names>Arline T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>“Damned If You Do: Culture, Identity, Privilege, and Teenage Childbearing in the United States.”</article-title> <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source> <volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geronimus</surname>
<given-names>Arline T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Korenman</surname>
<given-names>Sanders</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1992</year>. <article-title>“The Socioeconomic Consequences of Teen Childbearing Reconsidered.”</article-title> <source>The Quarterly Journal of Economics</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>Courtney P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>“Adolescent Decision Making: A Broadly Based Theory and Its Application to the Prevention of Early Pregnancy.”</article-title> <source>Adolescence</source> <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hamilton</surname>
<given-names>Brady E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>Joyce A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ventura</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Births: Final Data for 2007. National Vital Statistics Reports</source> <volume>57</volume>(<issue>12</issue>). <publisher-loc>Hyattsville, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirschi</surname>
<given-names>Travis</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1969</year>. <source>Causes of Delinquency</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hofferth</surname>
<given-names>Sandra L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>Lori</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mott</surname>
<given-names>Frank</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>“The Effects of Early Childbearing on Schooling over Time.”</article-title> <source>Family Planning Perspectives</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hotz</surname>
<given-names>Joseph V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McElroy</surname>
<given-names>Susan Williams</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sanders</surname>
<given-names>Seth G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>“Consequences of Teen Childbearing for Mothers Through 1993.”</article-title> <fpage>Pp. 52</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage> in <source>Kids Having Kids: Economic Costs and Social Consequences of Teen Pregnancy</source>, <comment>edited by</comment> <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Hoffman</surname>
<given-names>S. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maynard</surname>
<given-names>R. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-name>Washington, DC</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>The Urban Institute Press</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>Deirdre M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <source>Pregnant with Meaning: Teen Mothers and the Politics of Inclusive Schooling</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klaw</surname>
<given-names>Elena L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rhodes</surname>
<given-names>Jean E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
<given-names>Louise F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>“Natural Mentors in the Lives of African American Adolescent Mothers: Tracking Relationships Over Time.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Youth and Adolescence</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuzyk</surname>
<given-names>Ivan</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>A Hartford Primer &amp; Field Guide</source>, <publisher-name>2nd ed</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>Hartford, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cities Data Center at Trinity College</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leadbeater</surname>
<given-names>Bonnie J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>“School Outcomes for Minority-Group Adolescent Mothers at 28 to 36 Months Postpartum: A Longitudinal Follow-Up.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Research on Adolescence</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lesko</surname>
<given-names>Nancy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <article-title>“Curriculum Differentiation as Social Redemption:he Case of School-Aged Mothers.”</article-title> Pp. 113–136 in <source>Curriculum Differentiation: Interpretive Studies in U.S. Secondary School</source>, edited by R. Page and L. Valli. Albany, NY: State University of New York Press.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lesko</surname>
<given-names>Nancy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1995</year>. <article-title>“The ‘Leaky Needs’ of School-Aged Mothers: An Examination of U.S. Programs and Policies.”</article-title> <source>Curriculum Inquiry</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lohman</surname>
<given-names>Judith S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>“High School Drop-out Rate,”</article-title> <comment>OLR Report, February 24. Retrieved November 23, 2010</comment> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cga.ct.gov/ps99/rpt/olr">http://www.cga.ct.gov/ps99/rpt/olr</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luker</surname>
<given-names>Kristin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <source>Dubious Conceptions: The Politics of Teenage Pregnancy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luster</surname>
<given-names>Tom</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Small</surname>
<given-names>Stephen A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1994</year>. <article-title>“Factors Associated with Sexual Risk-Taking Behaviors among Adolescents.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marriage and the Family</source> <volume>56</volume>(<issue>August</issue>):<fpage>622</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luttrell</surname>
<given-names>Wendy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Pregnant Bodies, Fertile Minds: Gender, Race and the Schooling of Pregnant Teens</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manlove</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>“The Influence of High School Dropout and School Disengagement on the Risk of School Age Pregnancy.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Research on Adolescence</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marini</surname>
<given-names>Margaret Mooney</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <article-title>“Women’s Educational Attainment and the Timing of Entry into Parenthood.”</article-title> <source>American Sociological Review</source> <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McDade</surname>
<given-names>Laurie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1992</year>. <article-title>“Sex, Pregnancy, and Schooling: Obstacles to a Critical Teaching of the Body.”</article-title> Pp. 49-73 in <source>What Schools Can Do: Critical Pedagogy and Practice</source>, <publisher-loc>edited by K. Weiler and C.Mitchell. Albany,</publisher-loc> <publisher-name>NY: State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mozdzer</surname>
<given-names>Jodie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Day care Pressures</article-title>. <source>The Hartford Courant</source>, <volume>February 14</volume>, p. <fpage>A2</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">National Women’s Law Center</collab>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>“Two Sides of the Same Coin: Teen Pregnancy Prevention and Dropout Prevention.”</article-title> <comment>Retrieved March 10, 2010</comment> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ww.nwlc.org">http://ww.nwlc.org</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">NYCLU</collab>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>“Survey of New York City High School Admissions Practices Regarding Pregnant and Parenting Teens.”</article-title> <comment>Retrieved March 15, 2010</comment> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nyclu.org/news/survey-of-new-york-city-high-school-administration">http://www.nyclu.org/news/survey-of-new-york-city-high-school-administration</ext-link>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">NYCLU</collab>. <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Protecting Two Generations: The Need to Preserve and Expand Services for New York City’s Pregnant and Parenting Students</article-title>.” <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Reproductive Rights Project, New York Civil Liberties Union</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Perper</surname>
<given-names>Kate</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>Kristin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Manlove</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>“Diploma Attainment among Teen Mothers.”</article-title> <source>Child Trends Fact Sheet</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Child Trends</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Portraits Project</collab>. <year>2010</year>. <source>2010 Portrait of Women &amp; Girls in the Washington Metropolitan Area</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Washington Area Women’s Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pillow</surname>
<given-names>Wanda S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Unfit Subjects: Educational Policy and the Teen Mother</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pillow</surname>
<given-names>Wanda S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>“Teen Pregnancy and Education: Politics of Knowledge, Research, and Practice.”</article-title> <source>Educational Policy</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Records</surname>
<given-names>Kathryn A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1993</year>. <article-title>“Life Events of Pregnant and Nonpregnant Adolescents</article-title>.” <source>Adolescence</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scaramella</surname>
<given-names>Laura V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conger</surname>
<given-names>Rand D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Simons</surname>
<given-names>Ronald L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitbeck</surname>
<given-names>Les B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>“Predicting Risk for Pregnancy by Late Adolescence: A Social Contextual Perspective.”</article-title> <source>Developmental Psychology</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1233</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Teen Pregnancy and Education</collab>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>The National Campaign to Prevent Teen Pregnancy</article-title>. <comment>Retrieved January 10, 2010</comment> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thenationalcampaign.org/why-it-matters/pdf/education">http://www.thenationalcampaign.org/why-it-matters/pdf/education</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Upchurch</surname>
<given-names>Dawn M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>James</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <article-title>“The Timing of a First Birth and High School Completion.”</article-title> <source>American Sociological Review</source> <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>Gail A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rauh</surname>
<given-names>Virginia A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brunelli</surname>
<given-names>Susan A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garcia-Castro</surname>
<given-names>Maritza</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Necos</surname>
<given-names>Belkis</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <article-title>“Psychosocial Attributes and Life Experiences of Disadvantaged Minority Mothers: Age and Ethnic Variations.”</article-title> <source>Child Development</source> <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weis</surname>
<given-names>Lois</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Farrar</surname>
<given-names>Eleanor</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petrie</surname>
<given-names>Hugh G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <year>1989</year>. <source>Dropouts from School: Issues, Dilemma, and Solutions</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yampolskaya</surname>
<given-names>Svetlana</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Eric C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenbaum</surname>
<given-names>Paul E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>“Early Pregnancy among Adolescent Females with Serious Emotional Disturbances: Risk Factors and Outcomes.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Emotional &amp; Behavioral Disorders</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0160597611433269">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zellman</surname>
<given-names>Gail L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1981</year>. <source>The Response of the Schools to Teenage Pregnancy and Parenthood</source>. <comment>Report prepared for the National Institute of Education</comment>. <publisher-name>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Rand</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>