<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spach</journal-id>
<journal-title>Accounting History</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1032-3732</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1749-3374</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1032373213482556</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1032373213482556</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Publication list/Ad hoc referees list</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Accounting History: Publication List 2012</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1032373213482556">University of Ballarat, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>281</fpage>
<lpage>284</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The list of selected publications, including book reviews, published in English is intended to assist accounting history researchers and those with an interest in accounting history scholarship to gain an appreciation of recent contributions to the literature. It is not intended to be an exhaustive listing and the exclusion of a publication from the list is not a reflection of the quality or potential contribution of the publication. Rather, the items listed may be viewed as indicative of the types of research conducted over the period.</p>
<sec id="section1-1032373213482556">
<title>Articles</title>
<p>Accominotti O (2012) London merchant banks, the central European panic and the sterling crisis of 1931. <italic>The Journal of Economic History</italic> 72(1): 1–43.</p>
<p>Acheson GG, Turner JD and Ye Q (2012) The character and denomination of shares in the Victorian equity market. <italic>Economic History Review</italic> 65(3): 862–886.</p>
<p>Baker R and Rennie MD (2012) Accounting for a nation’s beginnings: Challenges arising from the formation of the Dominion of Canada. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17 (3&amp;4): 415–435.</p>
<p>Baños Sánchez-Matamoros J and Gutiérrez Hidalgo F (2012) Accounting for the production of coins: The enactment and implementation of the Spanish Ordinances of the Mints, 1730. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 351–367.</p>
<p>Bell S (2012) ‘A masterpiece of knavery’? The activities of the Sword Blade Company in London’s early financial markets. <italic>Business History</italic> 54(4): 623–638.</p>
<p>Bignon V, Flandreau M and Ugolini S (2012) Bagehot for beginners: The making of lender-of-last-resort operations in the mid-nineteenth century. <italic>Economic History Review</italic> 65(2): 580–608.</p>
<p>Bisman JE (2012a) Surveying the landscape: The first 15 years of <italic>Accounting History</italic> as an international journal. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(1): 5–34.</p>
<p>Bisman JE (2012b) Budgeting for famine in Tudor England, 1527-1528: Social and policy perspectives. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(2): 105–126.</p>
<p>Blancheton B (2012) The false balance sheets of the Bank of France and the origins of the Franc crisis, 1924-26. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(1): 1–22.</p>
<p>Buhr N (2012) Accrual accounting by Anglo-American governments: Motivations, developments, and some tensions over the last 30 years. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 287–309.</p>
<p>Burrows G and Chenhall RH (2012) Target costing: First and second comings. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(2): 127–142.</p>
<p>Camfferman K (2012) A contract-law perspective on legal cases in financial reporting: The Netherlands, 1880-1970. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 141–173.</p>
<p>Carnegie GD and Napier CJ (2012) Accounting’s past, present and future: The unifying power of history. <italic>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal</italic> 25(2): 328–369.</p>
<p>Carnegie GD and O’Connell BT (2012) Understanding the responses of professional accounting bodies to crises: The case of the Australian profession in the 1960s. <italic>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal</italic> 25(5): 835–875.</p>
<p>Chandar N, Collier D and Miranti P (2012) Graph standardization and management accounting at AT&amp;T during the 1920s. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(1): 35–62.</p>
<p>Collier DM (2012) A contextual analysis of the development and diffusion of depreciation accounting at the Bell System, 1910-37. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(1): 23–45.</p>
<p>Cordery CJ (2012) Funding social services: An historical analysis of responsibility for citizens’ welfare in New Zealand. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 463–480.</p>
<p>Czarniawska B (2012) Accounting and detective stories: An excursion to the USA in the 1940s. <italic>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal</italic> 25(4); 659–672.</p>
<p>Degos JG and Mattessich R (2012) German and French writers: Some relevant alternatives to IAS-IFRS conceptual framework. <italic>International Journal of Critical Accounting</italic> 4(4): 380–400.</p>
<p>Demirag I (2012) Regulatory regime change in Turkish banks: Reactive or proactive? <italic>Accounting Forum</italic> 36(1): 62–80.</p>
<p>Duff A and Ferguson J (2012) Disability and the professional accountant: Insights from oral histories. <italic>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal</italic> 25(1): 71–101.</p>
<p>Dyball MC and Rooney J (2012) Re-visiting the interface between race and accounting: Filipino workers at the Hamakua Mill Company, 1921-1939. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 221–240.</p>
<p>Farcas T, Tiron Tudor A, Matis D and Tinker T (2012) European accounting history: The contribution of Professor I.N. Evian - precursor to the development of accounting in Romania. <italic>International Journal of Critical Accounting</italic> 4(4): 466–479.</p>
<p>Fujimura D (2012) The old Du Pont company’s accounting system lasting a hundred years: An overlooked accounting system. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(1): 53–88.</p>
<p>Giroux G (2012) Financing the American Civil War: Developing new tax sources. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(1): 83–104.</p>
<p>Guidi-Bruscoli F (2012) John Cabot and his Italian financiers. <italic>Historical Research</italic> 85(229): 372–393.</p>
<p>Halabi AK, Frost L and Lightbody M (2012) Football history off the field: Utilising archived accounting reports to challenge “myths” about the history of an Australian football club. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(1): 63–81.</p>
<p>Hammond T, Clayton BM and Arnold PJ (2012) An “unofficial” history of race relations in the South African accounting industry, 1968-2000: Perspectives of South Africa’s first black chartered accountants. <italic>Critical Perspectives On Accounting</italic> 23(4&amp;5): 332–350.</p>
<p>Hilt E and Valentine J (2012) Democratic dividends: Stockholding, wealth and politics in New York, 1791-1826. <italic>The Journal of Economic History</italic> 72(2): 332–363.</p>
<p>Hollingsworth K (2012) Examining Frank Adair Jr. as an African American CPA pioneer: A historical note. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(2): 81–95.</p>
<p>Ikin C, Johns L and Hayes C (2012) Field, capital and habitus: An oral history of women in accounting in Australia during World War II. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 175–192.</p>
<p>Irvine H (2012) A genealogy of calculations at an early Queensland sugar mill. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 193–219.</p>
<p>Jackson WJ (2012) ‘The collector will call’: Controlling philanthropy through the annual reports of the Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh, 1837-1856. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(1): 47–72.</p>
<p>Jackson WJ, Paterson AS, Pong CKM and Scarparo S (2012) “How easy can the barley brie”: Drinking culture and accounting failure at the end of the nineteenth century in Britain. <italic>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal</italic> 25(4): 635–658.</p>
<p>Kirsh RJ (2012) The evolution of the relationship between the US Financial Accounting Standards Board and the international accounting standard setters: 1973-2008. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(1): 1–51.</p>
<p>Johns L and Ville S (2012) Banking records, business and networks in colonial Sydney, 1817-24. <italic>Australian Economic History Review</italic> 52(2): 167–190.</p>
<p>Lai A, Leoni G and Stacchezzini R (2012) Governmentality rationales and calculative devices: The rejection of a seventeenth-century territorial barter proposed by the King of Spain. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 369–392</p>
<p>Lee TA (2012) ‘A helpless class of shareholder’: Newspapers and the City of Glasgow Bank failure. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(2): 143–159.</p>
<p>Lee TA and Wolnizer PW (2012) An intellectual memorial to Robert Raymond Sterling, accounting reformer. <italic>Accounting Horizons</italic> 26(1): 135–146.</p>
<p>Levant Y and Nikitin M (2012) Can cost and financial accounting be fully re-integrated? The role of the French state in the separation of accounting systems and the failed attempt of the <italic>système croisé</italic> to re-integrate them. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 437–461.</p>
<p>Maltby J (2012) ‘To bind the humbler to the more influential and wealthy classes’. Reporting by savings banks in nineteenth century Britain. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(3): 199–225.</p>
<p>Miley F and Read A (2012) The implications of supply accounting deficiencies in the Australian Army during the Second World War. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(1): 73–91.</p>
<p>Narayan AK (2012) The role of government and accounting in the development of academic research commercialization: The New Zealand experience. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 311–329.</p>
<p>Noguchi M and Boyns T (2012) The development of budgets and their use for purposes of control in Japanese aviation, 1928-1945: The role of the state. <italic>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal</italic> 25(3): 416–451.</p>
<p>Nurnberg H (2012) Objectives of financial reporting, aboriginal cost, and pooling of interests accounting. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(2): 45–80.</p>
<p>Ó hÓgartaigh C, Ó hÓgartaigh M and Tyson T (2012) ‘Irish property should pay for Irish poverty’: Accounting for the poor in pre-famine Ireland. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(3): 227–248.</p>
<p>Öhman P and Wallerstedt E (2012) Audit regulation and the development of the auditing profession: The case of Sweden. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 241–257.</p>
<p>Parker RH (2012) The contingent career path of the young George O May in Bliss J, Jago C and Maycock C (eds) <italic>Aspects of Devon history, people, places and landscape</italic> 293–303. Exeter: Devon History Society</p>
<p>Praquin N (2012) Commercial legislation and the emergence of corporate auditing in France, 1856-1935. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(2): 161–189.</p>
<p>Richard J (2012) The victory of the Prussian railway “dynamic” accounting over the public finance and patrimonial accounting models (1838-1884): An early illustration of the appearance of the second stage of capitalist financial accounting and a testimony against the agency and the market for excuses theories. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(1): 91–126.</p>
<p>Robertson J and Funnell W (2012) The Dutch East-India Company and accounting for social capital at the dawn of modern capitalism 1602-1623. <italic>Accounting, Organizations and Society</italic> 37(5): 342–360.</p>
<p>Roybark HM, Coffman EN and Previts GJ (2012a) The first quarter century of the GASB (1984-2009): A perspective on standard setting (part one). <italic>Abacus</italic> 48(1): 1–30.</p>
<p>Roybark HM, Coffman EN and Previts GJ (2012b) The first quarter century of the GASB (1984-2009): A perspective on standard setting (part two). <italic>Abacus</italic> 48(2): 147–198.</p>
<p>Ryan JB (2012) Canning’s legacy. <italic>International Journal of Critical Accounting</italic> 4(4): 401–432.</p>
<p>Sangster A (2012) Locating the source of Pacioli’s bookkeeping treatise. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(2): 97–110.</p>
<p>Sangster A, Stoner G, De Lange P, O’Connell B and Scataglini-Belghitar G (2012) Pacioli’s forgotten book: The merchant’s <italic>Ricordanze. Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(2): 27–44.</p>
<p>Sargiacomo M, Servalli S and Andrei P (2012) Fabio Besta: Accounting thinker and accounting history pioneer. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(3): 249–267.</p>
<p>Sargiacomo M, Servalli S and Carnegie GD (2012) Accounting for killing: Accountability for death. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 393–413.</p>
<p>Sharma U, Lawrence S and Fowler C (2012) New public management and accounting in a Fiji telecommunications company. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 331–349.</p>
<p>Vosslamber R (2012a) Taxation for New Zealand’s future: The introduction of New Zealand’s progressive income tax in 1891. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(1): 105–122.</p>
<p>Vosslamber R (2012b) Narrating history: New Zealand’s “black budget” of 1958. <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 481–499.</p>
<p>Xue Q and Zan L (2012) Opening the door to accounting change. Transformations in Chinese public sector accounting. <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(3): 269–299.</p>
<p>Yamey BS (2012) Personal accounts, account books and their probative value: Historical notes, c.1200 to c.1800. <italic>Accounting Historians Journal</italic> 39(2): 1–26.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1032373213482556">
<title>Book Reviews</title>
<p>Bátiz-Lazo B, Maixé-Altés JC and Thomas P (eds) (2010) <italic>Technological innovation in retail finance: International historical perspectives.</italic> Abingdon: Routledge, in <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 259–261, by M Noguchi.</p>
<p>Bensadon D (2010) <italic>Les comptes de groupe en France (1929–1985). Origines, enjeux et pratiques de la consolidation des comptes.</italic> Rennes: Presses Universitaires de Rennes, in <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(1): 99–100, by RH Parker.</p>
<p>Capie F (2010) <italic>The Bank of England, 1950s to 1979.</italic> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, in <italic>Financial History Review</italic> 19(1): 119-121, by D Cobham, and in <italic>Business History</italic> 54(2): 285–286 by R Middleton.</p>
<p>Carey D and Finlay CJ (eds) (2011) <italic>The empire of credit: The financial revolution in Britain, Ireland and America, 1688-1815</italic>, Dublin and Portland OR: Irish Academic Press, in <italic>The Journal of Economic History</italic> 72(3): 850–851, by L Neal.</p>
<p>Cassis Y (2010) <italic>Capitals of capital: The rise and fall of international financial centres 1780-2009.</italic> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, in <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(2): 263–264, by B Bátiz-Lazo.</p>
<p>Finel-Honigman I (2009) <italic>A cultural history of finance.</italic> Abingdon: Routledge, in <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(2): 193–195, by J Rutterford.</p>
<p>Gleeson-White J (2011) <italic>Double entry: How the merchants of Venice shaped the modern world and how their invention could make or break the planet.</italic> Sydney: Allen and Unwin, in <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(3&amp;4): 501–510, by A Sangster.</p>
<p>Green D, Maltby J, Owens A and Rutterford J (eds) (2011) <italic>Men, women and money. Perspectives on gender, wealth and investment, 1859-1930.</italic> Oxford: Oxford University Press, in <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(3): 307–309, by RJ Morris.</p>
<p>Jones M (2010) <italic>Creative accounting, fraud and international scandals.</italic> Chichester: John Wiley, in <italic>British Accounting Review</italic> 44(3): 204, by TA Lee.</p>
<p>Lloyd-Jones R, Maltby J, Lewis MJ and Matthews MD (2011) <italic>Personal capitalism and corporate governance: British manufacturing in the first half of the twentieth century</italic>. Farnham: Ashgate Publishing, in <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(2): 191–193, by S McKinstry.</p>
<p>Katsari C (2011) <italic>The Roman monetary system: The eastern provinces from the first to the third century AD</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, in <italic>The Journal of Economic History</italic> 72(2): 544–546, by A Redish.</p>
<p>Kindleberger CP and Aliber ZR (2011) <italic>Manias, panics and crashes: A history of financial crises.</italic> (6<sup>th</sup> ed) New York: Palgrave Macmillan, in <italic>Economic History Review</italic> 65(4): 1609–1611, by R Michie.</p>
<p>Soll J (2009) <italic>The information master: Jean-Baptiste Colbert’s secret state intelligence system.</italic> Michigan: The University of Michigan Press, in <italic>Accounting History Review</italic> 22(1): 101–103, by W Funnell.</p>
<p>Trow DG and Zeff SA (2010) <italic>Accounting education and the profession in New Zealand: Profiles of the pioneering academics and the early university accounting departments1900-1970</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, in <italic>Accounting History</italic> 17(1) 123–125, by C Fowler.</p>
<p>Walker S (2010) <italic>Building accounts of All Souls College Oxford 1438-1443, with supplementary material by Munby J.</italic> Oxford: Oxford Historical Society, in <italic>Economic History Review</italic> (65)4: 1571–1572, by J Langdon.</p>
<p>Zeff SA (2010) <italic>Insights from accounting history: Selected writings of Stephen Zeff.</italic> Abingdon: Routledge, in <italic>British Accounting Review</italic> 44(2): 127–128, by GJ Previts.</p>
<p>Zuijderduijn CJ (2009) <italic>Medieval capital markets; Markets for renten, state formation and private investment in Holland (1300-1550).</italic> Leiden and Boston: Brill, in <italic>The Journal of Economic History</italic> 72(3): 827–829, by D Chilosi.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>