<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spijo</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Offender Ther Comp Criminol</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Offender Therapy and Comparative Criminology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0306-624X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6933</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0306624X11422224</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0306624X11422224</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>“If He Had 40 Cents He’d Buy Matches Instead of Lollies”</article-title>
<subtitle>Motivational Factors in a Sample of New Zealand Adolescent Firesetters</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>Daniel P.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0306624X11422224">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lambie</surname><given-names>Ian</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0306624X11422224">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0306624X11422224">
<label>1</label>Psychology Department, University of Auckland, New Zealand</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0306624X11422224">Ian Lambie, Psychology Department, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland, New Zealand Email: <email>i.lambie@auckland.ac.nz</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>57</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>71</fpage>
<lpage>91</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Motivation has been proposed as an important factor in both the causality and subsequent treatment of juveniles who deliberately light fires. Thus, a wide range of research has previously been completed, investigating such motives. This research has resulted in the creation of classifications of firesetting motives and behaviours, all of which fit upon a continuum of motivational categories—ranging from curiosity or match play, through to deliberate delinquent acts. This current study aimed to gain insight into how both firesetters and their caregivers perceived firesetting motivation. A total of 18 male youths, who had engaged in deliberate firesetting, and 13 parents were interviewed. Qualitative analysis gathered from interviews with adolescent participants reported personality and individual characteristic themes, the most frequent of these being <italic>anger, experimenting, peer pressure</italic>, and <italic>boredom</italic>. Parents on the other hand initially cited <italic>family historical factors</italic> as being a cause for their son’s firesetting. This study showed the difficulties in attempting to classify firesetters. It became clear that there were often multiple motivations involved in adolescent firesetting, meanwhile a variation of motivations were reported by parents and firesetters. The differences between and ambiguities inherent in existing motivational typologies also became evident. The study produced strong evidence for the effectiveness of utilising multiple sources to gain a comprehensive understanding as to why children deliberately light fires.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>arson</kwd>
<kwd>juvenile firesetting</kwd>
<kwd>delinquent behaviour</kwd>
<kwd>adolescents</kwd>
<kwd>behaviour motivation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0306624X11422224">
<title>Incidence and Prevalence</title>
<p>Firesetting behaviour has been found to occur in around 5% to 10% of children and adolescents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0306624X11422224">Chen, Arria, &amp; Anthony, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0306624X11422224">Dadds &amp; Fraser, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0306624X11422224">Martin, Bergen, Richardson, Roegar, &amp; Allison, 2004</xref>). However, higher prevalence rates of almost 30% have been reported in two recent adolescent community sample studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0306624X11422224">Del Bove, Caprara, Pastorelli, &amp; Paciello, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0306624X11422224">MacKay, Paglia-Boak, Henderson, Marton, &amp; Adlaf, 2009</xref>). Firesetting is a damaging and costly behaviour for which children and adolescents consistently account for a large percentage of offences in a range of national statistics. In New Zealand, for the year 2007-2008, those below 21 years accounted for 73% of all apprehensions for arson and those below 17 years for 55.6% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0306624X11422224">Statistics New Zealand, 2008</xref>). Similarly, in the United States, children aged 10 years or below account for a greater percentage of arson arrests than for any other crime, and approximately half of arson arrestees are below the age of 18 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0306624X11422224">Hall, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Although studies show extremely variant recidivism rates, high rates of repetitive firesetting have been found in recent adolescent community samples. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0306624X11422224">Mackay et al. (2009)</xref> found that just under 50% of those who reported firesetting stated they had set three or more fires in the past year. Meanwhile, another study found that at initial intake assessment, 40% of firesetters reported recurrent firesetting and 15% reported engagement in recidivism by follow-up (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0306624X11422224">Del Bove et al., 2008</xref>). Thus, the persistent nature of firesetting is evident.</p>
<p>One of the most consistent findings throughout the literature on the prevalence of juvenile firesetters is that males far outnumber females. Three early studies, based on state and national statistics in the United States, reported a ratio of nine males to every one female firesetter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0306624X11422224">Nurcombe, 1964</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0306624X11422224">Vandersall &amp; Weiner, 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0306624X11422224">Yarnell, 1940</xref>). Meanwhile, in a review of 22 descriptive studies, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0306624X11422224">Kolko (1985)</xref> found that 82% of the participants were male, and a recent range of community samples have found that firesetting is around 2 to 3 times more prevalent in boys than girls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0306624X11422224">Chen et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0306624X11422224">Del Bove et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0306624X11422224">Martin et al., 2004</xref>). There is some evidence that the gender ratio does not stay the same throughout childhood. For instance, authors using referrals to fire intervention programmes have found that females are represented at higher rates as adolescents, with close to 30% involvement reported in the 13- to 17-year age range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0306624X11422224">Porth, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0306624X11422224">Saunders &amp; Awad, 1991</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0306624X11422224">
<title>Models of Firesetting</title>
<sec id="section3-0306624X11422224">
<title>Early Formulations of Firesetting</title>
<p>Early formulations of firesetting were psychoanalytic in nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>). Firesetting was proposed to be the result of urethral-phallic fixated drives, often associated with masturbatory impulses. Block (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0306624X11422224">Lewis &amp; Yarnell, 1951</xref>) is reported to make a connection between fire and sexual behaviour: “All firesetting is a sadistic drive sexually coloured” (p. 437). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0306624X11422224">Freud (1905/1953)</xref> presented the case report of Dora and the interpretation of a dream where a house was on fire. This led him to suggest a link between sexual problems, enuresis, and firesetting. He later hypothesized his theory, proposing fire was symbolically expressive of libidinal and phallic-urethral drives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0306624X11422224">Freud, 1932</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0306624X11422224">
<title>Postpsychoanalytic Models of Firesetting</title>
<p>The first models that were not psychoanalytic in nature began to appear in the literature in the early 1980s. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0306624X11422224">Vreeland and Levin (1980)</xref> suggested a social learning theory model, explaining how social skill deficits of firesetters hinder the direct expression of aggression. They argue that firesetting may offer an individual control over a situation, without the need of interpersonal confrontation. According to their theory, the early modelling of fire-related behaviour such as that by adults (e.g., lighting camp fires, lighting barbeques, etc.), when combined with several maladaptive behaviour patterns, impacts on an individual’s propensity for subsequent firesetting behaviour.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1980)</xref> proposed a more complex dynamic behavioural model, which specified the interaction of environmental, historical, and antecedent variables. Historical factors, such as family dysfunction and school difficulties, would predispose a child toward antisocial behaviour. A child’s involvement in early match play (i.e., playing with matches that are used to light a fire) and the involvement of significant others with fire might act to reinforce a child’s fire-play behaviour. Immediate environmental stimuli, such as a negative life event, can also act as a trigger to initiate a firesetting event.</p>
<p>Another prevalent model of firesetting risk was presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0306624X11422224">Kolko and Kazdin (1986)</xref>, in an attempt to provide a basis for empirical research on firesetting. These authors presented three major domains of risk factors that may predispose a juvenile to be at risk for firesetting behaviour. The first domain, <italic>learning experiences and cues</italic>, includes early modelling, interests, cues, and incendiary materials as well as availability of current adult role models. The second domain, <italic>personal repertoire</italic>, is divided into cognitive abilities, such as a juvenile’s fire awareness and fire safety skills, behavioural skills (including interpersonal skills), and participation in covert antisocial behaviour. In the third domain, <italic>parent and family factors</italic>, factors such as supervision, level of parental involvement, external stressors, and parental pathology are included. Thus, this model is focused on environmental events in a juvenile’s life. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0306624X11422224">Jackson, Glass, and Hope (1987)</xref> proposed a model with very similar themes, but within a “functional analysis” framework. Thus antecedent events in the firesetters life, the firesetting behaviour specifically, and consequences arising from the firesetting behaviour are all influential for firesetting <italic>risk</italic> of an individual.</p>
<p>The models of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1980)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0306624X11422224">Kolko and Kazdin (1986)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0306624X11422224">Jackson, Glass and Hope (1987)</xref> all present the notion of multiple components combining to render a juvenile at risk. Thus, they demonstrate the shift from profiling firesetters on individual psychological variables only to testing the theory that personal and environmental factors interact to place an individual at risk for firesetting. A multifactor view of firesetting epidemiology remains predominant in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0306624X11422224">Del Bove, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1995</xref>) and is reflected in contemporary approaches to the assessment, treatment, and study of firesetters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0306624X11422224">Kolko 2002</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section5-0306624X11422224">
<title>Motivation for Firesetting Behaviour</title>
<p>Many attempts have been made to identify firesetting subtypes as a means of better understanding this diverse and complex population. The predominant approach is to classify firesetting individuals according to their reported motivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0306624X11422224">Stadolnik, 2000</xref>), such as those put forward by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden and Berkey (1984)</xref>:</p>
<list id="list1-0306624X11422224" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Curious (playing with matches)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Troubled (crying for help)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Delinquent</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pathological (severely disturbed)</p></list-item></list>
<p>Curious firesetters are characteristically 3 to 7 years old, impulsive, and described as “active and into everything.” Troubled or “cry for help” firesetters tend to be slightly older, are typically socially awkward, are poor at expressing their feelings, and many have experienced abuse. Delinquent firesetters are generally between 10 to 17 years and have poor interpersonal skills, a history of school and behavioural problems, and a disproportionate number meet criterion for conduct disorder. Finally, the pathologically motivated firesetter is typically 13 to 17 years old and often has a history of chronic cognitive or emotional deficit, resulting in poor interpersonal abilities and/or poor response to prior intervention. Cognitive functioning may also be compromised by psychotic phenomena, including hallucinations, delusions, and distorted thinking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0306624X11422224">Lambie &amp; Randell, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0306624X11422224">Stadolnik, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden and Berkey’s (1984)</xref> model presented a continuum, charting a range of juveniles—from those who have minimal concurrent psychosocial difficulty to those with major disturbance in their lives. A juvenile’s motive (e.g., curiosity or anger) for firesetting may be evident in their history of firesetting (recidivism), the severity of the firesetting incident, and/or the psychiatric and social maladjustment of the juvenile concerned (Kolko &amp; Kazdin, 1991a). According to this theory, juveniles involved in an isolated incident of firesetting as a result of experimentation will likely be motivated by curiosity, indicative of an individual who has a settled home life, is highly amenable to intervention, and feels remorseful or guilty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>One of the earliest typologies of firesetters was that proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1995)</xref>. Fineman proposed that there are two “nonpathological” firesetting subtypes (<italic>curiosity</italic> and <italic>accidental</italic>—both more likely to take occur in young children) and five “pathological” subtypes (<italic>cry for help, delinquent, severely disturbed, cognitively impaired, sociocultural</italic> and <italic>wildland).</italic></p>
<p>Another necessary consideration is that immediate antecedent factors may provide the primary motive for a firesetting incident or may act to compound a motive in a child at risk. Thus, a trauma or crisis such as moving school or house, divorce, and expulsion from school; new stepparent; rejection; molestation; or assault may compromise a child’s ability to cope with stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1995</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0306624X11422224">
<title>Limitations of Motivational Theory</title>
<p>Although motivation is an important consideration in assessment of firesetters, motivational typologies are problematic in a number of ways. Previous attempts to group juveniles who set fires have been criticized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0306624X11422224">Geller (1992)</xref> on a number of grounds. First, data are gathered only from those juveniles apprehended for setting fires, a sample that may be a bias proportion of all juveniles who set fires. In addition, it is not made clear how juveniles are actually categorised into various groups. Although the groups “sound” distinct, selection into groups is likely to be highly subjective. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0306624X11422224">Slavkin (2001)</xref> found clear differences between <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman’s (1995)</xref> “pathological” and “nonpathological” subtypes on measures of pathology and delinquency, significant differences between motivational subtypes within the pathological group were not found, suggesting that these subtypes may not be distinct.</p>
<p>In addition to this, motivational typologies fail to account for the fact that multiple motivations can play a role in an individual’s firesetting behaviour and that motivations are not necessarily mutually exclusive (Kolko &amp; Kazdin, 1991a). An individual may have multiple motivational characteristics, each of which contributes to firesetting behavior, and an individual who sets multiple fires may not do so for the same reason each time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0306624X11422224">Geller, 1992</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1995)</xref> acknowledged this possibility but does not indicate how best to categorise a firesetter who presents with motivations associated with more than one firesetting type.</p>
<p>The label “curiosity” firesetter, a common subtype throughout motivational typologies, has resulted in a perception that such behaviour is “nonsevere” in its nature and therefore of less concern than other subtypes. However, such assumptions have been increasingly contradicted by studies that show that curiosity, particularly fire curiosity, is actually associated with more severe, frequent, and persistent firesetting behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0306624X11422224">Del Bove, 2005</xref>; Kolko &amp; Kazdin, 1991a; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0306624X11422224">MacKay et al., 2006</xref>). “Curiosity” firesetters have been found to have heightened levels of externalising behaviour and aggression, to have a more extensive history of firesetting, and to be at greater risk of recidivism, when compared with low-curiosity firesetters (Kolko &amp; Kazdin, 1991a). Although curiosity of more pathological firesetters is likely to co-occur with other, possibly more salient motivations, due to its association with severe behaviour, curiosity should not be dismissed as a relatively benign motivation.</p>
<p>More recently, a motivational approach to deliberate firesetting in youth has been challenged by the first empirically derived typology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0306624X11422224">Del Bove, 2005</xref>). This identified three distinct firesetting clusters (conventional-limited, home-instability moderate, and multirisk permanent) that differed on a range of individual-, environmental-, and fire-specific variables. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0306624X11422224">Del Bove’s (2005)</xref> findings, it seems likely that there is more than one pathological subtype and that the differences between subtypes are subtle.</p>
<p>Therefore, recent empirical investigation of firesetting types suggests that a more multifactor approach to typology is likely to provide a better way of categorising firesetters. However, motivation does remain the predominant method of categorising firesetters, thus its utility and limitations therefore need to be further investigated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0306624X11422224">
<title>Rationale for the Present Study</title>
<p>The Fire Awareness and Intervention Programme (FAIP) was established in Auckland, New Zealand, in 1992 to address the needs of juveniles who set fires and reduce the incidents of fire-related behaviour in this population. The FAIP, now a nationwide programme, typically provides two to four educational intervention sessions for children under the age of 18 who deliberately light fires or caused parental concern due to dangerous match play incidents. The growth of the programme since its inception reflects a concerning level of youth firesetting and, therefore, a great need for intervention.</p>
<p>This study applies overseas research about juvenile firesetters to a sample of New Zealand juveniles. The current study, rather than using only a sample of firesetters, referred specifically for their firesetting behaviour, also included a community sample of firesetting adolescents. Despite the dominance of motivation in theory and practice with firesetters, few studies have addressed the issue of firesetting motivation and those that have addressed motivation tend to use a quantitative approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0306624X11422224">Del Bove, 2005</xref>; Kolko &amp; Kazdin, 1991a; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0306624X11422224">Slavkin, 2001</xref>). In approaching the concept of motivation through qualitative methodology, the current study aimed to gain insight into the perceptions of firesetting motivation from firesetters and their caregivers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0306624X11422224" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section9-0306624X11422224">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The participants for this research were 18 males ranging in age from 10.5 years to 16.5 years who were selected from a variety of sources. The sample consisted of 13 European juvenile males, 4 Maori juvenile males, and 1 Pacific Island juvenile male. A total of 13 individual parents/caregivers of the juveniles were also interviewed as part of the study. Attempts were made to contact all parents, but despite numerous attempts, some parents were not available to be interviewed due to time commitments. The reasons for this included the following: 6 of the youth were living in placements out of the home. None of the caregivers had been involved in the young person’s life at the time the young person set the fire and therefore could not complete the Behaviour Motivation Interview (BMI). Attempts were made to contact the biological parents of these children but 2 were unavailable due to being too busy, whereas the others could not be contacted or were not involved in the young person’s life anymore. Each of the parents interviewed was from a different child. Finally, of the parents interviewed, all identified the ethnicity of the child and for those 6 children who were in caregiver care, ethnicity was gained from both child and caregiver report.</p>
<sec id="section10-0306624X11422224">
<title>Recruitment sources</title>
<p>One source was the FAIP, in the Auckland and Northland Regions, from which five participants were accessed.</p>
<p>In addition, several community-based child and adolescent agencies agreed to approach current clients who were known to have set fire during the last 2 years. These programmes provide specialised therapy for conduct disorder, school and family behaviour problems, and sexual offending adolescents. The criterion for inclusion in the study was that the male had engaged in unsanctioned firesetting activity in the last 2 years (checked yes to the Child Behavior Checklist; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0306624X11422224">Achenbach, 1991</xref>) or had firesetting identified following clinical assessment. The 2-year cutoff time since the last firesetting incident was included to minimize variation in responses due to confounding variables, such as the effects of treatment these boys may have had since they set fire or the effects of maturation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0306624X11422224">
<title>Measures—The BMI</title>
<p>This measure was developed by the first author (D.W) and was based on questions from a profile sheet used by the New Zealand Fire Service, along with themes drawn from the literature. It is comprised of 10 items, designed to identify single or multiple motivational characteristics of the participant’s firesetting behaviour. Each question has a 3-point Likert-type scale (<italic>none, a little</italic>, and <italic>very much</italic>) to indicate the degree to which the participant felt motivated by each factor. Two of the questions in both the adolescent and parent versions of the BMI (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-0306624X11422224">appendix</xref>) were open ended and were intended to encourage unprompted responses from the participants. The remaining nine questions were specific and intended to probe themes that were derived from the literature.</p>
<p>The parent version of the BMI differed from the adolescent BMI in that it had one extra question relating to family historical factors: “Is there anything in your son’s life that might have contributed to fire-setting? If so, how did these things contribute to his fire-setting?”</p>
<p>In addition to administering the BMI, demographic and firesetting history was gathered. Throughout the interviews, each question was also probed for open-ended responses, to be included in a qualitative analysis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0306624X11422224">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>All interviews took place in the participants’ homes. This was done separately for the participant and their parent, and took between 20 to 30 min to complete.</p>
<sec id="section13-0306624X11422224">
<title>Data analysis—Qualitative analysis</title>
<p>The BMI was analysed using the qualitative methodology approach, “grounded theory” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0306624X11422224">Glasser, 1967</xref>). This allows the theory to be generated from the data, rather than from previous research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0306624X11422224">Glasser, 1995</xref>). The specific method used in the present study was “constant comparison of themes” analytic procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0306624X11422224">Glasser, 1995</xref>). Using this method, data text is analysed and sorted into themes or categories. The researcher then delineates categories from these themes for further analysis.</p>
<p>The data were categorised by reading through the interview responses and noting the themes. The themes that emerged were then grouped into categories, and each individual response was analysed against these categories. Once the responses had been coded into categories, these data were entered into a data set and separately analysed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0306624X11422224">
<title>Interrater reliability</title>
<p>Reliability checks were carried out on one third of the data to ensure that coding of the qualitative data was carried out to the highest degree possible. A psychologist who had 5 years of experience working with children and families carried this out. The percentage agreement between the two raters was calculated by identifying the number of phrases of text per category and the level of agreement on the allocation of phrases within these categories. Each phrase was considered a unit of data. Reliability checks reached a level of 90% agreement.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0306624X11422224" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section16-0306624X11422224">
<title>Firesetting History</title>
<p>In the summary profile sheet, 65% of the participants reported they had set multiple fires and only 35% had set a single fire. The firesetting participants were divided into those who were motivated by curiosity and those who were motivated for other reasons, as reported on the BMI. Nearly half (eight) of the participants reported <italic>experimenting</italic> as a motive for their firesetting, whereas all others (55%) reported a variety of motives that are discussed in more detail below.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0306624X11422224">
<title>Motivational Themes of Firesetting Participants</title>
<p>Data for the qualitative analysis were collected for 18 of the firesetting participants and 13 of their parents/caregivers (hereafter referred to as parents) from the BMI.</p>
<sec id="section18-0306624X11422224">
<title>Adolescents’ responses</title>
<p>Firesetting participants were asked to reflect on the last fire they had started. They were then asked to answer the questions from the BMI. Within the questions (which were unprompted by the researcher), the adolescents stated very similar themes to those predicted by the literature. However, the frequency of motivational themes reported by these participants changed markedly when they were prompted with specific questions. This was especially true for the themes <italic>anger, bored, experimenting</italic>, and <italic>peer influence</italic>. The number of participants who identified particular themes is outlined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0306624X11422224">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0306624X11422224" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Frequency of Prompted and Unprompted Themes Reported by Participants From Questions on the Behaviour Motivation Interview (Adolescent)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0306624X11422224" xlink:href="10.1177_0306624X11422224-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Motive</th>
<th align="center">Unprompted</th>
<th align="center">Prompted</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Angry</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attention</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bored</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Experimenting</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peer influence</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fascination</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Don’t know</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p>The most significant motivation reported by the firesetting participants to the unprompted, open-ended questions on the BMI was <italic>bored</italic> reported by eight (44.4%), for example, “We just were burning the tree things . . . burning them in this old pipe. Me and my friend were just bored and had just come back from the mall—before I was banned from there.” <italic>Experimenting</italic> and <italic>fascination</italic> were reposted, reported by four (22.2%) of the participants each,
<disp-quote>
<p>I like lighting fires—not the act of burning down but the challenge of getting the fire going. When I was small I would get in the fire place and get the fire going. I like watching it catch—it’s a challenge and it’s like look—I made this.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p><italic>Anger</italic> was identified by three participants (16%), and <italic>peer influence</italic> and <italic>don’t know</italic> were less remarkable, identified by two (11.1%) participants. <italic>Attention</italic> was not identified as motivational theme in response to the open-ended question.</p>
<p>The specific questions, however, revealed that 12 (66.7%) of the participants were <italic>bored</italic>, 10 were <italic>angry</italic> (55%), and 9 (50%) were <italic>experimenting</italic>, for example, “I wanted to see how good it would burn down, plastic and cardboard and tin . . . tin didn’t work.” Meanwhile, 9 (50%) cited <italic>peer influence</italic> as motivating factors.</p>
<p>Most of the participants (77.8%) reported more than one motivational theme in relation to their firesetting incident.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0306624X11422224">
<title>Parents’ responses</title>
<p>A total of 13 parents responded to the qualitative questionnaire. The themes that were identified from the open-ended questions of the BMI (parent version) and the prompted questions are summarised in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0306624X11422224">Table 2</xref>. <italic>Family historical factors</italic> were stated by just over half of the parents, in addition to this <italic>fascination, family history</italic> and <italic>anger</italic> were the only other motivational factors cited by more than one parent.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0306624X11422224" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Frequency of Prompted and Unprompted Themes Reported by Parents From Questions on the Behaviour Motivation Interview (Parent)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0306624X11422224" xlink:href="10.1177_0306624X11422224-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Motive</th>
<th align="center">Unprompted</th>
<th align="center">Prompted</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Anger</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fascination</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family historical factors</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peer influence</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Don’t know</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bored</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Experiment</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attention</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p>The most significant motivation reported by the 13 parents to the unprompted open-ended questions on the BMI was <italic>family historical factors</italic> (e.g., parental divorce and family moving a lot), reported by 7 (53.8%) and <italic>fascination</italic>, reported by 3 (23%),
<disp-quote>
<p>He’s ADHD and he loves fires—he’s always been attracted to it. If he had 40 cents he’d buy matches instead of lollies. Even though he loves lollies. He likes striking matches and flicking them. He makes flamethrowers and now that he’s smoking he has a lighter—he flicks, flick, flick. He’s never lit a major thank God.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p><italic>Anger</italic> and <italic>experimenting</italic> were each reported by two parents (15.4%). <italic>Peer influence, don’t know, bored</italic>, and <italic>attention</italic> meanwhile were only identified by one (7.7%) parent each.</p>
<p>The specific questions, however, revealed that 11 (85%) of the parents thought their son was angry at the time, for example,
<disp-quote>
<p>Life’s one big difficulty for C unfortunately. The fire at school was result of an altercation with school. He felt hard done by and walked out of class to find his dean . . . he had lit the edge of a cardboard sticking out of the lockers. He was angry at the time. The caretaker found the rubbish bin alight after C had been there.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Seven parents thought their son was bored (53%), and five thought he was experimenting at the time, for example, “I think it was just having a go . . . S. completely freaked out . . . he just would have a go—he was a bit of a fire-bug.” A further three (23%) parents thought the firesetting incident was in part, to gain attention</p>
<p>Of the parents, seven (53.8%) stated one motivational theme for their sons’ last firesetting incident, whereas one (7.7%) had no theme (don’t know) and five (38.5%) had more than one theme to account for their son’s firesetting.</p>
<p>In response to the open-ended question, one parent responded, “The excitement gets all too much for him—birthdays and Christmas—maybe he gets anxious or nervous.” Following this, she reported a <italic>family historical theme</italic>; when asked if the incident happened <italic>after a problem</italic>, she said,
<disp-quote>
<p>We thought so . . . yes. I left his father when he was 11 months . . . after access, within 2 days there was a fight reported over the phone or physical 3-4 times, even though there were other incidents.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>When given the opportunity to add any information, she introduced another <italic>family historical theme</italic>: “The child psychologist thinks he’s depressed, he’s stealing and lying and can’t leave sugar alone . . . he steals money.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0306624X11422224">
<title>Concordance of adolescent and parent responses</title>
<p>The overall concordance between each parent and their child was only 34%. For example, although <italic>fascination</italic> was the theme for one participant, “I like fire because it’s got red passionate colour about it. I like the colour red, it makes me feel happy and I like the warmth and the blue part in the lighter,” this participant’s parent could not identify what motivated her son. She stated, “I really don’t know . . . he’s a difficult boy to get into his head. He’s manipulative, He’s a very intelligent boy when he puts his mind to it.”</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0306624X11422224" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The results of the present study showed that all participants and parents were able to identify motives as to why either they (in the case of participants) or their son (in the case of parents) engaged in deliberate firesetting. The themes generated in this study were compared with those from previous research and finally their clinical implications are discussed.</p>
<p>This study reported a high incidence of experimentation. Traditionally, there has been a link found between curiosity and experimentation and younger children, 3 to 8 years old (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0306624X11422224">Stadolnik, 2000</xref>). This, however, does not account for the high incidence rate within this study, in which none of the participants were below the age of 10. It is possible in this case because <italic>experimenting</italic> co-occurs with other variables; on its own, it may not be sufficient explanation of an adolescent’s motive to set fire. Within this study, it was not established which of the factors was the <italic>primary</italic> motivating factor. For instance, five of nine participants of the present sample who stated they were <italic>experimenting</italic> also stated they were <italic>angry</italic> at the time and would have been classified as “cry for help” according to the systems of other authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden &amp; Berkey, 1984</xref>). This is also the case when motivational data are organised on a continuum from “non-severe” to “severe” as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0306624X11422224">Sakheim and Osborn (1999)</xref>. Variables deemed more “severe” such as <italic>anger</italic> or <italic>frustration</italic> will supersede those deemed “non-severe” such as <italic>experimenting</italic>. In such cases, <italic>experimenting</italic> would effectively be discounted as a possible salient motivating variable.</p>
<p><italic>Anger</italic> was a prominent motivational factor for the participants in the present study, cited by 55% of the sample when prompted. Although <italic>frustration, break or damage, get back</italic>, and <italic>after a problem</italic> were included in <italic>anger</italic> for the present study, for the FAIP sample over the 1999 period, these categories had scores totalling only 14%. Moreover, the categories frustration and revenge registered no positive responses at all (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0306624X11422224">New Zealand Fire Service, 1999</xref>). This discrepancy may be a result of the age difference of the two samples, as Kolko and Kazdin (1991a) stated that participants motivated by <italic>anger</italic> tend to be older and tend to have high levels of family disruption. The high percentage (55%) is, however, closer to that reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0306624X11422224">Lewis and Yarnell (1951)</xref>, who found that 36% of their sample was motivated by <italic>anger</italic> and <italic>frustration</italic> based on juveniles’ reports. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden and Berkey (1984)</xref> found that 39% of parents thought <italic>anger</italic> was a motivating variable for their children, which was 85% for the parents in the present study. It is also possible that because half of these adolescents were accessed from intervention programmes that deal with a high degree of antisocial behaviour (conduct disorder and sex offenders), the overall level of anger expressed in an antisocial manner may be slightly higher than in other research populations, such as psychiatric populations.</p>
<p>A total of 50% of the adolescents stated <italic>peer pressure</italic> as a motivational variable, when asked specifically. This is much higher than the 26% found in the FAIP sample, and is likely to be accounted for by the age difference of the two samples. <italic>Peer influence</italic> has been noted as a factor that influences older participants, more so than those below 10 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden &amp; Berkey, 1984</xref>). <italic>Peer pressure</italic> is also referred to as the key factor for “delinquent” type firesetters, as perceived by their parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0306624X11422224">Stadolnik, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden &amp; Berkey, 1984</xref>), and these participants made up 36% of the sample investigated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden and Berkey (1984)</xref>. The high rate of peer pressure reported in the present sample may also be due to the format of the semistructured interview, which differs from the dichotomous (yes/no) FAIP format, by encouraging descriptive answers. This may lead to a higher rate of response compliance. For instance, adolescents may not consider their firesetting to have happened as a result of peer pressure, even if there were others present—in the present study, only two (11%) of the adolescents identified peer pressure, without prompting. However, with prompting, a further seven participants stated the firesetting happened, in part, because of what others were saying or doing. This indicates that as expected, an interactive interview format obtains more information than a questionnaire response.</p>
<p>Four (22%) adolescents clearly described <italic>fascination</italic> with fire in the open-ended questions. This was the only variable that formed a category all of its own, although it was not prompted as a motivational variable on the BMI, suggesting that it was a salient motivational factor for these adolescents. <italic>Fascination</italic> is referred to as a subset of pathologically motivated, severely disturbed firesetters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0306624X11422224">Shekim, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0306624X11422224">Stadolnik, 2000</xref>) and is estimated to account for about 3% to 6% of samples and is associated with frequent, intentional and destructive behaviours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0306624X11422224">Kolko, 1999</xref>). A concurrent psychiatric diagnosis and extensive assessment of the adolescent’s history has usually been done to conclude pathological motivation. Again, it may be that because the sample was derived from populations of highly antisocial adolescents, the incidence of pathological firesetting will be higher than samples that include less acting out behaviours.</p>
<sec id="section22-0306624X11422224">
<title>Parents’ Responses</title>
<p>In the open-ended question of the BMI, half of the parents cited <italic>family historical factors</italic> as the greatest motivation to account for their son’s firesetting behaviour. Approximately a quarter of the parents reported <italic>fascination</italic> as the primary motive, whereas <italic>anger, peer influence, don’t know, bored</italic>, and <italic>experimenting</italic> were seldom cited.</p>
<p>The high rate of <italic>family historical factors</italic> reported by parents supports both the dynamic behavioural theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>) and the functional analysis approach, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0306624X11422224">Jackson et al., 1987</xref>). Both these models, and refinements thereof (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0306624X11422224">Heath, Hardesty, Goldfine, &amp; Walker, 1985</xref>), propose historical family and social circumstances as one of three important dimensions related to firesetting behaviour—though as general reasons for the adolescents’ behaviour, not necessarily specific to the firesetting.</p>
<p>When prompted, however, much more specific variables were identified by parents, including those that fit the description of personality and individual characteristics, according to the dynamic behavioural model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>). <italic>Anger</italic> was cited by more than three quarters of the parents, <italic>bored</italic> by half the parents, <italic>family historical factors</italic> and <italic>experimenting</italic> were cited by a third of the parents, whereas a few parents noted <italic>attention</italic>. Previous studies that have also reported that <italic>anger</italic> and <italic>revengeful</italic> feelings are prominent for firesetting juveniles as a whole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0306624X11422224">Gruber, Heck, &amp; Mintzer, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0306624X11422224">Kaufman, Heims, &amp; Reiser, 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0306624X11422224">Yarnell, 1940</xref>). The parents’ responses in the current study support theories that suggest an adolescent’s family history and social circumstances as influential in their current firesetting behaviour. Their responses of a range of factors (i.e., <italic>anger, experimenting, family historical factors</italic>, and being <italic>bored</italic>) being the most salient motivational variables that account for their son’s firesetting behaviour indicate that firesetters are most often “generalists” in their offending behaviour and therefore, parents and adolescents would not necessarily discuss <italic>anger</italic> specifically in relation to firesetting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0306624X11422224">
<title>Concordance Between the Responses of Parents and Sons</title>
<p>A key finding in the present study was that, with the exception of <italic>anger</italic>, there was a distinct lack of concordance between the parents’ perception of what motivated their son to set fire and their son’s report of their motivation for the firesetting incident as recorded on the BMI. This is in contrast with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0306624X11422224">Kolko and Kazdin (1988)</xref>, who found high concordance between parent and child reports on fire-related variables. However, in the case of this past study, there were seven screening items that evaluated the presence or absence of fire behaviours dichotomously (present/absent) and were not emotional in nature. Given the open-ended response format to questions of the BMI, both parents and adolescents were able to give richer, more descriptive answers. When given the opportunity to respond in this format, it has been demonstrated that juveniles and parents have very low agreement in reports of the juveniles’ emotional and behavioural problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0306624X11422224">Achenbach, McConaughy, &amp; Howell, 1987</xref>), which would appear to be the case in this study.</p>
<p>The <italic>family historical factors</italic> reported by such a large proportion of parents in the present study are included in the category of “crisis” motivated firesetters of previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden &amp; Berkey, 1984</xref>). These factors were mentioned by parents as global descriptions accounting for their son’s behaviour, not necessarily in relation to the firesetting event. Indeed, such <italic>family historical factors</italic> have been referred to extensively in the literature as correlates of firesetting participants, rather than motivational variables in themselves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0306624X11422224">Gruber et al., 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0306624X11422224">Hanson, Mackay-Soroka, Staley, &amp; Pignatiello, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0306624X11422224">Kazdin &amp; Kolko, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0306624X11422224">Rider, 1980</xref>). Parents’ response of <italic>family historical factors</italic> as the generic reason of their son’s behaviour reflects the parents taking direct responsibility for their son’s behaviour. This is in line with findings suggesting that parents will often take personal responsibility for their children’s behavioural difficulties in the wake of separation or abuse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0306624X11422224">Briere, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0306624X11422224">Herman, 1994</xref>). These responses also indicate a lack of a specific reason for their son deliberately lighting fires.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0306624X11422224">
<title>Discrepancy Analysis of Peer Pressure, Boredom, Fascination and Experimenting</title>
<sec id="section25-0306624X11422224">
<title>Peer pressure</title>
<p>Interestingly, although half of the adolescents acknowledged <italic>peer pressure</italic> as a motivational variable, only one parent in the present study did so. One possible reason for this is that firesetting behaviour is cited as being a covert activity, especially for the adolescent age group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306624X11422224">Gaynor &amp; Hatcher, 1987</xref>). It therefore is understandable that the parents had little knowledge of the incident or the circumstances surrounding the incident. However, in the case of the participants in the present study, all have been apprehended for their firesetting and the parents know of the incident. This perhaps suggests that many of the adolescents did not say they were with someone else at the time or that despite their son being with others, parents did not see this as a motivating factor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0306624X11422224">
<title>Boredom</title>
<p>Only one parent identified <italic>boredom</italic> as a motivating factor in answer to the open-ended questions, while more than half of the parents indicated that boredom was a motivating factor in answer to the specific <italic>boredom</italic> question from the BMI. This indicates that although <italic>boredom</italic> may play a role in these boys’ fire-setting incidents, it was not necessarily the primary motivation nor was it considered salient by parents. In other studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0306624X11422224">Stadolnik, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden &amp; Berkey, 1984</xref>), based on parent reports, <italic>boredom</italic> is not reported as a motivating factor per se but is alluded to in “accidental” firesetting episodes, and these participants are grouped in the “playing with matches” subgroup.</p>
<p>Although parents did not acknowledge boredom to the same extent as their sons, this does not necessarily reflect a lack of concordance. For both groups, boredom was never cited as a single motivational variable. Thus, this supports the idea that boredom, although often a factor contributing to firesetting behaviour, is rarely the sole motivation. Boredom was often constructed as having nothing to do from the adolescents’ point of view but not knowing how to use his time from the parents’ perspective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0306624X11422224">
<title>Fascination</title>
<p>Although about a quarter of both the parents and adolescents stated <italic>fascination</italic> as a motivating variable, only one of the parents and her son both stated <italic>fascination</italic>. Interestingly, for those parents who reported <italic>fascination</italic> and their son did not, <italic>fascination</italic> was embedded in personality issues, such as an aspect of a wider description of their son, whereas the adolescent responses were far more specific and focused on the qualities of the fire and how it affected them.</p>
<p>The responses indicated that for adolescents fascinated by fire, it is a repetitive and reinforcing event. Given it is a highly repetitive behaviour (and not particularly dangerous, such as staring at a lighter flame), it is not surprising that parents are highly aware of it. However, given the highly personal nature of the adolescents’ experiences, indicated by their responses, it is likely they won’t share with or tell others about it. The combined effect may explain the lack of concordance for parent and adolescent responses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0306624X11422224">
<title>Experimenting</title>
<p>Although more than a third of parents and adolescents reported <italic>experimenting</italic>, there was very low concordance between parents and their sons on this variable, and it was generally only mentioned by both groups when prompted. This finding, along with the finding that <italic>experimenting</italic> co-occurred with other motivational factors, suggests that <italic>experimenting</italic> was not a salient variable. <italic>Experimenting</italic> may be similar to the motivational factor <italic>bored</italic>, in that it is unlikely to be the sole motivational variable involved in a firesetting incident.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0306624X11422224">
<title>Multiple themes for adolescents and parents</title>
<p>An overwhelming majority of the adolescent participants identified multiple themes to account for a single firesetting incident when prompted. This supports the notion that multiple events or antecedents contribute in a cumulative manner, to provide sufficient motivation for firesetting to occur. This is indicated most strongly for <italic>anger, experimenting, peer pressure</italic>, and <italic>bored</italic>, which always co-occurred with other variables. Parents were more inclined to suggest a single motivational theme, and they presented fewer overall multiple themes, one of which was always <italic>family historical factors</italic>. Therefore, evaluation of multiple responses for each individual adolescent is necessary to give a more accurate description of motivation, rather than just a description of total responses for each variable for a whole sample. Furthermore, the different perspectives gained by using multiple sources gives a much broader picture of motivation, necessary to complete a motivational analysis such as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1980)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0306624X11422224">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>In the open-ended section of the BMI, the adolescents and parents revealed a single motive to account for a firesetting incident, whereas specific prompting questions revealed multiple motives for the same incident. Therefore, the data showed that in only three cases a single motive (<italic>anger</italic>) was cited for setting fire throughout the interview. For the remaining 15 adolescent participants, motives co-occurred with each other. Therefore, it is difficult to tell which was the primary motivating factor or whether any one of the motivation factors in isolation would be enough to initiate a firesetting incident. The adolescents reported personality and individual characteristic themes, the most frequent of these themes being <italic>anger, experimenting, peer pressure</italic>, and <italic>boredom</italic>. Parents on the other hand initially cited <italic>family historical factors</italic>, thereafter describing fewer themes when prompted. This revealed a trend in which adolescents tended to select more personal antecedent themes directly relating to the firesetting incident called for by the dynamic behavioural formulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>), whereas the parents were more inclined to select themes that indicate general difficulty in the adolescents’ life called for in a dynamic behavioural formulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>) of firesetting motivation.</p>
<p>The evident lack of concordance between adolescents’ reports and their parents’ reports suggested that neither descriptions of firesetting are complete representation of adolescent firesetting behaviour. Thus, a combination of the parent and adolescent descriptions is likely to give a more descriptive and accurate picture of what motivates firesetting activity.</p>
<p>Qualitative responses identifying motivation to set fire from adolescents and parents found distinct characteristics and both were important to gain sufficient information to identify motivational categories as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1980)</xref>. Much of the previous research is unclear as to whether the data have been gathered from adolescents or parents, thus making comparison challenging. In any research on adolescent firesetters, it is imperative to clearly state from whom information was gathered to enable more meaningful comparisons of motives to be carried out with past and future studies.</p>
<p>When assessing children who deliberately light fires, multiple information sources are preferable to gain the most comprehensive understanding of motivation.</p>
<p>This study showed the difficulties that arise from attempts to classify firesetters by motivation. It became clear that there were often multiple motivations, there was variation between parent and firesetter reports as well as differences between and ambiguities inherent in existing motivational typologies. Therefore, the development of a standardised classification is clearly needed and development of current assessment protocols should be in the context of attempting to standardise definitions internationally. The first attempt at an empirically derived classification system has suggested a shift from motivational based firesetting typologies, and these findings are in need of replication and further investigation.</p>
<p>In the present study, those who identified curiosity also identified other motivational themes to account for their firesetting incident. Given the present sample is comprised of all adolescents, the assumption of minimal intervention for curiosity firesetting must be viewed with some caution, and it highlights the importance of undertaking a thorough clinical assessment prior to commencing any treatment programme.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-0306624X11422224">
<title>Limitations of the Current Study</title>
<p>This current study is limited by its small sample size of only 18 adolescents and 13 parents. As well as this, the sample was not randomly selected and is only representative of those firesetters who are apprehended and thus may vary from a community sample that identifies those firesetters who remain undetected. In addition, the severity of the firesetting behaviour of the sample, the extent of comorbid pathology, and environmental or individual difficulties remained unknown.</p>
<p>It is a shortcoming in the qualitative section of the present study that immediate environmental conditions, the third dimension of the dynamic behavioral model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306624X11422224">Fineman, 1980</xref>), could not be clearly identified or separated from personality and individual characteristics. For instance, a parent identifying <italic>anger</italic> as a motivational variable could have meant internal anger (as a personality variable) or anger at an incident (environmental cause). Further probing of each variable would have been necessary to identify this.</p>
<p>The BMI, modelled from the profile sheet of the FAIP in its current form, is also unable in its current form to identify which theme is most salient for the respondent. This information could be useful in any assessment of firesetters.</p>
<p>It has also been difficult to draw meaningful comparisons between existing research and the current study, as allocation to categories has been subjective and inconsistent across research. For instance in Kolko and Kazdin’s (1991a) study, parents and participants rated themselves on 12 motivational categories that are very similar to the BMI. However, data from these 12 categories were grouped into 2 categories, <italic>curiosity</italic> and <italic>anger</italic>. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0306624X11422224">Wooden and Berkey (1984)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306624X11422224">Fineman (1995)</xref> classified firesetters as motivated by “curiosity,” “delinquent,” and “severely disturbed or curiosity,” “accidental,” “cry for help,” and “delinquent,” respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-0306624X11422224" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The current study has highlighted the complexity of identifying salient motivating factors for firesetting in adolescents. This supports previous research, indicating that there are a range of different firesetting motivations for young people and that these children are likely to have a range of different behavioural problems. Thus, researchers should attempt to identify “clusters” of motivational factors that may cumulatively motivate children to deliberately light fires.</p>
<p>Clearly, evident within this study was that motivation is important in the assessment of firesetters, but it is unlikely to be a useful way to typologize them. Motivation is likely to play a role in any empirically guided typology but only in terms of acknowledging that different motivations may be more prevalent in different types of firesetter and are also present across types. Typologies rely on identifying distinct motivations when providing treatment for young people, which are in fact unlikely to be clearly defined. Such classifications also oversimplify the role of motivation in firesetting and thus risk the assessor not gaining a full understanding of the young person. It is likely that more valuable information could be gathered in terms of motivation through examining how it is associated with behaviours (such severity and frequency), which motivations tend to correlate with which behaviours, whether motivations are more often associated with different age groups, and whether different motivations are related to different types of firesetting behaviours and antisocial “status.” This would likely help us more fully understand why it is that some young people engage in deliberate firesetting while others do not.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0306624X11422224">
<title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="section33-0306624X11422224">
<title>Behaviour Motivation Interview (Child Version)</title>
<p>Sometimes children have strong feelings of thoughts when they set fire. The following are a selection of feelings and thoughts that some children have talked about after they have set fire. I will read through the list and you tell me which you were feeling or thinking when you set fire. There may have been none of these thoughts or feelings, only one of these, or more than one at the same time.</p>
<p>An example may be that a boy who set a fire may have been angry about being expelled from school, and that he wanted to “get back” at teachers he was annoyed with.</p>
<list id="list2-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>1. Why do you think you set fire? (Were there things you were upset about at home or school?)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>2. Were you feeling angry when you set fire? (<italic>Mad or upset with someone or something that happened?)</italic> <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list3-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>3. Did you want attention, <italic>(someone to take notice)</italic> of you when you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list4-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>4. Were you feeling bored (<italic>like you had nothing to do, other things were stink</italic>) when you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list5-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>5. Were you experimenting <italic>(testing or curious to ‘see what would happen’</italic>) when you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list6-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>6. Were you feeling frustrated <italic>(like people don’t understand you, what you are thinking or feeling)</italic> when you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list7-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>7. Did you feel like you had to set fire because of what other kids were saying or doing? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list8-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>8. Were you feeling like you wanted to get back at someone <italic>(pay them back for something they did to you</italic>) when you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list9-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>9. Did you want to break or damage something when you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list10-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>10. Did you set fire after a problem with someone or something? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
<list id="list11-0306624X11422224" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>11. Is there anything you would like to add that may help me understand why you set fire? <bold>none a little very much</bold></p></list-item></list>
<p>If so can you tell me about that?</p>
</sec></app></app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Achenbach</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McConaughy</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Child/adolescent behavioral and emotional problems: Implications of cross-informant correlations for situational specificity</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Achenbach</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Manual for the Child Behaviour Checklist - 4-18 and the 1991 profile</source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington University, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Vermont, Department of Psychiatry</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Briere</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Psychological assessment of adult posttraumatic states</source> (<edition>1st ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arria</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Firesetting in adolescence and being aggressive, shy and rejected by peers: New epidemiologic evidence from a national sample survey</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Psychiatry and the Law</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dadds</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Fire interest, fire setting and psychopathology in Australian children: A normative study</article-title>. <source>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>581</fpage>-<lpage>586</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Del Bove</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>An empirically derived classification system for juvenile firesetters: Implications for firesetting behavior, mental health, outcome and treatment</article-title>. <source>Dissertation Abstracts International Section A: Humanities and Social Sciences</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>3564</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Del Bove</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caprara</surname><given-names>G. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pastorelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paciello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Juvenile firesetting in Italy: Relationship to aggression, psychopathology, personality, self-efficacy, and school functioning</article-title>. <source>European Child and Adolescent Psychology</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fineman</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Firesetting in childhood and adolescence</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Clinics of North America</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>500</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fineman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>A model for the qualitative analysis of child and adult fire deviant behaviour</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Forensic Psychology</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1953</year>). <source>Fragment of an analysis of a case of hysteria</source> (Standard Edition, <volume>Vol. 7</volume>, pp. <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogarth Press</publisher-name>. (Original work published 1905)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1932</year>). <article-title>The acquisition of power over fire</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>-<lpage>410</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaynor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hatcher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>The psychology of child firesetting</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brunner/Mazel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geller</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Arson in review</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Clinics of North America</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>623</fpage>-<lpage>643</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glasser</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>The discovery of grounded theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Glasser</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>1995</year>). <source>Grounded theory 1984-1994</source> (<volume>Vol. 1</volume>). <publisher-loc>Mill Valley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sociology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mintzer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Children who set fires: Some background and behavioral characteristics</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthopsychiatry</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>484</fpage>-<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Intentional fires and arson</source>. <publisher-loc>Quincey, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Fire Protection Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackay-Soroka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pignatiello</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Firesetters: A comparative study of delinquency and fire setting histories</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hardesty</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldfine</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Diagnosis and childhood firesetting</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>571</fpage>-<lpage>575</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Trauma and recovery</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pandora</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>A functional analysis of recidivistic arson</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>D. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heims</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>). <article-title>A re-evaluation of the psychodynamics of firesetting</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthopsychiatry</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Parent psychpathology and family functioning among childhood firesetters</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Juvenile firesetting: A review and methodological critique</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychology Review</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>-<lpage>376</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Firesetting in children and youth</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Van Hasselt</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hersen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of psychological approaches with violent offenders: Contemporary strategies and issues</source> (pp. <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>115</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Plenum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>2002</year>). <source>Handbook on firesetting in children and youth</source>. <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>A conceptualization of firesetting in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Parent-child correspondence in identification of firesetting among child psychiatric patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Aggression and psychopathology in matchplaying and firesetting children: A replication and extension</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Child Psychology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>201</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolko</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Motives of childhood firesetters: Firesetting characteristics and psychological correlates</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>-<lpage>550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lambie</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Randell</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Creating a firestorm: A review of children who deliberately light fires</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychology Review</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yarnell</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1951</year>). <source>Pathological firesetting (pyromania)</source> (<volume>Vol. 82</volume>). <publisher-loc>Nicholasville, KY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Coolidge Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Del Bove</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warling</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Fire interest and antisociality as risk factors in the severity and persistence of juvenile firesetting</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>45</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>1077</fpage>-<lpage>1084</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paglia-Boak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adlaf</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Epidemiology of firesetting in adolescents: Mental health and substance use correlates</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1282</fpage>-<lpage>1290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roegar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Correlates of firesetting in a community sample of young adolescents</article-title>. <source>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>New Zealand Fire Service</collab>. (<year>1999</year>). <source>Auckland 1998/1999 report. Fire awareness and intervention programme</source>. <publisher-loc>Auckland, New Zealand</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Auckland Fire Department</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nurcombe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>). <article-title>Children who set fires</article-title>. <source>Medical Journal of Australia</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>584</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Porth</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Juvenile firesetting: A four year perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Portland, OR</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SOS Fires Youth Intervention Programme</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rider</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>, <month>August</month>). <article-title>The firesetter: A psychological profile, part II</article-title>. <source>FBI Law Enforcement Bulletin</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sakheim</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Severe vs. nonsevere fire setters revisited</article-title>. <source>Child Welfare</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>434</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Adolescent female firesetters</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>404</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekim</surname><given-names>W. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Firesetting in children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Behavior Analysis</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>270</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slavkin</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Juvenile firesetters: An exploratory analysis</article-title>. <source>Dissertation Abstracts International: Section B: The Sciences and Engineering</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>6168</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stadolnik</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Drawn to the flame: Assessment and treatment of juvenile firesetting behavior</source> (<edition>1st</edition> ed.). <publisher-loc>Sarasota, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Professional Resource Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Statistics New Zealand</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <source>Calendar year apprehension statistics</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wdmzpub01.stats.govt.nz">http://wdmzpub01.stats.govt.nz</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vandersall</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Children who set fires</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vreeland</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Psychological aspects of firesetting</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Canter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Fires and human behaviour</source> (pp. <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wooden</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berkey</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Children and arson</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Plenum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0306624X11422224">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yarnell</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1940</year>). <article-title>Firesetting in children</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthopsychiatry</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>262</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>