<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PMJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppmj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Palliat Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>Palliative Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0269-2163</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-030X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269216312441382</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269216312441382</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs for the treatment of cancer cachexia: A systematic review</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0269216312441382">Nursing and Midwifery Research Unit, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Queen’s University Belfast, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0269216312441382">School of Pharmacy, Queen’s University Belfast, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-0269216312441382">Centre for Public Health, School of Medicine, Dentistry and Biomedical Sciences, Queen’s University Belfast, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff4-0269216312441382">School of Pharmacy, Queen’s University Belfast, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cantwell</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff5-0269216312441382">Centre for Public Health, School of Medicine, Dentistry and Biomedical Sciences, Queen’s University Belfast, UK</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0269216312441382">Joanne Reid, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Queen’s University Belfast, Room 06.312, Medical Biology Centre, Block 97 Health Sciences, 97 Lisburn Road Belfast BT9 7BL. Email: <email>j.reid@qub.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>295</fpage>
<lpage>303</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0269216312441382">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Cancer cachexia is a devastating syndrome of advanced malignancy which negatively impacts on patients’ morbidity, mortality and quality of life. Chronic inflammation is a key characteristic of cancer cachexia. Therefore, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may be able to break the cycle of cachexia.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0269216312441382">
<title>Aim:</title>
<p>To systematically review the literature on the use of NSAIDs for the treatment of cachexia in advanced cancer patients.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0269216312441382">
<title>Design:</title>
<p>All titles retrieved through searching were downloaded to a reference management database, duplicates were removed and the remaining citations were checked for eligibility. Full copies of all eligible articles were obtained and reviewed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0269216312441382">
<title>Data sources:</title>
<p>Electronic searches (from inception up to 09/2011) included CINAHL, MEDLINE, EMBASE, and Web of Science. Reference lists from reviewed articles, trial registers and abstracts from relevant conferences were searched. Eligibility criteria were (a) Randomised Controlled Trial; (b) participants were adults with cancer with weight loss or a clinical diagnosis of cachexia; (c) administration of oral NSAIDs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0269216312441382">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Four studies were included. These studies provided some evidence of positive therapeutic effect on quality of life, performance status, inflammatory markers, weight gain and survival, but there was insufficient evidence demonstrated for their widespread use in practice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0269216312441382">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>Insufficient studies have been performed to allow a conclusion to be formed with regard to the effectiveness of NSAIDs in the treatment of cachexia in advanced cancer. Major challenges in this patient cohort include the lack of uniformity of inclusion criteria across studies and the frailty of the patients recruited.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cancer cachexia</kwd>
<kwd>non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</kwd>
<kwd>systematic review</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section7-0269216312441382">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Cancer cachexia is a multifactorial syndrome characterized by loss of skeletal muscle (with or without loss of fat) that cannot be fully reversed with nutrition intervention and leads to progressive functional deterioration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269216312441382">1</xref></sup> Patients typically display profound weight loss and death tends to occur when an affected individual’s weight loss reaches 30% of pre-morbid levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269216312441382">2</xref></sup> This syndrome occurs in up to 80% of cancer patients and is the main cause of death in 20% of patients,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269216312441382">3</xref></sup> accounting for two million deaths worldwide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269216312441382">4</xref></sup> Cachexia also has psycho-social implications for affected individuals, in that it can lead to social isolation, altered body image<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269216312441382">5</xref></sup> and reduced quality of life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269216312441382">2</xref></sup> Cachexia is different from starvation, as the weight loss associated with cachexia is predominately wasting of lean muscle mass while visceral proteins are preserved.</p>
<p>While the exact pathophysiology of cachexia in advanced cancer remains unknown, it appears to be mediated through an amalgamation of the proinflammatory cytokine response of the host to tumour presence and the tumour manufacture of specific cytokines and catabolic factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269216312441382">6</xref></sup> Chronic inflammation is a main feature of cancer cachexia. Evidence suggests that a chronic low grade activation of the host’s immune system, induced by tumour presence, is involved in the condition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269216312441382">7</xref></sup> This activation shares characteristics with the acute-phase response found after major traumatic incidents. Therefore, anti-inflammatory agents may be able to break the cycle of cachexia, which is known to be both involuntary and progressive. Preliminary work demonstrated that levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, C-Reactive Protein (C-RP) and Interleukin–6 (IL-6), can be moderated by administering Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269216312441382">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269216312441382">9</xref></sup> Following on from this seminal work, research has focused on the effect of NSAIDs, used either solely or in multi-modal therapy (e.g. with megestrol acetate/fish oil), in reversing or ameliorating cachexia in advanced cancer patients. While current discussion around meaningful outcomes for this patient cohort is ongoing in the literature,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269216312441382">10</xref></sup> the most commonly used outcome in assessing the effectiveness of a treatment modality for cancer cachexia is change in body composition (including weight) and is the primary outcome examined in this review paper. While changes in weight are important, it negates a critical measure of changes in lean muscle mass, which gives a specific indication of the effect of a treatment on cachexia. Measuring body composition (including weight) overcomes this by using, for example, Dual Energy X-ray (DEXA) or mid-upper arm circumference to measure muscle mass, thereby ensuring that weight gain is more than simply water or fat gain. This is particularly relevant to cancer cachexia as it is characterized by a loss of muscle mass.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269216312441382">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Cachexia is a challenge to manage in clinical practice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269216312441382">12</xref></sup> and currently there is no optimal treatment for this syndrome of advanced cancer. Although reviews have examined different treatment modalities for cancer cachexia,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269216312441382">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269216312441382">14</xref></sup> evidence has not identified an optimum treatment. Preliminary studies of NSAIDs for cancer cachexia have demonstrated encouraging results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269216312441382">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269216312441382">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0269216312441382"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269216312441382"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269216312441382"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269216312441382"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269216312441382">20</xref></sup> However, the effectiveness of NSAIDs for cancer cachexia has not been systematically reviewed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0269216312441382">
<title>Aim</title>
<p>The aim of this review was to examine RCTs of NSAIDs versus placebo or alternative treatment modality for managing cancer cachexia in relation to the effectiveness of NSAIDs for cancer cachexia, and to identify and assess any adverse effects from NSAIDs on cancer cachexia.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0269216312441382" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section10-0269216312441382">
<title>Selection of studies</title>
<p>Electronic searches (from inception up to 09/2011) included CINAHL, MEDLINE, EMBASE, and Web of Science. The MEDLINE search terms are detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0269216312441382">Table 1</xref>. Reference lists from reviewed articles were examined for any additional studies. Trial registers were searched, including Current Controlled Trials (this encompasses the meta register of controlled trials and includes ASRCTN International register, Action Medical Research UK, MRC UK, NIH Clinical Trials, NIHR HTA UK, Wellcome Trust UK and the UK Trials Register – <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.controlled-trials.com/">http://www.controlled-trials.com/</ext-link>); National Cancer Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/search/">http://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/search/</ext-link>); Institute of Clinical Research, Clinical Trials Register (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icr-global.org/resources/ct-registers/">http://www.icr-global.org/resources/ct-registers/</ext-link>); and Clinical Trials.gov (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">http://clinicaltrials.gov/</ext-link>). Abstracts from relevant conferences, such as the International Cachexia Conferences, were hand-searched.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0269216312441382" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Search terms for NSAIDs and cancer cachexia.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0269216312441382" xlink:href="10.1177_0269216312441382-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1) cancer* or neoplasm* or tumor* or tumour* or malignan* or carcino*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2) cachex* or cachectic or malnourish* or malnutrition or emaciate* or weight reduction or weight los* or weight gain or wasting or wasted</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3) Anti-Inflammatory Agents or Anti-Inflammatory Agents, Non-Steroidal or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or Cyclooxygenase Inhibitors or NSAIDs or Anti-Inflammatory Agents, Non-Steroidal or diclofenac or ibuprofen or naproxen or fenbufen or fenoprofen or ketoprofen or dexketoprofen or flurbiprofen or tiaprofenic or aceclofenac or diflunisal or etodolac or indometacin or mefenamic acid or meloxicam or nabumetone or piroxicam or sulindac or tenoxicam or tolfenamic acid or Ketorolac Tromethamine or ketorolac or parecoxib or celecoxib or etoricoxib or rofecoxib or salicylates or indoles or propionic acids or fenamates or oxicams</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p>The following inclusion criteria were used to select studies: (1) the study design was a Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) that was double blinded, single blinded or unblinded; (2) the study recruited adults diagnosed with cancer (all types) with weight loss or a clinical diagnosis of cachexia; (3) participants were administered oral NSAIDs (regardless of dosage) for any duration versus placebo or an alternative experimental treatment modality. The primary outcome measure was change in body composition, measuring both weight (for example kgs) and muscle mass (via, for example, DEXA or mid-upper arm circumference). Secondary outcome measures were overall survival (OS), quality of life (QOL), fatigue and functioning (using psychometrically validated measures such as EORTC QLQ - C30, Multidimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory-Short Form (MFSI-SF) and Karnofsky Index), grip strength, serum levels of proinflammatory cytokines (IL-6, C-RP, interferon [INF] and tumour necrosis factor [TNF]) and adverse events.</p>
<p>All titles and abstracts retrieved through searching (<italic>n</italic>=919) were downloaded to a reference management database (RefWorks), duplicates were removed, and the remaining citations were read by two reviewers (JR and MC) and checked for eligibility. For abstracts not excluded at this stage, full copies of articles were obtained and reviewed. Any disagreements were resolved through discussion between the reviewers. Studies that were not deemed eligible for inclusion had clear reasons for exclusion documented. A flow chart detailing the selection of studies is detailed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0269216312441382">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0269216312441382" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>PRISMA 2009 Flow Diagram – adapted for NSAIDs and Cancer Cachexia.</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: Moher D, liberati A, tetzlaff J, Altman DG, The PRISMA Group (2009). <italic>P</italic>referred <italic>R</italic>eporting <italic>I</italic>tems for Systematic Reviews and <italic>M</italic>eta-Analyses: The PRISMA Statemant. PLos Med 6(6): e100097.doi10.1371/journal.pmed1000097</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269216312441382-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0269216312441382">
<title>Data extraction and management</title>
<p>Data were extracted from eligible studies using a standard data extraction form. The extraction form included details of the study type (RCT, blinded or unblinded), characteristics of participants (inclusion criteria, tumour type, age, stage, co-morbidity, previous treatment, performance status, weight loss), intervention(s) (dose, formulation, duration of treatment), duration of follow-up, outcomes and number enrolled in each study arm. Once complete, all information on the data extraction forms was presented in a tabular format. The methodological quality of all studies included in this review was examined using the Jadad scale,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269216312441382">21</xref></sup> the appropriateness of which is outlined elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269216312441382">22</xref></sup></p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section12-0269216312441382" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>As detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0269216312441382">Table 2</xref>, a total of four studies met the inclusion criteria for this review.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269216312441382"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269216312441382">26</xref></sup> There was substantial heterogeneity as the inclusion criteria and tumour types of the recruited participants differed across the studies. Additionally, cross-comparison of the studies was hindered by the differing outcome measures used. For these reasons data could not be pooled from the four studies, and therefore a narrative synthesis of the studies is presented. In relation to the methodological quality of the studies included in this review, the Jadad score<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269216312441382">21</xref></sup> ranged from two to three for the four studies highlighting the divergence of quality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0269216312441382">Table 3</xref>). It was noted that blinding, specifically the methods of blinding, was not discussed in sufficient detail by two of the studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269216312441382">26</xref></sup> Specific randomisation procedures were not discussed by two of the studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269216312441382">24</xref></sup> Additionally, reasons for participant drop-out was not presented in one study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref></sup> For the purposes of this review the four studies will be discussed based on the type of NSAID used in each trial.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0269216312441382" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of included studies.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0269216312441382" xlink:href="10.1177_0269216312441382-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Authors &amp; Year</th>
<th align="left">Treatment &amp; Study design</th>
<th align="left">Participants</th>
<th align="left">Inclusion criteria</th>
<th align="left">Outcome measures</th>
<th align="left">Summary of Results related to cachexia</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Cerchietti et al. (2007)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382">25</xref></sup></td>
<td>All patients received aspirin 75 mg daily and oral food supplement plus celecoxib (200 mg twice daily) and fish oil (2 g three times daily)
<break/>or placebo and fish oil (2 g three times daily).
<break/>Randomized trial</td>
<td>Advanced non small cell lung cancer patients.
<break/>Fish oil plus placebo <italic>n</italic>=12
<break/>Fish oil plus celecoxib <italic>n</italic>=10
<break/>6 weeks of treatment.</td>
<td>Advanced Non small cell lung cancer and evidence of SIMS – presence of cachexia &gt;10% weight loss, anorexia, performance status = or &gt; 2 ECOG, plus evidence of ACPR (C-RP &gt; 10 µg/ml)</td>
<td>Baseline and weekly Karnofsky’s performance score, appetite, nausea, fatigue, weight, fat mass, lean mass, total body water, caloric intake, handgrip. Baseline and weekly blood chemistry were taken for measurement of albumin, total protein, total and differential white cell count, sodium, potassium, ionic calcium, creatinine, urea, total and direct bilirubin, aspartate amino transaminase, alanine amino transaminase, lactate dehydrongenase, gamma glutamil transpeptidase, alkaline phosphate and C-RP.</td>
<td>“After 6 wk of treatment, patients receiving fish oil plus placebo or fish oil plus celecoxib showed significantly more appetite, less fatigue, and lower C-reactive protein (C-RP) values than their respective baselines values (P &lt; 0.02 for all the comparisons). Additionally, patients in the fish oil plus celecoxib group also improved their body weight and muscle strength compared to baseline values (P &lt; 0.02 for all the comparisons). Comparing both groups, patients receiving fish oil plus celecoxib showed significantly lower C-RP levels (P = 0.005, t-test), higher muscle strength (P = 0.002, t-test) and body weight (P = 0.05, t-test) than patients receiving fish oil plus placebo. The addition of celecoxib improved the control of the acute phase protein response, total body weight, and muscle strength. Additionally, the consistent nutritional support used in our patients could have helped to maximize the pharmacological effects of fish oil and/or celecoxib” (Cerchietti et al, 2007, p.14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lai et al. (2008)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref></sup></td>
<td>Celecoxib
<break/>21 day treatment
<break/>200 mg twice daily or placebo.
<break/>Randomized double-blind
<break/>placebo-controlled trial (pilot)</td>
<td>Head and neck or gastrointestinal cancer patients.
<break/>Treatment group <italic>n</italic>=4
<break/>Placebo <italic>n</italic>=7</td>
<td>Clinical diagnosis of cancer cachexia
<break/>Unintentional weight loss&gt;5% within six months without mechanical obstruction</td>
<td>Baseline and day 21 (end of pharmacological intervention) measurements were collected for body composition (BIA and DEXA). REE, serum cytokine including anti-inflammatory cytokines interlukin-1β, interleukin-2, interleukin-6, interleukin-8, interleukin-10, tumour necrosis factor-α, interferon-γ and C-reactive protein. Quality of life was measured using the FAACT (Version 4). Performance was measured using Karnofsky’s performance score. Weight and BMI.</td>
<td>“Patients receiving celecoxib experienced statistically significant increases in weight and body mass index (BMI), while patients receiving placebo experienced weight loss and a decline in BMI. Patients receiving celecoxib also had increases in QOL scores” (Lai et al, 2008, p. 67)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lundholm et al. (1994)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269216312441382">26</xref></sup></td>
<td>Indometacin (100 mg) or
<break/>Prednisolone (20 mg) or placebo until death.
<break/>Randomized trial.</td>
<td>Cancer patients with various tumour types.
<break/>Indometacin treatment group <italic>n</italic>= 45.
<break/>Prednisolone treatment group <italic>n</italic>=45.
<break/>Placebo group <italic>n</italic>=45.</td>
<td>Patients with cancer who had insidious or ongoing weight loss, no other efficient tumour treatment, most recent treatment finished six months prior to study, expected survival &gt;6 months</td>
<td>Heart rate, blood pressure, body temperature, respiratory frequency, fatigue, pain, handgrip strength, Karnofsky Index, energy expenditure (indirect calorimetry), nutritional state variables, tricep skin fold and arm muscle circumference, weight (kg). Blood chemistry included haemoglobin, white blood cells, thrombocyte count, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, C-reactive protein, plasma protein concentration, serum albumin and thyroid state, plasma electrolytes, serum creatinine and liver function tests.</td>
<td>“Indometacin and prednisolone treatment maintained Karnowsky index, while placebo-treated patients experienced a decreased index...Indometacin prolonged mean survival compared to placebo-treated patients from 250 plus/- 28 days to 510 plus/- 28 days (P &lt; 0.05). Survival analysis on observations from all patients treated with either indometacin or prednisolone demonstrated a significantly prolonged survival by anti-inflammatory treatment compared to placebo treatment (log rank, P &lt; 0.03).” (Lundholm et al, 1994, p. 5602)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>McMillan et al. (1999)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269216312441382">24</xref></sup></td>
<td>Combination Megestrol acetate (480 mg day) and Ibuprofen (1200mg day) or megestrol acetate (480 mg day and placebo) 12 weeks Tx.
<break/>Randomized placebo-controlled double blind trial</td>
<td>Advanced or metastatic gastro-intestinal cancer patients.
<break/>Dual treatment group (Megestrol acetate plus ibuprofen n= 35
<break/>Megestrol acetate plus placebo n=38</td>
<td>More than 5% weight loss, receiving supportive care only. No functional obstruction to food intake.</td>
<td>Baseline, 4–6 week and 12-week measurements included: total body water (Xitron 400B bioimpedance spectrum analyzer), appetite (linear analogue scale), skin fold anthropometry (biceps and triceps – Harpenden skin fold calipers); mid-upper arm circumference – stretch-resistant tape. C-reactive protein, albumin, Karnofsky performance status, general health state was measured by Euro-QoL-EQ-5D and linear analogue scale, EORTC QLQ-C30</td>
<td>“63% failed to complete the 12 week assessment. Of those evaluable at 12 weeks, there was a decrease in weight (median 2.8 kg) in the megestrol acetate/placebo group compared with an increase (median 2.3 kg) in the megestrol acetate/ibuprofen group (P&lt;0.001). There was also an improvement in the EuroQol-EQ-5D quality of life scores of the latter group (P&lt;0.05)” (McMillan et al, 1999, p. 495)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0269216312441382"><p>Abbreviations: DEXA, Dual-Energy X-ray Absorptiometry; BIA, bioelectrical impedance; REE, Resting Energy Expenditure, FAACT, Functional Assessment of Anorexia-Cachexia Therapy; BMI, Body Mass Index; SIMS, Systematic Immune-Metabolic Syndrome; ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; APRP, Acute Phase Protein Response.; Tx, Treatment; C-RP, C-Reactive Protein</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0269216312441382" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Jadad scores of assessed trials.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0269216312441382" xlink:href="10.1177_0269216312441382-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Author and year</th>
<th align="left">Randomization</th>
<th align="left">Blinding</th>
<th align="left">Description or withdrawals and dropouts</th>
<th align="left">Jadad score (Jadad et al., 1996)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Lai et al., 2008<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref></sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Macmillan et al., 1999<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269216312441382">24</xref></sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cerchietti et al., 2007<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382">25</xref></sup></td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lundholm et al., 1994<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269216312441382">26</xref></sup></td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<sec id="section13-0269216312441382">
<title>Celecoxib for cancer cachexia</title>
<p>Two RCTs,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382">25</xref></sup> one of which was double blinded,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref></sup> examined celecoxib in the treatment of cancer cachexia. One study randomised 11 head and neck or gastrointestinal cancer patients, with unintentional weight loss of &gt;5% within six months, to receive celecoxib at a dose of 200mg twice daily (<italic>n</italic>=4) or placebo (<italic>n</italic>=7) for 21 days.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref></sup> This study was conducted from cancer diagnosis to the start of anticancer therapy. After 21 days, one study reported an increase in body weight (mean change plus 1.0 kg) and BMI (mean change plus 0.31 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) in the celecoxib group, while the placebo group lost weight (mean weight loss 1.3 kg) and had a reduced BMI (mean change −0.56 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). The changes in mean BMI were statistically significantly different between the treatment and control groups (<italic>P</italic>=0.05). There was no difference in lean body mass (LBM) between the two groups and while the celecoxib group showed decreased levels of IL-6 after 21 days of treatment, this was not statistically significant, nor was there any significant change in CRP or Karnofsky Performance scores in either group during the study. However, quality of life was statistically significantly higher in patients receiving celecoxib compared with placebo (<italic>P</italic>=0.05). There were no serious adverse events reported. With regard to patient drop-out, 10 of the 11 participants completed the 21-day study.</p>
<p>The second study randomized 22 advanced non-small cell lung cancer patients, with weight loss of &gt;10%, to receive celecoxib 200 mg twice daily plus fish oil 2 g three times a day (<italic>n</italic>=10) or fish oil (2 g three times a day) plus placebo (<italic>n</italic>=12) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382">25</xref></sup>. Additionally, all patients were given aspirin 75mg daily and an oral food supplement equivalent to 20% of their basal metabolic rate at rest. Treatment lasted for 42 days. Results from this study highlighted that the celecoxib plus fish oil intervention group had significantly lower CRP levels (<italic>P</italic>=0.005) and higher hand grip strength (<italic>P</italic>=0.002) and body weight (<italic>P</italic>=0.05) compared to the fish oil plus placebo group after six weeks of treatment. There were no other significant differences reported in the study. There were no serious adverse events reported. With regard to patient drop-out, all participants (<italic>n</italic>=22) were available for assessment at six weeks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0269216312441382">
<title>Ibuprofen for cancer cachexia</title>
<p>A single RCT (double blinded) examined ibuprofen in the treatment of cachexia in patients (<italic>n</italic>=73) with advanced or metastatic gastrointestinal cancer with more than 5% weight loss and who were receiving supportive care only.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269216312441382">24</xref></sup> They were randomized to receive megestrol acetate 480 mg daily plus ibuprofen 1200 mg daily (<italic>n</italic>=35), or megestrol acetate 480 mg daily plus placebo (<italic>n</italic>=38), for 12 weeks. Notably, 46 (63%) of the patients did not complete the study, mainly because of disease progression requiring hospital admission. For the 27 patients who could be evaluated at 12 weeks (<italic>n</italic>=11, megestrol acetate plus placebo; <italic>n</italic>=16, megestrol acetate plus ibuprofen), there was a decrease in mean weight (median 2.8 kg) in the megestrol acetate plus placebo group and an increase in weight (median 2.3 kg) in the megestrol acetate plus ibuprofen group (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Additionally, an improvement in quality-of-life scores (measured by EuroQol-EQ-5D to provide a single index value for health status) was seen in the megestrol acetate plus ibuprofen group (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). Venous thrombosis occurred in three patients (one receiving megestrol acetate and placebo and two receiving megestrol acetate and ibuprofen). Upper gastrointestinal tract bleeding was recorded in three patients (one receiving megestrol acetate and placebo (fatal) and two receiving megestrol acetate and ibuprofen).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0269216312441382">
<title>Indometacin for cancer cachexia</title>
<p>A single RCT involving 135 cancer patients (solid tumours) and insidious weight loss examined indometacin in the treatment of cachexia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269216312441382">26</xref></sup> Participants were randomized to receive indometacin 100 mg (<italic>n</italic>=45), prednisolone 20 mg (<italic>n</italic>=45) or placebo (<italic>n</italic>=45) until death. No other established tumour treatment was available to the patients. Follow-up was performed every three months until death. It was expected that the study would take up to five years to complete, with the first evaluation planned when the 130th participant was included. However, due to the improved survival and palliation in both treatment groups (compared to the placebo group), the results were reported after the 130th participant data was analysed. No significant differences were seen between indometacin and placebo with regard to body weight, arm circumference or hand grip strength. However, the indometacin group maintained Karnofsky index scores at a significantly higher level, indicative of higher functional ability (<italic>P</italic>=0.03, placebo vs. indometacin and prednisolone vs. placebo); C-RP was lower in the indometacin group on follow-up (49.0 ± 5.00 mg/litre compared to 54.0 ± 4.0 mg/litre in the placebo group – non significant difference) and almost doubled survival time compared to placebo (<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.07). No serious adverse events were recorded for patients on indometacin treatment.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section16-0269216312441382" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="section17-0269216312441382">
<title>Principal findings of the review</title>
<p>Too few studies have been performed to allow a robust conclusion to be formed with regard to the effectiveness of NSAIDs in the treatment of cachexia in an advanced cancer population. Consequently, there is insufficient evidence to recommend the use of these drugs in clinical practice. However, the studies included in the review provide some evidence for a positive therapeutic effect on quality of life, performance status, inflammatory markers, weight gain and survival. The main limitations seen in the four studies in this review include the small sample sizes recruited and high attrition rates, which compound the difficulties in determining, with any degree of statistical significance, the impact of NSAIDs for the management of cancer cachexia. Weight (kg) was reported in all studies. However, due to the specific catabolic mediators associated with cancer cachexia and the preferential wasting of muscle mass, any decision made about potential treatments needs to demonstrate a positive impact on lean muscle mass and ensure that weight gain is not merely fat or water. Therefore, body composition measurements including weight, lean muscle mass, fat mass and water mass, most commonly using DEXA and bioelectrical impedance (BIA), as used in two studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269216312441382">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269216312441382">25</xref></sup> are a more definitive way of measuring this effect. In examining NSAIDs for cancer cachexia it is salient to bear in mind the side-effects of this group of drugs, particularly due to the frailty and polysymptomatic nature of this patient cohort. The risk of renal and hepatic impairment and gastro-intestinal bleeding underscores the caution that should be used in this patient population and clinicians should work towards providing the lowest effective dose of NSAIDs for the shortest period of time. Treatment with NSAIDs should be reviewed periodically due to the risk of serious adverse events, particularly in older people,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269216312441382">27</xref></sup> in whom cancer is also more common.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0269216312441382">
<title>Strengths and weaknesses of the review</title>
<p>While several systematic reviews have been published in relation to potential treatments for cancer cachexia, such as thalidomide,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269216312441382">28</xref></sup> megestrol acetate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269216312441382">13</xref></sup> and omega 3 fatty acids,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269216312441382">14</xref></sup> this paper presents a comprehensive systematic review of NSAIDs as a treatment for cancer cachexia. This review has sought to gain data from RCTs using NSAIDs to treat cancer cachexia. While substantial efforts have been made to gather all available data, it is accepted that unpublished or grey literature which is not easily accessible may be available. No such data is included in this review. Additionally, the results of this review focus on the physical aspects of cancer cachexia and the primary outcome measured is body composition, as this provides the most reliable measure of treatment effect on lean body mass. However, the psychosocial ramifications of cancer cachexia are acknowledged within the literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269216312441382">5</xref></sup> and it is accepted that they also require intervention, but this was beyond the remit of this paper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0269216312441382">
<title>What is already known about this topic and what this review adds</title>
<p>Clinical management of cancer cachexia continues to be a challenge and this has been compounded by lack of clarity regarding the definition of cachexia and lack of guidelines for its management. This review contributes to the knowledge base on treatment for cancer cachexia by systematically reviewing the effectiveness and safety of NSAIDs for this patient cohort.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0269216312441382">
<title>Implications of the review</title>
<p>The dearth of evidence in this field and the limitations of the studies identified highlight the challenges of conducting RCTs in this patient cohort. Perhaps the most significant challenge is that a consensus on defining cancer cachexia has only just been reached.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269216312441382">1</xref></sup> This is reflective of the lack of uniformity in the inclusion criteria in RCTs and reviewed studies, which compounds the difficulties in comparing results across trials. Cachexia trials, like palliative care trials in general, frequently recruit end-stage, frail patients and have high attrition rates, making compliance and completion problematic. In relation to cancer cachexia, such trials will not benefit patients who may have gained from earlier intervention<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269216312441382">29</xref></sup> and evidence suggests that the mechanisms associated with cancer cachexia are functioning in the early stages of the disease, signifying that anti-cachexia treatment may be effective in preventing or delaying the onset of this complex syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0269216312441382">30</xref></sup> Therefore, a cancer cachexia NSAID trial should be designed to run alongside first-line chemotherapy treatment for patients who, on initial cancer diagnosis, have ‘pre-cachexia’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0269216312441382">31</xref></sup> Pre-cachexia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0269216312441382">Table 4</xref>) includes patients with cancer who have a small amount of weight loss, a chronic or inflammatory response or anorexia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269216312441382">32</xref></sup> Recruiting patients at this stage as opposed to end-stage disease, where attrition rates are highest (63%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269216312441382">24</xref></sup>) and inclusion criteria have traditionally been variable and therefore not comparable across trials, could assist future trial development. Not only would the use of such a definition assist recruitment of a homogenous patient population across future trials, but it would also facilitate trials aimed at averting or impeding changes in body composition and nutritional complications associated with cachexia in the cancer population.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0269216312441382" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Definition of Pre-cachexia.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0269216312441382" xlink:href="10.1177_0269216312441382-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Pre-cachexia is defined on the presence of all of the following:</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1) Underlying chronic disease
<break/>2) Unintentional weight loss ≤5% of usual body weight during the last six months
<break/>3) Chronic or recurrent systemic inflammatory response
<break/>4) Anorexia or anorexia-related symptoms</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0269216312441382"><p>Source: Muscaritoli et al. (2010)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269216312441382">32</xref></sup></p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>While future trials aim to increase understanding of cachexia and potential treatment modalities, it is imperative that such studies employ outcome measures that are meaningful to patients. One such patient-centred objective end-point may be ‘non-exercise physical activity’ (e.g. walking), which is a substantial component of functional status and independence and is pertinent when assessing treatment effects of anti-cachexia therapies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269216312441382">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0269216312441382">33</xref></sup> The drive to establish accurate quantification of physical activity and energy expenditure during activities of daily living has led to the development of devices such as the ActivPal<sup>TM</sup>. <italic>This</italic> is an electronic device which attaches securely onto the thigh and records physical activity data. The validity and reliability of <italic>Acticv</italic>PAL™ has been established.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0269216312441382">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269216312441382">35</xref></sup> A feasibility study has demonstrated that the ActivPal<sup>TM</sup> is acceptable to patients and the authors outlined its potential future utility in cancer cachexia trials.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269216312441382">36</xref></sup> Incorporating endpoints such as non-exercise physical activity into future cachexia trials may help to establish the clinical meaningfulness of future treatment modalities as it could provide insight into patients’ physical and social capabilities and their overall quality of life. Additionally, the sustained application of agreed, clinically meaningful, patient-centred endpoints in future cachexia studies will assist the comparison of data across trials and ultimately facilitate systematic and meta-analysis of results.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section21-0269216312441382" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Inflammation plays an important role in cancer cachexia, yet very few studies have examined whether NSAIDs can reverse or ameliorate this syndrome of advanced cancer. Studies of this type have demonstrated the potential role that NSAIDs may have in halting weight loss due to cachexia by suppressing inflammation, along with providing improvement in quality of life and survival. Unfortunately, such studies have not generated sufficient data to make definitive recommendations for their use in cancer cachexia management. Therefore, there appears to be sufficient merit in conducting further trials into the use of NSAIDs for cancer cachexia. Additionally, future RCTs require significantly higher patient numbers, recruitment of patients at an earlier juncture of their cachexia journey, measures of compliance with treatment, and incorporation of patient-centred endpoints to draw definitive conclusions about the effectiveness of NSAIDs, either solely or in multi-modal therapies, for cachexia management.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0269216312441382">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bosaeus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Definition and classification of cancer cachexia: an international consensus</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0269216312441382">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of cancer cachexia</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>89</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0269216312441382">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical epidemiology of cancer cachexia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bruera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higginson</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Cachexia-Anorexia in Cancer Patients</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>1996</year>, pp. <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0269216312441382">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burckart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of muscle wasting in cancer cachexia: targeted anabolic and anticatabolic therapies</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0269216312441382">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitzsimons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The experience of cancer cachexia: a qualitative study of advanced cancer patients and their family members</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs Stud</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>606</fpage>–<lpage>616</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0269216312441382">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trebble</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Thalidomide in the treatment of cancer cachexia: a randomised placebo controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>54</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0269216312441382">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madeddu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Randomised phase III clinical trial of five different arms of treatment in 332 patients with cancer cachexia</article-title>. <source>The Oncologist</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0269216312441382">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of extended ibuprofen administration on cortisol, interleukin-6 and the acute phase protein response in colorectal cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>534</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0269216312441382">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of ibuprofen on the acute-phase response and protein metabolism in patients with cancer and weight loss</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source> <year>199</year>; <volume>82</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0269216312441382">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maddocks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity level as an outcome measure for use in cancer cachexia trials: a feasibility study</article-title>. <source>Support Care Cancer</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1539</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0269216312441382">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radbruch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elsner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trottenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <source>Clinical practice guidelines on cancer cachexia in advanced cancer patients</source>. <publisher-name>Aachen, Department of Palliative Medicine/European Palliative Care Research Collaborative</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0269216312441382">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Providing care for palliative cancer patients who have cachexia: are we meeting the challenge?</article-title> <source>Cancer Nursing Practice</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0269216312441382">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berenstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Megestrol acetate for treatment of anorexia-cachexia syndrome</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source> <year>2005</year>; <fpage>2</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0269216312441382">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baughan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA, an omega-3 fatty acid from fish oils) for the treatment of cancer cachexia</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source> <year>2007</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0269216312441382">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macciò</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madeddu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A phase II study with antioxidants, both in the diet and supplemented, pharmaconutritional support, progestagen, and anti-cyclooxygenase-2 showing efficacy and safety in patients with cancer-related anorexia/cachexia and oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0269216312441382">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cercheitti</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Navigante</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peluffo</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diament</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stillitani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cabalar</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of celecoxib, medroxyprogesterone, and dietary intervention on systemic syndromes in patients with advanced lung adenocarcinoma: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0269216312441382">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lundholm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daneryd</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bosaeus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindholm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Palliative nutritional intervention in addition to cyclooxygenase and erythropoietin treatment for patients with malignant disease: Effects on survival, metabolism, and function</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>100</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1967</fpage>–<lpage>1977</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0269216312441382">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lundholm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daneryd</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hyltander</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bosaeus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evidence that long-term COX-treatment improves energy homeostasis and body composition in cancer patients with progressive cachexia</article-title>. <source>Int J Oncol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0269216312441382">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Gorman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McArdle</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A pilot study of megestrol acetate and ibuprofen in the treatment of cachexia in gastrointestinal cancerpatients</article-title>. <source>Cancer Research Campaign</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0269216312441382">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falconer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plester</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maingay</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ibuprofen reduces energy expenditure and acute-phase protein production compared with placebo in pancreatic cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>72</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0269216312441382">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jadad</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the quality of reports of randomized clinical trials: is blinding necessary?</article-title> <source>Contr Clin Trials</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0269216312441382">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tuech</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Methodological Quality and Reporting of Ethical Requirements in Phase III Cancer Trials</article-title>. <source>J Med Ethics</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0269216312441382">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Results of a pilot study of the effects of celecoxib on cancer cachexia in patients with cancer of the head, neck, and gastrointestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Head and Neck</source>, <year>2008</year>; <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0269216312441382">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Gorman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McArdle</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A prospective randomized study of megestrol acetate and ibuprofen in gastrointestinal cancer patients with weight loss</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>79</volume>(<issue>3-4</issue>): <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0269216312441382">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cerchietti</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Navigante</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of eicosapentaenoic and docosahexaenoic n-3 fatty acids from fish oil and preferential Cox-2 inhibition on systemic syndromes in patients with advanced lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Nutr Canc</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0269216312441382">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lundholm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hyltander</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lönnroth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandström</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svaninger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Körner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gülich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kärrefors</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory treatment may prolong survival in undernourished patients with metastatic solid tumors</article-title>. <source>Canc Res</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>54</volume>(<issue>21</issue>): <fpage>5602</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0269216312441382">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<source>British National Formulary</source>, BNF No. 62, <month>September</month> <year>2011</year>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bnf.org/bnf/bnf/current/">http://bnf.org/bnf/bnf/current/</ext-link> (<access-date>date accessed 30/01/2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0269216312441382">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cantwell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cardwell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Thalidomide for managing cancer cachexia (Protocol)</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source>. <year>2010</year>: <fpage>9</fpage> DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD008664</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0269216312441382">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cancer cachexia and targeting chronic inflammation: A unified approach to cancer treatment and palliative/supportive care</article-title>. <source>Support Oncol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0269216312441382">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muscaritoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bossola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aversa</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellantoneb</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fanellia</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevention and treatment of cancer cachexia: New insights into an old problem</article-title>. <source>Eur J Canc</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>41.31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0269216312441382">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cancer cachexia: Developing multimodal therapy for a multidimensional problem</article-title>. <source>Eur J Canc</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1124</fpage>–<lpage>1132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0269216312441382">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muscaritoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anker</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Argiles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aversa</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biolo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Consensus definition of sarcopenia, cachexia and pre-cachexia: joint document elaborated by Special Interest Groups (SIG) “cachexia–anorexia in chronic wasting diseases” and “nutrition in geriatrics”</article-title> <source>Clin Nutr</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0269216312441382">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Research methodology: cancer cachexia syndrome</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0269216312441382">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tigbe</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Granat</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The validity and reliability of a novel activity monitor as a measure of walking</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source> <volume>2006</volume>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0269216312441382">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>MDP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Granat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Activity-monitor accuracy in measuring step number and cadence in community-dwelling older adults</article-title>. <source>J Aging Phys Activ</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0269216312441382">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maddocks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity level as an outcome measure for use in cancer cachexia trials: a feasibility study</article-title>. <source>Support Care Canc</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1539</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>