<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sperg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Ergonomics in Design: The Quarterly of Human Factors Applications</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1064-8046</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1064804612463694</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1064804612463694</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Features</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Improving the Accessibility of Investigation Reports Using Safety Factor Maps</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>Mark W.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>Renee</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>20</fpage>
<lpage>24</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Safety factor maps can provide a visual summary of the events associated with accidents and incidents. Because they employ conceptual mapping techniques, they enable both a hierarchical and temporal representation of the antecedents of an adverse event. We describe the development of safety factor maps and a strategy to assess both the reliability and the validity of the maps that are constructed. Our initial findings suggest that they have the potential to improve the accessibility of the outcomes of investigation reports.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>accidents</kwd>
<kwd>safety factor maps</kwd>
<kwd>conceptual mapping</kwd>
<kwd>accessibility</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Safety factor maps have the potential to reduce accident risk by more effectively communicating the precursors and outcomes of incidents.</p>
<p><bold>In recent years, advances in accident</bold> investigation technologies and approaches have resulted in a much more detailed and, many would argue, much more accurate understanding of the circumstances that precede aircraft accidents and incidents. However, the volume of occurrence reports that are generated, together with the complexity of these reports, potentially limits the accessibility of the outcomes to users within the operational environment.</p>
<p>We sought to use knowledge acquisition techniques to develop usable representations of both the elements of accidents or incidents and the relationship between these elements. Ultimately, our aim is to increase the accessibility of the information arising from occurrence reports, thereby facilitating translation of the outcomes into operational practice.</p>
<p>In this article, we describe the process and outcomes of safety factor mapping in the context of aviation occurrences. However, principles described can be applied across a range of industrial environments to improve the uptake of safety-related information.</p>
<sec id="section1-1064804612463694">
<title>Concept Mapping Applied to Safety Factor Maps</title>
<p>Knowledge acquisition involves the exploration of a construct at different levels of explanation that broadly reflect the complexity of the relationship between components. This process is consistent with the principles associated with accident and incident causation. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1064804612463694">Walker and Bills (2008)</xref> described the process of accident investigation as one that involves the elucidation of factors at different levels within a system and with differing proximity to the event.</p>
<p>We approached the problem of communicating the antecedents of accidents and incidents by drawing on a specific type of knowledge acquisition, referred to as <italic>concept mapping</italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1064804612463694">Novak, 1998</xref>). Concept mapping is a technique that represents complex ideas and arguments in a visual form that facilitates learning and understanding. It has been widely used in education (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1064804612463694">Tergan, Gräber, &amp; Neumann, 2006</xref>) and business (e.g., Cousins &amp; MacDonald, 1998) to successfully augment text-based information.</p>
<p>In our approach, we used the principles of concept mapping to develop visual depictions of the safety factors that were highlighted in previously published investigation reports. These visual depictions, known as <italic>safety factor maps</italic>, were designed to provide accurate summaries of the outcomes of investigation reports.</p>
<p>The advantage of using safety factors as the basis of visual representations of the antecedents of accidents and incidents is that they can be considered “concepts” for the purposes of the concept-mapping technique. Safety factors are events or conditions that increase safety risk, and they involve different levels of representation, including individual actions, technical failures, local conditions, risk controls, and organizational influences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1064804612463694">Walker &amp; Bills, 2008</xref>). Whereas organizational influences constitute the greatest level of representation, the individual actions of the operator represent the least.</p>
<p>Individual actions are any observable behavior performed by operational personnel that increases the risk of an occurrence. Operational personnel include any person(s) who has a relatively direct impact on the safety of a transport activity. Local conditions are immediate, contextual, or environmental conditions that have an adverse influence on individual actions. Finally, risk controls include problems with the preventive and recovery measures put in place by an organization to facilitate and ensure safe performance of the operational components of the system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1064804612463694">Walker &amp; Bills, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Risk controls are divided into five categories that include the influence of all relevant organizations that exercise control over risk (e.g., operators, maintenance organizations, air traffic services providers, equipment manufacturers, aerodrome operators): (a) equipment, (b) facilities and infrastructure, (c) procedures, (d) training and assessment, and (e) people management. Organizational influences are problems with the conditions that establish, maintain, or otherwise influence the effectiveness of an organization’s risk controls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1064804612463694">Walker &amp; Bills, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>In the context of accident investigation, higher levels of production are assumed to contribute to lower levels to a greater or lesser degree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1064804612463694">Reason, 1997</xref>). Therefore, the nature of these relationships needs to be depicted on safety factor maps. We represented these hierarchical relationships between safety factors as either a solid line or a broken line, depending on the proximate relationship between the safety factors and, ultimately, the occurrence. A solid line represents a causal relationship, whereby the subsequent safety factor would probably not have occurred in the absence of the preceding safety factor. A broken line reflects an indirect relationship, whereby the two safety factors were presumed to be related, but the relationship was not necessarily causal.</p>
<p>In addition to the hierarchical relationships between safety factors, there are some safety factors that emerge during a period preceding the occurrence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1064804612463694">Elvik, 2006</xref>). Therefore, it was important to incorporate a temporal dimension into the safety factor maps.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1064804612463694">
<title>Constructing the Safety Factor Maps</title>
<p>Given that the safety factor maps were developed from published accident and incident investigation reports, it was necessary to establish whether they accurately reflected the nature of the occurrences that were described in the reports. To begin this process, two coders developed safety factor maps independently, and then tests of interrater reliability were used to establish the congruence of the maps that were developed. Coders read through an investigation report and constructed a map that they considered best represented the sequence of events. For the purposes of an initial evaluation of the process, they were asked to develop 10 maps based on the same number of occurrences.</p>
<p>The 10 occurrences that were included in the interrater reliability analysis were selected at random from an Australian database of aircraft accidents and incidents that occurred between 1999 and 2004. We examined interrater reliability by assessing the consistency between the two raters as to the number and types of safety factors identified, the nature of the relationships between safety factors, and the nature of the temporal dimensions.</p>
<p>Overall, the comparison revealed 98.99% agreement between the two coders for both the number and types of safety factors that were identified in the reports and that were represented in safety factor maps. A mean 54.44% agreement was evident between the two coders for the relationships that were identified in the reports. However, it is important to note that initial agreement ranged from 33% for more complex cases to 80% agreement for less complex events. This range reflects the difficulty in extracting and representing the relationships between safety factors when previously published incident reports are used as the source. Although disagreements can be resolved through discussion between raters, ideally, safety factor maps would be generated by aircraft accident investigators as part of the investigation process, thereby obviating the difficulties associated with subsequent interpretations.</p>
<p>In contrast to the level of agreement evident between raters’ assessments of the relationship between safety factors, there was 94% (range of 83% to 100%) agreement between raters’ depictions of the sequence of events preceding the occurrence. Therefore, we concluded that it was possible to develop safety factor maps with a reasonable degree of reliability and that this was an important first step in developing accurate safety factor maps.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1064804612463694">
<title>Evaluating the Safety Factor Maps</title>
<p>A total of 31 first-year psychology students (25 females and 8 males) assisted in reviewing the utility of the safety factor maps. This sample was selected on the basis that they would have little or no knowledge of the domain and, therefore, would represent the least experienced users of safety factor maps. A descriptive analysis of the group revealed that 93.9% of the sample did not have any professional experience related to aviation and that they had a mean age of 22 (<italic>SD</italic> = 6.47).</p>
<p>For the purposes of the evaluation, we selected four safety factor maps at random from the series of 10 prototypes that were created originally (Occurrences 200003293, 200002379, 200000492, and 199903463). They were presented in a booklet (counterbalanced) in which reviewers were asked to initially describe the events or conditions that they considered were associated with the occurrence depicted in the safety factor map (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1064804612463694">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1064804612463694" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>An example of a safety factor map.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1064804612463694-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Having completed this phase, participants were asked to answer four multiple-choice, knowledge-based questions pertaining to the accident or incident that were derived from the original report. These questions were designed to assess reviewers’ understanding of the significant factors involved in the occurrence (e.g., How many factors contributed to the unsafe procedure for simulating a one-engine inoperative?), their understanding of the causal relationships that were depicted (e.g., According to the map, did the air traffic controller’s stress and anxiety levels contribute to the level of fatigue?), and their understanding of the temporal nature of the relationships between significant factors (e.g., When did the pilot perform an inappropriate handling technique?). In each case, three multiple-choice options were available, so that in response to “The air traffic controller’s stress and anxiety level contributed to . . .,” the options were (a) a communication error, (b) a monitoring and checking error, or (c) both.</p>
<p>To assess the utility of the safety maps, we first examined the accuracy of reviewers’ responses to the various questions. This phase was important because it tested whether the interpretations that arose from the safety factor maps were consistent with the reports from which they were derived. Overall, a comparative analysis indicated a mean 62.5% accuracy in the interpretation of the maps. This outcome was greater than would have been predicted by chance (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1064804612463694">Table 1</xref>), suggesting that the safety factor maps enabled the identification of safety factors and yielded interpretations that were broadly consistent with the occurrence report.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1064804612463694" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Accuracy of Safety Factor Maps and Comparison Against Chance</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1064804612463694" xlink:href="10.1177_1064804612463694-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Map</th>
<th align="center">Mean Accuracy</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Test Outcomes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Safety Factor Map 1</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td><italic>t</italic>(31) = 4.25, <italic>p</italic> ← .01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Safety Factor Map 2</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td><italic>t</italic>(31) = 4.49, <italic>p</italic> ← .01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Safety Factor Map 3</td>
<td>2.58</td>
<td><italic>t</italic>(31) = 3.26, <italic>p</italic> ← .01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Safety Factor Map 4</td>
<td>2.39</td>
<td><italic>t</italic>(31) = 2.39, <italic>p</italic> ← .01</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>This outcome is important, given that the participants lacked experience in safety factor maps or the domain and that the incidents ranged in complexity. On this basis, it might be surmised that further improvements in performance are likely to be related to experience in the domain, particularly in relation to users’ understanding of the nature of the environment in which the event occurred.</p>
<p>To assist with further design-related improvements to the safety factor maps, participants were asked to rate their perceptions of a number of features, including their perceived understanding of the maps, their impressions of the visual design of the maps, and their confidence in their interpretations of the information depicted on the map. The outcomes are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1064804612463694">Table 2</xref> and indicate that raters perceived some difficulty in the interpretation of displays, particularly in terms of the relationships between safety factors. Otherwise, positive ratings were evident in raters’ overall understanding of the maps and their confidence in the accuracy of their interpretations of the maps.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1064804612463694" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mean Ratings for Features of the Safety Factor Maps</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1064804612463694" xlink:href="10.1177_1064804612463694-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Feature</th>
<th align="center">Mean Rating (Standard Deviation)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Understood the safety factor maps</td>
<td>5.42 (1.01)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interpretation was clear</td>
<td>3.19 (1.85)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liked the visual design</td>
<td>5.61 (1.15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sufficient information</td>
<td>4.32 (1.54)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Color schemes helped understanding</td>
<td>5.39 (1.61)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Relevance of color schemes was clear</td>
<td>5.23 (0.99)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Confident of correct interpretation</td>
<td>4.87 (1.52)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sure about the meaning of connecting lines</td>
<td>4.00 (1.93)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Text was clear and readable</td>
<td>5.87 (1.18)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1064804612463694">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Scale from 1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic> to 7 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>. These statements were reverse scored.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1064804612463694">
<title>Implications and Suggestions</title>
<p>Our initial aim in this project was to determine whether concept mapping is a technique that could be used to depict visually both safety factors and the relationship between safety factors that emerged from accident and incident investigation reports. The broader goal was to augment the utility of accident reports and provide a visual summary that would potentially ease the interpretability of the information and thereby increase the accessibility of information. We considered that, at least in part, the great value of occurrence reports lies in their capacity to effect changes at the operational level of performance. However, this capability depends on the accessibility of information.</p>
<p>To ensure the accessibility of the material arising from accident and incident investigations, we consider the generation of safety factor maps as a process that should normally occur coincident with the development of an investigation report, the outcomes of which would be attached to the report as an addendum. Investigators themselves would be ideally suited to develop the maps, as they are best placed to represent the nuances associated with the sequences of events that preceded occurrences. This process would ensure that the safety factor maps that are generated clearly reflect the outcomes of the investigation process.</p>
<p>Although the development of safety factor maps as part of an investigation is optimal, this is not always possible, and our experience has demonstrated that useful information can be drawn from safety factor maps even if they are constructed following publication of the investigation report. However, in development of these safety factor maps, some important principles need to be considered to ensure that they both are useful and reflect the complexities associated with the occurrence.</p>
<p>In the first instance, it is important to adopt a well-established hierarchy of concepts that will enable the identification and categorization of the various safety factors. This hierarchy provides a level of structure for the subsequent representation of the factors, which increases the safety factor maps’ reliability and comparability. Thereafter, an accident or incident investigation report is examined to extract the safety factors that might have been associated with the occurrence. In doing so, it is clearly important to avoid supposition or the interpretation of factors that are not otherwise stated explicitly.</p>
<p>The hierarchy of concepts provides a framework for the representation of safety factors both at different levels of production and in temporal space. This framework enables a representation whereby higher levels of production, such as organizational factors, can be represented in relation to lower levels of production, such as individual actions. After the factors have been identified for each category, their relationship needs to be represented either as an immediate or as a delayed association. This step reflects the fact that in many occurrences, the relationships may emerge over time.</p>
<p>To ensure that the safety factors identified and their representation correspond as closely as possible to the original report, we advocate the use of at least two independent coders. The presence of two coders ensures a degree of reliability in the safety factor maps that are generated and increases the likelihood that items are included that might otherwise be overlooked. The result is a more comprehensive and, ultimately, more accurate representation of the sequence of factors that preceded an event.</p>
<p>In the selection of coders, consideration should be given to their familiarity with the domain and the conceptual hierarchy that underpins the safety factor maps. Expertise in the domain is not necessary and may, in fact, create difficulties when experts are inclined to read into reports safety factors that are not explicitly stated. Inevitably, a balance must be struck between the accuracy of the safety factor map as a representation of the report and the perceived accuracy of the map as a representation of the events that preceded the event.</p>
<p>In ensuring that the safety factor maps correspond as closely as possible to the investigation reports, one should test the validity of safety factor maps using participants who are naive to the domain. Naive participants represent those users who are likely to experience the greatest difficulty in accurately interpreting the safety factor maps. Therefore, we advocate an approach whereby interpretations of the safety factor maps are compared with the actual events outlined in the accident or incident report. This approach serves to ensure that the safety factor maps are, as closely as possible, a representation of the investigation reports from which they were derived.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1064804612463694">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our goal was to develop a strategy that increases the accessibility of the outcomes of accident and incident investigation reports. We approached the problem using a conceptual mapping framework in which we designed both a hierarchical and a temporal representation of the antecedents of adverse events based on the outcomes of published accident reports. We subsequently developed a strategy to test the reliability and validity of the safety factor maps to ensure their utility in the operational context.</p>
<p>Although opportunities remain to further improve the representation of the antecedents of adverse events, we have established an initial process that should, in time, improve the accessibility of accident- and incident-related information.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Funding for this research was provided by the Australian Transport Safety Bureau.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<p><bold>Mark Wiggins</bold> is an associate professor of organizational psychology and deputy director of the Centre for Elite Performance, Expertise, and Training at Macquarie University, Sydney, Australia. He received his PhD in psychology from the University of Otago in 2001.</p>
<p><bold>Renee Glass</bold> is a lead user experience researcher for Telstra, Australia’s largest telecommunications company. She received her PhD in psychology from the University of Western Sydney in 2007.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1064804612463694">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cousins</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Conceptualizing the successful product development as a basis for evaluating management training in technology-based companies: A participatory concept mapping application</article-title>. <source>Evaluation and Program Planning</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1064804612463694">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elvik</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Laws of accident causation</article-title>. <source>Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1064804612463694">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Learning, creating, and using knowledge: Concept maps as facilitative tools in schools and corporations</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1064804612463694">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reason</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Managing the risks of organisational accidents</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1064804612463694">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tergan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gräber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Mapping and managing knowledge and information in resource-based learning</article-title>. <source>Innovations in Education and Teaching International</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1064804612463694">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bills</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Analysis, causality, and proof in accident investigation</source> (AR-2007-053). <publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Transport Safety Bureau</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>