<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PEN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppen</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0148-6071</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2444</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0148607111432759</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0148607111432759</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Communications</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Human Leukocyte Death After a Preoperative Infusion of Medium/Long-Chain Triglyceride and Fish Oil Parenteral Emulsions</article-title>
<subtitle>A Randomized Study in Gastrointestinal Cancer Patients</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cury-Boaventura</surname><given-names>Maria Fernanda</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0148607111432759">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Torrinhas</surname><given-names>Raquel Susana Matos de Miranda</given-names></name>
<degrees>MB</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0148607111432759">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Godoy</surname><given-names>André Borella Pereira de</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0148607111432759">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Curi</surname><given-names>Rui</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0148607111432759">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Waitzberg</surname><given-names>Dan Linetzky</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0148607111432759">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0148607111432759"><label>1</label>Institute of Physical Activity and Sports Science, Cruzeiro do Sul University, São Paulo, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0148607111432759"><label>2</label>Department of Gastroenterology, Faculty of Medicine, University of São Paulo (LIM 35), São Paulo, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0148607111432759"><label>3</label>Department of Physiology and Biophysics, Institute of Biomedical Sciences, University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0148607111432759">Raquel Susana Matos de Miranda Torrinhas, Laboratório de Nutrição e Cirurgia Metabólica do Aparelho Digestivo, LIM 35, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo (FMUSP), Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 455 2° andar, sala 2108–Cerqueira César, CEP: 01246-903, São Paulo–SP, Brazil; e-mail: <email>torrinhas@uol.com.br</email> or <email>metanutri@usp.br</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>677</fpage>
<lpage>684</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>9</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Background</italic>: Parenteral lipid emulsions (LEs) can influence leukocyte functions. The authors investigated the effect of 2 LEs on leukocyte death in surgical patients with gastrointestinal cancer. <italic>Material and Methods</italic>: Twenty-five patients from a randomized, double-blind clinical trial (ID: NCT01218841) were randomly included to evaluate leukocyte death after 3 days of preoperative infusion (0.2 g fat/kg/d) of an LE composed equally of medium/long-chain triglycerides and soybean oil (MCTs/LCTs) or pure fish oil (FO). Blood samples were collected before (t0) and after LE infusion (t1) and on the third postoperative day (t2). <italic>Results</italic>: After LE infusion (t1 vs t0), MCTs/LCTs did not influence cell death; FO slightly increased the proportion of necrotic lymphocytes (5%). At the postoperative period (t2 vs t0), MCTs/LCTs tripled the proportion of apoptotic lymphocytes; FO maintained the slightly increased proportion of necrotic lymphocytes (7%) and reduced the percentage of apoptotic lymphocytes by 74%. In the postoperative period, MCT/LCT emulsion increased the proportion of apoptotic neutrophils, and FO emulsion did not change any parameter of apoptosis in the neutrophil population. There were no differences in lymphocyte or neutrophil death when MCT/LCT and FO treatments were compared during either preoperative or postoperative periods. MCT/LCTs altered the expression of 12 of 108 genes related to cell death, with both pro- and antiapoptotic effects; FO modulated the expression of 7 genes, demonstrating an antiapoptotic effect. <italic>Conclusion</italic>: In patients with gastrointestinal cancer, preoperative MCT/LCT infusion was associated with postoperative lymphocyte and neutrophil apoptosis. FO has a protective effect on postoperative lymphocyte apoptosis.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>lipids</kwd>
<kwd>fatty acids</kwd>
<kwd>parenteral nutrition</kwd>
<kwd>trauma</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0148607111432759">
<title>Clinical Relevancy Statement</title>
<p>Commercial parenteral lipid emulsions (LEs) containing medium/long-chain triglycerides (MCTs/LCTs) or based in fish oil (FO) were designed to provide less amounts of n-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) and higher n-3 PUFAs, respectively, than that provided by standard soybean oil LE (SO), as alternatives to minimize the risks associated with it, including potentially inflammatory and immunosuppressive effects.</p>
<p>Leukocyte death through apoptosis plays an important role for immune dysfunction observed in trauma and sepsis. We showed that, in surgical patients with gastrointestinal cancer, preoperative MCT/LCT infusion induced or did not protect against postoperative lymphocyte and neutrophil apoptosis, whereas FO has a protective effect on postoperative lymphocyte apoptosis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0148607111432759" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Lipid emulsions (LEs) are an integral part of parenteral nutrition (PN). As a source of nonglucidic energy and essential fatty acids, they contribute to the prevention of several metabolic disturbances associated with the intravenous (IV) feeding of amino acids and glucose alone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0148607111432759">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0148607111432759">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>The first well-tolerated LE was based on soybean oil (SO). SO is rich in long-chain ω-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs), which are precursors of potentially inflammatory eicosanoids. Several authors have described the impairment of neutrophil, lymphocyte, monocyte, and macrophage functions, including leukocyte death, in the context of parenteral therapy with SO emulsions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0148607111432759">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0148607111432759">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111432759"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0148607111432759"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0148607111432759"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0148607111432759">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>The impairment of leukocyte functions by SO emulsion may be related to the induction of leukocyte death. An excess of ω-6 PUFA raises the production of eicosanoids, reactive oxygen species (ROS), and reactive nitrogen species (RNS) and can cause cell death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0148607111432759">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0148607111432759">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0148607111432759">9</xref></sup> We previously reported that SO emulsion could impair immune function by decreasing lymphocyte proliferation and leading to neutrophil and lymphocyte apoptosis and necrosis in human healthy volunteers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0148607111432759">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>New LEs with different fatty acid compositions were designed for clinical use, aiming to decrease the amount of long-chain ω-6 PUFAs provided by SO. These LEs were achieved by diluting SO with medium-chain triglycerides (MCTs) or by creating LEs rich or based in long-chain ω-3 PUFAs. Commercial LEs containing 50% MCT and 50% SO (MCT/long-chain triglyceride [LCT]) may have a reduced impact on immune response because MCTs do not lead to eicosanoid synthesis and are not susceptible to lipid peroxidation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0148607111432759">2</xref></sup> Commercial lipid emulsion composed of fish oil (FO) contains a large amount of long-chain ω-3 PUFAs, which synthesize fewer inflammatory eicosanoids than ω-6 PUFA and have been shown to exert several other anti-inflammatory effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0148607111432759">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>Major abdominal surgery can lead to an intense systemic inflammatory response, which, in turn, may increase the risk of postoperative complications and multiple organ failure. Leukocyte death through apoptosis plays an important role for immune dysfunction and multiple organ failure observed in inflammatory conditions, such as trauma and sepsis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0148607111432759">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0148607111432759">11</xref></sup> Proinflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin (IL)–6, released during the surgical stress response, can induce leukocyte apoptosis and impair immune function.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111432759">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0148607111432759">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>In surgical patients, MCT/LCT emulsion prevented the impairment of bacterial killing activity of neutrophils and resulted in increased numbers of blood peripheral lymphocytes, in relation to SO emulsion,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111432759">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0148607111432759">15</xref></sup> and FO emulsion preserved the expression of leukocyte antigen HLA-DR and lymphocyte distribution and proliferation, prevented the postoperative drop in interferon (IFN)–γ release compared with SO emulsion, and also increased IL-2, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)–α, and IL-2R compared with PN without fat.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0148607111432759">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0148607111432759">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>To assess whether these positive findings regarding MCT/LCT and FO emulsions on leukocyte functions and counts in surgical patients are associated with a possible protective effect on leukocyte death, the impact of these LEs on cell viability, apoptotic markers, and expression of genes associated with cell death was investigated here in peripheral leukocytes from surgical patients with gastrointestinal cancer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0148607111432759" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section4-0148607111432759">
<title>Ethical Issues</title>
<p>The current study was carried out following the ethical recommendations of the Declaration of Helsinki and the Ethical Committee of the University of São Paulo “CAPPesq—Comissão de Ética para Análise de Projetos de Pesquisa do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo (HCFMUSP),” which approved the study protocol. All enrolled patients provided informed consent prior to the commencement of the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0148607111432759">
<title>Patient Selection</title>
<p>This prospective study evaluated 25 patients who were randomly selected from surgical patients with stomach or colon cancer enrolled in a larger study by the Department of Surgical Gastroenterology of the HCFMUSP, which was registered in the Clinical Trials Database (ID: NCT01218841). Patient selection aimed to include the first 10 patients allocated in each treatment arm of this large study who had successfully concluded the LE infusion protocol. Patients were adults (30–75 years old), had Karnofsky indices ≥60, and good venous condition suitable for parenteral therapy and blood collection. Exclusion criteria were intolerance or allergy to any ingredient of LE; diagnosis of infectious (ie, acquired immune deficiency syndrome), inflammatory (ie, arthritis), immunologic (ie, lupus), or metabolic diseases (ie, insulin-dependent diabetes); dementia; medicine intake that could significantly modulate metabolism; and implanted electromagnetic instruments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0148607111432759">
<title>LE Infusion Protocol</title>
<p>The infusion of MCT/LCT (Lipovenos MCT 10%; Fresenius Kabi, Bad Homburg, Germany) or FO (Omegavenos 10%; Fresenius Kabi) was performed in a double-blind manner. Infusion was performed for 3 days before surgery, at 0.2 g fat/kg body weight per day, for 6 hours continuously and with daily changes of exclusive peripheral venous access. Independent pharmacists (from Farmoterápica, SP Brazil) prepared LE bags according to a computer-generated randomized list.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0148607111432759">
<title>Cell Isolation</title>
<p>Immediately before the start of LE infusion (basal, t0), at the end of LE infusion (preoperative, t1), and on the third postoperative day (postoperative, t2), peripheral blood samples were collected in tubes containing ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA; 1 mg/mL) and analyzed for leukocyte death at the Department of Physiology and Biophysics, Institute of Biomedical Sciences, University of Sao Paulo. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs; a mixture of monocytes and lymphocytes) and neutrophils were isolated by Ficoll-Hypaque density gradient centrifugation. Blood was diluted in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; 1:1), added to a BD Falcon conical tube (BD Biosciences, San Diego, CA) containing HistopAQue-1077, and centrifuged (Harrier 18/80; Sanyo, London, UK) for 30 minutes at 800 <italic>g</italic> and 4°C. PBMCs were collected from the interphase and washed once with PBS. Neutrophils were isolated from the inferior sediment after erythrocytes were lysed with lysis buffer (150 mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 0.1 mM EDTA, pH 7.4). The PBMCs remained in RPMI 1640 medium for 30 minutes to allow monocytes to adhere to the plates. Next, the supernatant medium containing lymphocytes was collected to obtain a pure lymphocyte preparation (approximately 98%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0148607111432759">18</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0148607111432759">
<title>Cell Viability</title>
<p>Cells were centrifuged at 1000 <italic>g</italic> for 15 minutes at 4°C, and the obtained pellet was resuspended in 500 µL of PBS. Next, 50 µL of propidium iodide (PI) solution (50 mg/mL in PBS) was added, and the cells were analyzed using a FACSCalibur flow cytometer (BD Biosciences). PI is a highly water-soluble fluorescent compound that is excluded from viable cells. In cells that have lost membrane integrity, PI binds to DNA by intercalating between the bases with little or no sequence preference. Cell fluorescence was measured using the FL2 channel (orange-red fluorescence, 585/42 nm). Ten thousand events were analyzed per experiment. Cells with PI fluorescence were then evaluated using Cell Quest software (Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0148607111432759">
<title>DNA Fragmentation</title>
<p>DNA fragmentation was determined by flow cytometry after DNA staining with PI according to the method described by Nicoletti et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0148607111432759">19</xref></sup> Cells were resuspended in a solution containing detergents to allow the prompt incorporation of the dye into DNA. Briefly, cells were centrifuged at 1000 <italic>g</italic> for 15 minutes at 4°C. The pellet was gently resuspended in 300 µL hypotonic solution containing 50 µ/mL PI, 0.1% sodium citrate, and 0.1% Triton X-100. The cells were then incubated for 2 hours at room temperature. Fluorescence was determined by flow cytometry, as described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0148607111432759">
<title>Phosphatidylserine Externalization</title>
<p>Phosphatidylserine (PS) externalization was analyzed by flow cytometry after PS staining with annexin V–FITC, according to the method described by Vermes et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0148607111432759">20</xref></sup> Cells (1 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0148607111432759">6</xref></sup>) were washed twice with cold PBS and resuspended in 100 µL binding buffer (10 mM HEPES/NaOH, 140 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>); then, 5 µL of fluorescein-conjugated annexin V (annexin V–FITC) was added. Cells were gently agitated and incubated for 15 minutes in the dark at room temperature (20–25°C). Next, 10 µL of PI solution and 400 µL of binding buffer were added and cells were analyzed by flow cytometry. Annexin V–FITC fluorescence was measured in the FL1 channel (green fluorescence, 530/30 nm), and PI was measured in the FL2 channel (orange-red fluorescence, 585/42 nm) of a flow cytometer, as described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0148607111432759">
<title>Mitochondrial Transmembrane Potential</title>
<p>Cells were centrifuged at 1000 <italic>g</italic>, for 15 minutes at 4°C, and the pellet was resuspended in 1000 µL PBS. Rhodamine 123 is a cell-permeable, cationic, fluorescent dye that is readily sequestered by active mitochondria without inducing toxic effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0148607111432759">21</xref></sup> Rhodamine 123 (5 µM) was added and the cells were then incubated for 15 minutes at 37°C in the dark. Cells were washed twice with cold PBS and incubated for 30 minutes at 30°C in the dark. Fluorescence was determined using the FL1 channel (green fluorescence, 530/30 nm) of a flow cytometer, as described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0148607111432759">
<title>Gene Expression</title>
<p>Postoperative gene expression was evaluated in lymphocytes by comparing data from t0 and t1 samples and using the Codelink Expression Bioarray System (16-Assay Bioarray Hybridization and Detection) from Amersham Biosciences (Piscataway, NJ). The 16-Assay Bioarray Hybridization and Detection consists of 16 independent arrays and hybridization chambers in the space of a standard glass slide containing 800 genes related to inflammation, of which 108 were involved in cell death. We first obtained total RNA from lymphocytes and bacterial controls. We used the purified sample total RNA to prepare the first-strand cDNA synthesis (42°C, 2 hours) and second-strand cDNA (16°C, 2 hours). We incubated purified cDNA at 37°C for 14 hours to evaluate in vitro transcription and biotin labeling of cRNA. cRNA was fragmented at 94°C for 20 minutes and incubated at 37°C for 18–24 hours for hybridization. The slide was washed, stained with Cy5-streptavidin, and scanned using the GenePix 4000B (Union City, CA, USA). We analyzed the scanned image with Codelink Expression Analysis Software. Only signals that differed from the control by at least 2-fold in 2 independent experiments were considered significant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0148607111432759">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Results are presented as means ± SEM. The results were compared regarding treatment and time by 2-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and repeated measures with the Bonferroni posttest (GraphPad Prism version 4.0 for Windows; GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). The level of significance was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0148607111432759" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section15-0148607111432759">
<title>Description of Patients</title>
<p>Patient randomization was considered adequate because no differences in the mean descriptive characteristics (age, gender, type of tumor, nutrition status,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0148607111432759">22</xref></sup> type of open surgery, or comorbidities) were found between the patient populations of the 2 groups (χ<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic> ≥ .3169; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0148607111432759">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0148607111432759" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of Surgical Patients With Gastrointestinal Cancer Treated Preoperatively With a Parenteral Lipid Emulsion Composed of a Physical Mixture of Soybean Oil and MCT/LCT or a Parenteral Lipid Emulsion of Pure FO, According to Their Descriptive Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0148607111432759" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111432759-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Characteristics</th>
<th align="center">FO</th>
<th align="center">MCT/LCT</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Tumor site</td>
<td>Stomach</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>.1413</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Colon</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>7</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td>Male</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>.8908</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Female</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nutrition status<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111432759">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>Eutrophic</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>.8219</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Risk of malnutrition</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>8</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Malnutrition</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Open surgery<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111432759">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>Curative</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>.1591</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Palliative</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age, y</td>
<td/>
<td>55 ± 9</td>
<td>62 ± 11</td>
<td>.0725</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Comorbidities<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0148607111432759">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>.7896</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>8</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0148607111432759">
<p>FO, fish oil; LCT, long-chain triglyceride; MCT, medium-chain triglyceride.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0148607111432759">
<label>a</label>
<p>Scored patient-generated subjective global assessment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0148607111432759">22</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0148607111432759">
<label>b</label>
<p>Hypertension, nonsevere dyslipidemia, or non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus II in addition to basis disease.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0148607111432759">
<title>Leukocyte Death</title>
<p>The effect of LE infusion on leukocyte death before surgical trauma was assessed by comparing data from t0 and t1. In lymphocytes, MCT/LCT emulsion did not alter cell viability, PS externalization, DNA fragmentation, or mitochondrial depolarization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">Figure 1</xref>); FO emulsion decreased the proportion of viable cells by 5% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">Figure 1A</xref>). In neutrophils, LE infusion did not alter cell viability or any parameter of apoptosis.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0148607111432759" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The effect of fish oil (FO) or medium/long-chain triglycerides (MCTs/LCTs) on cell viability (A), DNA fragmentation (B), phosphatidylserine externalization (C), and mitochondrial polarization (D) in lymphocytes. Lymphocytes were freshly isolated from the peripheral blood of surgical patients with gastrointestinal cancer before infusion (t0), 3 days after infusion (t1), and 3 days after surgery (t2). Fluorescence was measured in FL3 (&gt;670 nm), FL2 (585/42 nm), or FL1 (530/30 nm) channels by flow cytometry. Ten thousand events were evaluated per experiment. The values are presented as mean ± SEM of 12–13 samples. Data are expressed as relative decrease; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 for comparison before (t0) and after infusion or surgery (t1 or t2).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111432759-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The impact of preoperative LE infusion on postoperative leukocyte death was determined by comparing data from t0 and t2. In lymphocytes, MCT/LCT emulsion tripled the proportion of cells with DNA fragmentation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">Figure 1B</xref>), and FO emulsion reduced the relative proportion of viable cells by 7% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">Figure 1A</xref>), reduced the percentage of cells with PS externalization by 74% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">Figure 1C</xref>), and had no effect on cell DNA fragmentation or mitochondrial depolarization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">Figure 1B</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111432759">D</xref>). In postoperative neutrophils, MCT/LCT emulsion did not alter cell viability, DNA fragmentation, or mitochondrial depolarization but increased the proportion of neutrophils with PS externalization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0148607111432759">Figure 2</xref>). FO emulsion did not change cell viability or any parameter of apoptosis in the neutrophil population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0148607111432759">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0148607111432759" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The effect of fish oil (FO) or medium/long-chain triglycerides (MCTs/LCTs) on cell viability (A), DNA fragmentation (B), phosphatidylserine externalization (C), and mitochondrial polarization (D) in neutrophils. Neutrophils were freshly isolated from the peripheral blood of surgical patients with gastrointestinal cancer before infusion (t0), 3 days after infusion (t1), and 3 days after surgery (t2). Fluorescence was measured in FL3 (&gt;670 nm), FL2 (585/42 nm), or FL1 (530/30 nm) channels by flow cytometry. Ten thousand events were evaluated per experiment. The values are presented as mean ± SEM of 12–13 samples. Data are expressed as relative decrease; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 for comparison before (t0) and after infusion or surgery (t1 or t2).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111432759-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>At the cellular level, there were no differences in lymphocyte or neutrophil death when MCT/MCT and FO treatments were compared during either preoperative or postoperative periods (<italic>P</italic> &gt; .05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0148607111432759">
<title>Postoperative Gene Expression in Lymphocytes</title>
<p>Of 108 genes related to cell death, MCT/LCT altered the expression of 12 genes and FO emulsion modulated the expression of 7 genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0148607111432759">Table 2</xref>). MCT/LCT infusion upregulated the expression of 7 genes related to cell death (TNF receptor–associated factor 5 [TRAF5], TNF receptor–associated factor 1 [TRAF1], Fas ligand [TNF superfamily, member 6—FASLG], v-myc myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog [avian—MYC], <italic>BCL2</italic>-like 1 nuclear gene encoding mitochondrial protein [BCL2L1], <italic>BCL2-</italic>antagonist of cell death [BAD], and melanoma inhibitory activity [MIA]) and 2 genes related to cell proliferation (vascular endothelial growth factor [VEGF] and connective tissue growth factor [CTGF]) and downregulated the expression of 3 genes related to cell death (BH3-interacting domain death agonist [BID], CASP8 and FADD-like apoptosis regulator [CFLAR], and cluster of differentiation 14 [CD 14]).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0148607111432759" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>List of the Lymphocyte Genes Related to Cell Death Up- and Downregulated in Postoperative Surgical Patients With Gastrointestinal Cancer Treated Preoperatively with a Parenteral Lipid Emulsion Composed of a Physical Mixture of Soybean Oil and MCT/LCT or a Parenteral Lipid Emulsion of Pure FO</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0148607111432759" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111432759-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Upregulation</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">MCT/LCT</th>
<th align="center">FO</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>TNF receptor–associated factor 5 (TRAF5)</td>
<td>TNF receptor–associated factor 3 (TRAF3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TNF receptor–associated factor 1 (TRAF1)</td>
<td>Colony-stimulating factor 1 (macrophage) (CSF1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fas ligand (TNF superfamily, member 6) (FASLG)</td>
<td>Colony-stimulating factor 2 (granulocyte-macrophage) (CSF2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Avian v-myc myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog (MYC)</td>
<td>BCL2-associated athanogene 4 (BAG4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Connective tissue growth factor (CTGF)</td>
<td>Nonmetastatic cells 1 (NME1) protein (NM23A)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nuclear gene encoding mitochondrial protein</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BCL2-like 1 (BCL2L1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BCL2-antagonist of cell death (BAD)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Melanoma inhibitory activity (MIA)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Downregulation<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">MCT/LCT</th>
<th align="center">FO</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BH3 interacting domain death agonist transcript variant 1 (BID)</td>
<td>Bifunctional apoptosis regulator (BFAR)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CASP8 and FADD-like apoptosis regulator (CFLAR)</td>
<td>Growth arrest and DNA damage–inducible alpha (GADD45A)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD14 antigen (CD14)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0148607111432759">
<p>FO, fish oil; LCT, long-chain triglyceride; MCT, medium-chain triglyceride; TNF, tumor necrosis factor.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>FO emulsion modulated the expression of 7 genes. FO emulsion upregulated the expression of 3 genes related to cell death (TNF receptor–associated factor 3 [TRAF3], <italic>BCL2</italic>-associated athanogene 4 [BAG4], and nonmetastatic cells 1 [NME1] protein [NM23A]) and 2 genes related to cell proliferation (macrophage colony-stimulating factor 1 [CSF1] and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor 2 [CSF2]) and downregulated the expression of 2 genes related to cell death (bifunctional apoptosis regulator [BFAR] and growth arrest and DNA damage–inducible alpha [GADD45A]).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0148607111432759" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>To achieve the effect of MCT/LCT and FO emulsions on leukocyte death under surgical trauma, we evaluated cell viability, apoptotic markers, and expression of genes associated with cell death in peripheral leukocytes from surgical patients with colon and gastric cancer who received a preoperative infusion of these LEs. Our choice to study surgical patients with both colon and gastric cancer is supported by a recent meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials that provided science-based conclusions concerning the safety and efficacy of using FO–enriched PN to decrease the postoperative infection rate and length of stay in hospitals and intensive care units (ICUs) of patients undergoing general major abdominal surgery, including both gastric and colon cancer patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0148607111432759">23</xref></sup></p>
<p>Our sample size was based on our previous experience with studies evaluating the effect of parenteral lipid emulsions on leukocyte death in healthy volunteers, where we were able to observe changes in leukocyte death after the infusion of LE when at least 10 participants per treatment were evaluated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0148607111432759">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0148607111432759">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although traditionally, FO emulsion has been infused as a supplement physically mixed with standard LEs (based on soybean or olive oil or rich in MCTs) in the amount of 10%−20% of total fat, its isolated use as a pharmacological agent has been considered to quickly modulate immune functions and possibly improve clinical outcomes. As recently demonstrated by Bahadori et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0148607111432759">25</xref></sup> in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, the infusion of pure FO emulsion at 0.2 g of fat per kilogram of body weight is safe, well tolerated, and sufficient to improve clinical symptoms. To contribute to the scientific background in assessing this current issue, we explored the effect of the infusion of pure FO emulsion on leukocyte death.</p>
<p>According to our data, in surgical patients with gastrointestinal cancer, the infusion of MCT/LCT emulsion before surgical trauma did not modify neutrophil or lymphocyte death but may induce postoperative apoptosis of these leukocytes, as indicated by the increased proportions of cells with PS externalization or DNA fragmentation.</p>
<p>There is only 1 published study on leukocyte death by the infusion of MCT/LCT emulsion. Buenestado et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0148607111432759">26</xref></sup> demonstrated that MCT/LCT emulsion does not induce apoptosis of stimulated neutrophils in vitro, as has been observed in the context of SO emulsion. Postoperative apoptosis mediated by MCT/LCT emulsion may occur through the influence of different factors, which depend on physiological interactions that are absent from simple in vitro models.</p>
<p>Major tissue injury response leads to the production of proinflammatory cytokines that may activate neutrophils and macrophages to release granular enzymes and produce ROS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111432759">12</xref></sup> Therefore, surgical stress can establish a cell-detrimental environment that is associated with organ dysfunction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0148607111432759">13</xref></sup> Delogu et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0148607111432759">27</xref></sup> demonstrated a significantly higher frequency of CD4+ and CD8+ T cell apoptosis at 24 hours after surgery. They also showed that the rate of CD8+ T cell apoptosis correlated with the rate of infectious complications manifested during the postoperative course. It is possible that the increase of postoperative lymphocyte and neutrophil apoptosis observed in patients infused with MCT/LCT emulsion arose from the modifications induced by surgical trauma, rather than from a proapoptotic effect of this LE.</p>
<p>Regarding the infusion of a pure FO emulsion, it resulted in a small proportional increase of lymphocytic death by necrosis, in relation to basal values (t0), but did not change cell apoptosis. Partly in agreement with our findings, the substitution of 20% and 40% of linoleic acid in 2 lipid emulsions by ω-3 PUFA also had no influence on apoptosis but was not associated with B and T lymphocyte necrosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0148607111432759">28</xref></sup> In our research, postoperative lymphocyte necrosis occurred at a very similar and slight extension compared with the preoperative period (5% vs 7%) and was probably not aggravated by surgical trauma.</p>
<p>In addition, we demonstrated that FO emulsion has a protective effect on postoperative lymphocyte apoptosis by substantially decreasing the proportion of these leukocytes with PS externalization. In addition, FO emulsion did not induce neutrophil death, even during the postoperative period, opposite to what was observed with MCT/LCT emulsion. Postoperative survival of neutrophils may represent an appropriated adaptive response to injury to eliminate invading pathogens and may be associated with the decreased postoperative rates of infectious complications observed in surgical patients treated with FO emulsion, compared with SO emulsion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0148607111432759">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0148607111432759">30</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the present study, for both LEs studied, changes in leukocyte death were accompanied by alterations in the expression of genes related to cell death. Fatty acids have been increasingly recognized as major biological regulators.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0148607111432759">31</xref></sup> Many of the effects of fatty acids in cell biology and human health and disease are associated with their abilities, mainly n-3 PUFA, to regulate gene expression and subsequent downstream events. Possible mechanisms for these effects include the expression or processing of transcription factors, nuclear hormone receptors, and lipid second messengers. For example, certain fatty acid–derived molecules have been shown to modulate inflammation by activating peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors (PPARs), transcription factors that, once activated, bind to their recognition sequences and regulate gene expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0148607111432759">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0148607111432759"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0148607111432759">34</xref></sup></p>
<p>Our molecular data suggest that increased postoperative apoptosis of lymphocytes from patients preoperatively infused with MCT/LCT emulsion can be associated with the preactivation of proapoptotic pathways mediated by BAD, BCL-xL, and BCL2 (via mediation of outer mitochondrial membrane channel opening) and also TRAF5, TRAF1, and FASLG (via TNF family members and their receptors, with the activation of NF-κB).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0148607111432759">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0148607111432759">36</xref></sup> However, MCT/LCT emulsion was also associated with the inhibition of proapoptotic genes. BID is a death agonist that mediates mitochondrial damage induced by caspase-8 through cytochrome c release; the activation of Fas-associated protein with death domain (FADD) by CFLAR also can recruit procaspase-8 or -10 and subsequently constitute the death-inducing signaling complex (DISC), leading to apoptosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0148607111432759">37</xref></sup> This finding suggests a possible regulatory mechanism for apoptosis, and it is difficult to exclude the influence of other physiological factors related to surgical trauma on the higher postoperative lymphocyte apoptosis observed in MCT/LCT-treated patients. A more detailed protein study should contribute to a better understanding of these molecular findings.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, FO emulsion demonstrates a clear protective effect on postoperative lymphocyte death by downregulating proapoptotic and upregulating antiapoptotic genes. This emulsion downregulated BFAR and GADD45A genes. BFAR interacts with both the intrinsic and extrinsic apoptotic pathways, and GADD45A is a member of a group of genes that are increased after treatment with DNA-damaging agents and environmental stress by mediating activation of the p38/JNK pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0148607111432759">38</xref></sup> In addition, FO emulsion also upregulated gene expression of TRAF3, CSF1, CSF2, and BAG4. TRAF3 serves as a negative regulator of the NF-κB pathway for TNF receptors, by blocking NF-κB activation via TRAF2/5.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0148607111432759">39</xref></sup> Members of the CSF family that play an important role in macrophage recruitment and activation (M-CSF) are synthesized through NF-κB and PPAR-γ regulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0148607111432759">40</xref></sup>; Maianski et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0148607111432759">41</xref></sup> suggested that CSF induces Akt protein phosphorylation, which inhibits proapoptotic proteins such as BCL-xl and BID. BAG4 is a member of the BAG1-related antiapoptotic protein family, which is associated with the death domain of TNF receptor type 1 (TNF-R1) and death receptor-3 (DR3) and thereby negatively regulates downstream cell death signaling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0148607111432759">42</xref></sup></p>
<p>The upregulation of antiapoptotic genes that involves PPAR and NF-κB is in accordance with previous reports that demonstrate the capacity of ω-3 fatty acids provided by FO to modulate gene expression by mediating these transcriptional factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0148607111432759">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0148607111432759">44</xref></sup> One proposed mechanism may include the displacement of lipid rafts, which are functional membrane microdomains related to the initiation and propagation of cell signaling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0148607111432759">45</xref></sup> Therefore, the expression of TRAF3, CSF1, CSF2, and BAG4 genes may be associated with the protective effect of FO emulsion on postoperative lymphocyte PS externalization; however, a more detailed protein study should be developed to confirm this hypothesis.</p>
<p>In summary, in patients with gastrointestinal cancer, the preoperative infusion of MCT/LCT is associated with postoperative lymphocyte and neutrophil apoptosis, whereas FO has a protective effect on postoperative lymphocyte apoptosis.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Financial disclosure: This research was supported by CNPq, FAPESP (08/00163-9), and CAPES.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0148607111432759">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hot topics in parenteral nutrition: rationale for using new lipid emulsions in parenteral nutrition and a review of the trials performed in adults</article-title>. <source>Proc Nutr Soc</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0148607111432759">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waitzberg</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torrinhas</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacintho</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>New parenteral lipid emulsions for clinical use</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0148607111432759">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nordenstrom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarstrand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiernik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decreased chemotactic and random migration of leukocytes during Intralipid infusion</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>2416</fpage>-<lpage>2422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0148607111432759">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gogos</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalfarentzos</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zoumbos</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different types of total parenteral nutrition on T-lymphocyte subpopulations and NK cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0148607111432759">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Granato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Le Boucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malnoe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dutot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of parenteral lipid emulsions with different fatty acid composition on immune cell functions in vitro</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0148607111432759">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Influences of soybean oil emulsion on stress response and cell-mediated immune function in moderately or severely stressed patients</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0148607111432759">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cury-Boaventura</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gorjao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Lima</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Toxicity of a soybean oil emulsion on human lymphocytes and neutrophils</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0148607111432759">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martins de Lima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gorjao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hatanaka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms by which fatty acids regulate leucocyte function</article-title>. <source>Clin Sci (Lond)</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0148607111432759">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The 2008 ESPEN Sir David Cuthbertson Lecture: fatty acids and inflammation—from the membrane to the nucleus and from the laboratory bench to the clinic</article-title>. <source>Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0148607111432759">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chaudry</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of Fas/Fas ligand signaling improves septic survival: differential effects on macrophage apoptotic and functional capacity</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>344</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0148607111432759">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hotchkiss</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Apoptotic cell death in patients with sepsis, shock and multiple organ dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1230</fpage>-<lpage>1251</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0148607111432759">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baigrie</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamont</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwiatkowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dallman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Systemic cytokine response after major surgery</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>757</fpage>-<lpage>760</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0148607111432759">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshidome</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohtsuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Immunosuppression following surgical and traumatic injury</article-title>. <source>Surg Today</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>793</fpage>-<lpage>808</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0148607111432759">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of medium-chain and long-chain triacylglycerols in pediatric surgical patients</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>406</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0148607111432759">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waitzberg</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellinati-Pires</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of total parenteral nutrition with different lipid emulsions of human monocyte and neutrophil functions</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0148607111432759">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gelas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cotte</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poitevin-Later</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of parenteral medium- and long-chain triglycerides on lymphocytes subpopulations and functions in patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome: a prospective study</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0148607111432759">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schauder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rohn</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of fish oil enriched total parenteral nutrition on DNA synthesis, cytokine release and receptor expression by lymphocytes in the postoperative period</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<supplement>suppl 1</supplement>):<fpage>S103</fpage>-<lpage>S110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0148607111432759">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boyum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Isolation of leucocytes from human blood: a two-phase system for removal of red cells with methylcellulose as erythrocyte-aggregating agent</article-title>. <source>Scand J Clin Lab Invest Suppl</source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0148607111432759">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Migliorati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pagliacci</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grignani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riccardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A rapid and simple method for measuring thymocyte apoptosis by propidium iodide staining and flow cytometry</article-title>. <source>J Immunol Methods</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0148607111432759">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vermes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haanen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steffens Nakken</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reutelingsperger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A novel assay for apoptosis: flow cytometric detection of phosphatidylserine expression on early apoptotic cells using fluorescein labelled Annexin V</article-title>. <source>J Immun Methods</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0148607111432759">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Darzynkiewicz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staiano-Coico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melamed</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increased mitochondrial uptake of rhodamine 123 during lymphocyte stimulation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>2383</fpage>-<lpage>2387</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0148607111432759">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ottery</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient-generated subjective global assessment</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McCallum</surname></name>
<name><surname>Polisena</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>The Clinical Guide to Oncology Nutrition</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Dietetic Association</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0148607111432759">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Safety and efficacy of fish oil–enriched parenteral nutrition regimen on postoperative patients undergoing major abdominal surgery: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0148607111432759">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cury-Boaventura</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gorjão</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Lima</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of olive oil–based emulsion on human lymphocyte and neutrophil death</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0148607111432759">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bahadori</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thonhofer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Omega-3 fatty acids infusions as adjuvant therapy in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0148607111432759">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buenestado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cortijo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Olive oil–based lipid emulsion’s neutral effects on neutrophil functions and leukocyte-endothelial cell interactions</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>-<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0148607111432759">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Delogu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antonucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Apoptosis and surgical trauma: dysregulated expression of death and survival factors on peripheral lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Arch Surg</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>1141</fpage>-<lpage>1147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0148607111432759">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scheinichen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jankowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruschulte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lack of influence of omega-3 fatty acid–enriched lipids on apoptosis and secondary necrosis of cultured human lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>445</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0148607111432759">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Safety and efficacy of fish oil–enriched parenteral nutrition regimen on postoperative patients undergoing major abdominal surgery: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0148607111432759">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of lipid emulsion containing fish oil on outcomes of surgical patients: systematic review of randomized controlled trials from Europe and Asia</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>474</fpage>-<lpage>481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0148607111432759">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clandinin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheema</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venkatraman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clandinin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dietary fat: exogenous determination of membrane structure and cell function</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>2761</fpage>-<lpage>2769</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0148607111432759">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Medzhitov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Origin and physiological roles of inflammation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>454</volume>:<fpage>428</fpage>-<lpage>435</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0148607111432759">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Devchand</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wahli</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The PPARalpha-leukotriene B4 pathway to inflammation control</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>384</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0148607111432759">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czimmerer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>PPARs are a unique set of fatty acid regulated transcription factors controlling both lipid metabolism and inflammation</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>1812</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1007</fpage>-<lpage>1022</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0148607111432759">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tumor necrosis factor–alpha-induced IKK phosphorylation of NF-kappaB p65 on serine 536 is mediated through the TRAF2, TRAF5, and TAK1 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>36916</fpage>-<lpage>36923</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0148607111432759">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavorgna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Filippi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Formisano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>TNF receptor–associated factor 1 is a positive regulator of the NF-kappaB alternative pathway</article-title>. <source>Mol Immunol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>3278</fpage>-<lpage>3282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0148607111432759">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The many roles of FAS receptor signaling in the immune system</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0148607111432759">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gadd45-alpha and Gadd45-gamma utilize p38 and JNK signaling pathways to induce cell cycle G2/M arrest in Hep-G2 hepatoma cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>2075</fpage>-<lpage>2085</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0148607111432759">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puschner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>TNF receptor (TNFR)–associated factor (TRAF) 3 serves as an inhibitor of TRAF2/5-mediated activation of the noncanonical NF-kappaB pathway by TRAF-binding TNFRs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>2874</fpage>-<lpage>2879</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0148607111432759">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonfield</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomassen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farver</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma regulates the expression of alveolar macrophage macrophage colony-stimulating factor</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0148607111432759">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maianski</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuijpers</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bid truncation, bid/bax targeting to the mitochondria, and caspase activation associated with neutrophil apoptosis are inhibited by granulocyte colony-stimulating factor</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>7024</fpage>-<lpage>7030</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0148607111432759">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eichholtz-Wirth</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sagan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Altered signaling of TNFalpha-TNFR1 and SODD/BAG4 is responsible for radioresistance in human HT-R15 cells</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0148607111432759">
<label>43.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deckelbaum</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Worgall</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>n-3 fatty acids and gene expression</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>S1520</fpage>-<lpage>S1525</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0148607111432759">
<label>44.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fatty acids as gatekeepers of immune cell regulation</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>639</fpage>-<lpage>645</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0148607111432759">
<label>45.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaloga</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stillwell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of lipid rafts by n-3 fatty acids in inflammation and cancer: implications for use of lipids during nutrition support</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>