<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PRF</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spprf</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Perfusion</journal-id>
<journal-title>Perfusion</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0267-6591</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-111X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0267659111419886</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0267659111419886</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Zero balance ultrafiltration for the correction of acute acidosis after a period of prolonged deep hypothermic circulatory arrest</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0267659111419886">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilberath</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0267659111419886">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0267659111419886">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>FitzGerald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0267659111419886">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0267659111419886"><label>1</label>Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Department of Cardiac Surgery, Boston, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0267659111419886"><label>2</label>Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Department of Anesthesia, Perioperative and Pain Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0267659111419886"><label>3</label>Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Department of Cardiac Perfusion, Boston, MA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0267659111419886">Daniel J. FitzGerald CCP, LP, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Department of Cardiac Perfusion, 75 Francis Street, Boston, MA. 02115 Email: <email>dfitzgerald1@partners.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A 36-year-old woman with normal renal function underwent a total arch replacement requiring 110 minutes of deep hypothermic circulatory arrest. Prior to rewarming, a pH of 7.063 with a base deficit of 10.8 was obtained. Zero-balance ultrafiltration (Z-BUF) was initiated during rewarming 7 minutes after resumption of cardiopulmonary bypass. After one hour (10L) of Z-BUF, all electrolyte and acid-base disturbances were fully corrected. Our case illustrates that Z-BUF offers a valuable option for the correction of severe electrolyte and acid-base disturbances in adults undergoing cardiac surgery. Its use should be considered in addition to the more standard pharmacologic approaches to such derangements as it offers rapid and predictable electrolyte and acid-base correction and potential anti-inflammatory benefits.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>zero balance ultrafiltration</kwd>
<kwd>deep hypothermic circulatory arrest</kwd>
<kwd>total aortic arch replacement</kwd>
<kwd>acid-base correction</kwd>
<kwd>PrismaSate®</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0267659111419886">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>Patient: A 36-year-old woman with a bicuspid aortic valve and a 4.5 centimeter ascending aortic aneurysm, diagnosed during pregnancy.</p>
<p>Two months following Cesarean section delivery, she presented for surgical repair. The patient had no medical comorbidities. At presentation, she was taking only a low-dose beta blocker. Preoperative transthoracic echocardiogram revealed a left ventricular ejection fraction of 60% with no major valvular dysfunction. Magnetic resonance angiography revealed an aneurysm of the ascending aorta measuring 4.5 cm. The sinotubular junction measured 3.3 cm and the aortic arch measured 2.9 cm, not returning to normal size until after the left subclavian artery.</p>
<p>The patient was actively breastfeeding at the time of presentation for repair, therefore, a minimally invasive approach was employed. Normothermic baseline arterial blood gas, hematocrit (Hct) and electrolytes were obtained prior to incision and were: pH 7.36, pCO<sub>2</sub> 40.2, PO<sub>2</sub> 200.7, base excess (BE) -3.0, Hct 33, Na 140.4 and K 3.02. An upper hemisternotomy was used to access the mediastinum and the innominate artery was exposed. A 6mm graft was affixed to this artery in an end-to-side fashion and attached to the arterial limb of the cardiopulmonary bypass circuit with a 3/8 in. by 3/8 in connector. A 21 Fr. percutaneous femoral cannula (Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN) was placed, using echocardiographic guidance, for venous drainage. A retrograde cardioplegia cannula was placed. Cooling to 18<sup>°</sup>C was initiated and, at ventricular fibrillation, an aortic cross-clamp was placed and antegrade and retrograde cardioplegia were administered. Cooling continued to a temperature of 18<sup>°</sup>C and maintained for 45 minutes. Isoelectric electroencephalogram (EEG) was confirmed prior to the initiation of circulatory arrest and antegrade cerebral perfusion. An alpha-STAT perfusion strategy was employed with a pHmax of 7.56 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0267659111419886">Figure 1</xref>). A total arch resection was indicated and, due to the difficulty of the distal anastomoses, a period of 110 minutes of circulatory arrest was required. Given the prolonged period of circulatory arrest, we anticipated a significant base deficit. As rewarming commenced, at a temperature of 18<sup>°</sup>C, a pH of 7.063 with a base deficit of 10.8 was obtained and zero-balance ultrafiltration was initiated during rewarming, 7 minutes after resumption of cardiopulmonary bypass.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0267659111419886" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Base Excess and pH measurements: prior to incision, BE was –3.0 and pH 7.36. After 110 mins of deep hypothermic circulatory arrest with antegrade cerebral perfusion, a BE of –10.8 and pH of 7.063 were obtained. Ten liters of zero-balance ultrafiltration completely normalized the patient’s BE and pH over 60 minutes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0267659111419886-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>We used a Hemocor HPH®1400 IUS Hemoconcentrator filter (Minntech Corp, Minneapolis, MN) to remove plasma water and PrismaSATE® BK0/3.5 solution, a zero-potassium, bicarbonate-based continuous renal replacement fluid (Gambro Corp, Lakewood, CO) for plasma water replacement (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0267659111419886">Table 1</xref>). Using this strategy, we obtained normal arterial blood gases, with a base deficit of zero (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0267659111419886">Figure 1</xref>) at a rewarmed temperature of 37<sup>°</sup>C after 10 liters of zero-balance ultrafiltration over 60 minutes. The patient was extubated 5 hours postoperatively and discharged from the intensive unit on postoperative day 3.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0267659111419886" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Components of PrismaSATE BK0/3.5</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0267659111419886" xlink:href="10.1177_0267659111419886-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Normal Plasma</th>
<th align="left">PrismaSATE BK0/3.5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Potassium K<sup>+</sup></td>
<td>3.5–5.0 mEq/L</td>
<td>0 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Calcium Ca<sup>2</sup><sup>+</sup></td>
<td>2.3–2.6 mEq/L</td>
<td>3.5 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Magnesium Mg<sup>2+</sup></td>
<td>1.4–2.0 mEq/L</td>
<td>1.0 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sodium Na<sup>+</sup></td>
<td>140 mEq/L</td>
<td>140 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chloride Cl<sup>−</sup></td>
<td>100–108 mEq/L</td>
<td>109.5 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bicarbonate HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup></td>
<td>22–26 mEq/L</td>
<td>32 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lactate</td>
<td>0.5–2.2 mEq/L</td>
<td>3 mEq/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dextrose</td>
<td>70–110 mOsm/L</td>
<td>0 mOsm/L</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Osmolarity</td>
<td>280–296 mOsm/L</td>
<td>287 mOsm/L</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0267659111419886">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The term zero-balance ultrafiltration (Z-BUF) was originally used by Journois, et al. to describe a technique of ultrafiltration during the rewarming phase of cardiopulmonary bypass in the pediatric population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0267659111419886">1</xref></sup>. Z-BUF involves hemofiltration for removal of plasma water, followed by replacement of this fluid with an equal volume of fluid containing specific (often physiologic) concentrations of electrolytes and glucose. In our institution, we use Z-BUF commonly during cardiopulmonary bypass in patients with renal failure, as well as in cases of more extreme physiologic derangement in patients with normal renal function, such as in the present case, but there is little discussion of such use in the literature.</p>
<p>In this case, the use of Z-BUF during rewarming effectively provided a substitute for renal function until the patient’s native kidneys were restored to normal physiologic conditions and allowed for the rapid, predictable, simultaneous correction of electrolytes and pH, as well as facilitating glycemic control. After one hour (10L) of Z-BUF, the base deficit was corrected from -10.8 to 0.6, the potassium was corrected from 7.3 to 3.4 and, in concert with insulin administration, the glucose was corrected from 201 to 86. Alternatives to using Z-BUF in this case would have been the administration of sodium bicarbonate for acid-base correction (as well as insulin with or without furosemide for hyperkalemia correction), or perhaps watchful waiting of the electrolyte and acid-base disturbances during rewarming.</p>
<p>The use of pharmacologic agents to effect electrolyte and acid-base normalization would have been less straightforward and required multiple additional manipulations, with less predictable results and other potential disadvantages. For example, if we had chosen to correct the base deficit by treating the patient with sodium bicarbonate, it would have likely required between 150-190 mEq of bicarbonate (about 3 ampoules of 8.4% sodium bicarbonate) and the accompanying sodium load, potentially leading to hypernatremia or exacerbating postoperative edema. Each ampoule of 8.4% sodium bicarbonate is metabolized to one liter of carbon dioxide, and manipulations of the sweep gas to avoid additional acid-base derangements would also have been required. The watchful waiting approach, relying on the patient’s recovering organs to correct the base deficit and electrolyte disturbances, would have avoided the sodium and carbon dioxide loads, but the correction would have been much less rapid and predictable.</p>
<p>An additional possible benefit of Z-BUF in adult cardiac surgery relates to its possible effect in ameliorating the systemic inflammatory response elicited by cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB). It has been shown that Z-BUF is capable of removing pro-inflammatory mediators such as tumor necrosis factor alpha, interleukin-6 and complement factors C3a and C5a<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0267659111419886">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0267659111419886">5</xref></sup>. Perhaps, as a result of the reduction of such circulating factors, use of Z-BUF during CPB has been shown to be associated with improved postoperative pulmonary function and decreased transfusion requirements in animal models and small human studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0267659111419886">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0267659111419886">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0267659111419886">7</xref></sup>.</p>
<p>In summary, our case illustrates that Z-BUF offers a valuable option for the correction of severe electrolyte and acid-base disturbances in adults undergoing cardiac surgery. Its use should be considered in addition to the more standard pharmacologic approaches to such derangements as it offers rapid and predictable electrolyte and acid-base correction, as well as potential anti-inflammatory benefits.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>None Declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0267659111419886">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Journois</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Israel-Biet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pouard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-volume, zero-balanced hemofiltration to reduce delayed inflammatory response to cardiopulmonary bypass in children</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology</source> <year>1996</year> <month>Nov</month>; <volume>85</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>965</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0267659111419886">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tallman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dumond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Inflammatory mediator removal by zero-balance ultrafiltration during cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title>. <source>Perfusion</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0267659111419886">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berdat</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Elimination of proinflammatory cytokines in pediatric cardiac surgery: analysis of ultrafiltration method and filter type</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>127</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1688</fpage>–<lpage>1696</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0267659111419886">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Linden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cytokine production and hemofiltration in children undergoing cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1499</fpage>–<lpage>1502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0267659111419886">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Derivation of sieving coefficients to determine the efficacy of the hemoconcentrator in removal of four inflammatory mediators produced during cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title>. <source>ASAIO J</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0267659111419886">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Searles</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-volume, zero balanced ultrafiltration improves pulmonary function in a model of post-pump syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Extra Corpor Technol</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0267659111419886">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Continuous ultrafiltration attenuates the pulmonary injury that follows open heart surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>76</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>