<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjpe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Planning Education and Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0739-456X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6577</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0739456X12455666</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0739456X12455666</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Who Says? Authority, Voice, and Authorship in Narratives of Planning Research</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>Robert W.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0739456X12455666">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zitcer</surname><given-names>Andrew W.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0739456X12455666">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0739456X12455666"><label>1</label>Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0739456X12455666"><label>2</label>Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0739456X12455666">Robert W. Lake, Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy, Rutgers University, 33 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick, NJ 08901, USA Email: <email>rlake@rci.rutgers.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>399</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association of Collegiate Schools of Planning</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Recent developments in communicative planning theory and participatory research methods emphasize collaboration between researcher and research subject in the process of knowledge production. We ask how the ideal of collaboration that is integral to the process of data collection extends to the authorial phase of planning narratives and we identify ethical, pragmatic, and substantive justifications for collaborative authorship. The multidisciplinary literature on the city reveals a variety of approaches to authorship including empathetic evocation, selective deployment, dialogic collaboration, and uninterpreted transcription. More successful collaboration might require the avoidance of abstraction, an emphasis on contextualization and intersubjectivity, and a reimagining of social science from inquiry to conversation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>collaborative knowledge production</kwd>
<kwd>narrative method</kwd>
<kwd>authorship</kwd>
<kwd>voice</kwd>
<kwd>authority</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>No need to hear your voice when I can talk about you better than you can speak about yourself. No need to hear your voice. Only tell me about your pain. I want to know your story. And then I will tell it back to you in a new way. Tell it to you in such a way that it becomes mine, my own. Rewriting you, I write myself anew. I am still author, authority. I am still colonizer, the speaking subject, and you are now at the center of my talk. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739456X12455666">hooks 1990</xref>, 343)</p>
<p>What once seemed only technically difficult, getting “their” lives into “our” works, has turned morally, politically, even epistemologically, delicate. . . . The very right to write . . . seems at risk. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">Geertz 1988</xref>, 130, 133)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Recent developments in planning theory and methods both reflect and contribute to a growing recognition of the collaborative nature of knowledge production. Theories of participatory or communicative planning rest on the premise that outcomes are improved when planning proceeds through the collaborative interaction of expert and lay participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0739456X12455666">Fischer 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0739456X12455666">Healey 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0739456X12455666">Innes and Booher 2010</xref>). Methods of data collection such as ethnographic research, open-ended interviews, oral and public history, and similarly unstructured techniques rest on the proposition that research subjects are able and qualified to articulate their lived experience and that, in doing so, informants in the field actively construct the “data” that are produced within the research process. Implicit (and sometimes explicit) within these developments in planning theory and methods is the premise that researcher and research subject share authority for the production of planning knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0739456X12455666">Frisch 1990</xref>).</p>
<p>Once data are collected and analyzed, however, much less attention is directed to identifying appropriate methods for the writing of planning narratives. This article focuses attention on the practice of writing in planning. Specifically, we ask how the ideal of shared authority, increasingly understood as integral to the process of data collection, extends to the authorial phase of the planning process. Our concern here is with questions of voice and authority in the practice of authorship. Whose voice appears on the page in narrative reports of planning research? Whose voice <italic>should</italic> appear on the page, and why does it matter? How does speaking <italic>about</italic> a subject—the authorial stance in most reports of planning research conducted within the traditional framework of rational planning—differ from the process of speaking <italic>for</italic> a subject as entailed, for instance, by advocacy planning? How do these differ in turn from the requirements of speaking <italic>with</italic> or <italic>to</italic> the subject implicit in forms of communicative planning? If planning knowledge is collaboratively produced, by what authority does the planner as author appropriate and present that knowledge as his or her own within the text? In raising these questions, the ideal of collaborative or participatory planning presents a challenge to conventional understandings of the role and identity of the researcher, the locus of expertise, whose voice predominates in the planning narrative, and the ethics of appropriating the experience and expertise of the research subject as a means for achieving the researcher’s personal, professional, or intellectual ends.</p>
<p>To address these issues, we examine the dilemmas of narrative in collaborative knowledge production, pointing to the challenge posed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0739456X12455666">Foucault’s (1984)</xref> apparently innocent question: “What is an author?” The question of authorship most directly applies to those forms of planning practice and research that are aligned with the normative ideals of collaborative or participatory planning. To the extent that collaborative planning provokes the reform of traditional planning analysis, however, the issue of collaborative authorship extends, if indirectly, to all forms of planning practice and research. In the remainder of the paper, we present ethical, pragmatic, and substantive justifications for extending shared authority to the authorial stage of planning; review a range of approaches to collaborative narration as illustrated by examples drawn from the multidisciplinary urban studies literature; and explore the implications of our discussion by offering a few initial and tentative strategies for planners seeking to extend the collaborative nature of their work to the authorship of planning narratives. Our intent is to encourage a consideration of these issues by the wider planning community rather than to presume to have addressed the question once and for all.</p>
<sec id="section1-0739456X12455666">
<title>Rethinking Authorship</title>
<p>The problem of authorship has been examined from various vantage points in planning and the social sciences. Writing more than twenty years ago, the anthropologist Clifford Geertz insisted on separating the question of the relationship between author and subject from the considerably different question of the relationship between author and text. The former, which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">Geertz (1988)</xref> described as the problem of being “There”—encountering, engaging with, and studying the subject—requires the researcher to solve problems commonly posed in terms of objectivity, subjectivity, science, perspective, positionality, engagement, and bias, issues usually treated in planning methods and theory courses. The latter—the relationship between author and text—described by Geertz as the problem of being “Here,” arises once the researcher withdraws from contact with the subject (whether in the field or on the spreadsheet) and confronts the text in deciding how to narrate the information produced in the process of research. Geertz objects to the too-easy conflation of these separate issues: the convenient belief that “if the relation between observer and observed can be managed, the relation between author and text will follow . . . by itself” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">Geertz 1988</xref>, 10). “The gap,” he says, “between engaging others where they are [being “There”] and representing them where they aren’t [being “Here”] . . . has suddenly become extremely visible” and, as a result, “the burden of authorship seems suddenly heavier” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">Geertz 1988</xref>, 130, 138).</p>
<p>The reasons for this increased burden have been explored at length in feminist, postcolonial, and narrative studies, encompassing both political and substantive arguments. How an author chooses to speak about, speak for, or speak with a subject is both a product and a cause of the broad-scale power relations constituting the social system within which both the author and the subject are constituent parts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0739456X12455666">Sharp 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0739456X12455666">Spivak 1988</xref>). As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0739456X12455666">Linda Alcoff (1995</xref>, 104-5), “rituals of speaking are politically constituted (and) who is speaking, who is spoken of, and who listens is a result, as well as an act, of political struggle.”</p>
<p>The politics of narration are double-edged. On one hand, speaking for others from a privileged position of authority and expertise, such as is implicit in advocacy planning, can confer legitimacy and presence on subjects who otherwise are excluded from the political process. On the other hand, “such speaking for others does nothing to disrupt the discursive hierarchies that operate in public spaces” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0739456X12455666">Alcoff 1995</xref>, 99) and instead may serve to reproduce and reinforce the hierarchical distinctions it purports to decry. Even more perversely, the practice of speaking for or about others confers legitimacy and authority on the speaker, making the speaker not only complicit in but dependent on the reproduction of inequality, “born of a desire . . . to privilege oneself as the one who more correctly understands the truth about another’s situation” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0739456X12455666">Alcoff 1995</xref>, 115). Or as Nietzsche caustically observed: “he who thinks in <italic>words</italic>, thinks as a speaker and not as a thinker . . . in point of fact, he only thinks of himself and his audience” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0739456X12455666">Nietzsche [1913] 2003</xref>, 78).</p>
<p>The implications of narrative strategy are substantive as well as political, ontological as well as epistemological. The author speaking about (or for) a subject constructs a representation of the subject but, also, more than that. The representation on the page does not stand at a distance from the “real” world in the field but instead becomes its own reality, constituting reality in the form of the representation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0739456X12455666">Mitchell 2002</xref>, 116). The problem is not whether the author presents an “accurate” representation of reality on the page—that question assumes a false dualism between reality and representation—but rather that the representation constitutes the discourse through which the reality can be apprehended. Foucault’s insistence that “the author does not precede the work” upends the established view of authorship as the process of creating and then narrating knowledge: “The author,” he says, “is not an indefinite source of significations which fill a work” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0739456X12455666">1984</xref>, 118). The written work, in this view, reveals more about what the author chooses to say than about the subject represented in the narrative. If the text conveys a portrait of the author rather than (or in addition to) a representation of the subject, then who says, that is, who is included in the practice of authorship, has direct substantive bearing on what gets said in the text.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0739456X12455666">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>The complexities of collaborative knowledge production are directly confronted in the methodologies adopted in participatory action research and oral and public history. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0739456X12455666">Cahill, Sultana, and Pain (2007</xref>, 312) describe participatory action research (PAR) as “a practice of researching <italic>with</italic> rather than <italic>on</italic> participants” that challenges conventional understandings of “Who has the ‘authority’ to represent the community’s point of view?” and asks “Who should speak for whom, and in what language?” The participatory practice of “researching with” employs the ideal of shared authority throughout the research process, extending from problem definition to research design, data interpretation, and selection of prescriptive solutions. (For discussion of the limitations of PAR, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0739456X12455666">Fisher 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0739456X12455666">Pain 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0739456X12455666">Macmillan and Scott 2003</xref>.) PAR proponents have also examined the question of authorship, exploring the potential of film and other media beyond the printed page to “report” research results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0739456X12455666">Cahill and Torre 2007</xref>) and, in some cases, rejecting authorship as a (or the only) desired outcome of the research process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0739456X12455666">Benson and Nagar 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Similar commitments and concerns arise in the collection and construction of oral history, in which informants narrate life experiences, and public history, involving communities (whether of interest or of place) constructing their own histories without the intervention of professional historians or institutionally formalized historical methods. Implicit in these practices is “a capacity to redefine and redistribute intellectual authority” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0739456X12455666">Frisch 1990</xref>, xx) in the process of what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0739456X12455666">Candida Smith (2002</xref>, 727) describes as “groping toward mutual understanding” between researcher and informant. The open-ended, collaborative nature of oral history, in which the interviewer initiates the process of knowledge production but the “informant” furnishes the content of the interview, gives new urgency to Foucault’s query “What is an author?” and inevitably raises the questions posed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0739456X12455666">Frisch (1990</xref>, xx):
<disp-quote>
<p>Who, really, is the author of an oral history . . . ? Is it the historian posing questions and editing results, or the “subject,” whose words are the heart of the consequent texts? . . . What is the relation between interviewer and subject in the generating of such histories—who is responsible for them and where is interpretive authority located? How are we to understand interpretations that are, essentially, collaboratively produced in an interview . . . ? How can this collaboration be represented, and how, more commonly, is it usually mystified and obscured, and to what effect?</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0739456X12455666">
<title>Justifications</title>
<p>We have identified three justifications—ethical, pragmatic, and substantive—for heightened attention to the challenges of shared narrative authority. These arguments assert that a reconsideration of narrative strategy is ethically necessary (it should be done); is pragmatically possible (it can be done); and is substantively advisable (it will produce better outcomes). Taken together, these justifications support a compelling case for rethinking the relationship between subject and researcher in the construction of planning narratives.</p>
<sec id="section3-0739456X12455666">
<title>Ethical Justification</title>
<p>The most frequently articulated of the three justifications involves the necessity of extending the ethics of research to the authorial phase of the work. As already noted, feminist and postcolonial theorists in particular have dissected the power imbalance that exists between research subject and researcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0739456X12455666">Attili 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0739456X12455666">Spivak 1988</xref>) and this inequality persists in the construction of the research narrative. When researchers speak for and about their informants, an overshadowing takes place that eclipses the voice and agency of the subject. The informant’s stories are merely source material, providing data as a means for the researcher’s ends. In the writing phase, the “real work” of scholarship, informant voices dim and the author’s voice commands the spotlight.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0739456X12455666">Janet Malcolm’s (1990)</xref> book-length meditation on the fraught relationship between journalists and their sources offers useful parallel insights on the complicated ways in which social scientists work with their “data” in the authorial phase of research. Malcolm’s book chronicles the case in which Jeff MacDonald, a convicted murderer, successfully sued journalist Joe McGinniss for defaming his character in McGinniss’s book, <italic>Fatal Vision</italic>. On the face of it, the charge that a book could tarnish the reputation of a convicted murderer seems absurd but Malcolm understands the story as a kind of revenge fantasy for the emotional violence done by journalists to their sources in the name of crafting a successful narrative.</p>
<p>As Malcolm observes, “the journalist must do his work in a kind of deliberately induced state of moral anarchy” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0739456X12455666">1990</xref>, 143). The moral vacuum at the heart of the journalistic process lies in the deception practiced by the journalist who cultivates the subject as a source of information but abruptly terminates collaboration in the writing of the story:
<disp-quote>
<p>The catastrophe suffered by the subject is no simple matter of an unflattering likeness or a misrepresentation of his views; what pains him, what rankles and sometimes drives him to extremes of vengefulness, is the deception that has been practiced on him. On reading the article or book in question, he has to face the fact that the journalist . . . never had the slightest intention of collaborating with him on his story but always intended to write a story of his own. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0739456X12455666">Malcolm 1990</xref>, 3)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The reporter or researcher getting the story and the person back at his or her desk writing the story (what Geertz calls being “There” and being “Here”) are functionally two different people. The objective of the former is to generate trust and rapport with the subject so as to gather the best data for the story. The latter is faced with a different task: creating a compelling narrative containing effective characters who populate a readable story. For the source, it is the relationship with the writer that matters and the writing is expected to follow the contours of that relationships. For the journalist, the relationship to the subject is a means to an end: a compelling story that does credit to the writer. The imbalance of power between researcher and subject, the researcher’s parasitic need for the subject’s “data,” and the resulting narrative bearing the sole authorship of the writer: these same moral pitfalls plague both the journalist and the social scientist and prompt a reconsideration of the authorial process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0739456X12455666">
<title>Pragmatic Justification</title>
<p>Such reconsideration is not only ethically necessary but also pragmatically possible. The pragmatic justification rests on the recognition that the rules of narrative production are constantly being rewritten. This is Foucault’s core assertion when he states that “given the historical modifications that are taking place, it does not seem necessary that the author function remain constant in form, complexity, and even in existence” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0739456X12455666">Foucault 1984</xref>, 119). Consequently, since the authorial process is already constantly in flux, it can be revised in ways that extend the collaboration between researcher and subject to the phase of narrative construction.</p>
<p>In the same vein, Derrida defends textual deconstruction as a means to disrupt the political authority of the canon in order to produce a deeper understanding of writing as an act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0739456X12455666">Olson 1990</xref>). We would do well, Derrida advises, to “deconstruct” not only written texts but the institution of composition and the very notion of “composition” itself. He suggests that we continually question and destabilize the authority of models of composition and that we seek to “invent each time new forms according to the situation” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0739456X12455666">Olson 1990</xref>, 3). Shared authority in the construction of narratives can be seen as another way of destabilizing the contours of composition, with its attendant political and pragmatic ramifications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0739456X12455666">
<title>Substantive Justification</title>
<p>The third—substantive—justification for reexamining the authorial process is straightforward: collaborative authorship makes better texts. The widely recognized principle that difference is a resource that enriches democratic deliberation applies with equal force to discursive practice, the collection of data, and the writing of planning narratives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0739456X12455666">Sandercock 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0739456X12455666">Young 2000</xref>). Multivocal authorship achieves what cultural critic Susan Sontag claimed to be “the aim of all commentary on art . . . to make works of art—and by analogy, our own experience—more, rather than less, real to us” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0739456X12455666">Sontag 1966</xref>, 14).</p>
<p>Sontag’s strategy is to focus on form in art rather than searching a work of art for its inner meaning. This entails using a “descriptive, rather than prescriptive, vocabulary” that guards against the “arrogance of interpretation” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0739456X12455666">1966</xref>, 12). But form, whether in art or in narrative, is a substantive rather than simply a stylistic matter. A redistribution of power and voice in the text affects not only its mode of speaking but also its substantive content. As Martha Nussbaum explains:
<disp-quote>
<p>form and style are not incidental features. A view of life is <italic>told.</italic> The telling itself—the selection of genre, formal structures, sentences, vocabulary, of the whole manner of addressing the reader’s sense of life—all of this expresses a sense of what matters and what does not, of what learning and communicating are, of life’s relations and connections. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0739456X12455666">Nussbaum 1990</xref>, 5)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The substantive argument for shared authority in the writing of texts is that it makes for better and stronger narratives. The composition of the text—the “Here”—is as substantively important as is the process of data collection out “There”.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0739456X12455666">
<title>Approaches to Narrative</title>
<p>In this section, we examine a variety of narrative strategies that authors have adopted to address the problem of authorship within a broad-ranging multidisciplinary literature on the city.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0739456X12455666">2</xref></sup> We find a helpful starting point in Geertz’s typology of narrative approaches culled from the ethnographic literature. For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">Geertz (1988)</xref>, the authorial challenge is how to express the relationship of the author to the subject within the relationship of the author to the text.</p>
<p>Geertz identifies five forms that this relationship might take, arrayed along a continuum between the “author-saturated” and the “author-evacuated” text (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">1988</xref>, 145). At the author-saturated end of this continuum is “<italic>ethnography-as-confession</italic>,” in which the author admits that the only reality that he or she can accurately convey is that of the researcher rather than that of the subject. As a consequence, the focus of analysis is the researcher’s experience of encounter in the field rather than the subject encountered there. In attempting to skirt the problem of representation, this approach makes the author the subject and reduces the role of the subject in the field to that of secondary or supporting player. At the opposite end of Geertz’s continuum is “<italic>text positivism</italic>,” in which the ethnographer attempts to serve as an honest broker reproducing the subject’s words on the page with the least possible alteration or authorial intervention.</p>
<p>Geertz’s remaining strategies fall between these two extremes. “<italic>Ethnographic ventriloquism</italic>” is the name he gives to the claim to “speak not just <italic>about</italic> another form of life but to speak from within it” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">1988</xref>, 145). Under this rubric, authors seek to serve as such effective storytellers that they can claim to take on the voice of their subjects. Geertz also highlights the common practice of “<italic>authorial self-inspection</italic>,” the hope that bias can be minimized or eliminated by the author’s up-front admission that it exists. Finally, there is “<italic>dispersed authorship</italic>,” the “heteroglossial” notion that the narrative task may be shared between the researcher and the research subject in a “direct, equal and independent way” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">1988</xref>, 145).</p>
<p>Following Geertz’s lead, we have developed a similar framework encompassing four narrative strategies, also arrayed along a continuum from the least to the greatest presence of the subject’s voice and authority in the text. We call these strategies <italic>empathetic evocation, selective deployment of informant narratives, dialogic collaboration</italic>, and <italic>uninterpreted transcription</italic>. This short list is not meant to be exhaustive (we exclude dogmatic or demagogic approaches, for example, as well as fictional narrative) but rather to continue the conversation Geertz has begun about the textual strategies available to us as authors of research narratives.</p>
<sec id="section7-0739456X12455666">
<title>Empathetic Evocation</title>
<p><italic>Empathetic evocation</italic> involves the use of redolent description to summon the situated experience of the subject for the reader. An example of empathetic evocation in the construction of urban narrative is AbdouMaliq Simone’s <italic>For the City Yet to Come: Changing African Life in Four Cities</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0739456X12455666">2004</xref>). His book centers on four case studies of emerging urbanism: Pikine, a suburb near Dakar, Senegal; Winterveld, a neighborhood in Pretoria, South Africa; the city of Douala, Cameroon; and among African workers in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. Simone’s stated goal is “to make common cause with the daily efforts of urban African residents” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0739456X12455666">2004</xref>, 16), and his empathetic reporting is based on intensive firsthand experience gained over fifteen years in various roles, from activist to professor to researcher and fellow Muslim, in these and other cities.</p>
<p>With clarity of vision and sensitive attention to detail, Simone provides evocative insights into the practices of daily life in each of these places. He explains early on the difficulty of doing traditional, systematic research in African cities, where the only constant is change and the structures and systems supporting life are fragile, volatile, and ephemeral. In a context of instability and impermanence, the research process similarly must be provisional and pragmatic and the themes of informality, invisibility, spectrality, and movement around which Simone frames his narrative were chosen to reflect the conditions he observed.</p>
<p>An excerpt from Simone’s text illustrates his attention to detail in evoking the conditions and complexities of everyday life:
<disp-quote>
<p>One rainy morning in July 2001, I saw scores of people in their best clothes carefully navigating their way in and out of one of the few well-constructed homes in the section of the Zone known as CCM-Oyok, a dense and rambling quarter built along a series of ravines. The porch of the house was crowded with families. . . . The home with all of the traffic was that of a local healer and clearly the center of community life. . . . Immediately in front of the “clinic” was the main water tap for the area, set in (an) 8 ft. x 8 ft. x 3 ft. basin intended to prevent runoff from either frequent use or leakage. But in this weather, diverted streams branching out across the ravine flooded the basin with dirty water, in which the tap was submerged. The fresh water could only be obtained by dipping a bucket into the dirty water—a problem that could easily have been resolved by fixing a rubber extension to the nozzle so as to elevate the flow. The relationship between the crowds at the local healer and the compromised water tap, on the surface, seemed obvious. Although the quarter was rife with many other difficulties, at least here it appeared as if a simple solution was possible. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0739456X12455666">Simone 2004</xref>, 103-4)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Simone goes on to describe the complex relationships between the healer and the townspeople and the roundabout way they found for addressing the water problem.</p>
<p>Through the practice of empathetic evocation, Simone successfully puts the reader in the scene and connects the reader to the place and moment portrayed in the narrative. Nonetheless, the roles and subjectivities of the people involved in the story remain obscured and the voices of participants do not (or only rarely) appear in the case study descriptions. While Simone may have employed a nontraditional social science research methodology, relying on his immersion in the case to collect and validate his observations, the resulting text closely hews to the format of a traditional research narrative. Although the book opens with profuse praise and effusive appreciation for the subjects’ contributions to Simone’s knowledge gained over fifteen years in African cities, subsequent chapters do not delve into those relationships or allow us direct access to the voices that the author might have heard.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0739456X12455666">
<title>Selective Deployment</title>
<p>Providing somewhat greater scope for the subject’s perspective and perhaps the most popular strategy employed in reports of qualitative research is the <italic>selective deployment of informant narratives</italic>. In this method, the author marshals selective excerpts from informant interviews to illustrate or support the author’s claims. While the subject’s words appear on the page, they are enlisted on behalf of the author’s point of view and it is the author’s voice that sounds throughout the text.</p>
<p>A particular version of selective deployment, Geraldine Pratt’s <italic>Working Feminism</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">2004</xref>), is a book with dual objectives. On one level, it is a case study of women domestic workers in Vancouver, Canada, that examines the working lives of Filipina nannies and their struggles to maintain their personal and work identities under conditions that are ripe for abuse and exploitation. The book’s second objective is to test feminist geographical theory against the materiality of the case study. Pratt’s textual strategy is to alternate empirical chapters describing the circumstances and experiences of the women and their employers with chapters devoted to theory development expressed at a very high level of abstraction. In the author’s words, <italic>Working Feminism</italic> “is a series of dialogues between highly abstracted theoretical and less abstracted empirical analyses. Ideally, it is also a means to other dialogues outside the text” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">Pratt 2004</xref>, 9).</p>
<p>In her empirical chapters, Pratt uses the relatively conventional tactic of inserting quotes from focus group participants as sort of “proof texts” around the point she seeks to make. In the passage below, Pratt mobilizes quotes obtained during an interview with employers of Rosa, a Filipina nanny, to restate and substantiate her observations:
<disp-quote>
<p>It is sometimes unclear . . . as to whether a domestic worker is an employee or “a family member” . . . and whether work beyond eight hours is done by choice or coercion. It is interesting to listen to one set of employers explain why their Filipina nanny works 12-13 hours a day for 8 hours’ worth of minimum wage.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<speech>
<speaker>Gary:</speaker>
<p>No, but then again, Rosa, on the other hand, I don’t know whether she likes to work or she feels compelled to work . . . . But she’d rather, I don’t know, do it. I guess. I don’t know.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Susan:</speaker>
<p>And they’re very hard working. . . . But now, I mean, she really likes [my son], and it works out well. . . . And so she’s extremely good to us.</p>
</speech>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>This short passage displays many of the ingredients that lead to persisting violations of labour codes: Rosa’s labour in the evening is interpreted as a gift (“she’s extremely good to us”); Rosa’s affection for their son is seen as compensation in itself; Rosa’s self-exploitation is interpreted as a cultural trait (“they’re very hard working”). But Gary remains somewhat troubled by Rosa’s long hours of work. (He wonders whether she likes to work or feels compelled to do so and repeatedly states: “I don’t know.”) Gary and Susan are not “bad” people, but this is really beside the point. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">Pratt 2004</xref>, 99-100)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This selection demonstrates the appropriation of the interview subject’s voice to buttress the author’s observations and judgments. Pratt’s textual strategy is to narrate through and around the quotes, explaining what each interviewee’s statement means and how it fits the story she seeks to tell. The quoted words are extracted from their narrative context in the focus groups and inserted into the author’s narrative, following in a subordinate or illustrative manner the author’s statements of fact or interpretation.</p>
<p>At a further extreme, in the chapters devoted to theoretical explication, Pratt’s is the only voice to be heard. For example:
<disp-quote>
<p>Discourses of sexuality involved a literal respatialisation of sexual practices: legitimate sexuality was consigned to the parental bedroom and illegitimate sexuality to the asylum and prison, where it could be controlled and contained. Psychoanalysis created a new, safe space for sexuality “between couch and discourse.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">2004</xref>, 21)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In the explication of social theory, there is no room for the voice of the subject. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">Pratt (2004</xref>, 8) admits that her case study participants evinced a lack of interest in the abstract framing devices she uses to elucidate their stories.</p>
<p>Following the alternating theoretical and empirical chapters in <italic>Working Feminism</italic>, Pratt uses her final chapter as a space for reflection, shifting focus entirely to the author as the subject of the narrative. [“I find it important to work away at the puzzle of my reactions . . . ” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">2004</xref>, 184)]. By making the author the subject, it is the part of the book that most completely bridges Pratt’s two worlds of theory and the case while further widening the gap between the world of the author and that of the Filipina nannies with whose lives she wishes to engage.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0739456X12455666">
<title>Dialogic Collaboration</title>
<p>Distinct from the practices of empathetic evocation or selective deployment is <italic>dialogic collaboration</italic>, in which the narrative emerges as a conversational exchange between author and subject. A master of dialogic collaboration was Joseph Mitchell who, as staff writer at the <italic>New Yorker</italic> magazine for more than fifty years, chronicled the life of the city’s marginal figures: the “bums” and night-shift workers and assorted denizens of the lower classes. <italic>Up in the Old Hotel</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0739456X12455666">Mitchell [1938] 2008</xref>) is a collection of Mitchell’s writings produced throughout his career, previously published in four books of essays including <italic>Joe Gould’s Secret</italic>, Mitchell’s last published work.</p>
<p>Mitchell rendered the experience of urban life in New York of the 1940s and 1950s through the characters he encountered on his forays around the city. In Mitchell’s hands, their stories are incredible and indelible, full of enigmatic twists, unlikely encounters, and stretches of the imagination. He achieves credibility through extremely detailed descriptions of sights, smells, and sounds, from architectural details to clothes and hairstyles, and by allowing his subjects’ voices to suffuse the narrative and speak for and about themselves.</p>
<p>Mitchell’s best-known work is his profile of the gadfly Joe Gould, a New York character who claimed to have authored an oral history (“An Oral History of Our Time”) that Gould insisted was the longest book ever written. As Mitchell explains in the opening sentence of <italic>Joe Gould’s Secret</italic>, “Joe Gould was an odd and penniless and unemployable little man who came to the city in 1916 and ducked and dodged and held on as hard as he could for over thirty-five years” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0739456X12455666">Mitchell [1938] 2008</xref>, 623). After conversing with Gould for decades, Mitchell comes to understand that the Oral History exists only in Gould’s imagination but Mitchell nonetheless agrees to perpetuate the myth of its existence until after Gould’s death.</p>
<p>Mitchell’s descriptions of Gould are painstakingly observed:
<disp-quote>
<p>We took a booth, and the waitress brought Gould’s coffee. It was in a thick white mug, diner style, and it was so hot it was steaming. Even so, tipping the mug slightly toward him without taking it off the table, he bent down and immediately began drinking it with little, cautious, quick, birdlike sips and gulps interspersed with little whimpering sounds indicating pleasure and relief, and almost at once color returned to his face and his eyes became brighter and his twitch disappeared. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0739456X12455666">2008</xref>, 636)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>But almost immediately, Gould’s voice becomes prominent in the narrative:
<disp-quote>
<p>“I suppose you’re puzzled about me,” he said. His tone of voice was condescending; he had got some of his confidence back. “If so,” he continued, “the feeling is mutual, for I’m puzzled about myself, and have been since childhood. I seem to be a changeling or a throwback or a mutation of some sort in a highly respectable New England family. Let me give you a few biographical facts. My full name is Joseph Ferdinand Gould, and I was named for my grandfather, who was a doctor.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0739456X12455666">2008</xref>, 636-37)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>And on Gould goes, narrating his own story nearly continuously for the next ten pages of the text. Often, the story proceeds through a back-and-forth dialogue in which Mitchell and Gould share the textual space as well as the burden of moving the narrative forward:
<disp-quote>
<p>A throbbing quality had come into Gould’s voice.</p>
<p>“Since that fateful morning,” he continued, squaring his shoulders and dilating his nostrils and lifting his chin, as if in heroic defiance, “the Oral History has been my rope and my scaffold, my bed and my board, my wife and my floozy, my wound and the salt on it, my whiskey and my aspirin, and my rock and my salvation. It is the only thing that matters a damn to me. All else is dross.”</p>
<p>It was obvious that this was a set speech and that he had it down pat and that he had spoken it many times through the years and that he relished speaking it, and it made me obscurely uncomfortable.</p>
<p>“Just now, when you told the waitress that you were an authority on the language of the sea gull,” I said, changing the subject, “did you mean it?”</p>
<p>Gould’s face lit up. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0739456X12455666">2008</xref>, 645)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0739456X12455666">
<title>Uninterpreted Transcription</title>
<p>At the furthest (author-evacuated) end of the authorial spectrum is what we are calling <italic>uninterpreted transcription</italic>, closely akin to Geertz’s category of “text positivism.” In this mode, the author gathers stories from the subject and then presents them unaltered in the text. Of course, there is no way to present truly unfiltered transcription. The researcher always makes choices about whom to interview, when to start and stop the tape recorder, what to include in the manuscript. But using the honest broker approach, the researcher attempts to interfere as little as possible, presenting the subject’s narrative as clearly and directly as possible given the constraints imposed by the exigencies of text production.</p>
<p>Studs Terkel’s <italic>Working</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0739456X12455666">[1974] 2004</xref>) is perhaps the most widely known example of uninterpreted transcription. It is the third of his studies of American life presented through the narratives of everyday people, following <italic>Hard Times</italic> ([1970] 2000) and <italic>Division Street</italic> ([1967] 2006). Terkel used essentially the same method to gather material for <italic>Working</italic> as for the two books that preceded it and, like AbdouMaliq Simone, he states that his method is preferable to a more conventional or systematic “research” method.</p>
<p>Terkel makes no attempt to seek out a random sample for his interviews. He states, “I had a general idea of the kind of people I wanted to see; who, in reflecting on their personal condition, would touch on the circumstances of their fellows” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0739456X12455666">[1974] 2004</xref>, xx). With this peripatetic mode of sample selection, the conventional academic interview technique was insufficient: “I realized quite early in this adventure that interviews, conventionally conducted, were meaningless. . . . The question-and-answer technique may be of some value in determining favored detergents, toothpaste and deodorants, but not in the discovery of men and women. . . . The talk was idiomatic rather than academic. In short, it was conversation” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0739456X12455666">[1974] 2004</xref>, xx-xxi).</p>
<p>Terkel speaks explicitly to the ethics of his research: “I was no more than a wayfaring stranger, taking much and giving little. . . . I was the beneficiary of others’ generosity. My tape recorder, as ubiquitous as the carpenter’s tool chest or the doctor’s black satchel, carried away valuables beyond price” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0739456X12455666">[1974] 2004</xref>, xviii). Terkel is not interested in the appearance of objectivity. He makes no effort to hide his feelings about the menial nature of the work performed by most of his informants, beginning the book with an invocation that links work with violence and struggle. But Terkel passes on the various stories of work, of fulfillment and despair alike, without further comment.</p>
<p>The nearly 600 pages in <italic>Working</italic> present the first-person narratives of more than 130 individuals describing their experience of work. Here are the words of a stone mason:
<disp-quote>
<p>I think a laborer feels that he’s the low man. Not so much that he works with his hands, it’s that he’s at the bottom of the scale. He always wants to get up to a skilled trade. Of course he’d make more money. The main thing is the common laborer—even the word <italic>common</italic> laborer—just sounds so common, he’s at the bottom. Many that works with his hands takes pride in his work. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0739456X12455666">[1974] 2004</xref>, xlvi)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Terkel presents these stories as whole unto themselves, uninterrupted by his observations or interpretations. The stories speak for themselves. Each narrative is introduced with a brief capsule description of the person and the setting: “He is a washroom attendant at the Palmer House . . . He has been at this for fifteen years” (106); “He is a widower and has five grandchildren. He lives with his two unmarried sisters” (110); “She has been a waitress in the same restaurant for twenty-three years” (293). And yet, while the words in the text are those of the individuals narrating their stories, <italic>Working</italic> is undeniably Terkel’s work, in which he tells <italic>his</italic> story about work and workers through their words and it is Terkel’s name that appears as author on the cover of the book.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0739456X12455666">
<title>Implications: Strategies for Collaborative Authorship</title>
<p>While the narrative strategies reviewed above reveal a range of author–subject relations and speaking positions, in no case does the research subject bridge the authorial divide and attain the status of (co)author of the narrative. Here is where we unavoidably part company with Geertz’s useful distinction between author-saturated and author-evacuated texts. If in the first (author-saturated) mode the author is reflexively speaking about himself or herself and in the second (author-evacuated) mode the author is dispassionately (“objectively”) speaking about the subject, in both cases it is the author who is doing all the talking and whose voice appears on the page. How, then, can authorship be shared, or can the collaborative nature of knowledge production find its way onto the page?</p>
<p>As a means to encourage a conversation that considers this question, we offer four authorial strategies that, while overlapping and potentially contradictory, may begin to narrow the persistent gap between author and subject in narratives of planning research. Three of these suggested strategies examine narrative practices without altering the authorial mode that is largely taken for granted in academic discourse, which entails representing knowledge to an external audience (i.e., external to the author–subject relation). The fourth strategy requires a more fundamental reconsideration of the purpose, practice, and participants in the process of knowledge creation.</p>
<sec id="section12-0739456X12455666">
<title>Avoiding Abstraction and Interpretation</title>
<p>A negative strategy, negative in the sense that it names a practice to avoid, concerns the often-critiqued but near-universal leap to interpretation and abstraction that is a hallmark of the social sciences. In contrast to prevailing practice, avoiding the leap to interpretation and abstraction and remaining close to the case holds open a greater space for the subject’s voice to appear on the page.</p>
<p>The validation of knowledge on the basis of its interpretive power beyond “mere” description underlies both the commonly accepted method of social research and the professional reward structures (e.g., publication, research funding, career promotion) within which most research occurs. Description of the case, in this approach, entails reporting the data collected in the field, while interpretation of what the data “really mean” and abstraction from the particulars of the case represent the added value provided by the analyst (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0739456X12455666">Flyvbjerg 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>But critiques of the leap to abstraction are equally longstanding, ranging from Nietzsche’s “renunciation of interpretation generally (that is, of forcing, doctoring, abridging, omitting, suppressing, inventing, falsifying, and all the other <italic>essential</italic> attributes of interpretation)” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0739456X12455666">Nietzsche [1913] 2003</xref>, 110) to Susan Sontag’s brief <italic>Against Interpretation</italic> (1966) to Timothy Mitchell’s assertion that “the theory lies in the complexity of the cases” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0739456X12455666">2002</xref>, 8) and Bruno Latour’s concern with “how to let the actors have some room to express themselves” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0739456X12455666">2005</xref>, 142). To take the interpretive leap is to leave behind the voice of the subject and to privilege the interpreter’s voice as dominant in the narrative. As demonstrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739456X12455666">Geraldine Pratt’s (2004)</xref> alternating chapters on theory and materiality, subjects rarely, if ever, speak in abstract terms. A solution, as Latour insists, is that “if your description needs an explanation, it’s not a good description. . . . Don’t try to shift from description to explanation: simply <italic>go on with</italic> description” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0739456X12455666">Latour 2005</xref>, 147, 150). What differentiates Latourian description from a mere journalistic recounting of events is that the former employs a genealogical method in which the relationships among actors are more important (and more difficult to discern) than the actors in isolation. As compared to the researcher’s impulse to distanced—and therefore monologic—interpretation, description in this mode stands a better chance of enrichment through collaborative authorship when both researcher and subjects speak from variously situated perspectives within the relation being described.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0739456X12455666">
<title>Contextualization</title>
<p>A possible (and thus positive) move toward collaborative authorship is the narrative strategy of contextualization. Enabled precisely by the researcher’s position outside the case, researcher and subject adopt a division of labor that encompasses complementary perspectives of inside and outside, the local and the global, in describing the case. Cahill et al note the “responsibility to locate our research in a social, structural, and geographical context. . . . We need to draw connections between personal, on-the-ground experiences and their broader geopolitical significance” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0739456X12455666">Cahill, Sultana, and Pain 2007</xref>, 312). In this strategy, the subject speaks for himself or herself and the researcher’s responsibility is to situate or contextualize the subject’s narrative in a broader descriptive framework. By contextualizing the subject’s practical knowledge, the researcher’s external perspective and the subject’s experiential vantage point can be complementary and collaborative rather than contradictory and exclusive.</p>
<p>The strategy of contextualization unites researcher and subject within a single descriptive narrative advancing along complementary planes. Contextualization, from this perspective, avoids the tendency to reduce the researcher–subject relation to a neat dualism of the abstract versus concrete. Such a move would elevate the researcher to the rarified world of abstraction while relegating the subject to the messiness of the “real” and would actually undermine the possibility of constructive collaboration by separating researcher and subject into incommensurable ontological categories of the abstract and the empirical.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0739456X12455666">
<title>Transcending Distanced Objectivity</title>
<p>The doctrine of distanced objectivity, much critiqued by postpositivist theorists, stands in the way of enlisting the situated subjectivity of research subjects in the authorship of planning narratives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0739456X12455666">Latour 2005</xref>, 146; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0739456X12455666">Rorty 1982</xref>, 196). In contrast to the axioms of rational planning, subjectivity can be appreciated as a resource and authorship can be conceptualized as a process for recognizing and adopting the distinctive perspectives of diverse collaborators. Understanding discourse as intersubjectively situated opens a space for researcher and subject to bring their perspectives into conversation within the narrative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0739456X12455666">Morris 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Enrolling the distinct subjectivities of researcher and subject in the project of authorship entails relinquishing the stance of objectivity conventionally understood as the hallmark of good research practice. Contrary to the belief inherited from Enlightenment epistemology, in this view, objectivity does not entail the absence of bias or presuppositions but, rather, can be understood as the alignment of thought with a prevailing paradigmatic perspective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0739456X12455666">Kuhn 1962</xref>). By the same logic, subjectivity is not the assertion of a biased (i.e., personal) perspective but rather expresses a perspective at odds with the reigning paradigm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0739456X12455666">Rorty 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0739456X12455666">1999</xref>). Collaborative authorship, from this perspective, transcends the necessity of aligning the multiple perspectives of researcher and subject into conformance with the requirements of a prevailing framework or paradigm.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0739456X12455666">
<title>Rethinking the Logic of Research</title>
<p>Just as the introduction of participatory planning theory prompted a disciplinary reconsideration of the methods of planning practice (e.g., to include mediation, facilitation, and communication skills in addition to physical plan-making), extending the collaborative ideal to the production of planning narratives may involve rethinking the goals and logic of research and the audience to which the narrative is directed. Before distinguishing between practices of speaking about, for, or with the subject is the virtue of reconsidering the will to speak at all, recognizing, after Nietzsche, that speaking is not necessarily the same as or the only means of knowledge production.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0739456X12455666">3</xref></sup> Listening, engaging, enabling, and conversing may comprise alternative practices of knowledge production in which the research “subject” is both the coproducer and the corecipient of knowledge. This alternative view sees research as a conversation <italic>with</italic> the subject, not an inquiry followed by a distinct reporting phase but as an end in itself, where knowledge is produced within the conversational process. For the researcher, this may involve more listening than speaking. It may involve an openness to how another’s perspective might inform one’s knowledge rather than informing others about what to know. Here knowledge is produced among participants in a conversation rather than reported to a distant audience, with the goal to expand the conversational circle rather than the size of the audience.</p>
<p>Adopting this strategy entails a more fundamental reconsideration of the purposes and premises of planning research. While there is ample potential for improving collaboration within the research process, for example by inviting subjects to review or edit the narrative products of analysis, it may be fruitful to consider the limitations on collaboration that the analytic model imposes by only speaking about the subject. The difference between analysis and conversation is what Richard Rorty has in mind in proposing that
<disp-quote>
<p>we do not think that when we say something we must necessarily be expressing a view about a subject. We might just be <italic>saying something</italic>—participating in a conversation rather than contributing to an inquiry. Perhaps saying things is not always saying how things are. Perhaps saying <italic>that</italic> is itself not a case of saying how things are. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0739456X12455666">1979</xref>, 371)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The narrative shift from representation to conversation suggested by Rorty, a shift in the author’s relation to the text, both produces and rests upon a reconsideration of the researcher’s relation to the subject. As Rorty explains,
<disp-quote>
<p>To see keeping a conversation going as a sufficient aim of philosophy, to see wisdom as consisting in the ability to sustain a conversation, is to see human beings as generators of new descriptions rather than beings one hopes to be able to describe accurately. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0739456X12455666">1979</xref>, 378)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Clifford Geertz concludes his deconstruction of ethnographic narrative by identifying as the “next necessary thing . . . to enlarge the possibility of intelligible discourse between people quite different from one another” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">1988</xref>, 147). Those quite different people to whom he refers are the researcher and the research subject engaged through conversation in the coproduction of knowledge for and with each other. It is perhaps in this sense that Rorty suggests that “we should think of language as a tool for breaking down people’s distrust of one another rather than as one for representing how things really are” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0739456X12455666">1996</xref>, 335). Rethinking the process of planning action and research as a conversation between researcher and subject rather than an inquiry by the researcher about the subject would inevitably produce different kinds of planning narratives and a reconsideration of what it means to be a planner.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0739456X12455666">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Ethical, pragmatic, and substantive considerations prompt the extension of collaborative practices to the authorial stage of knowledge production in planning action and research. A selective review of the multidisciplinary literature on the city reveals a variety of approaches, ranging from empathetic evocation to uninterpreted transcription, adopted by authors attempting to share narrative authority with their research subjects. Across this range of narrative styles, however, the author rarely relinquishes discursive authority and the collaborative ideal of participatory planning and research runs aground at the stage of narrative production.</p>
<p>Solutions to this dilemma move beyond conventional narrative practices in planning and the social sciences, beginning with the avoidance of interpretation as the purpose and product of analysis. The impulse to interpretation shifts the narrative away from the direct experience of the subject to a discussion of abstractions conveyed solely in the author’s voice. Within the interpretive frame, the potential for collaborative narration between author and subject deteriorates into the use of the subject as a means for the author’s narrative ends. In place of a narrative about the subject addressed to a distant audience, collaborative authorship envisions the goal of inquiry as a conversation within a discursive community composed of author and subject engaged in a project of mutual learning. Whether as communicative planning theory or participatory method, the collaborative ideal requires collaboration all the way down.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>The authors thank the faculty and participants at the 2009 Advanced Oral History Summer Institute at the Regional Oral History Office at the University of California–Berkeley who prompted the ideas that developed into this paper. We thank Robert Beauregard, Ann Markusen, Kathe Newman, Susan Saegert, Elvin Wyly, and three anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on earlier versions of this paper.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0739456X12455666">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Several reviewers have commented on the recursive difficulties raised by our authorship of a text that considers the practice and authority of authorship, and we are well attuned to the sensitivity of this dilemma. This is a case of the “double hermeneutic” inflecting our unavoidably selective interpretation of authorship as itself a selective and interpretive practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0739456X12455666">Brogden, 2010</xref>, 322–24). While readily acknowledging the inescapable partiality engrained in our own authorial practice, we believe there is something to be gained by addressing the issue of authorship in general while avoiding the infinite regress entailed in turning our analytic gaze on ourselves as particular authors. What <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739456X12455666">Geertz (1988</xref>, 145) refers to as the method of “authorial self-inspection” runs the risk, when taken to its extreme, of evicting the subject from the page.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0739456X12455666">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The specific texts excerpted in this section were selected as illustrations of particular narrative strategies or styles. We neither intend nor imply a substantive evaluation or critique of the selected works, which, in our view and in their respective ways, are exemplary contributions to the urban studies literature.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0739456X12455666">
<label>3.</label>
<p>In its most extreme form, reconsidering the will to speak echoes Alcoff’s caustic observation that “the impetus to speak must be carefully analyzed and, in many cases (certainly for academics), fought against . . . [T]he impetus to <italic>always</italic> be the speaker and to speak in all situations must be seen for what it is: a desire for mastery and domination” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0739456X12455666">1995</xref>, 111).</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Robert W. Lake</bold> is a professor of Urban Planning and Policy Development at the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University. His research focuses on community-based planning, urban and political geography, and social theory.</p>
<p><bold>Andrew W. Zitcer</bold> is an assistant teaching professor in Drexel University’s Westphal College of Media Arts and Design. His interests include participatory community organizations, consumer cooperatives, and the arts in community development.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alcoff</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1995</year>. “<article-title>The Problem of Speaking for Others</article-title>.” In <source>Who Can Speak? Authority and Critical Identity</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Roof</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiegman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Urbana</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Attili</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Ethical Awareness in Advocacy Planning Research</article-title>.” In <source>Ethics and Planning Research</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lo Piccolo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Collaboration as Resistance: Reconsidering the Processes, Products, and Possibilities of Feminist Oral History and Ethnography</article-title>.” <source>Gender, Place and Culture</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brogden</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Double Hermeneutic</article-title>.” In <source>Encyclopedia of Case Study Research</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durepos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pain</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>Participatory Ethics: Politics, Practices, Institutions</article-title>.” <source>ACME: An International E-journal for Critical Geographies</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>Beyond the Journal Article: Representations, Audience, and the Presentation of Participatory Research</article-title>.” In <source>Connecting People, Participation and Place: Participatory Action Research Approaches and Methods</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kindon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pain</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kesby</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Candida Smith</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2002</year>. “<article-title>Analytic Strategies for Oral History Interviews</article-title>.” In <source>Handbook of Interview Research: Context and Method</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gubrium</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2000</year>. <source>Citizens, Experts and the Environment: The Politics of Local Knowledge</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>Knock, Knock, Knocking on Closed Doors: Exploring the Diffuse Ideal of the Collaborative Research Relationship</article-title>.” <source>Area</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flyvbjerg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Five Misunderstandings about Case-Study Research</article-title>.” <source>Qualitative Inquiry</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1984</year>. “<article-title>What Is an Author?”</article-title> In <source>The Foucault Reader</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Rabinow</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pantheon Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. <source>A Shared Authority: Essays on the Craft and Meaning of Oral and Public History</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SUNY</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geertz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1988</year>. <source>Works and Lives: The Anthropologist as Author</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Healey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2006</year>. <source>Collaborative Planning: Shaping Places in a Fragmented Society</source>. <edition>2nd edition.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>hooks</surname><given-names>b.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. “<article-title>Marginality as Site of Resistance</article-title>.” In <source>Out There: Marginalization and Contemporary Cultures</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gever</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minh-ha</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Booher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>. <source>Planning with Complexity: An Introduction to Collaborative Rationality for Public Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1962</year>. <source>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</source>. <edition>2nd edition.</edition> <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Latour</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <source>Reassembling the Social: An Introduction to Actor-Network Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macmillan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2003</year>. “<article-title>On the Case? Dilemmas of Collaborative Research</article-title>.” <source>Area</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Malcolm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. <source>The Journalist and the Murderer</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House/Vintage Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1938</year>) <year>2008</year>. <source>Up in the Old Hotel</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House/Vintage Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2002</year>. <source>Rule of Experts: Egypt, Techno-politics, Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <year>2009</year>. <source>The Bakhtin Reader</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bloomsbury</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nietzsche</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1913</year>) <year>2003</year>. <source>The Genealogy of Morals</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dover</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. <source>Love’s Knowledge: Essays on Philosophy and Literature</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. “<article-title>Jacques Derrida on Rhetoric and Composition: A Conversation</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Advanced Composition</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pain</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. “<article-title>Social Geography: Participatory Research</article-title>.” <source>Progress in Human Geography</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>652</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. <source>Working Feminism</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rorty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1979</year>. <source>Philosophy and the Mirror of Nature</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rorty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1982</year>. “<article-title>Method, Social Science, and Social Hope</article-title>.” In <source>Consequences of Pragmatism</source>, <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rorty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1996</year>. “<article-title>Idealizations, Foundations, and Social Practices</article-title>.” In <source>Democracy and Difference: Contesting the Boundaries of the Political</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Benhabib</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rorty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1999</year>. <source>Philosophy and Social Hope</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sandercock</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2003</year>. <source>Cosmopolis II: Mongrel Cities of the Twenty-First Century</source>. <edition>2nd edition.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Continuum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Geography and Gender: Feminist Methodologies in Collaboration and in the Field</article-title>.” <source>Progress in Human Geography</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. <source>For the City Yet to Come: Changing African Life in Four Cities</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1966</year>. <source>Against Interpretation: And Other Essays</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Picador/Farrar Straus &amp; Giroux</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spivak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1988</year>. “<article-title>Can the Subaltern Speak?”</article-title> In <source>Marxism and the Interpretation of Culture</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grossberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Basingstoke, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Terkel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <year>2004</year>. <source>Working</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0739456X12455666">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2000</year>. <source>Inclusion and Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>