<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ADH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spadh</journal-id>
<journal-title>Advances in Developing Human Resources</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1523-4223</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3055</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1523422313487307</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1523422313487307</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Preface</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Scholar-Practitioner Case Approach</article-title>
<subtitle>Implications for Advancing Theory and Research Through Informed Practice</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="issue-editor">
<name><surname>Scully-Russ</surname><given-names>Ellen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="issue-editor">
<name><surname>Lehner</surname><given-names>Rachelle</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="issue-editor">
<name><surname>Shuck</surname><given-names>Brad</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Scully-Russ</surname><given-names>Ellen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1523422313487307">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lehner</surname><given-names>Rachelle</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1523422313487307">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shuck</surname><given-names>Brad</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1523422313487307">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1523422313487307"><label>1</label>The George Washington University, Ashburn, VA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1523422313487307"><label>2</label>Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1523422313487307"><label>3</label>University of Louisville, Louisville, KY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1523422313487307">Ellen Scully-Russ, The George Washington University, 44983 Knoll Square, Suite 147, Ashburn, VA 20147, USA. Email: <email>scullyru@gwu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>A Scholar-Practitioner Case Approach: Implications for Advancing Theory and Research Through Informed Practice</issue-title>
<fpage>243</fpage>
<lpage>251</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1523422313487307">
<title>The Problem</title>
<p>Though there is growing interest in the nature of scholarly practice in Human Resource Development (HRD) there is little understanding of how the everyday activities of HRD practitioners are mediated by HRD theories and research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1523422313487307">
<title>The Solution</title>
<p>This preface provides the framework for this special issue on HRD scholar-practitioners. Each article in this issue, with the exception of the final article by Lombardozzi, presents a real-world case on how HRD scholar-practitioners used HRD theory and research to navigate an intractable problem in their practice. This issue explores the wide and varying ways in which scholar-practitioners approach their work, how research and theory were both applied and extended in practice, and the implications for HRD theory, research, and practice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1523422313487307">
<title>The Stakeholders</title>
<p>HRD scholars, researchers, and practitioners who are members of the Academy of Human Resource Development (AHRD), as well managers, educators, and higher education administrators who have a stake in effective organizations may gain insight into the nature of HRD scholarly practice and the role of the HRD scholar-practitioner.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>HRD (human resource development)</kwd>
<kwd>scholarly practice</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The relationship between HRD (Human Resource Development) theory, research, and practice has been the subject of ongoing discussion and debate in the Academy of Human Resource Development (AHRD). For example in August <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1523422313487307">2009 Short, Kormanik, and Ruona</xref> published the first in a series of <italic>Advances in Developing Human Resources</italic> devoted to exploring the links between research and practice in HRD. Ironically, though the explicit purpose of the series was to begin a dialogue “… between scholars and practitioners in the field of human resource development” (p. 417), many of the articles were devoted to exploring the nature and role of the scholar-practitioner—implying that scholarship and practice were separate roles that one person could or should aspire to inhabit. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1523422313487307">Kormanik, Lehner, and Winnick (2009)</xref> described competencies required for scholar-practitioners; while other authors defined the role and delineate the challenges facing scholar-practitioners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1523422313487307">Moats &amp; McLean, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1523422313487307">Ruona &amp; Gilley, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1523422313487307">Tyler, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1523422313487307">Kuchinke (2004)</xref> in <italic>Human Resource Development International</italic> took a different approach. Rather than focus on the specific roles like scholars, researchers, practitioners, or scholar-practitioners, he advocated for a dialogue in HRD on how to connect learning (theory) with informed action (practice) in the context of real HRD endeavors. As both HRD theory and practice are requisite to the performance of HRD, HRD scholarship and practice cannot be separate “prerogatives of specific occupational cultures or roles” (p. 536). Kuchinke argued for a new, functional perspective in the field of HRD to explore how HRD theories and practice are mediated through ongoing research, theory building, and interventions, as well as how each of these activities are advanced through a continuous cycle of interaction in the context of real-world problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1523422313487307">Kuchinke, 2004</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section4-1523422313487307">
<title>Purpose of This Issue</title>
<p>As an extension of this ongoing dialogue in AHRD on the role of research, theory, and practice in HRD, this issue of <italic>Advances in Developing Human Resources</italic> explores how learning (theory) and doing (practice) were both employed and extended by HRD scholars, researchers, and scholar-practitioners in the context of HRD practice. The aim of this issue is not to define HRD scholarly practice or to advocate for particular HRD theories or best practices. In this issue, we shift the focus from the contours of HRD scholarship and practice, to examine the problems that HRD practitioners encounter and the choices they make in the context of their everyday activities to illustrate how practitioners bridge theory and practice. Except for the capstone article by Lombardozzi each article in this issue presents a case wherein an individual HRD scholar-practitioner or a team of HRD scholars and practitioners applied HRD theory and research to respond to an intractable problem in the real world. The nature of an intractable problem is discussed below, but in brief it is a problem that is very complex and stubbornly difficult to solve. By exploring HRD problems and approaches we hope to expose the limitations of HRD theories and research, while also pointing to how, at the same time HRD theory and research are enhanced and extended through their application in the real world.</p>
<p>The cases in this issue provide real-life examples and reflective questions that the reader can use to consider two overarching questions about HRD scholarly practice, including: (a) What is the nature of the problems facing the field that require a closer connection between HRD theory and informed practice, which we have called intractable problems; and (b) What are ways in which HRD theory, research, and practice interact and help to mediate interventions into real life, intractable problems in organizations today? A brief discussion of these central questions is followed by a description of the articles in this issue.</p>
<sec id="section5-1523422313487307">
<title>What is the Nature of HRD Problems?</title>
<p>A focus on the new and emerging issues and the types of the problems facing HRD can help readers better understand the conditions that call on HRD professionals to adopt the scholar-practitioner role and disposition. The editors of this special issue have used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1523422313487307">Rittlel and Webber’s (1973)</xref> <italic>wicked problems</italic> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1523422313487307">Engeström’s (2008)</xref> <italic>runaway objects</italic> to describe the nature of the problems that we think may call forth a HRD scholar-practice.</p>
<p>Wicked problems are social problems that are “… ill-defined; and they rely upon elusive political judgment for resolution, not “solution.” Social problems are never solved. At best they are re-solved—over and over again” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1523422313487307">Rittlel &amp; Webber, 1973</xref>, p. 160). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1523422313487307">Engeström (2008)</xref> explored runaway objects. As an activity theorist, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1523422313487307">Engeström (2008)</xref> saw productive human activity as object-driven. “Objects are concerns; they are generators and foci of attention, motivation, effort and meaning. Through their activity people constantly change and create new objects” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1523422313487307">Engeström 2008</xref>, p. 3). Further, he claimed that late modernity is characterized by the existence of “runaway objects” which quickly escalate and expand globally. Runaway objects are “… poorly under anybody’s control and have far-reaching unexpected effects. Such objects are monsters; they seem to have a life of their own that threatens our security and safety in many ways” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1523422313487307">Engeström, 2008</xref>, pp. 3-4).</p>
<p>Operationally, wicked problems and runaway objects are immense challenges that test the foundational premises of society. These problems and objects cannot be reduced to one or two areas of investigation that mirror preexisting professional or scholarly discourse; they require a convergence of knowledge. Nor can they be extracted from their context of everyday life so that neutral observers can examine them; they are embedded within the fabric of living and our experience of work and performance each day. Thus, these problems challenge the dualistic and reductionist thinking of the modern era and require innovative and collaborative thinking. They require both a dedication to scholarship and informed practice.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1523422313487307">Beck, Bonss, and Lau (2003)</xref> suggested that the answers or solutions to these problems demand legitimacy, responsibility, and a reflexive practical knowledge that… “does not flow from the scientific method; rather it is derived from extra-scientific criteria, including public recognition, personal experience, aesthetic judgment and the procedures that allocate money and resources” (p. 16). In this mind-set, science and rationality are not disregarded; instead the basic premises upon which formal knowledge rests are constantly scrutinized in the context of action within the world. This type of knowledge development makes it possible to learn and apply practical experience using a scholarly frame of reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1523422313487307">Beck et al., 2003</xref>). This new reflexive mind-set is what scholars call <italic>scholarly-practice</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1523422313487307">Short, Keefer, &amp; Stone, 2009</xref>). As this new mind-set continues maturing in the context of HRD, the emergence may demand an integration and transformation of the very theories and practices that have come to define the field as a profession.</p>
<p>Wicked problems and runaway objects are how the editors of this issue have chosen to frame and describe intractable problems found within HRD practice. The problems explored in the articles further illustrate what we mean by intractable problems, for example, resistance to change, incivility in the workplace, and the tension between performance and development in the context of HRD practice. To encourage diversity of thought, the authors were encouraged to highlight and consider the nature of their particular problem. For example, was the problem or challenge the scholar-practitioner faced intractable and why, or did the problem or challenge fit within the description of wicked problems and runaway objects? If not, are there other ways to describe the problem? Our aim with these questions was to encourage the authors to provide a deep description of their context so to shed new light on the deep contours of scholarly practice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1523422313487307">
<title>What is the Emerging HRD Praxis?</title>
<p>In this issue we looked to extend earlier work, specifically <italic>Advances in Developing Human Resources Bridging the Gap: Scholar-Practitioners in Human Resource Development</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1523422313487307">Short et al., 2009</xref>), which laid the foundation for what scholar-practice in HRD looked like. The current issue goes further, and takes the exploration of the scholar-practitioner role to the next level—that of application, with acknowledgment of the required competencies and skills of both HRD scholarship and practice.</p>
<p>To accomplish this, each author considered the mission of <italic>Advances</italic> which is “ … to bridge research and theory to and from practice in such a way as to help scholar-practitioners … work more effectively in human resource development” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1523422313487307">Lynham &amp; McDonald, 2011</xref>, p. 131). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1523422313487307">Figure 1</xref> depicts the interacting components of HRD praxis. HRD practice, and in particular work on intractable problems in real-world settings demands critical inquiry and reflection, or research. This inquiry can generate and extend HRD theory, which in turn calls for continuous inquiry (research). Together this inquiry (research) and theory-building leads to more thoughtful and hopefully impactful practice—that in turn calls for inquiry … and the cycle continues.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1523422313487307" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Interacting components of HRD praxis.</p>
<p>Source: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1523422313487307">Lynham and McDonald (2011)</xref>. Reprinted with permission.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1523422313487307-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The authors in this issue were asked to provide the reader with a lens onto their HRD praxis in the context of a real-life case. Each article in this issue describes the specific HRD theories used in the case, the type of HRD research that was conducted, and how this scholarship helped to frame the problem and develop the interventions that drove solutions. Authors also reflect on what they learned from the case and how their learning raised new research questions and/or enhanced HRD theory.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1523422313487307">
<title>Description of the Articles</title>
<p>To illustrate HRD scholarly practice in the context of real-world intractable problems, all articles (with the exception of the final article) are presented as a single case, using the context of a problem or specific challenge to frame the article. The framework and methodology for inclusion of the articles is loosely based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1523422313487307">Yin’s (2009)</xref> single case study design. The case-based approach is considered the preferred research methodology when the researcher intends to explore a bounded system with implications for informed scholarship such as is the case with this issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1523422313487307">Yin, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>To adhere to the case-based methodology, each article provides a background context to a problem and presents the dilemma for the reader as a framework (i.e., problem). This problem description allows the reader to more fully understand, appreciate, and step into the world of the practitioner, using their unique lens and perspective. Next, authors share the solution they settled on and analyze the HRD intervention and its impact. Each article also includes a discussion of the implications for HRD practice (i.e., solution).</p>
<p>In addition, to highlight the utility of each case as a tool for advancing theory and practice, each article also includes a critical thinking section at the conclusion of the case. The intended purpose of this section is to pose questions that engage the reader in critical thinking and informed scholarly practice. As editors, we recognize the critical thinking section is highly unusual; however, our hope is that these questions will promote the multipurpose utility of the issue as well as engage readers in the critical inquiry that is an integral feature of the scholarly practice praxis. Moreover, this approach further solidifies the operationalization of wicked problems and runaway object, of which, there could be many solutions. Bringing critical reflection on HRD practice problems and solutions to the forefront of the conversation seems an innovative and promising methodology for exploring the intersection and relationship between HRD theory, research, and practice.</p>
<p>In the first article, “Rearticulating Shared Values Through Action Learning at Children’s Hospital Colorado” Wukitsch, Simmons, and Hutt illustrate the powerful role of theory in addressing intractable problems encountered in a health care system undergoing great change. The concern was that new organizational structures fragmented the organization and led to a “cultural drift” that threatened organizational cohesion, values, and mission. The authors, a team of HRD scholars and practitioners, drew on a number of HRD theories including appreciative inquiry and U-theory to design an intervention to help staff rearticulate core values and anchor the organization in its historic mission of service. Like many other complex change interventions, this effort faced many challenges, including threats to the change process itself. This case shows how well-chosen and skillfully integrated HRD theories provide change agents the intellectual guidance and confidence they need to navigate the ambiguity and frustrations that are an inevitable part of HRD interventions.</p>
<p>The second article, “Designing a 3-D Virtual HRD Environment From a Scholar-Practitioner Perspective” by Short explored a scholarly-practice approach to an intractable problem, which he defined as a “space” where practice is out ahead of research. One such space is at the intersection of HRD and technology. The question in this case was: How can new 3-D virtual technology be used to design an online training environment to replicate many of the features and outcomes of traditional classroom training? This article speaks to how limitations in the scholarly literature on 3D environments and online training were overcome by combining the little research that existed with evidenced-based research and other sources of information, such as expert interviews, to design a new 3-D campus and a virtual approach to training. In this case, a scholarly approach of accessing appropriate literature, interpreting it within the context of specific organizations and projects, and combining it with other sources was used to fill the research–practice gap.</p>
<p>In Article 3, Gedro and Wang also encountered a poorly understood and under-researched problem, organizational incivility. In “Creating Civil Organizations: Application of Research to Practice” they explored a case in which a practitioner instinctively knew she had encountered a significant problem, but she could not get her arms around it until she encountered a scholarly article that presented a framework for understanding and addressing organizational incivility. The article offered a new language to help the practitioner and others make meaning of their experiences with incivility and it catalyzed a system-wide training intervention to help people recognize and respond to incivility. This case illustrates how scholarship can inform practice and the importance and power of disseminating research, particularly research on poorly understood issues and problems.</p>
<p>Busch in Article 4, “Determining Competencies for Frontline Sales Managers in For-Profit Organizations” addresses the problem of how to develop a new competency framework for front line sales manager that is highly fluid and rapidly changing due to new business models and shifting relationships in the occupation. Once drawn from the ranks of the sales superstars, sales managers today need business savvy and coaching skills not easily developed on the job. Employers in many industries need new competency frameworks to train sales managers and valid, reliable assessments to support high stakes employment decisions. This case describes how a large-scale and rigorous research project resulted in a new competency framework to support an emerging occupation.</p>
<p>Finally, Lombardozzi in Article 5, “The SMART Practice of Scholarly-Practice: Notes From the Field,” departs from the case-based methodology to explore the tense relationship between scholarly practice and the performance requirements of the organization. She presents a model of SMART practice, which combines HRD theory, research, and practice with business savvy and mind-set to help scholar-practitioners manage the competing priorities of human development and organizational performance in the context of HRD processes and interventions. This article also serves as the capstone of the issue for it illustrates how the tensions between scholarly-practices on the one hand and business demands on the other surfaced and were addressed in the context of each of the cases in this issue.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1523422313487307">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>HRD scholarly practice may reflect a renewed interest in the professionalization of HRD and as such, it has the potential to advance HRD theory, education, and practice. In addition, HRD scholarly practice has implications for individual HRD scholar, practitioners, and scholar-practitioners.</p>
<sec id="section9-1523422313487307">
<title>Professionalization of HRD</title>
<p>In this volume, individual scholar-practitioners have come together in a collective effort to name their practice and express their identities as members of a growing profession. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1523422313487307">Abbott (1991)</xref> might call this endeavor an event in the developmental pathway of a profession in which individuals, who engage in common work join in affiliation with others to name, describe, and take ownership over their collective knowledge and practice. In other words, this issue—and the communal effort that has gone into its development—may make a small contribution to the professionalization of the HRD profession.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1523422313487307">
<title>Potential for Advancing HRD Theory and Education</title>
<p>By exploring scholarly practice and the use of theory in practice from the perspective and experience of the practitioner, we argue that HRD theory can be made more relevant and more focused on solving important and intractable problems. Further, we hope to contribute new understandings of how HRD theory can inform the bounded and often pressurized constraints of practice. New ways of understanding our roles and our practice may emerge from the real-time interaction of theory and practice, and these new insights may cause the need to consider new ways of educating and supporting the professional development of individual HRD scholar-practitioners today.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1523422313487307">
<title>Potential for Advancing the Practice of HRD</title>
<p>The authors in this issue offer a wide range of case-based examples of HRD scholarly practice including emphasizing specific interventions where research and/or theory has been used to inform practice. The varied examples presented illustrate that, although there is little consensus of what scholarly practice is, it exists and we can continue to learn from each other as we seek to adopt it and use it in the context of our daily work. In addition, the critical thinking section has potential to serve as a developmental tool to assist practitioners in thinking critically about the incorporation of theory in practice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1523422313487307">
<title>Implications for HRD Scholar-Practitioners</title>
<p>If we are right, and this volume is an expression of HRD scholar-practitioner professionalization, then it can also be seen as a collective attempt by the individual contributors to describe, perform, and adopt a shared professional identity. A shared professional identity implies, among other things, an acceptance of a common set of values, norms, and habits that define who and what we do, and perhaps more importantly, to what end and in whose interest we perform our practice. The cases presented in this issue will illustrate HRD scholarly practice from the point of the view of the practitioner who has claimed the identity as such.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Author Note:</label>
<p>This article was subjected to a two-tier, blind review process that did not involve any of the contributing authors who are currently members of the editorial board.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Dr. Ellen Scully-Russ</bold> is assistant professor of Human and Organizational Learning at the Graduate School of Education and Human Development, The George Washington University. Her scholarship and practice are focused on the role of Adult Education in meeting the individual and the political-economic challenges of the emerging knowledge society. She has been an active member of AHRD and the AHRD Scholarly-Practice SIG since 2009. She has published in the <italic>HRD Review</italic> and <italic>Human Resource Development International</italic> as well as other HRD related journals. She was awarded the Monica Lee Research Excellence Award in 2013 and the AHRD Cutting Edge Award in 2010.</p>
<p><bold>Dr. Rachelle Lehner</bold> is assistant dean for Staff Development at Emory University School of Medicine in Atlanta, Georgia. She has published and presented on appreciative inquiry as a method of improving work environments and has presented on the importance of communication in organizational change, as well as the role of Scholar-Practitioners in HRD. A recipient of the 2005-2006 Malcolm S. Knowles Dissertation Award, she is a member of the AHRD Malcolm S. Knowles Dissertation of the Year selection committee charged with annually reviewing and selecting exceptional dissertations to receive this prestigious award. She also serves on the AHRD scholar-practitioner SIG which studies and facilitates ways to bridge the gap between scholars and practitioners of organization development.</p>
<p><bold>Dr. Brad Shuck</bold> is assistant professor of Organizational Leadership and Learning at the University of Louisville. His research agenda is focused on the use of employee engagement and positive psychology in HRD, workplace culture and climate, nontraditional methods of instructional design, and leadership development. He was the 2011 <italic>Malcolm Knowles Dissertation of the Year</italic> Runner-Up and the Advances Editorial Team named the Advances Issue he coedited entitled <italic>Employee Engagement &amp; HRD: Linking Theory and Scholarship to Practice</italic> as Issue of the Year. His research has appeared in publications such as <italic>Human Resource Development Review, Human Resource Development International</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Management Development, Advances in Developing Human Resources</italic>, and the <italic>Journal of European Industrial Training</italic>, among others.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The order of professionalism: An empirical analysis</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonss</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The theory of reflexive modernization: Problematic, hypothesis and research program</article-title>. <source>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Engeström</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The future of activity theory: A rough draft</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the ISCAR Conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>San Diego, CA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kormanik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lehner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winnick</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>General competencies for the HRD scholar-practitioner: Perspectives from across the profession</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>486</fpage>-<lpage>506</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuchinke</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Theorizing and practicing HRD: Extending the dialogue over the roles of scholarship and practice in the field</article-title>. <source>Human Resource Development International</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>-<lpage>539</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynham</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>There's nothing quite as practical as good research</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moats</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Speaking our language: The essential role of scholar-practitioners in HRD</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>507</fpage>-<lpage>522</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rittlel</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Dilemmas in a general theory of planning</article-title>. <source>Policy Studies</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ruona</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilley</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Practitioners in applied professions: A model applied to human resource development</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keefer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The link between research and practice: Experience of HRD and other professions</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>420</fpage>-<lpage>427</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kormanik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruona</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Linking research and practice in human resource development</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Moving beyond scholar-practitioner binaries: Exploring the liminal possiblities and borderlands</article-title>. <source>Advances in Developing Human Resources</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>523</fpage>-<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1523422313487307">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Case study research: Design and methods</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>