<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppic</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part C: Journal of Mechanical Engineering Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4062</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2983</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954406212444509</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954406212444509</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Dynamics and Control</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A study of the secondary piston motion arising from changes in the piston skirt profile using a simplified piston skirt model</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954406212444509"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954406212444509">Department of Engineering Science, Oxford University, Oxford, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954406212444509">PD McFadden, Department of Engineering Science, University of Oxford, Parks Road, Oxford, OX1 3PJ, UK. Email: <email>peter.mcfadden@jesus.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>38</fpage>
<lpage>47</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>An existing model of the interface between a parallel-sided piston skirt and the cylinder wall in an internal combustion engine is extended to allow the modelling of barrelling of the piston skirt. The effects of the skirt profile on the secondary motion of the piston and on the distribution of pressure in the lubricant film are examined. It is shown that piston secondary motion, and in particular rotation of the piston about the gudgeon pin, which might contribute to wear of the cylinder, can be reduced by appropriate positioning of the maximum diameter of the piston skirt in relation to the gudgeon pin and the centre of mass of the piston.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Internal combustion engine</kwd>
<kwd>dynamic analysis</kwd>
<kwd>lubrication</kwd>
<kwd>piston motion</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954406212444509" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The effects of barrelling of the piston on piston skirt loads and friction losses in an internal combustion engine have been investigated by Wong et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212444509">1</xref> and by Mansouri and Wong,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954406212444509">2</xref> but both used models which assumed an exactly constant crankshaft speed, and were therefore unable to explore what effect short-term variations in crankshaft speed during the engine cycle might have on the secondary motion of the piston.</p>
<p>Briaris<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212444509">3</xref> developed an engine model which differed from previously published work in that it was a fully dynamic model, where the crank speed was not assumed constant, but was determined by the gas pressure applied to the piston crown, the inertias and stiffnesses of the engine components and the magnitude of the brake load applied to the output shaft. A schematic view of the single-cylinder version of the model developed by Briaris and later reported by McFadden and Turnbull<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954406212444509">4</xref> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212444509">Figure 1</xref>. For a nominal crankshaft speed of 4000 r/min, it was found that the instantaneous crankshaft speed during the engine cycle varied between 3997 and 4009 r/min, confirming the importance of this approach. Briaris included a detailed and comprehensive model of the piston skirt and showed that it was possible for the piston to travel the full length of the bore without making contact with the walls of the cylinder. This was achieved when the gap between the piston skirt and the bore was both fully and partially filled with oil. It was also shown that barrelling of the piston skirt allowed the piston to undergo more secondary motion, although a gap between the piston skirt and the bore was still maintained.
<fig id="fig1-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic of crank and slider geometry: (a) side elevation and (b) front elevation in direction A.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Following the work of Briaris,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212444509">3</xref> McFadden and Turnbull<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212444509">5</xref> showed that changes in the way the journal bearings in the engine were modelled had little effect on the magnitude of the loads being carried by the journal bearings, but that changes in the way the piston skirt was modelled did have significant effects both on the secondary motion of the piston and on the magnitude of the loads being carried by the skirt. In contrast to the earlier works of Wong et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212444509">1</xref> and Mansouri and Wong,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954406212444509">2</xref> which were based on the surprising premise that the piston skirt underwent significant elastic deformation while the oil film played no part, the model used by McFadden and Turnbull<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212444509">5</xref> assumed a rigid piston, the motion of which was entirely controlled by the squeeze film forces in the lubricant between the piston skirt and the cylinder wall. The model of the piston skirt/cylinder wall interface used was very simple compared to that developed by Briaris, but it did predict values of interface pressures and secondary movement that came very close to those predicted by the much more complicated model. The success of the simple model, therefore, justified this article, in which the simple, parallel-sided piston skirt model is modified to include barrelling, and used to predict the effects of changing the barrel's parameters on the secondary motion of the piston.</p>
<p>For a full review of the relevant literature and for details of the model, the reader is referred to McFadden and Turnbull<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954406212444509">4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212444509">5</xref> respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954406212444509"><title>The model</title>
<sec id="sec3-0954406212444509"><title>General description</title>
<p>The mathematical model is as described by McFadden and Turnbull<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212444509">5</xref> and it comprises one cylinder of a multi-cylinder engine model. The bore and stroke are 80 mm, and all the elements of the engine are assumed to be rigid, with the mass and inertia concentrated at the centre of mass of each of the elements. All the journal bearings are assumed to carry the load hydrodynamically, along with the piston skirt. The hydrodynamic model is a simple one in that only the squeeze film term is retained, because Cameron<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954406212444509">6</xref> has stated that in internal combustion engines the hydrodynamic term can be ignored. The gas load on the piston has a peak pressure of 2.7 MPa, the brake load 21.3 N m and the nominal speed of the crankshaft 4000 r/min. The physical dimensions of the model are taken from an existing 1.6 L petrol engine. The equations of motion are solved using the Kutta–Merson method, the advantage of which is its ability to maintain a specified accuracy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954406212444509"><title>The barrelled piston</title>
<p>The piston skirt is divided into 32 identical ‘pads’, each occupying an angle of ±45° either side of the centre, and capable of carrying a load due to elastic contact with the wall of the cylinder and by a squeeze film pressure generated by the relative sideways velocity of the piston and the bore. In order to investigate the effect of barrelling of the piston skirt, a profiling function has been produced which modifies the shape of the piston skirt. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212444509">Figure 2</xref>, the three parameters which control the barrelling are RT and RB, the amount the piston radius has been reduced at the top and bottom of the skirt, respectively, (both set to 30 µm unless otherwise stated) and <italic>L</italic>/<italic>D</italic>, which is the point on the piston skirt where no reduction has been made, and hence where the maximum diameter occurs.
<fig id="fig2-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Definition of barrelling terms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>A simple polynomial of the form <italic>y</italic> = <italic>a</italic> + <italic>bx</italic> + <italic>cx</italic><sup>2</sup> has been used to shape the skirt, and when applying the boundary conditions, the following equations were evaluated
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0954406212444509"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0954406212444509"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>▵</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>{</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RT</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RB</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo/></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0954406212444509" xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212444509">Figure 3</xref> shows the way the profile can be changed by varying <italic>L</italic>/<italic>D</italic> and/or varying RB. The barrel profiles that will be investigated are <italic>D</italic> = 2, <italic>D</italic> = 4 and <italic>D</italic> = 4/3, which have their maximum diameter near the centre, top and bottom of the skirt, respectively. A fourth profile having no barrelling (i.e. with parallel sides) will be used as the basic shape with which the others can be compared.
<fig id="fig3-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Reduction of piston nominal radius for different skirt profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Real pistons may have more complex profiles, derived from experience and theory, and such profiles could be readily incorporated in the model using different functions to describe the variations in radius. The profiles used here are assumed to include the effects of thermal expansion.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954406212444509" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>To enable direct comparisons with the work of Briaris,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212444509">3</xref> the parameters of the model used to generate the following results are the same as those used by Briaris, including the subroutine which calculates the gas pressure above the piston crown, as described in McFadden and Turnbull.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212444509">5</xref> The piston height is 70 mm, with the centre of mass located 40 mm from the top and the gudgeon pin 45 mm from the top. There is no gudgeon pin offset. The initial radial clearance between the piston skirt and the cylinder wall was 20 µm, and barrelling increased this to 50 µm both at the top and bottom of the piston skirt.</p>
<sec id="sec6-0954406212444509"><title>Piston motion</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref> shows the effect of moving the point of maximum diameter of the piston skirt on the lateral translation of the centre of mass of the piston. It is seen that the parallel-sided piston has the least lateral translation of the centre of mass (i.e. displacement in the <italic>x</italic>-direction as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212444509">Figure 1(b)</xref>), whereas moving the maximum diameter close to the top of the piston skirt (i.e. <italic>D</italic> = 4) produces the greatest amount of translation. Conversely, moving the maximum diameter close to the bottom of the piston skirt (i.e. <italic>D</italic> = 4/3) produces a translation of the piston which is nearer to that produced by the parallel skirt. Wong et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212444509">1</xref> suggested that this latter piston shape is the one most favoured by engine manufacturers.
<fig id="fig4-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Lateral translation of centre of mass of piston for different skirt profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> shows the rotation of the piston about its centre of mass. It can be clearly seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">5</xref> that positioning the maximum diameter near to the bottom of the skirt appears to be the most advantageous, as it allows the piston to be barrelled with the minimum increase in both translation and rotation of the piston. Recalling that the gudgeon pin is located at 45 mm from the top of the piston, below the mid-height, it becomes clear that a barrelled piston with maximum diameter at mid-height (<italic>D</italic> = 2) or above (e.g. <italic>D</italic> = 4) will experience larger rotations because the increased vertical separation of the gudgeon pin and the maximum diameter will produce greater moments for a given horizontal component of the thrust of the connecting rod. Locating the maximum diameter close to the gudgeon pin (e.g. <italic>D</italic> = 4/3 for the engine configuration described here) will minimise the rotation of the piston, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref>.
<fig id="fig5-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Rotation of piston about its centre of mass for different skirt profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Briaris<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212444509">3</xref> investigated a piston with the same amount of barrelling as was used to generate <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">5</xref> (i.e. RT = RB = 30 µm) and with the maximum diameter in the centre of the piston skirt (i.e. <italic>D</italic> = 2). The movements of the piston predicted were very close to those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">5</xref>.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406212444509">Figure 6</xref> shows the rotation of the piston about its centre of mass for <italic>D</italic> = 4/3 with different amounts of piston radius reduction at the bottom of the piston, the original reduction being 30 µm. It can be clearly seen that reducing the amount of radius reduction near to the bottom of the skirt appears to be advantageous in that it reduces the amount of rotation of the piston without any significant change in the translation of the piston.
<fig id="fig6-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Rotation of piston about its centre of mass for different values of RB.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954406212444509"><title>Losses due to friction</title>
<p>As the model predicted no contact between the piston skirt and the cylinder wall, it was felt that an investigation of the losses due to viscous friction and the resistance from the piston rings would be worthwhile. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406212444509">Figure 7</xref> shows these friction forces, which are mainly due to viscous friction, the effect of the piston ring friction only being obvious in the small step change in force at the top and bottom dead centre where the direction of travel of the piston reverses, as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406212444509">Figure 7</xref> for 360°. It is interesting to note that the reduction in friction loss does not appear to depend on the shape of the barrelling, but depends mainly on the actual amount of material removed from the piston diameter.
<fig id="fig7-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Friction force between piston skirt and cylinder wall for different skirt profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0954406212444509"><title>Pressure distribution – parallel-sided piston</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> shows the distribution of pressure, for a complete engine cycle, for the parallel-sided piston. The contours on the right-hand side of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> show the pressures on the right-hand side (i.e. the thrust side) of the piston as viewed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212444509">Figure 1(b)</xref>, and similarly those on the left-hand side are for the left-hand side of the piston. Contour lines are drawn at intervals of 0.05 MPa for this and all subsequent plots.
<fig id="fig8-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Piston pad pressures for parallel-sided piston.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> shows that the maximum pressure of 0.51 MPa occurs at a crank angle of 585°, which is close to the maximum pressure predicted by Briaris, although in his case the pressure was not constant around the circumference of the piston, while here it is assumed constant for ±45° either side of the centre. However, the method of calculating the pressure in the oil between the two surfaces used here has the advantage of simplicity, and because of this, the pressure profile of the lubricating oil for a complete engine cycle can easily be calculated and the recorded results are not limited to a particular crank angle. It is worth noting that a similar calculation has been made for the four-cylinder model developed by McFadden and Turnbull,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212444509">5</xref> and although the distribution of pressure is the same as the single-cylinder model, the maximum pressure was 0.36 MPa.</p>
<p>The small peaks observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> near the top of the piston can be solely explained in terms of the angular velocity of the piston rotation about the gudgeon pin as deduced from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref>. At approximately 45°, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> shows the angular velocity of the piston has a large negative value, corresponding to a clockwise rotation in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212444509">Figure 1(b)</xref>, causing the top-right corner of the piston to move towards the right-hand side of the cylinder, thus producing a small pressure peak in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> at the top of the piston for this angle. At approximately 220°, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> shows that the angular velocity has a maximum negative value, giving rise to a similar but larger pressure peak in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> at the corresponding angle. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> also shows that the angular velocity of the piston has large positive values, corresponding to an anticlockwise rotation in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212444509">Figure 1(b)</xref>, at approximately 480° and 560°, moving the top-left corner of the piston towards the left-hand side of the cylinder and so producing the small peaks at the top of the piston at these angles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>. It is interesting to note that it is the angular velocity of the piston rotation deduced from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref>, not the translation shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref>, which determines the pressure peaks at the top of the piston, because the lateral velocities at the top of the piston due to rotation exceed the lateral velocities of the gudgeon pin due to translation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954406212444509"><title>Forces acting on the piston</title>
<p>The major peaks in the pressure distribution represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> further down the side of the piston can be qualitatively explained in terms of the ‘inertia force’ acting on the piston, equal to the mass of the piston multiplied by its acceleration but acting in the opposite sense to the acceleration, the gas pressure on the piston crown, the force in the connecting rod and the sideways force between the piston skirt and the cylinder. At this part of the cycle, the inertia effects of the connecting rod can be ignored because its linear and angular accelerations are relatively small. Viscous friction forces can also be ignored, given the small magnitudes shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406212444509">Figure 7</xref>. In the following explanation and in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9</xref>, it will be assumed for simplicity that the piston reaches its maximum velocity when the crank is horizontal, at angles 90°, 270°, 450° and 630°. In fact, for the crank and connecting rod lengths modelled here, the maximum piston velocity occurs when the crank is approximately 12° above the horizontal, at 102°, 258°, 462° and 618°.
<fig id="fig9-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Forces acting on the piston throughout the cycle. <italic>G</italic>: gas, <italic>I</italic>: inertia, <italic>C</italic>: connecting rod and <italic>N</italic>: normal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>At a crank angle of 0°, the beginning of the exhaust stroke, the piston is at bottom dead centre and has maximum upwards acceleration, corresponding to a maximum downwards inertia force <italic>I</italic>, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(a)</xref>. The gas force is negligible because the cylinder pressure is only a little above ambient. As a result, the force <italic>C</italic> in the connecting rod acts vertically upwards, but there is no lateral force between the piston and the cylinder wall. At a crank angle of 45°, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(b)</xref>, the gas force remains negligible and the piston acceleration is smaller so the inertia force has decreased, thus the vertical component of the force in the connecting rod has decreased. However, the connecting rod is now at an angle, and the horizontal component of its thrust on the piston must be countered by a normal thrust force <italic>N</italic> between the piston and the left-hand side of the cylinder wall, producing the pressure peak seen in the left-hand contours of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> between 0° and 90°. At a crank angle of 90° (actually 102°, as previously explained), the piston has maximum upwards velocity but its acceleration is zero, and the gas force remains small, so the force in the connecting rod is small as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(c)</xref>, and there is no significant sideways thrust on the cylinder wall, giving zero pressure on the piston pads, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>. For a crank angle of 135°, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(d)</xref>, the piston is being decelerated, resulting in a tension in the connecting rod which is reacted by a horizontal thrust on the piston from the right-hand cylinder wall, producing the pressure peak seen on the right-hand side of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>. Note that in the top half of the stroke, the piston accelerations and hence the inertia forces are larger than in the lower half of the stroke, due to the geometry of the crank and connecting rod. At a crank angle of 180°, the piston is at top dead centre, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(e)</xref>, and the sideways force is zero at bottom dead centre.</p>
<p>During the intake stroke, when the crank angle is 225°, the piston is accelerating downwards, but the cylinder pressure has fallen below ambient, producing an upwards gas force <italic>G</italic> on the piston which causes an increased tension in the connecting rod, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(f)</xref>, and thus a greater sideways thrust than at 45°, as indicated by the increased number of contour lines on the left-hand side in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>. At a crank angle of 270° (actually 258°, as previously explained), the piston has maximum downwards velocity but its acceleration is zero. However, the upwards gas force <italic>G</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(g)</xref> produces a small sideways thrust on the left-hand side of the cylinder. This is confirmed by the left-hand contours of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref> at 270°. Recall that there is no such sideways thrust at 90°. At 315°, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(h)</xref> shows the upwards gas force on the piston countering the downwards inertia force as the piston decelerates, producing a small resultant compressive force in the connecting rod and hence no significant sideways thrust, as observed for the lower pads in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>. At 360° in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(i)</xref>, the sideways thrust is zero, as explained for 0°, the beginning of the exhaust stroke.</p>
<p>At a crank angle of 405°, during the first part of the compression stroke, the cylinder pressure is still below ambient according to the trace used by Briaris<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212444509">3</xref> and McFadden and Turnbull,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954406212444509">4</xref> so the gas force on the piston is in the upward direction as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(j)</xref>, reducing the compressive force in the connecting rod and hence producing a resultant peak pressure on the left-hand side of the cylinder in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>, which is less than that for 45°, the corresponding position in the exhaust stroke. At 450°, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(k)</xref>, the gas pressure has increased to approximately ambient and the piston has zero acceleration, thus there is no sideways thrust. In the second half of the compression stroke, the gas pressure continues to rise, producing a downwards force on the piston, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(l)</xref>, which helps to decelerate the piston, thus reducing the force in the connecting rod and keeping the thrust on the right-hand side of the cylinder lower than at 135°, the corresponding position in the exhaust stroke.</p>
<p>At 540°, the piston is at top dead centre and there is no sideways thrust, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(m)</xref>. During the first part of the expansion stroke, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(n)</xref>, the large downwards gas force easily exceeds the upwards inertia force causing a thrust on the right-hand side of the cylinder, producing the peak pressure seen on the right-hand side of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figure 8</xref>. At 630°, the inertia force is zero, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(o)</xref>, and the remaining gas pressure continues to hold the piston against the right-hand side of the cylinder, a behaviour which is not seen elsewhere in the cycle. At 675°, in the second half of the expansion stroke, the gas force decreases but the increasing inertia forces holds the piston against the right-hand side, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(p)</xref>.</p>
<p>Armed with the understanding of the forces acting on the piston afforded by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9</xref>, the lateral translation and rotation of the piston shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figures 4</xref> to 6 can be examined further. It is important to note here that it is not the lateral acceleration of the piston that is related to the normal force, but the lateral velocity, because the pressure in the lubricant film is proportional to the rate of change of the thickness of the film. Thus, it is clear that the normal force is responsible for the ripples on the traces in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref>, because the gradient of the trace, representing the velocity of translation, closely matches the magnitude and direction of the normal force in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9</xref>. At 0°, 180°, 360°, 540° and 720°, when the piston is at top or bottom dead centre and the inertia force is entirely reacted by the connecting rod with no normal force between the piston and the cylinder, the lateral velocity of the piston shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref> is zero. At 45°, 135°, 225°, 315°, 405° and 495°, where the horizontal component of the force in the connecting rod produces a large normal force, the magnitude of the lateral velocity of the piston in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref> reaches a local maximum. Indeed, the largest negative velocity occurs near 225°, where <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(f)</xref> shows the inertia force and gas force combine to produce a large normal force on the left-hand side of the piston, and the largest positive velocity occurs a little before 585°, where <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(n)</xref> suggests the very large gas force will overcome the inertia force to give a large normal force on the right-hand side of the piston. If further confirmation of the validity of this approach were required, close examination of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref> shows that there is a small negative velocity at 270°, arising from the small normal force on the left-hand side of the piston caused by the small upwards gas force during induction.</p>
<p>The rotation of the piston shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> closely follows the lateral translation shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref>, because the moment on the piston about its centre of mass is dependent on the couple produced by the normal force and the horizontal component of the force in the connecting rod. Again, it is not the angular acceleration of the piston that is related to the normal force, but the angular velocity, because the pressure in the lubricant film is determined by the rate of change of thickness of the film. Reducing the diameter of the bottom of the piston skirt, as explored in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406212444509">Figure 6</xref>, reduces the pressure in the lubricant film in the lower part of the skirt, thus raising the line of action of the normal force further above the gudgeon pin and increasing the moment on the piston, and hence its angular velocity.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref> shows that barrelling of the piston skirt increases the amount of lateral translation. This will occur because the squeeze film pressure is inversely proportional to the third power of the film thickness, and barrelling therefore decreases the effective film damping coefficient, so that greater lateral velocities must be achieved before the required normal force is produced. For the engine configuration modelled here, with the gudgeon pin below the mid-height of the piston, rotation of the piston also becomes important. For example, with <italic>D</italic> = 4, the maximum diameter of the piston occurs near the top, so the resultant normal force will be above the mid-height, giving rise to a larger moment on the piston and therefore greater angular velocity of the piston. Thus, at 45°, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9(b)</xref> shows the connecting rod pushing the piston towards the left-hand side of the cylinder, as confirmed by the negative slope of the trace in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figure 4</xref> at 45°, and because the gudgeon pin is below the maximum diameter of the piston for <italic>D</italic> = 4, there will be a negative, or clockwise, moment applied to the piston, resulting in the negative angular velocity shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> at this angle. However, if the maximum diameter of the piston occurs lower, and hence nearer to the gudgeon pin, the moment produced will be smaller, and so therefore will be the translation and rotation, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212444509">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">5</xref> for <italic>D</italic> = 4/3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0954406212444509"><title>Pressure distribution – barrelled piston</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406212444509">Figure 10</xref> shows the distribution of pressure for the case when <italic>D</italic> = 2, when piston has been barrelled by an amount of 30 µm at the top and bottom of the piston, with the maximum diameter being equidistant from the top and bottom of the piston. It can be seen that, although the basic distribution of the pressure peaks is similar, the main peaks have moved up the piston near to but still a little below the mid-height where the diameter is greatest, and the magnitudes have significantly increased, reaching 0.87 MPa during the expansion stroke. The distribution and magnitude of pressure compare well with those predicted by Briaris.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212444509">3</xref> Note that the small pressure peaks near to the top of the piston generated by the piston rotation have decreased, even though <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref> indicates that the angular velocities of the piston have significantly increased.
<fig id="fig10-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Piston pad pressures for barrel piston, <italic>D</italic> = 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig10.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406212444509">Figure 11</xref> shows the distribution of pressure for the case where <italic>D</italic> = 4, for which the maximum diameter is close to the top of the piston skirt, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212444509">Figure 3</xref>. Although there is a general similarity between <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figures 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406212444509">11</xref>, the peak pressures have increased, reaching a maximum of 0.74 MPa during the expansion stroke, and have moved up the piston skirt, to approximately mid-height or a little above, but not as far as the position of the maximum diameter. Pressures generated near the top of the piston are higher than those for the parallel-sided piston throughout the entire cycle, because of the increased piston angular velocities evident in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref>.
<fig id="fig11-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Piston pad pressures for barrel piston, <italic>D</italic> = 4.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig11.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954406212444509">Figure 12</xref> shows the distribution of pressure for the case where <italic>D</italic> = 4/3, for which the maximum diameter is close to the bottom of the piston skirt, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212444509">Figure 3</xref>. Although there is a similarity between <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212444509">Figures 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954406212444509">12</xref>, the pressure is now concentrated near or just a little above the maximum diameter, with no peaks occurring near the top of the piston, due to the much smaller angular velocities indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212444509">Figure 5</xref>. The peak pressure is 0.71 MPa, during the expansion stroke.
<fig id="fig12-0954406212444509" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Piston pad pressures for barrel piston, <italic>D</italic> = 4/3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212444509-fig12.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0954406212444509" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>The results presented here demonstrate amply the capabilities of the simple piston skirt/cylinder wall model, which is able to produce estimates of the piston rotation and lateral translation, and the distribution of pressure in the lubricant film, throughout the entire engine cycle for any desired skirt profile. While the simplified model cannot deliver the same accuracy as a comprehensive finite element model, it can be used as a tool to explore qualitatively the likely effects of changes to clearances, skirt profile, position of gudgeon pin, position of centre of mass of the piston, piston mass and moment of inertia, connecting rod mass and moment of inertia, combustion pressure profile and engine speed, which if necessary can be refined later using more sophisticated but much slower models, or by experimental measurement.</p>
<p>Using the model, it has been shown that the piston skirt profile significantly affects the lateral translation of the piston and the rotation of the piston about the gudgeon pin. Positioning the maximum piston diameter at a similar height to the gudgeon pin and centre of mass of the piston tends to reduce the moment about the gudgeon pin produced by the normal force between the piston and the cylinder wall, which in turn reduces the rotation of the piston and thus the development of pressure peaks at the top of the piston skirt, as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954406212444509">Figure 12</xref>. A large vertical separation between the maximum piston diameter and the gudgeon pin produces larger rotations of the piston, giving rise to unwanted pressure peaks near the top of the piston, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406212444509">Figure 11</xref>. Different combinations of the positions of the maximum piston diameter, gudgeon pin and centre of mass of the piston could be easily explored using the model.</p>
<p>The simple model has also enabled a qualitative explanation to be proposed for the calculated variations in pressure distribution throughout the cycle, entirely in terms of the gas, inertia and normal forces acting on the piston, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212444509">Figure 9</xref>. The effects of lubricant friction and connecting rod dynamics are secondary. It is interesting to note that the gas force appears to play a noticeable role during the induction stroke, when the pressure is below ambient, even extending into the start of the compression stroke until the pressure finally rises above ambient. During the later stages of compression and the expansion stroke, the high gas pressure dominates, holding the piston against the thrust side of the cylinder. However, at part-throttle settings, when the induction pressure falls well below ambient and the combustion pressure is only small, the changed gas forces may significantly affect the pressure distribution in the lubricant. At low speeds, the gas forces will tend to dominate over the inertia forces, but at high speeds, the inertia forces will dominate, except perhaps during the expansion stroke. The influence of different gas pressure profiles and engine speeds could all be easily and quickly explored using the simplified model presented here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0954406212444509" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>An existing model of the interface between a parallel-sided piston skirt and the cylinder wall in an internal combustion engine has been extended to allow the modelling of barrelling of the piston skirt. The effects of the skirt profile on the piston secondary motion, that is, the lateral translation and rotation of the piston about its centre of mass, and on the distribution of pressure in the lubricant film, have been examined. It has been shown that the piston secondary motion, and in particular the rotation of the piston, which causes the top of the piston to move towards the cylinder wall and thus might contribute to wear of the cylinder, can be reduced by appropriate positioning of the maximum diameter of the piston skirt in relation to the gudgeon pin and the centre of mass of the piston. A qualitative explanation has been provided for the distribution of pressure in the lubricant between the piston skirt and the cylinder wall throughout the complete engine cycle, in terms of the gas, inertia and normal reaction forces acting on the piston. The simplicity of the model ensures that computation times are small, thus making the model suitable for the examination of the effects on the piston motion and lubrication of a wide range of operating conditions.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec13-0954406212444509"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954406212444509"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>A numerical model of piston secondary motion and piston slap in partially flooded elastohydrodynamic skirt lubrication</source>. <publisher-name>SAE paper 940606</publisher-name>, <year>1994</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954406212444509"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of piston design parameters on piston secondary motion and skirt-liner friction</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part J: J Engineering Tribology</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>219</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954406212444509"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briaris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic analysis of piston secondary motion in a single-cylinder engine and a four-cylinder engine operating under non-lubricated and lubricated conditions</article-title>. <source>DPhil Thesis</source>. <publisher-name>University of Oxford</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954406212444509"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic analysis of piston secondary motion in an internal combustion engine under non-lubricated and fully flooded lubricated conditions</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part C: J Mechanical Engineering Science</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>225</volume>: <fpage>2575</fpage>–<lpage>2585</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954406212444509"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of methods of modelling the bearing surfaces in an internal combustion engine</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part C: J Mechanical Engineering Science</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>226</volume>: <fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>920</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954406212444509"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><comment><italic>Basic lubrication theory</italic>. London: Longman Group Ltd., 1970, p.113</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>