<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Preventive Cardiology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2047-4873</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2047-4881</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1741826711425340</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1741826711425340</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Myocardial infarction</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original scientific papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Incidence and case fatality after day 28 of first time myocardial infarction in Sweden 1987−2008</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711425340">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dzayee</surname><given-names>Dashti Ali M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711425340">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Beiki</surname><given-names>Omid</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711425340">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1741826711425340">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>de Faire</surname><given-names>Ulf</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711425340">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>Lars</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711425340">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Moradi</surname><given-names>Tahereh</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1741826711425340">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1741826711425340"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1741826711425340"><label>1</label>Institute of Environmental Medicine, Division of Epidemiology, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1741826711425340"><label>2</label>Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences, Kermanshah, Iran.</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1741826711425340">Tahereh Moradi, Institute of Environmental Medicine, Division of Epidemiology, Karolinska Institutet, Nobels väg 13, Box 210, SE-171 77 Stockholm, Sweden Email: <email>tahereh.moradi@ki.se</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1304</fpage>
<lpage>1315</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The European Society of Cardiology 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">European Society of Cardiology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Aims:</bold> We studied trends in first-time myocardial infarction (MI) incidence and case fatality after day 28 and to examine the role of sex, education as an indicator for socioeconomic position, and birth country on these events in Sweden.</p>
<p><bold>Methods and results:</bold> Nationwide cohort including 6,752,655 individuals aged 35–89 years living in Sweden between January 1987 and December 2008, of which, 6,464,968 individuals and 366,085 nonfatal first-time MI patients were classified according to their sex, birth country, and education and followed over two decades. Main outcome measures: Incidence and case-fatality rate after day 28 of first-time MI and their trends. A decreasing trend for first-time MI incidence and case fatality after day 28 for both sexes regardless of birth country was observed (<italic>p</italic>-trend&lt;0.0001). The trend was, however, less pronounced among female and foreign-born. Men had higher incidence than women (incidence rate ratio, IRR 2.09, 95% CI 2.08–2.11). Men born in Southern and Western Asia had 50% (95% CI 40−60%) higher risk than men born in Sweden. Incidence was 50–80% higher in the least educated irrespective of sex and birth country (<italic>p</italic>-trend&lt;0.0001). This association was stronger for female and foreign-born. We observed a 15% higher case fatality after day 28 among men than women (hazard ratio, HR 1.15, 95% CI 1.13–1.17) and 20−40% lower case fatality after day 28 among patients with no diabetes. Low education was associated with 50% higher case fatality after day 28 regardless of sex and birth country (<italic>p</italic>-trend &lt;0.0001).</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> Although incidence of, and fatality after, first-time MI continued to decrease, low socioeconomic position, independent of birth country and sex, remained an important risk indicator for both events.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Case fatality after day 28</kwd>
<kwd>country of birth</kwd>
<kwd>first-time myocardial infarction</kwd>
<kwd>incidence</kwd>
<kwd>socioeconomic position</kwd>
<kwd>Sweden</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1741826711425340" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Myocardial infarction (MI) is a major cause of mortality and disability worldwide. Despite the recent decline in mortality from coronary heart diseases (CHD) in high-income countries, CHD with MI is still anticipated to be the dominating causes of mortality in the world over the next decades.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711425340">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1741826711425340">2</xref></sup> In Sweden cardiovascular diseases are the dominating burden of diseases where MI contributes to most years of life lost.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1741826711425340">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>There is a wide variation in incidence of MI both between countries and within countries,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1741826711425340">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1741826711425340">4</xref></sup> and between socioeconomic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1741826711425340">5</xref></sup> and ethnic groups.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1741826711425340">6</xref></sup> Furthermore, high blood pressure, high cholesterol level, diabetes, and smoking have been identified as the major risk factors for MI. There is a continuous rise of migrations worldwide which requires a better understanding of their health consequences. In Sweden about 13% of the population was immigrants in 2008.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1741826711425340">7</xref></sup> An increase in mortality and morbidity from CHD among foreign-born in Sweden has been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1741826711425340">8</xref></sup> which is in line with the results reported from USA and UK.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1741826711425340">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1741826711425340">10</xref></sup> Most of these studies have small sample sizes and relatively short study periods. Furthermore, information on important confounding factors was scarce in these studies.</p>
<p>In the present nationwide cohort study, we evaluated both incidence of and case fatality after day 28 after first-time MI in the total population and in subgroups of different immigrant populations adjusting for confounding factors during a period of 22 years in Sweden. In addition, we quantified recent trends in these events and in these subgroups.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1741826711425340" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec3-1741826711425340"><title>Database</title>
<p>We used the newly established Migration and Health Cohort.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1741826711425340">11</xref></sup> This cohort was built by linkage between 15 Swedish national registers. The linkages have been completed by the Swedish 10-digit unique personal identity number which is maintained by the National Tax Board for all individuals that have resided in Sweden since 1947. The data used in this study is part of the Migration and Health Cohort and included: (1) The National Patient Register, including the inpatient register established in 1964 which contains information on hospitalized patients and on the whole country since 1987. Since 2001, this register contains information on outpatient visits to specialist care and day visits to hospitals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1741826711425340">12</xref></sup> where we also retrieved information on potential risk factors for MI such as diabetes, hyperlipidaemia, and hypertension assessed through their ICD codes. (2) The Cause of Death Register, which contains information on date of death and cause of death since 1958.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1741826711425340">12</xref></sup> (3) The Total Population Register which contains all Swedish residents, including demographic variables such as country of birth and data on emigration and immigration. (4) The Swedish Population and Housing Census and longitudinal integration database for health insurance and labour market studies which contains information on education level.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1741826711425340">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1741826711425340">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>The linkages have been completed by Statistics Sweden and National Board of Health and Welfare. The study was approved by the Regional Board of The Ethical Committee, Stockholm.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1741826711425340"><title>Study cohort</title>
<sec id="sec5-1741826711425340"><title>Incidence</title>
<p>The study base consisted of 3,426,243 men and 3,326,412 women, aged 35−89 years living in Sweden any time during 1 January 1987 and 31 December 2008. Individuals born outside of Sweden were referred to as the foreign-born and individuals born in Sweden were referred to as Sweden-born.</p>
<p>We excluded individuals who had a history of MI (193,690 men and 93,997 women). In Sweden all patients discharged from hospitals are registered in the Swedish Patient Register. Almost all patients with a diagnosed acute MI are hospitalized in public hospitals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1741826711425340">15</xref></sup> Individuals dying outside of hospitals due to acute MI are recorded in the Cause of Death Register.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1741826711425340">15</xref></sup> Thus, it is possible to identify high proportions of all MI cases by means of these two registers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1741826711425340">16</xref></sup> Cases of first events of MI in the study base were identified based on the combined information on main or co-diagnosis from the inpatient register or underlying or contributing cause of death in the cause of death register. We only included cases without recorded previous episodes of MI for at least 18 years back in time and considered the included cases as suffering a first-time MI. For those foreign-born individuals living in Sweden less than 18 years, their previous MI events were checked back in time only since their first immigration date available in the Total Population Register.</p>
<p>The final cohort included 3,232,553 men and 3,232,415 women of whom 999,867 were foreign-born (491,126 men and 508,741 women).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1741826711425340"><title>Case fatality after day 28</title>
<p>A total of 271,805 men and 180,708 women in the study base were identified as having experienced a first event of MI and hospitalized. We excluded in-hospital fatal MIs: i.e. individuals who died within 28 days since their first diagnosis of MI (47,307 men and 39,121 women). Case fatality after day 28 was then studied among the 224,498 male and 141,587 female non-fatal cases of whom 35,066 were foreign-born (21,431 men and 13,635 women).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1741826711425340"><title>Follow- up</title>
<sec id="sec8-1741826711425340"><title>Incidence</title>
<p>Individuals were followed from 1 January 1987, first immigration date for foreign-born or the first date at age 35 years old, whichever occurred last, until the date of diagnosis of an acute MI (ICD-9 code: 410 and ICD-10 code: I21), first emigration date, death, first date at age 90 years old, or end of follow-up (31 December 2008), whichever occurred first. Only cases with a diagnosis of first-time MI were counted as an event. Patients with recurrent MI during these 21 years of follow-up were not counted as having the events. We repeated analysis and included I22 to consider (a) discontinuity at the time when the ICD-10 was adopted and (b) probable miscoding of I22 as first-time MI. We found no differences in the results of these two analysis and thus, the results are presented only for the first analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1741826711425340"><title>Case fatality after day 28</title>
<p>The non-fatal incident cases of first-time MI were followed from the date of diagnosis until the date of death due to MI either as underlying or contributory cause, death due to other causes, first emigration date, first date at age 90 years, or end of follow-up (31 December 2008), whichever occurred first. We performed analysis in three different ways to consider discontinuity at the time when the ICD-10 was adopted. First, we studied death due to first-time MI as underlying or contributory diagnosis (ICD-9: code 410 and ICD-10: code I21), second, we studied death to ischaemic heart disease to consider out-of-hospital death (ICD-9: code 410–414 and ICD-10: code I20−I25), and finally we repeated analysis to study death due to any causes as an event.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1741826711425340"><title>Classification of country of birth</title>
<p>We classified foreign-born individuals by their country of birth into six macro geographical regions: Africa, Asia, Europe, Latin-America, Northern America, and Oceania and geographical subregions according to United Nations world classification. As for country level, we reported only countries having five or more cases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1741826711425340"><title>Classification of socioeconomic positions (SEP)</title>
<p>We used ‘achieved highest education’ as the proxy for SEP. We divided levels of education into four categories: 0–9 years, 10–12 years, more than 12 years, and unknown.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1741826711425340"><title>Explanatory variables</title>
<p>Age was divided into 11 groups with 5-year intervals (35–39, 40–44,… 80–84, and 85–89). In 2000, World Health Organization criteria for MI were refined to emphasize more the importance of cardiac biomarkers for diagnoses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1741826711425340">17</xref></sup> The adaptation of these new criteria might have had effects of the incidence of MIs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1741826711425340">18</xref></sup> We, therefore, divided the total study period into four time periods: 1987–1990, 1991–1995, 1996–2000, and 2001–2008. Additional covariates considered in analysis were comorbidity status including history of diabetes, hypertension, and hyperlipidaemia registered in in- or outpatient registers any time during the study period (yes/no).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1741826711425340"><title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>This was a retrospective observational cohort study. We calculated the incidence rate ratios (IRRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) using Poisson regression models. For mortality, we calculated the hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% CIs using Cox Proportional Hazards models. All analyses were conducted separately for men and women, and were adjusted for age, calendar year of follow-up, education, and any history of diabetes, hypertension, and hyperlipidaemia. We further calculated age-standardized rates between 1987 and 2008 stratified by sex, education, and migration status using the world population as standard. We reported age-standardized rates in unit of per 100,000 person-years. The Joint-point regression models were used to find the best-fit line for trends of first-time MI incidence rates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1741826711425340">19</xref></sup> The estimated annual percent change (APC) was used to describe and test the statistical significance of the trends. The null hypothesis in this analysis is that there is no change in the trend. Miss data on our exposures were classified as unknown. Assumptions of Poisson regression and Cox regression were met. We used SAS version 9.2 for all analyses. A <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.05 was considered as statistically significant and all tests were two-sided.</p>
<p>Since we were unable to trace previous MI history before migration to Sweden for foreign-born individuals to identify the true first-time MI cases, and also since the inpatient register became national first in 1987, we repeated the analysis and confined our cohort to individuals living in Sweden between 1995 and 2008 and started the follow-up from 1995 or first date of the 9th year of residence in Sweden (for immigrants), whichever occurred last allowing identification and exclusion of occurrence of any MI event at least during 8 years prior to the inclusion to the study cohort. The results yielded the similar results as the ones reported here and thus are not shown.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1741826711425340" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec15-1741826711425340"><title>Incidence</title>
<p>We observed total 571,476 cases of first-time MI (344,349 men, 227,127 women) during 101.51 million person-years of follow-up in whom 29,655 men and 20,080 women were foreign-born. Male cases were on average younger than females. Foreign-born individuals were younger at the age of diagnosis than Sweden-born (mean ± SD; men: foreign-born 64.51 ± 12.01, Sweden-born 70.77 ± 11.23; women: foreign-born 72.12 ± 10.58, Sweden-born 76.09 ± 9.83).</p>
<p>The incidence of first-time MI decreased with increasing level of education in both sexes (<italic>p</italic> for trend &lt;0.0001). Overall, the risk was higher among men and women with less than 9 years of education compared with those with more than 12 years of education. This association was, however, stronger among women (men: IRR 1.66, 95% CI 1.64−1.68; women: IRR 1.99, 95% CI 1.95−2.03) (results not shown). The stratified analysis by country of birth yielded the same results in both sexes and among both Sweden-born and foreign-born. The increased risk remained stronger among women but was more pronounced in Sweden-born than foreign-born (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1741826711425340">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1741826711425340">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table1-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Male incidence rate ratios for first-time myocardial infarction in Sweden, 1987–2008</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1741826711425340" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="3">Sweden-born<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Foreign-born<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>IRR (95% CI)</th>
<th>Cases</th>
<th>Person–years</th>
<th>IRR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Years of education</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 9</td>
<td>164,877</td>
<td>15,270,026</td>
<td>1.60 (1.58–1.62)</td>
<td>11,820</td>
<td>1,579,919</td>
<td>1.49 (1.44–1.54)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 9−12</td>
<td>85,221</td>
<td>16,970,986</td>
<td>1.36 (1.34–1.37)</td>
<td>10,557</td>
<td>2,198,635</td>
<td>1.29 (1.24–1.34)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> More than 12</td>
<td>29,824</td>
<td>9,388,229</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4163</td>
<td>1,380,218</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>34,772</td>
<td>1,223,863</td>
<td>1.41 (1.39–1.44)</td>
<td>3115</td>
<td>327,946</td>
<td>1.18 (1.12–1.24)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Age at diagnosis (years)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 35−39</td>
<td>1515</td>
<td>5,645,772</td>
<td>0.01 (0.01–0.01)</td>
<td>497</td>
<td>967,733</td>
<td>0.02 (0.02–0.02)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 40–44</td>
<td>4249</td>
<td>5,751,757</td>
<td>0.02 (0.02–0.02)</td>
<td>1136</td>
<td>922,596</td>
<td>0.04 (0.04–0.04)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–49</td>
<td>9165</td>
<td>5,595,323</td>
<td>0.04 (0.04–0.04)</td>
<td>2026</td>
<td>824,249</td>
<td>0.07 (0.07–0.08)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 50–54</td>
<td>16,162</td>
<td>5,243,247</td>
<td>0.08 (0.08–0.08)</td>
<td>2911</td>
<td>714,464</td>
<td>0.11 (0.11–0.12)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–59</td>
<td>23,776</td>
<td>4,768,251</td>
<td>0.12 (0.12–0.12)</td>
<td>3654</td>
<td>605,438</td>
<td>0.16 (0.15–0.17)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 60–64</td>
<td>32,016</td>
<td>4,166,921</td>
<td>0.18 (0.18–0.18)</td>
<td>4084</td>
<td>499,648</td>
<td>0.21 (0.20–0.23)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–69</td>
<td>41,312</td>
<td>3,599,421</td>
<td>0.26 (0.26–0.26)</td>
<td>4303</td>
<td>388,553</td>
<td>0.29 (0.27–0.31)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 70–74</td>
<td>50,839</td>
<td>3,118,956</td>
<td>0.38 (0.37–0.38)</td>
<td>4229</td>
<td>266,025</td>
<td>0.43 (0.40–0.46)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 75–79</td>
<td>56,434</td>
<td>2,507,535</td>
<td>0.54 (0.53–0.55)</td>
<td>3357</td>
<td>167,343</td>
<td>0.58 (0.54–0.62)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 80–84</td>
<td>49,451</td>
<td>1,660,754</td>
<td>0.75 (0.74–0.77)</td>
<td>2312</td>
<td>90,574</td>
<td>0.80 (0.75–0.86)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 85–89</td>
<td>29,775</td>
<td>795,168</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1146</td>
<td>40,096</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Comorbidities</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> No hypertension</td>
<td>226,708</td>
<td>35 769,838</td>
<td>0.98 (0.98–0.99)</td>
<td>20,019</td>
<td>4,697,163</td>
<td>0.90 (0.87–0.92)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Hypertension</td>
<td>87,986</td>
<td>7,083,266</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9636</td>
<td>789,556</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> No diabetes</td>
<td>249,072</td>
<td>38 992,391</td>
<td>0.64 (0.63–0.64)</td>
<td>22,317</td>
<td>4,970,923</td>
<td>0.60 (0.58–0.62)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td>65,622</td>
<td>3,860,714</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7338</td>
<td>515,796</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> No hyperlipidaemia</td>
<td>272,333</td>
<td>40 734,902</td>
<td>0.32 (0.32–0.32)</td>
<td>23,158</td>
<td>5,189,882</td>
<td>0.28 (0.27–0.28)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Hyperlipidaemia</td>
<td>42,361</td>
<td>2,118,203</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>6497</td>
<td>296,837</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Calendar years of follow-up</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1987–1990</td>
<td>66,416</td>
<td>7,612,242</td>
<td>1.40 (1.38–1.41)</td>
<td>4273</td>
<td>748,218</td>
<td>1.23 (1.19–1.28)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1991–1995</td>
<td>78,077</td>
<td>9,569,181</td>
<td>1.28 (1.26–1.29)</td>
<td>5963</td>
<td>1,093,640</td>
<td>1.11 (1.07–1.14)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1996–2000</td>
<td>67,674</td>
<td>9,671,106</td>
<td>1.08 (1.06–1.09)</td>
<td>6598</td>
<td>1,266,510</td>
<td>1.00 (0.97–1.03)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 2001–2008</td>
<td>102,527</td>
<td>16,000,576</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>12,821</td>
<td>2,378,350</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1741826711425340"><p>Incidence rate ratios (IRR) are mutually adjusted for education, age, comorbidities, and calendar years of follow-up when applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Female incidence rate ratios for first-time myocardial infarction in Sweden, 1987–2008</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1741826711425340" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="3">Sweden-born<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Foreign-born<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>IRR (95% CI)</th>
<th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>IRR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Years of education</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 9</td>
<td>116,295</td>
<td>16 546,983</td>
<td>1.85 (1.81–1.89)</td>
<td>9712</td>
<td>2,181,397</td>
<td>1.77 (1.67–1.87)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 9−12</td>
<td>39,267</td>
<td>17,549,208</td>
<td>1.47 (1.44–1.50)</td>
<td>4898</td>
<td>2,292,431</td>
<td>1.46 (1.37–1.55)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> More than 12</td>
<td>10,391</td>
<td>10 532,509</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1334</td>
<td>1,465,487</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>41,094</td>
<td>2,122,589</td>
<td>1.82 (1.77–1.86)</td>
<td>4136</td>
<td>474,956</td>
<td>1.62 (1.52–1.73)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Age at diagnosis (years)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 35−39</td>
<td>469</td>
<td>5,369,178</td>
<td>0.01 (0.00–0.01)</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>967,733</td>
<td>0.00 (0.00–0.01)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 40–44</td>
<td>1200</td>
<td>5,514,661</td>
<td>0.01 (0.01–0.01)</td>
<td>207</td>
<td>922,596</td>
<td>0.01 (0.01–0.01)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–49</td>
<td>2486</td>
<td>5,421,949</td>
<td>0.02 (0.02–0.02)</td>
<td>399</td>
<td>824,249</td>
<td>0.02 (0.02–0.03)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 50–54</td>
<td>4209</td>
<td>5,167,603</td>
<td>0.04 (0.04–0.04)</td>
<td>735</td>
<td>714,464</td>
<td>0.04 (0.04–0.05)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–59</td>
<td>6775</td>
<td>4,840,635</td>
<td>0.06 (0.06–0.06)</td>
<td>1111</td>
<td>605,438</td>
<td>0.07 (0.06–0.07)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 60–64</td>
<td>11,165</td>
<td>4,428,745</td>
<td>0.10 (0.10–0.11)</td>
<td>1922</td>
<td>499,648</td>
<td>0.12 (0.12–0.13)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–69</td>
<td>17,909</td>
<td>4,103,140</td>
<td>0.17 (0.16–0.17)</td>
<td>2833</td>
<td>388,553</td>
<td>0.20 (0.19–0.21)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 70–74</td>
<td>28,681</td>
<td>3,894,865</td>
<td>0.28 (0.27–0.28)</td>
<td>3480</td>
<td>266,025</td>
<td>0.31 (0.29–0.32)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 75–79</td>
<td>42,444</td>
<td>3,547,643</td>
<td>0.46 (0.45–0.47)</td>
<td>3682</td>
<td>167,343</td>
<td>0.46 (0.44–0.49)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 80–84</td>
<td>50,101</td>
<td>2,788,282</td>
<td>0.70 (0.69–0.70)</td>
<td>3439</td>
<td>90,574</td>
<td>0.74 (0.70–0.78)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 85–89</td>
<td>41,608</td>
<td>1,674,587</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2195</td>
<td>40,096</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Comorbidities</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> No hypertension</td>
<td>137,996</td>
<td>38 504,879</td>
<td>0.92 (0.91–0.93)</td>
<td>11,959</td>
<td>5,331,001</td>
<td>0.79 (0.77–0.82)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Hypertension</td>
<td>69,051</td>
<td>8,246,410</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>8121</td>
<td>1,083,270</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> No diabetes</td>
<td>158,805</td>
<td>43 295,327</td>
<td>0.49 (0.48–0.49)</td>
<td>14,467</td>
<td>5,904,084</td>
<td>0.47 (0.45–0.48)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td>48,242</td>
<td>3,455,961</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>5613</td>
<td>510,187</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> No hyperlipidaemia</td>
<td>187,360</td>
<td>45 182,085</td>
<td>0.32 (0.32–0.33)</td>
<td>16,816</td>
<td>6,150,754</td>
<td>0.33 (0.31–0.34)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Hyperlipidaemia</td>
<td>19,687</td>
<td>1,569,203</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3264</td>
<td>263,517</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Calendar years of follow-up</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1987–1990</td>
<td>40,446</td>
<td>8,404,643</td>
<td>1.13 (1.12–1.15)</td>
<td>2559</td>
<td>886,104</td>
<td>1.09 (1.04–1.14)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1991–1995</td>
<td>49,706</td>
<td>10,559,489</td>
<td>1.08 (1.07–1.10)</td>
<td>3847</td>
<td>1,287,160</td>
<td>1.04 (1.00–1.08)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1996–2000</td>
<td>45,073</td>
<td>10,597,024</td>
<td>0.97 (0.96–0.98)</td>
<td>4611</td>
<td>1,482,535</td>
<td>0.99 (0.95–1.02)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 2001–2008</td>
<td>71,822</td>
<td>17,190,132</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9063</td>
<td>2,758,472</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.01</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1741826711425340"><p>Incidence rate ratios (IRR) are mutually adjusted for education, age, comorbidities, and calendar years of follow-up when applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>As expected, the risk increased continuously with increasing age for both men and women but about 5 years earlier in men compared with women (results are not shown). Men noted twice as high adjusted IRR as women (IRR 2.09, 95% CI 2.08–2.11). We observed the same pattern when we stratified the analyses by country of birth (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1741826711425340">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1741826711425340">2</xref>).</p>
<p>History of hypertension, diabetes, and hyperlipidaemia were independently associated with increased risk of first-time MI among both men and women and regardless of the country of birth. However, the negative effects of histories of hypertension or diabetes were more pronounced among foreign-born than Sweden-born women and men (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1741826711425340">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1741826711425340">2</xref>).</p>
<p>Men had higher age-standardized rates than women over the whole study period. We observed a clear decreasing age-standardized rate over the study period for men but less obvious for women (please refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1741826711425340">Figure 3</xref>). When stratified by birth country, we observed a significant decreasing trend based on joint point regression analyses during the whole study period which was more pronounced among Sweden-born (men: APC −2.1, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 and women: APC −1.0, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) than foreign-born (men: APC −1.2, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 and women: APC −0.4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1741826711425340">Figure 1</xref>).
<fig id="fig1-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Age-standardized first-time myocardial infarction incidence rate by sex and immigration status, Sweden 1987−2008. ASR = Age-standardized first MI incidence rate per 100,000 person-years.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Around the year of 2001, we observed temporary increases in age-standardized rates for both men and women despite the overall decreasing trends when the World Health Organization criteria for MI were refined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1741826711425340">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1741826711425340">2</xref>) (joint point regression analysis results not shown).</p>
<p>The results based on stratified analysis by level of education indicated a decreasing trend for men in all educational levels. For women, however, there was no obvious decrease especially for those of fewer than 12 years of education (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1741826711425340">Figure 2</xref>). The absolute risk difference between the highest and lowest educational level was higher among men than women (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1741826711425340">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig id="fig2-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Age-standardized first-time myocardial infarction incidence rate by sex and education, Sweden 1987−2008. ASR = Age-standardized first MI incidence rate per 100,000 person-years.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig3-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Age-standardized first-time MI incidence rate by sex: Sweden 1987−2008. ASR = Age-standardized first MI incidence rate per 100,000 person-years.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-fig3.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p>At the country level and compared with Sweden-born, men from Southern and Western Asia showed high first-time MI risk patterns. In contrast, men from Eastern and South-Eastern Asia, and Latin America showed low first-time MI risk patterns. Within Europe, there seemed to be a slight increasing risk trends from Southern and Western Europe to Northern and Eastern Europe. Women showed similar risk patterns as men, but with fewer countries at significant level. Moreover, women from a few African countries had a lower first-time MI risk than Sweden-born. There were a few exceptions which yielded the opposite risk differences from other countries in the same geographical region, notably Bosnia and Serbia in Europe (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1741826711425340">Table 3</xref> and online supplementary material).
<table-wrap id="table3-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Incidence rate ratios for first-time myocardial infarction by birth region and sex in Sweden, 1987−2008</p></caption><graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1741826711425340" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Country of birth</th><th colspan="3">Male<hr/></th><th colspan="3">Female<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Cases</th><th>Person-years</th><th>IRR (95% CI)</th><th>Cases</th><th>Person-years</th><th>IRR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Sweden</td>
<td>314,694</td>
<td>42,853,105</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>207,047</td>
<td>46,751,289</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Africa</td>
<td>451</td>
<td>261,601</td>
<td>0.92 (0.84–1.01)</td>
<td>116</td>
<td>160,171</td>
<td>0.67 (0.56–0.80)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Northern</td>
<td>205</td>
<td>92,646</td>
<td>0.97 (0.85–1.12)</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>39,072</td>
<td>0.62 (0.44–0.88)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Southern</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>6395</td>
<td>1.12 (0.76–1.64)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>5342</td>
<td>0.90 (0.47–1.73)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Western</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>44,860</td>
<td>0.87 (0.68–1.11)</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>23,186</td>
<td>1.14 (0.73–1.76)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Eastern</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>109,610</td>
<td>0.83 (0.71–0.98)</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>87,326</td>
<td>0.54 (0.40–0.71)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Middle</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>8090</td>
<td>1.07 (0.62–1.84)</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>5245</td>
<td>1.26 (0.60–2.64)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1741826711425340">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>34</td>
<td>29,219</td>
<td>0.76 (0.55–1.07)</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>33,872</td>
<td>0.59 (0.36–0.96)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Asia</td>
<td>3747</td>
<td>1 048,737</td>
<td>1.35 (1.31–1.40)</td>
<td>1591</td>
<td>960,260</td>
<td>0.96 (0.91–1.01)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Eastern</td>
<td>120</td>
<td>57,314</td>
<td>0.58 (0.48–0.69)</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>80,235</td>
<td>0.57 (0.46–0.71)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Southern</td>
<td>1258</td>
<td>364,795</td>
<td>1.47 (1.39–1.55)</td>
<td>481</td>
<td>290,986</td>
<td>0.98 (0.90–1.07)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> South-eastern</td>
<td>127</td>
<td>67,814</td>
<td>0.74 (0.62–0.88)</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>164,440</td>
<td>0.55 (0.44–0.68)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Western</td>
<td>2242</td>
<td>558,814</td>
<td>1.47 (1.41–1.53)</td>
<td>947</td>
<td>424,600</td>
<td>1.09 (1.02–1.16)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1741826711425340">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>36</td>
<td>15,013</td>
<td>1.15 (0.83–1.59)</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>53,891</td>
<td>0.74 (0.54–1.01)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Europe<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1741826711425340">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>24,355</td>
<td>3 832,127</td>
<td>1.06 (1.05–1.07)</td>
<td>17,665</td>
<td>4,922,030</td>
<td>1.05 (1.04–1.07)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Northern</td>
<td>14,623</td>
<td>2,081,557</td>
<td>1.07 (1.05–1.08)</td>
<td>11,690</td>
<td>2,896,335</td>
<td>1.08 (1.06–1.11)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Southern</td>
<td>3861</td>
<td>839,397</td>
<td>1.11 (1.08–1.15)</td>
<td>1756</td>
<td>753,749</td>
<td>1.04 (0.99–1.09)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Western</td>
<td>2600</td>
<td>416,736</td>
<td>0.93 (0.89–0.96)</td>
<td>1860</td>
<td>489,334</td>
<td>0.89 (0.85–0.93)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Eastern</td>
<td>3271</td>
<td>494,437</td>
<td>1.10 (1.06–1.14)</td>
<td>2359</td>
<td>782,612</td>
<td>1.06 (1.02–1.11)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1741826711425340">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>8</td>
<td>3029</td>
<td>0.91 (0.46–1.83)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>11,345</td>
<td>0.59 (0.31–1.13)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Latin America</td>
<td>446</td>
<td>229,134</td>
<td>0.74 (0.68–0.82)</td>
<td>242</td>
<td>256,521</td>
<td>0.58 (0.51–0.66)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> South</td>
<td>396</td>
<td>202,411</td>
<td>0.73 (0.66–0.81)</td>
<td>222</td>
<td>229,364</td>
<td>0.57 (0.50–0.65)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Central</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>15,744</td>
<td>0.70 (0.47–1.06)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>18,867</td>
<td>0.42 (0.22−0.82)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Caribbean</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>10,980</td>
<td>1.15 (0.79–1.67)</td>
<td>−</td>
<td>−</td>
<td>−</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1741826711425340">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>28</td>
<td>14,423</td>
<td>0.83 (0.57–1.20)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>34,476</td>
<td>0.42 (0.25–0.70)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Northern America</td>
<td>619</td>
<td>947 54</td>
<td>0.97 (0.90–1.05)</td>
<td>435</td>
<td>94,772</td>
<td>0.94 (0.85–1.03)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1741826711425340">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>319</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>N/A</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Oceania</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>10,681</td>
<td>0.92 (0.54–1.55)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>7500</td>
<td>1.19 (0.62–2.29)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Unknown</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>9683</td>
<td>0.48 (0.32–0.71)</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>13,016</td>
<td>0.47 (0.31–0.71)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1741826711425340"><p>Study population: 35–89 years old with a valid Swedish ID. Incidence rate ratios (IRR) are adjusted for age at follow-up, calendar period of follow-up, comorbidity, and education. IRR significantly different from 1 is highlighted. <sup>a</sup>Countries with fewer than five cases of myocardial infarction. <sup>b</sup>Ex-Czechoslovakia includes Czech Republic and Slovakia. Ex-Soviet Union includes Belarus, Moldova, Russian Federation, and Ukraine. Ex-Yugoslavia includes Croatia, Macedonia, Serbia, Slovenia, and Montenegro.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-1741826711425340"><title>Case fatality after day 28</title>
<p>We observed 37,416 and 25,122 cases of MI-specific deaths among men and women, respectively. There was a clear improvement of prognosis during the study period, regardless of sex and country of birth (<italic>p</italic> for trend &lt; 0.0001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1741826711425340">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1741826711425340">5</xref>). Overall, men had a worse multivariable adjusted survival than women (HR 1.15, 95 % CI 1.13−1.17) (results not shown). Patients with low level of education had around 50% statistically significantly worse prognosis compared with those with more than 12 years of education regardless of sex and country of birth (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1741826711425340">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1741826711425340">5</xref>). Old age at diagnosis was associated with worse prognosis in both sexes. Patients with no or unknown history of diabetes had about 20−40% lower risk of mortality than patients with such diagnosis (CI ranging from 0.56 to 0.75 at the lower level and from 0.68 to 0.81 at the higher level depending on sex and birth country) (results not shown). When we estimated case fatality after day 28 due to ischaemic heart disease and due to any causes, we found the same protective effect of high education but in a lesser degree, same improvement of prognosis during the study period and the same negative effect associated with a history of diabetes (results not shown).
<table-wrap id="table4-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Male hazard ratios for death after nonfatal first-time myocardial infarction in Sweden, 1987−2008</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1741826711425340" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="3">Sweden-born<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Foreign-born<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>HR (95% CI)</th>
<th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>HR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Years of education</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 9</td>
<td>19,651</td>
<td>691,668</td>
<td>1.41 (1.34–1.47)</td>
<td>1105</td>
<td>58,193</td>
<td>1.44 (1.25–1.66)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 9−12</td>
<td>7783</td>
<td>423,574</td>
<td>1.21 (1.15–1.27)</td>
<td>812</td>
<td>54,750</td>
<td>1.31 (1.13–1.52)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> More than 12</td>
<td>2222</td>
<td>153,824</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>222</td>
<td>21,342</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>5278</td>
<td>45,884</td>
<td>1.44 (1.36–1.52)</td>
<td>343</td>
<td>7710</td>
<td>1.53 (1.28–1.82)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Age at diagnosis (years)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 35−39</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>13,149</td>
<td>0.07 (0.05–0.08)</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>4076</td>
<td>0.06 (0.04–0.09)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 40–44</td>
<td>248</td>
<td>38,473</td>
<td>0.06 (0.05–0.07)</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>8618</td>
<td>0.06 (0.04–0.09)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–49</td>
<td>510</td>
<td>80,509</td>
<td>0.06 (0.05–0.07)</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>15,382</td>
<td>0.06 (0.05–0.08)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 50–54</td>
<td>1001</td>
<td>128,510</td>
<td>0.07 (0.07–0.08)</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>20,690</td>
<td>0.06 (0.05–0.08)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–59</td>
<td>1635</td>
<td>166,587</td>
<td>0.09 (0.08–0.09)</td>
<td>248</td>
<td>23,720</td>
<td>0.10 (0.08–0.13)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 60–64</td>
<td>2902</td>
<td>200,446</td>
<td>0.12 (0.12–0.13)</td>
<td>329</td>
<td>22,677</td>
<td>0.14 (0.11–0.18)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–69</td>
<td>4754</td>
<td>220,492</td>
<td>0.17 (0.17–0.18)</td>
<td>420</td>
<td>19,327</td>
<td>0.20 (0.16–0.25)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 70–74</td>
<td>6530</td>
<td>205,614</td>
<td>0.26 (0.24–0.27)</td>
<td>471</td>
<td>14,472</td>
<td>0.31 (0.25–0.38)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 75–79</td>
<td>7568</td>
<td>156,303</td>
<td>0.38 (0.37–0.40)</td>
<td>343</td>
<td>8424</td>
<td>0.39 (0.31–0.48)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 80–84</td>
<td>6410</td>
<td>83,359</td>
<td>0.59 (0.56–0.62)</td>
<td>262</td>
<td>3785</td>
<td>0.62 (0.50–0.78)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 85–89</td>
<td>3281</td>
<td>21,508</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>823</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Calendar years of follow-up</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1987–1990</td>
<td>12,527</td>
<td>361,849</td>
<td>2.21 (2.12–2.29)</td>
<td>755</td>
<td>31,984</td>
<td>2.33 (2.05–2.65)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1991–1995</td>
<td>10,900</td>
<td>410,228</td>
<td>1.64 (1.58–1.70)</td>
<td>716</td>
<td>41,189</td>
<td>1.66 (1.47–1.89)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1996–2000</td>
<td>6467</td>
<td>306,780</td>
<td>1.25 (1.20–1.30)</td>
<td>547</td>
<td>36,759</td>
<td>1.34 (1.18–1.52)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 2001–2008</td>
<td>5040</td>
<td>236,093</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>464</td>
<td>32,063</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1741826711425340"><p>Hazard ratios (HR) are mutually adjusted for education, age, comorbidities, and calendar years of follow-up when applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table5-1741826711425340" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Female hazard ratios for death after nonfatal first-time myocardial infarction in Sweden, 1987–2008</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1741826711425340" xlink:href="10.1177_1741826711425340-table5.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="3">Sweden-born<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Foreign-born<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>HR (95% CI)</th>
<th>Cases</th>
<th>Person-years</th>
<th>HR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="7"> Years of education</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 9</td>
<td>13,402</td>
<td>407,090</td>
<td>1.54 (1.42–1.66)</td>
<td>965</td>
<td>38,807</td>
<td>1.47 (1.16–1.87)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 9–12</td>
<td>3181</td>
<td>163,278</td>
<td>1.32 (1.21–1.43)</td>
<td>373</td>
<td>20,889</td>
<td>1.28 (1.00–1.64)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> More than 12</td>
<td>623</td>
<td>43,552</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>5339</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>6041</td>
<td>55,980</td>
<td>1.65 (1.51–1.80)</td>
<td>464</td>
<td>9719</td>
<td>1.43 (1.11–1.84)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Age at diagnosis (years)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 35−39</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>3536</td>
<td>0.07 (0.05–0.11)</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>573</td>
<td>0.06 (0.02–0.18)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 40–44</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>9376</td>
<td>0.07 (0.05–0.08)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1395</td>
<td>0.05 (0.02–0.11)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–49</td>
<td>125</td>
<td>19,843</td>
<td>0.07 (0.06–0.08)</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>2783</td>
<td>0.07 (0.04–0.11)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 50–54</td>
<td>177</td>
<td>31,145</td>
<td>0.06 (0.06–0.08)</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>5205</td>
<td>0.08 (0.06–0.12)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–59</td>
<td>397</td>
<td>46,250</td>
<td>0.09 (0.08–0.11)</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>7393</td>
<td>0.09 (0.06–0.12)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 60–64</td>
<td>850</td>
<td>69,667</td>
<td>0.13 (0.12–0.14)</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>11,266</td>
<td>0.13 (0.10–0.16)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–69</td>
<td>1910</td>
<td>100,719</td>
<td>0.18 (0.17–0.19)</td>
<td>246</td>
<td>14,321</td>
<td>0.17 (0.14–0.21)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 70–74</td>
<td>3485</td>
<td>128,577</td>
<td>0.26 (0.25–0.27)</td>
<td>360</td>
<td>13,654</td>
<td>0.26 (0.22–0.32)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 75–79</td>
<td>5674</td>
<td>132,647</td>
<td>0.40 (0.38–0.42)</td>
<td>379</td>
<td>10,073</td>
<td>0.37 (0.31–0.45)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 80–84</td>
<td>6203</td>
<td>95,057</td>
<td>0.59 (0.56–0.61)</td>
<td>396</td>
<td>6345</td>
<td>0.60 (0.51–0.71)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 85–89</td>
<td>4346</td>
<td>33,082</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>216</td>
<td>1745</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Calendar years of follow–up</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1987–1990</td>
<td>7469</td>
<td>163,951</td>
<td>2.06 (1.96–2.16)</td>
<td>486</td>
<td>13,839</td>
<td>2.26 (1.96–2.62)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1991–1995</td>
<td>7059</td>
<td>198,782</td>
<td>1.57 (1.50–1.64)</td>
<td>482</td>
<td>20,539</td>
<td>1.44 (1.26–1.66)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 1996–2000</td>
<td>4523</td>
<td>163,270</td>
<td>1.21 (1.16–1.27)</td>
<td>441</td>
<td>20,324</td>
<td>1.25 (1.09–1.43)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 2001–2008</td>
<td>4196</td>
<td>143,897</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>466</td>
<td>20,053</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>p</italic> for trend</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>&lt;0.001</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-1741826711425340"><p>Hazard ratios (HR) are mutually adjusted for education, age, comorbidities, and calendar years of follow-up when applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-1741826711425340" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this nationwide cohort study from Sweden, we found a continuing decreasing trend for first-time MI incidence among men, with the novel finding of a less pronounced decreasing trend among women and foreign-born. A clear improvement in prognosis after first-time nonfatal MI regardless of sex or country of birth was noticed. We further observed that men and women with low level of education regardless of their country of birth had an increased risk of and worse prognosis after first-time MI. To our knowledge, our study is the first exploring incidence and survival of first-time MI with detailed information on regions and individual countries of origins. The worse prognosis among men and women diagnosed at older age, being male, and among patients with comorbidity of diabetes found in our study were in line with the results of previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1741826711425340">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1741826711425340">24</xref></sup> Furthermore, a better prognosis for first-time MI patients over recent years as found in other studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1741826711425340">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1741826711425340">22</xref></sup> was confirmed by this study.</p>
<p>Our study of first-time MI incidence and prognosis in the total Swedish population, comprising a large and heterogeneous group of immigrants, during the past two decades with available information on important comorbidities have many strengths. These include high-quality data based on the Swedish established system of population-based registers encompassing reliable demographic and medical information, information of exposures before the occurrence of any outcome, and with possibilities of linkages between these registers.</p>
<p>Underestimation of the prevalence of comorbidities, if occurred and if different among immigrants and Sweden-born, may have biased our relative risk estimates. However, risk estimates based on stratified analysis by immigration status (Sweden-born, immigrant) yielded similar results among these two populations.</p>
<p>Our findings of the association between low level of socioeconomic position, measured by education, with increasing incidence of and worse survival after first-time MI confirmed the continuing role of socioeconomic position as an important MI risk indicator.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1741826711425340">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1741826711425340">27</xref></sup> The increased MI incidence among individuals with lower educational levels were, however, relatively stronger for women than for men and for Sweden-born than for foreign-born individuals while the worse prognosis among first-time MI patients with lower educational levels was similar for both sexes and birth places. Education might have an impact on risk of first-time MI indirectly via known MI risk factors such as smoking,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1741826711425340">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1741826711425340">29</xref></sup> overweight,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1741826711425340">29</xref></sup> prolonged exposure to heavy alcohol consumption,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1741826711425340">30</xref></sup> and cholesterol levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1741826711425340">31</xref></sup> Health seeking behaviour, treatment, and life style awareness might partially explain the worse prognosis among patients with low level of education. Lack of reliable information on these important life style risk factors especially among immigrants in Sweden is a limitation of our study.</p>
<p>In accordance with results of previous studies showing decreased MI trend during the earlier years up to 2004,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1741826711425340">8</xref></sup> we found that the multivariable adjusted risk of first-time MI continues to decrease among men irrespective of country of birth. For women, however, the risk decreased at a slower rate than men. Prevalence of some known MI risk factors such as smoking has historically been higher in men than women<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1741826711425340">28</xref></sup> but it seems to be switching toward an increasing prevalence in women and a decreasing in men.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1741826711425340">15</xref></sup> The slight increasing first-time MI incidences around year 2001 might be explained by better diagnostic criteria introduced in 2000. The new MI diagnosis criterion has included raised troponin T concentrations in addition to other factors. Some patients were classified as unstable angina according to previous diagnosis criterion would be now classified as having MI according to new criteria.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1741826711425340">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>The higher risk of first-time MI incidence among men and women born in Southern and Western Asia compared with men and women born in Sweden was in line with previous studies conducted in North America and Sweden.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1741826711425340">32</xref></sup> Immigrants born in Europe had a very small difference in incidence compared with Sweden-born. The 10% increased risk among Finnish immigrants compared with Sweden-born found in our study was much lower than the 70% increased risk observed in another Swedish study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1741826711425340">8</xref></sup> One of the possible explanations for this difference could be a different period used in that previous study where the observation period was from 1974 to 1976.</p>
<p>The noteworthy high risk of first-time MI among immigrants born in Serbia and Bosnia is in opposite of low risk results from surrounding countries in the same geographical region. A large number of Bosnian immigrants in Sweden are refugees from Bosnian Civil War.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1741826711425340">33</xref></sup> A high prevalence of posttraumatic stress disorders, a common anxiety disorder experienced after war, has been reported among immigrants from Bosnia and Serbia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1741826711425340">33</xref></sup> The high risk of first-time MI could hypothetically be explained by severe mental stress such as posttraumatic stress disorder among these immigrants.</p>
<p>Although both incidence of, and fatality after, first-time MI continued to decrease, low level of education as an indicator for socioeconomic position, independently of sex and country of birth, remained an important risk indicator for both incidence and case fatality after day 28. In addition, healthcare providers should be aware of high-risk populations among immigrants especially men from Southern and Western Asia.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec18-1741826711425340"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This study was supported by the Swedish Council for Working Life and Social Research (grant number FAS 2008–1128) and Karolinska Institutet doctoral funds.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec19-1741826711425340"><title>Conflict of interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1741826711425340"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Med Clin North Am</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>91</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>552; ix</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1741826711425340"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Loncar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Projections of global mortality and burden of disease from 2002 to 2030</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>3</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>e442</fpage>–<lpage>e442</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1741826711425340"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moradi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Allebeck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>[The burden of disease in Sweden measured with DALY. Neuropsychiatric diseases and cardiovascular diseases dominate]</article-title>. <source>Lakartidningen</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>103</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1741826711425340"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tunstall-Pedoe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuulasmaa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolonen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruokokoski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Amouyel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Contribution of trends in survival and coronary-event rates to changes in coronary heart disease mortality: 10-year results from 37 WHO MONICA project populations. Monitoring trends and determinants in cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>353</volume>(<issue>9164</issue>): <fpage>1547</fpage>–<lpage>1557</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1741826711425340"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Manrique-Garcia E, Sidorchuk A, Hallqvist J and Moradi T. Socioeconomic position and incidence of acute myocardial infarction: a meta-analysis. <italic>J Epidemiol Community Health</italic> 2010 (e-publication ahead of print)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1741826711425340"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosamond</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Flegal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Furie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenlund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Heart disease and stroke statistics − 2008 update: a report from the American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>117</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>e25</fpage>–<lpage>e146</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1741826711425340"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Moradi T, Sidorchuk A and Hallqvist J. Translation of questionnaire increases the response rate in immigrants: Filling the language gap or feeling of inclusion? <italic>Scand J Public Health</italic> 2010 (e-publication ahead of print)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1741826711425340"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlbom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Theorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of myocardial infarction among male Finnish immigrants in relation to length of stay in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source> <year>1982</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1741826711425340"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Syme</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Acculturation and coronary heart disease in Japanese-Americans</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <year>1976</year>; <volume>104</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1741826711425340"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balarajan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnic differences in mortality from ischaemic heart disease and cerebrovascular disease in England and Wales</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>302</volume>(<issue>6776</issue>): <fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1741826711425340"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beiki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegmayr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moradi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Country reports: Sweden</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Razum</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Spallek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeske</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Migration-sensitive cancer registration in Europe</source>, <publisher-loc>Pieterlen, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lang</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>; <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1741826711425340"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Socialstyrelsen. Kvalitet och innehåll i patientregistret and Cause of Death 2007. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.socialstyrelsen.se">www.socialstyrelsen.se</ext-link> (2007, 2009, consulted August 2010)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1741826711425340"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Statistics Sweden. Folk-och bostadsräkningar, FoB. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.scb.se">www.scb.se</ext-link> (2010, consulted February 2010)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1741826711425340"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Socialstyrelsen. Longitudinal integration database for health insurance and labour market studies [LISA in Swedish]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.socialstyrelsen.se">www.socialstyrelsen.se</ext-link> (2010, consulted August 2010)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1741826711425340"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Spetz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ysberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Attack rate, mortality and case fatality for acute myocardial infarction in Sweden during 1987–95. Results from the national AMI register in Sweden</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>248</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1741826711425340"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spetz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sex differences in survival after myocardial infarction in Sweden; data from the Swedish National Acute Myocardial Infarction Register</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1741826711425340"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Myocardial infarction redefined − a consensus document of The Joint European Society of Cardiology/American College of Cardiology Committee for the redefinition of myocardial infarction. <italic>Eur Heart J</italic> 2000; 21(18): 1502–1513</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1741826711425340"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of changing diagnostic criteria on incidence, management, and outcome of acute myocardial infarction: retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>326</volume>(<issue>7381</issue>): <fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1741826711425340"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Midthune</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Permutation tests for joinpoint regression with applications to cancer rates</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1741826711425340"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronnemaa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyorala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Laakso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mortality from coronary heart disease in subjects with type 2 diabetes and in nondiabetic subjects with and without prior myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>339</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1741826711425340"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norhammar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindback</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallentin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenestrand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improved but still high short- and long-term mortality rates after myocardial infarction in patients with diabetes mellitus: a time-trend report from the Swedish Register of Information and Knowledge about Swedish Heart Intensive Care Admission</article-title>. <source>Heart</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>93</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1577</fpage>–<lpage>1583</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1741826711425340"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term prognosis after hospital admission for acute myocardial infarction from 1987 to 2006</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source> <year>2010</year>. <comment>(e-publication ahead of print)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1741826711425340"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langorgen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Igland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vollset</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Averina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordrehaug</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tell</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Short-term and long-term case fatality in 11,878 patients hospitalized with a first acute myocardial infarction, 1979–2001: the Western Norway cardiovascular registry</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1741826711425340"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aengus Murphy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robb</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonagh</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dargie</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Declining renal function after myocardial infarction predicts poorer long-term outcome</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1741826711425340"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuomilehto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Salonen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Do cardiovascular risk factors explain the relation between socioeconomic status, risk of all-cause mortality, cardiovascular mortality, and acute myocardial infarction?</article-title> <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>144</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>942</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1741826711425340"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Shea</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of mortality with years of education in patients with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction treated with fibrinolysis</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1741826711425340"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Steg</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gersh</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Attained educational level and incident atherothrombotic events in low- and middle-income compared with high-income countries</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>122</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1167</fpage>–<lpage>1175</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1741826711425340"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ounpuu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Avezum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with myocardial infarction in 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): case-control study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>364</volume>(<issue>9438</issue>): <fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1741826711425340"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Due</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallqvist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The contribution of childhood and adult socioeconomic position to adult obesity and smoking behaviour: an international comparison</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1741826711425340"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fillmore</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kniep</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leino</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Romelsjo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol consumption and mortality. I. Characteristics of drinking groups</article-title>. <source>Addiction</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>93</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1741826711425340"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eliasson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Janlert</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegmayr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Time trends in population cholesterol levels 1986–2004: influence of lipid-lowering drugs, obesity, smoking and educational level. The northern Sweden MONICA study</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>260</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1741826711425340"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>South Asians and cardiovascular risk: what clinicians should know</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>113</volume>(<issue>25</issue>): <fpage>e924</fpage>–<lpage>e929</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1741826711425340"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thulesius</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakansson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Screening for posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms among Bosnian refugees</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Stress</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>