<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACD</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spacd</journal-id>
<journal-title>Australian Journal of Career Development</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1038-4162</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2200-6974</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1038416213486774</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1038416213486774</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Rejuvenate career counselling training in counsellor education</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Charles P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1038416213486774"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1038416213486774">University of Toronto, Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1038416213486774">Charles P Chen, Counselling Psychology Program, Department of Applied Psychology and Human Development, Ontario Institute for Studies in Education (OISE), University of Toronto, 252 Bloor Street West, 7th Floor, Toronto, Ontario M5S 1V6, Canada. Email: <email>cp.chen@utoronto.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>72</fpage>
<lpage>81</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Australian Council for Educational Research</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In addressing the significant role of career counselling as a key element for the entire counselling profession, this article points to the need of strengthening career counselling training in counsellor education. It argues that counsellor training programs and counsellor educators should draw more attention to the career counselling component in training. It also proposes some considerations of consolidating and refining the career counselling component in counsellor preparation, with a focus on helping counsellor trainees acquire theoretical knowledge and accumulate clinical competency in the career counselling domain.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Career counselling training</kwd>
<kwd>counsellor education</kwd>
<kwd>counsellor training programs</kwd>
<kwd>theoretical knowledge</kwd>
<kwd>clinical competency</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Since the pioneering framework laid by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1038416213486774">Parsons (1909)</xref>, the role of vocational guidance and career counselling has evolved significantly over the last century, along with the drastic changes that have occurred, and are happening in a dynamic and complicated world of work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1038416213486774">Brown, 2002b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1038416213486774">Isaacson &amp; Brown, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1038416213486774">Zunker, 2006</xref>). To help people cope with numerous challenges in this post-industrial and postmodern work world embedded in knowledge economy, digital revolution, globalization, war for talents, and other highly uncertain and often chaotic socio-political environments, career counselling practice is challenged to address people’s career development issues and needs that are more sophisticated than ever before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1038416213486774">Bright &amp; Pryor, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1038416213486774">Pryor &amp; Bright, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1038416213486774">Rifkin, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1038416213486774">Sharf, 2010</xref>). To prepare prospective career counsellors for best practice, counsellor education and counsellor educators are called upon to refresh and reinforce the career counselling training aspect within counsellor training in a meaningful and vigorous manner.</p>
<p>The main goal of this article is to draw attention to and reiterate the component of career counselling training in the whole picture of counsellor education. More specifically, it will (a) provide a terse rationale to review the significant role of career counselling in the helping profession, (b) argue that more attention is needed for highlighting and consolidating the career counselling aspect during training, and (c) propose some considerations for strengthening and refining the career counselling component within graduate level counsellor education programs. In combination with other knowledge and skills taught in the counsellor education framework, these proposals aim to provide both counsellor education programs and counsellor educators with heuristic thoughts on counsellor preparation, with a particular focus on accumulating expertise and enhancing competency in the career counselling domain. These considerations aim to strengthen not only the career counselling aspect but hopefully some other related variables and features in counsellor education as well.</p>
<p>For brevity, the terms “career component,” “career area,” “career aspect,” and “career domain,” will be used interchangeably in the forthcoming discussion. They all mean the training component focusing on the professional area of career development and counselling within the realm of graduate level counsellor education. Also, the terms “educators” and “trainees” will mean counsellor educators and counsellor trainees, respectively, unless specified otherwise. Furthermore, the term “career theories” will be used in a general and inclusive manner to collectively address theories regarding career development and choice, career counselling and vocational guidance, and theories concerning people’s worklife and vocational psychology. Of note, although the current discussion is framed within a North American context, namely, the United States and Canada, the issues addressed and the considerations/recommendations proposed may be of beneficial reference to the field in other countries around the world.</p>
<sec id="sec1-1038416213486774"><title>Significance of career counselling: A succinct rationale</title>
<p>Anyone who is familiar with the history and development of counselling psychology knows too well that career counselling and/or vocational guidance played an essential part in forming the contemporary counselling psychology discipline. That is, career counselling has always been instrumental in promoting the growth and maturity of counselling psychology profession in North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1038416213486774">Herr, Cramer, &amp; Niles, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1038416213486774">Niles &amp; Harris-Bowlsbey, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1038416213486774">Peterson &amp; Gonzalez, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1038416213486774">Zunker, 2006</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1038416213486774">Super (1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1038416213486774">1990</xref>), the late president of Division 17 (Counselling Psychology) of the American Psychology Association, made his mark as one of the greatest theorists, scholars, and practitioners in the counselling psychology field in general, and in the domain of vocational and career psychology, in particular. The two influential national organizations in the career area in the United States, i.e., National Career Development Association (NCDA) and National Employment Counselling Association (NECA), function as national divisions within the American Counselling Association (ACA); both play significant roles in the continuing growth of ACA. Parallels can be found in Canada as well. The Canadian Counselling and Psychotherapy Association (CCPA), formerly known as Canadian Counselling Association (CCA), has incorporated career counselling as a main component into its mission since the organization’s establishment in the 1960s. CCPA, in general, and its Career Development Chapter, in particular, has attracted many scholars, educators, and practitioners in the career development area to work together to increase the profile of career counselling in the entire counselling and helping profession in Canada.</p>
<p>With respect to counsellor education, providing the counsellor trainees with career counselling training has long been a norm for many graduate programs across North America. For some programs, the subject of career counselling is part of a compulsory curriculum, i.e., as required or prerequisite courses for a master’s degree. For others, the topic is built into the training process as either a mandatory or elective course component depending on the varieties of specialization that exist within a training program. While the majority of such courses may be open to graduate students of all levels (i.e., both master’s and doctoral level trainees), some programs offer career research seminar courses solely to doctoral students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1038416213486774">Kalbfleisch &amp; Burwell, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1038416213486774">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1038416213486774">Niles &amp; Harris-Bowlsbey, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1038416213486774">Sharf, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>This reality in counsellor training certainly echoes the significant role of career counselling as a key element for the entire counselling profession. Such significance is expected to continue to grow as the world of work and people’s vocational aspects of life have become more dynamic and complex than ever before. Counselling psychology, in general, and career psychology, in particular, must become more proactive and instrumental in understanding the role of work in people’s life. Likewise, counselling practice, especially career counselling practice, will need to be conducted in a more effective manner while helping individuals cope with fast emerging new issues and challenges in their worklives and career experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1038416213486774">Peterson &amp; Gonzalez, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1038416213486774">Sharf, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1038416213486774">Zunker, 2006</xref>). As the importance of career counselling has existed and will continue to expand, a call for improving and strengthening the quality of career development and counselling competence in counsellor education is justifiable, necessary, and very timely.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1038416213486774"><title>Accentuate career aspect in counsellor education</title>
<p>Notwithstanding its importance and relevance, the career counselling competency has historically not received enough attention in the counselling profession and counsellor education. In comparison to some other specializations within the counselling profession such as family counselling, couples and marriage counselling, and counselling on other personal/social life domains, career counselling is usually not considered an essential category in the discipline of counselling and psychotherapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1038416213486774">Corey, 2013</xref>). Career counselling is commonly seen as an easier and less demanding task that solely focuses on helping a client cope with a vocational issue, or simply put, find a job. Thus, it is very often regarded as a therapeutically less challenging and technically less sophisticated practice in the counselling field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1038416213486774">Corey, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1038416213486774">Crites, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1038416213486774">Osipow &amp; Walsh, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1038416213486774">Zunker, 2006</xref>). Influenced by such perceptions, counsellor educators whose professional and academic interest is not in the career development terrain may not pay much attention to the significance of career counselling aspect in training. Consequently, it is not surprising that the topic of career counselling is often ranked as secondary and more peripheral in counsellor education programs unless there is strong faculty resource in the career area within a program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1038416213486774">Kalbfleisch &amp; Burwell, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1038416213486774">2007</xref>).</p>
<p>To rejuvenate the career counselling component in counsellor preparation, the first and foremost important issue that needs to be addressed is perhaps the change of the attitude among counsellor educators who have lower awareness of the pivotal role of career counselling. Counsellor educators need to adopt a more open, broad, and integral perspective in considering the career component in training. The rationale for adopting this perspective rests on the fact that the role of work has become an increasingly important part in people’s total life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1038416213486774">Gysbers, Heppner, &amp; Johnston, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1038416213486774">Peterson &amp; Gonzalez, 2005</xref>). Worklife issues are almost always interrelated with other aspects of one’s personal and social life. Similarly, various issues in one’s personal life can often have an impact on his/her vocational and career prospects of life. In this sense, personal and social counselling on various intrapersonal and interpersonal issues (e.g., stress, anxiety, fear, conflict, relationship, marriage, family, etc.) is not restricted to the domain of personal counselling only (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1038416213486774">Krumboltz, 1993</xref>). Vocational well-being interacts dynamically with the whole state of a person’s general psychological and physiological well-being. A better understanding of vocational and career psychology may lead to enhancing the understanding of other aspects of human psychology, and vice versa.</p>
<p>The interactive coexistence of one’s personal life and worklife forms a sound rationale for strengthening the career component in a counsellor education program. An increased awareness to this truth seems necessary, as it can lead to an attitudinal change among many counsellor educators as well as training programs. That is, a more constructive, positive, and proactive attitude should be fostered when planning and implementing the career counselling training component during the counsellor training process. With a more positive attitude, counsellor educators and training programs may draw much more attention to the enhancement of the career counselling component. An effort toward this direction will benefit both the career component as well as other aspects of the entire training program.</p>
<p>Counsellor educators who are not specialized in the career area may find it very helpful to include some basic knowledge of career development in their repertoire. This is not to say that these educators should become experts in teaching career counselling curriculum or training career counsellors. Rather, gaining some professional knowledge in the career area may help these educators widen the scope of their professional specialty, and in turn, to enrich and enhance the knowledge in their own area of teaching and training. For example, coping with psychological distress in life is generally a personal counselling issue. Yet, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1038416213486774">Super’s (1990)</xref> notion of a variety of life roles presented in the life-career rainbow may be very helpful to understand the context and sources for stress. This is because life role conflict can often be part of the causes that trigger and intensify the stressful emotion in various intrapersonal, interpersonal, familial, and social situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1038416213486774">Slan-Jerusalim &amp; Chen, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Giving more attention to the career component means to allocate more resources to this training aspect. Such resources may include intangible means such as positive and constructive attitudes toward career counselling training from educators and programs. The resources should also include tangible efforts such as increasing the career counselling training profile and providing more time and content in teaching and learning. For example, with more focus on the career component, new training courses and/or course content may be added to the existing curriculum. This would provide trainees who are interested in career counselling issues with an opportunity for further professional development. Meanwhile, trainees who intend to specialize in other areas of counselling may also find these increased learning and training opportunities in the career area a plus to their knowledge and skill enhancement. This is because such elective training options can help to broaden their vision, stimulate their thinking, and enrich their experience within the general training program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1038416213486774">Chen, 2001</xref>). In this sense, the development of the career component is not an isolated attempt but a part of the integrated strategy to heighten the overall quality of counsellor preparation.</p>
<p>An emphasis on the career component will certainly provide counsellor educators in the career area with much needed incentive for refinement and development. They may feel both the excitement and responsibility, especially the latter sentiment, in strengthening the career component in the training process. Rather than feeling satisfied with maintaining the status quo of a less prioritized sub-discipline, the educators in the career area will feel a sense of priority and significance. This will, in turn, lead to a sense of urgency to improve the visibility and quality of the career component within the training system. First, educators in the career area may realize that they have to deal with their own biases toward the career topic, that is, the conscious or unconscious biases that are influenced by a variety of internal and external circumstances. Looking at the career construct too narrowly (e.g., in the sense of “work/job-related issue only”) or with a self-devaluing manner (e.g., in the sense of “not therapeutic enough in the counselling profession”) are examples of such attitudinal problems. The educators need to work out these perception issues themselves before they can appear more confident and convincing in the eyes of their trainees. Second, these educators need to be passionate in believing in the significance of the role of work and career in people’s total life. This passion is critical as it forms the very foundation for curiosity, sensitivity, and imagination, all which are of vital importance in generating creative and visionary insights for the continuing growth and vitality of the career component in counsellor training. Third, the educators need to be proactive in rendering new initiatives in training. That is, they should not only constantly renew their own professional knowledge of career development and counselling but also translate such knowledge into viable and updated means for training in a vigorous manner. As a result, an ongoing effort will be devoted to generating new and updated training methodology that will constantly stimulate counsellor trainees’ interest, and enhance the overall quality of teaching and learning in counsellor preparation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1038416213486774"><title>Considerations to enhance career counselling training</title>
<p>The more attention to the career aspect from the part of counsellor education programs in general, and counsellor educators in particular, provides the very philosophical foundation upon which the career construct can be refreshed and energized in counsellor education. With increased awareness and sensitivity, counsellor educators are called upon to consider some viable options for enhancing counsellor trainees’ competency in the career development and counselling area. These considerations are not intended to form a set of very specific training methodology but rather to generate some general rationale and recommendations that might be seen by counsellor educators as helpful and effective to facilitate and enhance the career counselling aspect in counsellor education.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1038416213486774"><title>Building theoretical foundation</title>
<sec id="sec5-1038416213486774"><title>Increasing awareness</title>
<p>To form a solid theoretical foundation is of essential importance in helping counsellor trainees enter the realm of career counselling. Although no one would question the necessity of acquiring theoretical knowledge, it is not unusual that before starting their training in this area, many trainees tend to unintentionally ignore the critical importance of this essential aspect of the learning task. In thinking about studying career counselling, a commonly shared expectation among trainees is to learn “how to do career counselling” technically, that is, trainees perceive that career counselling is a more technical and/or hands-on helping mechanism that merely deals with people’s vocational demands and problems. For these trainees, thus, enrolling in a career counselling course is about to gain career counselling skills that would have immediate relevance and applicability to clients who are, voluntarily or involuntarily, seeking employment or career change.</p>
<p>It is also a common phenomenon that the curriculum title <italic>career counselling</italic> attracts some trainees’ attention because of their personal needs to know something about career, from which they may benefit for the well-being of their own worklives. The learning expectation from this group is often vague and general, with no particular preference toward either the theoretical knowledge or practical interventions. Nevertheless, a small number of trainees may express their interest in learning career theories largely because of their working contexts. For example, they have been involved in career counselling and vocational guidance type of work, yet have not received any formal training in career counselling. They feel the need to learn theories in career counselling so that their practice can be better guided, leading to the refinement and enrichment of their counselling skills.</p>
<p>As expectations and needs vary, it is pertinent to establish among the trainees some common ground concerning gaining theoretical knowledge in the career domain. The educator may invite trainees to share their diverse views and observations regarding the role and function of theory in knowledge pursuit. This can be done in an open, extensive, and inclusive manner. That is, reflections on theory-building and theory-implication in various fields are considered relevant reference points. For example, a variety of theory-related issues in general psychology, sociology, education, health care, and other disciplines in social sciences and natural sciences can be utilized to refresh one’s perception on the topic. Rather than focusing on the specifics, the attention is drawn to the pivotal role that theory plays in forming the knowledge base for a discipline. As trainees can often come from a diverse baccalaureate background other than psychology, they may find it much easier in referring back to theories with which they have had some familiarity through their previous academic studies.</p>
<p>A sharing of such perceptions and reflections is very helpful, particularly for these core and introductory level career counselling courses and seminars. It sets up an essential foundation upon which more comprehensive conceptualization of complex life career issues may occur. Regardless of his/her prior experiences and expectations concerning the topic, each trainee may benefit from an increased awareness and interest in theory learning. First, the purpose and meaningfulness of theory learning is recognized. Second, the possible mysterious guise covering career theories will be unveiled when the common nature and characteristics of theories are revisited. Third, the unique usefulness of familiarizing oneself with key theoretical models and tenets in the career area are clarified and understood. Fourth, each trainee’s personal expectations of the career counselling training is linked more closely and coherently with the initial learning task of conceptualizing and digesting a number of major theoretical models in life career development and career counselling.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1038416213486774"><title>Digesting theory</title>
<p>Notwithstanding a higher motivation and clearer goal, a well-organized and coherent methodology should follow to stimulate, maintain, and enhance the trainees’ interest in the theory-learning process. Three basic points may be worth considering when approaching theory conceptualization.</p>
<p>Perhaps the first and foremost important training task at this stage is to survey each career theory in its unique historical context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1038416213486774">Brown, 2002b</xref>). According to major sources of literature that are suitable for adoption as textbooks for graduate career counselling courses, there are at least between 10 and 20 major career theories that trainees may have to encounter depending on the scope and purpose of a specific training curriculum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1038416213486774">Brown, 2002a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1038416213486774">Isaacson &amp; Brown, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1038416213486774">Sharf, 2010</xref>). From <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1038416213486774">Parson’s (1909</xref>) trait-and-factor frame to the emerging constructionist approaches in the last decade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1038416213486774">Cochran, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1038416213486774">Maree, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1038416213486774">Savickas, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1038416213486774">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1038416213486774">Young, Valach, &amp; Collin, 2002</xref>), the theory evolution in the domain of career and vocational psychology has contributed significantly to the field for more than a century, and it is still continuing. Both the historical background and current status of each theory need to be explained and understood in a sensible manner. More focus may be given to the current theoretical implications whenever appropriate, as the meaningfulness of studying a theory rests on its present applicability to the enhancement of knowledge and practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1038416213486774">Niles &amp; Harris-Bowlsbey, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1038416213486774">Sharf, 2010</xref>). For example, many established theories that were originated decades ago did not include the issue of diversity as one of the primary considerations, and this could pose a limitation when they are applied in the current world of work. Thus, a review of the past and an analysis of the present can be very helpful to capture the relevancy of such theoretical models in explaining the contemporary aspects of people’s worklife and vocational psychology in our society.</p>
<p>Second, abstract theoretical concepts need to be translated into lay persons’ language. Some work toward this end on the part of the educator is certainly worth the effort as it can improve the quality of both teaching and learning by taking down those unnecessary barriers in theory comprehension. A rule of thumb to follow is that every effort must be made to explain the complex theoretical constructs in a clear, concise, consistent, and most of all, simple manner. Technical jargon, special terminology, and sophisticated research evidence used to frame a career theory need to be simplified by plain illustrations that are easy to understand. For example, the concept of <italic>satisfactoriness</italic> in the work adjustment theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1038416213486774">Dawis, 2002</xref>) can be simply understood as an employer’s satisfaction of an employee’s performance. Also, the notion of human agency in social cognitive career theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1038416213486774">Lent, Brown, &amp; Hackett, 2002</xref>) and other constructionist approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1038416213486774">Cochran, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1038416213486774">1997</xref>) can be explained as human intention and action to make things happen.</p>
<p>Third, theoretical concepts are better discerned if they are directly connected with each trainee’s personal experience and context. This aspect is actually an extension of the prior two points. As each trainee conceptualizes theories with his/her background experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1038416213486774">Krumboltz &amp; Levin, 2004</xref>), abstract theoretical concepts become easier to understand and more concrete. Meanwhile, it helps the trainee focus more on the applicability of these concepts in the present work world, especially in working environments with which the trainee is more familiar. For example, several key components of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1038416213486774">Super’s (1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1038416213486774">1990</xref>) theory such as <italic>self-concept, developmental stages</italic>, and <italic>life roles</italic> become more vivid and down-to-the-earth when the trainee uses these concepts to take a close look at the vocational identity development in his/her own life career rainbow.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1038416213486774"><title>Broadening scope</title>
<p>A simultaneous training task alongside the theory comprehension is the integration and understanding of current issues in vocational psychology, in general, and in people’s worklife, in particular. This is because the centrality of theory comprehension lies with the meaningful explanation of the worklife reality we encounter in the current world of work and beyond. In other words, theory is to provide the means that will achieve the end of obtaining a better understanding of real career issues. With heuristic theoretical reference and guidance, career development issues may need to be explored in a broad horizon of life career integration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1038416213486774">Gysbers et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1038416213486774">Miller-Tiedeman, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1038416213486774">1999</xref>). A range of interactive and diverse issues may be integrated into the intellectual debate. This seems necessary in understanding the complex and dynamic human phenomenon of vocational and career psychology in the current society. A central point that calls for attention is to develop the critical thinking, as well as a more holistic view in perceiving career issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1038416213486774">Hansen, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1038416213486774">2001</xref>). A broader and more comprehensive perspective needs to replace a narrowly defined notion of career rooted in a traditional epistemology.</p>
<p>Within the general discipline of psychology, counselling psychology draws heavily on the psychological side of human life. Career counselling as a main component of counselling practice reflects this reality. An evident example is the fact that majority of the career development and counselling theories are psychology-based theories. While there is recognition of the influence of social environment in people’s psychological functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1038416213486774">Mitchell &amp; Krumboltz, 1996</xref>), very few theoretical models tend to give much attention to examining the macro-sociology that parallels individuals’ life career development. In addressing and perceiving career problems, career counselling training should provide more time and space for the inclusion of macro-sociology in the design and implementation of the training curriculum. The term “macro-sociology” here is intended to cover a variety of disciplines and facets in social as well as in natural and applied sciences, including but not limited to, subjects such as sociology, economics, political science, cultural anthropology, environmental studies, biology, engineering, computer science, etc. A career problem can hardly be confined and clarified in a mere “vocational” dimension. Rather, it needs to be defined and realized in its broad social and personal contexts.</p>
<p>To tackle the career issues with a more integral and sophisticated manner, the career counselling training needs to adopt a sense of openness and creativity in approaching issues, similar to what was elaborated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1038416213486774"/>Patton and McMahon (1999, 2006) as a systems worldview for life-career development. This complex system is composed of various contextual and relational factors influencing people’s worklife. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1038416213486774">Blustein (2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1038416213486774">2011</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1038416213486774">Richardson (1993)</xref>, it is these factors such as race, ethnicity, and social class that pose pivotal impact in shaping the career paths and career outcomes of many individuals. Thus, the necessity and benefit of drawing serious attention to these macro-sociological factors in people’s vocational wellness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1038416213486774">Blustein, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1038416213486774">2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1038416213486774">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1038416213486774">Patton &amp; McMahon, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1038416213486774">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1038416213486774">Richardson, 1993</xref>) is apparent. In doing so, more attention should be directed to the connection of a career problem and its broad context. The focus is on the interplay of various relationships in the formation and development of the career problem. It may be particularly relevant that the impact of the macro-sociological forces on one’s career choices and decisions are well addressed. For example, a change in the environmental and ecological system such as climate change and distinction of natural resources can critically alter the way the economy operates. Likewise, the arrival of a new technology and/or disappearance of an old one can have an impact on the requirement for the workforce. These factors may result a significant change of individuals’ worklife content, which may ultimately have an impact on many other aspects of personal and social lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1038416213486774">Chen, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>As the need for depth and breadth arises, career counselling training should give more focus on extensive learning with respect to course material and content. A variety of relevant contents in other disciplines, especially in the field of sociology, may be incorporated into the training process. The trainees can benefit substantially from having the opportunity of accessing interdisciplinary views on career in addition to learning the issue only from the angle of vocational psychology. For example, sociological views on worklife emphasize the vital impact of social, cultural, and political dynamics in forming one’s place in the society, and ultimately his/her vocational identity and experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1038416213486774">Hotchkiss &amp; Borow, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1038416213486774">Irving &amp; Malik, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1038416213486774">Johnson &amp; Mortimer, 2002</xref>). Similarly, the economic explanation on career ascribes individuals’ career movement to the macro- and micro-economy in general, and the supply-and-demand balance in the labour market in particular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1038416213486774">Rifkin, 1995</xref>). The integration of diverse and interdisciplinary perspectives as such can enrich and broaden the meaning of career. It helps the trainees realize that one’s career experience ultimately mirrors social and societal changes and evolution; career counselling must address such richness and complexity to produce meaningful and effective helping outcome.</p>
<p>An endeavor in adopting a broad and integral perspective is helpful. It provides a richer context for theory comprehension. It also encourages the trainees to generate more dynamic and holistic thinking while applying career theories to diverse issues and situations. With a wider scope, life career development issues can be perceived in a more comprehensive manner, leading to the learning and application of a variety of context-relevant helping strategies in career counselling practice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1038416213486774"><title>Enhancing career counselling competency</title>
<p>The skill training dimension in a career counselling curriculum should have several clear and consistent objectives. First, it serves as a bridge to connect theories, practical issues, and relevant helping methodology. Second, it provides the experiential learning opportunity from which the trainees will be able to start their initial experience of acquiring basic technical knowledge or micro-skills in counselling, in general, and in career counselling, in particular. Third, it facilitates the trainees to practice and improve their counselling skills, especially career counselling proficiency and techniques in real clinical contexts.</p>
<sec id="sec9-1038416213486774"><title>Bridging theory and practice</title>
<p>The ultimate goal of gaining theoretical and intellectual insight is to enhance better practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1038416213486774">Amundson, Harris-Bowlsbey, &amp; Niles, 2009</xref>). Acquiring clinical experience should always proceed together with the application and further development of theoretical knowledge. A systematic effort is required to make a coherent link between theories, issues, and practice. Thus, theory will guide practice, and practice becomes the means to achieve a higher level of theoretical learning and comprehension. The main training task here is to guide the trainees to think critically about the relevance of theories in real helping situations. As the trainees are encouraged to reflect on their past and present experiences, and look at their anticipated work environments, they will realize that some of the theoretical models seem more applicable than others, while career theories are applied to diverse client populations in various contexts.</p>
<p>A thorough discussion of the theoretical rationale that can guide the actual counselling intervention will be a necessary initial step to start this process of theory-practice bridging. It helps the trainees to gain insight in several respects. First, both the strengths and limitations of a theory are highlighted in dealing with real issues and clientele. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1038416213486774">Holland’s (1997)</xref> typology works excellently to pinpoint a person’s vocational preference based on his/her personality. Nevertheless, it does not provide explanation of how such personality has initially developed and formed. Second, it demonstrates to the trainees that intellectual insights such as theoretical tenets should be, and can be, utilized to deal with real career problems. For example, the matching concept from the trait-and-factor approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1038416213486774">Dawis, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1038416213486774">Holland, 1997</xref>), the narrative conceptualization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1038416213486774">Cochran, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1038416213486774">Maree, 2007</xref>), and the cognitive information processing framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1038416213486774">Sampson, Reardon, Peterson, &amp; Lenz, 2004</xref>) can all be implemented in the helping intervention with their unique strengths and efficacy. In particular, the narrative career counselling approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1038416213486774">Cochran, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1038416213486774">Maree, 2007</xref>) may provide a timely and meaningful mechanism in helping clients find their true inner voice in coping with issues of high complexity and uncertainty in today’s world of work. While the trainees can definitely benefit from learning and practicing the intervention techniques in this regard, perhaps the core of utilizing the narrative approaches lies within the essential awareness of the role of subjectivity, meaning making, intentionality, perspective-taking, goal-directed action, and the like, in people’s life-career trajectory. Thus, both the narrative theoretical essentials and helping strategies are utilized to facilitate clients to construct, deconstruct, reconstruct, and at times, co-construct, and project real narratives for improving their career wellness. Third, it encourages the trainees to think more critically and comprehensively of the theoretical rationale in diverse helping contexts. For example, trainees who are school teachers may find some concepts from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1038416213486774">Holland’s (1997)</xref> theory and Krumboltz’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1038416213486774">Mitchell &amp; Krumboltz, 1996</xref>) social learning theory are particularly useful in working with student populations. Likewise, trainees of community and social work background may find some particular relevance in using developmental approaches such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1038416213486774">Super’s (1990)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1038416213486774">Gottfredson’s (2002)</xref> models while working with their clients.</p>
<p>In order to establish an effective and truly meaningful link between theory and practice, research is very often a pivotal and necessary component that needs to be incorporated into the entire picture of training. A good theory requires support from empirical evidence. Such a theory should also stimulate research interest in furthering the theory and enhancing knowledge in the related fields. Likewise, research informs best practice, and also draws useful information from practice. Thus, the role and function of research deserves much attention in training. To this end, counsellor educators need to be active researchers themselves so that they possess the knowledge and expertise to combine research into their teaching. In other words, they should keep their ongoing involvement in research so that they are the true experts with both hands-on experiences and updated and leading-edge research knowledge in their own repertoire. This continuing effort of lifelong-learning, professional development, and knowledge renewal makes them comfortable, confident, and passionate in encouraging and empowering trainees to learn the vital role that research always plays in knowledge building and practice enhancement.</p>
<p>To this end, the research component is infused into the training process with coherent logic and relevancy, making sure that abstract information is explained in a clear, concise, and simple manner. For instance, to illustrate how career theoretical integration is applied to comprehend individuals’ life-career narratives via a cross-cultural transition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1038416213486774">Chen’s (2006)</xref> study in this regard may provide pertinent information that connects theory, research, and practice. Similarly, to utilize key tenets from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1038416213486774">Super (1990)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1038416213486774">Greenhaus and Powell (2006)</xref>, the research on the work-family enrichment phenomenon via a reciprocal positive transfer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1038416213486774">Shein &amp; Chen, 2011</xref>) may offer a meaningful demonstration as to how theoretical models and research can inform each other, as well as support each other. As such, purposeful and logical integration of current research into the training may greatly benefit the trainees. To do so, it exposes trainees to the vital role of research, nourishes their interests in research, inspires them to be involved in research whenever appropriate and possible, and prepares them with a critical mind and some basic skills in using research to inform and enhance their professional development and practice.</p>
<p>The theory-practice connection certainly provides some very pertinent direction for skill learning and attainment. As a result, the skill learning becomes more purposeful and goal-oriented. Meanwhile, the trainees find themselves becoming more open, flexible, and situational in adopting a combination of strengths from a series of theoretical models while considering various career development and counselling situations.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1038416213486774"><title>Integrating experiential learning</title>
<p>Experiential learning is by and large a classroom-based training process that focuses more on the practical skill aspects that will deepen the understanding of the theoretical models. Moreover, it intends to help trainees use the theoretical knowledge as a philosophical foundation upon which practical skills will be obtained. In other words, it prepares trainees for the basic expertise they need to acquire when career counselling clients. Experiential learning can be classified into two general categories, although both are interactive in nature and interrelated to each other. The first category is case conceptualization that focuses on generating rationale for skill application (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1038416213486774">Brown, 2002a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1038416213486774">Niles &amp; Harris-Bowlsbey, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1038416213486774">Sharf, 2010</xref>). It stimulates trainees to explore the “why” question when considering the use of a helping method or a set of counselling techniques. Class interactions such as discussion, small working groups, debate, case presentation and analysis, and example demonstration are all useful exercises in this regard.</p>
<p>The second category is action-oriented experiential learning. This learning task focuses on the initial trial of hands-on techniques that will enable the trainees to work with real clients later in a clinical setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1038416213486774">Amundson, 2009</xref>). The micro counselling skills that have been learned in other basic counselling training courses should be reviewed and well integrated into this learning process, as many such skills will be also applicable in career counselling situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1038416213486774">Egan, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1038416213486774">Ivey &amp; Ivey, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1038416213486774">Okun, 2002</xref>). Yet, career counselling does have its uniqueness in terms of helping procedures and contents. For example, the effective use of a variety of qualitative and psychometric assessment methods can be an essential part of the career counselling process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1038416213486774">Amundson, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1038416213486774">Gysbers et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1038416213486774">Niles &amp; Harris-Bowlsbey, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1038416213486774">Zunker &amp; Osborn, 2002</xref>). Both categories of these assessment techniques can provide trainees with some much needed basic knowledge and skills that will make the career intervention process to work. Simulation exercise, role-play, assessment technique attainment, and specific probing skill training and rehearsal can be very useful activities that provide trainees with some initial technical frame and know-how for career counselling intervention. Although these interactive exercises are done in an instructional environment, they can serve well to equip the trainees with some basic intervention skills that are required when the training proceeds into a real clinical context later.</p>
<sec id="sec11-1038416213486774"><title>Facilitating clinical practice</title>
<p>Termed “training clinic” or “practicum,” on-site training is a required training component for most graduate programs in counselling psychology and counsellor education. The main purpose of such requirement seems apparent – counsellor trainees need to not only acquire the knowledge from books and the classroom learning but also apply the knowledge to the real helping context. Effective practice is the ultimate goal for all the training effort. The on-site training provides trainees with an opportunity of practicing what they have gained in their previous learning about theory and techniques. Three points may be particularly worth noting in terms of career counselling training.</p>
<p>First, every effort should be made to accommodate trainees to find more appropriate practicum and/or internship site. Trainees who intend to become career counsellors will find their clinical training most valuable and pertinent should they have more access to career counselling clients. These trainees are better placed in career counselling settings such as career centers in postsecondary institutions and vocational consulting and rehabilitation services in public and private settings. It is understandable that very often compromise needs to be made in choosing a clinic site, and a prospective career counsellor may have to work in a general counselling environment. In this case, the trainee can be assigned clients seeking career counselling whenever possible.</p>
<p>Second, trainees should also gain clinical experience in personal and social domains, as well as in career counselling practice. As worklife and personal life represent the two sides of the same coin, a capable career counsellor should be a competent generalist who can counsell clients on a range of other psychological issues in the personal and social domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1038416213486774">Chen, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1038416213486774">Krumboltz, 1993</xref>). Following this intention, more guidance and supervision may be needed to help the trainees deal with the intertwined life-career complexity that is often reflected in a helping situation, gaining and improving counselling skills in other related personal aspects in the clinical setting. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1038416213486774">Zunker (1994)</xref> points out, “comprehensive career-counselling procedures require a wide range of expertise in counselling theory: Career-counselling approaches include trait-and-factor, client-centered, psychodynamic, developmental, and behavioral. In addition, the well-prepared career counsellor has a working knowledge of personality, learning and decision theory, career and human development, and occupational information delivery systems” (p.16).</p>
<p>Third, sufficient supervision must be available to the trainees. While a supervision course associated with the clinical training and/or practicum is necessary, more attention should be drawn to the on-site supervision that will provide trainees with effective feedback on skill learning and enhancement in a timely manner. That is, immediate feedback focusing on the clinical encounter between the counsellor trainee and the client should be provided whenever possible. This kind of here-and-now feedback is factual, specific, and concrete in nature; it focuses on both conceptual and behavioral facets reflected during the counselling encounter. Thus, it should help the trainee better understand the counsellor-client relational dynamics as well as the micro-skill dimensions that are critical to the improvement of the counselling process, in general and the career counselling intervention, in particular. A point always worth mentioning is that the site supervisor(s) and faculty supervisor should be knowledgeable and skillful in both personal and career counselling areas in order to facilitate the trainee to growth through this process of clinical skill attainment.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1038416213486774" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>As a basic knowledge and skill competency aspect, career counselling deserves much attention in the counsellor education and training process. To achieve this goal, counsellor education programs and counsellor educators are encouraged to adopt a more constructive and comprehensive view toward the role of career component in the entire counsellor preparation. Such a positive attitude is of critical importance for it opens the avenue for more eclectic and holistic considerations with respect to career counselling training. Rather than looking at the career construct as a narrowly defined and isolated training component, counsellor educators should be able to integrate the component into counsellor education in a more coherent, inclusive, and extensive manner. Guided by a positive attitude toward career counselling, counsellor educators can become more creative and integral in teaching and training. This will lead to the improvement and refinement of the trainees’ overall learning experience of becoming a competent counsellor, in general and a knowledgeable and skillful career counsellor, in particular.</p>
<p>The general considerations proposed in the foregoing discussion are some of the ideas that counsellor education programs and counsellor educators may find as heuristic and useful in enhancing counsellor trainees’ learning experience and helping skills. While these considerations are particularly directed to the training aspect in the career area, many principles behind or derived from these considerations may be quite applicable to the general professional training and preparation of counsellors who will specialize in a diversity of areas in counselling and psychotherapy. As such, counsellor education programs can benefit as a whole from this endeavor of strengthening training and learning experience that focus on life career development and career counselling.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec13-1038416213486774"><title>Declaration of conflicting interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1038416213486774"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This article was supported in part by a Research Grant awarded to Prof. Charles P. Chen from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada. Standard Grant Program. Award No. 410-2009-2394.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amundson</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Active engagement: The being and doing of career counselling</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Richmond, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ergon Communications</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amundson</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris-Bowlsbey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niles</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Essential elements of career counseling: Processes and techniques counselling</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Education</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blustein</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>The psychology of working: A new perspective for counseling, career development, and public policy</source>, <publisher-loc>Mahway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blustein</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The role of work in psychological health and well-being: A conceptual, historical, and public policy perspective</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blustein</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A relational theory of working</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>J. E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pryor</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Shiftwork: A chaos theory of careers agenda for change in career counseling</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Career Development</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>D.</surname><given-names>Brown</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002a</year>) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002b</year>) <article-title>Introduction to theories of career development and choice: Origins, evolution, and current efforts</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Career counselling as life career integration</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Education and Training</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Negotiating risks in career development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Risk, education and culture</source>, <publisher-loc>Aldershot, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>190</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Career endeavour: Pursuing a cross-cultural life transition</source>, <publisher-loc>Aldershot, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>The sense of vocation: A study of career and life development</source>, <publisher-loc>Albany, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Career counseling: A narrative approach</source>, <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <source>Theory and practice of counseling and psychotherapy</source>, <edition>9th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole Cengage Learning</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crites</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <source>Career counseling: Models, methods, and materials</source>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawis</surname><given-names>R. V.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Person-environment-correspondence theory</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The skilled helper - A problem management and opportunity development approach to helping</source>, <edition>7th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottfredson</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Gottfredson’s theory of circumscription, compromise, and self-creation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenhaus</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>When work and family are allies: A theory of work-family enrichment</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gysbers</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heppner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Career counseling: Process, issues, and techniques</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn and Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Integrative life planning: Critical tasks for career development and changing life patterns</source>, <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Integrating work, family, and community through holistic life planning</article-title>. <source>The Career Development Quarterly</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niles</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Career guidance and counseling through the life span: Systematic approaches</source>, <edition>6th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Education Inc</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Making vocational choices: A theory of vocational personalities and work environments</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Odessa, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Assessment resources</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotchkiss</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borow</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Sociological perspective on work and career development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>B. A.</surname><given-names>Irving</given-names></name><name><surname>B.</surname><given-names>Malik</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Critical reflections on career education and guidance: Promoting social justice within a global economy</source>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>RoutledgeFalmer</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Career information, career counseling, and career development</source>, <edition>7th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Needham Heights, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn and Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Intentional interviewing and counseling - Facilitating client development in a multicultural society</source>, <edition>5th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Career choice and development from a sociological perspective</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalbfleisch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burwell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The advancement of career counsellor education in Canada</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Career Development</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalbfleisch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burwell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Report on the Canadian career counsellor education survey</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Career Development</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krumboltz</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Integrating career and personal counseling</article-title>. <source>The Career Development Quarterly</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krumboltz</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A learning theory for career counselors</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Niles</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Adult career development: Concepts, Issues and Practices</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Tulsa, OK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Career Development Association</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krumboltz</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Luck is no accident: Making the most of happenstance in your life and career</source>, <publisher-loc>Atascadero, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Impact Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lent</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Social cognitive career theory</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>J. G.</surname><given-names>Maree</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Shaping the story: A guide to facilitating narrative career counselling</source>, <publisher-loc>Pretoria, South Africa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Van Schaik Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller-Tiedeman</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The Lifecareer process theory: A healthier choice</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Connection between spirit and work in career development</source>, <publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Davies-Black</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller-Tiedeman</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Learning, practicing, and living the new careering</source>, <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Accelerated Development</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krumboltz</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Krumboltz’s learning theory of career choice and counseling</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niles</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris-Bowlsbey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <source>Career development interventions in the 21st century</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle river, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Education</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okun</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Effective helping - Interviewing and counseling techniques</source>, <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>S. H.</surname><given-names>Osipow</given-names></name><name><surname>W. B.</surname><given-names>Walsh</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Career counseling: Contemporary topics in vocational psychology</source>, <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1909</year>) <source>Choosing a vocation</source>, <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Career development and systems theory: A new relationship</source>, <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Career development and systems theory: Connecting theory and practice</source>, <publisher-loc>Rotterdam, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sense Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>The role of work in people’s lives: Applied career counseling and vocational psychology</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth/Thomson Learning</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pryor</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>J. E. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Applying chaos theory to careers: Attraction and attractors</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source> <volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Work in people’s lives: A location for counseling psychologists</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling Psychology</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rifkin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>The end of work: The decline of the global labour force and the down of the post-market era</source>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>G.P. Putnam’s Sons</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Career counseling and services - A cognitive information processing approach</source>, <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savickas</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Constructivist career counseling: Models and methods</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Neimeyer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neimeyer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Advances in personal construct psychology</source>, <publisher-loc>Greenwich, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savickas</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Career construction: A developmental theory of vocational behavior</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharf</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Applying career development theory to counseling</source>, <edition>5th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole Cengage Learning</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shein</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Work-family enrichment: A research of positive transfer</source>, <publisher-loc>Rotterdam, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sense Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slan-Jerusalim</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Work-family conflict and career development theories: A search for helping strategies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</source> <volume>87</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Super</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>) <source>The psychology of careers</source>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Super</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1990</year>) <article-title>A life-span, life space approach to career development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development: Applying contemporary theories to practice</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A contextualist explanation of career</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Career choice and development</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zunker</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Career counseling: Applied concepts of life planning</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zunker</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Career counseling: A holistic approach</source>, <edition>7th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1038416213486774"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zunker</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Using assessment results for career development</source>, <edition>6th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Pacific Grove, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>