<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WES</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwes</journal-id>
<journal-title>Work, Employment &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0950-0170</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1469-8722</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0950017012458019</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0950017012458019</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Mats Alvesson, Todd Bridgman and Hugh Willmott (eds), <italic>Oxford Handbook of Critical Management Studies</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>Randy</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0950017012458019">Ohio State University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1040</fpage>
<lpage>1042</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Alvesson</surname><given-names>Mats</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bridgman</surname><given-names>Todd</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willmott</surname><given-names>Hugh</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Oxford Handbook of Critical Management Studies</source> <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>, <price>£27.50</price> pbk, (ISBN: <isbn>9790199593811</isbn>), <page-count count="608"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">BSA Publications Ltd.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This handbook provides an overview of the theoretical foundations, major topical areas and subdisciplinary venues for the emerging area of critical management studies. The audience will be mainly graduate students and faculty in management related fields, including sociology and organizational studies. Assembling these various components in one source book is a significant service to the field and will provide a foundation for the continuing growth of critical management studies.</p>
<p>The organizational structure of the book is solid and well considered, as is the style of the Oxford Handbook series more generally. The four parts are, in order: theoretical foundations; key concerns; subdisciplinary venues; and future prospects. The book includes 28 chapters, averaging 20 pages each. This concise and fixed format is both a strength and possibly a limitation. Readers are spared what could have been some discourses lacking discipline, yet some of the chapters seem sparse – more of an abstract of available knowledge than a substantive essay.</p>
<p>The theoretical foundations of critical management studies are organized in four major areas: critical theory (Frankfurt School); critical realism; post-structuralism; and studies in the labour process. Enunciating these four theoretical pillars provides both novice students and more advanced readers with a clear vision of the theoretical assumptions, arguments and orientations of critical management studies and the intellectual traditions out of which these emerge. The focus of Michael Reed on unfolding sequences as core to critical realism is particularly useful and well developed. Similarly, Campbell Jones’s outline of post-structuralism in terms of its focus on language, subjectivity and identity and anti-essentialism is lucid and useful. Finally, the insights of Paul Thompson on studies of the labour process as <italic>inherently</italic> critical and those of Damian O’Doherty on the issues of volatility and disorder in the labour process are quite compelling.</p>
<p>The core of the book is the 12 chapters on topics and issues, including power, identity, globalization, culture, discourse, ethics, history, gender and worker empowerment. David Knights’s topic of power is arguably the most foundational of these concerns. Perhaps the most useful stand-alone chapter is the one by Subhabrata Banerjee, Chris Carter and Stewart Clegg on globalization. This chapter provides a very systematic and inclusive model of the many interfaces between organizational and management studies and globalization, including a focus on both financial systems and corporate governance systems.</p>
<p>The six chapters on some of the less well recognized academic subdisciplines in which critical management studies has grown are a unique offering of the book. These subdisciplinary specialities include marketing, information systems, strategic management (long term planning), communication, human resource management and accounting. Readers of all levels will be informed by the discussions of how critical management studies have developed in unique directions in each of these settings. Each of these subdisciplinary settings has significant potential contributions to critical management studies because of the unique facet of management activities that it considers. In the spirit of critical studies, perhaps much more could have been attempted in at least two of these discussions. For instance, the chapter on information systems could have addressed the development of management information systems and global security systems and the profound implications of these information systems for the heightened surveillance of employees by corporations as well as the surveillance activities by authoritarian states of their own citizens. Similarly, the chapter on accounting did not significantly address the role of accounting practices and malpractices in the world financial collapse (consider here Enron’s Arthur Andersen Accounting firm). These are clearly important missed opportunities for a handbook on critical management studies.</p>
<p>The concluding chapters outline overarching themes and important topics for future work, such as challenging hierarchy and critical management education, as well as providing critical reflections on the contributions and limitations of the preceding essays in the book. The chapter by Steven Frenkel is particularly frank, considered and balanced in this regard and addresses the too frequent penchant of critical management studies scholars for writing about critical management studies in preference to actually providing a critical appraisal of management and organizations.</p>
<p>Following up on some of the concerns enunciated in these final chapters, this reviewer concurs that there is much potential in critical management studies and much work yet to be done. Some of the chapters are heir to a writing style that stresses writing about how to do critical analysis and the epistemological foundations and assumptions behind it rather than the more pressing work of actually doing critical analysis of management and organizations. I am eager to continue to read in this field in anticipation of more exemplars of applying critical analysis to important current topics, such as the global financial crisis and the issue of electronic surveillance mentioned above.</p>
<p>In short, a solid book and a good foundation for a field with great potential that is only beginning to be realized through application to concrete topics.</p>
</body>
</article>