<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spijl</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Low Extrem Wounds</journal-id>
<journal-title>The International Journal of Lower Extremity Wounds</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1534-7346</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6941</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1534734612457033</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1534734612457033</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Guest Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Wound Care in China</article-title>
<subtitle>From Repair to Regeneration</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Xiaobing</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534734612457033">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1534734612457033">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1534734612457033"><label>1</label>College of Life Sciences, Chinese PLA General Hospital, Beijing, Peoples’ Republic of China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1534734612457033"><label>2</label>First Affiliated Hospital, PLA General Hospital, Beijing, Peoples’ Republic of China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1534734612457033">Xiaobing Fu, The College of Life Sciences, Chinese PLA General Hospital, 28 Fu Xing Road, Beijing 100853, Peoples’ Republic of China Email: <email>fuxiaobing@vip.sina.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue on Wound Healing and Tissue Repair in China</issue-title>
<fpage>143</fpage>
<lpage>145</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Wounds in China are severe problems, and China has a huge demand for tissue repair and regeneration. In the past decades, there has been significant development in genetics, auxology, stem cell biology, and tissue engineering, which have been further translated into and integrated with clinical treatment of tissue injury. In China, this synergy has contoured the discipline of tissue repair and regeneration to be one of the best and fastest performing disciplines with regard to bench-to-bed connection and translation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>wound</kwd>
<kwd>repair</kwd>
<kwd>regeneration</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Wounds in China are severe problems, and China has a huge demand for tissue repair and regeneration. It is partly due to her huge population of more than 1.37 billion in 2010,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1534734612457033">1</xref></sup> which implies a large patient base for traumatic diseases. Another reason is the rapid economic growth and modernization, which is accompanied with numerous injuries and accidents during its course. According to the health statistics of 2010,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1534734612457033">2</xref></sup> among the top 10 causes for hospitalization in urban areas, injuries, toxicity, and other external factors account for 9.13%, lying at the third place (only after respiratory diseases at 12.41% and digestive diseases at 10.43%). In county-level hospitals, those 3 causes account for 14.07%, ranking it second (only following respiratory diseases at 16.43%). If we focus on chronic skin wounds, it is found that there is a great demand for their care, including diabetic foot, venous ulcers, pressure ulcers, and trauma ulcers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1534734612457033">3</xref></sup> Considering other wound or tissue pathologies including hereditary, metabolic, and chronic diseases, the number of patients who need to be treated with repair and regeneration technology is estimated to be around 100 million person-time per year.</p>
<p>In China, and even worldwide, tissue repair and regeneration is a time-honored medical topic but with modern implication. As early as in Han Dynasty of China, <italic>rehmanniae</italic> was widely used to treat inner bleeding and connect bone fracture. Tissue repair medicines or proved recipes were also recorded in classical traditional Chinese medicine literatures such <italic>Ben Cao Shi Yi</italic> (<italic>Supplement to Compendium of Materia Medica</italic>), <italic>Shennong Ben Cao Jing</italic> (<italic>Shennong’s Compendium of Materia Medica</italic>), and <italic>Zhi Bai Bing Fang</italic> (<italic>A Hundred Recipes for Common Diseases</italic>). In the past 20 years, there has been significant development in genetics, auxology, stem cell biology, and tissue engineering, which have been further translated into and integrated with clinical treatment of tissue injury. In China, this synergy has contoured the discipline of tissue repair and regeneration to be one of the best and fastest performing disciplines with regard to bench-to-bed connection and translation. Some basic research findings that are smoothly on the way of translation will definitely become the stars in the future.</p>
<p>Among all the areas applying theories and technologies of tissue repair and regeneration in China, 3 domains record the fastest development and gain general attention: stem cell biology, organ constitution and replication, basic research and product designing in tissue engineering research and trauma treatment. For example, Chinese academics have made important breakthroughs in the following basic research areas: replicating tetraploid complementation competent iPS mice by using pluripotent stem cells and iPS technology, obtaining functioning organ by heterogenic cell gomphosis or transdifferentiation, preparation of iPS large animal model, and establishment of induced differentiation system to differentiate somatic cells to multiple tissues.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1534734612457033">4</xref></sup> Meanwhile, somatic stem cells combined with induced differentiation technology has been demonstrated to be able to regenerate skin sweat glands after severe burns or trauma and blood vessels in diabetic or other vascular diseases of the lower limb.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1534734612457033">5</xref></sup> Some subjects have presented remarkable improvements in the 3-year follow-up. As an important approach of tissue regeneration, tissue engineering is another area in which China has made substantial progress. Apart from the 3 major elements including seed cell, matrix, and regulatory factors, other advancement of tissue engineering have given birth to more innovative technologies to constitute bones, cartilages, nerves, blood vessels, and tendons. Some of them have already been used clinically and have shown significant repair and regeneration benefits. For instance, tissue engineering acellular nerves have proved to be effective in repairing 8-cm-long and 5-mm-thick sciatic nerves, and chondrocytes injected to repair cartilage defect in weight-bearing areas have achieved great outcome in more than 300 clinical cases. How to realize synchronized regeneration of various tissues in wound is a pivotal research area. Some academics are exploring the methods to prevent overformation of scar tissue in wound when technically inducing skin stem cells to differentiate directly into neurons, osteocytes, adipocytes, and so on, without going through the iPS phase. Preliminary advancements in this area include “dermal template theory,” which explores the way to prevent scar formation, and “acclimated induction” methods, which induce multiple tissue regeneration in wound.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1534734612457033">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>We are active in keeping updated with the global trend while trying to make ourselves special and outstanding by agile translation from basic research to clinical application in all areas of tissue repair and regeneration. However, novelty of basic research and translation efficiency still remain challenges to us. These areas deserve our focus and efforts. Based on the great demand for repair and regeneration, we established some wound care centers especially for diabetic foot and other complicated skin wounds in Shanghai, Beijing, and other cities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1534734612457033">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>A strategy for preventing chronic wounds has become a key focal area in China. Chinese Tissue Repair Society (CTRS) has traditionally concentrated on developing technology for chronic wound repair and treatment and recently on educating health care professionals about chronic wound care. In 2010, the CTRS developed the National Chronic Wound Care Training Program for Doctors and Nurses Dealing with Patients with Diabetic Mellitus This project aims to improve the clinical skills and ability of physicians and nurses to manage chronic wounds, especially diabetic foot ulcers (DFUs). The project has an experienced expert advisory panel. It also developed a standard textbook, <italic>Management of the Diabetic Foot and Related Chronic Wounds</italic>. The book contains basic knowledge of DFUs, as well as the clinical pathway, new research, advanced wound-healing knowledge, and new technology. A national <italic>Guideline for Chronic Wound Diagnosis and Treatment</italic> was published as a standard treatment approach for training program participants.</p>
<p>Relevant government bodies and the academic circle pay close attention and give great assistance to the development of regenerative medicine. In <italic>Science &amp; Technology on Public Health in China: A Roadmap to 2050</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1534734612457033">Figure 1</xref>), published by Chinese Academy of Sciences, and <italic>Study on Medium- and Long-Term Development Strategy of Engineering Technology in China</italic>, published by Chinese Academy of Engineering, regenerative medicine has been listed as a key research direction. Stem cell technology has been categorized as a class III medical technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1534734612457033">7</xref></sup> in <italic>Management Guidelines for Therapeutic Tissue Transplantation Technology by Tissue Engineering (Trial)</italic>, published by the Ministry of Health. In addition, 2 editions of Xiangshan Science Conference in 2005 and 2010 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1534734612457033">Figure 2</xref>) organized by the academic circle had thorough discussion on the concept, scope, key areas to make breakthrough, and key scientific issues to be solved in the area of regenerative medicine. These actions have laid a great foundation and provided the assurance to the future of regenerative medicine in China.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1534734612457033">8</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig1-1534734612457033" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p><italic>Science &amp; Technology on Population Health in China: A Roadmap to 2050</italic>, published by Chinese Academy of Sciences, listing regenerative medicine as a key development direction</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534734612457033-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-1534734612457033" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Xiang-shan Science Conferences: regenerative medicine significantly promoted the development of regenerative medicine</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534734612457033-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In conclusion, regenerative medicine in China is expected to make substantial progress and breakthrough in the following areas: induced differentiation of stem cells and synchronized repair and regeneration of multiple injured tissues, constitution of large organ by tissue engineering, and large-scale clinical application of tissue engineering products. These progresses will be supported by the improvement of relative laws and regulations and establishment of scaled research sites for translation medicine.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work was supported in part by the National Basic Science and Development Programme (973 Programme, 2012CB518105) and a grant from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81121004).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1534734612457033">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>National Bureau of Statistics of China</collab>. <article-title>Communiqué of the National Bureau of Statistics of People’s Republic of China on major figures of the 2010 Population Census (No. 1)</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stats.gov.cn/english/newsandcomingevents/t20110428_402722244.htm">http://www.stats.gov.cn/english/newsandcomingevents/t20110428_402722244.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed July 19, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1534734612457033">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>China Health Statistics Yearbook</collab>. <year>2010</year> <article-title>China Statistics Press</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stats.gov.cn/tjsj/ndsj/2010/indexeh.htm">http://www.stats.gov.cn/tjsj/ndsj/2010/indexeh.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed July 19, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1534734612457033">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of chronic cutaneous wounds in China</article-title>. <source>Wound Rep Regen</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1534734612457033">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Qi Zhou</collab>. <article-title>Generation and evaluation of pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. In: <source>Regenerative Medicine in China. A Sponsored Supplement to Science</source>. <year>2012</year>:<fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1534734612457033">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regenerative medicine research in China: demands and practices</article-title>. In: <source>Regenerative Medicine in China. A Sponsored Supplement to Science</source>. <year>2012</year>:<fpage>3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1534734612457033">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Establishing a comprehensive wound repair and tissue regeneration center: a de novo model</article-title>. In: <source>Regenerative Medicine in China. A Sponsored Supplement to Science</source>. <year>2012</year>:<fpage>66</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1534734612457033">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Ministry of Health of China</collab>. <article-title>Tissue-engineered tissue transplantation therapy practice (trial)</article-title>. <comment>(Health Office of Medical Affairs [2009] No. 199 issued). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.moh.gov.cn/publicfiles/business/htmlfiles/mohbgt/s10639/200911/44629.htm">http://www.moh.gov.cn/publicfiles/business/htmlfiles/mohbgt/s10639/200911/44629.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed July 19, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1534734612457033">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Regenerative Medicine: From Basic to Clinic Research</source>. <edition>1st ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Shanghai, China</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Shanghai Scientific and Technical Publishers</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>