<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MCS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmcs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Media, Culture &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0163-4437</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-3675</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0163443713485492</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0163443713485492</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Collaboratively constructed contradictory accounts: online organizational narratives</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Tunby Gulbrandsen</surname><given-names>Ib</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nørholm Just</surname><given-names>Sine</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0163443713485492">Copenhagen Business School, Denmark</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0163443713485492">Ib Tunby Gulbrandsen, Copenhagen Business School, Kilevej 14A, Frederiksberg, 2300, Denmark. Email: <email>itg.ioa@cbs.dk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>565</fpage>
<lpage>585</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Based on a mixed-method case study of online communication about the Danish pharmaceutical company Novo Nordisk, this article argues that online communication plays out as a centrifugal narration process with centripetal consequences. Through a content analysis of communication about Novo Nordisk, three dominant online meaning constructions that present themselves as narratives are identified and their convergence into one overarching meta-narrative is identified. The meta-narrative of Novo Nordisk as the ruthlessly profit-seeking socially responsible heavenly work place is made up of the three interrelated, yet disparate tales about Novo Nordisk as (1) a socially responsible organization, engaged in society at large; (2) an organization primarily concerned with fulfilling its own objectives – profit maximization; and (3) a great and employee-centred workplace. The article then discusses the theoretical and methodological implications of the empirical findings. It is argued that although the findings are not in themselves surprising, they adequately reflect that online meaning formation is, indeed, a collaborative process in which centrifugal forces have centripetal consequences. Furthermore, the findings suggest that the chosen mixed-method case study successfully navigates the dilemma of studying online collaborative processes through the traces they leave behind.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>centripetal/centrifugal</kwd>
<kwd>mixed method</kwd>
<kwd>narratives</kwd>
<kwd>new media</kwd>
<kwd>online communication</kwd>
<kwd>organization</kwd>
<kwd>process</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Is the internet the campfire of McLuhan’s global village where we all meet to share and create our common story? Or does the rise of online communication platforms and social networks bear witness to the Lyotardian death of grand narratives? That is, should we understand current technological and communicative developments as centripetal or centrifugal forces? This question forms an important nodal point of the (academic) debate concerning the conceptualization of communication on the internet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0163443713485492">Dahlgren, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0163443713485492">Ess, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0163443713485492">Poster, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0163443713485492">Sagawa, 1997</xref>). While the two options are often perceived as mutually exclusive, we wish to re-orient the discussion by arguing that centrifugal forces may have centripetal consequences. We suggest that the myriad of ‘prosumed’ online micro-narratives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0163443713485492">Beck, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0163443713485492">Giddens and Pierson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0163443713485492">Scammell, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0163443713485492">Toffler, 1980</xref>) may, when studied independently of each other, point to the fragmentation of online meaning formation, but when emphasis is put on the interrelations between the many different stories, the contours of collaboratively constructed grand narratives appear.</p>
<p>Taking our cue from the ‘narrative turn’ in organization studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0163443713485492">Fenton and Langley, 2011</xref>) we assume that since humans use narratives to make sense of themselves and their surroundings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0163443713485492">Cronen et al., 1982</xref>), so do organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0163443713485492">Barry and Elmes, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0163443713485492">Boje, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0163443713485492">Czarniawska, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0163443713485492">Humphreys and Brown, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0163443713485492">Rhodes and Brown, 2005</xref>). The aim of this article is therefore to explore how organizational narratives play out online. We do so through a case study of online communication about Novo Nordisk, a market leader in diabetes care. The aim of the study is not to question or ‘prove’ that online narratives are collaborative, although we shall briefly introduce the premises that support this claim (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen and Just, 2011</xref>). Instead, we start from this theoretical assumption and attempt to come to terms with its empirical manifestations.</p>
<p>We begin the article with the methodological issue of how online collaboration can be studied as a process concerned with producing narratives about organizations. Next, we present the case study of the narratives about Novo Nordisk that are produced on selected online platforms. We then present the empirical findings, highlighting how three collaboratively constructed contradictory narratives become linked in and productive of a meta-narrative about Novo Nordisk. In the last part of the article, we reflect critically on the study and its possible implications for the field of online communication. First, we will argue that regardless of their internal contradictions, micro-narratives come to construct meta-narratives about the object with which they are concerned. And, second, we ‘turn on ourselves’, asking whether the act of identifying micro- and meta-narratives is not, in fact, a violation of the golden rule that processes cannot be studied outside the process. Are we not, when claiming that the process has meta-narrative ‘products’, reducing the complex collaborative dynamics to a question of cause and effect?</p>
<sec id="section1-0163443713485492">
<title>Studying online collaborative communication</title>
<p>The study of online collaboration, as we propose to undertake it, is undergirded by three premises:</p>
<list id="list1-0163443713485492" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Online communication is a two-way mass communicative process in which ‘the one interacts directly with the few, and indirectly with the many’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen and Just, 2011</xref>). This premise is grounded in the intertwinement of socio-technical affordances and social practices of online communication which allow for collaborative meaning formation; the former by providing opportunities for the sharing and co-production of meaning, the latter by utilizing or altering these opportunities through both direct action (e.g. posting comments) and indirect action (e.g. formulating and enforcing communication regulations).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The process of online communication is driven by a willingness to participate in and an ability to invite collaboration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen and Just, 2011</xref>). This premise springs from the idea that ‘any concrete utterance is a link in the chain of speech communication of a particular sphere’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0163443713485492">Bakhtin, 1986</xref>: 91). Generally speaking, meaning does not lie comfortably within any single utterance, but arises in and through the collaborative process of weaving utterances together. And, in the more specific context of online communication, meaning is created through the process of digital bricolage; by assembling separate materials and information at hand, by re-using existing artefacts and incorporating independent bits and pieces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0163443713485492">Hartley, 1996</xref>: 22; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0163443713485492">Deuze, 2006</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Finally, the co-production of meaning, the collaborative construction of digital bricolages, happens through and as narration processes. This premise is based upon the fundamental insight that people make and present meaning through narratives; or, as Fisher puts it: ‘all forms of human communication can be seen fundamentally as stories, as interpretations of aspects of the world occurring in time and shaped by history, culture and character’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0163443713485492">1989</xref>: 57; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0163443713485492">Fisher, 1985</xref>). Organizational activities can also be anticipated prospectively and understood retrospectively as narratives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0163443713485492">Cooren, 2001</xref>: 181), because ‘organizations literally are the narratives that people concoct, share, embellish, dispute and retell in ways which maintain and objectify reality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0163443713485492">Humphreys and Brown, 2002</xref>: 405). This becomes even more apparent in the case of online communication where organizations cannot be understood as individualist and monological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0163443713485492">Gergen, 2010</xref>), but rather as throwaway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0163443713485492">March, 1995</xref>), encounter-based (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0163443713485492">Gutek, 1995</xref>), communitarian and interdependent constructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0163443713485492">Barry and Elmes, 1997</xref>). As such, narratives become constitutive of organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0163443713485492">Fairhurst and Putnam, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0163443713485492">Taylor and Van Every, 2000</xref>). And given that the constitutive narratives are collaboratively constructed by anyone with a vested interest in the organization, both insiders and outsiders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0163443713485492">Gioia et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0163443713485492">Hatch and Schultz, 1997</xref>), they are also bound to be multiple and divergent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0163443713485492">Laine and Vaara, 2007</xref>). The existence of competing narratives, however, does not preclude the construction of an overarching meta-narrative in which the different narratives both coalesce and become aware of themselves and each other, implicitly or explicitly addressing their participation in the collaborative process of narrating the organization as such (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0163443713485492">Eriksson and Kovalainen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0163443713485492">Fludernik, 1996</xref>). To the contrary, and as we will investigate in this article, inconsistencies and antagonisms between micro-narratives may turn out to be the very stuff meta-narratives are made of.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0163443713485492">
<title>Renewed commitment to process</title>
<p>The main methodological implication of these premises is a renewed commitment to the study of communication/narration as process – and not to be lured into simplifying the process in terms of contributors (focusing only on specific actors or sites) or straightening it out in terms of contributions (focusing only on specific answers and responses). It is widely recognized that studying process <italic>as</italic> process is not an easy task (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0163443713485492">Dawson, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0163443713485492">Nayak, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0163443713485492">Smith, 1972</xref>), and we can only begin to undertake it by openly admitting the researcher’s role as a participant in the process. What one studies is an assemblage or interpretation of the process; it is ‘a construct, a snapshot of a collaborative process’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen and Just, 2011</xref>: 1105). However, the quality of this snapshot – here, measured in terms of its ability to capture the ‘uncapturable’, to fixate without distorting – may be ensured by mixing qualitative and quantitative data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0163443713485492">Hausman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0163443713485492">Miller et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>In making this claim we are inspired by Norbert Elias’ work on figuration and the ‘<italic>longue durée</italic>’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0163443713485492">Elias, 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0163443713485492">1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0163443713485492">1994</xref>). Elias argues that, from the moment we are born, we enter into a complex figuration of social interdependencies that develop gradually over time. There is no simple relation between ‘action’ and ‘outcome’, or ‘strategy’ and ‘effect’; instead, all actions must be understood as complex interdependencies, and not by ‘stepping out’ of them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0163443713485492">Elias, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0163443713485492">Newton, 1999</xref>). Applying this insight to online communication means that we need to follow the shifting figurations of the communication process rather than search for ‘truth’ in single utterances, particular sites or specific moments. It becomes important to view online meaning formation in the ‘<italic>longue durée</italic>’.</p>
<p>The snapshot, then, if we are to stay with the photographic metaphor, must be taken with a wide angle and long exposure time. It does, however, need a focus, and we propose to highlight what the collaboration is about rather than a particular site for or actor in the collaborative process. A similar focus has been promoted within science and technology studies where network analyses or ‘maps’ of the development of issues and knowledge controversies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0163443713485492">Horst, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0163443713485492">Marres, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0163443713485492">Whatmore, 2009</xref>) have greatly extended our understanding of such processes. We will apply a similar network analytic approach to online organizational narratives, but develop a distinct method for doing so. Although there are tools for studying online networks, for instance using the issue crawler software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0163443713485492">Marres and Rogers, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0163443713485492">Rogers, 2010</xref>), these tend to focus on actual links between websites. We are interested in the collaboration in a less material sense, asking how narratives arise through invitation and participation on and across different platforms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0163443713485492">
<title>The Novo Nordisk case study</title>
<p>Following these methodological guidelines, we have conducted a mixed-method single case study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0163443713485492">Denzin and Lincoln, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0163443713485492">Flyvbjerg, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0163443713485492">Johnson and Onwuegbuzie, 2004</xref>) of online communication about the Danish pharmaceutical company Novo Nordisk. We focus on how online meaning formation about this organization plays out on selected communication platforms, as this may give us an empirical understanding of the ‘realities’ of online communication. Thus, we seek to answer the following two research questions:</p>
<list id="list2-0163443713485492" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>RQ1: What organizational narratives are collaboratively constructed about the Danish pharmaceutical company Novo Nordisk across selected online communication platforms?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>RQ2: What – if any – overarching online organizational meta-narrative emerges from the combined collaborations?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The first research question deals with the centrifugal forces of online communication, while the latter is about their (possible) centripetal consequences.</p>
<sec id="section4-0163443713485492">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>In order to answer the research questions, a quantitative sample of all communication about Novo Nordisk on four platforms was collected. The chosen platforms are:</p>
<list id="list3-0163443713485492" list-type="order">
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.facebook.com">www.facebook.com</ext-link> (a social networking site)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com">www.youtube.com</ext-link> (a video sharing site)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com">www.flickr.com</ext-link> (a picture sharing site)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wikipedia.com">www.wikipedia.com</ext-link> (an information gathering site)</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The selection of the platforms reflects the wish to study a broad spectrum of sites providing the organization and its stakeholders with different opportunities. From the possibility to create a company profile mediated by the organization (e.g. on Facebook) to more open platforms (e.g. Wikipedia) and platforms that predominantly communicate through visuals (e.g. YouTube and Flickr). Finally it was important to us to include only publicly accessible platforms, as this study is concerned with public meaning creation and not closed online communities.</p>
<p>The sample, collected in the third quarter of 2011, covers all communication about the organization on these platforms from the fourth quarter of 2004 to the second quarter of 2011. The total number of communicative contributions included in the sample is 1770 communicative contributions (100% of the total sample). Of this Facebook accounts for 843 contributions (47.6% of the total), YouTube for 158 (8.9%), Flickr for 521 (29.4%), and Wikipedia for 248 (14%). Since a large portion of online communication is composed of ‘likes’ and ‘dislikes’ and since all text can be edited, the sample was broken into major and minor contributions. This was done during the data collection in order to give a more nuanced depiction of the collaborative process. When all minor contributions (likes, dislikes, spelling corrections, etc.) were discounted, the number of contributions was 987. Of this Facebook accounts for 194 contributions (19.7% of the total), YouTube for 139 (14.1%), Flickr for 518 (52.5%) and Wikipedia for 136 (13.8%) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0163443713485492">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0163443713485492" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Contributions – platforms, major and minor.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0163443713485492" xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Source</th>
<th align="left">No. of contributions</th>
<th align="left">Percentage of total</th>
<th align="left">No. of major contributions</th>
<th align="left">Percentage only major</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Facebook</td>
<td>843</td>
<td>47.6</td>
<td>194</td>
<td>19.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>YouTube</td>
<td>158</td>
<td>8.9</td>
<td>139</td>
<td>14.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Flickr</td>
<td>521</td>
<td>29.4</td>
<td>518</td>
<td>52.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wikipedia</td>
<td>248</td>
<td>14.0</td>
<td>136</td>
<td>13.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Total</bold></td>
<td><bold>1770</bold></td>
<td><bold>100.0</bold></td>
<td><bold>987</bold></td>
<td><bold>100.0</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0163443713485492" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Contributors (major contributions).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0163443713485492" xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Source</th>
<th align="left">Number of contributions</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Organization</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Stakeholder</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Facebook</td>
<td>194</td>
<td>19.7</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>68.4</td>
<td>155</td>
<td>16.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>YouTube</td>
<td>139</td>
<td>14.1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>10.5</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>14.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Flickr</td>
<td>518</td>
<td>52.5</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>21.1</td>
<td>506</td>
<td>54.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wikipedia</td>
<td>136</td>
<td>13.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td>136</td>
<td>14.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Total</bold></td>
<td><bold>987</bold></td>
<td><bold>100.0</bold></td>
<td><bold>57</bold></td>
<td><bold>5.8</bold></td>
<td><bold>930</bold></td>
<td><bold>94.2</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0163443713485492">
<title>Measurement and coding</title>
<p>A systematic coding scheme was established with inspiration from previous literature on content analysis of online communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0163443713485492">Cho and Huh, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0163443713485492">McMillan, 2000</xref>). During the coding four measures were applied: (1) contributor, (2) type of contribution, (3) major/minor contribution and (4) contribution sentiment.</p>
<p>A ‘Contributor’ was defined as the source of the utterance and coded as (a) Organization and (b) Stakeholder. In the instances where the communicator was clearly identifiable as the organization (e.g. when using the onscreen name ‘Novo Nordisk’ on the company-controlled Facebook page) the contribution was coded as ‘Organization’, while ‘Stakeholder’ was used in the instances where the communicator was identifiable as being distinct from the organization, hence representing all other identified actors participating in the process. Though a more nuanced breakdown of the different stakeholders might have been desirable, this was not possible, nor was it the aim of the study. Online communication platforms like Facebook, Wikipedia and YouTube are often constructed in ways that reduce social clues and create the possibility of anonymity or alternative selves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0163443713485492">Carnevale and Probst, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0163443713485492">McKenna and Bragh, 2000</xref>). In most instances, it is therefore impossible to distinguish the different stakeholders from each other. This arguably creates a freer space for contributions, as the contributors do not have to disclose their identities, but at the same time it becomes difficult to identify the contributors. This ‘good-bad’ quality of online communication is hard to ignore or circumvent. And any attempt to circumvent it would, in our opinion, be extremely speculative as this would entail a close reading of each individual post, followed by a more or less qualified guess regarding what kind of stakeholder the contributor might be. In other words, the stakeholder group, as we use it in the coding, contains anyone with a vested interest in the organization, for example (1) patients with diabetes, (2) general practitioners (providing patient care and prescribing drugs), (3) investors and (4) shareholders, (5) patient organizations, (6) governments, (7) families (of those affected by diabetes), (8) employees and (9) the general public.</p>
<p>As a further note on our coding of the contributors, it is important to keep in mind that ‘identity’ here only refers to online identity, and not the contributors’ offline identity. The offline identity of the contributors is of no interest in this study, as it is solely the online collaborative meaning creation that is investigated.</p>
<p>‘Type of contribution’ was defined as (a) Text, (b) Video, (c) Picture and (d) Like/Dislike. In the cases where the contribution was a combination of these, an individual assessment was made in order to clarify which was the dominant. ‘Major/minor contribution’ was coded as (a) Major or (b) Minor. A minor contribution was defined as using the like/dislike option or correcting mistakes in hyperlink addresses or text. A major contribution was typically an original post or comment, but also an edit or any other contribution that went beyond those identified as minor. Finally, the measurement ‘Contribution sentiment’ was coded as (a) Positive, (b) Negative and (c) Neutral. Positive was defined as contributions that expressed support for or goodwill towards the organization. Negative was defined as expressions of unflattering sentiments about or animosity towards the organization. Neutral was used in instances where neither positive nor negative sentiments could be traced in the contribution.</p>
<p>In addition, all major contributions were manually marked and systematized by the coder according to the following content categories: (1) socially responsible, (2) profit seeker, (3) employee and (4) product information. This manual coding served as the basis for the qualitative analysis that is at the centre of the ensuing presentation of our findings and for which the quantitative data provide backing.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0163443713485492">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>The first step in answering our research questions was to determine what elements the process was made up of, asking: what contributors and what kinds of contributions does the narrative co-production consist of?</p>
<p>The data collected reveal that collaboration is dominated by the stakeholder group. Of all major contributions they account for 94.2%. While it could be argued that the organization might participate under different and non-revealing online identities, the large percentage of stakeholders active in the collaboration still confirms that the organization and the stakeholders interact.</p>
<p>With regard to what kinds of contributions are made, the quantitative analysis reveals that of the 1770 contributions included in the investigation, 37.9% were what we call ‘minor contributions’ (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0163443713485492">Table 3</xref>). This means that over one-third of the contributors used the options of ‘like’ and ‘dislike’ rather than posting or re-posting material. This is significant because it suggests that a dominant trait of the collaborative process is the act of acknowledging others’ communicative contributions. It confirms the notion presented above that in online communication the one interacts directly with the few, and indirectly with the many (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen and Just, 2011</xref>). In addition, it points to the process as being more than textually driven, underscoring the argument for not focusing on specific utterances (often seen as text) but on the interaction, since the collaboration also takes place in-between the utterances, here visible in the act of liking or disliking others’ utterances.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0163443713485492" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Type of contribution.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0163443713485492" xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Total contributions</th>
<th align="left">% of total</th>
<th align="left">Major contributions</th>
<th align="left">% of major cont.</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Text</td>
<td>478</td>
<td>27.0</td>
<td>374</td>
<td>37.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Video</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>8.1</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>14.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Picture</td>
<td>478</td>
<td>27.0</td>
<td>470</td>
<td>47.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Like/dislike</td>
<td>670</td>
<td>37.9</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>1770</td>
<td>100.0</td>
<td>987</td>
<td>100.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The importance of looking beyond the textual level also becomes apparent when all minor contributions are removed from the sample. The quantitative analysis shows that there are more pictorial (47.6%) than textual (37.9%) contributions (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0163443713485492">Table 3</xref>). And if one adds the video contributions (14.5% of all major contributions) to the pictorial contributions under a ‘visual contributions’ heading, over half of the online organizational narrative about Novo Nordisk is constructed through visual means (which in this case does not refer to design or website architecture, but to the form of the specific contribution). This is significant, since written or transcribed text is often given more emphasis and weight in organizational narrative studies, but, as the data show, that might be an inadequate approach to online narration. As a prerequisite for answering RQ1, then, we have established that the collaboration is dominated by Novo Nordisk’s stakeholders, it is mostly made up by minor contributions and in the major contributions visual and textual contributions are equally represented.</p>
<p>But what organizational narratives are these contributors collaboratively constructing with these different types of contributions about the Danish pharmaceutical company Novo Nordisk across the selected online communication platforms? Based on the initial thematic coding, the qualitative analysis of the sample suggests that three dominant narratives emerge from the online collaboration of the organization and its stakeholders: (a) Novo Nordisk as socially responsible, (b) Novo Nordisk as profit seeker and (c) Novo Nordisk as employee heaven. The three narratives were identified by looking at the most recurrent and thematically related meaning formations about the organization as these developed over time and across the platforms included in the investigation. Or put differently, the most often repeated and highly intertextual opinions/stories/constructions of who and what Novo Nordisk is. In the following these three narratives will be presented with examples from the different platforms they are constructed on. It should be noted that all spelling errors in the contributions cited here are kept as in the original.</p>
<sec id="section7-0163443713485492">
<title>Novo Nordisk as socially responsible</title>
<p>The narrative about Novo Nordisk as socially responsible is best exemplified by the repeated contributions about the organization’s ties to the World Diabetes Day (WDD), although it is also constructed in and through contributions about other specific actions and events. The WDD is an annual awareness day/campaign for diabetes held on 14 November. It was introduced in 1991 by the International Diabetes Federation and the World Health Organization – and, according to a contribution on Wikipedia, this was made possible by the actions of Novo Nordisk.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0163443713485492" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>On 22 September 2009 ‘167.206.144.30’ writes:<disp-quote>
<p>Novo Nordisk have sponsored the International Diabetes Federation’s Unite for Diabetes campaign — one of many campaigns that helped to successfully pass UN Resolution 61/225, making November 14 World Diabetes Day.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Not only does this post connect the organization with the Diabetes Day, it also points to the organization’s role in passing a United Nations (UN) resolution that put diabetes on the UN agenda. For a company that is dependent on people having diabetes (selling them drugs is what Novo Nordisk is all about), raising awareness about the disease with the intention of reducing the number of people affected (e.g. due to malnutrition or lack of exercise) is a strong marker of commitment to being socially responsible.</p>
<p>This ‘socially responsible’ narrative is repeated throughout the period of time that we studied and on several of the platforms included in the investigation. One example is a post made on Flickr, a year after the quoted Wikipedia entry (25 October 2010):</p>
<p>The contributor, ‘international diabetes federation’, not only participates in the collaborative meaning formation about Novo Nordisk’s ties to WDD, but seeing that the contributor is one of the main figures behind the day, it also endorses Novo Nordisk’s engagement and participation in WDD. The picture shows the organization’s headquarters bathed in blue light, an act organizations and public entities are encouraged to undertake in order to show support for the day and the cause (notable examples of buildings/monuments that have been bathed in blue light are the Sphinx in Egypt, the Empire State Building in New York and the Acropolis in Athens). This picture is only one of many tagged ‘Novo Nordisk’ and showing the organization’s participation in WWD, suggesting a larger trend of contributions concerned with visual participation in the narration about Novo Nordisk as a socially responsible organization.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0163443713485492" position="float"><caption>
<p>Employees at Novo Nordisk in Princeton, New Jersey take to the stage for World Diabetes Day, 14 November<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0163443713485492">1</xref></sup>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Similar contributions are found on YouTube and Facebook. One example from YouTube is a post by ‘WorldDiabetesDay2010’ made one day prior to WDD in 2010 (10 November 2010):</p>
<p>The video depicts the employees at Novo Nordisk’s Princeton, US office in a music video made for WDD over the Contours’ ‘Do you love me?’ from 1962. The video opens with a male employee miming ‘And here it is, the World Diabetes Day. It’s time to stand up …’, followed by music video featuring the employees miming and dancing to the tune. Only four days later, on 14 November 2010 the same video is re-posted on Facebook by ‘Lisa Centifanti Gates’, not only allowing for a continued collaboration in the making of the story about the socially engaged organization, but also tying the communication platforms together.</p>
<p>These four contributions are illustrative of a much larger set of data in which different collaborators over time have participated in the co-production of a narrative about Novo Nordisk as an organization that contributes to raising awareness about diabetes. A tale about how the organization is not only focused on producing the best medicine to diabetics, but also actively supports and promotes initiatives to prevent more people from being affected. The selected posts show a collaboration that has taken place over several platforms, using both independent contributions and re-posts from other platforms, in which the story of the socially responsible company was built up, sustained and even enhanced over time. In the specific examples, the story of Novo Nordisk’s commitment to WDD functions as a synecdoche for the organization’s social responsibility, and the larger theme of the narrative emerges from the persistence of the posts on WDD. While other stories of Novo Nordisk as socially responsible do circulate, contributions on WDD are by far the most frequent and form the backbone of the narrative. Thus, the narrative is not contained within one specific contribution, platform or period of time, but only comes into being in and through the collaboration across all three parameters.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0163443713485492" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0163443713485492">
<title>Novo Nordisk as profit seeker</title>
<p>The ‘socially responsible’ narrative about Novo Nordisk does, however, not stand uncontested. A large amount of the data contributes to another ongoing narrative process about Novo Nordisk as a ruthless profit seeker. One example is a contribution by ‘pradip_rabindranath’ on Flickr, posted on 31 August 2007:</p>
<p>The title of the picture is ‘Killer in Life Saving Drugs’ and it depicts a piece of glass in a bottle of insulin from Novo Nordisk. In the comment section underneath the picture, ‘pradip_rabindranath’ states:<disp-quote>
<p>This insulin botlle by Nova Nordisk has a glass piece and God knows what other deadly contamination. […] I would like to get an explaination from Novo Nordisk staff and Shareholders on what they feel about letting down it’s trusting patients with this kind of acts. What about their hi-talk about Changing Diabetes Treatment for the better? […] They are opportunists and have little comittments to their mission that they describe.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>By posting this picture and comment the contributor comes to participate in a communicative process about how Novo Nordisk is making short cuts in its production, and hence potentially harming others (the short cut here being lack of quality control ensuring that their products do not contain unintended glass pieces). Another example of contributions to the ‘short cut’/profit-seeking narrative is ‘USFac’s’ entry on Wikipedia in the same year (10 December 2007), presenting another kind of short cut:<disp-quote>
<p>Ragaglitazar is […] intended to restore insulin sensitivity and correct diabetic dyslipidemia, which was created by Novo Nordisk in 2001. During the clinical testing that took place in India, Novo Nordisk did not complete it preliminary testing of Ragaglitazar on animals before moving on to human testing. While administering the drug to humans, Novo Nordisk and its research scientists recognized urinary bladder tumors on the rats that were given Ragaglitazar during the animal test and therefore stopped all human testing and trials. […] It is regulated by law that all preclinical or preliminary trials must be complete for the FDA to approve the drug testing to be performed on humans. Novo Nordisk failed to do this when they were developing Ragaglitazar.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The contribution tells the story of how Novo Nordisk rushed the testing of a new drug along, hence potentially harming the humans on which the drug was tested. The post becomes a piece in a bigger narrative construction about the organization’s willingness to sacrifice safety in the pursuit of quicker production processes, arguably with the intent of maximizing profits by spending less on the development. Interestingly enough, less than six months later, this contribution was removed by ‘152.73.104.23’ (7 April 2008). Though the participant who removed the post was coded as ‘stakeholder’, as mentioned earlier, it might just as well have been the organization itself that removed the contribution, acting under cover in an attempt to silence the narrative construction process, or at least limit the number of contributions.</p>
<p>Regardless of the removal of specific posts and the contestation of others (more on this later), the narrative construction about Novo Nordisk as a profit-seeking organization is continued. On 29 May 2010 for instance ‘Stephen Brown’ writes on Facebook as a response to Novo Nordisk pulling its insulin products out of Greece due to the economic crisis of the country (and hence the fear of the Greeks being unable to pay for the drugs):<disp-quote>
<p>You miserable bastards putting the health of Greek diabetics at major risk!!!</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In simple text, it adds to the notion of Novo Nordisk as a careless company that will risk the well-being of others in pursuit of its self-interest. The contribution supplements the construction of a tale about an organization willing to bypass official channels in a quest to secure profits, regardless of any concerns about being socially responsible.</p>
<p>Again, the contributions shown here, being representative of a large pool of the data, were made over time, across platforms, yet with a similar focus. But unlike the contributions presented in the examples about WDD, these contributions do not relate to the same direct topic; instead, the narrative of the profit-seeking organization arises as a series of responses to specific events or situations in which the company has chosen profits over ethics. The overriding theme, then, is not built up through repetitions of the same story, but because it is a recurrent interpretation of Novo Nordisk’s actions in situations that are not otherwise related. The two accounts presented so far point to two different ways of constructing; one being topic-oriented (Novo Nordisk is connected to WDD), the other more sentiment-oriented (Novo Nordisk is evil).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0163443713485492" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0163443713485492">
<title>Novo Nordisk as employee heaven</title>
<p>In the construction of the third dominant narrative, these two ways of constructing merge in creating the tale about Novo Nordisk as a heaven for employees. One example is found on Flickr where ‘Tine Rugaard Møller’ posts the following picture on 1 October 2007.</p>
<p>In the comments below the picture, the contributor writes:<disp-quote>
<p>Ny arbejdsplads med fine blomster</p>
<p>[Translation: New workplace with nice flowers]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The picture shows how ‘Tine Rugaard Møller’ was welcomed to her new workplace with flowers on her desk. She has tagged the picture ‘Novo Nordisk’, therefore we assume this is the workplace she is referring to. Being greeted at your new workplace with flowers is hard to interpret as anything but welcoming and a sign of an organization that takes good care of its new employees. This narrative is corroborated by ‘Gouthamkilli’ who on Wikipedia on 28 January 2009 contributes with:<disp-quote>
<p>Novo Nordisk has been ranked 57 among 100 Best companies to work for 2009 by CNN Money</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<fig id="fig5-0163443713485492" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Though not directly concerned with being welcomed as a new employee at Novo Nordisk, nor the specific case of ‘Tine Rugaard Møller’, the post is directly related to the topic of being an employee at Novo Nordisk. Given that there are thousands and thousands of companies in the world, being number 57 on the top 100 list cannot be seen as anything but good. The tale of ‘employee heaven’ is continued, or added to, on the same platform one year later when ‘69.116.49.245’ writes, on 27 March 2010:<disp-quote>
<p>Novo Nordisk has been ranked 25 among 100 Best companies to work for 2010 by Fortune.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This time the organization is number 25 out of 100, hence further strengthening the construction process by not only referring to an external source, but also by implying a climb in the ranking.</p>
<p>Later the same year, on 4 April 2010, the narrative is given a visual input, with ‘runeherholdt’s’ video on YouTube called ‘verdens bedste laboratorium’ (the world’s best laboratory). It shows employees at one of the organization’s Danish offices singing ‘We are the champions’, directly referring to them seeing themselves as the best laboratory in the world. The video is a promotional video for ‘Firmagospel.dk’, a Danish company specializing in using gospel singing for teambuilding, but becomes a contribution to the narrative about the ‘employee heaven’: not only is Novo Nordisk the best, they even sing gospel celebrating themselves. Of course, gospel and old Queen tunes may not be read as ‘heaven’ by everyone, but it is highly unlikely that anyone would mind a motivational workplace that caters to its employees.</p>
<p>A final example of contributions to this narrative is an entry on Facebook by ‘Mariam HWaye’ on 29 August 2010.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I feel proud to be working in an organization which-besides making a good profit - does so much for humanity!</p>
<p>Being a Danish born woman -with Pakistani roots - I am greatfull with how Novo Nordisk Denmark always support victims of disasters all over the world - and this time the victims in Pakistan! THANK YOU!</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The post portrays an employee who is proud of her workplace, something probably all employees want to be, whereby the contributor comes to participate in constructing the narrative of the heavenly organization. But she also ties the narrative processes together, bringing the organizational narratives of social responsibility, profit-seeking and employee heaven into one. This leads us to the second research question: does an overarching online organizational meta-narrative emerge from the collaboration?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0163443713485492">
<title>Is there a meta-narrative?</title>
<p>While we have highlighted individual examples of the three dominant narratives, we do not believe that these narratives are constructed in and through the individual contributions or by individual contributors, but in the collaboration between them. It is, for instance, not ‘pradip_rabindranath’s’ picture of the bottle with the piece of glass that creates the narrative of Novo Nordisk as profit seeker; instead, the meaning formation in and of that picture both relies upon and contributes to this narrative. It is a link in the communicative chain, as Bakhtin would have it; or perhaps more accurately, it represents an interpretative frame that is (re-)activated in response to the way in which the organization handles certain situations. Thus, temporally disparate instances are tied together by the contributors’ common ascription of meaning to them. Similarly, the narrative about Novo Nordisk as a socially responsible organization is co-created by the various contributions that describe how the organization contributes to raising awareness about diabetes. Here, it is the repetition of a theme or topic rather than an interpretation of it that stabilizes the narrative over time. The many and often directly interrelated contributions become powerful vehicles of the narrative in showing how the organization is not only concerned with providing better medicine to diabetics, but also actively supports and promotes initiatives that may help protect people from becoming diabetics. Finally, the story of Novo Nordisk as a great workplace is not contained in either the individual employee’s experience of being well-received or the accounts of the organization’s good results in workplace rankings, but arises from the interplay of these contributions. Thus, each of the three narratives is made up of a number of smaller and/or more specific narratives that do not always go uncontested and are often not wholly consistent with each other, but nevertheless, through their spatio-temporal recurrence (across platforms and over time), come together as distinct narratives about Novo Nordisk.</p>
<p>The three narratives may be seen as expressions of the centrifugal forces of online communication: the splitting up of communicative processes into different strands of meaning formation. However, each strand may also be seen as a ‘pulling together’ of distinct narratives and as such be deemed centripetal. For instance, the stories of the glass piece, the prematurely ended testing and pulling of products out of Greece because of the financial crisis come together to form the story of the ruthless profit seeker. And if each of the three narratives is made up of numerous smaller stories, could they also themselves be part of a larger narrative? Is it possible that the centrifugal forces that pull the three narratives apart and make them distinct from each other also have centripetal consequences? Do they create a meta-narrative about Novo Nordisk?</p>
<p>In answering this question we find three factors to be of particular importance. First, the three narratives do not run parallel, but overlap at various junctions. Thus, one platform does not tell one story, but rather contains elements of all three, so that a particular user who encounters Novo Nordisk on, say, Wikipedia, would not only be exposed to one narrative. This is, for instance, apparent in the analyzed examples where Wikipedia contains contributions about Novo Nordisk’s ties to WWD, the Ragaglitazar scandal, and the organization’s workplace ratings.</p>
<p>Second, the three narratives not only cohabit the same spaces but also share the same temporality. This is partially due to the specific characteristics of online communication as being dislocated from physical space and time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen and Just, 2011</xref>). Not only can you access anything anytime independently of your geographical time zone, but contributions to online communication also leave traces and/or remain available; they can be taken up for further circulation or comment at any given time. Online, our traditional understanding of chronological causality, with its concomitant progressive storyline of beginning, middle and end, is substituted by a perpetual ‘now’ in which anything is potentially present. This is not to say that the three narratives do not develop over time, and they would certainly not be so dominant if they were not repeated over time as well as across platforms. It does, however, mean that a particular user is not only exposed to all three narratives regardless of his or her platform(s) of choice, but also independently of the specific time of the encounter (for more on this, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163443713485492">Gulbrandsen, 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>Third, the narratives not only coincide in online space and time, but are also directly formative of each other in two ways: (a) as collaborating or converging narratives and (b) as antagonistic or competing narratives. We have already seen one conspicuous example of the former process in ‘Mariam HWaye’s’ contribution where Novo Nordisk is lauded as a great workplace because it is making profit and taking social responsibility. Here, the narratives of social responsibility and profit-seeking are both invoked in support of the narrative of the great workplace. The same tendency is more indirectly present in the example of the YouTube video with Novo Nordisk employees shown celebrating WDD. Here, the display of enthusiasm for one’s work is subsumed under, and contributes to, the narrative of social responsibility; a point that becomes explicit in ‘jgst516’s’ comment to the video: ‘ABSOLUTELY AWESOME.!!!!! CONGRATULATIONS to all of you and Novo Nordisk. What a fun place to work.’</p>
<p>The latter process of antagonistic interaction between the narratives is most explicit in the stories of Novo Nordisk as a profit-seeking organization. Here, contributors often challenge the alternative story about the organization as a socially responsible company with examples of how social responsibility is being neglected in the pursuit of profit. We may, therefore, perceive the story of the profit-seeking organization as a counter-narrative to the story of the socially responsible organization – and to a lesser extent also to the narrative of Novo Nordisk as a great workplace. It is a counter-narrative that does not enter directly into the two other narratives, but challenges and questions the meaning and value of the organization.</p>
<p>In sum, and answering RQ2: yes, given the ways in which the three narratives coexist on the various platforms, challenge each other across contributions, and converge in specific utterances, one may identify a meta-narrative about Novo Nordisk as a ‘profit-seeking socially responsible great work place’. Or put differently: yes, there is a continuous meaning construction about Novo Nordisk taking place online that can be interpreted as a centripetal consequence of centrifugal forces, creating a snapshot of an organizational narrative that is both positive and negative in its sentiment.</p>
<p>We find further support for this claim by returning to the quantitative analysis of the total data set (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0163443713485492">Table 4</xref>). Of all the posts included 51,1% are positive, 35% are negative and 14% are neutral – meaning that almost half of the input to the narration process is promoting negative or neutral sentiments, and as such creating grounds for the narrative meaning formation about the socially wonderful, responsible, yet careless organization.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0163443713485492" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sentiment of contributions.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0163443713485492" xlink:href="10.1177_0163443713485492-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">% of all contributions</th>
<th align="left">% of major contributions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Positive</td>
<td>51.1</td>
<td>64.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Negative</td>
<td>35.0</td>
<td>13.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neutral</td>
<td>14.0</td>
<td>21.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Total</bold></td>
<td><bold>100.0</bold></td>
<td><bold>100.0</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Interestingly, the snapshot of the process changes if the minor posts are removed. Of the major posts 64.3% are positive, while only 13.9% are negative, and 21.8% are neutral. This implies that the participants in the process are more inclined to be negative through acknowledgements, rather than by original posting. The major negative inputs (text, pictures, comments, links, etc.) are thus generated by relatively few contributors, but ‘liked’ by far more actors than their positive counterparts. Conversely, the textual and visual contributions made are more likely to be positive or neutral, while the support and indirect contributions are more likely to be negative. This not only underscores the collaborative nature of the process, but also the importance of going beyond text in order to get the fullest possible picture of what happens in the process.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we have identified three dominant online narratives about Novo Nordisk that converge into one overarching meta-narrative. The meta-narrative being Novo Nordisk as the ruthlessly profit-seeking socially responsible heavenly work place, constructed of the three interrelated, yet disparate tales about Novo Nordisk. A collaboratively constructed contradictory account of the organization – collaborative in its (constant) becoming and contradictory in its (interpreted) meaning.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0163443713485492">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Reflecting upon the case study of the online organizational narration of Novo Nordisk and its possible theoretical implications, we are first confronted with the issue that the identified narratives are hardly surprising. Is this not the story about any organization? Some love it, others hate it, and contributors to the narrative either join up with others who share their views in order to have it confirmed or they confront those who have different views in order to disconfirm these. Existing studies of Novo Nordisk might have told us as much – and given further insights into the distinct narratives to boot (for three conspicuous examples of such research see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0163443713485492">Morsing and Oswald, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0163443713485492">Palacios et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0163443713485492">Søderberg and Holden, 2002</xref>). Does our focus on the collaborative process of telling the organizational narrative mean we have lost sight of what the narrative is all about, namely the organization? We are inclined to plead guilty to this charge, but hasten to argue that what we lose in terms of the detailed content of the narrative(s), we have gained in relation to an understanding of the collaborative process of online narration. The analysis shows that a common understanding or meta-narrative of the organization is constructed in and through the collaborative process in which all contributors are involved. The analytical findings concerning the content of this narrative are hardly surprising, but that is actually the point rather than a sign of analytical weakness. At the empirical level we have shown that, regardless of the differences, inconsistencies and contradictions that exist both within and across the three distinct narratives, an overarching narrative of the socially responsible, employee-centred profit seeker emerges in and through the juxtaposition, opposition and entwinement of individual contributions and distinct narratives that constitute the narrative process as such. This seems to confirm our suggestion that online collaboration should be conceptualized as a centrifugal process with centripetal consequences.</p>
<p>Making this assertion, however, begs the questions of whether we were not simply finding what we were looking for and, perhaps more jarringly, whether the very act of identifying narratives does not undermine the commitment to the study of process? Or, combining the two issues: is it possible to say anything about a narrative without stepping outside the narrative process and, in fact, constructing a narrative of our own? In the methodological section of this article, we anticipated these issues somewhat by recognizing our role as co-constructors of the narrative, and we argued that taking a snapshot of the collaborative process with a wide angle and a long exposure time (that is, gathering material on several platforms and over time) is the best way of guarding against undue researcher bias. We do, therefore, assert with some confidence that the organizational narrative we have presented emerges in and through the collaborative process of online communication (as we have studied it). In the more specific sense of whether we would have found the process to be more disparate had we focused only on centrifugal elements or, conversely, the process to be more uniform if we had only looked for centripetal elements, that would undoubtedly be the case. This fact, however, only highlights the need to understand online communication as a centrifugal process with centripetal consequences and to study both of these aspects of online communication. As a final remark on this issue we would like to stress that the centrifugal and centripetal elements of the process are in no way harmonious. Rather, the constant tension between the various narratives that form part of the collaborative narration process spur the process on; it is because the tale is contradictory that it is continually retold.</p>
<p>Having addressed the issue of the self-referentiality of our study, the question of whether the analytical snapshot becomes a historical anachronism the moment it is taken continues to haunt us. To the extent that the process only lives as process in the process, what have we actually ‘captured’? (And doesn’t this choice of words already say it all?). This is not a critique we can counter, but rather a fact of life; no matter how wide the angle or how long the exposure, when the snapshot is taken the process is frozen, and the living process has already moved elsewhere – and this is true regardless of the ways in which online narration processes circumvent traditional notions of chronological time; it is not in the potentiality of presence, but in its actualization that the process lives. This is, however, not so much a critique of our method as it is a fundamental condition of processes; they do not exist independently of their contents and can only be seen in and through these – if there was nothing to communicate about, there would not be any communication at all and, conversely, the content of the communication would also disappear if the communicative process stopped. In studying online organizational narratives we are not privy to the process in and of itself, but to the traces it leaves behind; traces such as invitation and participation, centrifugal forces and centripetal consequences, and contradictory collaboration. By applying these concepts to the theory and practice of online communication we can continue to expand our understanding of this ever-elusive process. In doing so, theoretical conceptualizations and empirical investigations of the collaborative process of online communication must navigate the Scylla and Charybdis of saying too little and too much about the content of this process; the content must never become the point of the processual study, but it is the only trace we have of the process. We can only study the process through the meaningful content, the narratives, it leaves behind.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of conflicting interest</label>
<p>The author declares that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0163443713485492">
<label>1.</label>
<p>See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6L1k5083yBM">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6L1k5083yBM</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakhtin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Speech Genres and Other Late Essays</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elmes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Strategy retold: toward a narrative view of strategic discourse</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>Risk Society: Towards a New Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boje</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The storytelling organization: a study of story performance in an office-supply firm</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carnevale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Conflict on the internet</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kiesler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Culture of the Internet</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Content analysis of corporate blogs as a relationship management tool</article-title>. <source>Corporate Communications: An International Journal</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooren</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Translation and articulation in the organization of coalitions: the Great Whale River Case</article-title>. <source>Communication Theory</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cronen</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>The coordinated management of meaning: a theory of communication</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dance</surname><given-names>FEX</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Human Communication theory: Comparative Essays</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper and Row</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Czarniawska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Narrating the Organization: Dramas of Institutional Identity</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The internet, public spheres, and political communication: dispersion and deliberation</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Reshaping Change: A Processual Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Denzin</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2005</year>) <source>The Sage Handbook of Qualitative Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deuze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Participation, remediation, bricolage: considering principal components of a digital culture</article-title>. <source>The Information Society</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <source>What Is Sociology?</source> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>The Society of Individuals</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>The Civilizing Process</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovalainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Qualitative Methods in Business Research</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ess</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2001</year>) <source>Culture, Technology, Communication: Towards an Intercultural Global Village</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fairhurst</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Organizations as discursive constructions</article-title>. <source>Communication Theory</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Strategy as practice and the narrative turn</article-title>. <source>Organization Studies</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1171</fpage>–<lpage>1196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The narrative paradigm: in the beginning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Clarifying the narrative paradigm</article-title>. <source>Communication Monographs</source> <volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fludernik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Towards a ‘Natural’ Narratology</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flyvbjerg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Case study</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Denzin</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Sage Handbook of Qualitative Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gergen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Co-construction, causality and confluence: organizing in a world without entities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hernes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maitlis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Process, Sensemaking and Organizing</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giddens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Conversations with Anthony Giddens: Making Sense of Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gioia</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Forging an identity: an insider–outsider study of processes involved in the formation of organizational identity</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source> <volume>55</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gulbrandsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <source>‘This Page is Not Intended for a US Audience’ – A Five-act Spectacle on Online Communication, Collaboration and Organization</source>. <publisher-loc>Frederiksberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Doctoral School of Organisation and Management Studies, Copenhagen Business School</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gulbrandsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The collaborative paradigm: towards an invitational and participatory concept of online communication</article-title>. <source>Media, Culture &amp; Society</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1095</fpage>–<lpage>1108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gutek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>In the future: transacting with strangers and not-so-strange machines</article-title>. <source>Organization</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>): <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Relations between organizational culture, identity and image</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>5/6</issue>): <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Popular Reality: Journalism, Modernity and Popular Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arnold</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hausman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A multi-method investigation of consumer motivations in impulsive buying behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Marketing</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The laboratory of public debate: understanding the acceptability of stem cell research</article-title>. <source>Science and Public Policy</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Narratives of organizational identity and identification: a case study of hegemony and resistance</article-title>. <source>Organization Studies</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Onwuegbuzie</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mixed methods research: a research paradigm whose time has come</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>P-M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Struggling over subjectivity: a discursive analysis of strategic development in an engineering group</article-title>. <source>Human Relations</source> <volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>March</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Disposable organizations and the rigidities of imagination</article-title>. <source>Organization</source>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>): <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marres</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>No Issue, No Public</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Amsterdam</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marres</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Recipe for tracing the fate of issues and their publics on the web</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Latour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weibel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Making Things Public: Atmospheres of Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>922</fpage>–<lpage>935</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>KYA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bragh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Plan 9 from cyberspace: the implications of the internet for personality and social psychology</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Review</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The microscope and the moving target: the challenge of applying content analysis to the world wide web</article-title>. <source>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</source> <volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seibold</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Advancing research in organizational communication through quantitative methodology</article-title>. <source>Management Communication Quarterly</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morsing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sustainable leadership: management control systems and organizational culture in Novo Nordisk A/S</article-title>. <source>Corporate Governance</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>On the way to theory: a processual approach</article-title>. <source>Organization Studies</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Power, subjectivity and British industrial and organizational sociology: the relevance of the work of Norbert Elias</article-title>. <source>Sociology</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pirson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Novo Nordisk – Making a Difference in Diabetes Treatment</source>. Working Paper 2010–018. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fordham University School of Business</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Poster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Virtual ethnicity: tribal identity in an age of global communication</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Cybersociety 2.0</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Narrative, organizations and research</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Management Reviews</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Internet research: the question of method</article-title>. <source>Journal of Information Technology &amp; Politics</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sagawa</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The Balkanization of the internet</article-title>. <source>McKinsey Quarterly</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The internet and civic engagement: the age of the citizen-consumer</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Communication research and the idea of process</article-title>. <source>Speech Monographs</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Søderberg</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rethinking cross-cultural management in a globalizing business world</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Cross Cultural Management</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Every</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>The Emergent Organization</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Toffler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>The Third Wave</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bantam Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0163443713485492">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whatmore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mapping knowledge controversies: science, democracy, and the redistribution of expertise</article-title>. <source>Progress in Human Geography</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>