<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjrp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Reinforced Plastics and Composites</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0731-6844</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-7964</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0731684412449700</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0731684412449700</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Rheological properties of ground rubber tire filled isotactic polypropylenes of different molecular weight characteristics</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Prut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412449700">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0731684412449700"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412449700">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Karger-Kocsis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0731684412449700">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Solomatin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684412449700">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0731684412449700"><label>1</label>Department of Polymer and Composite, Semenov Institute of Chemical Physics of Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0731684412449700"><label>2</label>MTA--BME Research Group for Composite Science and Technology and Department of Polymer Engineering Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Budapest University of Technology and Economics, Budapest, Hungary</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0731684412449700">E Prut, Department Polymer and Composite, Semenov Institute of Chemical Physics of Russian academy of sciences, Kosygin 4, 119991 Moscow, Russia. Email: <email>evprut@center.chph.ras.ru</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>24</issue>
<fpage>1758</fpage>
<lpage>1771</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Dynamic rheological properties of the thermoplastic composites containing ground rubber tire have been investigated. Isotactic polypropylenes of different molecular weights were used as thermoplastic polymer matrices. Ground rubber tire powder with a particle size of d = 0.1−0.4 mm was incorporated into the polypropylene by melt blending. The dynamic viscoelastic properties, such as storage and loss moduli, complex viscosity, and loss tangent of polypropylene/ground rubber tire composites were determined in function of ground rubber tire loading and compared with those of the parent polypropylene. The rheological properties of the composites showed shear thinning and power-law behavior. A significant improvement in the melt flowability of polypropylene/ground rubber tire composites was found to depend on the polypropylene molecular weight and the content of ground rubber tire. The higher was the ground rubber tire loading in the composites, the greater was the deviation from the Newtonian flow behavior. Results showed that the viscosity of polypropylene of high molecular weight significantly decreased with the addition of ground rubber tire up to 10 wt.%. The appearance of a minimum in the viscosity curve was traced to the formation of additional free volume in the polymer layers adjacent to the ground rubber tire particles. The dynamic rheological behavior of composites depended strongly on the degree of agglomeration of the ground rubber tire powder.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Polypropylene</kwd>
<kwd>ground rubber tire</kwd>
<kwd>composite</kwd>
<kwd>dynamic rheological properties</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0731684412449700" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Polymer composites are of major scientific and technological interest because of the potential to achieve property improvements compared to the parent polymer. Composites often consist of two components: one of them forms a continuous phase (matrix) whereas the other a discrete dispersed phase within. Composites based on polymeric matrices are numerous.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0731684412449700">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Composites containing ground rubber tire (GRT) powder as discrete phase became under spot of interest because the economic recycling of used tires is a great challenge nowadays.<sup>2−6</sup> GRT itself is a complex material containing various elastomers, carbon black, processing oils, and other fillers.</p>
<p>In our laboratory of Semenov Institute of Chemical Physics of the Russian Academy of Sciences (RAS), considerable efforts have been directed to the use of GRT as filler in thermoplastics.<sup>7−13</sup> However, the addition of GRT into a thermoplastic matrix deteriorates the mechanical properties of the related composites. The change in the properties depends on the nature, content and particle size of GRT, type of the polymer matrix, and the interfacial interaction between the components.</p>
<p>Among the various polymers used as matrices for GRT incorporation, isotactic polypropylene (PP) is the most common. PP is a thermoplastic material, processable by various techniques and used in many different commercial applications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0731684412449700">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0731684412449700">16</xref></sup> PP is characterized by high tensile strength, high stiffness, and high heat deflection temperature. PP-based blends have been extensively studied by many researchers throughout the past decades. Easy incorporation of high content of fillers and reinforcing agents, and the ability to produce blends with other polymers, including rubbers, makes PP a versatile material.</p>
<p>However, little has been published in the literature on the rheological behavior of PP/GRT composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684412449700">17</xref></sup> The rheological behavior, which reflects interactions between the polymer and the reinforcing filler, becomes more complex in case of filled polymers than in unfilled ones. Studies on the rheological behavior of polymer composites are of great relevance to their processing and final shaping.</p>
<p>The main goal of this work is to study how the molecular weight characteristics of PP affect the rheological behavior of PP/GRT composites. Recall that the rheological behavior of the molten PP is governed primarily by its weight-average molecular weight and its molecular weight distribution.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0731684412449700">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0731684412449700">16</xref></sup> Incorporation of GRT in a thermoplastic matrix alters its processability via the related change in the viscosity. Beside of the GRT content, the large surface area of GRT particles, triggering interparticle interactions, has also a major impact on the rheology of PP/GRT systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0731684412449700"><title>Experimental</title>
<sec id="sec3-0731684412449700" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<p>Commercial available PPs (Petrochemical Company, Tomsk, Russia) of different molecular weights were used in this study. The molecular weights and molecular weight distributions were determined by gel permeation chromatography. The molecular weight, polydispersity index (IP), and melt flow index (MFI) of the PPs are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0731684412449700">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table1-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Molecular weight values, polydispersity index, and melt flow index for PP</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0731684412449700" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Polymer</th>
<th><italic>M</italic><sub>z</sub> (g/mol)</th>
<th><italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> (g/mol)</th>
<th><italic>M</italic><sub>n</sub> (g/mol)</th>
<th>IP = <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>/<italic>M</italic><sub>n</sub></th>
<th>MFI, 190°, 2.16 kg</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>PP-1</td>
<td>360,000</td>
<td>150,000</td>
<td>40,000</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>10.0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-2</td>
<td>535,000</td>
<td>230,000</td>
<td>63,000</td>
<td>3.7</td>
<td>3.0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-3</td>
<td>520,000</td>
<td>280,000</td>
<td>95,000</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>0.3</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0731684412449700"><p>IP: polydispersity index; MFI: melt flow index; PP: polypropylene.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Rubber crumb prepared from truck tire treads (Chehov regeneratniy zavod, Moscow province, Russia). The composition of tread rubber was as follows: polyisoprene rubber (43 wt.%) and polybutadiene rubber (57 wt.%). Particle size of the crumb varied within 0.5–1.5 mm. This crumb was subjected to grinding by passing through a rotor disperser designed at our Institute. This disperser is based on a single-screw extruder providing intensive shear during processing (the screw diameter was 32 mm, the length-to-diameter ratio was 11, and the screw rotation was 45 rpm).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684412449700">18</xref></sup> The rotor disperser was equipped with a head designed as a cam element rotating inside a channeled cylinder. The crumb rubber resided in the disperser for about 5 min at 150−155°C. This method is referred to solid-state shear pulverization (S<sup>3</sup>P).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0731684412449700">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>The rubber powder (GRT) formed at the output of the rotor disperser was fractionated with a sieve set (Ecros Laboratory, Sankt-Petersburg, Russia). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0731684412449700">Table 2</xref> shows the particle size distribution of GRT. The rubber powder with a particle size of d = 0.1−0.4 mm was used to prepare PP/GRT composites. Powder particles were of asymmetric form and had a surface area of 750–1200 cm<sup>2</sup>/g. Two characteristic regions with a distinct boundary between them were observed at the surface of the particles. The rugged surface was caused by plastic whereas the smooth one by brittle fracture.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684412449700">8</xref></sup>
<table-wrap id="table2-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Particle size distribution of GRT</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0731684412449700" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Particle size (mm)</th>
<th>d &lt; 0.1</th>
<th>0.1 &lt; d &lt; 0.4</th>
<th>0.4 &lt; d &lt; 0.63</th>
<th>0.63 &lt; d &lt; 0.8</th>
<th>d &gt; 0.8</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Content (%)</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>90.7</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0731684412449700"><p>GRT: ground rubber tire.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0731684412449700"><title>Composite preparation</title>
<p>Composite with different compositions, viz. PP/GRT = 95/5, 90/10, 85/15, 80/20, 70/30, were prepared by mixing the components in a Plastograph EC (Brabender GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Düsseldorf, Germany) at 190°C, 100 rpm for 10 min. The mixing was continued until the recorded torque reached an equilibrium value. Time of mixture was minimized to avoid the PP degradation. For further investigations, sheets were prepared by molding the melt mixed composites in a hot press at 190°C for 10 min.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0731684412449700"><title>Rheological measurements</title>
<p>The rheological behavior of composites of different composition was investigated with plate-plate rheometer (ARES, Rheometric Scientific, Piscataway, NJ, USA). The samples in form of circular disc (1 mm thickness and 25 mm in diameter) were punched from compression-molded sheets and mounted in the gap between the plates of the rheometer. Dynamic rheological measurements were carried out at the temperatures 190°C and 230°C.</p>
<p>Dynamic frequency scan tests were conducted at 190°C at different strain sweep and strain amplitude (1%). Strain sweep was carried out to determine the linear viscoelastic region. This was to assure that the tests were in the linear viscoelastic region. Some dynamic rheological measurements were carried out at the temperature 230°C.</p>
<p>The oscillatory flow properties, namely, the storage modulus (<italic>G</italic>′), the loss modulus (<italic>G</italic>″), the complex viscosity (η*), and the loss tangent (tan δ) were determined.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0731684412449700">20</xref></sup> <italic>G</italic>′ and <italic>G</italic>″ were assessed in the angular frequency range from ∼0.1 to 100 rad/s.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0731684412449700" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<p>The rheological behavior of polymer melts, neat and filled, is in focus of interest from both scientific and industrial sides, and hence studied experimentally and theoretically. The incorporation of GRT powder was without problems even at high loading. Recall that in the PP/GRT composites the GRT particles are dispersed in the continuous PP matrix.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0731684412449700">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>All viscoelastic materials behave either more solid-like (elastic) or more liquid-like (viscous) depending on the frequency at which they are exposed to deformation. The elastic and viscous characteristics of the polymer materials are well reflected by plots depicting the storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′ versus the frequency ω, and the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″ versus ω. The storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′ is a measure of the energy stored and recovered per cycle while the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″ is a measure of the energy dissipated. The storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′ and the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″ are manifestations of the relaxation spectrum of a material. At low frequency the <italic>G</italic>′ value provides information about the long-range relaxation (high molecular weight chains), whereas the related value at high frequency is relied on the short range relaxation (lower molecular weight chains).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0731684412449700">20</xref></sup> One would expect to see strong dependences when plotting <italic>G</italic>′ and <italic>G</italic>″ versus ω, as well as <italic>G</italic>′ versus <italic>G</italic>″.</p>
<sec id="sec7-0731684412449700"><title>Strain sweep</title>
<p>Strain sweep was carried out to characterize the strain dependence of viscoelastic properties of the samples and to determine the linear viscoelastic region. It is well known that filled polymers, especially highly filled materials, often show nonlinear viscoelasticity. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0731684412449700">Figure 1</xref> displays plots of the storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′, the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″, complex viscosity η*, and loss tangent tan δ versus strain amplitude for PP-3 and PP-3/GRT = 90/10, 80/20, 70/30 composites at 230°C. As expected, <italic>G</italic>′, <italic>G</italic>″, η*, and tan δ show first a linear region followed by a nonlinear one with increasing strain amplitude.
<fig id="fig1-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″ and log η*, and (c) tan δ versus strain amplitude for (1) PP-3 and PP-3/GRT = (2) 90/10, (3) 80/20, (4) 70/30 at 230°C. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>It is seen that an addition of 10 wt.% of GRT to PP-3 drastically decreases the values of <italic>G</italic>′, <italic>G</italic>″, and η* of composites, and sharply increases the values of tan δ. The further addition of GRT to PP-3 increases the values of <italic>G</italic>′, <italic>G</italic>″, and η* of composites, and decreases the values of tan δ of PP-3/GRT composites in comparison with the 10 wt.% GRT modified PP. However, the values of <italic>G</italic>′, <italic>G</italic>″, and η* of the PP-3/GRT = 80/20 and 70/30 composites are still less than those of the neat PP-3, and the tan δ values of these composites are higher than the neat PP-3. This difference is seen especially clearly in the nonlinear region.</p>
<p>The addition of 10 wt.% of GRT to PP-3 does not alter the linear region in comparison with the neat PP-3. Deviation from linearity occurs, however, at lower strains for PP-3/GRT = 80/20 and =70/30 blends compared to the PP-3/GRT = 90/10. The main reason for this behavior is likely the agglomeration of the GRT particles.</p>
<p>The tan δ versus strain amplitude curves indicate that the energy dissipation is maximum for PP-3/CRT = 90/10. <italic>G</italic>″ dominates over <italic>G</italic>′ in the entire strain amplitude range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0731684412449700">Figure 1(c)</xref>).</p>
<p>Accordingly, the storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′, the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″, complex viscosity η*, and the loss tangent tan δ, all exhibit a linear region at low strain values. A nonlinear region is resolved at high strains. Such behavior resembles to the so-called Payne effect of highly filled (with carbon black and silica) rubbers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0731684412449700">21</xref></sup> According to the related explanation, nonlinearity is due to the disintegration of agglomerates, which created a filler network structure.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0731684412449700"><title>Dynamic rheological behavior of neat PP</title>
<p>The dependencies of the storage and loss moduli, complex viscosity and loss factor as a function of frequency ω for the PPs of different molecular weights are presented in double logarithmic scales in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684412449700">Figure 2</xref>. One can notice that both log <italic>G</italic>′ and log <italic>G</italic>″ significantly increase with increasing frequency. The molecular architecture of neat polymers is mainly composed of physical crosslinks created by trapped entanglements. The trapped entanglements can support stress for short period of time, generating a transient network. Therefore, as the frequency increases, the log <italic>G</italic>′ versus log ω and log <italic>G</italic>″ versus log ω curves for the PPs of different molecular weights become close to each other.
<fig id="fig2-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′ and log η*, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″ and tan δ versus log ω for neat PP with different molecular weight: (1) PP-1, (2) PP-2, (3) PP-3. PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Both the storage <italic>G</italic>′ and the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″ increase with increasing of the PP molecular weight independently of the frequency. The larger <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> is, the higher <italic>G</italic>′ and <italic>G</italic>″ will be. High molecular weight samples have higher degree of chain entanglements and this hampers the relaxation of the polymer chains involved.</p>
<p>From the plot of log <italic>G</italic>′ versus log ω and log <italic>G</italic>″ versus log ω (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684412449700">Figure 2</xref>), the slopes are calculated and are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684412449700">Table 3</xref>. The slopes of log <italic>G</italic>′ (logω) and log <italic>G</italic>″ (log ω) curves decrease with increasing ω and with increasing PP molecular weight. In the high frequency region, the slope is lower than in the low frequency region. This is typical for a material exhibiting a shear thinning phenomenon.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0731684412449700">1</xref></sup>
<table-wrap id="table3-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Slopes of the curves for PP at various frequencies</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0731684412449700" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Polymer</th>
<th>log ω = 0</th>
<th>log ω = 1</th>
<th>log ω = 2</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="4">log <italic>G</italic>′ – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-1</td>
<td>1.23</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.62</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-2</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.48</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-3</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.28</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">log <italic>G</italic>″ – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-1</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>0.34</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-2</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.25</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-3</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.23</td>
<td>0.07</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">tan δ – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-1</td>
<td>−0.40</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>−0.23</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-2</td>
<td>−0.35</td>
<td>−0.27</td>
<td>−0.23</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-3</td>
<td>−0.27</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>−0.21</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">logη* – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-1</td>
<td>−0.14</td>
<td>−0.34</td>
<td>−0.54</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-2</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>−0.42</td>
<td>−0.60</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-3</td>
<td>−0.43</td>
<td>−0.61</td>
<td>−0.77</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0731684412449700"><p>PP: polypropylene.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The variation of the moduli with the frequency is typically for viscoelastic fluids, that is, <italic>G</italic>′ scales with ω<sup>2</sup> and <italic>G</italic>″ with ω<sup>1</sup>. In the terminal region at low frequencies, however, the scaling changes for <italic>G</italic>′ ∼ ω<sup>n</sup> and <italic>G</italic>″ ∼ ω<sup>m</sup>, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0731684412449700">20</xref></sup> From <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684412449700">Table 3</xref> it is seen that at ω = 1 rad/s for PP-1, PP-2, and PP-3 <italic>n</italic> = 1.23, 1.07, and 0.73, respectively. Consequently, for PP-1, and PP-2 <italic>n</italic> changes from 1 to 2 (1 ≤ <italic>n</italic> &lt; 2) and for PP-3 <italic>n</italic> is less than 1 (<italic>n</italic> &lt; 1). For all PPs <italic>m</italic> is less 1 (<italic>m</italic> &lt; 1) because for PP-1, PP-2, and PP-3 <italic>m</italic> = 0.83, 0.72, and 0.47, respectively. This change may be attributed to the polydispersity of the PPs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0731684412449700">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684412449700">Figure 2</xref> displays also the plots of the tanδ and the complex viscosity η* versus log ω for the neat PPs. The values of tan δ are defined as the ratio of <italic>G</italic>″/<italic>G</italic>′. Perfectly viscous fluids have an infinite tanδ, whereas ideal elastic solids would have it as zero. The plots of tan δ versus logω for the PPs of different molecular weights tend to decrease with increasing frequency ω (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684412449700">Figure 2</xref>). As can be observed, an increase of the PP molecular weight produces a significant decrease of tan δ, that is, the viscous dissipation becomes less significant. The absolute value of slopes of tan δ (log ω) curves decreases with increasing ω and increasing molecular weight of the PP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684412449700">Table 3</xref>). Thus, at low frequencies, <italic>G</italic>″ is larger than <italic>G</italic>′, and liquid-like behavior predominates. As the testing frequency is increased, <italic>G</italic>′ takes over <italic>G</italic>″ and solid-like behavior prevails. At a certain frequency, tan δ = 1 and <italic>G</italic>″ is equal to <italic>G</italic>′, that is, <italic>G</italic>′ = <italic>G</italic>″, representing a critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub>, which is inversely proportional to the relaxation time τ. Dumoulin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0731684412449700">22</xref></sup> reported that in PP the crossover point <italic>G</italic><sub>c</sub> = <italic>G</italic>′ = <italic>G</italic>″ (i.e. tan δ = 1) at ω = ω<sub>c</sub> depends on of the molecular weight <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> and the molecular weight distribution <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>/<italic>M</italic><sub>n</sub>. From <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0731684412449700">Table 4</xref> it is seen that the value of ω<sub>c</sub> increases with decreasing <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>, that is, ω<sub>c</sub> is inversely proportional to <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>. Therefore, the relaxation time τ is proportional to <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub>.
<table-wrap id="table4-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Effect of iPP and iPP/GRT ratio on a critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0731684412449700" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th colspan="2">Composition</th>
<th>ω<sub>c</sub>, rad/s</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>PP</td>
<td>GRT</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>PP-1 PP-2 PP-3</td>
<td>- - -</td>
<td>63.1 39.8 1.6</td></tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3">PP-1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95 90 85 80 70</td>
<td>5 10 15 20 30</td>
<td>100 100 100 100 100</td></tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3">PP-2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95 90 85 80 70</td>
<td>5 10 15 20 30</td>
<td>100 100 100 25.1 15.8</td></tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3">PP-3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95 90 85 80 70</td>
<td>5 10 15 20 30</td>
<td>63.1 63.1 26.1 2.5 1.6</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0731684412449700"><p>GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Because <italic>G</italic>′ is related to the stored energy, the above finding indicates that samples of PP-3 have higher elasticity at medium and high frequencies (ω<sub>c</sub> ≥ 1.6 rad/s), and at the same time PP-1 has higher elasticity only at high frequencies (ω<sub>c</sub> ≥ 63.1 rad/s).</p>
<p>As shown on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684412449700">Figure 2</xref>, the complex viscosity log η* of PP decreases with increasing ω in the whole range of the studied frequency. The complex viscosity exhibits a short Newtonian viscosity plateau at low frequencies, followed by a shear thinning behavior. Within the measured frequency range, PP-3 does not reach a viscosity plateau, and exhibits increasing viscosity with decreasing frequency. A viscosity plateau could probably be observed at the frequency ω &lt; 0.1 rad/s.</p>
<p>This pseudoplastic or shear thinning behavior could be found for all samples investigated. Pseudoplasticity of the neat polymers is due to the random molecular structure and highly entangled state of the macromolecules, which under high shear get disentangled and become oriented. This is associated with a reduction of the viscosity. At low frequencies the difference between log η* values of the PPs is becoming larger than at high frequencies. The log η* versus log ω curves of the PPs with different molecular weights become close to one another as the frequency increases. The slopes of log η* versus log ω curves depend on the PP molecular weight (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684412449700">Table 3</xref>). The absolute value of the slopes of log η* versus log ω curves for PP-3 are higher than those for lower molecular weights (PP-1 and PP-2).</p>
<p>The viscosity curve at low frequency can be fitted by a power-law expression η* = Aω<sup>p</sup>, where A is the pre-exponential factor, ω is the low frequency, and <italic>p</italic> is the power-law index. The value of <italic>p</italic> can be determined from the slope of straight line drawn for the log η* versus log ω plot in the low frequency region. The power-law index <italic>p</italic> is proposed to be a semi-quantitative measure of the dispersion within the sample. A higher slope indicates a higher degree of shear thinning. The absolute value of <italic>p</italic> increases with increasing molecular weight of the PP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684412449700">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<p>The increase in the temperature from 190°C to 230°C decreases <italic>G</italic>′, <italic>G</italic>″, and η* and rises the tan δ values for PP-3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0731684412449700">Figure 3</xref>). The related change depends on the frequency. As the frequency increases, the log <italic>G</italic>′ (log ω), log <italic>G</italic>″ (log ω), and η*(log ω) curves become close to each other. The value of tan δ linearly decreases over the entire range of frequency investigated. As the temperature rises from 190°C to 230°C tan δ increases as well, indicating that PP-3 has higher dissipated energy.
<fig id="fig3-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′ and η*, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″ and tan δ of PP-3 versus log ω for different temperature (1) 190 and (2) 230°C. PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0731684412449700"><title>Dynamic rheological behavior of PP/GRT composites</title>
<p>It is well known that the microstructure markedly influences the rheological behavior of composites. The viscoelastic properties of two-phase polymer materials depend on the size and deformability of the dispersed phase. It is worth of noting that the deformability of the dispersed domains is greatly affected also by their sizes.</p>
<p>The dependencies of log <italic>G</italic>′ versus log ω and log <italic>G</italic>″ versus log ω for PP-1/GRT, PP-2/GRT, and PP-3/GRT composites are shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700">6</xref>, respectively. It is seen that the values of <italic>G</italic>′ and <italic>G</italic>″ increase with increasing ω for all composites.
<fig id="fig4-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′ and log η*, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″ and tan δ versus log ω for PP-1 and PP-1/GRT composites: (1) PP, (2) 95/5, (3) 90/10, (4) 85/15, (5) 80/20, (6) 70/30. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig5-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′ and log η*, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″ and tan δ versus log ω for PP-2 and PP-2/GRT composites: (1) PP, (2) 95/5, (3) 90/10, (4) 85/15, (5) 80/20, (6) 70/30. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′ and log η*, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″ and tan δ versus log ω for PP-3 and PP-3/GRT composites: (1) PP, (2) 95/5, (3) 90/10, (4) 85/15, (5) 80/20, (6) 70/30. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The increase of <italic>G</italic>′ with increasing frequency is due to the increasingly imposed restriction on polymer, and the increase of <italic>G</italic>″ is due to the higher energy required for the viscous response of the macromolecules. This is a characteristic feature for the pseudoplastic or shear thinning behavior.</p>
<p>In order to observe how the rheological characteristics derived vary with the compositional ratio, the related data in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700">6</xref> were read at the different frequencies, viz. ω = 1, 10, and 100 rad/s, and plotted as a function of the GRT content (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9</xref>). By considering these results, one can observe that the addition of 5 wt.% of GRT to PP-2 and PP-3 decreases log <italic>G</italic>′ and log <italic>G</italic>″ of PP/GRT composites (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9</xref>). The values of log <italic>G</italic>′ and log <italic>G</italic>″ of PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT composites go through a minimum at a loading of about 10 wt.% GRT. However, as seen from Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9</xref>, the minimum value decreased in comparison with the neat PP as the frequency increased.
<fig id="fig7-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″, (c) log η*, and (d) tan δ versus GRT loading for (1) PP-1, (2) PP-2, (3) PP-3. Frequency ω = 1 rad/s. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig8-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″, (c) log η*, and (d) tan δ versus GRT loading for (1) PP-1, (2) PP-2, (3) PP-3. Frequency ω = 10 rad/s. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig9-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Plots of (a) log <italic>G</italic>′, (b) log <italic>G</italic>″, (c) log η*, and (d) tan δ versus GRT loading for (1) PP-1, (2) PP-2, (3) PP-3. Frequency ω = 100 rad/s. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig9.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The addition of GRT to PP-1 did not influence the frequency dependence of either log <italic>G</italic>′ or log <italic>G</italic>″, and the related plots of log <italic>G</italic>′ (log ω) and log <italic>G</italic>″ (log ω) for all PP/GRT composites became independent of the composition (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>–9(a) and (b)). The values of the storage modulus log <italic>G</italic>′ (log ω) and the loss modulus log <italic>G</italic>″ (log ω) of PP-1/GRT composites coincide with the values of the minimum for PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT composites (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9(a) and (b)</xref>). Consequently, the addition of a relatively small amount of GRT (5−10 wt.%) reduces both <italic>G</italic>′ and <italic>G</italic>″ of the corresponding two-phase system compared to the matrix. On the other hand, this reduction depends on the PP molecular weight. The slopes of log <italic>G</italic>′ (log ω) and log <italic>G</italic>″ (log ω) curves decrease with increasing ω (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0731684412449700">Table 5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table5-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Slopes of the curves for PP/GRT at various frequencies</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0731684412449700" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-table5.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">PP/GRT</th>
<th colspan="3">PP-1<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">PP-2<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">PP-3<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>log ω = 0</th>
<th>log ω = 1</th>
<th>log ω = 2</th>
<th>log ω = 0</th>
<th>log ω = 1</th>
<th>log ω = 2</th>
<th>log ω = 0</th>
<th>log ω = 1</th>
<th>log ω = 2</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td colspan="10">log <italic>G</italic>′ – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>100/0</td>
<td>1.23</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.28</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95/5</td>
<td>1.37</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.53</td>
<td>−</td>
<td>1.06</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>1.42</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.51</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>90/10</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>0.97</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>1.42</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>0.64</td>
<td>1.37</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>0.60</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>85/15</td>
<td>1.20</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>1.33</td>
<td>1.10</td>
<td>0.68</td>
<td>1.20</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>0.43</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>80/20</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>1.01</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.28</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>70/30</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.55</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.27</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">log <italic>G</italic>″ – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>100/0</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>0.07</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95/5</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.67</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>0.23</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>90/10</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.64</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.30</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>85/15</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>0.97</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.77</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.17</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>80/20</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.23</td>
<td>0.07</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>70/30</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>0.32</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.06</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">tan δ – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>100/0</td>
<td>−0.40</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>−0.35</td>
<td>−0.27</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>−0.27</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>−0.21</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95/5</td>
<td>−0.52</td>
<td>−0.31</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>−0.15</td>
<td>−0.39</td>
<td>−0.28</td>
<td>−0.56</td>
<td>−0.36</td>
<td>−0.28</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>90/10</td>
<td>−0.40</td>
<td>−0.33</td>
<td>−0.25</td>
<td>−0.46</td>
<td>−0.38</td>
<td>−0.28</td>
<td>−0.44</td>
<td>−0.40</td>
<td>−0.30</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>85/15</td>
<td>−0.30</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>−0.25</td>
<td>−0.26</td>
<td>−0.41</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>−0.43</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>−0.26</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>80/20</td>
<td>−0.16</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>−0.25</td>
<td>−0.31</td>
<td>−0.26</td>
<td>−0.22</td>
<td>−0.28</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>−0.21</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>70/30</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>−0.28</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>−0.25</td>
<td>−0.25</td>
<td>−0.21</td>
<td>−0.27</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>−0.20</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">log η* – log ω</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>100/0</td>
<td>−0.14</td>
<td>−0.34</td>
<td>−0.54</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>−0.42</td>
<td>−0.60</td>
<td>−0.43</td>
<td>−0.61</td>
<td>−0.77</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>95/5</td>
<td>−0.12</td>
<td>−0.33</td>
<td>−0.52</td>
<td>−0.05</td>
<td>−0.26</td>
<td>−0.50</td>
<td>−0.11</td>
<td>−0.36</td>
<td>−0.60</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>90/10</td>
<td>−0.11</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>−0.50</td>
<td>−0.03</td>
<td>−0.27</td>
<td>−0.50</td>
<td>−0.06</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>−0.54</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>85/15</td>
<td>−0.09</td>
<td>−0.30</td>
<td>−0.51</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>−0.48</td>
<td>−0.19</td>
<td>−0.43</td>
<td>−0.65</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>80/20</td>
<td>−0.11</td>
<td>−0.30</td>
<td>−0.51</td>
<td>−0.26</td>
<td>−0.45</td>
<td>−0.63</td>
<td>−0.43</td>
<td>−0.62</td>
<td>−0.76</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>70/30</td>
<td>−0.18</td>
<td>−0.35</td>
<td>−0.55</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>−0.47</td>
<td>−0.64</td>
<td>−0.45</td>
<td>−0.64</td>
<td>−0.77</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0731684412449700"><p>GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>To distinguish among homogeneous and heterogeneous blends, Han<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0731684412449700">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0731684412449700">25</xref></sup> introduced a criterion based on the representation of <italic>G</italic>′ versus <italic>G</italic>″ (Cole−Cole plots). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0731684412449700">Figure 10</xref> gives plots of log <italic>G</italic>′ versus log <italic>G</italic>″ for PP/GRT composites with PP matrices of different molecular weights. As seen, the storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′ values increase with the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″ for all composites. The <italic>G</italic>′−<italic>G</italic>″ curves of different composites coincide at high values of <italic>G</italic>′ and <italic>G</italic>″ and deviates from one another at their very low values. Recall that they were captured in the low frequency region and thus associated with some scatter. But in the higher frequency region, all the curves are superimposed to one another resulting in a single ‘master curve.’ This is an indication that at low frequency the relaxation mechanisms in the composites are different from that of the reference matrix (viz. PP), whereas at higher frequencies the gross relaxation mechanisms are similar for all composites. It is interesting to note that the curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0731684412449700">Figure 10</xref> are independent of the PP molecular weight.
<fig id="fig10-0731684412449700" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Plots of log <italic>G</italic>′ versus log <italic>G</italic>″ for PP and PP/GRT composites: (a) PP-1, (b) PP-2, (c) PP-3. (1) PP, (2) 95/5, (3) 90/10, (4) 85/15, (5) 80/20, (6) 70/30. GRT: ground rubber tire; PP: polypropylene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684412449700-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700">6</xref> display the plots of the tan δ and the complex viscosity η* versus log ω for PP-1/GRT, PP-2/GRT, and PP-3/GRT composites, respectively. A monotonic decrease of the loss tangent tan δ is observed with increasing ω for all composites. The curves of tan δ versus log ω for PP-1/GRT composites coincide at high frequencies and separate from one another at low frequencies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">Figure 4</xref>). The values of tan δ for all PP-1/GRT composites are independent of the GRT loading at ω ≥ 1 rad/s, so the ratio of energy dissipated (<italic>G</italic>″) to the energy stored (<italic>G</italic>′) is not sensitive to the GRT loading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">Figures 7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>−9(d)). The values of tan δ ≤ 1 for all PP-1/GRT composites at ω ≥ 100 rad/s, that is, the viscous properties are smaller than the elastic ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">Figure 9(d)</xref>). Consequently, for all PP-1/GRT composites exists a critical crossover frequency of ω<sub>c</sub> ≈ 100 rad/s (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0731684412449700">Table 4</xref>). Therefore, for all PP-1/GRT composites liquid-like behavior predominates up to 100 rad/s.</p>
<p>The addition of a relatively small amount of GRT (5 wt.%) increases tan δ in both the PP-2/GRT and the PP-3/GRT composites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700">Figures 5</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>−<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9(d)</xref>). This increment depends on the PP molecular weight. The values of tan δ of both the PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT composites go through a maximum at a GRT loading of about 10 wt.%. Similar curves are observed for all frequencies ω. With increasing frequency the maximum value of tan δ decreases compared to the neat PP. The value of tan δ of composites decreases with increasing molecular weight of the PP when the GRT content exceeds 20 wt.%, that is, the viscous dissipation becomes less significant. Thus, in this case the values of tan δ of the blends are controlled by the PP characteristics.
</p>
<p>For the PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT composites, the critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub> is tabulated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0731684412449700">Table 4</xref>. The change in the critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub> depends on PP/GRT ratio. So, for PP-2/GRT = 95/5, 90/10, and 85/15 the critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub> increases compared to that of the neat PP-2. The critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub> decreases sharply from 100 rad/s for PP-2/GRT = 85/15 to 25.1 rad/s and 15.6 rad/s for PP-2/GRT = 80/20 and 70/30, respectively. These frequencies are lower than ω<sub>c</sub> of the neat PP-2. Consequently, these composites have higher elasticity. Therefore, the addition of GTR increases the range of solid-like behavior in comparison to that of the neat PP-2.</p>
<p>For PP-3/GRT = 95/5 and 90/10 the critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub> increases in comparison with that of the neat PP-3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0731684412449700">Table 4</xref>). For PP-3/GRT = 70/30 a critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub> is equal to that of neat PP-3. Therefore, the shift of the critical crossover frequency for iPP-3/GTR composites indicates a transition from a more viscous to a more elastic behavior.</p>
<p>The dependencies of the complex viscosity η* versus log ω for PP-1/GRT, PP-2/GRT, and PP-3/GRT composites are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">Figures 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700"/>−<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700">6</xref>. PP-1 and all PP-1/GRT composites show a pronounced Newtonian behavior within the frequency range lower than ω = 5 rad/s. The complex viscosity η* exhibits a short Newtonian viscosity plateau at low frequencies, however, only for PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT = 95/5, 90/10, 85/15. These samples exhibit a complex viscosity η* lower than that of neat PP-2, PP-3. The Newtonian zone of these composites becomes broader when compared to those of the neat PP-2 and PP-3. PP-3/GRT = 80/20, 70/30 blends show a non-Newtonian behavior at low frequency and a linear variation of the complex viscosity η* in the whole range frequency. Thus, the shear-thinning of PP-3/GRT = 80/20, 70/30 blends starts early at low frequency. The Newtonian viscosity plateau of PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT disappears when the GRT loading exceeds 20 wt.%.</p>
<p>The complex viscosity η* decrease monotonously with increasing ω for all composites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684412449700">Figures 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684412449700"/>−<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684412449700">6</xref>). The PP/GRT composites exhibit a rheological behavior, which is characteristics for non-Newtonian fluids, because their viscosity decreases with increasing frequency. Thus, all the composites exhibit shear thinning behavior similar to the PPs. The complex viscosity η* versus log ω curves for PP/GRT composites become close to each other, as the frequency increases. At low frequencies some differences arise for the composites with high GRT loading. For each type of PP, the composites with 30 wt.% GRT possess a complex viscosity η* that is much higher than that of the system containing only 10 wt.% GRT.</p>
<p>The curves of the complex viscosity η* versus log ω for PP-1 and PP-1/GRT composites coincide at high frequencies. The complex viscosity η* of PP-1 and PP-1/GRT with various GRT loading are independent of GRT loading. Thus, the rheological behavior is dominated by the PP matrix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">Figures 7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>−<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9(c)</xref>).</p>
<p>Differences between the composites with the same GRT loading but with different PP grades exist, as well. The viscosity of the composites of PP-3 with 5 wt.% of GRT is higher than that for composites with PP-2 and PP-1.</p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the values of the complex viscosity η* of PP-3/GRT and PP-2/GRT composites goes through a minimum at a content of about 10 wt.% GTR. Similar curves are observed for all frequencies ω. Consequently, incorporation of a relatively small amount of GRT (10 wt.%) reduces the complex viscosity η* of composites. This decrement depends on the PP molecular weight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684412449700">Figures 7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684412449700"/>−<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684412449700">9(c)</xref>).</p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the viscosity curve at low frequency can be fitted in the power-law equation η* = Aω<sup>p</sup>, where A is sample pre-exponential factor, ω is the low frequency, and <italic>p</italic> is the power-law index. The value of <italic>p</italic> can be determined from the slope of straight line obtained in the low frequency region in the log η* versus log ω plot. The absolute value of <italic>p</italic> depends on the PP molecular weight and PP/GRT ratio (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0731684412449700">Table 5</xref>). For PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT composites, there is minimum value of p, which depends on the GRT loading. This value goes through a minimum at a content of about 10–15 wt.% GTR.</p>
<p>The reduction of the particle−particle distance with increasing GRT loading restricts the mobility PP chains and, thus, increases the complex viscosity and the storage of modulus of composite. It is clearly seen that all composites with various GRT loading display an increase in elastic response with increasing frequency. The appearance of a minimum in the viscosity curve is most probably associated with the formation of additional free volume in the polymer layers adjacent to filler particles.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0731684412449700">26</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0731684412449700" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this paper, dynamic rheological properties were carried out on the thermoplastic composites containing GRT as filler. Three grades of isotactic polypropylenes with different molecular weights (PPs) were used as thermoplastic polymer matrices. From these investigations, the following conclusions may be derived: Strain sweep study indicated that the addition 20 and 30 wt.% of GRT to PP-3 decreased linear viscoelastic region for the storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′, the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″, complex viscosity η*, and the loss tangent tan δ in comparison with the neat PP-3.</p>
<p>The complex viscosity log η* of the neat PPs and PP/GRT composites decreased with increasing frequency. All the composites and polymers exhibited a pseudoplastic or shear thinning. The higher the GRT loading in the composites, greater is the deviation from the Newtonian behavior.</p>
<p>The storage and loss moduli of neat PPs and PP/GRT composites were shown to increase as the frequency rose. The value of critical crossover frequency ω<sub>c</sub>, for which <italic>G</italic>″ is equal to <italic>G</italic>′, increased with decreasing PP molecular weight (from 1.6 rad/s for PP-3 to 63.1 rad/s for PP-1).</p>
<p>The addition of a relatively small amount of GRT (5−10 wt.%) reduced <italic>G</italic>′, <italic>G</italic>″, and η* of the corresponding two-phase system compared to the matrix. This decrease depended on the PP molecular weight. The values of log <italic>G</italic>′, log <italic>G</italic>″, and η*of PP-2/GRT and PP-3/GRT composites went through a minimum at a loading of about 10 wt.% GRT. The addition of GRT to PP-1 did not change log <italic>G</italic>′, log <italic>G</italic>″, and η* for all frequencies. The flowability of PP/GRT composites depended on the PP molecular weight and GRT loading. The dynamic rheological behavior of composites depended strongly on the degree of agglomeration of the powdery filler. The appearance of a minimum in the viscosity curve was reasoned by supposing the formation of additional free volume in the interphase adjacent to filler particles.</p>
<p>A monotonic decrease of the loss tangent tan δ was observed with increasing ω for all composites. The values of tan δ of both the PP-2/GRT and the PP-3/GRT composites went through a maximum at GRT loading of about 10 wt.%. The addition of GTR increased the range of solid-like behavior in comparison to that of the neat PP. The shift of the critical crossover frequency for iPP-3/GTR composites indicated a transition from a more viscous to a more elastic behavior.</p>
<p>There were significant differences in the low frequency data between the composites. The PP/GRT composites with high molecular weight of PP exhibited solid-like behavior. In contrast, the low frequency response for the PP/GRT composites with low molecular weight revealed liquid-like behavior. The values of the storage modulus <italic>G</italic>′, the loss modulus <italic>G</italic>″, complex viscosity η*, and the loss tangent tan δ of the composites were controlled by the PP characteristics.</p>
<p>The rheological properties of the composites showed complex behavior, which is not readily predictable. On the other hand, the rheological properties are highly sensitive to the structure of the composites, in our case to the GRT dispersion in the PP matrix. This study suggests that it is possible to obtain composites with good rheological properties at low cost.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec11-0731684412449700"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors thank the Ministry of Education and Science of Russian Federation for the financial support (contract 14.740.11.0372).</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0731684412449700"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Multiphase flow in polymer processing</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <year>1981</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0731684412449700"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajalingam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ground rubber tyre/thermoplastic composites: effect of different ground rubber tires</article-title>. <source>Rubb Chem Technol</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>664−667</fpage>–<lpage>664−667</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0731684412449700"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Burford</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Study on powder utilization of waste tirer as a filler in rubber compounding</article-title>. <source>Rubb Chem Technol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1028−1041</fpage>–<lpage>1028−1041</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0731684412449700"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Radusch</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intensification of interfacial interaction in dynamic vulcanization</article-title>. <source>J Macromol Sci Phys</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>265−273</fpage>–<lpage>265−273</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0731684412449700"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Karger-Kocsis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>LDPE-based thermoplastic elastomers containing ground tire rubber with and without dynamic curing</article-title>. <source>Polym Degrad Stab</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>137−144</fpage>–<lpage>137−144</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0731684412449700"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lievana</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Karger-Kocsis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of ground tyre rubber (GTR) in thermoplastic polyolefin elastomer compositions</article-title>. <source>Prog Rubb Plast Recycl Technol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>1</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0731684412449700"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prut</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Novikov</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thermoplastic vulcanizates based on polyolefines and rubber waste</article-title>. <source>Polym Mater Sci and Eng ACS</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0731684412449700"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trofimova</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Novikov</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kompaniets</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Modification of crumb rubber</article-title>. <source>Polym Sci</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>45A</volume>: <fpage>537−544</fpage>–<lpage>537−544</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0731684412449700"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhorina</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prut</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Blends based on ground tire rubber</article-title>. <source>Polym Sci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>46A</volume>: <fpage>151−159</fpage>–<lpage>151−159</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0731684412449700"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchepel</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhorina</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Static and dynamic vulcanizates containing ground tire rubber</article-title>. <source>Prog Rubb Plast Recycl Technol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>85−96</fpage>–<lpage>85−96</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0731684412449700"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prut</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of vulcanization on the mechanical properties of ethylene-propylene-diene terpolymer blends with crumb rubber</article-title>. <source>Polym Sci</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>47A</volume>: <fpage>1245−1253</fpage>–<lpage>1245−1253</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0731684412449700"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trofimova</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kompaniets</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Novikov</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Strain properties of blends based on isotactic polypropylene and crumb properties</article-title>. <source>Polym Sci</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>47B</volume>: <fpage>159−162</fpage>–<lpage>159−162</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0731684412449700"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dementienko</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tikhonov</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect vulcanization on the properties of polymer – elastomer blends containing crumb rubber</article-title>. <source>Polym Sci</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>49A</volume>: <fpage>1218−1225</fpage>–<lpage>1218−1225</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0731684412449700"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Karger-Kocsis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Polypropylene: structure, blends and composites</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name>, <year>1995</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0731684412449700"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>EP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>. <source>Polypropylene handbook</source>, <publisher-loc>Munich</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hanser</publisher-name>, <year>1996</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0731684412449700"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Karger-Kocsis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Polypropylene: an A-Z reference</source>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic</publisher-name>, <year>1999</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0731684412449700"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Prut E, Kuznetsova O, Chepel’ L, et al. Thermoplastic elastomers based on ground rubber tire. In: <italic>RAPRA TPE 2005</italic>. The Eighth International Conference on Thermoplastic Elastomers. 14–15 September, Berlin, Germany, Conference Proceedings, paper no 13</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0731684412449700"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prut</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plastic flow instability and multiple fractures (grinding) of polymers: review</article-title>. <source>Polym Sci</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>36A</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0731684412449700"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Isayev</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Khait</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Rubber recycling</source>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0731684412449700"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Viscoelastic properties of polymers</source>, <edition>3rd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0731684412449700"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Low strain dynamic properties of filled rubbers</article-title>. <source>Rubb Chem Technol</source> <year>1971</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0731684412449700"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumoulin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Utracki</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rheological and mechanical properties of ternary blends of linear-low-density polyethylene/polypropylene/ethylene-propylene block polymers</article-title>. <source>Polym Eng Sci</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1319</fpage>–<lpage>1326</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0731684412449700"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Rheology and processing of polymer materials</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0731684412449700"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Criteria for the rheological compatibility of polymer blends</article-title>. <source>J Appl Polym Sci</source> <year>1985</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>4431</fpage>–<lpage>4431</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0731684412449700"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rheological behavior of compatible polymer blends. I. Blends of poly(styrene-co-acrylonitrile) and poly(ε-caprolactone)</article-title>. <source>J Appl Polym Sci</source> <year>1987</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1199</fpage>–<lpage>1199</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0731684412449700"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shumsky</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipatov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Getmanchuk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Viscoelasticity and morphology of poly(ethylene-co-vinyl acetate)/polyisobutylene blends</article-title>. <source>J Appl Polym Sci</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>2700−2707</fpage>–<lpage>2700−2707</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>