<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">specs</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Cultural Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1367-5494</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-3551</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1367549412440530</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1367549412440530</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Interviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Janice Radway</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Radway</surname><given-names>Janice</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1367549412440530">Northwestern University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1367549412440530">Janice Radway, School of Communication, Northwestern University, 2240 Campus Drive, Evanston, IL 60208, USA. Email: <email>j-radway@northwestern.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Reflecting on Cultural Studies in the US</issue-title>
<fpage>327</fpage>
<lpage>342</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<speech>
<speaker>Jon Cruz (JC):</speaker>
<p>One of the first things I would like to begin with is your early work in American studies, to which you brought an interest that came from critical literary studies. Your work in that area can be seen as both distinct from, yet quite kindred to, cultural studies: I’m thinking about your pioneering work on reception studies. You took reception theory and reception studies more specifically to ethnographically grounded explorations, particularly around the idea of interpretive communities. That struck me as kindred to much of the vibrant work that was being developed in the larger ethnographic traditions, and certainly in early cultural studies.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Janice Radway (JR):</speaker>
<p>I said some of this, I think, in one of the revised introductions to <italic>Reading the Romance</italic>. My training was different from a lot of people associated with cultural studies in the United States. What I mean by that is that I think of cultural studies as – at least when it was explicitly termed ‘cultural studies’ – having ties to communication studies departments and the discipline of communication. My background, as your question suggests, was somewhat different. I was trained in an English department and in particular, in an American Studies programme in the 1970s at Michigan State University. I worked under the direction of Russel Nye, who himself was a cultural historian and one of the first people in the United States to take American popular culture seriously. It was partly because of my interest in his work that I moved in that direction and became pretty much focused on popular culture. When I finished at Michigan State in 1977 I presented myself as someone who was interested in popular literature and popular culture more generally. When I was in graduate school, again, this was really through the 1970s, this was a moment when critical theory, European-based theory, was beginning to be felt in English departments, and there were several young faculty members at Michigan State who were especially interested in poststructuralism and French theory. Evan Watkins was there and had some interest in the German tradition as well. Also, at the same time, feminist studies was really becoming important. Elaine Showalter’s book [<italic>A Literature of their Own</italic>] came out while I was in graduate school. So my work, although focused on popular culture, was done in the context where feminist studies and critical theory were beginning to develop. There were also friends of mine in graduate school who were beginning to work with Stanley Fish’s writing. They were people specializing in the Renaissance and were dealing with his early work in the field of early modern studies. All of this influenced my dissertation, which I have never published and in some ways repudiated, because it was a theoretical effort to write about the differences between popular and elite literature. I tried to deal with it as a theoretical issue and I now think that was mistaken, so I just abandoned it. But what’s really relevant is that I was then hired by the American Civilization department at the University of Pennsylvania: that department had an enormous impact on my work. The Penn Am-Civ department was somewhat different from other American Studies departments in the sense that it was not solely produced by a combination of history and literary faculty. It was under the direction of Murray Murphy and Anthony Garvan, and they were very interested in the concept of culture: in fact, the culture concept as it was used in anthropology. When I arrived at Penn, in the graduate programme, one of the basic required courses of graduate students were ethnographies. Several were taught. Drew Faust taught an ethnography of the American South; there was also an ethnography of the Pennsylvania Germans. It was really there that I began to think, I would say, more broadly about culture. My colleagues in that department were critical of what they thought of as the belletristic tradition in American studies. You would say things about the nature of American culture based on reading the high literary tradition, and they were quite sceptical about that and felt that one needed to pay more attention to popular culture, to the culture of ordinary American citizens; and so that’s of course why they were interested in someone like me, who was thinking about popular culture.</p>
<p>All of that had an enormous impact on my work, as I was trying to figure out what to do about my dissertation. Part of my dissertation had some material in it on the popular Gothic, then the popular Gothic novel that had come out of the British tradition of the Gothic, but was quite popular and being produced in paperback. I began to think about that and began to think ‘Well, what does it mean that the genre that developed into bodice rippers is becoming increasingly popular and important?’ So all of these influences came together and I began to think, ‘Well, what would it mean to think about the actual reading of popular literature?’ That’s when I began to put together critical theory, Stanley Fish’s reader response criticism and this kind of more culturally oriented approach to the study of the US.</p>
<p>What’s interesting is that I did not know really of the separate cultural studies tradition. I had read one of Stuart Hall’s early works as part of my PhD reading list; the book that he wrote with Paddy Whannel called <italic>The Popular Arts</italic>, and Russ Nye also introduced me to the very early work of Pierre Bourdieu and Robert Escarpit in the sociology of literature and culture. So I knew of that tradition, but as an Americanist I didn’t read very widely in French or the other tradition. So I can’t say that early work of mine came out of cultural studies. It’s interesting that it’s absolutely contemporaneous with what was going on in Birmingham. I think that that’s very interesting, and whenever I’ve taught cultural studies since then, I’ve tried to make a point with my students that it’s important to understand that the impulse to connect culture with social development, with economic and political development, is the trend that was broader than what was going on at Birmingham. It was part of a particular historical moment that had happened for feminists: it happened with people working on ‘race’-based studies and on ethnic studies, and one could tell the history of cultural studies in a much more expansive way that wouldn’t see it as somehow originating only out of the British tradition.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>What comes to mind in terms of ethnic studies and going to graduate school in the Bay Area was the legacy that erupted significantly earlier. The ‘Third World’ strike for example, at San Francisco State, that basically forced the University of California system to start admitting into the canon all of those marginal literacies and practices and cultural formations that had been hitherto invisible or explained away.</p>
<p>But you raise something really interesting, and I’ve been thinking about this and I’m sure readers would be curious about this too. This sort of co-terminous set of developments that emerged with a kind of critical American studies tradition, along the lines of what was taking place as the Birmingham School starts to get organized. I was struck – and I want to raise this with you – by the conclusion in a piece that you developed significantly later, in <italic>Critical Inquiry</italic> in autumn 2004. The article is entitled ‘Research universities, periodical publication and the circulation of professional expertise: On the significance of middlebrow authority’. At the tail end of that you kind of lambast, in some ways quite critically, the English professoriate for their inability (by definition I suppose, and by exclusionary tactics) to grasp the literary practices that are full of meaning in the context of so-called middlebrow work, whether in publishing or readership. I was struck by your conclusions, because in some ways they remind me of arguments that Richard Hoggart was making in the late 1950s when he was trying to retrieve a critical appraisal of literary practices, reading practices – I guess that’s the term for it – that in some way exonerated the existential, the experiential, the social circumstance, the cultural situatedness of reading as a practice.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Right. That’s exactly right. I think that that is the direction I’ve gone, along with my criticism of English as a discipline and the way in which it evolved out of a certain kind of preoccupation with aesthetics and declarations of value and judgement. Of course, Raymond Williams did a huge amount of work explaining how that happened, how it came out of the culture and society tradition, replacing a certain kind of religious tradition. I think maybe now I wouldn’t be as critical as I was earlier, but I do think that because of the way <italic>value</italic> was constructed in English departments, and the way in which the text was authorized and legitimated as a beautiful thing, an artefact, there was less attention to the social efficacy of reading literary texts and reading as a kind of social practice. So it made it impossible to really understand that literature acts in the world very powerfully and in multiple ways for different kinds of people, and so that’s sort of the overall direction that I’ve gone. <italic>Reading the Romance</italic> really came out of that constellation, and it was only after I began to do that work and teach that work that some of my students introduced me to cultural studies. Also, that happened because I was invited in 1984 to give a talk at a conference at the Annenberg School of Communication at the University of Southern California. Larry Grossberg, Ellen Wartella and Constance Penley were there. They had already become associated with cultural studies, that’s how I met them. Then, they invited me to speak at Illinois. That was really how I then became familiar with the British tradition and really began to read systematically.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>I’m curious about the relationship of ideas in development, in tandem, in conjoining modes, because there was a number of studies out, historiographies of American studies in relationship to cultural studies, that take up the argument that in the early 1990s cultural studies was somehow being watered down as it became incorporated into the American context, becoming Americanized. Some of these voices, perhaps in a critical romantic way, go after English departments for being the site in which cultural studies took hold; but, of course, from their perspective it was simply a kind of reassertion of the primacy of the text at the expense of context. The more that I think about it and the more that I read about this, my curiosity remains, and because of the convergences that you talk about and that you’ve actually experienced and worked through. As you suggest, we see in operation a more complicated and quite different story, one that speaks of a tremendous amount of prehistory to all of this that brings significant convergences between the British Left and the American Left, struggling with the whole Cold War legacy of politics and looking for opportunity structures to bust out with some sort of critical reflection by which the cultural can be rethought. This occurs with C. Wright Mills: he ends up becoming somewhat of a folk intellectual hero for American intellectuals, but a significant number of British thinkers as well, who have aspirations of a resurgent Left. There is a critical cycling of thought back and forth, which is already there 20 years earlier, and so the convergences that sort of happen, that develop over time, raise questions that are fascinating. What you described is a trajectory that, I think, speaks to a good number of American intellectuals who work in the tradition of critical American studies, who then find resonation with cultural studies and vice versa. That cross reading I think is really quite fascinating.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>The question of the relationship between critical American studies and cultural studies, it seems to me, is a complicated one. I know the claim that cultural studies gets watered down when it’s Americanised. That’s the problem with origin narratives: it assumes that cultural studies is authentic in the UK and in Birmingham, and that somehow it travels across the ocean and then it gets watered down here. I think, in fact, the situation was much more complicated. I do see the Birmingham tradition and the British cultural studies tradition as extremely important, but I do think that there is a difference between Birmingham cultural studies and some of what became cultural studies here. I think in part that has to do with the importance of class in the UK, the importance of Marxism as an indigenous tradition that everyone was familiar with, and the role of Stuart Hall. I think all of that is really important and interesting.</p>
<p>That said, I do think that some of the impulses that produced the people at Birmingham’s interest in turning to culture, were in response to similar forces at work in the US and in the universities. That turn was realised variously and differently in different pockets of academic practice. As you say, in ethnic studies, in ‘race’-based studies and in feminist studies there’s a turn towards an interest in culture and an interest in trying to link it to politics, and it then hooks up in some ways with the cultural studies tradition, but in some ways it doesn’t. I’ve not yet seen a good history of what I think happens to English departments during the periods that we associate with the culture wars. I think cultural studies became a term that referred to critical work, canon questioning work, and I think that it’s important not simply to see that as a watering down of something that originated somewhere else. It’s a different situation. Anyway, it’s complicated.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>Yes. I’m thinking about the critical ethnographies that Paul Willis in Britain developed, aspects shared in Dick Hebdige’s early work on subcultures. There are interesting historicities behind that kind of work with regard to developments around critical criminology that emerged in the United States, and a series of cross-readings and cooperative intellectual assimilations that move back and forth. There are links that operate intellectually and feed into and are not simply forged by later work.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Yes, I was sort of aware of this through friends in the Education School at Pennsylvania, but all of this became clearer to me this year, because I decided to teach a class about the American high school. Part of what I decided to do was a series of ethnographies of schooling, of high school, because I wanted to get at questions about ‘race’, questions about class, questions about gender and sexual preference construction. There’s a vast literature of ethnographies of education, but there’s also a vast literature of ethnographies of American high school, and virtually all of them have been profoundly influenced by Paul Willis and that tradition that he comes out of – it’s very, very interesting. So that’s a whole other area that people I think sometimes forget about, when they are thinking about cultural studies.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>You’ve outlined your own trajectory a bit here, as you’ve described getting established intellectually and working the paradigmatic contours that were important to you. I was also recently reading your 1998 presidential address that you gave for the American Studies Association, and it struck me as a very strong attempt to try to restate the problematics around the term ‘American studies’, and how that term had traditionally or historically, in many ways, pivoted on some kind of essentialist or uniform notion that was in itself always in contention.</p>
<p>In your address you present some of the key critical incursions or eruptions that were becoming established around queer studies, feminist theory, new explorations in sexuality and gender, ‘race’ and ethnicity: areas and problems that were not as prominent as the class problem in the early cultural studies tradition. There are some indications in British cultural studies’ own reflections that the Marxian inheritance of class reductionism, while powerful, occluded or didn’t quite know how to work with the problems of gender and ‘race’. Stuart Hall is good about flagging this, as he lays that out with regard to work carried out by Paul Gilroy and Angela McRobbie, who bring in ‘race’ and gender.</p>
<p>But here we have in the American context, in American studies, your presidential address which, in many ways, iterates attention to similar blind spots. You ask those questions, you restate those emergent irruptions, you ask and probe what has been marginalized, and you argue that such problems must be central to the whole business of grasping society and culture and all of its differences. What was it like to chart that kind of intervention to the professional association? What was it like to struggle with formulating that kind of intervention and critique with regard to American studies?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Well, that address was very controversial for reasons I didn’t always fully understand. For me, it came out of a dialogue between my earlier training in American studies and where I was at the moment, which was the literature programme, and secondarily the English department at Duke University. There, queer theory was being pursued vigorously by Eve Sedgwick and Jonathan Goldberg and a number of others. Fredrick Jameson and the group in literature was really at that point, as even now, moving past discussions of postmodernism and really thinking about globalization and postcolonial studies. So the reflections on American studies came out of what I would say was the internationalism and comparative perspective that I was party to as a member of the literature programme.</p>
<p>I think in part, the argument is stated a little too baldly in the address, in the sense that it didn’t give enough due to the counter-traditions within American studies which have always been there, and which I think Michael Denning’s book, <italic>The Cultural Front</italic>, does a really good job of bringing to the fore. He stresses the fact that there has always been a dissenting tradition within the US, but also within a broadly conceived American studies, and so I think people were upset that that dissenting tradition seemed to get backgrounded for a more unitary notion of the American at the heart of American studies. I think that criticism of the address is fair. What I was trying to do was to call into question the way that large frameworks and rubrics get stated at particular moments: even though they are critiqued from within, when they are retained in place, they continue to carry a certain kind of force. So even though there’s a dissenting tradition within the American tradition, to consistently label it ‘American’ and to be preoccupied, say, with the differences within, is to forget that the US has always been in a relationship to the rest of the world, that the population has always been fluid, mobile and hybrid. I think that I didn’t articulate that well enough, and certainly since then there’s been a vigorous and vibrant conversation about American studies around the world, and what it means to pursue the study of the United States from outside of its borders.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>The very term ‘American’ has become geographically as well as ideologically plastic or rubbery, so to speak. But it also seems, at the same time, that your argument and perspective you presented in your address did flag the lacuna, the silencing, that was in many ways part of the Cold War legacy of uniformity – despite diversity. So it seems one can go back to Denning’s work and say, ‘Yes, the Left was always already there.’ One can keep going back and back and find these pockets of resistance, but in terms of the dominant and the normative, it seems to me that you were correctly challenging that. The tension seems understandable.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Right. That’s certainly what I was trying to do. I was also coming out of a theoretical moment that was attempting to call into question the implicit valorisation of a certain kind of nationalism. What made people uneasy was the assertion that, well yes, even though American studies is critical, it’s still embedded and intertwined within its fundamental formulations of assumption about nationalism. I was trying – maybe not as articulately as I might have – to call that into question, to say: ‘That seems to be problematic.’ I think some of that came out because it was clear that people didn’t want to give up that nationalism.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>I’d like to switch gears and ask you to go back to some of your own work and comment on some of the implications that I think are provocative. This has to do with going back to some of your earliest conceptualizations, and in relationship to perhaps where that might also extend to your present concerns. Let me begin by going back to the ‘Interpretive communities and variable literacies’ piece. You end that essay with a kind of reflexive concern with regard to the limitations of the anthropological and ethnographic moment where grasping reading practices and structures of meaning are themselves meaningful, but yet one can’t necessarily hold onto those as findings over time. As I read it, you problematize the fixed ethnographic moment as you begin to raise the question of what it would mean to follow readers over a longer period of time, where modalities of interpretation, the very idea of an interpretive community and all that this presupposes, could actually shift over time. It raises the question of how one actually links ethnography with history in rethinking the problem of culture. Could you comment on this?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Well, it seems to be something that preoccupies me always, which is the question of temporality and change over time. One of the things that has always troubled me is the ways in which a lot of scholarly work pronounces on the political effects of particular cultural forms, whether it’s the romance or a TV show or zines – I’m working on <italic>girl zines from the 90s</italic> right now. There is often a kind of normative evaluation going in such work, a gauging of political effects. People ask: are such zines feminist or not, politically Left or not, authentic or corrupted? Are they legitimately feminist, or only a watered-down form of feminism because of the impact of third wave feminism or whatever. I worry that this kind of judgement truncates temporality and it assumes that the effects of cultural practices are felt in the short term, in the immediate environment. It seems to me that change is actually a long evolution and more random. What’s involved is a process of articulation, and so I constantly find myself now going back to Stuart Hall’s work on articulation and on the question of linkages. I’m increasingly interested in thinking about what happens to cultural production over time, what happens to human subjects through time. Human subjects, it seems to me – and here I mean human subjectivity – is not finished. It’s an ongoing project, where subjects are constituted in particular environments and those environments are constantly moving and changing. So I am interested in the question of diachrony – if you think back to that division between synchronic and diachronic. I am obsessed with that, trying to figure out, ‘Well, how would you study that?’ It’s not easy because how do you constitute a research project over time? It becomes really almost necessary that it be collaborative, and that it range not only across fields and regions but through time. I just taught the history of British cultural studies to graduate students and I kept coming back to the Stuart Hall volume <italic>Policing the Crisis</italic>, which I think is absolutely stunning and masterful. When you look at what they achieved in that volume, you realise that that could not have been done by one person.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>That’s right. It’s a remarkable collective work.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>It’s incredible, it’s an incredible book, and it ranges across and over time, so it’s as much influenced by historical training as it is by a kind of cultural studies interest in mapping the cultural moment synchronically. I guess I should say that attention to the synchronic relationships is not enough to help us understand how political change is happening, or how we might influence political change.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>As I think of your own initial intellectual work, if you were to back up from the perspective of where you discovered a particular interpretive formation or reading formation, the interpretive communities around the romance, if you back up in time, at some point that disappears. That formation isn’t necessarily there. So the question is, when, how and why does it come into being, and how does it transform?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Yes that’s right. How does it change, how is it transformed and what happens to people who are reading romances as those romances evolve in response to a whole confluence of factors?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>This rub of history we are opening up here seems to be picked up in your ensuing editorial work, <italic>The History of the Book in America</italic>. I know that has a time period, 1880 to 1940, and in some ways it strikes me as intellectually consistent with these questions that I think you’re exploring: how does one sort of look at this process as a historical formation?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Yes, one of the things I’ve realised more and more is even as much as I’m interested in popular culture, as much as I’m interested in theoretical formulations, there’s something about my orientation to the world that is fundamentally historical. If you look at <italic>Reading the Romance</italic>, the first chapter there – I think it’s called ‘The institutional matrix’ – really goes back to the historical constitution of mass-marketed paperback literature as a way of trying to explain why, in the 1970s, women could go into a supermarket and pick up a paperback romance. In other words, there’s an effort to understand that there are material conditions of possibility, there are economic conditions of possibility, and ideological and cultural conditions of possibility that call romance reading into being. I was trying to see and understand those contributing factors historically, to see those as the context within which any particular performance of cultural production and cultural reception takes place. That still preoccupies me.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>Yes. That makes a lot of sense. I’d like to now ask you to turn to the contemporary moment and ask where you think cultural studies, loosely defined, is going. Or where, perhaps, should it go? What are the nagging and unresolved issues?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>That’s a really interesting and very difficult question, and I don’t have a summary take on it all. It seems to me that the horizon of what cultural studies has to face includes a rampant neoliberalism, the expansion of global capitalism, the impact that this has had on growing extremes of income differentiation, the creation of an extraordinarily wealthy cosmopolitan class and an increasingly immiserated population, the declining middle class, not just in the US, but globally. It raises questions about the future of nationalism and the rise of internationalism and the impact this has on xenophobia – and not to put too fine a point on it, fear and racism. All of which, it seems to me, characterize the present environment and make any kind of political work incredibly difficult – whether it’s an officially designated political sphere or, say, in cultural environments like the university.</p>
<p>So it seems to me that cultural studies has to address that as the horizon of its work. If you think of cultural studies as, at least in part, an academic practice, obviously the other thing that cultural studies scholarship has to contend with is the changing nature of the university in this world. Obviously, it’s not just American universities that are being crushed by this, but the university globally. I think American universities are deeply challenged by some of these political developments. The social and political dispensation that enabled the rise of the American university in the 1880s to 1920s, that disposition seems to be evaporating, and there is no longer a willingness to fund any kind of public education and any kind of strong university system. So increasingly it’s being privatised, increasingly it’s being decimated, and that raises questions for people doing cultural studies scholarship in both public and private institutions.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>Yes. It seems to me that it brings that process of institutional support into much more crucial and critical light. But also, as you speak, I again recall your presidential address in 1998, which was written at the high point of the dot com boom era, or at least close to that period, where there was some kind of expansion of the university and a tentative willingness to open the curriculum and other kinds of intellectual forms of enquiry. Your presidential address talked specifically about how important it was to grasp relations of difference: it seems that, given the crash of Wall Street, there is a moment enabling a deeper interrogation of the temporarily transparent corporatization that has grown so incredibly formidable as teetering between exhaustion and renewed gravity. What does the moment hold, if we bring back a critical reach for the domestic situation that is now full of all this deep unease and forms of anxiety about difference? Indeed, relations of difference become dystopian flashpoints in some sectors of the political will. Do you have any thoughts about this kind of juncture? If you were to give that presidential address to the American studies profession today, how would you recast that initial challenge?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>That’s a really good question. I think you’re right in pointing to the domestic reaction to those developments. It seems to me the reactions are deep: deep fundamental anxiety and paralysing fear. It does seem to me that those affects are abroad in the land, as it were, and increasingly I find work on affect absolutely crucial and important to the development of the cultural studies project. So part of my zines project has me reading people like Lauren Berlant, Sara Ahmed, Sianne Ngai and Anne Cvetkovich: people who are theorizing affect in a way that becomes important at a local level. It seems to me that cultural studies does enable, for those who participate in it and deal with it, an investment in the local, an investment in the immediate scene. One of the things that has troubled me throughout my career – since I’ve been located at private institutions and therefore teaching relatively privileged populations, populations that come from fairly homogenous backgrounds – is how to move my teaching to feature as absolutely central a preoccupation with difference, to feature a preoccupation with questions of ‘race’, class, different gender and sexual orientation. To address undergraduates in and around this – and that’s where this class on high school entered my teaching – because it seemed to me that it might be an interesting way to get students to think about their own, in many cases highly privileged, backgrounds by reading about high school experiences and thinking about high school as a disciplinary environment in a comparative way. So they started with <italic>The Breakfast Club</italic> and Foucault. They found it pretty interesting.</p>
<p>I’m not sure I could say how I would rewrite the presidential address, but I can say that my daily practice and teaching is an effort to address my students in a way that would get them to think that way and, you know, I can do that because I’ve had training in cultural studies and feminist studies. I haven’t had much experience working on ‘race’ or working on ethnicity, so that’s partly why I chose a subject like high school, so I could draw on that work but not present myself as someone who is an expert in it.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>I think that your move to bring these questions back to pedagogy is crucial. You’ve spent a lot of time and energy unpacking insights into the practice of reading, but now we’re entering a period of the digital culture where the processes of production and reading and distribution are shifting. I’m curious if you have any thoughts about whether or not reading itself is changing, perhaps impacting what we think of as interpretive communities. Do you think the practice of reading is changing along new fronts, new areas or new issues that are going to become increasingly important?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>I don’t have a pat answer about all of that either. Again, that may be because of my respect for history and the long view. We don’t yet know what is going to happen. It seems to me that a great deal is happening as these technologies change. That’s part of the reason I wanted to move into a communication studies department, because I saw a communication studies department grappling much more seriously and expansively with new technologies, digital forms of communication and electronic resources. I am not of the group that is involved in jeremiads about the book and about reading. I don’t think that the book and reading are going to disappear. I think, as you formulated it, that they are changing. How they are changing, I think we don’t even begin to have a clue. Obviously, reading is a fundamental part of everyone’s day: you’re reading when you’re tweeting, you’re reading when you’re texting, you’re reading when you’re searching the web. What does that mean in terms of one’s use of reading? We need extensive studies of that to try to understand what is happening. We need to understand what’s happening with something like the Kindle and the iPad. It’s extremely interesting to see these technologies taking over and people downloading novels and reading novels. I think we don’t yet know how the practice of reading, as a social practice, is going to change, because of course reading isn’t just impacted by the technology; it’s impacted by the changing nature of working life, the changing nature of family life, the fact that more people are under economic duress, the fact that work exacts many more hours a day, the fact that there is very little leisure time. All of these are factors affecting reading as a social practice, and so to study it you have to really have a sort of complex view of that social situation. I don’t have an easy answer about these ‘conjunctural’ changes, as cultural studies would have it. I think it’s a prime question to be answered and investigated.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>But it also suggests that ethnography can’t abandon this level, but is further challenged by it.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>I think it can’t, I agree. I think it really is essential. I think interviewing is really important. I think it’s really critical.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>There’s some argument to be made about parallel developments with music and the rise of the iPod, for example and the disappearance of the album, the shrinking down of the musical package through the $0.99 single song and, of course, then downloading that with the convenience of mass storage, allowing individuals to amass huge amounts of musical files with music consumed in privacy or relative isolation. Or to use Raymond Williams’ term, ‘mobile privatization’, which he applied to domestic television viewing. Do you see that happening, and to what extent is it a kind of reading or listening formation?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>That obviously is an issue. I remember when I first visited my daughter at college five years ago. I walked out of my hotel to meet her somewhere, and I noticed that every undergraduate at the University of Wisconsin was on a cellphone. Obviously not talking to someone there, present, not paying attention to the immediate environment, but connected to someone else. So yes it’s isolating, and yes it’s singular, but these technologies are also enabling other forms of connection and context – other forms of sociability. What that means again, I’m not entirely sure we know. So again, I’m wary of these kinds of easy generalizations.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>Do you think phenomena like Facebook produce new modalities of interpretive communities? Are there any kind of relationships where that kind of theorising can be applied to this kind of technology?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>It seems to me that those cultural practices require in-depth research and an effort to understand people’s uses of them. I don’t think that you can simply look at the Facebook page and easily generalise about it. I think that one needs to know how it’s being used, and my guess is that those uses are multiple – I mean, grandparents keep up with their grandchildren. Once again, I’m wary of the idea. I’m absolutely against technological determinism that suggests that these technologies are producing a major shift in development. I’m wary of that, I don’t think that’s right: I think that these technologies both enable and constrain. I think cultural studies scholarship that really attends to social practices can really attempt to elicit and understand the nuances of these practices. One of the things that I especially appreciate in the British cultural studies tradition is the ties to sociology and its interest in thinking about social practice and thinking about the social. That seems to me something that’s especially valuable about the British cultural tradition and it wasn’t as strong, it seems to me, in the kinds of cultural studies that were developed in the United States. Again, I think this is critical.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>What are questions are you currently exploring? Are there horizons that you’d like to investigate and unpack at this point?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Well, it’s similar to the question of temporality that we were talking about earlier. I’m very interested in the phenomenon of alternative publishing. I’ve written about mass-market publishing and I’ve written about middlebrow literature and the production process. Now, I’m very interested in alternative production, what’s called self-publishing – I’m very interested in girls’ zines. But what I’m especially interested in is what I call the afterlives of girls zines, or their itineraries through space and time. What has happened both to zines and the girls who created them in the 1990s since the 1990s? I’m interested in zine-ing from the 1990s and then the ways in which that zine-ing as a social practice produced ‘zinesters’ – girls of a certain type, people who become fans of zines – and the way in which those zines then travelled in different environments. So zines get taken up by zine librarians, they get archived in libraries, they get written about by academics, they get taught in high school classes by teachers who want to convince their students that they shouldn’t just be media consumers. It’s this itinerary and the articulation of zines to new practices that most interests me.</p>
<p>Why has that come about? That comes out of my feeling that there’s too much of a tendency to say, ‘Well, zines were not really radical’ or ‘Yes, they were radical’, to assume that we can see what their effects were, when I think that those effects are still playing out and they’re playing out through these different itineraries and connections among and between people who’ve had contact with them. So that’s what I’m particularly interested in doing. I’ve been thinking about zines for quite a long time, but now I really am embarking on what I would call an oral history of girls zine-ing in the 1990s and its afterlife.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>That’s fascinating. To my limited knowledge, such zines are provocative in a cultural shift taking place, enabling girls to work in a sphere that has predominantly been male-dominated, particularly in popular music. There’s a kind of cultural critique deeply invested in that writing, which is just remarkable.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Yes, and what were the ties to feminism? Some of that was explicit. But then I think girl zine-ing also got taken up by girls who didn’t have that kind of politicized background and didn’t have that kind of explicitly feminist focus, yet felt energized and activated by this kind of perspective. So in some way they’re subjectively constituted differently; I am trying to trace that.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>While we’re on this topic of alternative forms of publishing, I’m curious if you have any thoughts about some of the new ruptures that are beginning to break with regard to university presses and debates about marketing. I’m aware of scholars who have wonderful manuscripts who are kind of getting stiff-armed these days because they can’t guarantee 3000 sales. How do we think about junior faculty who are coming up through the ranks, who may have difficulties with books? Do the young professoriate and intelligentsia need to do with publishers what Napster did to the recording industry?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>What do you mean?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>Well, Napster basically did an ‘end run’ around the whole historical hegemony of the corporate form of musical distribution, which then impacted recording and publishing. Napster took the hinges off the gatekeeping. Add to this the institution of peer review, a model that is trumped by peer-to-peer; it is a different relationship of legitimization. Traditionally, a journal article could be in the pipeline for a year or so before it is seen. Yet, there has always been such an immediacy of intellectual production taking place all the time on campuses and other venues, most of which never gets logged in print. Conferences happen all the time, people give public presentations, ask vibrant and engaging questions. It seems to me that there are these digital opportunities, perhaps even digital libraries or digital publishing enterprises, that some universities are trying to open up as ways of somehow capturing this market, but nonetheless they don’t seem to be quite there.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Right. Obviously this is a huge problem, as the economics of publishing make it harder and harder for university presses to survive. They’re one of the first institutions to go, particularly for public universities that lose substantial money because of isolated budget cuts, etc. So university presses are struggling and in fact they may not survive. I think it’s not well understood that the American university system is utterly bound up with publishing and completely dependent on the publication system. Without that publication system, there’s really going to be a problem. So I think we are going to see many more electronic journals, many more websites where research is shared and collaboratively circulated rapidly.</p>
<p>What also has to happen – and this is where, it seems to me, locally-based activism has to happen – is that tenure committees need to be appraised of the situation and a really probing discussion about standards and rigour has to be had, because there still are too many people who believe that certain kinds of publications, certain kinds of journals, are the way that you evaluate faculty members’ productivity. If those faculty members are constrained from engaging in that because of larger factors, then that simply has to be changed. So there have to be people who are willing to make those arguments at the level of those committees. New standards are going to have to be worked out. New ideas of how scholarship circulates and how its evaluation gets done are going to have to be developed.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JC:</speaker>
<p>In some ways this brings us back to the sort of initiating impulses of cultural studies as an intellectual enterprise that confronted the boundaries of the traditional academic gatekeeping systems by way of paradigms of thought and disciplines. But now we’re talking about, in many ways, the survivability of intellectual discourse in a context in which market forces seem to want to reduce that down to vulgar pragmatism. In some ways it raises the question, not of cultural studies’ fit within the academic disciplines, or of cultural studies needing to do an ‘end run’ around the academy, but of cultural studies actually being something central to the very struggle of the contemporary university that is engaged in the critical questions of the larger political, economic and cultural context in which it is caught?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>JR:</speaker>
<p>Right. There were moments obviously in the 1970s, post-1968, as cultural studies thrived, where people wanted to be very critical of academic-based work and saw academic-based work, academic journal article writing, as something that was not fully politically responsible. Certainly a certain kind of critique can be made of that, but in this kind of context, where it looks like this kind of space for intellectual work is rapidly deteriorating, it becomes clear that the university is in fact a very complicated institution and that it preserves a certain kind of public space, albeit closed off and elite in some ways. It’s an essential place that has to be preserved.</p>
</speech>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Biographical note</title>
<p>Janice Radway is the Walter Dill Scott Professor of Communication Studies at Northwestern University, and Professor Emerita of Literature at Duke University. She is past president of the American Studies Association and has served as editor of the <italic>American Quarterly</italic>. Among her publications are <italic>Reading the Romance: Women, Patriarchy and Popular Literature</italic> (University of North Carolina Press, 1984), <italic>A Feeling For Books: Book-of-the-Month Club, Literary Taste and Middle-class Desire</italic> (University of North Carolina Press, 1999); she is co-editor of <italic>A History of the Book in America</italic> (with Carl F. Kaestle and David D. Hall, University of North Carolina Press 2008) and <italic>American Studies: An Anthology</italic> (with Kevin Gaines, Barry Shank and Penny von Eschen, Wiley-Blackwell, 2009). Currently she is exploring zines and their relationship to feminist theorising.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>