<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TJX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptjx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Theology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-571X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2044-2696</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040571X11430892</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040571X11430892</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Schizophrenia in young people and the <italic>nekrōsis</italic> of Christ</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0040571X11430892"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040571X11430892">Gloucestershire</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0040571X11430892"><email>anthony.harvey@virgin.net</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>115</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>92</fpage>
<lpage>98</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article describes the experience of a priest who has devoted the greater part of his ministry to offering companionship and community to a household of young people suffering from severe mental illness. His own description of their condition (which in due course began to affect his own spiritual state) is in terms of regression to an earlier stage of human evolution; but it has theological resonance in relation to Paul’s account of his own near-death experience in 2 Corinthians.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Darwin</kwd>
<kwd>exceptional ministry</kwd>
<kwd><italic>nekrōsis</italic></kwd>
<kwd>schizophrenia</kwd>
<kwd>2 Corinthians</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>March/April 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It is often observed that some of the most significant and creative movements in the history of the Church have their origins on the margin, outside institutional structures and even in defiance of them. Donald McNeile, a priest of the Church of England, has not started a movement; but for nearly forty years he has pioneered an extreme and innovatory form of ministry that has met with apparent indifference or incomprehension from Church authorities but which is validated by the help it has brought to young sufferers from severe mental illness and raises searching questions for therapists, for theologians and for the guardians of the Church’s traditional structures of ministry.</p>
<sec id="sec1-0040571X11430892"><title>The experience</title>
<p>Ordained after training at Mirfield, McNeile had curacies in working-class parishes in the north of England, after which (searching for a form of ministry more relevant to certain forms of suffering) he worked in a mental hospital near St Albans as a nursing assistant. In 1969 he moved to a village on the edge of Oxford, having bought a large and dilapidated farmhouse, with yard and fields, which he refurbished at his own expense with a view to pursuing a ministry of healing. There, with his wife Irmgard (a trained nurse from Germany), he began to give board and lodging to patients referred to him, first by the Warneford Hospital in Oxford and then by St Andrew’s, Northampton. These were all severe cases for whom every known form of medical and psychiatric treatment had been unavailing – for the most part seriously violent young men and women who, ever since they were teenagers, had returned to hospital again and again after brief periods of liberty in the community. A short time after he began this work the diocesan office was established within a few hundred yards of his house; but, perhaps understandably, neither the diocese nor his local parish church showed enthusiasm to support this ministry, which was generally regarded as quixotic, unsustainable and at times seriously dangerous for McNeile and his wife. For them, in the midst of bringing up their own family, it meant unremitting vigilance seven days a week, fifty-two weeks a year, for thirty-five years.</p>
<p>Apart from drastically reducing their medication (though still under medical guidance), he offered no professional help to the residents. Instead, he simply accepted them on their own terms and treated them with the dignity and respect he believed they deserved. Their self-respect and sense of being at home in the world grew through doing manageable tasks in the kitchen garden and with the animals and poultry, through unsupervised (but carefully planned) excursions to local shops, the launderette and the city centre, and through learning to take some responsibility themselves for their own community of about ten fellow-sufferers. It was a venture fraught from the start with uncertainty: things could go wrong at any time. But the pent-up frustration and rage these sufferers had formerly been projecting on to hospital staff, their families and the outside world could now be focused on a single individual – their unprotected host. When in due course this came to a head and erupted in violence, authority figures had to be called in – the GP, the duty social worker, the psychiatrist and the police (always the most humane). But then it was the turn of the violent one, in one crowded hour, to have a voice (always denied up to now), to take the stage, to be in command, to be the one laying down the law. A process of negotiation could begin, as it were between equals. The young schizophrenic was helped to see that there were just two options: either to persist in violent rebellion and return immediately to virtual incarceration and loss of liberty in an institution, or to persevere in a still accepting household with its companionship, its tolerance and its potential for dignity and freedom. In the end the majority chose the latter, and were eventually restored to a condition in which they could find a place in their families and in the wider society. McNeile is shy of talking about a ‘success rate’; but he does not hesitate to claim he has brought to many of them release from the deadlock and isolation of their rage, and a small new beginning – even a return home – to individuals for whom every form of conventional treatment and restraint had been ineffective. Parents would refer to the change as ‘getting the old John/Joan back again’. They seldom asked how it had been done; nor could McNeile easily have explained it to them. But something had happened for which’resurrection’ was at least a possible metaphor.</p>
<p>Without his wife’s unfailing help McNeile could not have done it. It was she who learnt to listen and respond to the household’s incoherent and sometimes barely intelligible accounts of themselves. These people had their own stories to tell: and here was someone who believed them, accepted them and valued them. But his own role was crucial. He understood that, in such serious cases, it was necessary that there should be a person always available, not merely to listen, and not merely to endure patiently and unresistingly the other’s urge to vent a lifetime’s anger and frustration on any individual or object within reach – dishes and furniture were routinely destroyed – but to continue to accompany the sufferer even when all the resources of a non-judgemental and unprotesting acceptance appeared to be making no headway and achieving no change in the situation. At these moments McNeile was personally confronted with the real possibility that this whole costly enterprise was futile. When it seemed that all hell was let loose, that faith, hope and love were all equally ineffectual and that one might have to abandon any belief in the possibility of redemption, then one was beginning to share the depth of despair and darkness being endured by the person one was trying to help. But by not turning away at this point (other ‘engagements’ were never allowed to intervene or provide a pretext for withdrawal), by not adopting a professional ‘distance’ (as other professional carers have been trained to do), and by continuing to endure the agony, McNeile made it possible for the sufferer to find (perhaps for the first time ever) a companion, one who would never command or dictate, never evade or withdraw, and with whom a personal relationship could be formed such that no act of violence and rebellion would sever it.</p>
<p>It was thus that McNeile began to understand his own vocation as one that involved standing alongside the sufferers and accompanying them into the darkest moments of human experience until some form of remission and healing could take place; but it was only in the last years of this ministry that he became fully aware of the personal cost this had involved. In exchange for the companionship he had offered, he had taken into himself something of the utter dislocation of these sick persons’ minds. He had experienced, with them, a sense of life being lost beyond recall, a meaningless void from which there seemed to be no return, an irrecoverable relapse into a state of existence that removed all possibility of being at home in the world. For him, this became a spiritual crisis from which he was rescued only by the intuition – unpremeditated and unprepared for – that Christ had been there before him, and that, even there, resurrection was a possibility, a reality.</p>
<p>Had his life’s work been a form of Christian ministry? Not necessarily; for it was a ministry that involved moments when faith and hope seemed to have no place and ‘love to the loveless shown’ seemed totally ineffective: physical and emotional stamina, and a dogged determination not to abandon the sufferer, had seemed the only resources. But McNeile, as a priest, felt impelled to find a theology that would make sense of it in Christian terms. A wise friend, a bishop, gave him a simple clue: <italic>Holy Saturday</italic>. And this, for Donald McNeile, led down pathways of discovery.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0040571X11430892"><title>Holy Saturday</title>
<p>What happened on Holy Saturday? Christian tradition, on the strength of some enigmatic words in 1 Peter (3.19; 4.6), affirms that there was a ‘descent’ – <italic>descensus ad inferos.</italic> At first this was imagined, quite literally, as a downward trajectory to the ‘underworld’ of the dead; the early (possibly second-century) <italic>Acts of Pilate</italic> offers a vivid description of the defeat of Satan, the ruler of the Underworld, and the breaking down of the gates of hell. But it could also be understood as a powerful metaphor, suggesting a visitation to some other realm – that of the dead – where Christ’s victory over evil and death could be acknowledged and in some way appropriated. Given the (by then) almost universal belief in life after death and in the existence of myriads of ‘spirits’ who had died before the time of Christ, there must be some ‘place’ where Christ could go to join them; and a descent ‘downwards’ seemed an appropriate metaphor – down from heaven, down to hell, and only then ‘up’ to the Father, carrying redeemed humanity ‘upward’ with him. This belief lies at the heart of Irenaeus’ doctrine of ‘recapitulation’, which stemmed from the word used in Ephesians 1.10 (<italic>anakephelaiousthai</italic>) to describe the totality of Christ’s agency ‘recapitulating everything on heaven and on earth’. Those ‘under the earth’ could hardly be excluded.</p>
<p>This metaphor had immediate resonance for McNeile. Indeed we apply it, quite naturally and unconsciously, when we recognize that the truth about ourselves requires looking ‘down’ into our past: we have to go ‘down’ with penitence into earlier fears, frustrations and traumas if we are to be brought ‘up’ through grace into the light of a present that can be forgiven and redeemed by Christ. So much is involved in any serious quest for Christian self-understanding. But McNeile’s experience has led him to extend the metaphor very much further. Our age, our whole mentality, is necessarily post-Darwinian. The beasts and demons deep down in our psyche are relics of a past that goes far back through history into geological time. We are what we are because of what we have evolved from. The basic instincts of the cave man – the survivor, the hunter, the aggressive predator – still torment our subconscious. In schizophrenics these may surface at the level of consciousness, inducing all manner of violence, acquisitiveness and the implacable will to prevail over all opposition. To those in this condition, what we call the civilized world of the twenty-first century (its family obligations, its societies and institutions) may seem nothing but a set of intolerable constraints on primordial urges. All authority figures – professionals, parents, even friends hoping to persuade by reason and affection – are a threat to be resisted and if possible overcome. McNeile can then ask, Is it not <italic>this</italic> humanity, with the full weight of its primitive past, that Christ came ‘down’ to redeem? In Irenaeus’ terms, is it now, not the Adam of the Garden of Eden and his descendants who have to be rescued from the power of evil, but our much more distant ancestors, only just beginning to emerge into moral consciousness? If we are to believe that the Christian story is valid for all human beings, including those of the past, and that Christ ‘recapitulated’ the whole of human history, must we not extend this history back to its very earliest phase of evolution and believe that we can be redeemed even from the atavistic state into which, through acute mental illness, an individual may still ‘descend’? When, in the darkness of these depths, some light dawns (perhaps through encountering for the first time the possibility of an enduring relationship with another human being) and an ‘ascent’ begins (as McNeile has usually found it to do, both for the sufferer and for himself), it seems appropriate to talk of ‘resurrection’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0040571X11430892"><title>The crisis in Second Corinthians</title>
<p>McNeile’s evolutionary analysis would have to be tested in the disciplines of anthropology, psychology and sociology. But I believe there is a theological account of his experience that may be found already in the New Testament, in particular in the spiritual crisis underlying Paul’s Second Letter to the Corinthians. This letter was written, Paul tells us, following the experience of having ‘despaired of life’ (1.10). There is no means of knowing what the circumstances of the crisis had been. Possibly a spell of near-lethal persecution, more likely an attack of acute illness. But the effect had evidently been traumatic. For Paul himself, who had previously talked confidently of being among those who would be alive at the imminent return of Christ (1 Thess. 4.15), this confrontation with imminent death (involving, as we shall see, the experience of black despair in the face of it) must have caused a personal crisis: surely his mission and apostleship should have been proof against such things? Moreover it had evidently unleashed scepticism: the man who had so confidently proclaimed himself to be beyond criticism as an apostle was now shown to be a fraud; his desperate condition was surely nothing but a demonstration that his gospel was unavailing against the justice of God, who would inevitably bring retribution upon him for his secret faults. To meet this criticism (and doubtless to strengthen his own faith) Paul developed – possibly for the first time in western thought – a theology of physical suffering that revealed it to be, not a contradiction of the life of faith, nor a negative episode to be surmounted by stoical endurance, but a profound experience with a positive potential for himself and for others.</p>
<p>This theological understanding of suffering was evidently based upon his own experience, and in the course of the letter he enumerates (possibly with an element of rhetorical exaggeration) the trials he had endured. But in the course of the crucial discussion in chapter 4 of the meaning of suffering borne in solidarity with Christ, he makes the extraordinary claim to be ‘bearing in my body the <italic>nekrōsis</italic> of Jesus’ (2 Cor. 4.10). The word <italic>nekrōsis</italic> is rare and puzzling. Literally, it means the physical condition of a corpse. Metaphorically, it could describe the ‘deadness’ of the heart or the emotions (as in an ancient textual variant of Mark 3.5 D, ‘Jesus was grieved at the <italic>nekrōsis</italic> of their hearts’). But there is evidence that it was occasionally used for the increasingly corpse-like condition of one who is close to death.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0040571X11430892">1</xref></sup> In this passage it is usually translated ‘the death’ of Jesus, and interpreted as a figurative way of speaking of the solidarity of the Christian sufferer with the experience of Christ before and during the crucifixion. But, on the cross, Jesus is reported to have prayed in words drawn from Psalm 22.2 (‘My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?’). This may be a factual report by a bystander; more likely it is the interpretation offered by the evangelist or his source of the cry (<italic>eli</italic>, ‘my God’) which Jesus was heard (or imagined) to utter in the moments before his death. But in either case it is probable that the mental and physical condition of Jesus at that moment was such that the psalm was felt by him, or believed by others, to be appropriate to his situation. The psalm is the prayer of a righteous man apparently approaching death, still convinced that a righteous God could not abandon him in his extremity and therefore must surely rescue him before it was too late. But Jesus, before he actually expired, will have experienced the shock of realizing that his physical decline into death had become irreversible: his body was undergoing <italic>nekrōsis,</italic> becoming inexorably corpse-like, so that all possibility of rescue and vindication was extinguished. At this stage nothing was left to hope for, faith had become irrelevant. Nothing was left but the blackness of despair: all options were closed save the last spasms of a struggle for survival, like the feeble beating of a dying insect’s wings. It was a moment (in McNeile’s understanding) when human life reverted to a previous stage of its evolution, an atavistic sense of blind impotence in the face of a hostile world.</p>
<p>Paul goes on, ‘we are all our life being handed over to death’ (<italic>thanatos</italic>, 2 Cor. 4.11). What sort of ‘death’ is this? Might it be, not just a metaphor for extreme physical suffering, or the ‘dying to self’ that Paul (following Jesus) put at the heart of Christian discipleship, but a word deliberately chosen by Paul to describe that primordial experience of utter darkness and defencelessness, entered into by Christ in his very last moments on the cross, and shared, exceptionally, by a Christian such as Paul? Paul, certainly, had a profound sense of the newness of life lived in unity with the risen Christ. He soon had to meet the objection that in his case at least (and doubtless that of others) this by no means excluded physical and mental suffering (he lists both in his account of the tribulations he had endured during his travels). Part of the argument in 2 Corinthians is to demonstrate that, far from invalidating his claims, these afflictions actually supported them by reason of the inner transformation taking place in the believer. But it now appears that this transformation did not even exclude an experience comparable with the primordial darkness of Christ’s <italic>nekrōsis</italic>, to which Paul may have been subjected or even have deliberately subjected himself.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0040571X11430892">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>But the passage also contains a sentence that has always puzzled interpreters: ‘Thus death is at work in us, and life in you’ (4.12). Why does Paul appear to distinguish between himself and others? Why does he not say, ‘thus death and life are both at work in us?’ – if not because he was aware that his experience had been exceptional, endured by only very few individuals for the benefit of ‘you’, that is, of all who enjoy their resurrection life without the searing interruption of the excruciating mental and physical sensation described as <italic>nekrōsis</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0040571X11430892"><title>Recognition and reception</title>
<p>Not all Christians are called to such extreme experiences, any more than all are called to be pacifists or hermits; nor can any such extreme form of Christian service be one that the institutional Church could be expected to make room for in its structures, any more than the professional agencies working with mental illness could easily adapt their procedures to such a costly form of therapy – though its evident effectiveness may be a challenge to conventional practice.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0040571X11430892">3</xref></sup> But some of the most profound and creative movements in the Church have begun from the margin of normal church life – the foundation of Anglican religious orders, the great missionary societies, the healing ministry and, today, widespread stirrings of a desire to explore new forms of spirituality and community. These have subsequently become recognized as representing a vocation for some Christians – perhaps only a few, and certainly not all. The first step must be the recognition and acknowledgement of such a ministry as a valid expression of Christian experience and understanding. May not McNeile’s lonely journey, unassimilable as it may appear to be into normal Church life and Church institutions, provide an impetus from the margin to stimulate thought and action within the ongoing life of the Church? And may it not also witness to an experience (known, I have suggested, to St Paul) that is inaccessible to most but is nevertheless integral to a full understanding of what is involved in the central Christian mystery? God became man and thus, through that man’s story of ‘descent’ into regions of (as it seems) primordial darkness and rebellion, and ‘ascent’ from there into the realized promise of resurrection life, achieved the redemption of humanity, and with it the ‘recapitulation’ of all things, stretching back even to the earliest stages of evolution, and thereby offering hope to those whose mental condition, in its uncomprehending rejection of civilized restraint, is comparable to the blind struggle for survival of our most primitive ancestors.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group><title>Notes</title>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0040571X11430892"><label>1</label><p>See A. E. Harvey, <italic>Renewal through Suffering: A Study of 2 Corinthians</italic> (Edinburgh: T&amp;T Clark, 1996), p. 58 and n. 8. McNeile’s experience suggests a significance in Paul’s use of this word which goes beyond the one argued for there. For references to ancient medical sources, see John T. Fitzgerald, <italic>Cracks in an Earthen Vessel</italic>, SBL Diss. Series 99 (Atlanta, Georgia: Scholars Press, 1988), p. 177.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0040571X11430892"><label>2</label><p><italic>paradidometha</italic> in 2 Cor. 4.11 may be a middle, not a passive form, meaning, not ‘we are handed over’, but ‘we hand ourselves over’, as suggested by Fitzgerald, <italic>Cracks in an Earthen Vessel</italic>, p. 180. Cf. also 1 Peter 2.23, Christ ‘handed himself over’ (the verb <italic>paredidou</italic> is active with an unexpressed object).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0040571X11430892"><label>3</label><p>Soteria Houses, described as ‘small, homelike, quiet, supportive, protective and tolerant social environments’ and founded in response to the Soteria Research Project in the USA, exist in a number of European countries and use non-medical staff with a minimum of medication. This approach has been found to be not necessarily more expensive than conventional psychiatric treatment.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes><title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Anthony Harvey</bold> was formerly a Lecturer in Theology (New Testament) at Oxford University, and Canon and Sub-Dean of Westminster. He was also for a few years a part-time chaplain at the Warneford Hospital, Oxford.</p>
</notes>
</back>
</article>