<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">QHR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spqhr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Qual Health Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Qualitative Health Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-7323</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7557</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732312448541</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049732312448541</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Pearls, Pith, and Provocation</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Patient and Public Involvement in the Coproduction of Knowledge</article-title>
<subtitle>Reflection on the Analysis of Qualitative Data in a Mental Health Study</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Gillard</surname><given-names>Steve</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049732312448541">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>Lucy</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1049732312448541">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>Kati</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049732312448541">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lucock</surname><given-names>Mike</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1049732312448541">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1049732312448541">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1049732312448541"><label>1</label>St George’s, University of London, London, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1049732312448541"><label>2</label>University of Southampton, Southampton, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1049732312448541"><label>3</label>University of Huddersfield, Huddersfield, United Kingdom</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1049732312448541"><label>4</label>Kingston University, Kingston, United Kingdom</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049732312448541">Steve Gillard, Section of Mental Health, St George’s, University of London, Cranmer Terrace, London SW17 0RE, UK Email: <email>sgillard@sgul.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Mental Health</issue-title>
<fpage>1126</fpage>
<lpage>1137</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Patient and public involvement in health research is increasingly well established internationally, but the impacts of involvement on the research process are hard to evaluate. We describe a process of qualitative data analysis in a mental health research project with a high level of mental health service user and carer involvement, and reflect critically on how we produced our findings. Team members not from research backgrounds sometimes challenged academic conventions, leading to complex findings that would otherwise have been missing. An essential component of how we coproduced knowledge involved retaining methodological flexibility so that nonconventional research voices in the team could situate and critique what was conventionally known. Deliberate and transparent reflection on how “who we are” informed the knowledge we produced was integral to our inquiry. We conclude that reflecting on knowledge (co)production is a useful tool for evaluating the impact of patient and public involvement on health research.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>epistemology</kwd>
<kwd>health care, users’ experiences</kwd>
<kwd>interpretive methods</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge construction</kwd>
<kwd>mental health and illness</kwd>
<kwd>qualitative analysis</kwd>
<kwd>reflexivity</kwd>
<kwd>research participation</kwd>
<kwd>self-care</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Patient and public involvement in health care research has become increasingly common internationally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049732312448541">Holmes, Stewart, Garrow, Anderson, &amp; Thorpe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049732312448541">Mosavel, Simon, van Stade, &amp; Buchbinder, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049732312448541">Schneider et al., 2004</xref>) and is now a requirement in most publically funded research in the United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049732312448541">Department of Health, 2006</xref>). The recent history of active involvement in the research process of people who use health and social care services is well documented and has begun to be systematically evaluated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049732312448541">Staley, 2009</xref>). The involvement of mental health service users in research has been particularly well described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049732312448541">Sweeney, Beresford, Faulkner, Nettle, &amp; Rose, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>It has been argued that, given the expertise that people experiencing mental health problems have in managing their lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049732312448541">Faulkner &amp; Layzell, 2000</xref>), building an evidence base for mental health services should be conducted as a marriage of expertise by experience and expertise by profession (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049732312448541">Faulkner &amp; Thomas, 2002</xref>). The difficulties of assessing the epistemological impact on the research process of involving service users have been acknowledged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049732312448541">Smith et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049732312448541">Staley, 2009</xref>). Without this insight, the knowledge claims of research involving patients and the public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049732312448541">Beresford, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1049732312448541">Simpson &amp; House, 2002</xref>) remain hard to assess. The potential for that research to improve health care practice is constrained as a result, especially when strict hierarchies prevail about what constitutes good scientific evidence.</p>
<p>A small, qualitative study of organizational change in a United Kingdom mental health service organization undertaken by some of the authors identified impacts on the design of the study and on the processes of data collection and data analysis resulting from involvement of mental health service users as members of the research team (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049732312448541">Gillard, Turner, et al., 2010</xref>). In addition, a reflexive process undertaken by the team suggested that service user involvement not only had added “expertise by experience” to the research process but also to some extent had changed the process. Some of the academic conventions of doing research about mental health had been challenged, and there was something different about the way the research had been done as a result.</p>
<p>Recent thinking about science and society has labeled this different way of doing research as the “coproduction” of knowledge, a blurring of the boundaries between scientific practitioners and those on the receiving end of scientific enquiry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049732312448541">Nowotny, Scott, &amp; Gibbons, 2001</xref>). A move away from conventional scientific research, led by a single academic discipline based within a university department, toward a model that involves a range of scientific and nonscientific expertise—an “expert laity”—has been noted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049732312448541">Gibbons et al., 1994</xref>). This new means of coproducing scientific knowledge has been characterized as
<disp-quote><p>transdisciplinary rather than mono- or multidisciplinary. It is carried out in nonhierarchical, heterogeneously organized forms which are essentially transient. It is not being institutionalized primarily within university structures. [It] involves the close interaction of many actors throughout the process of knowledge production and this means that knowledge production is becoming more socially accountable. . . . Overall, the process of knowledge production is becoming more reflexive and affects at the deepest levels what shall count as “good science.” (Gibbons et al., p. vi)</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Coproduction has some clear similarity to participatory action research (PAR) or community-based participatory research (CBPR; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049732312448541">Mosavel et al., 2005</xref>), especially in the way trust, collaboration, shared decision making, and shared ownership of the research across the range of stakeholders are sought. An important distinction is that PAR/CBPR strives to produce action and change as an integral part of the research process. In the research project considered here—commissioned through the university sector—the more traditional academic approach of producing new knowledge was the end point of the process.</p>
<p>The integration of different episteme in the production of knowledge about health has been documented. For example, health care practitioners have been shown to integrate scientific, evidence-based knowledge with other types of knowledge to inform their practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049732312448541">James, Andershed, Gustavsson, &amp; Ternestedt, 2010</xref>), and mental health researchers have described a reflexive process of collectively constructing knowledge as a methodological solution to analyzing qualitative interviews when the face validity of the data is hard to establish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049732312448541">Patterson, Hart, &amp; Weaver, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>In this article, we reflect critically on a systematically documented process of data analysis to describe the way knowledge was produced through that process, and to consider who produced that knowledge. We examine a mental health research project that had a high level of involvement of people with personal experience of mental health issues, of using mental health services, or of caring for someone with mental health issues, alongside clinical and conventional university researchers. The aims of the research project were to investigate ways in which United Kingdom mental health service organizations were supporting people to care for their own mental health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049732312448541">Gillard, Edwards, et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>We focus exclusively on describing and reflecting on the process of analyzing data, which is a key site of knowledge production in qualitative research. The detailed processes of reporting qualitative analysis are often lacking in research articles, in part because the complex, messy, and often intuitive tasks involved do not always sit easily with the academic conventions required of clean retrospective reporting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049732312448541">Simons, Lathlean, &amp; Squire, 2008</xref>). In the study, we adopted a team approach to qualitative analysis that necessitated a detailed documentary record of the analytical decisions made. We use this documentary record to track and articulate the extent to which the team engaged in knowledge coproduction, from preliminary analyses conducted early in the study through to the writing up of findings and recommendations published in the final report.</p>
<sec id="section1-1049732312448541">
<title>Aim</title>
<p>In this article we aim to (a) describe the team process of qualitative data analysis undertaken in a study of support for self-care in mental health in the United Kingdom, (b) reflect on the extent to which we coproduced knowledge through the qualitative analysis process as a research team with a high level of patient and public involvement, and (c) consider the implications of research coproduction for study findings. In the discussion of our analysis process, we also consider whether the concept of research coproduction offers a tool for considering the impact of service user and carer involvement in mental health services research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1049732312448541">
<title>The Team</title>
<p>Our research team of 17 individuals comprised health service researchers (<italic>n</italic> = 6), a human resource management researcher, service user (patient) and carer (family or friend caregiver) researchers (<italic>n</italic> = 7), clinicians (<italic>n</italic> = 4), and National Health Service (NHS; U.K. statutory health service) managers (<italic>n</italic> = 2). Some members of the team had more than one role and have been counted in each relevant category; one of the carer researchers was also a clinician, one of the clinicians was also a manager in the NHS, and one of the managers was also a health services researcher. All service user and carer researchers had first-degree-level education, but only two service user researchers had experience of research outside of the context of completing an undergraduate degree. Some service user researchers were still receiving formal care and treatment for mental health issues. Two of the clinicians had little experience of research prior to their involvement in this project.</p>
<p>The study was initially led by the university members of the team, with support from clinical and managerial members of the team. The role of the latter group was to ensure the research reflected priorities of health service delivery and to facilitate access to health service sites. Two service user researchers were involved in the team from the outset, developing the proposal and supporting the involvement of other service user and carer researchers. One was already employed as a researcher in a university, and the other as a researcher and trainer in the NHS. Five service user and carer researchers, who undertook the data collection and much of the analysis at each of the three study sites, were recruited to their positions through open employment recruitment and selection processes. Personal experience of mental health issues or of caring for someone with personal experience of mental health issues and some prior research experience were stipulated as essential criteria for applicants to these posts. These researchers were employed by the relevant university or health service provider organization, giving them full access to organizational facilities and staff development opportunities. Bespoke training on research interviewing and data analysis was given by other members of the research team and external providers as required.</p>
<p>Frequent, usually weekly, meetings were held in each study site where the service user and carer researchers were supervised by the site lead. Five whole-team meetings took place throughout the study, with communications and discussions taking place by teleconference and email between meetings. One service user researcher left the project after 15 months and was replaced, again through an open recruitment process. Continuity was promoted at this site because another service user researcher remained in post throughout.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049732312448541">
<title>The Study: Supporting Self-Care in Mental Health</title>
<p>We employed a mixed-methods cohort study design in this study. A total of 120 new users of a range of adult mental health services supporting self-care at three case study sites undertook qualitative and quantitative interviews, both when they started using the service and again 9 months later. Participants’ expectations and understandings of self-care were explored in qualitative interviews at baseline. Their experiences of the self-care support service were explored in follow-up interviews 9 months later. Quantitative data collected at baseline and follow-up included sociodemographics and psychiatric history, service use, and a range of standardized measures of psychosocial outcome. Participants’ informal carers, managers, and staff working in the self-care support services also undertook qualitative interviews about their views and experiences.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1049732312448541" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method of Analysis</title>
<p>In the self-care study, qualitative analysis proceeded through a number of stages, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1049732312448541">Figure 1</xref>. Early stages of the process were repeated as each data set (service user, carer, and staff interviews) was collected. We describe each stage of the analysis process in detail below and illustrate the process with examples of analytical material generated during the process.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Flow chart of the analysis process</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section5-1049732312448541">
<title>Stage 1: Preliminary Analysis</title>
<p>Service user and carer researchers had been involved in the process of developing semistructured interview schedules and conducted the vast majority of interviews. In carrying out interviews, they were encouraged to ask additional questions to follow lines of inquiry that seemed to be relevant to participants (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049732312448541">Gillard, Edwards, et al., 2010</xref>). These same researchers then undertook preliminary analyses of a subsample of interviews. Service user and carer researchers were trained together in using data coding tools common to inductive thematic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049732312448541">Ritchie &amp; Lewis, 2003</xref>). We used an open coding approach to organize text into categories on the basis of content of the talk in the interviews.</p>
<p>Service user and carer researchers were encouraged to create their own thematic categories, guided by the data, as they read and coded the text. In so doing we recognized that a layer of interpretation would inevitably begin to be imposed from researchers’ individual perspectives. To keep track of this interpretive process, researchers were directed to keep memos of decisions they made about the creation and labeling of new categories. We summarized this preliminary analysis into tables using examples from the text to illustrate each category. An example of a page from a summary document is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1049732312448541">Table 1</xref>, documenting one researcher’s preliminary analysis of the first section—Getting Involved—of two baseline interviews with service user participants.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Example of Preliminary Analysis</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1049732312448541" xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Source</th>
<th align="center">Getting Involved<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1049732312448541">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Participant 2</td>
<td>INFORMATION GIVEN (about intervention): “I’ve seen the videotape.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>DIFFICULTY CONCENTRATING: Felt that mind was wandering, difficulty taking in information</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>LACK OF KNOWLEDGE (of intervention): “I don’t know an awful lot about it.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>SERVICE USER ROLE IN GETTING INVOLVED: “We had to go to it. . . . I didn’t think I had a choice. . . . I don’t really mind.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>STAFF REFERRAL: Service user reports if someone had not said that they had to attend groups they would not have attended.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 3</td>
<td>STAFF REFERRAL: Staff nurse at rehabilitation unit suggested she get involved.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AMBIVALENCE (ambivalent about taking part): “I just thought I’d give it a go, it seems to be well spoken of so I thought I’d give it a go.”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1049732312448541">
<label>a</label>
<p>Preliminary analysis of data collected in the first section of the service user baseline interview under the heading Getting Involved.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1049732312448541">
<title>Stage 2: Developing an Analytical Framework</title>
<p>At whole-team meetings, the service user and carer researchers who had undertaken the preliminary analysis presented their analyses of each successive set of interviews (e.g., service user baseline, staff) to the whole research team. We used a process of face-to-face team discussion to produce a single analytical framework, employing a modified matrix approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049732312448541">Averill, 2002</xref>) to organize and compare analyses from the different sites. Prior to each meeting, we compiled preliminary analyses onto a single matrix that presented sections of the interview schedule on the horizontal axis and case study sites on the vertical axis. Each cell of the matrix was populated with a summary of the relevant preliminary analysis. At meetings we projected these matrices onto a screen to facilitate discussion. We used an additional row on the matrix to record the discussion as it took place, with members of the team offering their individual interpretations of the data as they were presented. When we offered different interpretations, we considered in our discussion why different members of the team understood the data differently. Through this process we developed and refined, as a team, an inclusive set of themes that enabled us to (a) integrate the analyses from each site and (b) capture the interpretive perspectives of all members of the team. An example of a page from the matrix is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1049732312448541">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Example of Matrix Analysis</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1049732312448541" xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Unit of Analysis</th>
<th align="center">Getting Involved<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1049732312448541">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Site 1</td>
<td><bold>Referral:</bold> Self (active) and other</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><bold>Motivation:</bold> High or low</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Site 2</td>
<td>Given information/watched video (about intervention)/by care coordinator/looked quite good</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>“I didn’t know a lot about it”; difficulty taking in information</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Staff referral/had to go/lack of choice/would not have gone if had not been told to</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Suggested by care coordinator/“think about it for a week”/recommended for anxiety</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Intervention part of care plan Ambivalence/“give it a go,” “Well spoken of”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Site 3</td>
<td>Unclear referral process; discover by word of mouth, leaflet on ward</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Referral/discharged/“pushed”/encouraged by psychiatrist, mental health team, social services</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Clinicians not aware, reservations about risk; alcohol/drug use, abstinence, timing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Self-referral, choice, control, own decision, motivation; part of/outside of care planning</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>To keep safe, reduce isolation &amp; risk of self-harm; alternative to medication, day care; try it out</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Integrated analysis</td>
<td><bold>Referral</bold>—self vs. told—lack of clarity—actively sought information (links to motivation) vs. staff direction (coercion?); contradiction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Professional staff not clear about process—information provided through services then self-referral</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Question arises referring to staff attitudes to self-care/mental health and so who they pass information to</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Supported self-referral—spectrum of self-referral experiences</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Does referral process affect whether it is self-care or treatment?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Self-care seen as easy option for professional staff—abdicating responsibility</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><bold>Motivation</bold>—Other interest/reason to go, wanting to stay involved, not wanting endings</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Taken out of comfort zone as part of “getting better”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Timing—too unwell/ready to take part—waiting a few weeks until ready—choice about when to start</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Internal &amp; external reason to participate—reducing harm vs. taking opportunities</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>How does trust “use” self-care to “manage” people with long-term conditions?; managing relapse or recovery</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Perception that trust’s motivation is closing services/saving money</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Depends on other opportunities available locally (e.g., arts, community education)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1049732312448541">
<label>a</label>
<p>Summaries of preliminary analyses of the first section of the service user baseline interview—Getting Involved—as undertaken at each site and then integrated through research team discussion</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Following each meeting we expanded and modified as necessary the set of themes that constituted the analytical framework. This work was undertaken by the lead author (a health services researcher) and by service user and carer researchers. We circulated drafts of the framework across the team to ensure that idiosyncrasies of data at all sites were captured. Examples of themes and descriptors derived from the Getting Involved section of the service user baseline interview are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1049732312448541">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Examples of Categories and Descriptors Derived From Analysis of Baseline Service User Interviews</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1049732312448541" xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Category</th>
<th align="center">Descriptor</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>(Self-)referral process</td>
<td>Experiences and views on referral or self-referral to the self-care project</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other treatment options</td>
<td>Availability or lack of availability of other treatments that might have affected reasons for becoming involved in self-care project</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Information and support (or lack of)</td>
<td>Description/views on information and support given about the self-care project and/or the process of referral/self-referral to the project</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Timing</td>
<td>Views on the timing of referral/involvement in self-care and its appropriateness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Motivation</td>
<td>Reasons for choosing/agreeing to attend self-care project</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Practical expectations</td>
<td>Concrete examples of what the participant expects to be doing as part of the self-care project</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049732312448541">
<title>Stage 3: Applying the Analytical Framework</title>
<p>We then used these themes and descriptors to code all interviews in each qualitative data set, building up a comprehensive database of coded text. Again, the vast majority of this work was undertaken by service user and carer researchers. When interview data did not fit comfortably into the framework, or when researchers were unsure how to code data, we resolved issues and modified the framework through team discussion (facilitated by email in between meetings). These discussions became an important part of the analysis process. An example of this process of clarifying and modifying themes and their descriptors is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1049732312448541">Table 4</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Modification of Themes: Example of Process</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1049732312448541" xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Researcher</th>
<th align="center">Communication<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1049732312448541">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Email discussion of use of the “personal philosophies” theme when coding service user interviews</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Researcher 1</td>
<td>I just wanted to clarify a few things about coding . . . when people define self-care very generally, e.g., “self-care is looking after yourself,” I’ve been putting this under <italic>“personal philosophies”</italic>?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Researcher 2</td>
<td>This is how I have used it. I wanted to make sure I was using this correctly, e.g., a lady talks about self-care as doing things for herself, not wanting to rely on things. I’ve coded this under <italic>“personal philosophies.”</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Discussion returned to by email as staff interview data were analyzed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Researcher 2</td>
<td>I have coded staff attitudes affecting service user involvement—they are not always supportive of this—under <italic>“new roles,” “barriers + facilitators,”</italic> and <italic>“general relationships with staff,”</italic> but do we need a new theme about staff attitudes and how this affects service user involvement and self-care? The participant talks about values and the importance of the value base of staff.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Researcher 1</td>
<td>I personally feel that the <italic>“personal philosophies”</italic> theme is sufficient for this as it includes attitudes, but perhaps we need to say more about values in the descriptor. I think of <italic>“personal philosophies”</italic> being more about attitudes to self-care than to service users, but I think it could go here as well as under <italic>“personal challenges”</italic> or <italic>“implementation challenges.”</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Researcher 2</td>
<td>I feel there is already a lot under <italic>“personal philosophies”</italic> and I feel we would lose this data on attitudes and values because it’s not always about self-care but service user involvement and attitudes to other staff and service users.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">New theme of “staff attitudes” created, and descriptors of both “staff attitudes” and “personal philosophies” themes modified as a result of email discussion</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1049732312448541">
<label>a</label>
<p>Examples of text from email exchanges between service user and carer researchers as themes and descriptors were modified.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1049732312448541">
<title>Stage 4: Stakeholder Conferences</title>
<p>Toward the end of the project we presented our emerging analysis to groups of stakeholders at each of the case study sites. Participants comprised a total of 28 service users, 4 carers, 25 clinical staff, and 14 managers of mental health services. Participants included people who had taken part in the main study as well as others invited because they were involved in other similar interventions in their mental health service organizations (e.g., self-management programs, supported employment projects). Carers were partners of service users who attended with them. Clinicians included community mental health service staff, employment specialists, and psychological therapists. Managers included senior strategic managers, human resource managers, and managers of clinical services. We used structured group discussions to enable participants to discuss the relevance of each of the themes in terms of their own personal experience. Participants highlighted a number of issues as particularly relevant and offered interpretations of some issues that had not been in the forefront of our analyses. Examples of issues indicated in those feedback discussions are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1049732312448541">Table 5</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption><p>Examples of Feedback Conference Workshop Output</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1049732312448541" xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Sites<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1049732312448541">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Issues Indicated by Participants</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>All sites</td>
<td>Timing of self-care support must be appropriate to individual’s needs (must be well enough, but also if too well can be experienced as infantilizing or depressing; the importance of choice about when to seek support for self-care and self-referral)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Self-care experienced as “abandonment” by the trust (in the absence of parallel, ongoing access to trust services)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sites 1 and 2</td>
<td>Unclear relationship between (self-care) crisis plan and access to trust crisis services</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Risk of becoming “too comfortable” in the self-care project</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Site 1</td>
<td>Shared risk issues with related projects (self-management and depression; supported employment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxieties around groups (e.g., personal disclosure of difficult issues)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Site 2</td>
<td>Not separate enough from trust services</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Site 3</td>
<td>Creative arts as a vehicle for overcoming personal challenges and accessing mainstream community opportunities</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1049732312448541">
<label>a</label>
<p>Indication of where issues were raised at workshops at more than one site or were specific to individual sites</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1049732312448541">
<title>Stage 5: Asking Questions of the Qualitative Data</title>
<p>The application of the analytical framework described above represented a first-level analysis in which we aimed primarily to organize the data to facilitate a deeper analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049732312448541">Mason, 1996</xref>). Issues we identified at the feedback conference helped inform a series of specific questions we asked of the qualitative data set using the “query” function of the qualitative data analysis software. We generated additional queries through a process of synthesizing qualitative and quantitative analyses. When we found associations to be statistically significant in the quantitative data set, for example between particular participant characteristics and changes in outcome, those individual participant characteristics were assigned to interview transcripts in the database. We then ran queries that enabled us to compare qualitative data coded to relevant themes (e.g., Changes in Care) between particular groups of participants (e.g., participants who chose whether or not to take medication as prescribed). Examples of the queries we ran are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1049732312448541">Table 6</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-1049732312448541" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption><p>Examples of Queries Run on the Qualitative Data Set</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1049732312448541" xlink:href="10.1177_1049732312448541-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Quantitative Findings</th>
<th align="center">Queries (Themes by Attributes)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>A higher number of psychotropic medications and a lower Clinical Outcomes in Routine Evaluation (clinical severity) nonrisk score at baseline associated with higher quality of life at follow-up</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A lower number of psychotropic medications and choosing to take medication as prescribed at baseline associated with higher empowerment at follow-up</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Choosing not to take medication as prescribed at baseline was associated with higher mental health confidence at follow-up</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td>The following themes searched by “Choosing to take medication as prescribed” (yes—partial—no):<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Changes in care</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Changes in experiences of mental health</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Changes in self-care</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rationale for change</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Progress and moving on</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Medication</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p>Various members of the research team (including the lead researcher, and service user and carer researchers) then wrote “query reports” based on each query. In these reports we organized data in terms of specified axes of comparison (e.g., case study site, clinical severity of participants at baseline). We wrote narratives that sought to find meaning in commonalities and differences between comparison groups.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1049732312448541">
<title>Stage 6: Writing Up the Research</title>
<p>Through the process described above, we generated a “library” of query reports that we used as a resource to write sections of the final report. Once again, we assigned writing tasks to various members of the team. Drafted sections were then circulated to the whole team, going through a number of iterative revisions in the process. It has been noted that writing is a stage in the process of qualitative inquiry in its own right, that the act of writing makes things known to the researcher that would not otherwise have been known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049732312448541">Richardson, 2000</xref>). As such, we were concerned that our writing should continue to give voice to the range of interpretive perspectives within the team, even as that writing became the responsibility of a smaller number of individuals. We reflect on tensions that arose at the final writing-up stage of the process in some depth in the discussion section below.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1049732312448541" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The detailed documentation of our analysis process has enabled us to describe in depth the involvement of different members of the team, including service user and carer researchers, in the research process (Aim 1). This provides us with an opportunity to consider the extent to which knowledge was coproduced in our research (Aim 2). In the introduction we offered a working definition of research coproduction characterized by</p>
<list id="list1-1049732312448541" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>a move away from academically led research institutionalized within the university</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>a transdisciplinary approach involving a range of scientific and nonscientific expertise</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>nonhierarchical, heterogeneously organized forms of undertaking research</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>an increasing reflexivity and social accountability of knowledge production</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>a challenge to what is counted as “good science” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049732312448541">Gibbons et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049732312448541">Nowotny et al., 2001</xref>)</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In this discussion we adopt a “radical reflexive approach” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049732312448541">Cunliffe, 2003</xref>) to consider the extent to which our research was coproduced. We borrow this approach from a qualitative study about United Kingdom local government chief executives in which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049732312448541">Orr and Bennett (2009)</xref> considered the extent to which, as academic and practitioner, they jointly constituted the knowledge that emerged from the research, as opposed to a more simplistic production of an academic monologue. Where there is evidence that our work demonstrates these characteristics of coproduction, we also consider how the coproduction process has affected the study’s findings and recommendations (Aim 3). Finally, we consider the extent to which research coproduction offers a conceptual tool to evaluate the impact of service user and carer involvement on mental health services research.</p>
<sec id="section12-1049732312448541">
<title>How Were Service User and Carer Researchers Involved in the Research?</title>
<p>We illustrate the mechanics of service user and carer researcher involvement in our description of the process of generating an analytical framework from our interview transcripts (Stages 1 to 3). Service user and carer researchers were integral to the decision-making process about coding interview data alongside other members of the team; we also briefly indicated the role played by service user and carer researchers in developing and undertaking interviews. Service user and carer researchers often led on generating analytical categories and presenting these to the team for discussion and refinement. The creation of an additional Staff Attitudes category to preserve the distinctiveness of data capturing service user participants’ Personal Philosophies—Table 4—was an example of the growing confidence demonstrated by service user and carer researchers to make research decisions as the project progressed.</p>
<p>Researchers were at times concerned about the impact their personal interpretive perspectives might be having on the analytical decision-making process. We used repeated cycles of going back to the team to remain aware of this possibility but were also careful not to use the team to reduce analysis to an exercise in interrater reliability. Conventionally, much clinical research uses “triangulation by perspective” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049732312448541">Patton, 1990</xref>). Such an approach would have limited the production of knowledge to that which we could all reliably agree on. Instead, the range of perspectives in the team enabled us to elicit different possible interpretations of the data and to explore the particular validity of all interpretations by reflecting on the analytical lens—of health services researcher, clinician, service user, and so on—through which the interpretation was made (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049732312448541">Mason, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>For example, in our initial analyses of data coded under Getting Involved (Tables 1-3), we identified self-referral into support services as an important issue for research participants. Service user, carer, and clinical and organizational researchers all offered different perspectives on these data. The process of integrating, through team discussion, a range of perspectives enabled us to move beyond a simplistic analysis (see discussion of impact on findings below).</p>
<p>We were also able to invite other nonconventional research voices into the knowledge production process through our feedback conferences (Stage 4). Participants in those conferences—including service users and carers—flagged the importance of a range of issues that had not been prominent in our emerging analysis. For example, as a result of the feedback conferences, we revisited our data to make sure we acknowledged the ambivalence to self-care that some participants expressed. This ambivalence included both the sense of abandonment some service users associated with what they experienced as being discharged from supportive services to self-care and the risk of creating new sites of dependence where peer groups successfully created a strong sense of identity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1049732312448541">Table 5</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1049732312448541">
<title>To What Extent Did We Coproduce Knowledge in Our Research?</title>
<p>We described above our integration of different interpretive perspectives in the research team to create a more nuanced picture of self-care. Sometimes this process fostered tensions within the team, particularly in the later writing-up stages (Stages 5 and 6). These tensions are particularly well illustrated in the writing up of findings around the relationship between psychiatric medication and self-care (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1049732312448541">Table 6</xref>). Medication had not emerged as an important theme in the qualitative analysis, but the parallel quantitative analysis had revealed a number of statistically significant associations between medication (including whether or not participants chose to take their medication as prescribed) and changes in outcome measures (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1049732312448541">Table 6</xref>).</p>
<p>As a team we were able to offer a range of explanations for these different associations but were unable to agree on the importance of them. Some members of the team, especially service user researchers, insisted that even though these findings might be statistically significant, we had produced them only because, at the outset of the project, the university researchers had decided to ask structured, quantifiable questions about medication. The health services researchers on the team countered that, because the findings were there, we were duty bound to report them. On this issue in particular, the team discussion became very heated, although always focused on issues related to the data. The service user researchers asserted that simply accepting academic conventions would compromise both what they thought they had been told by participants during interviews and the trust and partnership developed thus far in the team. Finding a way through this tension felt very uncomfortable at times, and we eventually agreed to return to the qualitative data to explore the issue of medication in more depth.</p>
<p>We ran queries on the qualitative data set using qualitative analysis computer software that enabled us to compare medication accounts between groups of service users who reported choosing to take their medication as prescribed with those who had chosen not to. Through this analysis we revealed a complex set of experiences with and attitudes toward taking medication, its benefits and negative impacts on people’s lives, and the relationship of medication to self-care. Our writing up became an exercise in articulating tensions in the analysis as a means of trying to understand the complex relationship between self-care and medication.</p>
<p>The prominence of these findings related to medication had taken us all by surprise as none of the case study interventions had focused on medication. When the importance of medication findings was questioned, we were able to reflect on the “social accountability” of decisions we made about how to do the research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049732312448541">Gibbons et al., 1994</xref>). We had produced these findings because the structured questions we asked about medication were the sorts of questions that university researchers on the team routinely used in clinical studies. These studies had been positively peer reviewed by other academics. We noted the lack of coproduction—and involvement of service user and carer researchers—at the early stages of developing the funding bid for this research when these questions were included, uncritically, in the research protocol.</p>
<p>We had followed conventions of statistical analysis until a number of team members, primarily service user researchers, had strongly challenged the assumption that statistical significance meant that findings about medication were necessarily of such importance that they should dominate the study’s conclusions. In other words, what university members of the research team had seen at the study’s inception to “count as good science” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049732312448541">Gibbons et al., 1994</xref>) was challenged from perspectives outside of the conventional team. The impact of this process of challenging research conventions on our findings is considered below.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1049732312448541">
<title>How Did Coproduction Affect Research Findings?</title>
<p>Our reflection on the process of coproduction described above allows us to consider the impact of that process on research findings. For example, in our coproduced analysis of interview data concerning self-referral, different members of the team offered and advocated for the importance of different possible interpretations of the data. We noted professional “gatekeeping” of self-referral—wherein professionals’ protective attitudes to risk management determined who was allowed to “self-refer”—and also how service user participants were concerned with the safety of groups that were wholly open access. Our discussions foregrounded the recognition by clinicians, managers, and carers of the sense of empowerment experienced by service users who were exercising control over when and how they accessed services, as well as acknowledging the challenges that that presented to caring relationships.</p>
<p>This integrative approach to analysis enabled us to move beyond simplistic juxtaposition of service user accounts of being allowed or denied choice with clinician accounts of risk management. As a result, we made recommendations in our final report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049732312448541">Gillard, Edwards, et al., 2010</xref>) that added to ongoing debates about positive risk taking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049732312448541">Morgan, 2000</xref>), self-referral (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049732312448541">Rogers, Oliver, Bower, Lovell, &amp; Richards, 2004</xref>), and punitive discharge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049732312448541">Lester, Tritter, &amp; Sorohan, 2005</xref>) in mental health services.</p>
<p>The tensions noted in the team around integrating quantitative and qualitative analyses very directly affected the findings we produced. Our revisiting of the qualitative data around medication revealed an additional layer of interpretation that would otherwise have been missing from our findings. We found that service user participants who felt supported clinically made decisions either to take medication as prescribed or to come off medication as an important aspect of their self-care (compared to other participants who were still struggling with whether to take medication or not). Complex and subtle findings emerged about relationships between the service user and clinician, medication, choice, and self-care. Recommendations we made in our final report added to ongoing debate around medication and shared decision making (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049732312448541">Deegan &amp; Drake, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1049732312448541">Schauer, Everett, del Vecchio, &amp; Anderson, 2007</xref>), and concordance and adherence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049732312448541">Horne et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The broader literature on research coproduction suggests that sustainable change and translation of knowledge into practice is more likely when coproduction between practitioners and academics has taken place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049732312448541">Baumbusch et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049732312448541">Hall, 2006</xref>). In the health service management field, knowledge coproduction has been shown to close a relevance gap between research and practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049732312448541">Starkey &amp; Madan, 2001</xref>). The potential benefits of involving users of health services in writing up research—more hard-hitting and user-friendly reporting—have been noted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049732312448541">McLaughlin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1049732312448541">Sutton &amp; Weiss, 2008</xref>). However, a general lack of involvement of service user researchers in the writing up stage has also been identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049732312448541">Smith et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>In our case, the conventional, economically driven practice of disbanding a university-based research team once the funding has run its course and the final report to sponsors has been written did not work to our advantage. Even though we noted above the extent to which writing as an integral part of the analysis process during the project worked to realize and articulate coproduction in the research process, we were equally challenged by the drop off of coproduction as the research came to a close and the wider team disbanded.</p>
<p>For example, to complete the conventional medical school research cycle, it was necessary for the university members of the team to submit our main findings for publication in a high-impact medical journal. This required us to follow the detailed and exacting guidelines for the reporting of observational studies, Strengthening The Reporting of OBservational studies in Epidemiology (STROBE; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049732312448541">von Elm et al., 2007</xref>), and in so doing our painstaking qualitative analyses were reduced to the status of “other analyses” used to explore subgroups and confounders emerging in the statistical analysis. In fulfilling these requirements we lacked the space, methodologically as well as in terms of word count, both to articulate the subtlety of our coproduced findings and to report reflectively on how those findings were the product of the particular identities and perspectives of different members of the research team.</p>
<p>We were in danger of rewriting, or reproducing our research as an academic monologue as a result (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049732312448541">Orr &amp; Bennett, 2009</xref>), distilling the additional layers of meaning we had so carefully worked to uncover and articulate. Other ways and means of writing up and disseminating research can be pursued, but the university requires its researchers to prioritize high-impact, peer-reviewed output. We think that this challenge to knowledge coproduction in health services research remains unresolved and largely unexplored.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1049732312448541">
<title>Considering the Impact of Service User and Carer Involvement on Research</title>
<p>We began this discussion by presenting a generic definition of knowledge coproduction. We have shown above how coproduction in our research took on a particular form, shaped by the specifics of the project; a mental health services research project that introduced high levels of service user and carer involvement into an otherwise reasonably conventional, multidisciplinary clinical–academic research team. Coproduction of knowledge in our study was characterized as follows:</p>
<list id="list2-1049732312448541" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>High-value research decision-making roles were distributed across a research team including university, clinical, service user, carer, and managerial researchers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Different interpretations of data within the research team were owned and understood in terms of who offered the interpretation; proper consideration was given to the question of how who we are has shaped the knowledge we have produced.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Consideration was given to whether all members of the team were involved in the production of knowledge throughout the research project; when there was unevenness in the coproduction of knowledge, the impact of this was considered.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Methodological flexibility was allowed in the research process when the scientific conventions of how research is usually done in the university constrained the input of particular team members.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rigorous and critical reflection on why the research was done in the way it was (rather than just a rigorous application of scientific method) was integral to the conduct of the research.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Research outputs were attempted that reported critically on how knowledge was produced so readers of the research would be able to understand how findings were shaped by those involved.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>We suggest here that it is a self-conscious and explicit reflection on the process of knowledge coproduction, as described above, that in itself offers a conceptual tool for considering the impact of service user and carer involvement in mental health services research. Specifically, this means reflecting on the involvement of all members of the research team in the process of knowledge production, and not singling out the involvement of service user and carer researchers as a “radical” addition to a conventional academic team. Service user knowledge, or more specifically “survivor-produced knowledge,” has been described as a radical alternative to medically produced knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049732312448541">Rose, 2009</xref>). The limitations of seeing specific sites of knowledge production as radical have been noted in the past by critical epistemologists who have argued that knowledge produced from any one particular standpoint cannot exist autonomously from other knowledge in the same referential frame (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049732312448541">Harding, 1991</xref>); any knowledge can only be understood in relation to those other standpoints around it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049732312448541">Keller, 1984</xref>).</p>
<p>Our study shows how the power of service user and carer produced knowledge did not lie in its refuting of medically or academically produced knowledge, but in the opportunity it offered to situate and critique that more dominant discourse. The presence of service user and carer voices in the mental health research team did not oblige us to choose between alternative perspectives as more or less valid than each other, or that we should understand them as separate, irreconcilable accounts. Rather, we found that those different voices provided our research team with an opportunity to begin bridging the apparent dichotomy of what was conventionally known and what was “radically” known. Our university researchers lost their exclusive status as arbiters of good science. Instead, we asked ourselves how our respective contributions to the research process were socially situated, and what that meant for the knowledge that was produced.</p>
<p>We wondered if “doing good science” might be about this act of critical reflection itself and that, as a deliberate and transparent process, this reflection should become an integral component of doing research. So that knowledge claims made for the research can be understood in the context of their socially situated production—who was involved in the production of knowledge—both the means and meaning of coproduction should be made available to the reader of the research, as we have attempted to do in this article.</p>
<p>Coproducing knowledge in mental health services research thus goes beyond adding voices to an academic monologue—the aim of some methods of patient and public involvement—and instead conceptualizes a creative process of producing new knowledge through colloquy, the exploration and articulation of what different voices mean in relation to each other. Our systematic reflection on the extent to which knowledge was coproduced, aided by a detailed documentary record of the research process, offers a conceptual tool for evaluating the impact of service user and carer researchers on our research.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1049732312448541" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this article, we describe a team process of qualitative data analysis, using a detailed documentary record of the process to reflect on the involvement of service user and carer researchers. In our reflexive discussion, we show how we were coproducing knowledge in terms of many of the generic characteristics of coproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049732312448541">Gibbons et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049732312448541">Nowotny et al., 2001</xref>). In addition, we advance a more specific understanding of knowledge coproduction in the context of mental health services research. We also illustrate how coproduction in our project directly affected research findings in a number of areas, including issues such as self-referral, positive risk taking, and shared decision making in mental health services. In doing so, we demonstrate the potential of systematic reflection on the process of knowledge coproduction—as characterized above—as a conceptually useful means of trying to understand how service user and carer involvement impacts on research. We stress that that reflection should be both integral to the research process and made explicit to the reader so he or she can make sense of how the knowledge has been produced and by whom. That critical reflection should focus on researchers from within the conventional clinical–academic research team, as much as on service user and carer researchers.</p>
<p>This article is limited in that we report a process of knowledge coproduction in research, in vivo, and reflect on that process retrospectively. We have necessarily not been able to test more widely the strengths and weaknesses of our particular understanding of knowledge coproduction as a tool for evaluating service user and carer involvement in mental health research. Additional research could write that prospective testing into a suitable project. Nonetheless, this article demonstrates the potential for using the concept of knowledge coproduction as a tool for considering how service user and carer involvement affects the research process and research findings.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This project was funded by the National Institute of Health Research, Health Services and Delivery Research programme (project number 10/1008/15), United Kingdom. The views and opinions expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of the NIHR HS&amp;DR programme, NIHR, NHS, or the Department of Health.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Steve Gillard</bold>, PhD, is a senior lecturer in social and community mental health, and head of the Section of Mental Health, Division of Population Health Sciences and Education, St George’s, University of London, London, United Kingdom.</p>
<p><bold>Lucy Simons</bold>, PhD, is an honorary senior research fellow in the Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Southampton, Southampton, United Kingdom.</p>
<p><bold>Kati Turner</bold>, BA, is a service user researcher in the Section of Mental Health, Division of Population Health Sciences and Education, St George’s, University of London, London, United Kingdom.</p>
<p><bold>Mike Lucock</bold>, PhD, is a professor of clinical psychology in the School of Human and Health Sciences, University of Huddersfield, Huddersfield, and associate director of psychological therapies research, South West Yorkshire Partnership NHS Foundation Trust, Wakefield, United Kingdom.</p>
<p><bold>Christine Edwards</bold>, BA, MSc, FCIPD, is a professor of human resource management in the Kingston Business School, Kingston University, Kingston, United Kingdom.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Averill</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Matrix analysis as a complementary analytic strategy in qualitative inquiry</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>855</fpage>-<lpage>866</lpage>. doi:10.1177/104973230201200611<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/104973230201200611</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumbusch</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirkham</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Semeniuk</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Pursuing common agendas: A collaborative model for knowledge translation between research and practice in clinical settings</article-title>. <source>Research in Nursing &amp; Health</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>. doi:10.1002/nur.20242<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nur.20242</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beresford</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Developing the theoretical basis for service user/survivor-led research and equal involvement in research</article-title>. <source>Epidemiologia e Psichiatria Sociale</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cunliffe</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Reflexive inquiry in organizational research: Questions and possibilities</article-title>. <source>Human Relations</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>983</fpage>-<lpage>1003</lpage>. doi:10.1177/00187267030568004<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00187267030568004</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deegan</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Shared decision making and medication management in the recovery process</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Services</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>1636</fpage>-<lpage>1639</lpage>. doi:10.1176/appi.ps.57.11.1636<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.57.11.1636</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Best research for best health: A new national health research strategy</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Layzell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Strategies for living: A report of user-led research into people’s strategies for living with mental distress</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mental Health Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>User-led research and evidence-based medicine</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>180</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>3</lpage>. doi:10.1192/bjp.180.1.1<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.180.1.1</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Limoges</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nowotny</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwatrzman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>The new production of knowledge</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Turner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>The barriers and facilitators of supporting self-care in NHS mental health trusts</source>. <publisher-loc>Southampton, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute for Health Research Service Delivery and Organisation programme</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Addicott</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Ferlie</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>“Staying native”: Coproduction in mental health services research</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Public Sector Management</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>-<lpage>577</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Professionalizing action research—A meaningful strategy for modernizing services?</article-title> <source>Journal of Nursing Management</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2934.2006.00584.x<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2934.2006.00584.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Whose science? Whose knowledge? Thinking from women’s lives</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garrow</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Researching Aboriginal health: Experience from a study of urban young people’s health and well-being</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1267</fpage>-<lpage>1279</lpage>. doi:10.1016/S0277-9536(01)00095-8<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0277-9536(01)00095-8</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cribb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Concordance, adherence and compliance in medicine taking</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Coordinating Centre for NHS Service Delivery and Organisation Research &amp; Development</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andershed</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ternestedt</surname><given-names>B.-M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Knowledge constructions in nursing practice: Understanding and integrating different forms of knowledge</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1500</fpage>-<lpage>1511</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1049732310374042<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732310374042</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Reflections on gender and science</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tritter</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sorohan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Patients’ and health professionals’ views on primary care for people with serious mental illness: Focus group study</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>330</volume>, <fpage>1122</fpage>-<lpage>1126</lpage>. doi:10.1136/bmj.38440.418426.8F<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.38440.418426.8F</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Qualitative researching</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Involving young service users as co-researchers: Possibilities, benefits and costs</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Social Work</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>1395</fpage>-<lpage>1410</lpage>. doi:10.1093/bjsw/bch420<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bch420</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Risk-making or risk-taking?</article-title> <source>Openmind</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mosavel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Stade</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buchbinder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Community-based participatory research (CBPR) in South Africa: Engaging multiple constituents to shape the research question</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>2577</fpage>-<lpage>2587</lpage>. doi:10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.04.041<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.04.041</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nowotny</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Rethinking science</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Reflexivity in the co-production of academic-practitioner research</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research in Organizations and Management</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Delusions and qualitative confusions: A dialogic collaborative exploration</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1008</fpage>-<lpage>1018</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Qualitative evaluation and research methods</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Writing: A method of enquiry</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Denzin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of qualitative research</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>923</fpage>-<lpage>948</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Qualitative research practice</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Peoples’ understandings of a primary care-based mental health self-help clinic</article-title>. <source>Patient Education and Counseling</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:10.1016/S0738-3991(03)00114-9<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0738-3991(03)00114-9</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Survivor produced knowledge</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beresford</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nettle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>This is survivor research</source> (pp. <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Ross-on-Wye, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PCCS Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>del Vecchio</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Promoting the value and practice of shared decision-making in mental health care</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Rehabilitation Journal</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>54</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scissons</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arney</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Sunderland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Communication between people with schizophrenia and their medical professionals: A participatory research project</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>562</fpage>-<lpage>577</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1049732303262423<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732303262423</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lathlean</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Shifting the focus: Sequential methods of analysis with qualitative data</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>120</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1049732307310264<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732307310264</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>House</surname><given-names>A. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Involving users in the delivery and evaluation of mental health services: Systematic review</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>325</volume>, <fpage>1265</fpage>-<lpage>1267</lpage>. doi:10.1136/bmj.325.7375.1265<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.325.7375.1265</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manthorpe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brearley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sitzia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beresford</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Service user involvement in nursing, midwifery and health visiting research: A review of evidence and practice</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Nursing Studies</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>298</fpage>-<lpage>315</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Staley</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Exploring impact: Public involvement in NHS, public health and social care research</source>. <publisher-loc>Eastleigh, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>INVOLVE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Starkey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Bridging the relevance gap: Aligning stakeholders in the future of management research</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Management</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>S3</fpage>-<lpage>S26</lpage>. doi:10.1111/1467-8551.12.s1.2<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-8551.12.s1.2</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Involving patients as advisors in pharmacy practice research: What are the benefits?</article-title> <source>International Journal of Pharmacy Practice</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>. doi:10.1211/ijpp.16.4.0005<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1211/ijpp.16.4.0005</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beresford</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nettle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>This is survivor research</source>. <publisher-loc>Ross-On-Wye, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PCCS Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1049732312448541">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gøtzsche</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: Guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>370</volume>, <fpage>1453</fpage>-<lpage>1457</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>