<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spscm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Scottish Medical Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-9330</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2045-6441</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0036933013482675</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0036933013482675</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Historical Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Karl Koenig: the Austrian refugee doctor who founded a worldwide movement in Scotland</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0036933013482675"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0036933013482675">Honorary Fellow, Karl Koenig Institute, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0036933013482675">Robin Jackson, Karl Koenig Institute, Aberdeen AB15 0AP, UK. Email: <email>robin@dalmaik.demon.co.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>58</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>124</fpage>
<lpage>127</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The Scottish Medical Journal</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In this paper, the circumstances which led to the creation of the Camphill Movement in Scotland are described. Attention is drawn to the rejection by Dr Karl Koenig – co-founder of the Movement – of too narrow an approach to the treatment of children and adults with intellectual disabilities and his advocacy of a holistic approach. Koenig was one of the first medical practitioners in Britain to proclaim and demonstrate that all children with an intellectual disability, regardless of the severity of that disability, have a potential that can be unlocked and developed. There are now over 100 Camphill communities in more than 20 countries making it one of the largest independent providers of services for children and adults with intellectual disabilities in the world.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Camphill Movement</kwd>
<kwd>holistic approach</kwd>
<kwd>intellectual disability</kwd>
<kwd>Karl Koenig</kwd>
<kwd>social care</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0036933013482675" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>On 9 December 2012, <italic>The Independent on Sunday</italic> carried an article entitled ‘The NHS was forged from care, not box-ticking’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0036933013482675">1</xref></sup> In the article, reference was made to the situation that had occurred at Stafford Hospital 3 years ago where hundreds of patients had died after inadequate treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0036933013482675">2</xref></sup> and the content of the recently published Care Quality Commission report, which stated that 27% of hospitals and care homes were failing to meet minimum standards.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0036933013482675">3</xref></sup> It was argued that a contributory factor to this situation was the character of professional training which had moved from an apprenticeship model where one learnt on the job to an academic model where one acquired information at remote distance in the lecture hall. As a result one quality that was missing, according to the Chief Nursing Officer for England, was compassion.</p>
<p>Seventy years ago an Austrian doctor in Aberdeen argued that the quality of professional treatment could only be improved if the nature of the caring relationship was changed to one of equality and where that relationship was imbued with genuine humanity. It might be tempting to dismiss such a view as being overly idealistic and unworkable – indeed unprofessional – were it not for the fact that the doctor in question subsequently succeeded in establishing a care model that embodied precisely those qualities. The doctor in question was Dr Karl Koenig who co-founded the Camphill Movement in Aberdeen in 1940. Today there are well over 100 Camphill communities in more than 20 countries throughout the world. Who, then, was Dr Koenig?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0036933013482675"><title>Karl Koenig (1902–1966)</title>
<p>Karl Koenig was born on 25 September 1902, in Leopoldstadt – the original Jewish ghetto in Vienna.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0036933013482675">4</xref></sup> As a child Koenig was precociously intelligent and far ahead of his peers. At home he had an extensive and unusual library for a teenager including books on philosophy by Schopenhauer and Kant. In 1920 Koenig entered the medical faculty of the Vienna University, which was the most prestigious centre of learning in Austria. On completion of his degree in 1927 he was offered a part-time post by Dr Ita Wegman head of the Klinisch-Therapeutische Institut in Arlesheim in Switzerland.</p>
<p>Dr Wegman was exceptional in many respects not least because in 1907 she had entered the University of Zurich, one of the pioneer universities of the time where women were allowed to study medicine and where she qualified as a doctor in 1911. In 1920 she opened the Klinisch-Therapeutische Institut, which developed over the years into the first centre for anthroposophical medicine. In 1922 she established a home for children with intellectual disabilities called the Sonnenhof. It was here for the first time that Koenig became acquainted with children with physical and mental challenges who needed special care. Koenig accepted the offer of the post for he felt that he had a direct affinity with the children.</p>
<p>In the spring of 1928, Koenig was offered and accepted the post of physician responsible for the medical care of the children and young people with special needs at a new curative educational institute at Pilgramshain in Silesia (now Kreis Schweidnitz in Poland). However, by 1933 Koenig’s medical work there had become progressively more difficult largely because of the growing number of restrictions imposed by the National Socialist government. Given the increasingly hostile climate, coupled with the ever-present threat of arrest because of his Jewish background, it was decided that the situation had become too dangerous. In March 1936, the Koenig family were forced to return with their four children to Koenig’s native city of Vienna and arrived there in an impoverished condition. He had to start all over again; however, his reputation as a good doctor soon spread and his practice grew. But he was forced to flee Austria when the political situation further deteriorated and the predicament of those from Jewish backgrounds grew increasingly more serious.</p>
<p>After his flight from Austria, Koenig stayed for a while at Arlesheim and it was whilst he was in Switzerland that Dr Wegman suggested he should think of going to Scotland. She indicated that she had a friend near Aberdeen who might be willing to help him start work there and to build a new future. This was dependent upon Koenig’s inclusion in the small group of Austrian doctors permitted entry into the UK. The Home Office in joint consultation with representatives of the medical profession had agreed the admission of 50 Austrian doctors for the purpose of studying and later practising in the UK.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0036933013482675"><title>Scotland</title>
<p>The Minutes of the Senatus Academicus of St Andrews University for the 9 December 1938 record that the Co-ordination Committee for Refugees had asked St Andrews University if it would be prepared to accept <italic>one</italic> of the selected Austrian doctors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0036933013482675">5</xref></sup> The Faculty of Medicine agreed to recommend to Senatus the acceptance of one doctor on condition that he was not allowed to compete for University Prizes or class medals! A Minute of the Faculty of Medicine meeting held on 10 February 1939 noted that Dr Karl Koenig had been nominated by the Refugee Committee as the Austrian doctor to study at Dundee – the location of St Andrews University Medical School. In a Minute to the University of St Andrews Court (26 June 1939) reference is made to an appeal by the Faculty of Medicine on behalf of Dr Koenig. In that appeal it was stated that Koenig was entirely without resources with which to pay tuition fees, so a Grant was asked for to cover the fees incurred by Koenig. The Court agreed to grant Koenig exemption from the payment of fees.</p>
<p>The friend in Scotland to which Dr Wegman had made reference was Emily Haughton who lived with her husband at Williamston House, Insch, in Aberdeenshire. And so it was that Koenig, his family and a group of colleagues moved into a former manse – Kirkton House – on the grounds of the Haughton’s estate. Thus it was Williamston, not Camphill, that became the first, albeit very short-lived, curative educational institute in Scotland. It soon became apparent to Koenig that the accommodation at Kirkton was too small and remote to serve efficiently as an Institute. When the opportunity came to leave Williamston and move to Camphill (a property on the outskirts of Aberdeen), Koenig quickly took it. Camphill estate at that time was owned by Will Macmillan, a member of the Macmillan publishing dynasty which included Harold Macmillan the former British Prime Minister. Will Macmillan had met with Koenig on an earlier occasion because he had been looking for a suitable location for his son Alister who had an intellectual disability. With the help of a loan from Will Macmillan and the Scottish Christian Council for Refugees, a move to the Camphill estate became possible. However on 12 May, just before the proposed move to Camphill scheduled for 1 June 1940, Koenig and the rest of the men in Kirkton House, were arrested as ‘enemy aliens’; the married men were interned on the Isle of Man, while the single men were transported either to Canada or to Australia.</p>
<p>Once Koenig was released from internment on 3 October 1940, he re-commenced his re-qualifying course but this time, for the sake of geographical convenience, at the University of Aberdeen. However, Koenig eventually decided to withdraw from the course. This decision meant that he was not able to act as the medical officer for Camphill in the same way that he had at Pilgramshain. The reason commonly advanced for his withdrawal was that he was too preoccupied with the process of setting up Camphill. Another possible reason is that whilst on his course Koenig may have encountered some hostility, for as Weindling and Collins have indicated there was some opposition from both the BMA and the MPU to the influx of so many refugee doctors into Britain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0036933013482675">6</xref></sup> In some instances there was an anti-semitic element in that opposition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0036933013482675">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Another possible reason for Koenig’s withdrawal can be advanced. This may be found in an article written by Koenig which appeared in <italic>The Coracle</italic> – a periodical published by The Iona Community.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0036933013482675">8</xref></sup> George MacLeod, founder of the Iona Community, had invited Koenig to contribute four articles for <italic>The Coracle</italic> covering a number of broad themes: Integration, Medicine, Education and Agriculture. Only the first two were ever published and these two according to Ferguson, Macleod’s biographer, caused uproar.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0036933013482675">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>The content of Koenig’s article on ‘Medicine’ is unlikely to have endeared him to many doctors and nurses in Scotland. His basic criticism was that members of the medical and nursing professions were essentially technicians who as a direct result of their training had become too distant from their patients and provided a service which lacked basic humanity. His attack is perhaps not altogether surprising given his commitment to a holistic approach to the needs of the individual and not a clinical approach that he saw as narrow, fragmented, and superficial. This trenchant criticism should not be interpreted as a particular attack on the quality of the professional training provided in Scotland for Koenig had been equally unhappy with the character of the medical training on offer at the University of Vienna when he was a young undergraduate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0036933013482675">4</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0036933013482675"><title>Camphill</title>
<p>What Koenig was seeking to do at Camphill was something quite new. In an interview with the <italic>Aberdeen Press and Journal</italic> on 21 October 1940 he indicated that the Board of Control in Edinburgh had informed him that Camphill was the first private institution for children with intellectual disabilities in Scotland. This fact reflected the prevailing professional opinion that children and young people with intellectual disabilities were incapable of responding to and thus benefiting from an education. In England such children were formally categorised as ‘subnormal’ which, whether intentionally or not, conveyed the impression that they were in some way less than human. Koenig was well aware of the fact that in his home country, now Nazi controlled, the inevitable fate for children with an intellectual disability was either intentional starvation in hospital or extermination in a concentration camp.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0036933013482675">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>What is beyond dispute is that Koenig was ahead of his time. He rejected the medical model of disability which he saw as incompatible with taking a holistic approach to the child with intellectual disabilities. In an address delivered on 27 May 1956 at the official opening of a Camphill community in North Yorkshire, Koenig expressed his strong opposition to psychometry and the categorisation of children according to measured intelligence which he argued led to children being concealed behind a label. As an Austrian refugee from a Jewish family background, Koenig was only too well aware of the impact of labels that stigmatised.</p>
<p>Under Koenig’s guidance and tutelage the Camphill communities over the years have attempted to create and maintain an environment where the economic, social and spiritual life of the community complement each other and where its members, whatever their abilities, help to support the needs of their fellows, while they themselves are supported in turn. It was Koenig’s intention that the schools which formed part of the Camphill Movement should be integrated communities in which the children and staff lived together and shared their lives in such a way as to foster mutual help and understanding. A community of co-workers is thus established which shares all the work that has to be done whether it is teaching, caring, household work, gardening, etc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0036933013482675">11</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0036933013482675" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>It is acknowledged that Koenig was greatly helped in the early years by well-connected members of the Society of Friends of Camphill which included Sir William Hamilton Fyfe, Principal of the University of Aberdeen; Hon. Dr WS Maclay, Ministry of Health (Mental Health); Professor Douglas MacCalman, Professor of Mental Health, University of Aberdeen; and Mr H Stewart Mackintosh, Director of Education, Glasgow. Perhaps the most significant support in the formative years came from George MacLeod who saw in Koenig something of himself – an outspoken, resolute and uncompromising individual who had a clear mission. Both MacLeod and Koenig challenged accepted thinking and practice in their respective fields. Ferguson, in his biography of MacLeod, describes his subject as ‘a man of action who had an uncanny quality to see important issues before others’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0036933013482675">9</xref></sup> In that regard, MacLeod and Koenig were similar. As MacLeod’s son freely conceded to this author, his father ‘would have loved Koenig because he was a doer.’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0036933013482675">12</xref></sup> The Iona Community and the Camphill Movement in Scotland are testaments to the foresight, inner conviction and resolve of the founders.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec6-0036933013482675"><title>Declaration of conflicting interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0036933013482675"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0036933013482675"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Vallely P. The NHS was forged from care, not box-ticking. <italic>The Independent on Sunday.</italic> 9 December 2012. Retrieved from http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/the-nhs-was-forged-from-care-not-boxticking-8395848.html (accessed 12 December 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0036933013482675"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Healthcare Commission</collab>. <source>Investigation into Mid-Staffordshire NHS Foundation Trust</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Healthcare Commission</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0036933013482675"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Care Quality Commission</collab>. <source>The state of health care and adult social care in England</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stationery Office</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0036933013482675"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Müller-Wiedemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Karl Koenig: A Central European biography of the twentieth century</source>, <publisher-loc>Botton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Camphill Books</publisher-name>, <year>1996</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0036933013482675"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>University of St Andrews. Minutes of the Senatus Academicus 1938–1939 [UY452/41]: Faculty of Medicine Report; Friday 9 December 1938</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0036933013482675"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weindling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Medical refugees and the modernisation of British medicine, 1930–1960</article-title>. <source>Soc Hist Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0036933013482675"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Go and learn: The international story of Jews and Medicine in Scotland</source>, <publisher-loc>Aberdeen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aberdeen University Press</publisher-name>, <year>1988</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0036933013482675"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integration in medicine</article-title>. <source>The Coracle</source> <year>1942</year>, pp. <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0036933013482675"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>George MacLeod: Founder of the Iona Community</source>, <publisher-loc>Glasgow</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wildgoose Publications</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0036933013482675"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Karl Koenig, Stanley Segal and Herbert Gunzburg: Pioneers in the field of intellectual disability in Britain</article-title>. <source>Int J Develop Disabil</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0036933013482675"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Discovering Camphill: New perspectives, research and developments</source>, <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Floris Books</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0036933013482675"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>MacLeod M. <italic>Dr and Tilla Koenig/Camphill</italic>. In conversation with Robin Jackson, 1 December 2012</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>