<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptra</journal-id>
<journal-title>Trauma</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1460-4086</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0350</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1460408612462311</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1460408612462311</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The totality of burn care</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>Leigh Ann</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>Stephen M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1460408612462311"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1460408612462311">Johns Hopkins Burn Center, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1460408612462311">Stephen M Milner, Johns Hopkins Burn Center, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, 4940 Eastern Avenue, Baltimore, MD, USA. Email: <email>smilner3@jhmi.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>16</fpage>
<lpage>28</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The overall improvement in mortality following severe burns has dramatically increased in the last half century with enhanced methods of resuscitation, treatment of inhalation injury, control of infection, early wound excision and novel methods of skin resurfacing. Although burn care begins at the onset of injury, reconstruction and rehabilitation feature highly throughout the various stages of treatment. Ultimately, we will have achieved little if the patient cannot be integrated back into society. For descriptive purposes burn care has been considered chronologically under the following headings: (1) First Two Minutes (Prehospital Care/First Aid), (2) First Two Hours (Emergency Room care), (3) First two days (resuscitation), (4) First Two Weeks (surgical excision and grafting), (5) First Two Months (rehabilitation and psychology), (6) First Two Years (reconstruction).</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Burns</kwd>
<kwd>mass casualties</kwd>
<kwd>resuscitation</kwd>
<kwd>trauma</kwd>
<kwd>reconstruction</kwd>
<kwd>plastic surgery</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1460408612462311" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The care of the burned patient begins the minute the injury takes place and continues until the patient is finally rehabilitated into society. Over the course of treatment, there are a number of dramatic and pathophysiological changes, so that modification of treatment is essential as the process evolves. The burn injury, therefore, can be considered as a series of phases which will be discussed in separate sections.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1460408612462311"><title>The first 2 minutes (prehospital care/first aid)</title>
<p>The initial treatment of thermal injury begins at the scene and should halt the burning process. Patients must be rapidly removed from the source of injury. Flames are best extinguished by smothering the patient in a blanket or getting the patient to “Stop, Drop and Roll.” First responders should protect themselves from contact with chemicals. Dry agents should be brushed off and the skin irrigated with copious quantities of clean water for 20–30 minutes. Patients with electrical injuries are removed from contact with the electrical source. All burned clothing should be removed, unless firmly stuck.</p>
<p>In minor burns, cooling is beneficial if started within 3 hours of injury, significantly reducing pain. It has also been shown to reduce the depth of a burn by decreasing cell metabolism, increasing dermal perfusion and dampening the inflammatory response; the latter by reducing the release of histamine and lactate and by decreasing levels of thromboxane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1460408612462311">Cuttle et al., 2009</xref>). Cooling, however, has been found to be more effective if the wound is flushed rather than immersed and is ineffective if delayed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1460408612462311">Baldwin et al., 2012</xref>). First aid recommendations guard against the use of ice and prolonged cooling, which can cause hypothermia and/or frostbite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1460408612462311">Demling et al., 1979</xref>).</p>
<p>Patency of the airway is vital. If the patient is unconscious or exhibiting signs of respiratory distress, such as hoarseness or stridor, endotracheal intubation should be performed. All victims of fires should receive 100% oxygen to reduce severity of carbon monoxide poisoning. Life-threatening injuries are appropriately managed, haemorrhage is controlled and fractures stabilized. The patient is kept warm and covered with a clean dry sheet for transport. The wound and blisters are left undisturbed. Ointments should not be applied since wound assessment, necessitates removal by the medical team, which is painful, delays treatment and can cause tissue damage.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1460408612462311"><title>The first 2 hours (emergency room)</title>
<sec id="sec4-1460408612462311"><title>Airway management</title>
<p>Intubation is only indicated when the airway is threatened, gas exchange or compliance mandate mechanical ventilatory support, or for airway protection when mental status is inadequate. Although there is no indication for prophylactic intubation for inhalation injury alone, the patient should be carefully monitored since airway edema can evolve during the resuscitation period.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1460408612462311"><title>Fluid resuscitation</title>
<p>Following a burn there is a massive release of chemical mediators, including histamine, complement, arachidonic acid, products of the coagulation cascade, cytokines and oxygen free radicals. The result is an increase in vascular permeability and microvascular hydrostatic pressure resulting in an imbalance of physical forces controlling fluid flux across the capillary as fluid passes from the vascular to the interstitial compartments. In burns greater than 25% total body surface area (TBSA) these changes are also seen in nonburned tissue. Failure to correct the fluid losses will result in decreased cardiac output, renal failure and cardiovascular collapse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1460408612462311">Demling, 2005</xref>). Injury may also occur at the cellular level, and a progressively diminishing cell membrane potential and cellular shock may be the final common pathway to multiorgan failure and death. Resuscitation following thermal injury, however, is complicated because huge transvascular fluid shifts occur, and the resulting obligatory burn edema has attendant risks of increased vascular compromise, airway obstruction and conversion of a viable, deep second-degree burn to a nonviable, full-thickness injury, increasing morbidity and mortality. A new term “resuscitation morbidity” has been coined to include such sinister complications as abdominal compartment syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1460408612462311">Kirkpatrick et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, the basic principle of fluid resuscitation is to carefully titrate the fluids administered to provide the least amount necessary to maintain adequate organ perfusion. Intravenous fluid resuscitation is required for all patients with second- and third-degree burns greater than 10% TBSA in patients younger than 10 or older than 50 years of age and for those with greater than 20% TBSA in all other age groups. Venous access is best obtained by large-bore (16-gauge) catheters, preferably placed percutaneously through nonburned skin, although central access may be necessary. These patients also require a Foley catheter and a nasogastric tube.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1460408612462311"><title>Burn size</title>
<p>Traditionally fluid requirements are calculated from mathematical formulae related to the weight of the patient and the size of the burn, the latter most simply estimated from the “rule of nines” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1460408612462311">Knaysi et al., 1968</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1460408612462311">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1460408612462311">Allgöwer and Siegrist, 1975</xref>) or body surface area charts such as that described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1460408612462311">Lund and Browder (1944)</xref>. All current methods have the inherent problem of transferring a three-dimensional (3D) injury onto a 2D piece of paper for analysis and so have limited accuracy. The use of the patient’s hand to estimate irregular or scattered burned areas is described and approximates to just less than 1% TBSA. This has been estimated when considering the hand as a rectangle. Modern methods using electronic devices may reduce some of the guesswork; however the future requires 3D body measurement for greater accuracy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1460408612462311">Miller et al., 2002</xref>).
<fig id="fig1-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The rule of nines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<sec id="sec7-1460408612462311"><title>Formulae</title>
<p>There are numerous formulae that can be used for successful fluid resuscitation, however, no prospective randomized studies have been undertaken to enable comparison, and all formulae are only a starting point. The volume administered should be continuously titrated to the urine output to avoid over-resuscitation or under-resuscitation. Increased fluid requirements are seen following inhalation injury, after high-voltage electrical injuries, and in children. The most popular fluid used for resuscitation in the United States is lactated Ringer’s solution, with a sodium concentration of 130 mEq/l. This solution is most commonly prescribed for adults, using the Parkland Formula and recommends 4 ml/kg/h with half the volume given in the first 8 h. This was calculated to produce a urine output of 0.5 to 1 ml/kg/h.</p>
<p>Pigmented urine resulting from the presence of hemochromogens is often associated with high-voltage electrical injuries (&gt;1000 volts). To avoid injury to the renal tubules, the pigment should be cleared as quickly as possible. The rate of crystalloid infusion can be increased to produce a urine output of 2 ml/kg/h. Mannitol can be administered to facilitate the diureses, and sodium bicarbonate can be used to alkalinize the urine to decrease the precipitation of myoglobin in the renal tubules. Rhabdomyolysis may be complicated by hyperkalaemia, and serum potassium should be monitored frequently until the urine clears.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1460408612462311"><title>Treatment of mass casualties</title>
<p>It may be somewhat impractical, however, to use formulae when large numbers of casualties are seen and several alternative regimens have been described. The ISR “Rule of Tens” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1460408612462311">Chung et al., 2010</xref>) calculates for patients 40–80 kg the initial hourly rate of IV fluids by multiplying the % TBSA burn by 10. For patients over 80 kg, 100 cc is added for every additional 10 kg. During the First Gulf War, mathematical calculations were simplified by assuming the patients to be of standard weight (appropriate for a military setting) and displaying the information in simple tabular form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1460408612462311">Milner et al., 1993</xref>). Later this concept was expanded for use in the civilian population and included children. Multiple tables were represented in disc form, which progressed to the “Burn Wheel” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1460408612462311">Milner and Rylah, 1993</xref>). The process was subsequently automated by a computer program, which ran on a hand held device (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1460408612462311">Roth et al., 1997</xref>). More recently, we have produced a mobile application which provides an input component where the health care provider is able to manipulate a 3D model and an output component that provides a treatment plan, which includes a comprehensive tutorial on how to perform each step (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1460408612462311">Figure 2(a) and (b)</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1460408612462311">Figure 2(b)</xref> illustrates how sites inaccessible on the burn surface area chart can be mapped on the 3D model.
<fig id="fig2-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(a) Burn application. (b) Comparison three-dimensional (3D) model and standard burn chart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1460408612462311"><title>Children</title>
<p>Fluid resuscitation requirements differ in children. When venous access cannot be accomplished, fluid can be delivered by cannulation of the bone marrow. A 16-gauge spinal needle can be inserted directly into the tibial plateau, medial malleolus, anterior iliac crest or distal femur and used to deliver fluid rates of up to 100 ml/h. Because children have a disproportionately larger head, they are best resuscitated with formulae based on surface area rather than weight, such as the modified Carvajal formula used in Galveston, Texas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1460408612462311">Table 1</xref>), and urine output should be titrated to 1 ml/kg/h. Body surface area can be obtained from a standard height-weight nomogram (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1460408612462311">Table 2</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1460408612462311">Carvajal, 1977</xref>). Lactated Ringer's solution is prescribed for children older than 2 years; however, infants younger are prone to hypoglycemia because of small glycogen stores and therefore should receive a dextrose-containing electrolyte solution.
<table-wrap id="table1-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Total 24-h fluid requirements in children.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1460408612462311" xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>5000 ml × BSA * burned (m<sup>2</sup>)  (burn-related losses)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>+ 2000 ml × TBSA (m<sup>2</sup>) (maintenance fluids)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1460408612462311">
<p>TBSA: total body surface area.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Nomogram.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1460408612462311" xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-table2.tif"/>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1460408612462311"><title>Colloid</title>
<p>The oncotic pressure generated by plasma proteins serves to maintain the intravascular volume. Following all resuscitative regimens, severe hypoproteinemia is seen following major burns, and this in turn potentiates further edema. The administration of colloid is therefore logical but controversial, and much debate exists as to when capillary integrity is established and whether infused protein stays within the vascular compartment. Experimentally this has been shown to be at about 8 h after the burn injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1460408612462311">Demling, 1987</xref>). Therefore, colloids generally are prescribed in burns greater than 40% TBSA, after the first 8 h and in patients with oliguria who are not responding to crystalloid resuscitation. The choice of protein solution is either fresh frozen plasma (0.5–1 ml/kg/%burn) or albumin, which can be conveniently given by adding 50 g of albumin to each liter of crystalloid. Fresh frozen plasma has the theoretical advantage of replacing clotting factors and is the colloid of choice when the INR goes above 1.5. It also contains fibronectin, an adhesion molecule and key fibroblast-derived signal protein, which helps initiate healing of the burn wound.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1460408612462311"><title>Burn depth</title>
<p>Classification of the depth of burns has traditionally used the degree system. First degree involves the epidermis only; second degree (or partial thickness) burns extend into the dermis and third (or full thickness) burns destroy the entire skin. An additional fourth degree is sometimes used to describe injury to underlying muscle, tendon or bone. A more practical classification is to describe burns as either superficial or deep as this determines both treatment and prognosis. Superficial burns involve the papillary dermis, with its rich vascular plexus, and the epidermis which contain sufficient epithelial appendages to allow healing within 2 weeks with minimal scarring. They appear wet, pink, blistered, blanch with pressure and are painful. Deep burns, however, involve reticular dermis and subcutaneous fat, have insufficient epithelial appendages. If healing occurs, it will be slow with resultant unstable skin, hypertrophic scarring and contracture, best treated by excision and skin grafting. Their appearance ranges from cherry red, mottled, white and nonblanching to leathery, charred and brown.</p>
<p>While bedside evaluation of very superficial or deep wounds presents little diagnostic difficulty, clinical assessment of the “indeterminate” or mid-dermal burn is accurate in only about two thirds of cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1460408612462311">Heimbach et al., 1992</xref>). Thus, more sophisticated techniques have been developed to assist accurate diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1460408612462311">Devgan et al., 2006</xref>). Ultrasonography, biopsy, various optical means such as orthogonal polarization spectral imaging, thermography and nuclear magnetic resonance imaging have been employed but have been found to be neither reliable nor practical. Newer developments focus on measurements of tissue perfusion. Laser Doppler imaging which scans a burned area and generates a colour-coded perfusion map corresponding to various burn depths is the latest and most accurate modality for diagnosing burn wound depth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1460408612462311">Milner et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1460408612462311">Pape et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1460408612462311">Still et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1460408612462311"><title>Wound care and escharotomy</title>
<p>The burn wound is carefully inspected, loose skin debrided and the depth and size of the burn charted. The treatment of blisters is controversial. We favour removal since the contained metabolites of arachidonic acid and other inflammatory agents in blister fluid may be a factor in converting the wound to a deeper injury. Systemic antibiotics are rarely able to reach areas of avascular eschar and increase the risk of opportunistic infections. Silver sulfadiazine (a.k.a. Silvadene®, Thermazene®, Flamazine® and SSD®) is the most commonly used prophylactic topical antimicrobial in burn patients. It is used for deep or infected wounds. SSD is an insoluble, white cream, available in a 1% concentration and is applied twice daily. It has the advantages of being relatively painless to apply, and its activity against a wide variety of organisms, including <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Klebsiella</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, Proteus, the Enterobacteriaceae and <italic>Candida albicans</italic>.</p>
<p>Prospective studies have concluded that in superficial burns infection is uncommon, that there is no difference in overall wound healing rates between nonantibacterial and antibacterial impregnated dressings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1460408612462311">Nance et al., 1972</xref>) and that infection rates are not influenced by the specific antibacterial agent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1460408612462311">Heinrich et al., 1988</xref>). Nevertheless it is customary to protect the wound with nonadherent dressings such as vaseline gauze supplemented with topical antibacterial agent such as bacitracin, neomycin and polymyxin B.</p>
<p>Deep burns which are circumferential may act as a tourniquet around a limb as edema develops so that it is necessary to make relieving incisions through the eschar to prevent vascular impairment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1460408612462311">Pruitt et al., 1968</xref>). The decision to operate is performed on suspicion and should be made early since once palpable pulses are absent muscle necrosis may have already occurred. Direct measurement of compartmental pressures may be helpful and a wick catheter technique has established the need for escharotomy at a threshold of 30 mm Hg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1460408612462311">Saffle et al., 1980</xref>). Once escharotomies are performed, continued monitoring is necessary to identify recurrence of elevated pressures.</p>
<p>Incisions are made along the mid-lateral lines extending from the proximal to the distal extent of the burned area. They should not be carried across joints and should be deep enough into the superficial fascia to allow the wound edges to separate. Bleeding is controlled with electrocautery. In the upper extremity care is taken to avoid injury to the ulnar nerve, behind the medial epicondyle, and the superficial radial nerve over the dorsum of the wrist. The latter is easily injured if the hand is not kept palm upwards during the procedure. Similarly, deep burns around the trunk can impede the patient’s ability to breathe. Suggested placement of escharotomy sites are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1460408612462311">Figure 3(a)–(c)</xref>.
<fig id="fig3-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>(a) Arm in anatomic position. (b) Arm as it returns to resting position. (c) Escharotomy on torso.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1460408612462311"><title>First 2 days (hours 3–48)</title>
<sec id="sec14-1460408612462311"><title>Inhalation injury</title>
<p>Inhalation injury constitutes a major cause of mortality following thermal injury. It is defined as aspiration of superheated gases, steam, hot liquids or noxious products of incomplete combustion which cause a number of physiological abnormalities. Mucosal edema, bronchospasm, intrapulmonary shunting and ventilation/perfusion mismatch contribute to respiratory failure and this may be further complicated by secondary infection leading to tracheobronchitis and pneumonia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1460408612462311">Mlcak et al., 2007</xref>). The diagnosis is made chiefly by history and physical examination and can be confirmed by bronchoscopy, which may reveal carbonaceous endobronchial debris and mucosal ulceration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1460408612462311">Massanes et al., 1994</xref>). It should be particularly suspected in patients who have sustained burns in a closed space and have deep burns of the face. Early chest x-rays are routinely normal. The PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio of less than 300 indicates a degree of intrapulmonary shunting and serum carboxyhemoglobin percentage is also of value. Intubation is required for all patients with threatened airways and those who require mechanical ventilation.</p>
<p>At high concentrations, carbon monoxide binds avidly to haemoglobin and other iron-containing enzymes, including those in the mitochondria and can interfere with delivery and utilization of oxygen. In all, 100% oxygen should be administered for 6 to 12 h, which reduces the half life of COHgb from approximately 2.5 h to 40 min. Significant exposure may manifest as headache, irritability, personality changes, loss of memory and gross motor deficits, and patients are at risk of developing both acute and delayed neurologic sequelae. Children and pregnant women and their foetuses are said to be at particular risk. The data supporting the use of hyperbaric oxygen is not strong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1460408612462311">Seger and Welch, 1994</xref>) but may be appropriate for those with documented or strongly suspected serious exposures (carboxyhemolobin levels &gt;25%) with depressed mental status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1460408612462311">Ireton-Jones et al., 1987</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-1460408612462311"><title>Fluid resuscitation in the second 24 h</title>
<p>After 24 h, extravasation of fluid from the microcirculation is minimal, serum sodium levels are high and protein is low. However, maintenance requirements may be high because there is continued evaporative loss from the raw surface of the burn wound. Thus, urine output can be maintained by hypotonic solutions such as D5 1/2N Saline. The addition of dextrose is necessary because glucose stores are depleted by catecholamine release. Protein losses should be replaced to minimize further edema and restore blood volumes when albumin levels fall below 1.5 mg/l. The volumes of enteral nutrition, usually begun at approximately 6 h, are factored into any calculations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-1460408612462311"><title>Paediatric resuscitation</title>
<p>In the following 24 h, fluid requirements are 3750 ml/m<sup>2</sup> TBSA (to replace losses caused by evaporation from the wound) plus 1500 ml/m<sup>2</sup> TBSA (for maintenance).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-1460408612462311"><title>Burn nutrition</title>
<p>Enteral feedings should commence within the first 24 to 48 h from the time of burn. It should be advanced to goal quickly to preserve gut mucosal integrity, prevent bacterial translocation, achieve nutritional goals in the hypermetabolic state and promote wound healing. With the sustained increase in energy consumption, there is a parallel increase in energy demand and a shift in substrate use from glucose to amino acids as the preferred source of fuel. The result is mobilization of amino acids and protein catabolism with loss of muscle and other proteins. The hypermetabolic response is perpetuated by fever, pain, burn eschar, multiple surgical procedures and recurrent infection and may last until wound closure is achieved.</p>
<p>Actual energy requirements are best determined by use of indirect calorimetry within the first 72 h after the burn injury and weekly thereafter. There are, however, several predictive equations that can be used to estimate total caloric requirements. We have found the use of the Ireton-Jones equation to be the most consistently applicable to our adult population in determining resting metabolic rate. The Curreri and Harris-Benedict equations have been found to overestimate and underestimate caloric requirements, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1460408612462311">Cureri et al., 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1460408612462311">Harris and Benedict, 1919</xref>). In larger burns (&gt;20% TBSA), protein should be provided as 20% to 25% of the total calories, or 1.5 to 2.5 g protein per kg of body weight.</p>
<p>Elevated C-reactive protein (CRP) levels are indicative of the stress response and should be monitored in conjunction with prealbumin and transferrin. Albumin does not reflect acute changes in nutritional status because of its sensitivity to fluid shifts, plasma leakage and a longer half-life and therefore should not be used as a nutritional marker. Glucose control (80–110 mg/dl) has been associated with improved clinical outcomes, and insulin, being an anabolic hormone, may assist in nitrogen utilization and retention.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-1460408612462311"><title>First 2 weeks (48 h–2 weeks)</title>
<sec id="sec19-1460408612462311"><title>Surgical excision</title>
<p>For deep partial thickness and full thickness burns, operative wound excision and skin grafting are paramount. Wound debridement removes necrotic tissue which acts as a nidus for proliferation of bacterial and invasive burn sepsis.</p>
<p>Since the report of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1460408612462311">Janzekovic (1979)</xref>, it has been shown that early excision and wound closure decrease infection rate and shorten hospital stay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1460408612462311">Burke et al., 1974</xref>). In addition, this technique has been shown to benefit indeterminate burns, decreasing the severity of hypertrophic scarring, joint contractures and speeding rehabilitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1460408612462311">Ramzi et al., 1999</xref>). Such wounds in major burns can be temporarily resurfaced with cadaver allograft or other biological dressings until donor autograft becomes available.</p>
<p>Wound excision should be performed on all burns as soon as we are sure that healing will not occur with conservative therapy. With regards to major burns, this takes place as soon as the patient becomes stable. Sequential surgeries are carried out on alternate days until all the eschar is removed. Mortality can be by reduced by minimising blood loss and control of body temperature during transport to and in the operating room. The former is achieved by use of tourniquets and topical application of adrenaline applied on nonadherent Telfa pads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1460408612462311">Gomez et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>There are two main techniques. In fascial excision the burn is excised down to the muscle fascia, removing all the skin and subcutaneous tissue. Its principal advantage is to offer a well-defined vascularised plane that is optimal for skin graft “take.” This is especially important where donor sites are limited since graft failure in these circumstances is likely to prove fatal. Furthermore, the excision can be rapidly performed with electrocuatery reducing blood loss. The major drawback, however, is that healthy subcutaneous tissue may be removed along with superficial nerves and lymphatics, producing severe contour deformities. It should be borne in mind that when this procedure is performed on the anterior trunk of a female the procedure incorporates a bilateral mastectomy.</p>
<p>The second technique is tangential excision and involves excising sequential layers in a tangential fashion until punctuate bleeding is seen from the underlying viable tissue. The instrument of choice is a Humby knife (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1460408612462311">Figure 4</xref>) or a Goulian Knife (Weck blade) for smaller and more delicate areas such as the face and hands and feet.
<fig id="fig4-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Tangential excision of burned leg.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<sec id="sec20-1460408612462311"><title>Skin grafting</title>
<p>Autografts from nonburned skin remains the mainstay of treatment. For most adult patients, the antero-lateral thigh is the site of choice. Larger grafts can be harvested from the back, buttocks and abdomen. Such grafts can be expanded by a process of meshing to ratios ranging from 1:1 to 1:4. Meshing however comes with a cosmetic price, with scarring of the interstices, so that unmeshed or sheet grafts are used for sites seen by the public, such as the face, neck and hands.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec21-1460408612462311"><title>Grafting of burns over 90% TBSA</title>
<p>Such massive injuries are particularly challenging. Any available site is harvested and used to cover the neck and clavicular areas so that our lines and any subsequent tracheostomy can be placed through good skin. At the same sitting a biopsy is taken for cultured epithelial autograft (CEA). The culture and transplantation of keratinocytes was considered a major advance in the treatment of severe burns whereby sufficient epithelial regeneration can occur under laboratory conditions and in 3 weeks transferred to the patient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1460408612462311">Bannasch et al., 2003</xref>). Results, however, have been disappointing since lack of dermal component renders the new skin fragile and take is often poor. We have improved our results by using a sandwich technique. Skin is harvested from any available site. This includes the scalp and scrotum, facilitated by, tumescence with a 1:500,000 solution of adrenaline. The skin is meshed to a ratio of 4:1 and the CEA is placed over this.</p>
<p>Probably the best cover is ultimately achieved, however, by continual reharvesting of donor sites, typically reepithelialising every 2 weeks, and applying these widely meshed grafts while protecting the interstices with 2:1 meshed allograft in the so called Alexander Technique.</p>
<p>Attempts to achieve “off the shelf” skin has met with varying success. Yannas and Burke pioneered the use of a bilayered construct under the commercial name of Integra (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1460408612462311">Burke et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1460408612462311">Yannas et al., 2011</xref>). The epidermal component is composed of a sialastic membrane, and the dermal component is a porous matrix of fibres of cross-linked bovine collagen and a single GAG protein (chondroitin-6-sulphate). The neodermal component is incorporated into the wound bed within 3 weeks allowing the sialastic layer to be removed and a thin autograft applied. The process can be accelerated by use of negative pressure dressings, which also help splint the graft preventing shear. We have found Integra useful in burns of the hands and face and has an advantage in that it can be applied to relatively avascular areas such as small exposures over tendons and bone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1460408612462311">Kosutic et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec22-1460408612462311"><title>First 2 months (2–8 weeks; rehabilitation, psychology)</title>
<sec id="sec23-1460408612462311"><title>Rehabilitation and psychology</title>
<p>The goals of treatment are to prevent loss of motion, protect anatomic structures, prevent deformity and preserve skin graft integrity to promote functional independence. The position of comfort equals position of contracture. Techniques available to attempt to restore function include splinting, early motion (including soft tissue massage) and pressure therapy. Compression garments are applied as soon as the wounds have healed to help control scar hypertrophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1460408612462311">Simons et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The psychological burn-related issues are attended to as early as practicable. Common burn-related clinical issues may include: delirium, sleep derangements, pain, acute stress disorder, posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), body image dissatisfaction and depression. Such services need to be provided on both an inpatient and outpatient basis in an effort to help patients and their families achieve maximum recovery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1460408612462311">Blakeney et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec24-1460408612462311"><title>First 2 years (reconstruction)</title>
<p>The general guideline that reconstruction should not be undertaken until scars fully mature is trumped by concerns for tissue viability or progressive functional limitations, such as severe joint contractures, microstomia or ectropion and by patient and parent concerns regarding the impact of scarring and deformity on psychosocial development. Accurate diagnosis and planning is essential from the beginning. This is facilitated by the use of inventory forms which are divided into anatomical units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1460408612462311">Brou et al., 1989</xref>). The photos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1460408612462311">Figure 5(a) and (b)</xref>) show a patient who sustained acid burns to his face a year ago.
<fig id="fig5-1460408612462311" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Extensive scarring following deep facial burns.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612462311-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>One can see alopecia of the scalp and bilateral eyebrows, loss of epicanthal folds causing a webbing appearance, loss of left nostril, lack of left alae and nasolabial fold, missing ears, loss of ear canal with hearing loss, flattening of his nasal bridge, scar contracture of the upper lip, commissure contracture, apart from extensive hypertrophic scarring in the presence of folliculits. Functional improvement is a priority. For this patient such reconstruction of his nasal airway was performed early. In other patients, associated neck contractures which impede anaesthesia or eyelid ectropion that endanger the cornea will have to be released urgently. The reconstructive ladder, as classically conceptualized, generally provides a hierarchical model for the choice of reconstructive techniques.</p>
<p>Burn wounds resulting in extensive scar contracture and tissue loss will require release and closure of the defect with split skin grafts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1460408612462311">Robson et al., 1992</xref>), pedicled flaps or Z-plasty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1460408612462311">Huang, 2007</xref>). Alopecia can be treated by tissue expansion and hair bearing transplantation. Ectropions of lip and eyelid are best corrected by release with full thickness skin. Musculoskeletal deformity or destruction may necessitate joint fusion, or repair with vascularised tissue.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec25-1460408612462311" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Improvement in burn care has been driven by an explosion of technology and research, yet countless topics need to be addressed. These include: the roles of pharmacological agents to alter capillary leakage, molecular techniques to aid bacterial identification, immune enhancing nutrients, methods to improve scar control, use of hyperbaric oxygen and use of transplantation of composite tissue allograft. Advances in the care of the thermally injured patient have had a dramatic effect on improvement and prognosis of the patient over the last 50 years. Such translational research supports our multidisciplinary team involved in all phases described above.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec26-1460408612462311"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allgöwer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegrist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1975</year>) <source>Verbrennungen. Pathophysiologie Pathologie Klinik Therapie</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, p. <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Attinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>How to cool a burn: a heat transfer point of view</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care and Research</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bannasch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fohn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Unterberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Skin tissue engineering</article-title>. <source>Clinics in Plastic Surgery</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blakeney</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Psychosocial care of persons with severe burns</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Inventory of potential reconstructive needs in the patient with burns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care &amp; Rehabilitation</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondoc</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinby</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Primary burn excision and immediate grafting of burns: a method of shortening illness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yannas</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinby</surname><given-names>WC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Successful use of a physiologically acceptable artificial skin in the treatment of extensive burn injury</article-title>. <source>Annals of Surgery</source> <volume>194</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvajal</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Fluid therapy for the acutely burned child</article-title>. <source>Comprehensive Therapy</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Renz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Simple derivation of the initial fluid rate for the resuscitation of severely burned adult combat casualties: in silico validation of the rule of 10</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>69</volume>(<supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement>): <fpage>S49</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cureri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marvin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Dietary requirements of patients with major burns</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Dietetic Association</source> <volume>65</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuttle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A review of first aid treatments for burn injuries</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>775</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demling</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Fluid resuscitation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bostwick</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group> (eds) <source>The Art and Science of Burn Care</source>. <publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aspen</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demling</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The burn edema process: current concepts</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care &amp; Rehabilitation</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demling</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazess</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldberg</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>The effect of immediate and delayed cold immersion on burn edema formation and resorption</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devgan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylward</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Modalities for the assessment of burn wound depth</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burns and Wounds</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>e2</fpage>–<lpage>e2</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Logsetty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reduced blood loss during burn surgery</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care &amp; Rehabilitation</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedict</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1919</year>) <source>A Biometric Study of Basal Metabolism in Man</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carnegie Institute of Washington</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heimbach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Engrav</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grube</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Burn depth: a review</article-title>. <source>World Journal of Surgery</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuono</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>The role of topical treatment as a determinant of infection in outpatient burns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care &amp; Rehabilitation</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Overview of burn reconstruction</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Total Burn Care</source>, <edition>3rd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders Elsevier</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>674</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ireton-Jones</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The effect of burn wound excision on measured energy expenditure and urinary nitrogen excretion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janzekovic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>A new concept in the early excision and immediate grafting of burns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1103</fpage>–<lpage>1103</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Intraabdominal hypertension and the abdominal compartment syndrome in burn patients</article-title>. <source>World Journal of Surgery</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1142</fpage>–<lpage>1149</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knaysi</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Criklair</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>The rule of nines in history and accuracy</article-title>. <source>Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>563</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosutic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beasung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Demsey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Single-layer Integra for one-stage reconstruction of scalp defects with exposed bone following full-thickness burn injury: a novel technique</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Browder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1944</year>) <article-title>The estimation of areas of burns</article-title>. <source>Surgery, Gynecology &amp; Obstetrics</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massanes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lioret</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Fiberoptic bronchoscopy for the early diagnosis of subglottal inhalation injury: comparative value in the assessment of prognosis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuwalder</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>BurnWare: “a review of computer-aided body surface area determination”</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care &amp; Rehabilitation</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Observations on the microcirculation of the human burn wound using orthogonal polarization spectral imaging</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgetts</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rylah</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The burns calculator: a simple proposed guide for fluid resuscitation</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>342</volume>(<issue>8879</issue>): <fpage>1089</fpage>–<lpage>1091</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rylah</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>War burns: a simplified resuscitation protocol</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Hospital Medicine</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mlcak</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Suman</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Respiratory management of inhalation injury</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nance</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Aggressive outpatient care of burns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Skouras</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>An audit of the use of laser Doppler imaging (LDI) in the assessment of burns of intermediate depth</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moncrief</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>Escharotomy in early burn care</article-title>. <source>Archives of Surgery</source> <volume>96</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramzi</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barret</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Thermal injury</article-title>. <source>Critical Care Clinics</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitch</surname><given-names>IOW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Prevention and treatment of postburn scars and contracture</article-title>. <source>World Journal of Surgery</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A personal digital assistant for determination of fluid needs for burn patients</article-title>. <source>Biomedical Sciences Instrumentation</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saffle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeluff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Warden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Intra-muscular pressure in the burned arm: measurement and response to escharotomy</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Surgery</source> <volume>140</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>825</fpage>–<lpage>831</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide controversies: neuropsychologic testing, mechanism of toxicity and hyperbaric oxygen</article-title>. <source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Occupation therapy and physiotherapy for the patient with burns: principles and management guidelines</article-title>. <source>Journal of Burn Care &amp; Rehabilitation</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Still</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Klavuhn</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Diagnosis of burn depth using laser-induced indocyanine green fluorescence: a preliminary clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Burns</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1460408612462311"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yannas</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Orgill</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Template for skin regeneration</article-title>. <source>Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery</source> <volume>127</volume>(<supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement>): <fpage>60S</fpage>–<lpage>70S</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>