<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IBE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spibe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Indoor and Built Environment</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1420-326X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1423-0070</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1420326X11411501</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1420326X11411501</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Indoor and Personal Carbon Monoxide Exposure Risk Assessment in Sample of Apartment Buildings in Santiago, Chile</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Martínez</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1420326X11411501">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Caba</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1420326X11411501">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1420326X11411501">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1420326X11411501">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1420326X11411501">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Cáceres</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1420326X11411501">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1420326X11411501">d</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1420326X11411501"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1420326X11411501"><label>a</label>School of Medical Technology, Faculty of Medicine, University Diego Portales, Santiago de Chile</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1420326X11411501"><label>b</label>Science Health Faculty. Tarapacá University, Arica, Chile</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1420326X11411501"><label>c</label>Epidemiology Division. School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of Chile, Santiago de Chile</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1420326X11411501"><label>d</label>Grups de Recerca d´America i África Llatines, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1420326X11411501">Dante D. Cáceres, Epidemiology Division. School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of Chile, Santiago de Chile. Tel. <phone>56 2 9786546</phone>, Fax <fax>56 2 7377121</fax>, E-Mail <email>dcaceres@med.uchile.cl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>474</fpage>
<lpage>480</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2011. Reprints and permissions: http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Society of the Built Environment</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Indoor carbon monoxide (CO) exposure is considered around the world as one of the most important causes of poisoning with fatal outcomes. This study determined indoor CO levels and personal CO exposure and related risk factors during human activities in 96 apartments in a community of Santiago, Chile during the period from September to December of 2003. Indoor levels and personal exposure were determined using fixed, personal and single-breath CO monitors, respectively. Exposure risk factors and time-activities patterns were evaluated through an <italic>ad hoc</italic> exposure assessment questionnaire. Regression models were fitted to evaluate the effects of these risks factors on the personal CO levels. The median indoor CO level was 1 ppm; interquartile range (IQR): (0–1). The median personal CO level was 1 ppm; IQR: (0–7); CO exhaled was 3.0 ppm; IQR: (1–33). The number of cigarettes smoked and the levels of indoor environmental CO were significant predictors of the concentration of CO exhaled. This study showed that indoor median levels were below the national standard and the most important predictors of CO exposure were tobacco smoke and the smoking habit in apartments.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Carbon monoxide</kwd>
<kwd>Risk assessment</kwd>
<kwd>Indoor air quality</kwd>
<kwd>Apartment building</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1420326X11411501"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>One of the most frequent and dangerous indoor pollutants is carbon monoxide (CO), which is a product of the incomplete combustion of organic compounds. Its main emission sources are vehicle exhaust, heating systems (gas, kerosene, firewood, coal) and anthropogenic activities (smoking and cooking), among others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1420326X11411501">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1420326X11411501">4</xref>]. CO is an odourless and colourless toxic gas. The inhalation of high amounts of CO could lead to hypoxic injury, neurological damage and possibly death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1420326X11411501">5</xref>]. At lower levels of exposure, CO can cause mild effects that are often mistaken for flu. These symptoms include headaches, dizziness, disorientation, nausea and fatigue. The effects of CO exposure can vary greatly from person to person depending on age, overall health, the concentration and length of exposure among other factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1420326X11411501">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1420326X11411501">8</xref>].</p>
<p>Every year around the world (especially during the winter time) a great number of persons die accidentally due to intoxication from CO in indoor microenvironments (homes, buildings). The main causes of high level of exposure reported are usually associated with diverse intoxication grades due to incomplete combustion of heating and cooking systems, inadequate ventilation and low quality of maintenance and uses of heating devices in small areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1420326X11411501">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1420326X11411501">11</xref>]. The most susceptible individuals are pregnant women, small children and older people who suffer anaemic diseases or haematological disorders, cardiovascular and chronic respiratory diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1420326X11411501">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1420326X11411501">15</xref>].</p>
<p>Studies in Chile, have found high concentrations of CO in indoor environments. The source of origin were different fuels used for heating, repeatedly exceeding the national standards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1420326X11411501">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1420326X11411501">17</xref>]. In terms of national requirements of air quality standard to CO, the last revision was made in August 2002 where the CO levels of 9 parts per million (ppm), as an 8-h average and 26 ppm, as a 1-h average was promulgated in 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1420326X11411501">18</xref>]. There is no specific standard to residential indoor air quality for CO, except occupational exposure. On the other hand, it has also been established that in urban areas with high traffic, outdoor concentrations of CO have great influence on the indoor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1420326X11411501">19</xref>]. It is estimated that the contribution of residential combustion CO is about 5134 tons per year, mainly generated by burning wood, kerosene, LPG and piped gas in homes. Other types of biomass fuel are excluded in calculating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1420326X11411501">20</xref>]. The purpose of this investigation was to assess the exposure to CO and risk factors for persons living in building apartments in a community of the Metropolitan Region of Santiago de Chile.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1420326X11411501"><title>Material and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec3-1420326X11411501"><title>Study Design</title>
<p>A cross-sectional study was carried out in a random sample of 96 apartments in the Providencia Community in Santiago of Chile, during the period from September to December of 2003. In general, these apartments were located in residential areas, with moderate levels of vehicular traffic. The apartments are not situated near any industrial areas. This community is located near to downtown of the Santiago City.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1420326X11411501"><title>Description of the Apartments Characteristics and Subjects</title>
<p>The apartments selected for the study had an average of 2.72 bedrooms in each apartment; 55.2% had a surface greater than 80 m<sup>2</sup>, 39.6% and 21.9% of the apartments had a gas removal system in the kitchen (extraction system over stove) or in the bathroom (fan system), respectively, and 1.0% reported to have a gas removal system in the main bedroom. Only 70.8% reported having a water heating system heated by gas combustion. Of these, 57.4% and 32.4% were in the kitchen and the lodge, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1420326X11411501">Table 1</xref>). On the other hand, the type of fuel used for cooking most often was, natural gas (68.8%), followed by gas piping (24.0%). The large percentage of respondents used the water heater between 0 and 4 h (98.2%). During the monitoring period, the heating systems were not used.
<table-wrap id="table1-1420326X11411501" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of 96 apartments studied in Providencia Community, Santiago of Chile. September to December, 2003</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1420326X11411501" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11411501-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th>Mean</th>
<th>SD</th>
<th>Minimum</th>
<th>Maximum</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>No. of bedrooms</td>
<td>2.72</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Apartment size (m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>40–79; <italic>n</italic>, %</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>44.8</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>80–160; <italic>n</italic>, %</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>55.2</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Windows (m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Kitchen</td>
<td>1.27</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Living room</td>
<td>4.41</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Bath room</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Bed room</td>
<td>2,82</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Indoor gas removal system (n, %)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Kitchen</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>39.6</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Bathroom</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>21.9</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Bedroom</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Water heating system</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>70.8</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Kitchen</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>57.4</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Bathroom</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Logia</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>32.4</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Closet</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Bedroom</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Backyard</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1420326X11411501"><p>SD: Standard Deviation.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1420326X11411501">Table 2</xref> presents the average profile of apartment room and personal activities. The windows of the kitchen, the bathroom, and the living room stayed open for an average of 11.66 h, 10.95 h and 16.5 h, respectively, with a range from 0 to 24 h in all the cases. The windows of the dormitories stayed open for an average of 1.56 h (0–24 h). On the other hand, the median time spent indoors was 18.32 h, with a range of 10–24 h. There was no difference in usage between weekdays and weekends. With regard to mechanical ventilation, 100% of apartments reported an extraction system in the kitchen, which on average remained in use, about 2 h a day, ranging from 0 to 4 hours. In the apartments, 24.4% and 1.2% of the bathrooms and bedrooms have mechanical system, respectively. With respect to natural ventilation, the windows of the kitchens were kept open between 0 and 4 h. In the bedrooms most used was natural ventilation (98.8%); the windows were open on an average for 7 h with a range of 0–20 h. In the living room, windows were kept open from 5 to 9 h. In the dining room, windows were usually open from 0 to 4 h.
<table-wrap id="table2-1420326X11411501" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Average of time activities in apartments and people interviewed in Providencia Community, Santiago of Chile. September to December, 2003</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1420326X11411501" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11411501-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th>Mean</th>
<th>SD</th>
<th>Minimum</th>
<th>Maximum</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td><italic>Open windows, h.</italic>
</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Kitchen</td>
<td>11.66</td>
<td>7.83</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Bath room</td>
<td>10.95</td>
<td>10.89</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Living room</td>
<td>16.5</td>
<td>7.56</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Bed room</td>
<td>1.56</td>
<td>5.16</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Gas removal “on”, h</italic>.</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Kitchen</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Bedroom</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Water heating “on” h.</italic>
</td>
<td>5.27</td>
<td>3.76</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Time spent in different places</italic>
</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>In the week</italic>
</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Apartment</td>
<td>19.25</td>
<td>18.32</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Transport</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0.59</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Work or study</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>3.36</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>14</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other place</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.79</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>In the weekend</italic>
</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Apartment</td>
<td>19.0</td>
<td>18.67</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Transport</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Work or study</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Other place</td>
<td>4.00</td>
<td>4.64</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>18</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1420326X11411501"><p>SD: Standard Deviation.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1420326X11411501">Table 3</xref> presents the characteristics of the participants of this study. In terms of age, 36.2% were older than 70 years, of which 38.9% were women. In terms of education, 39.6% of the participants had finished high school level, 42.6% had completed college and 17.7% had technical education. Approximately 45.8% had an outdoor job, 61.1% of them being men. With regard to smoking, 37.5% of respondents reported smoking cigarettes, usually in the living/dining rooms (59.5%), smoking a range of 1–3 cigarettes during the period of monitoring. Notably, of the total of smokers within the apartments, 72.2% were women.
<table-wrap id="table3-1420326X11411501" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of 96 subject participants of CO indoor exposure study, Providencia Community, Santiago of Chile. September to December, 2003</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1420326X11411501" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11411501-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th colspan="2">Male<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Female<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Total<hr/></th></tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Age (y)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> &amp;#60;20</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>5.7</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 20–39</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>22.1</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>29.8</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> 40–69</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>20.0</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>37.2</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>30.9</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> &gt;70</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>31.4</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>38.9</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>36.2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Student/worker</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Outdoor</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>45.8</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Indoor</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>26.9</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>73.1</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>54.2</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1420326X11411501"><p>y = years; <italic>n</italic> = number.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1420326X11411501"><title>Measurements of Indoor and Personal CO</title>
<p>The indoor and personal CO concentrations in the apartments were measured using a real-time CO monitor (MicromacTM) Personal Alarm, equipped with data logging of up to 20 h storage capacity and with a range of measurements from 0 to 1000 ppm and a resolution 1 ppm. Breath CO in exhaled air was measured using the piCO Smokerlyzer Breath CO monitors (Bredfont Scientific Ltd, England, UK), with a linear range from 0 to 99 ppm and a resolution of 1 ppm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1420326X11411501">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1420326X11411501">23</xref>]. These equipments were calibrated in accordance with the standards of the Health Public Institute of Chile under EPA recommendations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1420326X11411501"><title>Exposure Assessment Questionnaire</title>
<p>An exposure assessment questionnaire was conducted to inquire about the apartment’s characteristics, about the family and personal lifestyle behaviour and on different symptoms related to CO exposure. This was performed on the occupants of the buildings during the study on the day following indoor and personal CO determinations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1420326X11411501"><title>Procedures and Ethical Aspects</title>
<p>In the present study we measured the indoor and personal CO levels of people living in apartment buildings located in residential areas in the Community of Providence in Santiago, Chile during the winter and spring of 2003. From the databases of the Building Department of Providence and the Electricity and Fuels Agency, the total of registered apartments was 38,478. Of these, 96 were selected through simple random sampling without replacement using a table of random numbers. The sample size was calculated under the following assumptions: 95% confidence interval, maximal variance and 10% error. Informed consent was obtained and the study was approved by the Ethical Committee of the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Chile.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1420326X11411501"><title>Indoor CO Measurements</title>
<p>For each building, the concentration of indoor environmental CO was measured with a fixed monitor at the breathing height at 1.5 m away from windows and doors in the main area where the participants spent most of their time in the apartment. The sampler was installed at 9.00 and air sampling was finished at 21.00 h. Smoking, cooking, heating and different time-activities were recorded by the person selected to assess CO exposure level during the sampling period. The eligibility criteria were determined in the exposure assessment questionnaire which asked who was the person who spent most time in the apartment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1420326X11411501"><title>Personal CO Measurements</title>
<p>Each participant carried a personal monitor located near the participant’s breathing zone, the personal monitoring were conducted simultaneously with indoor environmental CO measurements. At the end of the monitoring period the breath CO exhaled was measured. Each person was asked to provide at least two breaths to evaluate repeatability of the test.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1420326X11411501"><title>Data Handling and Statistical Analyses</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics were used to characterise the data of the questionnaire and the CO measurements. Univariate and bivariate analyses were performed using the level of CO assessed in blood. Finally a multivariable regression model was fitted by considering those variables that were significant in the bivariate analysis. The data were analysed with the statistical package STATA 6.0.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1420326X11411501"><title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1420326X11411501">Table 4</xref> presents the measured CO levels inside and outside the apartments and the personal CO exposure. In the case of indoor environment levels, the median was 1 ppm, with 46.9% of the apartments presenting undetected CO levels. Levels of 1 to 2 ppm were found in 53.1% of the apartments. Similarly, the median personal CO level was 1 ppm, with 22.9% at 2 ppm, 38.5% at 1 ppm and 1% at 7 ppm.
<table-wrap id="table4-1420326X11411501" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Indoor CO levels (average 12 h) in apartments, personal monitoring and exhaled air of 96 subjects in Providencia Community, Santiago of Chile. September to December, 2003</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1420326X11411501" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11411501-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th>CO levels (parts per million)</th>
<th>Median</th>
<th>IQR</th>
<th>Minimum – Maximums</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Apartments</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0–1</td>
<td>0–3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal monitoring</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0–2</td>
<td>0–7</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Breath Exhaled CO</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>2–8</td>
<td>1–33</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1420326X11411501"><p>ppm: parts per million; IQR: interquartilic range.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
<p>Median breath exhaled CO was 3 ppm, with a range of 1–33 ppm; 70.0% of the participants had levels equal to and below 7 ppm of CO, the rest having levels between 7 and 33 ppm.</p>
<p>The median CO levels determined in outdoors for the area represented by the national network of monitoring (MACAM) were significantly lower (&amp;#60;1 ppm) than those reported for the interior of the apartments and the personal ones. When the CO levels were monitored monthly, the outdoor levels were observed to have diminished significantly during the springtime, from 0.80 in September to 0.44 ppm at the end of December. On the other hand, the apartment’s indoor levels showed low median levels during September and October compared with November and December with median value of 1 ppm (data not shown). We found an inverse relationship not significant between outdoor and indoor CO levels (&#128;<italic>p</italic> = 0.106).</p>
<p>A multivariate linear regression model was fitted to the results with the objective of predicting the exhaled CO levels, considering the different risk factors associated with CO exposure. The correlation coefficient by the model was 0.927. Only the number of cigarettes smoked during monitoring periods, deeply smoked inhalation and environmental indoor CO levels were significant predictive variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1420326X11411501">Table 5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table5-1420326X11411501" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Adjusted linear regression model to exhaled CO dependent variable of 96 subjects participants of Providencia Community, Santiago of Chile. September to December, 2003</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1420326X11411501" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11411501-table5.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th>β</th>
<th>Standard error</th>
<th><italic>p</italic>-Value</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Job or study out</td>
<td>0.014</td>
<td>0.117</td>
<td>0.746</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Average time of open windows</td>
<td>0.037</td>
<td>0.011</td>
<td>0.409</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Smoking in the apartment (yes, no)</td>
<td>−0.029</td>
<td>0.078</td>
<td>0.560</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of cigarettes smoked</td>
<td>0.022</td>
<td>0.100</td>
<td>0.666</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Inhaled Smoke (yes, no)</td>
<td>0.370</td>
<td>0.157</td>
<td>&amp;#60;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of cigarettes smoked</td>
<td>0.314</td>
<td>0.233</td>
<td>&amp;#60;0.001</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal levels of CO, ppm</td>
<td>0.116</td>
<td>0.097</td>
<td>0.106</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Indoor Environmental, CO ppm</td>
<td>−0.254</td>
<td>0.128</td>
<td>0.001</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1420326X11411501"><p>Correlation coefficient:<italic> R:</italic> 0.927;<italic> R<sup>2</sup></italic>:0.859.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1420326X11411501"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>In the present study the personal and indoor environmental CO exposure and risk factors for people living in a building apartment were evaluated. The residential sector monitored were of residents with medium to high income, with a major percentage of older inhabitants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1420326X11411501">24</xref>]. In the last decades in Chile, several cases of persons poisoned by CO have been reported, especially those living in buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1420326X11411501">25</xref>]. This situation has been more frequent during winter. The objective of this study was to determine indoor and personal CO exposure and the associated risk factors.</p>
<p>The main findings were that a low percentage of the apartments had a gas removal system and that its use did not go beyond a maximum of 3 h on average. On the other hand, a high percentage informed to have a water heating system operated by gas combustion and a little less than 58% reported that these were located in the interior of the kitchen. With regard to ventilation, the owners of these apartments used to have at least one window open during a great part of the day, which would explain the low levels of CO determined during the monitoring period. Similar findings were reported by Willers et al. (2006), who evaluated a questionnaire-based system for classifying homes regarding combustion products produced by cooking systems in two different periods of the time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1420326X11411501">26</xref>]. They determined that the removal of combustion products produced during cooking was more efficient in a new building due to a better design of kitchens and better informed occupants of the risk of CO poisoning. Tuomainen et al. (2003) studied the indoor climate of two new blocks for 3 years and concluded that the levels of indoor air pollutants were lower compared with those of older buildings used as a control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1420326X11411501">27</xref>].</p>
<p>From the questionnaire study of the present study, the members of the family who would spend most of the time inside the apartments were the older people, who were in the apartments practically 80% of the day. Similar results were described by Leech et al., who assessed the time that people spent in different micro-environments in Canada and their relation with environmental contaminants. They found that older respondents spent the majority of their time indoors (88.6%), with smaller proportions of time spent outdoors (6.1%) and in vehicles (5.3%). Similar results were found when the same authors studied the situation of Americans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1420326X11411501">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1420326X11411501">29</xref>]. It does mean that these persons who are most susceptible to the effects of CO are at risk of an accident exposure to CO as the cause. In the present study we found that in spite of having a good level of schooling, above the national average, there is a widespread ignorance on what CO is and the effects it can have on people’s health. Furthermore, respondents reported not to know if their building had any alarm system or any kind of records about technical inspection on the quality of the pipelines of gas evacuation.</p>
<sec id="sec13-1420326X11411501"><title>Indoor Environmental CO</title>
<p>The assessed levels of CO were moderate and below the national outdoor standard. In general, the levels in more than half of the studied apartments were not detected by the monitors. In those apartments that had some open window most of the time or have mechanical gas removal system, the levels were low. Springston et al. (2002), in a study performed in New York on 136 commercial buildings, reported that 99.9% of the CO readings were below 10 ppm. These levels were higher than those determined in our study probably due to that study having been performed in commercial buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1420326X11411501">30</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1420326X11411501"><title>Personal CO Exposure</title>
<p>The levels in a low percentage of the determinations (1%) were on average equal to or above 7 ppm, which in general were associated with the moment of consumption of tobacco. In general, the levels determined in this study were below the national standard, the exception being those levels determined in homes where people smoked. Similar results were reported by Henderson et al. (2006), who performed a study in households with smokers and non-smokers, where the levels determined were less than 1 ppm and 0.1 to 21 ppm, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1420326X11411501">31</xref>]. Those measurements determined outdoors by the official monitoring network were significantly low compared with those assessed in the indoor environments (data not shown). When the monthly outdoor and indoor CO levels were compared, a clear corresponding relationship was not found. In wintertime, as expected, CO outdoor levels were higher than springtime. Indoor levels showed a not so clear distribution based on time, which were probably affected by indoor activities.</p>
<p>In the analysis of CO exhaled levels, approximately 70% fell within the ranges described for non-smoking individuals, and the high levels were detected in individuals who had smoked recently. Similar results were reported by Hung et al. (2006) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1420326X11411501">32</xref>]. A linear regression model was fitted to the results of those factors that have been described to be associated with the presence of CO in the organism and that were consulted by the questionnaire study of the exposure assessment. The number of cigarettes smoked, the inhalation of tobacco smoke and the CO levels measured inside the apartments were significant predictors of the CO exhaled levels. Dorevitch et al. (2007) evaluated the levels of CO exhaled by 27 subjects who are the residents of public housing and concluded that exhaled concentrations were more strongly associated with indoor than with outdoor concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1420326X11411501">33</xref>]. Approximately half of the variability in exhaled monoxide concentrations over time can be explained by changes in indoor monoxide concentrations. Raw et al. (2004) concluded that the seasonal effects on CO were largely due to indoor sources than ventilation systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1420326X11411501">34</xref>]. The American Cancer Society in June 1998 concluded that smoking cigars is a major source of fine-particle and CO indoor air pollution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1420326X11411501">35</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-1420326X11411501"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In general, the CO levels determined in building apartments were moderate. Older people are most at risk of exposure to high levels of CO, because they spend a lot of their time indoors. The main source and predictors of CO exposure continued to be tobacco smoke and the smoking habit inside apartments.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec16-1420326X11411501"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This study is funded by Pan-American Health Organization (PAHO), Project No. RES CHI-3145.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1420326X11411501"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Indoor air pollution: NO, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>: <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source> <year>1994</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>2 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1420326X11411501"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Indoor air pollutants: a literature review</article-title>: <source>Rev Environ Health</source> <year>1991</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1420326X11411501"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fullerton</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Semple</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalambo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Malamba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Suseno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Biomass fuel use and indoor air pollution in homes in Malawi</article-title>: <source>Occup Environ Med</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>783</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1420326X11411501"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar-Villalobos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Naeher</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Residential exposures to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and CO in Cusco, a high-altitude city in the Peruvian Andes: a pilot study</article-title>: <source>Arch Environ Occup Health</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1420326X11411501"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Carbon monoxide: the invisible killer</article-title>: <source>J R Soc Promot Health</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1420326X11411501"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Health effects of indoor combustion products</article-title>: <source>J R Soc Health</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1420326X11411501"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marbury</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spengler</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Health effects and sources of indoor air pollution. Part I</article-title>: <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source> <year>1987</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1486</fpage>–<lpage>1508</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1420326X11411501"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effects of low concentration carbon monoxide on human physiological function</article-title>: <source>Space Med Med Eng (Beijing)</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1420326X11411501"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Epidemic carbon monoxide poisoning following a winter storm</article-title>: <source>J Emerg Med</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1420326X11411501"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwela</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Cooking smoke: a silent killer</article-title>: <source>People Planet</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1420326X11411501"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Deru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Carbon monoxide poisoning at motels, hotels, and resorts</article-title>: <source>Am J Prev Med</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1420326X11411501"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu-Nolf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Poisons in the air: a cause of chronic disease in children</article-title>: <source>J Toxicol Clin Toxicol</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>491</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1420326X11411501"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omaye</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Metabolic modulation of carbon monoxide toxicity</article-title>: <source>Toxicology</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>180</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1420326X11411501"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Indoor air quality investigation according to age of the school buildings in Korea</article-title>: <source>J Environ Manage</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1420326X11411501"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marik</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group>: <comment>Carbon monoxide poisoning: Internet J Emergency Intensive Care Med 1997;1(N2): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ispub.com/journals/IJEICM/Vol1N2/CO.htm">http://www.ispub.com/journals/IJEICM/Vol1N2/CO.htm</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1420326X11411501"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Adonis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Retamal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ancic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Valencia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Indoor air pollution in a zone of extreme poverty of La Pintana, Santiago-Chile</article-title>: <source>Rev Med Chil</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1420326X11411501"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyarzun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaeta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effect of atmospheric pollution on the respiratory system</article-title>: <source>Biol Res</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1420326X11411501"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Secretaria General de la Presidencia: Norma de calidad primaria de aire para monóxido de carbono (CO)</collab>: <article-title>in Ministerio Secretaria General de la Presidencia Presidencia, Santiago, Decreto Supremo N° 115 del Gobierno de Chile</article-title>, <year>2002</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1420326X11411501"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Adonis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Impact of outdoor pollution on indoor air quality. The case of downtown Santiago (Chile)</article-title>: <source>Rev Med Chil</source> <year>1995</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1420326X11411501"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>CONAMA</collab>: <article-title>Plan de prevención y descontaminación atmosférica para la región Metropolitana: in Diario Oficial de la República de Chile</article-title>, <publisher-loc>Comisión Nacional del Medio Ambiente</publisher-loc>, <year>1998</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1420326X11411501"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vesey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Low cost carbon monoxide monitors in smoking assessment</article-title>: <source>Thorax</source> <year>1986</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>886</fpage>–<lpage>887</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1420326X11411501"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vreman</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmatz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanaroff</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Validation of the natus CO-Stat end tidal breath analyzer in children and adults</article-title>: <source>J Clin Monit Comput</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>7–8</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1420326X11411501"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Idle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boreham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Carbon monoxide in breath in relation to smoking and carboxyhaemoglobin levels</article-title>: <source>Thorax</source> <year>1981</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1420326X11411501"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>CDS</collab>: <article-title>Memoria 2007</article-title>: in: <source>Corporación de Desarrollo Social de Providencia</source>, <publisher-loc>Santiago</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Ilustre Municipalidad de Providencia</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1420326X11411501"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aceituno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Urrutia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sujima</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>González-Hernández</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Manifestaciones neurológicas de la intoxicación aguda por monóxido de carbono: revisión de la literatura a propósito de un caso</article-title>: <source>Revista Memorizacom</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1420326X11411501"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willers</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunekreef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldenwening</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerkhof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vries</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Gas cooking, kitchen ventilation, and exposure to combustion products</article-title>: <source>Indoor Air</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1420326X11411501"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuomainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuomainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liesivuori</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasanen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>The 3-year follow-up study in a block of flats - experiences in the use of the Finnish indoor climate classification</article-title>: <source>Indoor Air</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1420326X11411501"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Raizenne</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>It's about time: a comparison of Canadian and American time-activity patterns</article-title>: <source>J Expo Anal Environ Epidemiol</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1420326X11411501"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>The Canadian human activity pattern survey report of methods and population surveyed</article-title>: <source>Chronic Dis Can</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1420326X11411501"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springston</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleversey</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Baseline indoor air quality measurements collected from 136 metropolitan New York region commercial office buildings between 1997-1999</article-title>: <source>AIHA J (Fairfax, Va)</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1420326X11411501"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Real-time measurement of short-term peaks in environmental CO concentrations in the homes of the elderly in South Wales</article-title>: <source>J Expo Sci Environ Epidemiol</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1420326X11411501"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Exhaled carbon monoxide level as an indicator of cigarette consumption in a workplace cessation program in Taiwan</article-title>: <source>J Formos Med Assoc</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1420326X11411501"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorevitch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demirtas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheff</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Persky</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Bias and confounding in longitudinal measures of exhaled monoxides</article-title>: <source>J Expo Sci Environ Epidemiol</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1420326X11411501"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raw</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coward</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Exposure to air pollutants in English homes</article-title>: <source>J Expo Anal Environ Epidemiol</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S85</fpage>–<lpage>S94</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1420326X11411501"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Crammer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Repace</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Henningfield</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shopland</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Health risks associated with cigar smoking</article-title>: <source>JAMA</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>284</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>