<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TDO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptdo</journal-id>
<journal-title>Tropical Doctor</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0049-4755</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1758-1133</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0049475513491726</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0049475513491726</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Short Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Primary small bowel volvulus in adults can be fatal: a report of two cases and brief review of the subject</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Weledji</surname><given-names>Elroy P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0049475513491726">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0049475513491726">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0049475513491726"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Theophile</surname><given-names>Nana</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0049475513491726">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0049475513491726"><label>1</label>Senior Lecturer in Anatomy and Clinical Surgery, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Buea, Cameroon</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0049475513491726"><label>2</label>General Surgeon, Regional Hospital Buea, Cameroon</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0049475513491726"><label>3</label>Physician, Department of Surgery, Regional Hospital Buea, Cameroon</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0049475513491726">Elroy P Weledji, PO Box 126, Limbe, SW Region, Buea, Cameroon. Email: <email>elroypat@yahoo.co.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>75</fpage>
<lpage>76</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Primary small bowel volvulus is a relatively rare cause of small bowel obstruction but can be fatal. The chief problem is in differentiating it from other causes of obstruction that can be treated conservatively. We report two cases of primary small bowel volvulus in a regional hospital in the south west region of Cameroon within a 2 month period and briefly review the literature.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Primary small bowel volvulus</kwd>
<kwd>strangulation obstruction</kwd>
<kwd>‘virgin’ abdomen</kwd>
<kwd>high fibre diet</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0049475513491726" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Acute intestinal obstruction may occur as a closed-loop obstruction with a volvulus or an obstructed hernia. Gangrene occurs rapidly in a closed-loop obstruction. Primary small bowel volvulus is often seen in Africa and Asia but only sporadically in the Western world. It occurs in the ‘virgin’ abdomen, that is, where there has been no previous abdominal operation, no anatomic abnormalities (i.e. short or long mesenteric axis, narrow attachment to posterior abdominal wall) and no other predisposing factors including parasitic infestations. It seems to be associated with special dietary habits (ingestion of fibre-rich foods in a short time or following a long fast).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0049475513491726">1</xref></sup> Central abdominal pain resistant to narcotic analgesia should heighten the suspicion of the diagnosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491726">2</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0049475513491726" sec-type="cases"><title>Case 1</title>
<p>A 29-year-old woman was admitted as an emergency with a short history (∼6 h) of a sudden onset colicky abdominal pain associated with: copious vomiting; a progressive central abdominal distension; and absolute constipation. The frequency of the colicky pain increased with time from about every 30 min to about every 5 min on admission. She had undergone no previous operations. Following resuscitation with intravenous fluids and analgesia she became less restless but the pain was constant. On examination she was moderately dehydrated with a tachycardia. She had a normal blood pressure and temperature. She had no hernia, nor abdominal scar. Her abdomen was centrally distended and tense with tinkling (obstructive) bowel sounds. There was generalized rebound tenderness. A chest examination was unremarkable; a full blood count was normal; and erect chest and plain abdominal X-rays were also unremarkable. A diagnosis of an acute small bowel obstruction with probable peritonitis was made for which she underwent a laparotomy ∼2 h after admission. Laparotomy revealed a twisted black segment (∼20 cm long) of the mid-ileum. The volvulus was untwisted. There was a demarcated margin of ischaemia and the ‘black’ gut was resected with a good margin of well-vascularized small bowel in order to allow an end-to-end anastomosis. Apart for a few days of postoperative ileus, she made good postoperative recovery and was discharged 1 week later. She had no further complaints on follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0049475513491726" sec-type="cases"><title>Case 2</title>
<p>A 30-year-old man was admitted as an emergency in the medical ward with an acute generalized abdominal pain associated with vomiting after feed and suffering from diarrhoea. The abdomen was mildly distended centrally but did not elicit rebound tenderness. His bowel sounds were normal. He was treated for an acute enteric infection with intravenous fluids, antibiotics and analgesia. After 24 h he was able to tolerate food but his symptoms worsened the following day and a surgical opinion was sought. On examination he was dehydrated, hypotensive and tachycardic. There was no abdominal scar or hernia. There was rebound tenderness on a board-like abdomen with absent bowel sounds. The abdomen was only mildly distended centrally. A diagnosis of an acute abdomen was made. He was aggressively resuscitated with intravenous fluids, antibiotics and analgesia and taken to theatre about 2 h later for a laparotomy. At laparotomy, there was free serosanguineous fluid in the peritoneal cavity and most of the ileum was black except for about 3 cm of the terminal ileum. Again, a definite margin of ischaemia was seen. The ‘black’ gut was resected and a jejuno-ileal anastomosis was done. Postoperatively he developed an absolute constipation with a persistent abdominal distension for 1 week which suddenly responded to an enema. He was then discharged and had no further complaints on follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0049475513491726" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Small bowel volvulus is an uncommon but important cause of small intestinal obstruction. It often results in ischaemia or even infarction from venous congestion involving mostly the ileum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491726">2</xref></sup> Delay in diagnosis and surgical intervention increases morbidity and mortality rates as seen in the second case that required greater bowel resection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0049475513491726">3</xref></sup> Based on the cause, the small bowel volvulus can be divided into primary and secondary type. Goals for treatment of small bowel volvulus should include: awareness of this uncommon diagnosis; accurate work-up; and advanced surgical intervention.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0049475513491726">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491726"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0049475513491726"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0049475513491726"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0049475513491726">5</xref></sup> The cardinal presenting symptom is abdominal pain. There is no single specific diagnostic clinical sign or abnormality in laboratory or radiological finding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491726">2</xref></sup> Clinical examination and plain film radiography may miss the diagnosis of primary small bowel volvulus leading to delay in surgical intervention with a subsequent increase in morbidity and mortality. Plain abdominal X-ray may reveal a distended small bowel with air-fluid level, prominent valvulae conniventes and an absence of gas in the large bowel but cannot show if the bowel is strangulated. Computed tomography (CT) can diagnose ischaemic bowel and reveal the aetiology of the small bowel obstruction. The ability of CT to show the cause of small-bowel obstruction makes it an important additional diagnostic tool to a plain abdominal X-ray, especially when other causes of obstruction that can be treated conservatively are suspected.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0049475513491726">4</xref></sup> Otherwise, in practice, as time is the essence and the patient may not be stable, the diagnosis should be made by laparotomy. The failure to perform an exploratory laparotomy for this life-threatening emergency is deplorable.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0049475513491726">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491726"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0049475513491726"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0049475513491726"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0049475513491726">5</xref></sup> Early diagnosis and early surgery are the keys for the successful management of strangulation obstruction of the small bowel.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec5-0049475513491726"><title>Declaration of conflicting interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0049475513491726"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0049475513491726"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwuagu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Deans</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Small bowel volvulus: a review</article-title>. <source>J R Coll Surg Edinb</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0049475513491726"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roggo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottinger</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Acute small bowel volvulus in adults. A sporadic form of strangulating intestinal obstruction</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>216</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0049475513491726"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wert</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarpl</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwino</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Small bowel volvulus: time is the essence</article-title>. <source>Surg Rounds</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0049475513491726"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maglinte</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reliability and role of plain film radiography and CT in the diagnosis of small-bowel obstruction</article-title>. <source>Lin Ann Surg</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>216</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0049475513491726"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Primary small bowel volvulus in rural Nepal</article-title>. <source>Trop Doct</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>