<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjch</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Contemporary History</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0094</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7250</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022009412461814</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022009412461814</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘Must Will Peace’: The British Brokering of ‘Central European’ and ‘Balkan Locarno’, 1925–9</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bakić</surname><given-names>Dragan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0022009412461814"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0022009412461814">Institute for Balkan Studies of the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts, Belgrade, Serbia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022009412461814">Dragan Bakić, Knez Mihailova 35/IV, 11000 Belgrade, Serbia. Email: <email>drabakic@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>48</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>24</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article examines the British attempt to use the momentum created after the conclusion of the Locarno Agreements of October 1925 to promote a similar settlement in Central Europe among the Little Entente countries and Hungary, and in the Balkans, where Bulgaria had to be reconciled with her neighbours, particularly with Yugoslavia (Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes), with each region being dealt with in a separate settlement. The approach of the Foreign Secretary, Sir Austen Chamberlain, was to induce the leaders of the countries in question to come into personal contact and tackle their mutual antagonisms, while at the same time securing that Britain, France and Italy maintained a common stance and spoke with one voice to all the concerned governments. The article outlines the main lines of diplomatic intercourse and analyses the reasons for the ultimate failure of both ‘Central European’ and ‘Balkan Locarno’. It is argued here that Chamberlain’s policy, his distorted perceptions, delusive premises and fallacious judgement accounted for the inevitable breakdown of his Locarno-like scheme. This failure became apparent towards the end of the period studied here and its consequences heralded difficult times in the years to come.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Balkan</kwd>
<kwd>Central European</kwd>
<kwd>Chamberlain</kwd>
<kwd>Locarno</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>When the Locarno agreement was initialled on 16 October 1925 it raised great hopes and expectations across Europe that it would usher in a new era in international relations relieved of the anxieties and conflicts left over from the First World War. The exuberance of optimism was especially manifest in Britain and the role of the Foreign Secretary, Sir Austen Chamberlain, in bringing it about was extolled. Ever since the war a doctrine had been gaining ground that the root of the world catastrophe had been the secret diplomacy of the pre-war era whereby a few policy-makers had concluded clandestine military pacts which had divided Europe into hostile blocs. The ensuing conflagration had been but a natural progression of such a sinister situation; a new era of postwar open diplomacy under the aegis of the fledgling League of Nations was meant to ensure that the continent would not revert to the old bad ways.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0022009412461814">1</xref></sup> The Locarno agreement appeared to have offered a perfect solution in accordance with the postwar ideals: two antagonistic countries, Germany and France, consented to regard their common border as final, an undertaking that was guaranteed by Britain and Italy.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0022009412461814">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Locarno settlement, however, clearly distinguished between the mutual Franco–German–Belgian frontiers, on the one hand, and the German eastern frontiers with Poland and Czechoslovakia, on the other. The Germans solemnly acknowledged the former, and agreed to a guarantee by two other Great Powers, whereas they refused to extend the same recognition to the latter and conceded only arbitration treaties for the settlement of disputes. In fact, this implied derogation of the sanctity of the eastern borders ‘was widely interpreted as a green light for Germany in the east’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0022009412461814">3</xref></sup> Indeed, the German Foreign Minister, Gustav Stresemann, gloated over the fact of his Polish and Czechoslovak counterparts being marginalized and ultimately defeated in a diplomatic struggle to have their countries included in the pact of mutual guarantee on par with the Western European participants. He later fondly recalled how Edvard Beneš of Czechoslovakia and Alexander Skrzyński of Poland had ‘had to sit in the neighbouring room until we let them in’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0022009412461814">4</xref></sup> Thus despite Beneš’s brave face and inclination to look at the Locarno treaties from the more positive angle of general European pacification and the enhanced security that Prague could derive from such a development,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0022009412461814">5</xref></sup> it does not seem plausible to interpret his diplomatic record at Locarno as successful.</p>
<p>The formula of a voluntarily contracted agreement between former enemies seemed an obvious solution for the rest of the continent as well and talk was rife in the House of Commons about the extension of the Locarno principles to the Balkans.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0022009412461814">6</xref></sup> There was also a bitter feeling between Hungary and the three states of the Little Entente – Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia and Romania – an alliance formed for the specific purpose of keeping in check Hungarian irredentism and preventing a possible Habsburg restoration in that country. This local confrontation on the Danube presented another area where the Locarno prescription appeared to be a well suited remedy. British diplomacy took a prominent role in an attempt to promote Locarno-like agreements in both Central Europe and the Balkans. However, this intriguing and ultimately abortive endeavour has received little scholarly attention.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0022009412461814">7</xref></sup> This article aims to contribute towards filling that void by outlining the main lines of diplomatic intercourse and suggesting some reasons for its failure. As there were separate proposals for agreements pertaining to the two regions, the article is divided in two sections. The first one deals with ‘Central European’ Locarno that was supposed to embrace Hungary and the Little Entente countries; the second one focuses on ‘Balkan Locarno’ which was intended to reconcile Bulgaria and her neighbours. On account of geographical reasons both schemes included Yugoslavia (whose official name up to 1929 was the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes) and Romania, and because of that were expected, as one British diplomat put it, to interlock.</p>
<p>In a comprehensive memorandum pertaining to British policy in regard to European security, written in the wake of the German proposal for a mutual guarantee pact in the West, the Historical Adviser of the Foreign Office, James Headlam-Morley, did not neglect the necessity to provide for the security of Central and Eastern Europe or overlook the grave dangers of a failure to meet this requirement:<disp-quote>
<p>Has anyone attempted to realise what would happen if there were to be a new partition of Poland, or if the Czechoslovak State were to be so curtailed and dismembered that in fact it disappeared from the map of Europe? The whole of Europe would at once be in chaos. There would no longer be any principle, meaning or sense in the territorial arrangements of the continent. Imagine, for instance, that under some improbable condition, Austria rejoined Germany; that Germany, using the discontented minority in Bohemia, demanded a new frontier far over the mountains, including Carlsbad and Pilsen, and that at the same time, in alliance with Germany, the Hungarians recovered the southern slope of the Carpathians. This would be catastrophic, and, even if we neglected to interfere in time to prevent it, we should afterwards be driven to interfere, probably too late.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0022009412461814">8</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>For Headlam-Morley, a fervent advocate of the maintenance of the settlement of 1919, notwithstanding any necessary and even desirable minor rectifications, a clear and official British statement of policy in regard to Central and Eastern Europe was required not only to accommodate the uncertainties and vagueness of the League of Nation’s mechanism, but also to assure the smaller states of the region of their existence and peaceful development. The goal, he proposed, was a rapprochement between the Little Entente countries and Hungary in such a way as to lead to a conversion of the treaties binding the former into a mutual treaty of guarantee.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0022009412461814">9</xref></sup> Thus, the system of separate alliances, ‘fundamentally inconsistent with the Covenant of the League’, would be transformed into a more general agreement, eventually European in scope. Headlam-Morley’s suggestion of a clear-cut guarantee for the small successor states was never seriously contemplated for it ran contrary to the prevailing opinion in the Foreign Office. Austen Chamberlain, in particular, made a sharp differentiation between the region across the English channel with which Britain was closely involved and that on the eastern fringes of the continent which did not seem to touch directly on British interests:<disp-quote>
<p>I would say broadly that in Western Europe we are a partner, that comparatively speaking in Eastern Europe our role should be that of a disinterested <italic>amicus curiae</italic>. Our safety in certain circumstances is bound up with that of France or Belgium or Holland. If this be secured I do not believe that it is bound up with Roumania for example; &amp; if I rightly apprehend him [Headlem-Morley], I could not contemplate linking our fortunes so closely with the Eastern States as he would do.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0022009412461814">10</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Chamberlain’s self-denying profession was not based on the simple under-appreciation of the concept of indivisibility of peace. It was rather an integral part of his strategic thinking relating to European security. In Chamberlain’s view, Franco–German conflict was the main danger spot and the only one that could set fire to the whole of the continent. If that conflict could be resolved and a good working relationship established between France, Germany, Britain and Italy, then European stability would be assured; small powers could not disturb continental stability on their own without being encouraged and supported by powerful patrons.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0022009412461814">11</xref></sup> His approach and practical conduct of diplomatic initiative for a conclusion of ‘Central European’ and ‘Balkan Locarno’ bore witness to such strategic appreciation.</p>
<p>Chamberlain was quick to seize the momentum and used the occasion of the Locarno gathering to advance a suggestion to Beneš that a similar arrangement might be reached between the Little Entente countries and Hungary and Austria.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0022009412461814">12</xref></sup> The Czech was responsive and promised that he would work to that end. Indeed, Beneš did discuss the subject with the Yugoslav Foreign Minister, Momčilo Ninčić, but the report of the British Minister at Belgrade, Howard Kennard, was not too encouraging – the two Foreign Ministers thought that the initiative should come from either Britain or France and they believed that Italy would make trouble as regards Austria while Hungary would put forward impossible demands.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0022009412461814">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>When Kennard reported that Ninčić was sceptical about the prospects of the Balkan pact and more hopeful of a Central European variant, the Foreign Office concurred with his estimation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0022009412461814">14</xref></sup> Chamberlain cleared his mind on the subject as well and his views were expressed in circular instructions to Prague, Vienna, Budapest, Belgrade and Bucharest. The Foreign Secretary used a rather moralizing language:<disp-quote>
<p>For their part His Majesty’s Government would most cordially welcome and give their fullest support to any proposal having for its object the extension to Central Europe of the principles established at Locarno. Salvation, however, must come from within, and there can be no real peace but by consent. If the Great Powers were to impose peace, such peace would remain an outer garment, which could be thrown off at any moment. The Governments directly concerned must will peace. When they do, and then only, will peace be a reality.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0022009412461814">15</xref></sup></p></disp-quote></p>
<p>On the more practical side, Chamberlain pointed out two preliminary conditions to be preached to all and sundry: a policy of conciliation towards the minorities in the successor states and the cooperation and goodwill of the Italians.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-0022009412461814">16</xref></sup> The latter provision showed that he pragmatically appreciated that insuperable obstacles were more likely to come from a Great Power than from the smaller successor states. At the same time it was a logical ramification of his concept of consensual direction of European affairs by the concert of Great Powers.</p>
<p>The British Minister at Budapest, Colville Barclay, sounded out the Hungarian Foreign Minister, Lajos Walko, about the idea and concluded that the country at large was far from sharing the spirit of Locarno.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-0022009412461814">17</xref></sup> His pessimism was shared by Lampson and the Permanent Under-Secretary, William Tyrell, who maintained that the minority grievances were not a genuine concern of the Hungarian government but rather a means of keeping an irredentism alive until a favourable occasion had arisen to restore direct rule from Budapest over those minorities and the lost territory.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-0022009412461814">18</xref></sup> Barclay’s impression was confirmed in a conversation between Lampson and the Hungarian Minister in London when the latter resolutely refused even the suggestion of concluding general arbitration treaties with the neighbouring states.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-0022009412461814">19</xref></sup> Chamberlain was also disillusioned about the true Hungarian motives in the matter.</p>
<p>In terms of practical politics, then, how could a Locarno-modelled agreement realistically be promoted? The invidious task of conjuring up a concrete plan was undertaken by Howard Smith. His basic assumption was that Hungary, unlike Germany with her occupied Rhineland and trading interests, lacked any special inducement to seek a rapprochement with her neighbours. On the other hand, the Little Entente states needed a spell of settled peace in order to consolidate their administration and their hold on the new provinces peopled by different nations. Hence, it was the Little Entente that had to initiate reconciliation by offering reasonable and sufficiently attractive concessions to its adversary:<disp-quote>
<p>The agreement might be something on the following lines. Hungary would agree to accept the frontiers as laid down by the Treaty of Trianon. Any revision of the frontiers is impossible now. Certain areas might be declared demilitarised zones of a certain depth on each side of the frontier, and each of the States concerned – Hungary, Czechoslovakia, Roumania, Jugoslavia and, if necessary, Austria – would undertake to resist any other State which violated the demilitarised zones. In this way the Little Entente would still exist and operate in the case of Hungarian aggression, while Hungary would herself have the assistance of all the other Powers in the contrary case. This would meet Hungary’s present objection that she, who is disarmed, is surrounded by enemies armed to the teeth; and would tend towards general disarmament in this part of Europe.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-0022009412461814">20</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Nothing could, however, be accomplished without addressing the minority issue. In this respect Howard Smith proposed an entirely new approach. Hitherto all the minority grievances had been dealt with in accordance with the terms of the minority treaties through the medium of the League of Nations. The experience was, Howard Smith claimed, deeply unsatisfactory as the procedure had been giving undue importance to insignificant complaints and affording the Hungarians a valid and perpetual excuse to foment irredentism and allege afterwards that the League had not given a fair hearing to minority petitions; moreover, it had been producing nothing but interminable and unsolvable bickering which, in turn, could only further exacerbate the relations between the parties concerned. By mutual agreement such a procedure should be abandoned and replaced by ‘conciliation boards, which would be called on to settle any question affecting the treatment of the Hungarian minority which the Hungarian Government should see fit to bring up.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-0022009412461814">21</xref></sup> The concept of conciliation boards would be borrowed from the Locarno treaties. Though the appeals would no doubt be abundant in the beginning, they could reasonably be expected to diminish in time. If accepted, this would be a major concession on the part of the Little Entente as it would effectively allow the Hungarian government to interfere in their internal affairs.</p>
<p>The memorandum envisaged a further concession by the Little Entente which consisted of revoking the ban upon a Habsburg restoration. The suggestion was justified on the grounds that the peace treaties did not even mention the House of Habsburg and its dethronement as opposed to the German dynasty and that the anti-Habsburg law passed in the Hungarian parliament in 1921 had come into being under direct pressure from both the Little Entente and the Great Powers. The gesture of the former in this sense would alleviate tension and bring closer a general appeasement.</p>
<p>The suggestions advanced tended to underrate the main problem – Hungary’s utter refusal to acquiesce in the status quo concerning the frontiers – an attitude of mind which was clearly recognized in the Central Department of the Foreign Office. That in itself rendered pointless any effort to treat the minority issue as the crux of the problem. Yet, the memorandum represented a fairly elaborate and skilful attempt to tackle the obstacles which stood in the way of a Central European Locarno and, given the circumstances, it could have hardly made more far-reaching proposals.</p>
<p>A more precise indication of the practical lines on which the thoughts of the Foreign Office were running was outlined in reply to Kennard’s suggestion unobtrusively to encourage the Yugoslavs in the direction of a Balkan Locarno. The Chief of the Central Department underlined that the scheme for Central Europe and the Balkans fell into two distinct headings, although they might under favourable conditions ‘ultimately interlock to some extent’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-0022009412461814">22</xref></sup> As regards the former he was hopeful that something would come to pass following the forthcoming conversations with the Hungarian Prime Minister, Count István Bethlen, at Geneva and he believed that ‘we must look to Beneš to keep things going in that particular sphere rather than to Ninčić.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-0022009412461814">23</xref></sup> Hungary was to be treated with the utmost patience so as not to add to her Prime Minister’s domestic difficulties and in general the process of Central European pacification should be left to run its course.</p>
<p>A chance to instil the idea of a Central European agreement among the states concerned offered itself during the usual pourparlers during the League sessions in Geneva. Chamberlain, accompanied by Lampson, met with Count Bethlen and urged him to come to terms with the Little Entente states.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-0022009412461814">24</xref></sup> Having frankly admitted that no Hungarian government could ever recognize the territorial settlement under the peace treaty as final and pointed out all the difficulties standing in the way of any Danubian Locarno, the Prime Minister still intimated that he would take the opportunity of the proceedings of the Hungarian Committee of the League in March 1926 to discuss the question personally with Beneš and propose some sort of arbitration agreement.</p>
<p>At the time when progress in the negotiations was expected, however, the franc forgery scandal clouded the prospect of a successful issue. In December 1925 a few Magyar nationals were arrested in Holland after counterfeit bank notes had been found in their possession. The fact that those arrested were prominent members of the irredentist Awakening Hungarians society and that the tentacles of the affair reached some persons belonging to Regent Miklós Horthy’s entourage caused a storm of protest, particularly in Prague. At this juncture a show of British support greatly strengthened the hand of the Hungarian government on the international stage. Since the establishment of Horthy’s regentship in March 1920, and even more so after Bethlen took the reins of premiership the following year, the British had been increasingly backing Budapest in its conduct of both foreign and economic policies. Despite its anti-democratic nature the Horthy regime was deemed a solid conservative creation which presented the only alternative to internal chaos in Hungary and a guarantee of a sensible foreign policy.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-0022009412461814">25</xref></sup> The most visible sign of British sympathy was the support extended to the Bethlen government in connection with the Hungarian reconstruction loan of 1924.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-0022009412461814">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>The initial reaction of the Foreign Office to the forgery affair confirmed the unswerving trust vested in the Hungarian leadership. Lampson spoke his mind in a private letter to the Minister Plenipotentiary at Paris, Eric Phipps, in no uncertain terms:<disp-quote>
<p>Frankly, I remain completely sceptical as to there being any official backing by the Hungarian Government behind it. It is quite incredible that anyone outside a lunatic asylum should take up such a fantastic scheme. It is true, as we all know, that many Hungarians are not quite normal when it is a question of recovering Hungary’s lost domains, or of re-establishing the Crown; but I repeat that I refuse to believe that, even allowing for this national lack of balance, either Bethlen or any other responsible Hungarian (I of course include Horthy) can have had anything whatever to do with this madness.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-0022009412461814">27</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Chamberlain instructed Sir George Clerk in Prague and other Ministers accredited to the Little Entente countries to state British confidence in the correct attitude of the Hungarian authorities and in Bethlen’s will to see the judicial procedure being carried out. In his defence of the British attitude he was emphatic that ‘it is hardly open to question that Count Bethlen is the only statesman in Hungary with any breadth of outlook, and his fall might well be disastrous, not only to his country, but to the prospects of the re-establishment of good relations between Hungary and her neighbours.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-0022009412461814">28</xref></sup> Chamberlain’s estimate was strongly supported by information supplied by the Legation at Budapest. Barclay credited Bethlen with a sincere desire to suppress the Awakening Hungarians and hoped that he might emerge triumphant from the crisis, notwithstanding the earlier indulgence of the authorities towards the irredentist society which had been enjoying the support of the Regent himself.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-0022009412461814">29</xref></sup> The Minister made full allowance for the fact that the premier lacked the strength directly to attack the Awakening Hungarians who had intended, in his opinion, to bring about a coup d’état and put Albrecht Habsburg on the throne.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-0022009412461814">30</xref></sup> In the light of such a reading of Hungarian politics Barclay’s appreciation of its central dilemma seems to have been somewhat contradictory:<disp-quote>
<p>Some say that as long as Horthy is Governor there will be constant trouble from the Awakening Hungarians, constant complaints from the Little Entente and consequently no peace in Central Europe. Personally I cannot agree with this view. Horthy with the aid of Awakening Hungarians restored order out of chaos and has kept it for over five years. If this combination were broken up the Awakening Hungarians would certainly be more troublesome than ever.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-0022009412461814">31</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Barclay’s views were wholeheartedly endorsed in the Central Department. The Prime Minister’s decision to treat the forgery affair as a purely criminal incident without a political background was exonerated as the right one bearing in mind the strength of the irredentist organization and its close connection with the Regent; after all, that was the only policy which would keep both Hungarian leading men in charge.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-0022009412461814">32</xref></sup> Consequently, the Little Entente’s sharp reaction to the scandal and the peril it entailed for the maintenance of the current Hungarian regime was detested in Whitehall:<disp-quote>
<p>The Little Entente was undoubtedly out for Bethlen’s blood (1) because as a general principle they fear Hungary and consequently don’t want a strong man there, (2) because they want to promote chaos in Hungary &amp; hence talk of ‘democratising’ her – a perfectly mischievous proposal and not even genuinely meant. I hold our proper policy to be <italic>discreet</italic> support of Bethlen and a deliberate announcement to all our foreign visitors of the categorical assurances he has given us.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-0022009412461814">33</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Having heard of the stiff note being sent by the French government to Budapest, the Central Department was most anxious to forestall such an action and decided to urge Paris to ‘go slowly over Hungary’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-0022009412461814">34</xref></sup> The British were worried lest the forgery business would arrest and prevent a speedy winding up of the remaining issues concerning Hungarian disarmament and the withdrawal of the Control Commission from that country. When the forgeries trial started in May 1926 the accumulated evidence pointed to connivance on the part of the government and went a long way to justify all the accusations coming from Prague and Paris. The occasion made the Permanent Under-Secretary, William Tyrell, lay bare the attitude of the Foreign Office towards the Hungarian regime: ‘It is quite clear that Count Bethlen is sufficiently to blame, if there is in any quarter a desire to involve his responsibility. Our role should be to advise all and sundry that in the general interest of peace &amp; settlement it would be wise not to upset him over this affair.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-0022009412461814">35</xref></sup></p>
<p>Thus at all times the British bore in mind the adverse affect that the forgery scandal could have on the ongoing attempt to procure a Locarno-type agreement. Lampson insisted that it was necessary to spare no effort to scotch the affair lest it should prejudice an attempt to achieve conciliation between Hungary and her neighbours.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-0022009412461814">36</xref></sup> Howard Smith was more pessimistic in his prediction that hopes of any settlement were being delayed for many months and perhaps years.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-0022009412461814">37</xref></sup> This prognostication proved very accurate. On the occasion of a personal meeting with Lampson at Geneva on 8 March 1926 Bethlen admitted that nothing could be done in the matter of an arbitration treaty with Czechoslovakia due to the bitterness aroused in Hungary by Beneš’s part in the agitation over the forgeries scandal.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-0022009412461814">38</xref></sup> The Hungarian suggested that conciliation might be initiated with Yugoslavia instead and his new proposal was well received at the Foreign Office.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-0022009412461814">39</xref></sup> Indeed, it had long been obvious that certain factors rendered an understanding between Hungary and Yugoslavia much easier to realize than a rapprochement between Hungary and the other two Little Entente members. The smallest tract of former Hungarian territory with comparatively few Hungarians had been ceded to Belgrade as compared with the large Magyar minorities in Romania and Czechoslovakia. Finally, there was an important psychological proclivity, noted by all British observers, to come to terms with Yugoslavia: whereas the Magyars, proud of their military tradition, were contemptuous of the Czechs and Romanians in terms of their war record, they had a wholesome respect for Serb military virtues. The British were aware of how formidable a difficulty this intolerance and the reactions it caused on the other side presented:<disp-quote>
<p>If the issues involved were not so serious the attitude of Hungary towards the Little Entente would be amusing. It is stupid of the Hungarians to talk as they do, and they despise the Czechs and Roumanians and do not seem to be able to resist telling them so with consequent fury and fear from Prague and Bucharest. As a matter of fact Hungary is powerless and if only Prague and Bucharest could take no notice the Hungarians would probably desist.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-0022009412461814">40</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>For that reason it seemed very opportune to start the process of reconciliation from the quarter where the chances appeared to have been most favourable.</p>
<p>Furthermore, as a result of the forgery scandal Beneš was suspected of being primarily interested in getting rid of Count Bethlen. When Beneš’s overtures to Hungary for the conclusion of an arbitration treaty were rejected, the Foreign Office was full of understanding for the intricacies of Bethlen’s internal position; by contrast, the Czech was generally charged with insincerity and an eagerness to score a point at the expense of his adversary.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-0022009412461814">41</xref></sup> The negotiations between Hungary and Yugoslavia proceeded well for a while and Walko told Chamberlain in September 1926 that an arbitration agreement might be signed by the following month as a first step towards something in the nature of a Locarno settlement.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-0022009412461814">42</xref></sup></p>
<p>This was not to be, however, as Mussolini made sure that Hungary would not come to terms with Belgrade at the same time as Italian relations with Yugoslavia reached a breaking point in connection with the Albanian crisis. The Duce had attempted to turn the Locarno formula to his own benefit and organize a grandiose Danubian–Balkan pact in which Italy would be the sole arbiter and from which France would be absolutely excluded.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-0022009412461814">43</xref></sup> His plan had failed as he was unable to pressure the Yugoslavs into complete abandonment of France and he now embarked on courting revisionist states, the neighbours of Yugoslavia, in order to encircle that country and bring her to heel. Hungary had a crucial role to play in the encirclement of Yugoslavia and Mussolini went out of his way to gain her as an ally. He succeeded in signing a pact of friendship with Hungary during Bethlen’s official visit to Rome on 5 April 1927 which was accompanied by a secret agreement on the illicit arming of the Hungarian army; the details of this arms smuggling into Hungary, as well as the training of Hungarian pilots in Italy and the purchase of 300 aircraft in contravention of the Trianon Peace Treaty, were worked out during the visit to Rome of Bethlen’s personal emissaries in July.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-0022009412461814">44</xref></sup></p>
<p>The British had no idea what actually transpired at Rome nor did they suspect any sinister development. Not even the Little Entente officials suspected the conclusion of any kind of military understanding and their diplomats calmly commented on Bethlen’s visit during their interviews at Whitehall. But it became apparent that arbitration treaties between Hungary and Yugoslavia or – still less likely – the other Little Entente states were not to be expected. After the Little Entente conference at Jáchimov in May 1927 the Yugoslav Foreign Minister, Vojislav Marinković, informed Kennard that the negotiations for an arbitration treaty with Hungary would not be continued.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-0022009412461814">45</xref></sup></p>
<p>The reaction of the Foreign Office was a manifestation of all its essential illusions and misconceptions in regard to Hungarian foreign policy. Barclay asseverated from Budapest, his views being unreservedly accepted in London, that although the outstanding feature of Hungary’s foreign relations throughout 1927 had been a continued rapprochement with Italy, the overtures had been invariably coming from Rome. This situation could not have failed adversely to affect relations with the Little Entente, particularly with Yugoslavia, but the Minister was sure that Hungary had no desire to be a mere satellite of Italy and was not likely to side with her in the case of Italo-Yugoslav hostilities. Predictably, Count Bethlen’s remaining in office was deemed the surest guarantee of the Magyars not adopting any adventurous course, in addition to a common sense assumption that given Hungary’s geostrategic position ‘she may be absolved of the folly of entertaining dreams of aggressive action’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46-0022009412461814">46</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the circumstances, the drift of events was bound to cause a deterioration in the Central European situation. On 1 January 1928 the Austrian customs officials at the Italian frontier station of St. Gotthard discovered five truck loads of machine-gun parts falsely declared and destined for Hungary. The Little Entente countries brought the incident to the attention of the League of Nations, accusing Hungary of secretly arming in defiance of the Trianon Treaty. The inconclusive decision as to the responsibility of the Hungarian government reached by the committee of enquiry appointed by the Council of the League left the Little Entente with a feeling of considerable disappointment. The British attitude towards the incident had a lot to do with this outcome. The Foreign Office decided – and succeeded in convincing the French on this point – that the best means of disposing of the Hungarian arms traffic was one that would keep the matter ‘out of court, or rather out of [the] League’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47-0022009412461814">47</xref></sup> Nothing definite could follow from the thorough examination of such an affair, the Foreign Office believed, and it was for the best to smooth the matter away. When a year later another incident involving arms smuggling into Hungary occurred, Edward Crowe stated that Hungarian breaches of the military clauses were commonplace while Howard Smith simply expressed the opinion that the Foreign Office should not ‘bother about this’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48-0022009412461814">48</xref></sup> When the irritation with Italian surreptitious dealings became particularly pronounced there was even talk of ‘getting [the Ambassador in Rome] Graham to make it quite plain to Mussolini that we are fully aware of the vast traffic in arms between Italy and Hungary’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49-0022009412461814">49</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the midst of the St. Gotthard affair Beneš asked for Britain’s full moral support in order to disillusion the Hungarians as to the prospects of frontier revision and thus pave the way for a Locarno-modelled agreement.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50-0022009412461814">50</xref></sup> Having heard Beneš’s views, the Foreign Office once more studied the possibility of the application of the Locarno pattern to the states of Central and South Eastern Europe. Although it was acknowledged that the growing rivalry between France and Italy in the region presented a chief obstacle, and that there were other hindrances pertaining to relations between the states concerned themselves, Howard Smith maintained that a mutual guarantee pact could still be obtained.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51-0022009412461814">51</xref></sup> He reiterated his conviction that it was for the Little Entente to offer concessions to Budapest in order to induce her to come to terms. The analysis showed that the Foreign Office stuck to its old formulae without any regard for the substantial deterioration which had taken place during the preceding few years. Beneš developed his views in a further conversation with the League’s Secretary-General, Sir Eric Drummond, but the opinion remained in the Central Department that his proposals did not go far enough to be crowned with success.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52-0022009412461814">52</xref></sup> When in a speech to his electors in March 1928 Count Bethlen spelled out that a Central European Locarno did not appeal to Hungary as she had no intention of renouncing her claim for frontier revision, the scheme was definitely put to rest. Although Bethlen’s outright rejection of Beneš’s advances and the public manner in which it was done was deplored in the Central Department, the overall impression was one of indifferent resignation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53-0022009412461814">53</xref></sup></p>
<p>The tensions in Central Europe surged anew when on 21 June 1928 Mussolini openly professed himself in favour of the Hungarian demands during an interview granted to the <italic>Daily Mail</italic>, the proprietor of which, Lord Rothermere, had already been championing the revisionist campaign. This new departure in Italian policy towards the Danubian region, and particularly the strenuous attempt at distinguishing between the need for Hungarian revision and the immutability of the new Italo–Austrian border at the Brenner Pass, did not impress Chamberlain too much: ‘Signor Mussolini sees the weakness of his position but is not wise enough to hold his peace.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54-0022009412461814">54</xref></sup> As for the Rothermere campaign, the Central Department officials came to realize the undesirable effects it produced both in Hungary and the Little Entente countries, but it was maintained that the latter were calming down as they understood that it had nothing to do with the official policy and that it would be a mistake to give it renewed publicity by a public disclaimer.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55-0022009412461814">55</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Little Entente countries were becoming increasingly wary of Hungarian revisionism and the overt support it was given by fascist Italy. From May 1929 onwards they started closing their ranks by the tightening of the mutual political treaties and evolving more precise and binding military conventions for the purpose of meeting Hungarian – and Bulgarian – threat. Although not apprised of the details of these arrangements, the Foreign Office was not enamoured with the continuation of the pre-war alliance agreements which were a negation of the Locarno spirit. The cementing of ties between the three states was thus viewed in London in the same unfavourable light as heretofore: ‘The continued existence of the Little Entente is in itself a perpetual provocation to Hungary and it is hardly surprising if she takes any opportunity of abusing it.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56-0022009412461814">56</xref></sup> When in the wake of one of the Little Entente conferences the Czechoslovak Minister of War made a speech during a visit to Belgrade praising the unity of the alliance and the importance of its military and economic collaboration, the Head of the Central Department, Orme Sargent, succinctly remarked, in an allusion to the new Permanent Under-Secretary Sir Robert Vansittart’s famous metaphor for the viciousness of the old militaristic mentality: ‘Old Adam at his worst.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57-0022009412461814">57</xref></sup> The Belgrade Legation soon confirmed such suspicions, reporting that the Czechoslovak War Minister had no qualms suggesting that military cooperation meant jointly elaborated plans by the respective General Staffs. The news heightened the wariness of the Central Department and a junior official, Douglas Busk, gave vent to the general feeling: ‘I suppose the Little Entente have some conceivable cause for alarm according to their lights but this sort of attitude will not get them anywhere.’; Vansittart’s disquiet led him to propose the compilation of a ‘brief annual bulletin of the old boy’s [Old Adam] progress’ in order to ‘keep his medical record, and symptoms such as these might be noted for his temperature chart.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58-0022009412461814">58</xref></sup></p>
<p>The corollary of this unsympathetic attitude towards the Little Entente was as always the distinctly lenient treatment of the Hungarian government. The difficulties of the Bethlen government in dealing with the Little Entente’s representations, incurred on account of irredentist manifestations in Hungary, were looked upon with the utmost sympathy. Count Bethlen was still believed not to be promoting irredentism but rather struggling to keep in check ‘a disease in the Hungarian people themselves’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59-0022009412461814">59</xref></sup> On the other hand, although Bethlen’s qualities remained highly valued in the Foreign Office the appraisal of the Hungarian attitude towards Central European appeasement showed marked signs of a more critical assessment. When the Hungarian leader put forward a demand for the cancellation of the Little Entente alliance treaties as a precondition for the conclusion of arbitration treaties between Hungary and her neighbours, Howard Smith underwent a complete volte-face from his earlier position and now proclaimed that it was ‘for Hungary to come forward like Germany at Locarno, and make a definite offer: but this is not in the Hungarian mentality.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60-0022009412461814">60</xref></sup></p>
<p>The attempt to come to some sort of a Balkan Locarno followed the review of British policy in the Balkans in mid-1925 which had been provoked by Kennard’s enquires from Belgrade as to the main lines of such policy. The discussion clearly demonstrated the Central Department’s frame of mind. Lampson cold shouldered any inference that Britain should have an active policy in the region, the state of which he did not on the whole find too disturbing:<disp-quote>
<p>Now that Russia &amp; Austria have been eliminated, the Balkans are far less dangerous to us than they were before 1914. Heaven forbid that we should start interfering with unwanted advice or trying to mould the course of events down there. Let us carefully observe; let us look to our representatives to keep us fully informed; let us try to increase trade etc between this country &amp; Serbia. But do not let us go further than that.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61-0022009412461814">61</xref></sup></p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Chamberlain expounded the view that the lack of immediate British interests in the region precluded a necessity to plump for ‘any particular solution of any of its many problems’. He recapitulated a dictum that the internal and external peace among the Balkan nations would in due course bring about their prosperity and economic development ‘from which we should desire the natural advantage of a great trading nation which is the only thing we desire <italic>for ourselves</italic>.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62-0022009412461814">62</xref></sup></p>
<p>Kennard, who took a much graver view of the Balkan situation as seen from Belgrade, did not subscribe to the Foreign Office’s ‘present policy… to have no policy’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63-0022009412461814">63</xref></sup> He was convinced that any thought of bringing Italy and France together was doomed to failure given their conflicting policies and was in favour of a more far-reaching and bolder approach centred on his current post:<disp-quote>
<p>In my own humble opinion we should aim at the encouragement of a Balkan federation, however remote. It is our best chance of resisting the ultimate pressure from Germany and Russia which may otherwise be prolonged indefinitely. Romania is, of course rotten; Greece is wobbly and Bulgaria will require time to get on her feet again. The Yugs are certainly the soundest and while they may be suffering from swollenheadedness and ultranationalism, they have all the elements of a strong nation and if they can only settle their internal differences, should play the major role in the Balkans in the future.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64-0022009412461814">64</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Kennard’s proposal for the encouragement of a Balkan federation did not meet with approval in Whitehall,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65-0022009412461814">65</xref></sup> while his suggestion in regard to the leading part that should be bestowed on Yugoslavia found some favourable reception subject to reservation that ‘we could be certain that the SCS Kingdom would never effect a junction with Slav Russia &amp; form a channel for the divertion [<italic>sic</italic>] of Russian ambitions in Constantinople to one of the more important Greek ports’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66-0022009412461814">66</xref></sup> After careful consideration it was decided ‘that the best line for HMG to follow in the Balkans was to strengthen the League’s influence (through Serbia), but to curb the more truculent moods of Belgrade.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67-0022009412461814">67</xref></sup></p>
<p>To properly understand British policy towards the Balkans it is necessary to survey certain perceptions and basic assumptions concerning the chief security challenges in the region. Yugoslavia’s perennial conflict with Italy provided the greatest cause for concern in the maintenance of peace in the region. The dispute over the town of Fiume (Rijeka) was settled by an agreement concluded in January 1924 and accompanied by the Pact of Rome that was supposed to usher in an era of good neighbourly relations. That was not to be the case. Albania provided a permanent stumbling block in these relations as it remained the arena of fighting between the parties sponsored by the Adriatic rivals. In the minds of the policy-makers in Belgrade, Italian entrenchment in Albania was nothing short of the repetition of the unfortunate experience with the Austro–Hungarian mandate and the overt annexation of Bosnia and Herzegovina of 1908, an analogy they never failed to draw to the attention of the representatives of ‘big’ allies ever since the Paris Peace Conference.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68-0022009412461814">68</xref></sup> They did not doubt for a moment that Italy intended to use that country as a springboard for further penetration in the Balkans. From the strategic point of view the Yugoslavs were frightened of the peril of the Italians ‘joining hands’ from Albania with the Bulgarians across the Vardar valley in Serb Macedonia, thus cutting off the vital Belgrade–Salonica railway in much the same fashion as the Bulgarian army had actually done in 1915.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69-0022009412461814">69</xref></sup> The stance on the Albanian question was formed accordingly. The Yugoslav delegation at the Paris Conference plumped for the independence of Albania in her 1913 frontiers as sketched by the London Conference after the First Balkan War under the slogan ‘the Balkans for the Balkan peoples’.</p>
<p>The British, however, did not recognize as defensive the stance taken by Belgrade and suspected that Yugoslavia was often more guilty than the Italians of stirring up trouble in the neighbouring state. The Central Department firmly believed that Yugoslavia, at least up to 1925, professed a desire for an independent Albania with a view to the elimination of Italian preponderance in that country and the establishment of her own dominance.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70-0022009412461814">70</xref></sup> In May 1926 it was under the illusion that ‘it is not impossible that Italy and Serbia might come to some agreement as to spheres of influence in the country, the Serbs to have Scutari and the Italians Valona.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71-0022009412461814">71</xref></sup> An eventual Italian possession of the Adriatic port of Valona was not thought vitally to affect British naval and military interests in Eastern Mediterranean and was thus viewed indifferently.</p>
<p>Belgrade was also embroiled in a bitter dispute with Bulgaria over the Yugoslav province of Macedonia whose Slav inhabitants were claimed by both sides as their co-nationals. Having made a tour of southern districts, the British military attaché at Belgrade, Lieutenant-Colonel James Blair, concluded that the rank and file of the population was neither pro-Serb nor pro-Bulgar but was desirous of peace and ‘would be pro-any Government that governed them well.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72-0022009412461814">72</xref></sup> King Alexander of Yugoslavia privately admitted the truth of such a view.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73-0022009412461814">73</xref></sup> In the final instance the British attitude was determined by practical considerations. Both the Ministers at Belgrade and Sofia, and their superiors in Whitehall, concurred that the assimilation of the Macedonian population within Yugoslavia afforded ‘the best hope of permanent peace in the Balkans’ as it was believed that the terrorist Internal Macedonian Revolutionary Organisation’s (IMRO) demand for autonomy was only envisaged as the first step towards a union with Bulgaria which could thus bring about ‘an almost certain cause of future conflict.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74-0022009412461814">74</xref></sup> Belgrade was repeatedly advised to improve the administration in the southern province as the best means of facilitating a fast assimilation of the local population.</p>
<p>The Bulgarian government was suspected of using the trouble instigated by IMRO to internationalize the Macedonian imbroglio as they nurtured a hope that their aspirations in regard to Macedonia might be realized at some more favourable juncture in the future.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75-0022009412461814">75</xref></sup> On the basis of its intelligence the Foreign Office deemed that the action undertaken by Sofia in order to discourage the <italic>comitadji</italic> raids was calculated mainly for the sake of appearance.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76-0022009412461814">76</xref></sup> On the other hand, the Bulgarian government was thought to be powerless against a well-organized Macedonian movement which had infiltrated the whole administrative apparatus of the state. In addition, it was believed that IMRO’s activity was welcome to the authorities as it provided them with a strong case to argue that the military weakness imposed on Bulgaria by the Neuilly Treaty was the sole reason for their inability to maintain order on their own soil.</p>
<p>Given the bitter feeling existing between Yugoslavia and Bulgaria it was all the more surprising that some of the Central Department officials believed that the only thing that could bring the two countries together was their common ‘desire to push Greece out of her new Aegean coastline’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77-0022009412461814">77</xref></sup> Others were more sceptical. Sir Eyre Crowe, the Permanent Under-Secretary of State, dismissed the idea out of hand: ‘There is no such policy in Serbia’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78-0022009412461814">78</xref></sup> British perceptions of the likelihood of Yugoslav descent down the Vardar valley on the Greek port of Salonica were heavily influenced by a deep mistrust and antipathy towards the veteran Prime Minister, Nikola Pašić and his People’s Radical Party. The First Secretary of the Central Department, Harold Nicolson, was a mouthpiece of such views: ‘Mr Pašić is a danger to Europe. Old, obstinate, venerable and ingratiating he combines all the futilities of a Balkan politician with the appearance and prestige of an elder statesman. The only hope for Jugo Slavia [sic] is that he should disappear.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79-0022009412461814">79</xref></sup> Even when other dire preoccupations of domestic and external policy seemed to have rendered the design on Salonica highly unlikely, the doubts were still alive, for ‘with M. Pasic one never knows!’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80-0022009412461814">80</xref></sup> This prejudice appears to have distorted the outlook on the true disposition of Yugoslav political factors in respect to ‘Vardar policy’. There is no compelling evidence of Pašić’s expansionist drive southwards and the British Minister in Belgrade, Sir Alban Young, was reluctant to take it seriously.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81-0022009412461814">81</xref></sup> On the contrary, Vojislav Marinković, one of the leading figures of the Radicals’ rival Democratic Party and a future Foreign Minister (1927–32), who was liked and respected by the British diplomats as a more enlightened and progressive statesman, was the one who contemplated a more assertive policy towards Greece. In his notes on the general tasks of Yugoslav foreign policy he included a need to ‘reduce Greece to her real ethnographic frontiers’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82-0022009412461814">82</xref></sup> Young, on his part, hinted at ‘Mussolini’s encouragement to the Yugoslavs to extend to the Aegean’ as a possible source of all rumours.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83-0022009412461814">83</xref></sup> If Yugoslavia channelled her alleged expansion towards the Aegean the Italians would gain an unchallenged mastery of the Adriatic.</p>
<p>It is most exemplary of the endless and almost fantastic echoes of Balkan intrigue reverberating in London that in mid-1924 it was suspected, and later denied, that Yugoslavia and Bulgaria, with the tacit support of Rome, had reached an agreement to gain access to the Aegean by joint action against Greece and seizure of the ports of Salonica, Dedeagatch and Kavalla respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84-0022009412461814">84</xref></sup> When on 17 November 1924 Belgrade denounced the Greco–Serbian alliance treaty of 1913, presumably to bring pressure to bear on Greece so as to make her more accommodating in providing railway facilities for the transport of goods from Yugoslav Macedonia to Salonica and force her to drop the minority convention concluded that September between her and Bulgaria,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85-0022009412461814">85</xref></sup> new doubts arose among the Foreign Office officialdom. ‘Is this another manifestation of the anti Greek policy of Italy acting through a secret pact with Serbia?’, wondered John McEwen, the Third Secretary of Central Department.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86-0022009412461814">86</xref></sup> Young’s report on the surreptitious dealings of the Italian Minister at Belgrade, General Bodrero, was not conducive to allaying the suspicions.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87-0022009412461814">87</xref></sup> It was even suspected in the Foreign Office that General Bodrero was so influential with King Alexander after the conclusion of the Pact of Rome as to obtain the retention of Pašić’s radicals in office.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88-0022009412461814">88</xref></sup></p>
<p>After Mussolini had repudiated the charge of encouraging Serbian adventurism,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89-0022009412461814">89</xref></sup> the Italian factor was quickly discounted and the Central Department went back to the issue of whether Yugoslavia, in a likely combination with Sofia, had cast her eye on the Aegean coast. As had been the case earlier, the Foreign Office diplomats could not agree in their assessment of the situation. While Eyre Crowe found the alleged designs rather speculative, Nicolson was convinced that what the Serbs wanted was ‘not the smooth running of the transit agreement through Salonica, – but Salonica itself’, and, moreover, he was sure that ‘one day they will get it.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90-0022009412461814">90</xref></sup> Failing to make up his mind about what was really going on, the Chief of the Central Department, Miles Lampson, found it easiest to fall back on a not too ingenious gibe: ‘The average English mind is not so constituted as to be able to fathom the depths of Balkan intrigue.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91-0022009412461814">91</xref></sup></p>
<p>It was on such a basis of misperceptions and miscalculations relating to Balkan politics that Chamberlain embarked on a mediatory role in promoting a Locarno-modelled settlement. Besides strictly local conditions the Foreign Secretary’s doctrine required enlisting the support of Rome, all the more so as Italian policy in the Balkans was hitherto deemed ‘obscure and vacillating.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92-0022009412461814">92</xref></sup> On 10 June 1925, assuming that he could muster up loyal Italian cooperation in the Balkans, Chamberlain, together with Briand, addressed a personal appeal to the Duce for his continued support and collaboration in the preservation of peace there.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93-0022009412461814">93</xref></sup> The idea originated with Nicolson and it disclosed all the fundamental fallacies of the British estimation of the situation. It was founded on two premises: firstly that ‘the prime offender is the S[erbo].C[roat].S[slovene]. State egged on by Italy’ and secondly that based on the first assumption the only way of pacifying the region was to ‘rope in Italy’ into joint action with France and Britain which should be attained by ‘playing up directly to Mussolini’s vanity.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94-0022009412461814">94</xref></sup> The scheme was at the same time riddled with incompatible suspicions about Italian conduct that had been entertained at the Foreign Office for a long time. When the message of the British and French Foreign Ministers to Rome failed to produce any impact this was not a cause for concern in Whitehall. Quite the contrary, Lampson was much relieved that ‘Mussolini appears to have put our recent letter to him in a pigeon-hole!’ as he believed that the Italians would never loyally cooperate over the Salonica issue on account of their encouragement of Yugoslavian aspirations in the port’s direction.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95-0022009412461814">95</xref></sup> In fact, Chamberlain was told that the telegram had reached Mussolini shortly before the two of them met on the occasion of the initialling of the Locarno treaty in mid-October 1925. The Secretary of State repeated his suggestion to the Duce but received ‘a rather non-committal answer.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96-0022009412461814">96</xref></sup> Mussolini’s reticence did not augur well for the future and was moreover found to have given ‘colour to the recent secret reports we have had as to the doings of Italy in the Balkans.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97-0022009412461814">97</xref></sup> Despite unfavourable signs regarding Italian policy, the British remained unshaken in their conviction that the only way of proceeding with a Balkan Locarno was in cooperation with Rome. It seems that the Foreign Office maintained that Mussolini had not adopted any definite, and still less a definitely destructive, course in the Balkans (or Central Europe) and therefore steadfastly persevered in cultivating his good will.</p>
<p>This was amply demonstrated in dealing with ever louder and more frequent Yugoslav warnings pertaining to Italian intentions. When Ninčić communicated to Kennard the Yugoslav General Staff’s fear of an Italian military coup the Foreign Office discounted such utterances as unfounded. Lampson made full allowance for rampant Italian intrigue but doubted whether it would ‘materialise into definite dangers’, while John McEwen thought that the fear might have the wholesome effect of making Belgrade more tractable over the Salonica railway.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98-0022009412461814">98</xref></sup> On receipt of a report from the Rome Embassy denying military preparations in Italy Nicolson was much harsher on Ninčić, ‘a stupid &amp; unscrupulous man &amp; therefore dangerous’ and dismissed the whole story as the latter’s ‘scare-crow’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99-0022009412461814">99</xref></sup></p>
<p>The rift between Yugoslavia and Italy became apparent in Albanian matters after the swift succession of two revolutions in that country. The first one saw pro-Italian bishop Fan-Noli overthrowing the President Ahmed Bey Zogu in June 1924. With covert Yugoslav military support Ahmed Zogu then re-established himself at Tirana in December the same year. What at first appeared to have been a clear victory for Yugoslav foreign policy soon proved to be a false hope. Rome provided desperately needed funds for Ahmed Zogu’s administration and gradually attained an undisputed hold on Albanian economic life which rendered the independence of the country a mere chimera.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100-0022009412461814">100</xref></sup> It was not long before the Yugoslav military envoy at Tirana, Lieutenant-Colonel Tanasije Dinić, reported to the Great General Staff that Ahmed Zogu had definitely transferred his and his country’s allegiance to Italy in return for generous financial support.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101-0022009412461814">101</xref></sup> Indeed, Yugoslavian suspicions of the thrust of Mussolini’s policy were not amiss as Italy and Albania concluded a secret military accord in August 1925 by which the former was pledged to support the territorial ambitions of the latter at the expense of Yugoslavia.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn102-0022009412461814">102</xref></sup> This was followed by the conclusion of the Italo–Albanian treaty of 27 November 1926 (the first Pact of Tirana) which was a prelude to further trouble in South-Eastern Europe. From Belgrade’s point of view the treaty was deliberately couched in vague terms as to what might constitute a disturbance against the political, juridical and territorial status quo in Albania in order to establish a thinly veiled protectorate which enabled the Italians to land troops on any flimsy pretext.</p>
<p>Yugoslavia’s attitude towards Italy was far from being exaggerated and unreasonable. The Italian General Staff had been preparing plans for attack on Yugoslavia since May 1925 and on 2 October 1926 the Duce ordered his Chief of General Staff to have 20 divisions ready to teach Yugoslavia a lesson. An anti-Yugoslav press campaign and overt statements by Fascist jingoists declaring their pretensions on the Dalmatian coast left no doubt in Belgrade about the true nature of Italian intentions. On 12 March 1925 King Alexander, Ninčić and the military authorities requested from the Czechoslovak Minister an urgent delivery of 100,000 rifles, 100,000,000 rounds of ammunition and 100,000 grenades for the purpose of a defensive war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn103-0022009412461814">103</xref></sup> Beneš fully shared Belgrade’s suspicions and on 26 November promised the Yugoslav military attaché covert and active military help.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn104-0022009412461814">104</xref></sup> A month later the two men had another conversation and the Yugoslav relayed to Beneš a personal plea from his sovereign enumerating the direst necessities of the Yugoslav Army, namely aircraft and pilots who should be dispatched as volunteers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn105-0022009412461814">105</xref></sup> The Czechoslovak Foreign Minister gave positive assurances in respect of all necessary military material. Having discussed the possibility of an Italo–Yugoslav conflict in his recent visit to Paris and London, he also stated that France was unreservedly behind Belgrade, while Chamberlain was convinced that Italy would not dare to attack Yugoslavia as she was currently contemplating aggression against Turkey.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn106-0022009412461814">106</xref></sup></p>
<p>Since Yugoslav professions concerning the Italian menace were disbelieved, Oliver Harvey, fresh from the Rome Embassy, suspected that Ninčić was trying to delay or avoid any negotiations for a Balkan pact.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn107-0022009412461814">107</xref></sup> As the Foreign Minister grew more nervous about Italian aggressive intentions and vented his concerns to Kennard, the latter was more inclined to scoff at his ‘somewhat puerile apprehensions’ and administer a warning that the contempt often felt in Yugoslavia for Italian military strength might be disastrous for the country.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn108-0022009412461814">108</xref></sup> Still, in time Kennard was increasingly struck with the genuineness of Yugoslav perturbation as regards Rome’s designs but his renewed reports to that effect did not change the opinion held in the Foreign Office that it was ‘so much moon-shine – a mere rehash of the usual Balkan talk to which we are accustomed’, a reference to Ninčić’s repeated outpourings on the subject.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn109-0022009412461814">109</xref></sup> The Ambassador at Rome vehemently confirmed the views of his superiors as to the perfectly pacific policy of the Italian Duce.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn110-0022009412461814">110</xref></sup> The Central Department officials argued that the Balkans could not provide the room needed for Italian colonization and thus could not be a suitable victim of Mussolini’s aggression.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn111-0022009412461814">111</xref></sup></p>
<p>Kennard was eager to get the ball rolling and egged on Ninčić towards taking the initiative in the matter of a Balkan Locarno. As a beginning he recommended a rapprochement with Bulgaria to which, he optimistically professed, the Macedonian problem would not be an insuperable obstacle.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn112-0022009412461814">112</xref></sup> The Minister’s zeal and general course of action were approved by the Central Department. Yugoslavia and her Foreign Minister, Lampson confirmed, were marked out for the leading part in the Balkans.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn113-0022009412461814">113</xref></sup> Belgrade should be encouraged to conclude arbitration treaties of the type signed between Germany and Poland and Germany and Czechoslovakia at Locarno as the sort of treaties concluded between Germany and France and Germany and Belgium were applicable to neither Central Europe nor to the Balkans since there was no question of anyone guaranteeing agreement in the way Britain and Italy had done in Western Europe. The Yugoslavs should be tempted to proceed in the desired direction by the prospect of soaring international standing and prestige. In the meanwhile Kennard was instructed to preach the desirability of conciliatory methods in dealing with individual points of friction such as the Ghevgheli–Salonica railway as the best way of preparing the ground for a comprehensive settlement. Lampson thought that the suggestion should be put to Belgrade to approach Bulgaria and Greece simultaneously in order to avoid the impression in both countries that a rapprochement with one of them was aimed against the other. Lampson’s recommendation was that whereas Central European pacification should be encouraged as unobtrusively as possible Yugoslavia should adopt a more forward policy in the Balkans subject to avoiding the impression ‘(a) that <italic>we</italic> are thrusting the thing down the throats of anyone, or (b) that Serbia is trying to do so.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn114-0022009412461814">114</xref></sup></p>
<p>Before the British got involved in promoting a Balkan Locarno the idea had already been mooted by Greece. On 3 November 1925 the Secretary-General of the League of Nations, Sir Eric Drummond, was handed a note on behalf of the Greek government which set forth a suggestion that the League should take the initiative in promoting a security pact in the Balkans. The rationale behind this proposal was the Greek wish to overcome the outstanding questions with their neighbours and step out of their political isolation by dint of a general security arrangement. However, there was no prospect that the League would undertake such a task and in addition the initiative was resented in Yugoslavia.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn115-0022009412461814">115</xref></sup> Nevertheless, at the beginning of 1926 the British closely watched what they hoped to be a development in the right direction. The Yugoslav government embarked on fresh negotiations with Greece and Bulgaria with a view to concluding a Balkan Locarno. The Yugoslav approach was to resolve all the outstanding questions with Athens as a prerequisite for the successful conclusion of an arbitration treaty.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn116-0022009412461814">116</xref></sup> On 17 August 1926 the agreement between Greece and Yugoslavia was finally reached, comprising of a political treaty of understanding and friendship and a set of conventions covering railway and transit questions, including the administration of the Ghevgheli–Salonica Railway, the Yugoslav free zone in Salonica and a minority convention. However, when a revolution broke out in Greece just a few days after the signature of these conventions, the dictatorship of General Pangalos was deposed and the new Greek government never ratified the agreement.</p>
<p>Nor was the position as regards Bulgaro-Yugoslav relations any better. The arbitration treaty offered by Belgrade at the end of April 1926 was refused by the Bulgarian government as it contained articles aimed at the suppression of IMRO which were found impossible to undertake in Sofia and which raised fears that they would give a legal ground for interference in Bulgarian internal affairs. The Foreign Office could not comprehend the Yugoslav attitude towards Bulgaria – the insistence on the suppression of the IMRO, besides being difficult to fulfil, was bound, in its view, to prevent any chance of coming to terms with the government at Sofia.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn117-0022009412461814">117</xref></sup> The long-standing British view was that ‘given time a fairly representative Bulg[arian]. Govt will be able to deal with them without outside interference – just as, in the course of time, the SCS Govt will be able to deal with the [I]MRO’s activities in S[outh]. Serbia.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn118-0022009412461814">118</xref></sup> Opinion was unanimous in the Central Department that it was once more Ninčić’s profound ignorance, whether real or contrived, that was ‘becoming increasingly dangerous as a factor in European relations.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn119-0022009412461814">119</xref></sup></p>
<p>The firm belief that salvation from the Macedonian imbroglio was to ‘come from within Bulgaria’ accounted for British determination to see a loan for the settlement of the refugees from Greek Macedonia in Bulgaria through the medium of the League.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn120-0022009412461814">120</xref></sup> A settled state of the peasantry would cut the ground from under IMRO’s feet and thus contribute to political stabilization in Bulgaria and ultimately to Balkan peace. The loan produced a markedly unfavourable impression in Yugoslavia and went to prove, according to a report from Belgrade, the feeling of suspicion and mistrust which rendered any Balkan Locarno impossible. George Ogilvie-Forbes of the Belgrade Legation attributed such a state of affairs to the general backwardness of the country, the state of civilization of which he compared to ‘England in the days of Sir Robert Walpole’; he prophesied that it would take a generation for it to find its Pitt who would equip her for the great role she was destined to fulfil in South-Eastern Europe.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn121-0022009412461814">121</xref></sup> The Foreign Office brushed aside Yugoslav, Romanian and Greek opposition and lent their support to the refugee loan which was pushed through mainly by the determined efforts of the Treasury and the Bank of England.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn122-0022009412461814">122</xref></sup></p>
<p>The end of September 1927 was marked by an intensified terrorist campaign on the part of IMRO which culminated in the assassination of General Kovačević, the commander of the brigade located at the Yugoslav town of Štip, on 6 October. IMRO was supplied with arms and money by the Italians.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn123-0022009412461814">123</xref></sup> The Central Department acquired intelligence information, including intercepted letters, confirming what the Yugoslavs took for granted - that Macedonian <italic>comitadjis</italic> were actively supported by Italy and operating from Albanian territory – but such information was treated as not definite and no great importance was attached to it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn124-0022009412461814">124</xref></sup></p>
<p>The new Yugoslav Foreign Minister, Vojislav Marinković, adopted an entirely different attitude towards the Bulgarian government than his predecessor Ninčić and was determined to maintain as friendly relations with Sofia as possible. His approach accorded with British assessments that the outrages of IMRO were actually desperate measures to revive its waning strength and put an end to a rapprochement between Yugoslavia and Bulgaria. The Foreign Office was therefore receptive to Marinković’s plea to bring pressure to bear on the Bulgarian authorities and the Foreign Minister Bouroff was admonished that his government had to go out of its way to prevent further incidents, the continuation of which would destroy all chance of Bulgaria obtaining another much-needed reconstruction loan.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn125-0022009412461814">125</xref></sup> Although the crisis was smoothed away, the circumstances were far from conducive to any détente between Yugoslavia and her eastern neighbour.</p>
<p>Therefore, by the end of 1927 it became obvious that nothing would materialize out of attempts to reach a Balkan Locarno and that the political situation in the region was actually worse than before. As far as the Foreign Office was concerned, the responsibility for this dismal failure was mostly laid at the door of the Yugoslav Foreign Ministry. In his annual reports Kennard painted a bleak picture of Ninčić’s unstable and lamentable policy which made overtures to Bulgaria with a view to intimidating Greece and then approached Greece in order to frighten Bulgaria. The only result was the isolation of his own country.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn126-0022009412461814">126</xref></sup> Yugoslavia was, in the British view, the one country with a capacity to break the Balkan deadlock and Yugoslav vacillations were seen as dangerous turns of policy.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn127-0022009412461814">127</xref></sup></p>
<p>This estimation corresponded only too well with the inveterate and highly unfavourable perception of Yugoslav foreign policy which had taken hold in the Foreign Office for quite some time:<disp-quote>
<p>The Yugoslavs have uneasy consciences. They aspire to be the big Balkan State &amp; in fact believed they were all-powerful. They rejected the Greek alliance &amp; have been so stiff in their terms of renewal that Greece, weak tho’ she is, turned &amp; rejected them. Nor has Yugoslavia made friends with Bulgaria. She never trusted the Italians or even attempted to turn over a new leaf after the Pact of Rome. She has banked on belief in her own strength &amp; on support from France. She is now reaping the harvest of her policy of arrogance &amp; double-dealing, &amp; is isolated.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn128-0022009412461814">128</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>Although there was certainly a good deal to be said for the deficiencies of Belgrade’s foreign policy, such an appreciation was much exaggerated and completely left out of consideration a factor of paramount importance in the Balkans, namely the insidious impact of Mussolini’s foreign policy. It was but another confirmation of Chamberlain’s firm conviction that Yugoslavia was the sole offender in the Balkans and that France was further aggravating a bad situation by stepping forward as her protector:<disp-quote>
<p>I may be quite wrong but as I see things it is Yugo Slavia which is at present the disturbing factor. I wish that France would speak more resolutely at Belgrade. Yugo Slavia is the most powerful of the Balkan States; therefore France courts her &amp; thinks of yet another alliance, but Yugo Slavia is restless, bullying and unreasonable in her demands on Greece &amp; in her attitude (in the past, at any rate) to Bulgaria. And because she is all this herself, she is nervous &amp; suspicious about others, &amp; her policy tends to provoke in other countries reactions which give some ground for her fears.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn129-0022009412461814">129</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>The blame for the deadlock in relation to Italy was equally distributed between Belgrade and Paris. The latter was suspected of affecting a fear of the Italians while actually being actuated by jealousy alone.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn130-0022009412461814">130</xref></sup> Having learned of the French standpoint Lampson was struck by what he saw as an extraordinarily narrow view that regarded Italy as bent on trouble – one which he declined to accept and which he thought was a consequence of misunderstanding and a lack of proper communication.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn131-0022009412461814">131</xref></sup> Even the notoriously Francophile Chamberlain simply confessed that he could not ‘understand why France needs to meddle in this affair.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn132-0022009412461814">132</xref></sup></p>
<p>In this connection, the Foreign Secretary’s attitude towards French policy might perhaps offer an interesting insight and contribution to the much debated question of his alleged ‘pro-French’ bias. A portrait of the decidedly pro-French Chamberlain as established in a number of works has been challenged by Richard Grayson arguing that Sir Austen treated Germany and France in an even-handed manner; Grayson’s interpretation has, in turn, time and again been severely criticized by Gaynor Johnson who refutes the claim that Chamberlain was as sympathetic to Germany’s security concerns as to those of France, and thus reaffirms the previous view.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn133-0022009412461814">133</xref></sup> In this respect, the case of British outlook on the Franco–Italian rivalry over Yugoslavia, although limited in scope, presents a more nuanced picture which is not entirely in line with either Grayson or Johnson. In this case Chamberlain appears to be critical of French approach to the problem at hand albeit not so vociferously as his subordinates. But there is an important differentiation of view with regard to French policy-making to be observed. The Foreign Office was convinced that the misdeed of concluding the treaty of friendship with Yugoslavia on 11 November 1927 was the work of the die-hard forces in the Quai d’Orsay, headed by the Secretary-General and ‘the villain of the peace’, Philippe Berthelot, against the better judgment of Chamberlain’s dear friend, the pacific and sensible Briand.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn134-0022009412461814">134</xref></sup> In the words of the Permanent Under-Secretary Tyrell, the wretched ways of past diplomacy prevailed over Locarno ideas: ‘This is a sad legacy left by M. [Raymond] Poincaré to M. Briand. We must stand by with buckets of cold water to pour over all parties that will need it. Let us keep cool.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn135-0022009412461814">135</xref></sup> Therefore, Chamberlain’s Foreign Office made a sharp difference between Briand and the officialdom at the Quai d’Orsay and it was the latter that was the object of criticism. This was entirely based on the perception of their respective policies, whether real or imagined, and showed no sign of any effective influence that Chamberlain’s Francophile outlook might have had. On the other hand, it is also possible to argue that the more charitable appreciation of Briand could have been the result of Chamberlain’s highly favourable view of the Frenchman, or more widely a partial concession to his pro-French bias. Be that as it may, it seems that further examination of the differentiation between Briand and the officials at his ministry, as viewed from Whitehall, might be a fruitful field for historians in their attempts to shed new light on this question.</p>
<p>As for Yugoslavia, when Marinković contended that in the absence of the friendship of some other Great Power such as Britain, she must lean on France to fend off a hostile Italy, Howard Smith revealed a fundamentally different perception of the perplexed relations within the Franco–Italo–Yugoslav triangle and an entirely different British conception of the proper policy for Belgrade to pursue:<disp-quote>
<p>I think that M. Marinkovitch argues the wrong way round. One of the reasons, though perhaps not the main one, of Italian suspicion of Serbia is her close connection with France, Italy feeling that by this connection France maintains a predominant influence in the Balkans to which Italy aspires. In fact it is just jealousy of France. If Serbia would give up her dependence on France, then I fancy Italy would at once become more friendly to her especially if she showed Italy that she was quite ready to stand alone and was not afraid of her. And we know that Italy does not want war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn136-0022009412461814">136</xref></sup></p></disp-quote>In fact, Italy’s behaviour was interpreted as a fearful reaction to what that country perceived to be the hindering of her legitimate aspirations by France through the agency of Belgrade.</p>
<p>Quite like in Central Europe, the impact of Italian meddling was soon to become evident in the Balkans. The Central Department received secret information about Bulgaria’s armament constituting an open breach of the military clauses of the Neuilly Treaty which was undertaken with the connivance of the Italian military authorities, if not the government itself.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn137-0022009412461814">137</xref></sup> The impossibility of taking effective measures to enforce the treaty obligations coupled with the ineffective machinery of the League to penalize the guilty party led the officials to agree that ‘the unheroic course of doing nothing is the right one’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn138-0022009412461814">138</xref></sup></p>
<p>However, in the Bulgarian case the most dangerous situation threatening the preservation of peace always arose out of the intermittent IMRO outrages. A new stimulus for the continued terrorist campaign also came from the Italian side. Having learned from the new Italian Foreign Minister, Dino Grandi, that the Fascist government intended to keep on good terms with IMRO as they found the latter a useful tool in their dealings with Belgrade,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn139-0022009412461814">139</xref></sup> the Foreign Office became aware of ‘Italy’s disreputable game of intriguing with the disruptive elements in the Balkans in order to weaken Yugoslavia’ and insisted on the strenuous observation of the peace treaties so as not to be appearing to co-operate with Rome in her policy.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn140-0022009412461814">140</xref></sup> Although Sargent did not want to force matters to an issue, he hoped that cooperation with France in making official representations to the government in Sofia with a demand for resolute action against IMRO would ‘have a salutary effect on Mussolini in making him realise that we are not prepared to acquiesce in and still less support him in the dangerous game of encircling Yugoslavia, which he seems to be inclined to play at in the Balkans at the present time.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn141-0022009412461814">141</xref></sup></p>
<p>To reinforce the point Chamberlain persisted in conveying the warning to Sofia not to lend herself to supporting Italy to the detriment of relations with a neighbouring country, a piece of advice the soundness of which he thought the Bulgarians began to realize.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn142-0022009412461814">142</xref></sup> Sargent even came to believe that it was malevolent Italian influence that was at the bottom of the troubled relations between Sofia and Belgrade. His assessment was fully shared by the new Permanent Under-Secretary, Sir Robert Vansittart: ‘Our Balkan policy is the exact opposite of Italy’s. We must always be trying to draw together what she is pulling apart. The antithesis is unfortunate, but it is not our fault, and we must go our way resolutely.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn143-0022009412461814">143</xref></sup> When in March 1930 fresh terrorist outrages were committed on Yugoslav territory Vansittart thought it necessary to ‘do anything to force the Italians away from their murderous pets, the [I]MRO’ and tried without success to rope Mussolini into making a joint representation to the Bulgarian government together with the British and French.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn144-0022009412461814">144</xref></sup></p>
<p>Despite periodical outbursts of violence, the Foreign Office was of the opinion, based on information from its Legation at Sofia and independent secret sources, that IMRO, which had lost any constructive purpose of existence and degenerated into a criminal gang, would die a natural death with the passage of time. Meanwhile the only available policy was to urge moderation all round: to press the government of Andrey Lyapchev into taking more determined measures in order to rein in IMRO and to restrain Belgrade from contemplating any drastic action on its part.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn145-0022009412461814">145</xref></sup> Being exposed to constant terrorist outrages the Yugoslavs were hardly put to the test in continuing their policy of restraint towards the Lyapchev government, especially so as they, unlike the British, found both the Bulgarian Prime Minister and King Boris duplicitous and unwilling to oppose IMRO, as well as ill-disposed to sincere cooperation with Belgrade.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn146-0022009412461814">146</xref></sup> The time when an arbitration treaty with Bulgaria seemed feasible had been long gone.</p>
<p>The Locarno settlement of 1925 raised hopes in London of a similar understanding in Central Europe and the Balkans. Two preconditions stood in the way of success. First, a basis of agreement needed to be found among the smaller states of the region. Chamberlain believed that it would be counter-productive to impose a solution on unwilling parties and that salvation must come from within. The Foreign Office was optimistic as to the prospects of both a Central European and a Balkan Locarno as it was thought that Bethlen was prepared to work to that end along the Danube and that Yugoslavia could be made an axis of settlement in the Balkans. Although British assessments suffered from a general inclination to pose as a patron of Bethlen’s government and take an unduly dim view of Yugoslav foreign policy, the approach was fundamentally sound. But its successful outcome actually depended on the second precondition – concerted action on the part of the Great Powers. It was apparent that Franco–Italian rivalry presented a grave obstacle to any stabilization and a permanent settlement in the Danubian/Balkan regions. If there was to be any chance of a Locarno-type agreement the two Powers had to abstain from pursuing conflicting policies and recruiting clients and lend their support to a mutually agreed settlement.</p>
<p>With this in view, Britain’s dealing with Fascist Italy in South-Eastern Europe was of particular importance. Grayson’s analysis of Chamberlain’s policy towards Mussolini’s Italy with regard to the Balkans, and particularly Albania, is as muddled as it is brief. He has merely noted that ‘there was talk in the Foreign Office of a Balkan Locarno’ and some hope that such an agreement might be introduced in ‘central and eastern Europe, but nothing materialised.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn147-0022009412461814">147</xref></sup> Grayson is at a loss to explain the substance of Chamberlain’s policy towards Italy and concedes that he was not watchful enough in his dealings with the Duce. Given the fact that Rome was a factor in British policy towards the Middle East and North Africa, it might be suspected that Chamberlain was lenient towards Italy’s role in the Balkans and Central Europe as some form of a quid pro quo. Grayson’s study covers all these aspects of Anglo–Italian relations, but it does not find any connection between them. Indeed, there is no evidence to the contrary. Another study of Anglo–Italian relations argues that, despite ‘his covert association with Balkan revisionism’ and ‘unconditional support of Hungary’ which Chamberlain strongly discouraged, Mussolini’s ‘activities in the “Locarno-Geneva system” in the mid-1920s were relatively unexceptionable’; consequently, the Foreign Secretary’s policy is seen as perfectly sensible.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn148-0022009412461814">148</xref></sup></p>
<p>This article, however, suggests that Chamberlain completely and utterly misjudged Mussolini’s policy. In his view, shared by others in the Foreign Office, Italy was not bent on adventure and aggressive enterprises, despite her childish and tiresome bullying of Yugoslavia. His appreciation seems to have been influenced by a personal rapport with the Duce whom he met face to face five times.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn149-0022009412461814">149</xref></sup> ‘I maintain to all my faith that Italian policy is what Signor Mussolini has repeatedly assured me that it is’, Chamberlain confirmed – though he was fully aware that there were those who ‘think me blinded by my regard to him.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn150-0022009412461814">150</xref></sup> The Foreign Secretary’s views on Mussolini, his regime and foreign policy were rather typical of those held by the Foreign Office and British Conservative opinion in general.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn151-0022009412461814">151</xref></sup> British attitude towards the Horthy-Bethlen regime, as discussed above, is rather reminiscent of that adopted towards the Duce’s Italy.</p>
<p>But it would be wide of the mark entirely to put the distinctive leniency shown to Italy down to Chamberlain’s benevolence towards the Italian dictator. It was equally, if not more so, inspired by the British strategic appreciation, however misguided, that Italy was provoked by the existence of a close understanding between France and Yugoslavia. On that basis, it was for those powers to reassure Italy that her fears were groundless rather than the other way round. Howard Kennard was alone in exclaiming from Belgrade that ‘It is after all ridiculous for Italy to block all proposals for a genuine settlement of Central Europe and the Balkans and the sooner she is made to realise that her ridiculous susceptibilities and intrigues can no longer be humoured the better.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn152-0022009412461814">152</xref></sup> On the contrary, Chamberlain was convinced that Italy could be induced to repeat what she had already done, albeit rather unwillingly, in connexion with the Franco–German conflict<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn153-0022009412461814">153</xref></sup> and contribute to a Locarno-like agreement, and he banked his whole policy on that presumption. The fact that Italy’s true motives and surreptitious dealings were totally misperceived was a staggering blunder in the Foreign Office’s handling of the constructive idea of ‘Central European’ and ‘Balkan Locarno’.</p>
<p>The British policy defeated its ends in the long run. Its main tenet was the idea that the most dangerous thing for the preservation of peace was a division of states into hostile blocs on the pre-war pattern. The Foreign Office believed itself to be doing its best in order to avoid such a development when in fact, due to fundamental misperceptions and erroneous judgments, it facilitated that very outcome. The failure to bring about a Locarno-style settlement and thus prevent Mussolini’s later championing of Hungary’s cause deepened the tendency towards a clear-cut division between the revisionist and anti-revisionist countries in the region. ‘Locarno’ remained just an empty word which statesmen would keep using into the 1930s as an expression of pious dedication to peaceful settlement of Central Europe and the Balkans but without any relation to practical politics.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-0022009412461814"><label>1</label><p>G. Craig, ‘The British Foreign Office from Grey to Austen Chamberlain’, in G. Craig and F. Gilbert (eds)<italic> The Diplomats, 1919-1939</italic>, 2 Vols (Princeton, NJ 1953), I, 15–48 (22–4); P. Kennedy, <italic>The Realities behind Diplomacy: Background Influences on British external policy, 1865-1980</italic> (London 1981), 243–4.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-0022009412461814"><label>2</label><p>J. Jacobson, <italic>Locarno Diplomacy: Germany and the West, 1925–1928</italic> (Princeton, NJ 1972), part one; D. Johnson, ‘The Locarno Treaties’, in N. Waites (ed.)<italic> Troubled Neighbours: Franco-British Relations in the Twentieth Century</italic> (London 1971), 100–24; R. Grayson, <italic>Austen Chamberlain and the Commitment to Europe: British Foreign Policy, 1924–29</italic> (London and Portland, OR 1997), Ch. 3; A. Orde, <italic>Great Britain and International Security, 1920–1926</italic> (London 1978), Ch. 5; D. Dutton, <italic>Austen Chamberlain: Gentleman in Politics</italic> (Bolton 1985), 240–58.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-0022009412461814"><label>3</label><p>S. Marks, <italic>The Illusion of Peace: International Relations in Europe 1918–1933,</italic> 2nd edn (New York 2003), 79.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-0022009412461814"><label>4</label><p>Quoted in P. Wandycz, <italic>France and her Eastern Allies, 1919–1925: French-Czechoslovak-Polish Relations from the Paris Peace Conference to Locarno</italic> (Minneapolis, MN 1962), 360–1; see also analysis in Jacobson, <italic>Locarno Diplomacy</italic>, 29–30.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-0022009412461814"><label>5</label><p>Z. Gasiorowski, ‘Beneš and Locarno: Some Unpublished Documents’, <italic>The Review of Politics</italic> 20, 2 (1958), 209–24</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6-0022009412461814"><label>6</label><p>F. Northedge, <italic>The Troubled Giant: Britain among the Great Powers, 1916–1939</italic> (London 1966), 269–70.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn7-0022009412461814"><label>7</label><p>G. Bátonyi, <italic>Britain and Central Europe, 1918–1933</italic> (Oxford 1999), Ch. 7 is somewhat misleadingly titled ‘The Failed Hopes of an “Eastern Locarno”’ for it gives scant information on its alleged subject; more to the point is a brief discussion to be found on 206–8.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn8-0022009412461814"><label>8</label><p>J. Headlam-Morley, <italic>Studies in Diplomatic History</italic> (London 1930), 170.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn9-0022009412461814"><label>9</label><p>Ibid., 184.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn10-0022009412461814"><label>10</label><p>Minute by Chamberlain, 21 February 1925, FO 371/11064/1252/9, cited in B. McKercher, ‘Austen Chamberlain and the Continental Balance of Power: Strategy, Stability, and the League of Nations, 1924–29’, <italic>Diplomacy &amp; Statecraft</italic> 14, 2 (2003), 207–36 (219).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn11-0022009412461814"><label>11</label><p>For an appraisal of Chamberlain’s strategic views – a very appreciative one – see ibid., particularly pp. 218--220.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn12-0022009412461814"><label>12</label><p>Kew, The National Archives [hereafter TNA], Foreign Office Records, General Correspondence, Chamberlain to Tyrell, 19 October 1925, C 13131/13131/62, FO 371/10701.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn13-0022009412461814"><label>13</label><p><italic>British Documents on Foreign Affairs: Reports and Papers from the Foreign Office Confidential Print</italic> [hereafter BDFA, references are to part II, series F], K. Bourne and D. Cameron Watt (eds) (University Publications of America, 1986–), Vol. 6, Doc 159, Kennard to Chamberlain, 22 October 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn14-0022009412461814"><label>14</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Bateman, 23 October 1925, Howard Smith and Lampson, 24 October 1925, C 13386/13131/62, FO 371/10701; The Chief of Central Department, Miles Lampson, was a pessimist in regard to the possibility of an agreement which he believed would founder on the Hungarian intransigence. Romanian Foreign Minister Duca in contrast to his Little Entente colleagues regarded the Balkans as better field for the conclusion of mutual security pacts than Central Europe. See BDFA, vol. 2, Doc. 109, Dering to Chamberlain, 7 November 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn15-0022009412461814"><label>15</label><p><italic>Documents on British Foreign Policy, 1919–1939</italic> [hereafter DBFP], E. Woodward and R. Butler (eds) (London: Her Majesty’s Stationary Office, 1947–), Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. I, No. 39, Chamberlain to Clerk, 30 October 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn16-0022009412461814"><label>16</label><p>Ibid.; also No. 40, Chamberlain to Graham, 30 October 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn17-0022009412461814"><label>17</label><p>BDFA, vol. 2, Doc. 106, Barclay to Chamberlain, 6 November 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn18-0022009412461814"><label>18</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Lampson, 12 November 1925 and Tyrell, 13 November 1925, C 14270/13131, FO 371/10701; Contrary to the official policy Hungarophile Lampson personally felt ‘that a restoration of at least Transylvania would be in the <italic>ultimate</italic> interest of European civilisation.’ Emphasis in original.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn19-0022009412461814"><label>19</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 11 November 1925, C 14474/13131/62, FO 371/10701.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn20-0022009412461814"><label>20</label><p>BDFA, vol. 2, Doc.108, Memorandum respecting the Situation in Central Europe [written by Howard Smith], 11 November 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn21-0022009412461814"><label>21</label><p>Ibid.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn22-0022009412461814"><label>22</label><p>TNA, Lampson to Kennard, private, 28 December 1925, C 16693/13131/62, FO 371/10701; A copy of this letter was privately sent to Budapest, Prague, Bucharest, Sofia, Athens, Paris and Rome.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn23-0022009412461814"><label>23</label><p>Ibid.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn24-0022009412461814"><label>24</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. I, No. 137, Record of a Discussion between Sir Austen Chamberlain, Mr. Lampson and Count Bethlen, Geneva, 8 December 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn25-0022009412461814"><label>25</label><p>D. Bakić, ‘Great Britain, the Little Entente and Security in Danubian Europe, 1919–1936’. Unpublished doctoral thesis, University of Leeds (2010), 68–78.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn26-0022009412461814"><label>26</label><p>O. Carmi, <italic>Le Grande-Bretagne et la Petite Entente</italic> (Genève 1972), 89–114; G. Juhász, <italic>Hungarian Foreign Policy, 1919–1945</italic> (Budapest 1979), 67–72; M. Ádám, <italic>The Little Entente and Europe, 1920–1929</italic> (Budapest 1993), 256–64.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn27-0022009412461814"><label>27</label><p>Cambridge, Churchill Archives Centre, The Papers of Sir Eric Phipps [hereafter PHPP], 2/20, Lampson to Phipps, private, 8 January 1926; also Lampson to Barclay, private, 8 January 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn28-0022009412461814"><label>28</label><p>TNA, Chamberlain to Clerk, 15 January 1926, C 468/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn29-0022009412461814"><label>29</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 2, Doc. 122, Barclay to Chamberlain, 8 January 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn30-0022009412461814"><label>30</label><p>TNA, Barclay to Chamberlain, 13 January 1926, C 613/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn31-0022009412461814"><label>31</label><p>TNA, Barclay to Lampson, 18 January 1926, C 652/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn32-0022009412461814"><label>32</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Harvey, 19 January 1926 and Howard Smith, 20 January 1926, C 652/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn33-0022009412461814"><label>33</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 21 January 1926, C 652/210/21, FO 371/11364. Emphasis in original.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn34-0022009412461814"><label>34</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 21 January 1926 and Lampson to Phipps, private, 22 January 1926, C 840/210/21; Phipps to Lampson, private, 24 January 1926, C 1049/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn35-0022009412461814"><label>35</label><p>TNA, Minute by Tyrell, 1 June 1926, C 5985/210/21, FO 371/11367; for the complicity of Hungarian officials see Juhász, <italic>Hungarian Foreign Policy</italic>, 79–80.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn36-0022009412461814"><label>36</label><p>TNA, Lampson to Phipps, 14 January 1926, C 417/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn37-0022009412461814"><label>37</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 20 January 1926, C 652/210/21, FO 371/11364.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn38-0022009412461814"><label>38</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 2, Doc. 139, Memorandum by Mr. Lampson, 8 March 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn39-0022009412461814"><label>39</label><p>TNA, Minute by Aveling, 8 April 1926, C 4319/1618/62, FO 371/11243.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn40-0022009412461814"><label>40</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 22 May 1925, C 6761/3066/62, FO 371/10699; also minute by Howard Smith, 7 April 1925, C 4851/4851/21, FO 371/10778.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn41-0022009412461814"><label>41</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 3 March 1926 referring to Dodd to Chamberlain, 25 February 1926, C 2591/1618/62, FO 371/11242; Barclay to Chamberlain, 1 March 1926 and minute by Sargent, 12 March 1926, C 2841/1618/62, FO 371/11242.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn42-0022009412461814"><label>42</label><p>TNA, Chamberlain to Parr, 14 September 1926, C 10169/3641/21, FO 371/11372.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn43-0022009412461814"><label>43</label><p>J. Burgwyn, <italic>Italian Foreign Policy in the Interwar Period, 1918–1941</italic> (Westport, CT 1997), 36–40.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn44-0022009412461814"><label>44</label><p>V. Jelinek, ‘The Hungarian Factor in Italian Foreign Policy, 1918–1927’. Unpublished doctoral thesis, New York University (1977), 319–20; also Juhász, <italic>Hungarian Foreign Policy</italic>, 82–4, 91.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn45-0022009412461814"><label>45</label><p>TNA, Kennard to Chamberlain, 18 May 1927, C 4529/532/62, FO 371/12111.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn46-0022009412461814"><label>46</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 2, Doc. 199, Barclay to Chamberlain, 4 January 1928; also TNA, Minutes by Bateman, 10 January 1928 and Howard Smith, 11 January 1928, C 186/186/21, FO 371/12937; Annual Report on Hungary for 1927, C 2769/2632/21, FO 371/12939.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn47-0022009412461814"><label>47</label><p>Churchill Archives Centre, PHPP, 2/7, Phipps to Sargent, private, 15 January 1928.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn48-0022009412461814"><label>48</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Crowe, 9 January 1929 and Howard Smith, 10 January 1929, C 120/120/21, FO 371/13664.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn49-0022009412461814"><label>49</label><p>Churchill Archives Centre, PHPP, 2/16, Phipps to Vansittart, private, 9 February 1930.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn50-0022009412461814"><label>50</label><p>TNA, Drummond to Selby, 6 February 1928, C 1045/G and Maclaey to Chamberlain, 18 February 1928, C 1382/1382/12, FO 371/12867.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn51-0022009412461814"><label>51</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. IV, No. 142, Memorandum respecting the Adaptability of the Locarno System to Central and Eastern Europe by Howard Smith, 15 February 1928.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn52-0022009412461814"><label>52</label><p>TNA, Record of Interview, 20 February 1928, enclosed in Drummond to Selby, 21 February 1928 and minutes by Howard Smith, 24 February 1928 and Sargent, 25 February 1928, C 1467/1403/62, FO 371/12871.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn53-0022009412461814"><label>53</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Bateman and Howard Smith, 15 March 1928 and by Sargent, 23 March 1928, C 1973/34/21, FO 371/12933.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn54-0022009412461814"><label>54</label><p>TNA, Minute by Chamberlain, 31 March 1928, C 2520/182/21, FO 371/12936.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn55-0022009412461814"><label>55</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Bateman and Howard Smith, 13 April 1928, C 2818/182/21; Minutes by Sargent, 13 June 1928 and Tyrell, 14 June 1928, C 4982/182/21; both in FO 371/12936. For details on the Rothermere campaign see Carmi, <italic>Le Grande-Bretagne et la Petite Entente,</italic> Ch. 4.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn56-0022009412461814"><label>56</label><p>TNA, Minute by Crowe, 3 September 1929, C 6761/718/62, FO 371/13587.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn57-0022009412461814"><label>57</label><p>TNA, Minute by Sargent, 8 July 1930, C 5549/3004/62, FO 371/14349.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn58-0022009412461814"><label>58</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Busk, 17 July 1930 and Vansittart, 19 July 1930, C 5660/3004/62, FO 371/14349.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn59-0022009412461814"><label>59</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Bateman, 15 July 1929 and Howard Smith, 18 July 1929, C 5086/348/21, FO 371/13664; In contrast Victor Wellesley, the Deputy Under-Secretary, claimed that popular opinion in a more democratic Hungary would show ‘less obsession over frontiers’. This reappraisal of the merits of a potential change of the regime in Budapest appears to have been initiated by Arthur Henderson, the new Labour Foreign Secretary, who was reported, shortly after his coming to office, to have ‘taken a particular interest in the possibility of bringing about a more democratic form of Government in Hungary, and was anxious to review the whole situation’. See TNA, Private Office Papers, The Papers of Sir Orme Sargent, Sargent to Chilston, 10 August 1929, FO 800/276. The discussion remained purely academic.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn60-0022009412461814"><label>60</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 18 July 1929, C 5119/348/21, FO 371/13664.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn61-0022009412461814"><label>61</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 17 May 1925, C 6952/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn62-0022009412461814"><label>62</label><p>TNA, Minute by Chamberlain, 21 May 1925, C 6952/251/62, FO 371/10695. Emphasis in original.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn63-0022009412461814"><label>63</label><p>TNA, Kennard to Nicolson, private, 22 June 1925, C 8682/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn64-0022009412461814"><label>64</label><p>TNA, Kennard to Nicolson, private, 19 June 1925, C 8497/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn65-0022009412461814"><label>65</label><p>‘I am quite a little perturbed at Mr. Kennard’s zeal to get all the loose ends in the Balkans tidied up.’ – Lampson minuted on 30 June 1925, C 8682/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn66-0022009412461814"><label>66</label><p>TNA, Minute by Bateman, 26 June 1925, C 8497/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn67-0022009412461814"><label>67</label><p>TNA, Minute by Bateman, 10 August 1926, C 8806/626/7, FO 371/11220.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn68-0022009412461814"><label>68</label><p>L. Dimić and D. Borozan (eds)<italic> Jugoslovenska država i Albanci,</italic> 2 Vols (Beograd 1998), I, No. 852, Pašić to Protić, 18 April 1919; No. 968, Pašić to Davidović, 23 December 1919; No. 972, Memorandum on Albania submitted to Wilson [American President], undated; <italic>Jugoslovenska država i Albanci, II,</italic> No. 12, The position of the Yugoslav delegation in relation to the memorandum of 9 December 1919, 8 January 1920.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn69-0022009412461814"><label>69</label><p><italic>Jugoslovenska država i Albanci,</italic> II<italic>,</italic> No. 14, Dr Trumbić’s [the Foreign Minister] expose at the meeting of the allied Prime Ministers on 10 and 12 January 1920.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn70-0022009412461814"><label>70</label><p>TNA, Minute by Sargent, 29 June 1931, C 5007/475/90, FO 371/15146.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn71-0022009412461814"><label>71</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 6, Doc. 271, Memorandum respecting Italy and Albania by Howard Smith, 25 May 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn72-0022009412461814"><label>72</label><p>TNA, Blair to Young, 28 June 1922, enclosed in Young to Balfour, 28 June 1922, C 9474/419/7, FO 371/7370.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn73-0022009412461814"><label>73</label><p>TNA, Young to Macdonald, 24 January 1924, C 1558/195/7, FO/371/9659.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn74-0022009412461814"><label>74</label><p>TNA, Erskine to Macdonald, 2 February 1923; Minute by Bateman, 18 February 1924, C 2353/195/7, FO 371/9659.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn75-0022009412461814"><label>75</label><p>TNA, Erskine to Macdonald, 20 February 1924; Minute by Nicolson, 28 February 1924, C 3163195/7, FO 371/9659; Minute by Nicolson, 5 March 1924, C 3719/195/7, FO 371/9659.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn76-0022009412461814"><label>76</label><p>TNA, Foreign Office to Cabinet Offices, 3 July 1922, C 9035/419/7, FO 371/7370.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn77-0022009412461814"><label>77</label><p>TNA, Minute by Troutbeck, 11 January 1922, C 419/419/7, FO 371/7370.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn78-0022009412461814"><label>78</label><p>TNA, Minute by Crowe, C 419/419/7, FO 371/7370; D. Todorović, <italic>Jugoslavija i balkanske države, 1918–1923</italic> (Beograd 1979), 102 and 117 argues that the Bulgarians did try to strike a deal along those lines but were ignored by mistrustful Yugoslavs.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn79-0022009412461814"><label>79</label><p>TNA, Minute by Nicolson, 16 March 1922, C 3689/3689/92, FO 371/7685.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn80-0022009412461814"><label>80</label><p>TNA, Minute by Nicolson, 15 September 1922, C 12949/12949/19, FO 371/7606.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn81-0022009412461814"><label>81</label><p>DBFP, XXII, No. 524, Young to Curzon, 14 November 1921; XXIV, No. 350, Young to Curzon, 26 April 1923.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn82-0022009412461814"><label>82</label><p>Archives of the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts [hereafter A SANU], Vojislav Marinković Papers, 14439/434, ‘A plan for a state policy’, in manuscript and without date.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn83-0022009412461814"><label>83</label><p>TNA, Young to Curzon, 6 December 1922, C 17006/12949/19, FO 371.7606; Indeed, the Foreign Office received reports that the Italians were prepared to endorse Yugoslav claim on Salonica in return for commercial facilities on the Dalmatian coast. See TNA, Minute by Bateman, 2 July 1924, C 10510/10510/62, FO 371/9719.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn84-0022009412461814"><label>84</label><p>TNA, Crewe to MacDonald, 26 June 1924, C 10230/6098/19; Graham to MacDonald, 26 June 1924, C 10412/6098/19; Erskine to MacDonald, 1 July 1924, C 10556/6098/19; Young to MacDonald, 1 July 1924, C 10812/6098/19; Erskine to MacDonald, 1 July 1924, C 10875/6098/19; all in FO 371/9894.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn85-0022009412461814"><label>85</label><p>By the terms of the Greco–Bulgarian minority treaty the Slav inhabitants of the Greek part of Macedonia were considered as ethnic Bulgarians which had serious implications insofar as it undermined the Yugoslav contention that Slav population of Macedonia (Serbian and by implication Greek part of the province) were of Serb origin. The treaty therefore considerably embittered Belgrade against its Greek ally.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn86-0022009412461814"><label>86</label><p>TNA, Minute by McEwen, 20 November 1924, C 17537/17537/19, FO 371/9897.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn87-0022009412461814"><label>87</label><p>TNA, Young to FO, 20 November 1924, C 17603/17537/19 and Young to Chamberlain, 27 November 1924, C 18095/17537/19, FO 371/9897; Lampson doubted that a genuine agreement was possible between the Yugoslavs and Italians given their mutual jealousies but was reticent to aver so especially after ‘the wicked old man, M. Pasic’ had come back into office in Belgrade. See Minute by Lampson, 22 November 1924, C 17649/17537/19 and 26 November, C 17733/17537/19, FO 371/9897 and also Note by Mr Lampson, 2 December 1924, enclosed in Chamberlain to Eyres, 8 December 1924, C 18493/17537/19, FO 371/9897.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn88-0022009412461814"><label>88</label><p>TNA, Minute by Bateman, 27 May 1924, C 8457/123/92.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn89-0022009412461814"><label>89</label><p>TNA, Graham to MacDonald, 26 June 1924, C 10412/6098/19, FO 371/9894.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn90-0022009412461814"><label>90</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Crowe and Nicolson, 16 December 1924, C 18796/17537/19, FO 371/9897; After some initial hesitation Young expressed the opinion that there were no ulterior motives behind the denunciation of the Greco-Serbian treaty. See TNA, Young to Lampson, 10 December 1924, C 18819/17537/19, FO 371/9897.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn91-0022009412461814"><label>91</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 24 December 1924, C 18895/17537/19, FO 371/9897.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn92-0022009412461814"><label>92</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. I, No. 129, Memorandum respecting the Balkan Problem and British Policy in the Balkans, 4 December 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn93-0022009412461814"><label>93</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I, Vol. XXVII, No. 137, London (Geneva) to Chamberlain, 10 June 1925 containing the translation of telegram to Mussolini of the same date.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn94-0022009412461814"><label>94</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Nicolson [quoted] and Tyrell, 4 June 1925, C 8327/251/62, FO 371/10695; For Nicolson’s memorandum on the subject see DBFP, Ser. I, vol. XXVII, No. 137, London (Geneva) to Chamberlain, 10 June 1925, footnote 2.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn95-0022009412461814"><label>95</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 30 June 1925, C 8682/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn96-0022009412461814"><label>96</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 6, Doc. 155, Record of Conversation between Mr. Austen Chamberlain and M. Mussolini, 15 October 1925; The official and platitudinous reply was handed in at the Foreign Office 10 days after the Chamberlain-Mussolini talk at Locarno. The text is enclosed in Doc. 156, Della Torretta to Lampson, 24 October 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn97-0022009412461814"><label>97</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 20 October 1925, C 13129/251/62, FO 371/10695; It is not clear from Howard Smith’s words what was the content of those secret reports but they probably referred to Italian penetration into Albania.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn98-0022009412461814"><label>98</label><p>TNA, Minutes by McEwen and Lampson, 20 July 1925, C 9523/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn99-0022009412461814"><label>99</label><p>TNA, Minute by Nicolson, 21 July 1921, C 9582/251/62, FO 371/10695; on further reflection Nicolson stated that Ninčić invented the Italian bogey ‘to scare us into accepting the Serb point of view regarding Salonica and the Albanian frontier [minor rectification in the area of the monastery of St. Naum]’. See Minute by Nicolson, 29 July 1925, C 9923/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn100-0022009412461814"><label>100</label><p>Ž. Avramovski, ‘Italijanska ekonomska penetracija u Albaniju 1925. do 1939. godine’, <italic>Istorija 20. veka</italic> 5 (1963), 137–224.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn101-0022009412461814"><label>101</label><p>Belgrade, Military Archives [hereafter VA], registry 17, box 95b, fascicle 1, 4/1, Dinić to Great General Staff, 25 May 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn102-0022009412461814"><label>102</label><p>A. Cassels, <italic>Mussolini’s Early Diplomacy</italic> (Princeton, NJ 1970), 317–8.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn103-0022009412461814"><label>103</label><p>V. Vinaver, ‘Ugrožavanje Jugoslavije’, <italic>Vojnoistorijski glasnik</italic> 1 (1968), 127–47 (138).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn104-0022009412461814"><label>104</label><p>VA, registry 17, box 95e, fascicle 3, 4/1, Military Attache (Prague) to King Alexander, 26 November 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn105-0022009412461814"><label>105</label><p>VA, registry 17, box 95e, fascicle 3, 5/1, Military Attache (Prague) to King Alexander, 23 December 1925; since this military help was supposed to remain an undercover operation Beneš planned to repaint the emblems on Czechoslovak planes before sending them to Yugoslavia. The Central Department official was shown what purported to be a report of a Czechoslovak general in which allusions were made to a certain understanding between Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia stipulating the amount of technical assistance the former was to provide to the latter in the case of a war with Italy. See TNA, Minute by Bateman, 19 January 1927, C 532/532/62, FO 371/12111.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn106-0022009412461814"><label>106</label><p>Chamberlain had no qualms about admitting to the French Ambassador that the Italian threat to Asia Minor was beneficial to Britain as it made Turkey more yielding in the ongoing dispute with Britain over the oil-rich fields of Mosul in Iraq. See TNA, Chamberlain to Crewe, 22 April 1926, N 1871/718/38, FO 371/11533. P.G. Edwards, ‘Britain, Fascist Italy and Ethiopia, 1925-8’, <italic>European Studies Review</italic>, 4, 4 (1974), 359–74 dismisses the allegation that Chamberlain struck a bargain with the Duce whereby he offered concessions in Ethiopia in return for Italy’s frightening the Turks into giving way to Britain over Mosul (359–60).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn107-0022009412461814"><label>107</label><p>TNA, Minute by Harvey, 23 November 1925, C 14936/798/19, FO 371/10768.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn108-0022009412461814"><label>108</label><p>TNA, Kennard to Chamberlain, 16 December 1925, C 16338/276/92, FO 371/10794.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn109-0022009412461814"><label>109</label><p>TNA, Lampson to Graham, private, 30 December 1925, C 16372/276.92, FO 371/10794; when enquiring in a private letter as to Graham’s views on the subject Lampson stressed that ‘I have chosen this method of private correspondence in order to avoid “panic” despatches being circulated and thus starting what I trust are groundless apprehensions all round.’</p></fn>
<fn id="fn110-0022009412461814"><label>110</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. I, No. 166, Graham to Chamberlain, 1 January 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn111-0022009412461814"><label>111</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Harvey, 13 January 1926 and Tyrell, 14 January 1926, C 415/77/22, FO 371/11383</p></fn>
<fn id="fn112-0022009412461814"><label>112</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 6, Doc. 178, Kennard to Chamberlain, 23 December 1925.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn113-0022009412461814"><label>113</label><p>TNA, Lampson to Kennard, private, 28 December 1925, C 16693/13131/62, FO 371/10701.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn114-0022009412461814"><label>114</label><p>Ibid. Emphasis in original.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn115-0022009412461814"><label>115</label><p>TNA, Kennard to Chamberlain, 11 November 1925, C 14595/14170/62, FO 371/10701.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn116-0022009412461814"><label>116</label><p>The Archives of Yugoslavia [hereafter AJ], Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, 334-9-29, Gavrilović to Ninčić, 9 January 1926, confidential no. 20.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn117-0022009412461814"><label>117</label><p>TNA, Chamberlain to Kennard, 18 May 1926, C 5843/70/92 and minute by Bateman, 18 May 1926, C 5775/100/92, FO 371/11404; BDFA, vol. 7, Doc. 57, Record of Conversation between Mr. Sargent and the Serb-Croat-Slovene Minister, 5 October 1926, enclosed in Doc. 56, Chamberlain to Kennard, 18 October 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn118-0022009412461814"><label>118</label><p>TNA, Minute by Bateman, 6 July 1926, C 7509/92/7, FO 371/11217.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn119-0022009412461814"><label>119</label><p>Ibid. Ninčić was succinctly described in the Foreign Office as a ‘horrid fellow’. See TNA, Minute by Bentinick, 31 July 1926, C 8750/626/7, FO 371/11220; there are more unflattering remarks in minute by Lampson, 9 June 1926, C 6471/100/92, FO 371/11404.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn120-0022009412461814"><label>120</label><p>TNA, Minute by Bateman, 2 July 1926, C 7509/92/7, FO 371/11217.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn121-0022009412461814"><label>121</label><p>BDFA, Vol. 7, Doc. 13, Ogilvie-Forbes to Chamberlain, 21 July 1926.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn122-0022009412461814"><label>122</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Lampson and Chamberlain, 17 August 1926, C 9638/626/7 and Niemeyer to Lampson, 27 August 1926, C 9657/626/7, FO 371/11220.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn123-0022009412461814"><label>123</label><p>C. Macartney and A. Palmer, <italic>Independent Eastern Europe: a History</italic> (London 1962), 263–4.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn124-0022009412461814"><label>124</label><p>TNA, Sargent to Kennard, private, 24 October 1927, C 8459/4526/7, FO 371/12090.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn125-0022009412461814"><label>125</label><p>TNA, FO to Kennard, 8 October 1927, C 8175/4526/7; Kennard to Chamberlain, 6 October 1927, C 8250/4526/7; in FO 371/12090; BDFA, vol. 7, Doc. 180, Erskine to Chamberlain, 11 October 1927.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn126-0022009412461814"><label>126</label><p>TNA, Annual Report on Serb-Croat-Slovene Kingdom for 1925, C 1288/1288/92, FO 371/11410; Annual Report on Yugoslavia for 1926, C 241/241/92, FO 371/12212.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn127-0022009412461814"><label>127</label><p>TNA, Notes on Monsieur Djuric (S.C.S. Minister) and outstanding questions connected with Yugoslavia, 18 May 1926; also Kennard to Howard Smith, private, 13 May 1926, C 5878/5878/92, FO 371/11413.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn128-0022009412461814"><label>128</label><p>TNA, Minute by Harvey, 13 December 1926, C 13051/391/90, FO 371/11207.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn129-0022009412461814"><label>129</label><p>TNA, Minute by Chamberlain, 16 February 1926, C 2137/385/90, FO 371/11204; also minute by Chamberlain, 19 June 1926, C 7291/100/92, FO 371/11404.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn130-0022009412461814"><label>130</label><p>TNA, Minute by Sargent, 22 March 1926, C 3560/1618/62, FO 371/11242.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn131-0022009412461814"><label>131</label><p>TNA, Minute by Lampson, 30 March 1926, C 3945/1618/62, FO 371/11242.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn132-0022009412461814"><label>132</label><p>TNA, Minute by Chamberlain, 9 April 1926, C 4265/1618/62, FO 371/11242.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn133-0022009412461814"><label>133</label><p>For the ‘pro-French’ view see D. Johnson, ‘Austen Chamberlain and the Locarno Agreements’, <italic>University of Birmingham Historical Journal</italic>, 8, 1 (1962), 62–81; Jacobson, <italic>Locarno Diplomacy</italic>, 12–3, 16–7; Orde, <italic>Great Britain and International Security</italic>, 71–8; Dutton, <italic>Gentleman in Politics</italic>, 238–41; E. Maisel, <italic>The Foreign Office and Foreign Policy, 1919–1926</italic> (Brighton 1994), 158; Grayson has countered it in <italic>Chamberlain and the Commitment to Europe</italic>, 32, 44–7; Gaynor Johnson has expounded her views in: ‘Lord D’Abernon, Sir Austen Chamberlain and the Origin of the Treaty of Locarno’, <italic>Electronic Journal of International History</italic>, 1, 1 (2000); ‘Austen Chamberlain and Britain’s Relations with France, 1924–1929’, <italic>Diplomacy &amp; Statecraft</italic>, 14, 4 (2006), 753–69; and ‘Sir Austen Chamberlain, the Marquise of Crewe and Anglo-French Relations, 1924–1928’, <italic>Contemporary British History</italic>, 25, 1 (2011), 49–64.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn134-0022009412461814"><label>134</label><p>TNA, Minute by Sargent, 25 November 1927, C 9498/25/90, FO 371/12065.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn135-0022009412461814"><label>135</label><p>TNA, Minute by Tyrell, 9 November 1927, C 9001/808/92, FO 371/12218.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn136-0022009412461814"><label>136</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 11 May 1927, C 4111/808/92, FO 371/12217; Both Sargent and Tyrell briefly stated their agreement below Howard Smith’s minute.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn137-0022009412461814"><label>137</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Bateman, 19 March 1928, Howard Smith and Sargent, 20 March 1928, C 2161/96/7, FO 371/12857.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn138-0022009412461814"><label>138</label><p>TNA, Minute by Howard Smith, 20 March 1928, C 2161/96/7, FO 371/12857.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn139-0022009412461814"><label>139</label><p>Ibid.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn140-0022009412461814"><label>140</label><p>TNA, Sargent to Sperling, private, 1 October 1928, C 7022/42/7, FO 371/12856.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn141-0022009412461814"><label>141</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. V, No. 160, Sargent to Kennard, private, 17 September 1928.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn142-0022009412461814"><label>142</label><p>TNA, Sargent to Waterlow, private, 11 November 1929, C 8230/197/7 and Memorandum by Sargent on policy of HMG as regards Bulgaria, 17 December 1929, C 9815/197/7, FO 371/13573.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn143-0022009412461814"><label>143</label><p>TNA, Minutes by Sargent, 25 February 1930 and Vansittart, 26 February 1930, C 1328/82/7, FO 371/14314.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn144-0022009412461814"><label>144</label><p>TNA, Minute by Vansittart, 12 March 1930, C 1964/82/7, FO 371/14314.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn145-0022009412461814"><label>145</label><p>TNA, Memorandum on Bulgaro–Yugoslav relations by Balfour, 13 March 1930, C 2412/82/7, FO 371/14315; Memorandum on the Macedonian question, 10 May 1930, C 4470/82/7, FO 371/14316; Minute by Vansittart, 21 July 1930, C 5459/82/7, FO 371/14317.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn146-0022009412461814"><label>146</label><p>AJ, London Legation, fascicle I, I-3, Karović [Foreign Ministry] to Djurić, 3 April 1930, confidential no. 228; In December 1930 a plan for preventive military action that would destroy IMRO’s strongholds in the Bulgarian part of Macedonia was approved by the Defence Minister but never executed. See M. Bjelajac, <italic>Vojska Kraljevine Srba, Hrvata i Slovenaca - Jugoslavije: 1922–1935</italic> (Beograd 1994), 239–40.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn147-0022009412461814"><label>147</label><p>Grayson, Chamberlain and the Commitment to Europe, 123–5, 282.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn148-0022009412461814"><label>148</label><p>P.G. Edwards, ‘Britain, Mussolini and the “Locarno-Geneva System”’, <italic>European Studies Review</italic> 10, 1 (1980), 1–16.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn149-0022009412461814"><label>149</label><p>P.G. Edwards, ‘The Austen Chamberlain-Mussolini Meetings’, <italic>Historical Journal</italic> 14, 1 (1971), 153–64.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn150-0022009412461814"><label>150</label><p>DBFP, Ser. I<sc>A</sc>, Vol. II, No. 347, London (Geneva) to Tyrell (following from Chamberlain), 10 December 1926; also TNA, Minute by Chamberlain, 23 December 1926, C 13351/391/90, FO 371/11207.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn151-0022009412461814"><label>151</label><p>P.G. Edwards, ‘The Foreign Office and Fascism, 1924–1929’ and R.J.B. Bosworth, ‘The British Press, the Conservatives, and Mussolini, 1920–34’, both articles in <italic>Journal of Contemporary History</italic> 5, 2 (1970), 153–61 and 163–82 respectively; R. Lamb, <italic>Mussolini and the British</italic> (London 1997), 2, 27, 61–3, 66–7, 76, 85, 88–9.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn152-0022009412461814"><label>152</label><p>TNA, Kennard to Nicolson, private, 22 June 1925, C 8682/251/62, FO 371/10695.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn153-0022009412461814"><label>153</label><p>S. Marks, ‘Mussolini and Locarno: Fascist Foreign Policy in Microcosm’, <italic>Journal of Contemporary History</italic> 14, 3 (1979), 423–39.</p></fn></fn-group>
<bio><title>Biographical Note</title>
<p><bold>Dragan Bakić</bold> was awarded a PhD from the University of Leeds. His forthcoming publications include: ‘Diplomacy and Loans: The Foreign Office, Economic Reconstruction and Security in South-Eastern Europe in the 1920s’, <italic>International History Review</italic>, vol. 34, no. 4 (December 2012) and ‘The Port of Salonica in Yugoslav Foreign Policy, 1919--1941’, <italic>Balcanica</italic>, 43 (December 2012). He has also completed an article, ‘Three is a Crowd: The Italo-Yugoslav Conflict over Albania, 1919--1939’ based on Serbian/former Yugoslav sources, which is currently under review.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>