<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EUS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">speus</journal-id>
<journal-title>Education and Urban Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0013-1245</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3535</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013124510392567</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0013124510392567</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Beyond Story Grammar</article-title>
<subtitle>Looking at Stories Through Cultural Lenses</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0013124510392567">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0013124510392567"><label>1</label>University of Northern Colorado, Greeley</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0013124510392567">Jennifer Urbach, University of Northern Colorado, School of Special Education, 34 McKee Hall, Campus Box 141, Greeley, CO 80639 Email: <email>Jennifer.urbach@unco.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>392</fpage>
<lpage>411</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Literacy is a socially constructed ideology (Barton &amp; Hamilton, 1998; Street, 1995). Current representations reduce literacy to standards, skill testing, and the five components of reading (NICHD, 2000). This view of literacy discounts the knowledge and skills of many students. This article examines the oral story of Aisha, an African American first grader, through traditional and nontraditional measures. The findings highlight two contrasting perspectives of Aisha’s story: One that views the story as weak and below grade level and another that highlights her rich literacy abilities. This study argues that it is important to consider the social and historical features that may influence children’s stories. A definition of literacy that recognizes and values the continuum of literacy experiences is advocated in this article.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>social justice</kwd>
<kwd>students</kwd>
<kwd>urban education</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>What counts as knowledge and what counts as literacy are socially constructed ideologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0013124510392567">Barton &amp; Hamilton, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0013124510392567">Street, 1995</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0013124510392567">Mehan (2000)</xref> argued that how someone or something gets constructed is based on knowledge that is seen as legitimate. Coined the “politics of representation,” this process of legitimizing knowledge is often based on social and historical features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0013124510392567">Mehan, 2000</xref>, p. 259). These notions ultimately marginalize different types of knowledge and, thus, different cultural or social groups.</p>
<p>Current representations of literacy reduce literacy to standards, skill testing, and the five components of reading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0013124510392567">NICHD, 2000</xref>). This view of literacy discounts the knowledge and skills of many students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013124510392567">Cazden, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0013124510392567">Heath, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0013124510392567">Invernizz &amp; Abouzeid, 1995</xref>). This article proposes that “literacy” reflects an ongoing accomplishment rather than a checklist of predetermined skills. To leave “no child behind,” it becomes important to examine and value the literacy skills of our students and to build on those skills in the classroom. The specific purpose of this article is to examine one African American student’s story through multiple lenses and to discuss how her “funds of knowledge” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0013124510392567">Moll &amp; González, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0013124510392567">Moll &amp; Greenberg, 1990</xref>) can be seen as an asset, rather than a deficit, in the development of a rich understanding of literacy.</p>
<sec id="section1-0013124510392567">
<title>Cultural Knowledge of Literacy</title>
<p>Literacy learning begins before students enter school. It begins within the family and community in which one belongs. The early literacy experiences of many students are different from those expected in school-based literacy (Craig &amp; Washington, 2005) and throughout the past three decades, the marginalization of certain types of literacy has been well documented. In her seminal work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0013124510392567">Heath (1983)</xref> showed how two distinct communities’ (i.e., a White and an African American working-class community) literacy practices were culturally incongruent with the mainstream, middle-class literacy model predominately found in schools.</p>
<p>This cultural mismatch often led to the failure of students because they had not implicitly developed the “habits of performing” associated with the preferred school-based knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0013124510392567">Heath, 2000</xref>, p. 174). This cultural incongruence has often led to the perception by the dominant culture that students from backgrounds that diverge from the mainstream lack literacy and language skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0013124510392567">Bliss &amp; McCabe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013124510392567">Cazden, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0013124510392567">McCabe &amp; Bliss, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0013124510392567">Michaels 1981</xref>) For instance, in the late 1980’s Courtney Cazden published a study that illuminated how culture and cultural values impact our view and understanding of literacy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013124510392567">Cazden (1988)</xref> described how an African American’s elaborate and poetic stories full of symbolism and figurative language were perceived by both African American and White Harvard graduate students. After looking at a transcription of the story, the Harvard graduate students were asked to share their perceptions of the girl’s story. White graduate students called the story “incoherent” and judged the student as having language problems, low school achievement, and emotional problems. Four out of five of the African American graduate students reported that the story was “interesting” and “well formed.” They perceived the student as being bright and verbally successful. These two drastically different views illuminate the diverse understandings of what literacy should entail.</p>
<p>Various cultural groups’ story patterns emphasize and value different parts of the story (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013124510392567">Cazden, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0013124510392567">Champion, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0013124510392567">Invernizz &amp; Abouzeid, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0013124510392567">McClure, Mason, &amp; Williams 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0013124510392567">Michaels, 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0013124510392567">1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0013124510392567">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0013124510392567">Miller, Grace, &amp; Bracey, 2005</xref>). Given the diverse values of different cultural groups, the structure of the story may differ from the traditional White, middle-class structure. For example, studies have shown that some African American students may not emphasize the mainstream topic-centered approach to stories or chronologically sequence story events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0013124510392567">Bliss &amp; McCabe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013124510392567">Cazden, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0013124510392567">Champion, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0013124510392567">McCabe &amp; Bliss, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0013124510392567">Michaels, 1981</xref>). Rather, some African American students tell “topic-associative” stories that focus on thematically related episodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0013124510392567">Bliss &amp; McCabe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>Literacy knowledge is often based on implicit cultural values and beliefs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0013124510392567">Fairbanks (1996)</xref> stated that the “distinct features of African–American literary discourse are rooted in the economics of slavery and to the response of African Americans to racial discrimination through the matrix of the blues” (p. 325). Stylistic features such as repetition, vowel elongation, rhythm, and audience interaction are also influenced by the church (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0013124510392567">Champion, 1997</xref>). Even though these stylistic aspects of literacy have not been historically valued within the school, especially at the primary grades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0013124510392567">Heath, 1983</xref>), this does not mean that they are not important aspects of literacy.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0013124510392567">Smitherman (1994)</xref> illuminated the importance of stylistic aspects when she highlighted the power and literary value of African American discourse in her analysis of African American essays written for the National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP). Smitherman noted that students using a discernable African American discourse scored high on both persuasive and imaginative essays. The imaginative essays received the highest scores, as a result of aspects such as of fluency and power within their writing style. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0013124510392567">Lee (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0013124510392567">2006)</xref> also noted the importance of students’ cultural language. In her cultural modeling project, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0013124510392567">Lee (2006)</xref> used signifying, a routine practice in African American Vernacular English, involving “a high use of figurative language, including symbols, irony and satire” as a strategy to assist students in their analysis of literature (p. 309).</p>
<p>Even though there are a number of studies that look at literacy knowledge as it relates to ethnicity, it would be false to assume that other factors do not influence one’s cultural knowledge of literacy. Rather, researchers and teachers must look at all of the “patterns of affiliation” that influence students. Other studies have looked at class and gender differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0013124510392567">Mainess, Champion, &amp; McCabe, 2002</xref>). In a dependency analysis of 16 African American students’ narrative abilities, Mainess et al. found that girls and low SES students were more likely to tell elaborate stories than their counterparts. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee (1996)</xref> examined how three groups of student from different social classes discussed and analyzed a book in different ways.</p>
<p>Finally the influence of popular culture knowledge on children’s literacy knowledge cannot be overlooked. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0013124510392567">Dyson (1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0013124510392567">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0013124510392567">2003</xref>) illustrated how music, video games, and movies assist students as they become composers and literate beings. Dyson suggested that students regularly borrow elements from popular culture and transform theses materials into a new product. She argued that this vehicle into literacy is largely ignored.</p>
<p>Given these different views of culture and literacy, researcher and educators must acknowledge that all students will come to literacy through different paths. These paths are closely connected to our beliefs and values and thus our identities. In the next section, I will examine the belief of literacy as Discourse and how this informs our literacy knowledge.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0013124510392567">
<title>Literacy as Discourse</title>
<p>As the literature review reveals, there are numerous cultures to which we all belong. Culture is the “shared implicit and explicit rules and traditions that express the beliefs, values and goals of a group of people” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0013124510392567">Kalyanpur &amp; Harry, 1999</xref>, p.3). This is closely connected to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee’s (1996)</xref> concept of Discourse. Gee distinguished “Discourses” with a capital D from “discourses” with a lowercase d. While the word “discourse” denotes written or spoke communication, “Discourse” denotes the ways a person talks, acts, interacts, values, and thinks: It is, as Gee puts it, an “identity kit” or a way of consciously or unconsciously associating with a specific group (p.127). Part of what drives individuals to understand a story in a certain way are the knowledge and values they bring to a story.</p>
<p>All people belong to a variety of Discourse groups and each of these different Discourse groups informs and shapes the ways in which we understand and tell stories. Thus, our understanding of literacy is unique to each of us but, paradoxically, it is never ours alone. Literacy stands between our own reading or telling of a text and those historical and cultural influences that come before this one. Our reading or telling depends on the Discourse(s) that drive(s) it. It is dynamic and complex and thus our literacy abilities and understanding of story will be as diverse as we are as people.</p>
<p>Thus researchers and educators must begin to think of story in a different light. To broaden the definition of literacy then, researchers and educators must <italic>acknowledge</italic> that literacy is an on-going endeavor fundamental to our very being and to the historical and cultural context in which we live. It is even more important that educators begin to <italic>value</italic> the different literacy elements students bring to story. Looking at the story through more than one or two measures illuminates the complexity of literacy and highlights different literacy elements that are not always valued.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0013124510392567" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section4-0013124510392567">
<title>The Context</title>
<p>The school, named here as Monte Vista, was a small Midwestern school. It was a unique school for the district in the respect that 84% of the students were African American, 13% were Hispanic, and 3.6% of the students were White. A majority of the faculty and staff at Monte Vista Elementary were also African American. Many of the students came from a low socioeconomic background, with 83.4% of the student body receiving free or reduced lunch.</p>
<p>This study was part of a larger study that examined oral storytelling within an inner-city first-grade class of 30 students, 28 of whom were African American (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0013124510392567">Urbach, 2006</xref>). It was embedded within the language arts curriculum of an inner-city first-grade classroom. Students were given opportunities to listen to, tell, and write stories in both large and small-group settings. This process was based on <italic>The Storytime Exchange</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0013124510392567">Cliatt &amp; Shaw, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0013124510392567">Palmer, Harshbarger, &amp; Koch, 2001</xref>). It occurred in a formal setting where the teacher, researcher, and community members engaged in a storytelling process with the students. The students had opportunities throughout the study to listen to the adults and other students tell stories and to comment on these stories. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0013124510392567">Spradley’s (1980)</xref> domain analysis was used to examine the overall themes and patterns of the study. From that, three case studies were picked for in-depth case study analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013124510392567">Stake, 1995</xref>). Each student was purposively picked for the study because his or her interactions and stories were noteworthy in that they supported or diverged from central themes found within the class.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0013124510392567">
<title>Participant and Data Sources</title>
<p>In this article, one story, drawn from one of the case studies illuminated in the larger project, is examined. Ashia is an African American first grader considered average in her first-grade class. She was not a particularly strong student, or extremely weak. Like most of the students, she was just beginning to read short stories within the classroom. If you walked into the classroom, she would not stand out, yet she came alive when she told stories. Aisha was the first student to tell a story that engaged the audience. Yet Aisha’s stories did not always fit the expected school-based narrative structure. By examining one of her stories through both traditional and nontraditional analyses, it became clear that literacy is much more complex than a traditional view assumes.</p>
<p>The particular story chosen for this article was the second of five stories told by Aisha. It was the first story that garnered a reaction from the audience yet, from my perspective, was difficult to follow. This story was purposively picked for an in-depth study so that I could reconcile these dichotomous viewpoints.</p>
<p>The oral story reported in this article was audiotaped and transcribed. The story was transcribed for a number of voice markers: Pitch, stretching of sounds, volume, speed, and pauses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0013124510392567">Couper-Kuhlen, 2003</xref>; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0013124510392567">appendix</xref>).The story was broken up into communication units for narrative analysis purposes. Communication units facilitated the segmentation of a narrative and made it easier to analyze a story. Communication units were segmented by one of the following rules: Independent clauses plus modifiers; answers to questions; yes or no answers; utterances that were not an independent clause but were followed by silence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0013124510392567">Hughes, McGillivray, &amp; Schmidek, 1997</xref>). Obvious false starts found within the story were originally transcribed but most were dropped for this article. In addition to the transcription of the oral story, field notes were also recorded. The fieldnotes helped to describe the physical movements and interactions of both the storyteller and the audience.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0013124510392567">
<title>Data Analysis Procedures</title>
<p>The oral story examined in this study was analyzed through traditional and nontraditional measures of literacy. Although I argue that we need to move beyond traditional measures, it is important to examine students’ knowledge through both traditional and nontraditional measures. It is through the examination of both traditional and nontraditional measures that we may gain a more holistic view of literacy.</p>
<sec id="section7-0013124510392567">
<title>Traditional analysis of stories</title>
<p>I used two traditional measures. First, I examined the story through <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0013124510392567">Stein and Glenn’s (1979)</xref> story grammar elements. Story grammar analysis is used in many school-based classrooms. However, it may underrate stories that aren’t told in the European tradition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0013124510392567">McCabe &amp; Bliss, 2003</xref>). Typically, stories most easily analyzed with this type of measurement are those where the protagonist carries out a series of goal-based behaviors to solve a problem. There are eight categories of information that can be analyzed through Story Grammar: Setting, initiating events, internal response, internal plan, an attempt, consequence, resolution, and an ending. The setting, a basic element which establishes the scene for the story, usually describes the time, place, and some of the characters in the story. Initiating events can be called the “complications” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0013124510392567">Hughes et al., 1997</xref>, p. 118). These events are typically problematic in that they make the protagonist want to change something. The internal response of the character lets the reader know how the protagonist is feeling about the initiating event. This is generally followed by the internal plan, a statement or plan of how to fix the problem. The attempt is an action taken by the protagonist to solve the problem. Events that come after the attempt and that are causally linked are considered the consequences. The resolution is different than the consequence because it is the final statement relating to the initiating event: It can be an event or statement such as “and then they became friends.” The ending is some sort of statement that the story is over. Of these eight, four elements are considered optional: The setting, the internal response, the internal plan, and the ending.</p>
<p>In addition to the specific story structure elements, I analyzed the story’s structure by using a binary decision tree and developmental chart of story structure developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0013124510392567">Hughes, et al. (1997)</xref>. The binary decision tree consisted of a set of questions that helped determine a story’s placement on a developmental chart. The questions relied heavily on story grammar elements. The chart summarized ten developmental stages of story structure: Descriptive sequence, action sequence, reactive sequence, abbreviated episode, incomplete episode, complete episode, multiple episodes, complex episodes, embedded episodes, and interactive episodes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0013124510392567">
<title>Nontraditional analysis of stories</title>
<p>Aisha’s story was also analyzed through two nontraditional measures. “Stanza analysis” is an alternative analysis of structure that breaks the story up into episodes, or stanzas, within the larger story. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0013124510392567">McCabe and Bliss (2003)</xref> state that this method is often useful for highlighting the story structure of some cultures such as Zuni, Japanese, and African American topic-associative stories. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe (1997)</xref> listed a number of characteristics of topic-associated stories. First, they are often longer than topic-centered stories and give the impression of having no beginning, middle, or end. They are also characterized as “a series of associated segments that may seem anecdotal in character, linked implicitly to a particular topical event or theme” (p. 11). In addition, relationships between the parts are not explicit and have to be inferred by the listener. Temporal indicators occur more often in topic associated stories. Finally, McCabe also noted that time, location, and focus often shifts and that these shifts are marked by pitch and temporal markers.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013124510392567">Labov’s (1972)</xref> analysis of evaluation comes from his work with South-Central Harlem preadolescent, adolescent, and adult personal experience narratives. Labov consistently mentioned the importance of evaluation to a fully developed narrative.</p>
<p>Labov categorized these evaluative devices into four groups: Intensifiers, comparators, correlatives, and explicatives. Intensifiers evaluate the story by intensifying the events of the story. This can be complete by using devices such as: Repetition, gestures, expressive phonology, quantifiers, and repetition. Intensifiers, although they do not always change the complexity of the sentence, contribute to the colorfulness of the story.</p>
<p>Comparators are devices used to compare one event with events that did not happen. These become a way of considering “unrealized possibilities” or what might have happened (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013124510392567">Labov, 1972</xref>, p. 387). Some comparators that are commonly used are the following: Negatives, future tense, quasimodals (e.g., supposed to, had to), modals (e.g., can, could, should), or clauses, superlatives, and comparatives. Questions and imperatives can also be considered comparators because they can be seen as requests implicitly situated against the possible implications of not granting the request. Correlatives report secondary activities which occur simultaneously with the primary event in an independent clause. These can be marked by devices such as appended participles, double attributives, double appositives. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013124510392567">Labov (1972)</xref> noted that progressive tense verbs can be used to show simultaneous action. However, not all progressive tense markers can be coded as correlative devices. According to Labov, progressive tense verbs are only evaluative if they are considered narrative clauses (clauses that have to occur in a specific sequence) rather than free clauses that can occur anywhere within a scene. Finally, Labov identified explicative devices. Although correlatives bring together two events, explicatives momentarily pause the event in order to explain it. Explicatives are often found in the dependent clause of a complex sentence.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0013124510392567">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>The story discussed in this article was Aisha’s second story and is representative of many of Aisha’s stories in that it engaged the audience but did not fit the expected school-based narrative structure. This story came shortly after Halloween and at a time where several students were telling stories about Halloween. It also marked the first time a student’s story provoked a reaction from the audience. To highlight Aisha’s rich literacy skills, it becomes important to look at the multiple layers of literacy that can go on in a story. First, I look at the story through traditional measures and then I examine the story through nontraditional measures.</p>
<sec id="section10-0013124510392567">
<title>Traditional Analyses</title>
<p>The first analysis was a story grammar analysis. Based on the suggestion by Hughes, et al.(1997) this story is broken into narrative clauses. For this analysis, each line was analyzed for the elements of story grammar. Occasionally, one story grammar element runs across more than one narrative clause. These incidents are noted with the word “continued.”</p>
<p>When analyzed through a story grammar lens, this particular story was hard to follow and did not have a clear beginning, middle, and end. It seemed to wander off topic making it difficult to analyze (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0013124510392567">Figure 1</xref>). There were many actions identified but many were not related to initiating events, attempts, and consequences. Sometimes initiating events were not followed by explicit attempts to solve the problem. Consequences were not always followed up with explicit resolutions. In addition, since characters changed throughout the story it became difficult to identify attempts, which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0013124510392567">Hughes, et al. (1997)</xref> defined as the actions of the main character that attempt to solve the problem. To resolve this problem, the “attempts” in the story are marked in response to an assumption that the main character of the story changes.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0013124510392567" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Aisha’s story viewed through a story grammar lens</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013124510392567-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>For the most part, actions appear to be causal (e.g., when a person is chased he or she will run), but the protagonist didn’t seem to have a plan to reach a specific goal—in fact, because the characters changed, it was hard to identify a protagonist. Thus, a person listening to this story from a topic-centered view might conclude that Aisha’s story was incoherent. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0013124510392567">Hughes et al.’s (1997)</xref> developmental structural patterns, this story had lots of action, most of which was causally linked, yet it was missing goal-directed behavior and a consistent plot that ran throughout the story. Therefore, this story was categorized as a reactive sequence, a preschool-level story.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0013124510392567">
<title>Nontraditional Analyses</title>
<p>Based on traditional analyses, Aisha’s story seemed to be rather weak; however, a different perspective emerged when the story was examined through nontraditional analyses. Through these analyses, it was clear that her story was actually very strong on a variety of levels. For the sake of brevity, only two of the original analysis are presented here.</p>
<p>In many of her stories, Aisha employed a “predator versus prey” theme. In some stories, she would actually use the words predator or prey, but in this story the theme was more implicit. However, given the consistent theme running throughout her story and taking into account that some African American stories are considered “topic associated” instead of “topic centered,” it made sense to look at the story as stanzas linked by a theme or topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0013124510392567">Bliss &amp; McCabe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe, 1997</xref>). By parsing the story into communication units and then separating the story into specific stanzas, the story was examined as topic-associated stanzas woven together by the predator versus prey theme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013124510392567">Gee, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe, 1997</xref>). Using this method, a definite structure emerged (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0013124510392567">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0013124510392567" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Aisha’s story through stanza analysis</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013124510392567-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Not only does the stanza format uncover the structure in Aisha’s story, it also helps to illuminate her skill in using orientation. If we look at her story through the stanzas (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0013124510392567">Figure 2</xref>), we can see that Aisha set the scene for each new series of events. Most interesting to note is that although she used minimal orientation (i.e., identification of the characters and what they were doing) to introduce similar scenes, she used an entire stanza to introduce new predators and their different course of actions. Looking at her story through this different lens, one would have to say that Aisha’s knowledge of how to structure a story was exceptional.</p>
<p>The different analyses examined thus far revealed a strong structure woven into Aisha’s story. Yet, the final analysis of the story illuminates that, by far, Aisha’s greatest asset as a storyteller was her ability to develop the secondary structure of a story, the internal evaluation. Aisha was the first student who seemed to understand how to get other students interested in her story. Throughout the story, the audience laughed and carried on. She was also the first student to use a number of evaluation devices in her story. After her effort, she was met with great enthusiasm from the teacher: “So much expression! That was really good. And you used the word humongous—my goodness!”</p>
<p>In a story with 63 narrative clauses, Aisha used evaluation devices a total of 41 times. In contrast, the other 16 stories coded for evaluation devices showed an average of eight evaluative devices in 23 narrative clauses. The excerpt below illustrates how Aisha often used internal-evaluation devices.</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Then! Once there was this (other) lady</p>
<p>and she was creepy.</p>
<p>and she was creepy. (INTENSIFIER: REPETITION)</p>
<p>and she was like {makes growling noise—audience laughing} (INTENSIFIER: EXPRESSIVE PHONOLOGY)</p>
<p>and then she walked and walked and walked and walked (INTENSIFIER: REPETITION)</p>
<p>and then she saw the old lady witch (CORRELATIVE: DOUBLE ATTRIBUTIVE)</p>
<p>and she (felt that) she was hungry! {rubbing her tummy as she tells—audience laughing}. (INTENSIFIER: GESTURES)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>As the excerpt shows, the majority of the evaluation devices used were considered intensifiers. Aisha used 35 intensifiers such as gestures, expressive phonology, repetition, and quantifiers. Although intensifiers were used most of the time, other devices were also used. Two comparators in the form of negatives (“didn’t” and “no”) were used to compare events to those that didn’t occur. Correlatives were also used. One double attributive, “old lady witch,” was used twice within the story. Likewise, three past progressives (was . . . going) were determined to be temporally bound and thus could be considered correlatives. The only category of evaluations not used by Aisha was the category called explicatives.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0013124510392567" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The purpose of this article was to highlight the many ways that we can tell or read a story and to allow us to see the rich literacy abilities that are often marginalized in a traditional view of literacy. The analysis above illustrates how the same story can be viewed as either “weak” or “strong” depending on the lens or stance taken. When viewed through a traditional topic-center lens, the story appeared to be weak and developmentally below grade level. However, when examined through a topic-associative lens, a structure emerged, just not a structure typically seen in schools.</p>
<p>Although the above finding—that Aisha’s story follows a topic-associated pattern rather than the traditional pattern—is important in and of itself, we were able to see more of her strengths by looking at the story through <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013124510392567">Labov’s (1972)</xref> analyses. The story presented in this article was riddled with evaluation devices such as gestures, repetition, and changes in voice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013124510392567">Labov, 1972</xref>). Devices like these highlighted her purpose in telling the story—to evoke emotions and reaction. These devices seem to align with what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0013124510392567">Champion (1997)</xref> refers to as stylistic features (e.g., repetition, rhythm, vowel elongation, and audience interaction) in African American discourse.</p>
<p>If we accept that Discourse(s) connect us with specific groups and involve both explicit and implicit beliefs, values and ways of thinking or interacting, then it should not surprise us that we draw on these Discourses when we create or read stories. It appears that the topic-associated structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0013124510392567">Bliss &amp; McCabe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe, 1997</xref>) and stylistic features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0013124510392567">Champion, 1997</xref>) may be associated with Aisha’s African American heritage. Furthermore, her elaborative stories may also align with the Discourse of African American girls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0013124510392567">Mainess et al., 2002</xref>). Yet to say that Aisha’s stories were only related to these elements would be a mistake. A final analysis discussed in the larger study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0013124510392567">Barthes, 1970/1974</xref>) revealed that Aisha’s membership in the first-grade class, as well as her larger membership in the pop culture world, impacted her story. This was evident in her use of her classmates’ names or Halloween-themed characters (i.e. the witch, Chucky, a popular character from scary movies) as well as when she borrowed phrases or events from past stories told within the class. Thus, it is important to recognize and value the multiple Discourses that drive our understanding of story.</p>
<p>This study suggests that literacy is socially constructed and that a narrow view of literacy potentially marginalizes literacy knowledge. It contributes to the vast amount of research that argues for an expansive view of literacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0013124510392567">Barton &amp; Hamilton, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0013124510392567">Street, 1995</xref>). However, it also builds on this line of research by highlighting a specific story through multiple lenses. The use of many different lenses helps to highlight not only the contrasting view points but also illuminates the argument that one analysis (no matter if it is a traditional or nontraditional measure) cannot capture all of one’s strengths. By using stanza analysis and Labov’s analysis, I was able to see multiple levels of Aisha’s story knowledge.</p>
<p>Too many times in our classrooms, students who have a different knowledge base than their teachers are seen as having a “deficit of knowledge” rather than a different, but equally as rich, type of knowledge. Educators need to be able to recognize that our students’ literacy knowledge is built on a variety of Discourses, and thus entails diverse ways of thinking, acting, believing and valuing literacy. This study strongly asserts that if our educational system continues to promulgate the traditional view of literacy, then many students’ rich literacy abilities will be ignored and underdeveloped. If we want our students to develop a deep understanding of literacy, then we need to start by recognizing the rich literacy skills that students use and value. Once teachers recognize these skills, they are better able to help their students build on their knowledge.</p>
<sec id="section13-0013124510392567">
<title>Directions for Future Research</title>
<p>Indeed, the Discourses that drive us are complex and dynamic. We can neither state that there is one definition of “good literacy” nor can we assume there is one path to literacy. Instead, we must acknowledge the funds of knowledge that students bring with them to school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0013124510392567">Moll &amp; González, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0013124510392567">Moll &amp; Greenberg, 1990</xref>).Yet acknowledging our students’ funds of knowledge is not enough. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0013124510392567">Michaels (2005)</xref> stated, “We as a community, have to go beyond claims and documentation of difference . . . and show specifically how these differences can be recruited, in school, as strength (p. 137). Although this study highlights the differences as strengths, it does not examine how we can use these strengths in schools. Moll’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0013124510392567">Moll &amp; González, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0013124510392567">Moll &amp; Greenberg, 1990</xref>) work on funds of knowledge and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0013124510392567">Lee’s (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0013124510392567">2006)</xref> research on cultural modeling begin to illuminate this path, however, more research is still needed.</p>
<p>Finally, by examining one story through multiple lenses, this study illustrated the complexity and richness of literacy that often can be overlooked. This study focused on the teller’s story rather than the influence of the audience on a teller’s stories. Studies that examine the interaction between the teller and the audience allow us to see how stories are negotiated. Continued exploration of this process may help us recognize the Discourse(s) of both the teller and the audience and when and why certain aspects of literacy are highlighted or marginalized. By examining literacy in this dynamic and interactive environment, the picture of what literacy “is” will continue to evolve.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0013124510392567">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>As stated earlier, this study was part of a larger study of storytelling within a first-grade class. Therefore, I do not have an in-depth description of Aisha’s home life and how that impacts her storytelling. The purpose of this article was to focus on looking at one story and how viewing the story through multiple lenses can help us see the rich literacy abilities of our students rather than to investigate Discourse(s) used. Although we can speculate what Discourses were used to create such a complex and literacy-rich story, we cannot say definitively the Discourses used. Future research exploring the Discourses children use as they tell stories will greatly benefit the argument that literacy is embedded in context.</p>
<p>As previously mentioned, one of the analyses used in this study was stanza analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0013124510392567">McCabe &amp; Bliss, 2003</xref>). As stated in the methods section, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013124510392567">McCabe (1997)</xref> listed a number of characteristics of topic-associated stories. Although many of McCabe’s characteristics do fit this story, temporal indicators and shifts based on pitch and tempo markers do not seem to be strong in this story. Lines 46 to 47 indicate a change in time (in the morning, on the way home), yet there aren’t any other changes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0013124510392567">Figure 2</xref>). Likewise, although line 26 definitely starts with a pitch change, no other line starts with a significant pitch change, so changes in pitch and tempo do not seem to be associated with a shift in focus. Although I was able to capture large shifts in pitch or tempo, I am not a trained linguist and may have missed a few of the subtle prosodic shifts. A closer analysis of linguistic markers may have allowed me to pick up more shifts in the story.</p>
<p>Finally, this study examined one story through multiple lenses. Thus, we must remember that this story is not generalizable. Yet that is precisely the point. The story used in this study is unique. A comparison between Aisha’s story and the other stories found in the larger study shows that some students’ stories fared better under the traditional analyses. Yet that is the beauty of literacy and Discourses. We all bring different beliefs and values to the stories we read and tell.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0013124510392567" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>As our society becomes increasingly multicultural, we can no longer afford to view literacy through a single lens. Literacy is more than a set of skills. It’s a dynamic and complex process that is driven by our Discourses—our beliefs, values, and ways of thinking that are associated with our cultural groups. Literacy then is not a set of checklists but a way to express ourselves. Thus, we cannot afford to look at our children stories through one lens. Looking at story or literacy as if it should fit a specific mold depersonalizes the act of literacy. It marginalizes individuals as well as the richness that is literacy. It becomes our job to challenge the “politics of representation” and to expand the definition of literacy.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<table-wrap id="table1-0013124510392567" position="float">
<label>Appendix</label>
<caption>
<p>Transcription Conventions</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0013124510392567" xlink:href="10.1177_0013124510392567-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Line! Final pitch falling to low from high starting point</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Line? Final pitch rising to high</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wo::rd Lengthened sound or syllable</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WORD sound or syllable louder than the others</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(word) unsure transcription</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(.) brief pause</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Measured pause</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(acc) accelerando (acc) word or phrase which is sped up</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0013124510392567">
<p>Source: Adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0013124510392567">Couper-Kuhlen (2003</xref>, pp. 33-34)</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author received no financial support for the research and/or authorship of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Jennifer Urbach</bold>, PhD, is currently an assistant professor of in the School of Special Education at the University of Northern Colorado. She graduated from the University of Colorado at Boulder in 2006 with a PhD in education. Her research focuses on literacy development, culturally responsive teaching, and effective professional development.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barthes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <source>S/Z: An essay</source> (<person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Trans.). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hill &amp; Wang</publisher-name>. (<comment>Original work published 1970</comment>)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Local literacies: Reading and writing in one community</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Personal narratives: Cultural differences and clinical implications</article-title>. <source>Topics in Language Disorders</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>162</fpage>-<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cazden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Classroom discourse: The language of teaching and learning</source>. <publisher-loc>Portsmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Tell me somethin’ good: A description of narrative structures among African American children</article-title>. <source>Linguistics and Education</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cliatt</surname><given-names>M. J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>The storytime exchange: Ways to enhance it</article-title>. <source>Childhood Education</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Couper-Kuhlen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Intonation and discourse: Current views from within</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schiffrin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tannen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The handbook of discourses analysis</source> (pp. <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Recent research on the language and literacy skills of African American students in the early years</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of early literacy research</source> (<volume>Vol. 2</volume>, pp. <fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Social worlds of children learning to write in an urban primary school</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Teachers College Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Where are the childhoods in childhood literacy? An exploration in outer (school) space</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Welcome to the jam: Popular culture, school literacy, and the making of childhoods</article-title>. <source>Harvard Educational Review</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>328</fpage>-<lpage>361</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fairbanks</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Telling stories: Reading and writing research narratives</article-title>. <source>Journal of Curriculum and Supervision</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>320</fpage>-<lpage>340</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Social linguistics and literacies: Ideology in discourse</source>. (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Falmer Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Ways with words</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>What no bedtime story means: Narrative skills at home and school</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>B. A. U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borman</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eisenhart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Schooling the symbolic animal: Social and cultural dimensions of education</source>, (pp. <fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>189</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGillivray</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmidek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Guide to narrative language: Procedures for assessment</source>. <publisher-loc>Eau Claire, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thinking Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Invernizz</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abouzeid</surname><given-names>M. P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>One story map does not fit all: A cross cultural analysis of children’s written story retellings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Narrative and Life History</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalyanpur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Culture in special education: Building reciprocal Family-professional relationships</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paul H. Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Labov</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>). <source>Language in the inner city: Studies in Black English Vernacular</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basil Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Is October Brown Chinese? A cultural modeling activity system for underachieving students</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Every good-bye ain’t gone: Analyzing the cultural underpinnings of classroom talk</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Studies in Education</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mainess</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Telling the unknown story complex and explicit narration by African American preadolescents: Preliminary Examination of gender and socioeconomic issues</article-title>. <source>Linguistics and Education</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Cultural background and storytelling: A review and implications for schooling</article-title>. <source>The Elementary School Journal</source>. <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>473</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Patterns of narrative discourse: A multicultural, life span approach</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn &amp; Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Sociocultural variables in children’s’ sequence of stories</article-title>. <source>Discourse Processes</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mehan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Beneath the skin and between the ears: A case study in the politics of representation</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>B. A. U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borman</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eisenhart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Schooling the symbolic animal: Social and cultural dimensions of education</source> (pp. <fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowan &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>“Sharing time”: Children’s narrative styles and differential access to literacy</article-title>. <source>Language in Society</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The dismantling of narrative</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Developing narrative structure</source> (pp. <fpage>303</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Can the intellectual affordances of working class storytelling be leveraged in school?</article-title> <source>Human Development</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>E. C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bracey</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Working-class children’s experience through the prism of personal storytelling</article-title>. <source>Human Development</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>González</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Lessons from research with language-minority children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Literacy Research</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Creating zones of possibilities: Combining social contexts for instruction</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Vygotsky and education: Instructional implications and applications of sociocultural psychology</source>. (pp. <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>348</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</collab>. (<year>2000</year>). <source>Report of the National Reading Panel. Teaching children to read: An evidence-based assessment of the scientific research literature on reading and its implications for reading instruction</source>. (<comment>NIH Publication No. 00-4769</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Government Printing Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harshbarger</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Storytelling as a constructivist model for developing language and literacy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Poetry Therapy</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smitherman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>“The blacker the berry, the sweeter the juice”: African American student writers</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Genishi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The need for story: Cultural diversity in classroom and community</source>. (pp. <fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>101</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Urbana, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Council of Teachers of English</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spradley</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Participant observation</article-title>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Holt, Rinehart and Winston</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stake</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>The art of case study research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>An analysis of story comprehension in elementary school children</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Freedle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Advances in discourse processing: Vol. 2 New directions in discourse processing</source> (pp. <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Norwood, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ablex</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Street</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Social literacies: Critical approaches to literacy in development, ethnography, and education</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0013124510392567">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>The door into Narnia: Orchestrating a broader view of literacy</source>. <comment>Unpublished doctoral dissertation</comment>, <publisher-name>University of Colorado</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boulder</publisher-loc></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>