<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LSJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splsj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Labor Studies Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0160-449X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-9758</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0160449X12455409</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0160449X12455409</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Intimate Labors: Cultures, Technologies, and the Politics of Care</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>LaBarbera Twarog</surname><given-names>Emily E.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0160449X12455409">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Chicago, IL, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>324</fpage>
<lpage>325</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Boris</surname><given-names>Eileen</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parreñas</surname><given-names>Rhacel Salazar</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Intimate Labors: Cultures, Technologies, and the Politics of Care</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="360"/> pp. <price>$24.00</price> (paper).</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 UALE</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">United Association for Labor Education</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Eileen Boris and Rhacel Salazar Parreñas’s <italic>Intimate Labors: Cultures, Technologies, and the Politics of Care</italic> is an excellent read and resource for those of us in the field of labor studies. Boris and Parreñas provide a collection of brief essays that examine “the intersections of money and intimacy in everyday life, by looking at the ways that intimacy as a material, affective, psychological, and embodied state characterizes such labors” (p. 1). Simply put, this book reaffirms the value of intimate labor.</p>
<p>The essays focus on a wide array of intimate labor from nail technicians to sex workers as well as domestic labor, home health care providers, and child care workers. Boris and Parreñas divide the essays into three sections: technology and globalization, culture and social relations, and politics and mobilization. I chose to focus on the third section, politics and mobilization, which highlights different models of organizing.</p>
<p>These essays effectively show that “mobilization of domestic, care, and sex workers illuminates the possibilities for reaching low-paid, immigrant, and women of color workforces that straddle formal and informal economies and involve active communication or engagement between workers and clients” (p. 183). In doing so, they add a scholarly perspective to the work that many of us are already engaged in, whether with community organizations, workers centers, or unions.</p>
<p>In her essay, “Power, Intimacy, and Contestation: Dorothy Bolden and Domestic Worker Organizing in Atlanta in the 1960s,” historian Premilla Nadasen examines the ways in which African America women workers used the public sphere to influence their employers in private homes. Nadasen’s case study of the National Domestic Workers Union of American (NDWUA) reveals how isolated workers with little leverage “redrew the boundaries of hierarchy and deference that defined employer-employee relations” (p. 205). Rather than relying on marches and protests, Atlanta’s domestic workers organized for respect and dignity on the job by demonstrating that domestic work was in fact skilled labor. One of NDWUA’s strategies was to create a training program that would allow domestic workers to acquire, in the words of a NDWUA pamphlet, “specialized and technical training to provide better services in the field of Household Management” (p. 211).</p>
<p>Women received training in comparison shopping, cooking, driver’s education, child care, elder care, and first aid. At the end of the training, women received a certificate that emboldened them to see themselves as “professional women” with a discrete skill set. “I have completed my training as a household technician and know that I don’t have to scrub floors down on all fours anymore,” declared one graduate when her employer insisted she get down on her hands and knees to scrub the floor (pp. 212-13). The training program gave the women the confidence to speak up to their employer as well as see themselves as part of a set of skilled workers who deserved dignity on the job.</p>
<p>I highly recommend this book to anyone engaged in organizing and educating care workers. It is well written, is thought provoking, and challenges us to understand the definition of intimate labor and how it functions in a neoliberal marketplace. In an economy increasingly dependent on intimate labor, this is a must-read volume of essays.</p>
</body>
</article>