<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjpl</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Planning Literature</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0885-4122</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6593</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885412213497466</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0885412213497466</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Greening Berlin: The Co-production of Science, Politics, and Urban Nature</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eisenman</surname>
<given-names>Theodore S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0885412213497466"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0885412213497466"><italic>University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>258</fpage>
<lpage>259</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lachmund</surname>
<given-names>Jens</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2013</year>. <source>Greening Berlin: The Co-production of Science, Politics, and Urban Nature</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>. <page-count count="320"/> pp. <price>$42.00</price>, <isbn>ISBN: 978-0-262-01859-3</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Amidst a bloom of interest in urban greening today, Jens Lachmund offers a timely and insightful assessment of how species protection emerged as a focus of scientific and political concern in Berlin, Germany, during the latter half of the twentieth century, and how this led to new ways of planning and managing the urban landscape. Important scientific innovations are often connected to specific places—exemplified through Chicago and urban sociology, and the Galapagos Islands and evolutionary biology—and this in-depth study gains heightened relevance in light of Berlin’s pioneering role in urban ecology.</p>
<p>The book is organized around two goals: to shed light on the changing place of nature in the modern city and to understand the political use of science in an important environmental conflict. To this end, Lachmund, a lecturer in Science and Technology Studies at Maastricht University in the Netherlands, first traces Berlin’s history of urban greening through four periods or “nature regimes.” He then illustrates how ecologists between the 1950s and 1970s extended their field of study to urban sites, notably remnant rubble fields from World War II, and how this laid the foundation in the 1980s for the West Berlin Species Protection Program, a novel urban planning initiative that involved close interaction between ecological scientists and municipal administrators. These two phenomena—sustained scientific observation and the interaction of research with a politics of nature that prioritized wildlife protection in urban areas—are the scaffolding upon which Lachmund builds a central thesis: West Berlin gave rise to an “urban nature regime that exceeded the formal boundaries of institutionalized science” (p. 221) and “fundamentally ecologized” land use planning (p. 2).</p>
<p>Through detailed analysis of administrative reports, peer-reviewed articles, press coverage, activist materials, and unpublished archives, as well as over thirty qualitative interviews, we learn how, “A patch of ground next to the market became habitat for a foreign species. An ugly bombed plot between housing areas became a ruderal habitat with an interesting succession pattern. Urban parks such as the <italic>Tiergarten</italic> turned from pleasant recreation spaces for human visitors to biotopes, and their embellishment by gardeners hence became a threat to its potential for biodiversity” (p. 88). Indeed, the tension between open space as places for human recreation versus species protection is a defining characteristic that distinguishes this “biotope protection regime” (p. 9) from other periods in Berlin’s history of greening.</p>
<p>Lachmund ascribes this emergence to “co-production,” where scientific knowledge is produced and appropriated within the sociopolitical frameworks in which it is mobilized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885412213497466">Latour 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885412213497466">Jasanoff 2004</xref>). In the case of Berlin, three mechanisms converged to co-produce ecological knowledge and policy. First, the objects of scientific observation were never purely neutral; the mere act of studying rubble sites implied that they should also be protected. Second, political stakeholders such as local naturalists and nature conservation authorities were the audiences that ecological scientists had in mind when they selected research sites, conducted fieldwork, and presented findings. And third, scientific research was conducted on behalf of, or in close cooperation with, public institutions.</p>
<p>In elucidating this “co-production of science, politics, and urban nature,” Lachmund offers a cautionary tale that has implications for contemporary urban greening research and practice. Berlin’s biotope protection regime influenced the city’s political and physical landscape, and “ecologists seeking to expand their jurisdiction into public affairs experienced a need to make compromises with the rationales of administrators, which often threatened their academic standards” (p. 230). Yet, the goal of an urban ecological planning paradigm never fully took root, and species protection was eventually realized in only the most conventional form: nature parks or reserves set apart from the city.</p>
<p>According to Lachmund, a primary reason for this limited influence was the tension between urban ecology’s expansive reform ambitions and the socioeconomic realities of a large city. Another obstacle was the disconnect between urban ecology’s conception of the city as an interconnected system of biotopes along a density gradient, and planning’s practical expression through spatial districts. A third obstacle was significant competition over green space from other stakeholders. Municipal landscape planners strongly embraced an ecological perspective in the 1970s, but over time they realigned their priorities with a more aesthetic ideal. Likewise, an ascendant counterculture advocated for public access and recreation, and pursued new forms of activism by appropriating urban space through “guerilla gardening” and urban agriculture. Nevertheless, the author concludes that this tension is not insurmountable: incorporating ecology into urban planning will require greater discernment between spaces in which wildlife is prioritized and places dedicated to more human-oriented uses. Moreover, “forging such new forms of coexistence will require not only the proliferation of knowledge about the city and nature but also public reflection on how we know what we know about the city and its natures” (p. 236).</p>
<p>At times, Lachmund’s academic prose can be difficult to penetrate, and the deep analysis of a single case study may sustain only the most dedicated of readers. In addition, the concluding chapter could have benefited from situating findings within the broader context of contemporary trends in urban greening. But these drawbacks are minor. As long-standing efforts to integrate city with nature evolve, this account of the Berlin experience in urban ecology is an important contribution to the literature.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0885412213497466">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jasanoff</surname>
<given-names>Sheila. ed.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. <source>States of Knowledge: The Co-production of Science and Social Order</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0885412213497466">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Latour</surname>
<given-names>Bruno</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1993</year>. <source>We Have Never been Modern</source>. <publisher-loc>Translated by Porter, Catherine. Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>