<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922811429483</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922811429483</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Resident Rounds</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Severe Metabolic Acidosis in a Newborn With an Abnormal Newborn Screen</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Schrier</surname><given-names>Samantha A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922811429483">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ficicioglu</surname><given-names>Can</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922811429483">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922811429483"><label>1</label>The Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922811429483">Can Ficicioglu, The Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Biochemical Genetics, CTRB #9054, 3501 Civic Boulevard, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA Email: <email>ficicioglu@email.chop.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>518</fpage>
<lpage>520</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0009922811429483">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>The full-term baby girl (3940 g) born to a 25-year-old mother via normal spontaneous vaginal delivery was discharged from the hospital at 48 hours of life. Pennsylvania newborn screening returned abnormal at 72 hours of life for elevations in the C6 and C8 species. Initial contact with the mother at 4 days of life by the pediatrician revealed that her daughter was having difficulty nursing as well as taking formula and was beginning to show signs of dehydration. The family was referred to the local emergency room; an initial metabolic panel revealed a glucose of 41 mg/dL, bicarbonate of 8 mEq/L, blood urea nitrogen of 8 mg/dL, and AST (aspartate aminotransferase) and ALT (alanine aminotransferase) were slightly elevated at 135 units/L and 161 units/L, respectively. Because of the significant metabolic acidosis and concern for further decompensation, the patient was transferred to our institution’s neonatal intensive care unit.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922811429483">
<title>Hospital Course</title>
<p>The infant underwent a sepsis workup and fluid resuscitation with D10W and one-fourth normal saline along with PO (per os) feeds. Her acidosis quickly resolved with hydration. A repeat basic metabolic panel revealed sodium of 139, potassium slightly hemolyzed at 6.6, chloride of 111, bicarbonate of 26, blood urea nitrogen of 12, Sodium 139 meq/L, Chloride 111 meq/L, Bicarbonate 26 meq/L, Potassium 6.6 meq/L, and Blood urea nitrogen 12 mg/dL. Cerebrospinal fluid, blood, and urine cultures were negative at 48 hours, and she was discharged with improved breastfeeding after 2 days.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922811429483">
<title>Final Diagnosis</title>
<p>Urine organic acids showed a dicarboxylic aciduria, with elevations in suberic acid, adipate, as well as hexanoylglycine and suberylglycine. Genotyping subsequently revealed 2 copies of the 985A → G mutation, confirming the diagnosis of medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (MCADD).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922811429483">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency, a well-described inborn error of metabolism, is the most common form of fatty-acid oxidation deficiency with an estimated prevalence in the United States as 1:15 700.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922811429483">1</xref></sup> Affected individuals suffer from hypoglycemia after fasting, which can result in hepatic and other organ failure. Although most children with MCADD experience metabolic decompensation beginning at several months of age, newborns are still at risk. This newborn, with a screen positive for MCADD, presented with signs of dehydration, hypoglycemia, and metabolic acidosis. This case reinforces the need for awareness on the part of primary care clinician to recognize and consider MCADD as a disease that may present in the neonatal period.</p>
<p>Fatty-acid oxidation is employed in times of fasting to provide both energy and ketogenesis for use by the body. Individuals with fatty-acid oxidation disorders, including short-, medium-, long- and very-long-chain deficiencies, present clinically with symptoms that reflect the body’s deprivation of energy. Patients may display hypoketotic hypoglycemia, Reye-like hepatopathy, and subsequent organ failure.</p>
<p>Given the potentially fatal sequelae of unrecognized disease, MCADD is now a standard component of newborn screening.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922811429483">2</xref></sup> Although the majority of individuals with MCADD do not show symptoms until the first several months of life, and may not even present until adulthood,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922811429483">3</xref></sup> some children may present in the neonatal period.</p>
<p>Although the literature reports cases of individuals presenting in the newborn period with positive newborn screening or subsequent confirmatory testing for MCADD,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922811429483">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922811429483">5</xref></sup> the risk of metabolic decompensation is often thought to be highest between 3 and 30 months of age. It is therefore crucial that clinicians caring for newborns be aware that hypoglycemia and subsequent organ involvement may occur within the first several days of life. Difficulties with breast-feeding, poor suck, and suck–swallow discoordination may contribute to decompensation by exacerbating fasting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922811429483">6</xref></sup> These events may present before newborn screening has returned. The above case demonstrates the series of events that can precipitate a metabolic decline in these individuals.</p>
<p>Newborn screening concerning for MCADD will return with an elevated C8 level; this abnormality should prompt the clinician to contact the family immediately to notify them of the results as well as schedule an evaluation within the same day. Evaluation should ensure that feeding is going smoothly, and the family should be counseled on the potential severity of the disease as well as the importance of frequent feedings (no less often than every 4 hours at least for the first 3 months of life).</p>
<p>Emphasis should also be placed on the need for children with MCADD to be evaluated during times of illness, especially with vomiting. Prior to newborn screening, MCADD was believed to be a significant cause of unexplained sudden death in infants with Reye-like hepatic steatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922811429483">7</xref></sup> A retrospective study of 120 individuals diagnosed with MCADD revealed that 18% of the cohort presented with sudden death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922811429483">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Newborn screening clearly has resulted in decreased morbidity and mortality due to MCADD; however, there are still reports of sudden death in known cases of MCADD because of less than aggressive management during illnesses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922811429483">9</xref></sup> The prognosis remains excellent for individuals diagnosed prior to presentation with appropriate management. A total of 41 patients studied prospectively between 10 months and 14 years after the diagnosis of MCADD demonstrated only 1 subsequent death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922811429483">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>ACADM</italic> is the only known gene to cause MCADD, with several different mutations reported. Genotype–phenotype correlations have been proposed, with some mutations predicting a milder course of the disease. Although the majority of MCADD patients (99%) have at least 1 copy of the common 985A → G mutation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922811429483">7</xref></sup> in vivo and in vitro studies with the c.199T → C mutation show a potentially less severe outcome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922811429483">11</xref></sup> Conversely, the 583A mutation and the splice-site mutation IVS3-1G have been shown to cause severe hypoglycemia or sudden neonatal death.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0009922811429483">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>While for any newborn, a change in demeanor, mental status, or regular feedings necessitates an immediate call to their physician, the urgency is magnified in patients with MCADD. Clinicians should be particularly vigilant of feeding in these individuals to ensure adequate glucose stores and prevent metabolic decline. The presentation of this neonate illustrates the importance of primary care awareness of MCADD as a potentially life-threatening entity in the neonatal period and importance of following up abnormal newborn screening result urgently.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922811429483">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chace</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiPerna</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sgroi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Electrospray tandem mass spectrometry for analysis of acylcarnitines in dried postmortem blood specimens collected at autopsy from infants with unexplained cause of death</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1166</fpage>-<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922811429483">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Venditti</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venditti</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Newborn screening by tandem mass spectrometry for medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency: a cost-effectiveness analysis</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>1005</fpage>-<lpage>1015</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922811429483">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rinaldo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency: sudden and unexpected death of a 45-year-old woman</article-title>. <source>Genet Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922811429483">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uttley</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Neonatal presentation of medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency in two families</article-title>. <source>J Inherit Metab Dis</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>370</fpage>-<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922811429483">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cyriac</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A fatal neonatal presentation of medium-chain acyl coenzyme a dehydrogenase deficiency</article-title>. <source>J Int Med Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>-<lpage>610</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922811429483">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jirapradittha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Neonatal ventricular tachyarrhythmias in medium chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency</article-title>. <source>Neonatology</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922811429483">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iafolla</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medium-chain acyl-coenzyme A dehydrogenase deficiency and sudden infant death</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>325</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922811429483">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iafolla</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medium-chain acyl-coenzyme A dehydrogenase deficiency: clinical course in 120 affected children</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>-<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922811429483">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yusupov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finegold</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sahai</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waisbren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sudden death in medium chain acyl-coenzyme A dehydrogenase deficiency (MCADD) despite newborn screening</article-title>. <source>Mol Genet Metab</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922811429483">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome of medium chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency after diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0009922811429483">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The first three years of screening for medium chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (MCADD) by newborn screening ontario</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>