<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Men and Masculinities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1097-184X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6828</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1097184X11432113</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1097184X11432113</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Hegemonic Masculinity and Beyond</article-title>
<subtitle>40 Years of Research in Sweden</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Hearn</surname>
<given-names>Jeff</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1097184X11432113">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1097184X11432113"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1097184X11432113">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>Kjerstin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1097184X11432113">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Balkmar</surname>
<given-names>Dag</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1097184X11432113">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gottzén</surname>
<given-names>Lucas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1097184X11432113">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klinth</surname>
<given-names>Roger</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1097184X11432113">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pringle</surname>
<given-names>Keith</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1097184X11432113">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sandberg</surname>
<given-names>Linn</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-1097184X11432113">6</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1097184X11432113">
<label>1</label>Gender Studies, Linköping University, Sweden </aff>
<aff id="aff2-1097184X11432113">
<label>2</label>Education, Karlstad University, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1097184X11432113">
<label>3</label>Child Studies, Linköping University, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1097184X11432113">
<label>4</label>Social and Welfare Studies, Linköping University, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff5-1097184X11432113">
<label>5</label>Sociology, Uppsala University, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff6-1097184X11432113">
<label>6</label>Social and Welfare Studies, Linköping University, Sweden</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1097184X11432113">Jeff Hearn, FLO, Hanken School of Economics, Arkadiankatu 22, Helsinki, FIN-00101, Finland Email: <email>jefhe@tema.liu.se</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>55</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article discusses the status of the concept of hegemonic masculinity in research on men and boys in Sweden, and how it has been used and developed. Sweden has a relatively long history of public debate, research, and policy intervention in gender issues and gender equality. This has meant, in sheer quantitative terms, a relatively sizeable corpus of work on men, masculinities, and gender relations. There is also a rather wide diversity of approaches, theoretically and empirically, to the analysis of men and masculinities. The Swedish national context and gender equality project is outlined. This is followed by discussion of three broad phases in studies on men and masculinities in Sweden: the 1960s and 1970s before the formulation of the concept of hegemonic masculinity; the 1980s and 1990s when the concept was important for a generation of researchers developing studies in more depth; and the 2000s with a younger generation committed to a variety of feminist and gender critiques other than those associated with hegemonic masculinity. The following sections focus specifically on how the concept of hegemonic masculinity has been used, adapted, and indeed not used, in particular areas of study: boys and young men in family and education; violence; and health. The article concludes with review of how hegemonic masculinity has been used in Swedish contexts, as: gender stereotype, often out of the context of legitimation of patriarchal relations; “Other” than dominant, white middle-class “Swedish,” equated with outmoded, nonmodern, working-class, failing boy, or minority ethnic masculinities; a new masculinity concept and practice, incorporating some degree of gender equality; and reconceptualized and problematized as a modern, heteronormative, and subject-centered concept.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>boys</kwd>
<kwd>children</kwd>
<kwd>health</kwd>
<kwd>hegemonic masculinity</kwd>
<kwd>men</kwd>
<kwd>masculinities</kwd>
<kwd>schooling</kwd>
<kwd>Sweden</kwd>
<kwd>violence</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1097184X11432113">
<title>National Context</title>
<p>Sweden has a population of over 9 million, with about 85percent living in the southern part of the country. Though over 80 percent of people belong to the Lutheran church, most are non-practicing, and Sweden is primarily secular. The country industrialized late, moving in less than 100 years from poverty to one of the wealthiest modern welfare states. Though traditionally militarily “nonaligned,” Sweden joined the European Union in 1995.</p>
<p>The Social Democratic party held power alone or in coalition for most of the twentieth century. The welfare state was created through democratic and economic developments that lasted from the beginning of the twentieth century until the end of the century. This process was based on cooperation between the state, workers, and business. World War II is described as the turning point in transforming Sweden from a country of emigration into one of immigration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1097184X11432113">Bernhardt et al. 2007</xref>). Since the 1940s, immigration has accounted for over 40 percent of population growth. The environment in which the welfare state was initially developed was a male-dominated industrial society with the welfare model linked to a male breadwinner ideal. The social insurance system developed during the 1960s and 1970s strengthened relations between the individual and the state, with abolition of married couple taxation in 1971. Highly developed government-funded child care facilitated women’s participation in the labor market. Health care, education, care for the young and old, and social welfare are seen as primary responsibilities of the state. These relatively generous provisions are made possible by relatively high taxation.</p>
<p>In 2007, 81 percent of women and 87 percent of men were in the labor force, and 50 percent of employed women worked full time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1097184X11432113">Statistics Sweden (SCB) 2008</xref>). Yet the Swedish labor market is one of the most gender segregated in Europe, partly due to the size of the welfare state and public sector, where many women work. During the 1990s, unemployment rose, along with cutbacks in public spending and welfare provision. Since then, the situation has eased somewhat, but limitations on welfare, entrenchment of low income, stressful work conditions, and stress-related ill-health continue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr117-1097184X11432113">Statens offentliga utredningar (SOU) 2001</xref>), exacerbated in the current economic climate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1097184X11432113">
<title>Feminism and Gender Equality</title>
<p>Like other Nordic countries, Sweden ranks very highly in UN and World Economic Forum assessments of gender equality. The first attempts to involve men in reforming gender relations were in the radical family political debate of the 1930s. The social reformers Gunnar and Alva Myrdal questioned the traditional family and called for change in both men’s and women’s roles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-1097184X11432113">Myrdal and Myrdal 1934</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1097184X11432113">Myrdal 1938</xref>). Despite the Myrdals’ efforts, men were hardly visible in the extensive 1940s and 1950s family and social policy programs. Until the early 1960s attempts to change traditional gender roles were usually labeled in gender-specific terms such as “women’s issues” or “women’s questions” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1097184X11432113">Klinth 1999</xref>). However, in the early 1960s a substantial shift occurred in Swedish debate, when the women’s movement started there, interestingly earlier than in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1097184X11432113">Franklin 2010</xref>, 97).</p>
<p>Gender equality has been politically advocated since 1970s, as part of broader feminist politics; since then efforts have been strengthened, particularly around sexual harassment, women’s careers, and gender pay gap. The state has often been seen as woman-friendly and a very strong sponsor of gender equality policies, promoted partly by state feminism. Many governments have worked for more women in leading positions and equal political representation of women and men. New gender equality laws were introduced in 1980 and 1992, when gender equality statistics became part of official statistics. Organizations with more than 25 employees must produce gender analyses of salaries and a gender equality plan. Polices have been directed at reducing the gender segregation of the labor market, and granting women better employment and career opportunities, along with combining parenthood and employment. Gender analyses are mainstreamed in all political areas and decisions; women comprised 47 percent of parliamentarians in 2006. For a Swedish politician to take an explicitly antifeminist position is considered politically incorrect, even if the previous Minister for Gender Equality refused to call herself a feminist. However, there is relative failure in allowing women to occupy the most powerful governmental positions of prime minister and finance minister.</p>
<p>Policies directed at men are tightly connected to gender equality research and linked mainly to the gender equality project. Governments have sought to facilitate men’s active involvement in efforts to increase gender equality and have set out to investigate and remove obstacles preventing men from engaging in gender equality questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2005a</xref>, 62–97; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1097184X11432113">Statistics Sweden (SCB) 2008</xref>). Governmental interest in encouraging them to take greater part in household responsibilities and childrearing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2003</xref>, 76–80; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2005a</xref>, 62–97) must be considered in the light of the gender equality debate and the Swedish focus on full-time waged work for women as the way toward gender equality (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth 2002</xref>). Since 1974, men have had access to paternity and parental leave. Parents are entitled parental leave to a total of 480 days, 60 of which are reserved for each parent and forfeited if not used; men accounted for 21 percent of parental leave days in 2007 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1097184X11432113">Statistics Sweden (SCB) 2008</xref>). The school curriculum emphasizes the importance of treating boys and girls equally. Even with the strong critiques against gender equality policy and rhetoric raised by some Swedish gender scholars, this broad context has been central for the development of studies on men and masculinities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1097184X11432113">
<title>Studies on Men and Masculinities</title>
<p>The gradual growth of studies on men in Sweden can be seen as an indirect effect of the gender equality project and Women’s Studies, later to evolve into gender and feminist studies. Thus, critical research on men in Sweden has been and still is tightly linked to Women’s and Gender Studies. In a survey of the situation up until 2000, almost 60 percent of research done on men was carried out by women researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1097184X11432113">Folkesson 2000</xref>). The fact that studies and debate developed in Sweden relatively early means that there are national traditions that pre-date the hegemonic masculinity approach. Moreover, most writing on and conceptualizations of men and masculinities have developed in Sweden, until recently, in the Swedish language. Indeed, much Swedish academia has been rather self-referential to national and Scandinavian sources, rather than based on Anglophone conceptualizations. Though Anglophone texts have had considerable impact, Sweden can be seen as representing a semi-autonomous regional “center,” in terms of research, ideas, and debates on men and masculinities. Gender research, including that on men and masculinities, has developed in two main ways. The first builds on Swedish traditions and classics, most obviously Yvonne <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1097184X11432113">Hirdman’s (1988)</xref> historical scholarship on different historical societal gender contracts, and Jonas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1097184X11432113">Frykman’s (1981)</xref> work in ethnology. The second draws on Anglophone, sometimes Francophone, scholarship, translating it literally and conceptually into Swedish language and contexts. Connell’s theorizing on hegemonic masculinity is in the latter category.</p>
<sec id="section4-1097184X11432113">
<title>The 1960s and the 1970s: Before Hegemonic Masculinity</title>
<p>This first main phase of research on men and masculinity developed within the frame of critical sex role approaches<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1097184X11432113">1</xref>
</sup> and structural gender power, and before the formulation of the concept of hegemonic masculinity. There is thus much critical gendered work in Sweden, which does not use the frame of “hegemonic masculinity.” The early research about men as gendered beings has mainly been directed to women’s problems with men, in connection with the gender equality project. This project was promoted by researchers, activists and “femocrats,” some high profile, paving the way for much of the social policies and parental leave of this era. Connell’s theory can be said to reflect earlier Swedish critical gender research that in the 1960s problematized male sex roles. However, what made the Swedish experience somewhat unusual was the explicit focus on men and fatherhood. From the 1970s critical studies on the male sex role were not a separate research area in Sweden, with research concerning men done mainly by women from a feminist perspective integrated within Women’s Studies.</p>
<p>An important indicator of new ways of conceptualizing gender relations was an article in 1961 by a young academic, Eva Moberg, provocatively entitled “Women’s conditional release.” This critically scrutinized the dominant framework of the Swedish women’s movement, attacking, as “conditional release,” the notion of “women’s two roles,” that women should be encouraged to develop one role as mother, another as worker. In this, women were allowed to leave the house temporarily, if they promised to keep responsibility for home and children. Instead, Moberg argued for dual roles for both women and men; to substantially change the gender order, women’s entrance to public life must be paralleled by a similar entry of men into the private (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1097184X11432113">Franklin 2010</xref>, 98–100).</p>
<p>Moberg also suggested a new term for gender equality—<italic>jämställdhet</italic>—which soon became common in Swedish debates and policy processes. There is no synonym in the English language, but it could translate as “standing side by side.” Characteristically, the term “emancipation” was used for both men and women, generally framed in terms of the long-term political vision of double emancipation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth and Johansson 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1097184X11432113">Moberg 1961</xref>), as part of a welfare state feminist idea and a corporative political vision of a gender egalitarian society by way of equal parenthood. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1097184X11432113">Holth and Mellström (2010</xref>, 16) put it, “Men had to take a reproductive responsibility and women had to enter the labor market to a much higher degree than in the 1950’s and 1960’s. The general political vision and belief was, and still is, that male emancipation is to be achieved through men’s active fatherhood. Fatherhood became a most important project of the gender equality politics of Swedish state feminism. This is what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth (2002)</xref> calls <italic>daddy politics.</italic>” Implicit in <italic>jämställdhet</italic> was the heteronormative/normative assumption that women and men should be treated as equals with the same rights and responsibilities. It has been both radical and yet quite moderate, in not pointing out power asymmetries; men and women were placed side by side as gender-neutral beings. It could be said that <italic>jämställdhet</italic> was coined to create a sense of unity regardless of economic class, not challenging heterosexuality as a norm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1097184X11432113">Florin and Nilsson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1097184X11432113">Dahl 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The concept of emancipation,<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1097184X11432113">2</xref>
</sup> as well as that of <italic>jämställdhet</italic>, was closely connected to critical sex role theory. This theory, introduced to the Swedish debate in the early 1960s, became the major framework of interpretation for the emerging gender equality movement. Some radical commentators used it to emphasize the androgynous core of humans and how destructive sex roles force men and women into stereotypical gender positions. Critical sex role theory was also the starting point for studies on masculinity and fatherhood studies from the early 1960s until the late 1980s. In the groundbreaking book <italic>The Life and Work of Women</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1097184X11432113">Dahlström 1962</xref>), which became a landmark book for the Swedish gender equality movement, issues of men and masculinity were discussed at length. The sociologist Rita <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1097184X11432113">Liljeström (1968)</xref> presented research on the dangers of the male role, not least correlation between lack of active fatherhood and development of self-destructive/destructive behavior. In the mid-1970s, the government funded a research program on masculinity and fatherhood. In this, the psychologist Lars <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1097184X11432113">Jalmert (1979)</xref> completed a report on men and fatherhood (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1097184X11432113">Jalmert 1984</xref>, for a popularized version), coining the expression “in principle men,” whereby Swedish men tend to agree on general ideas of gender equality but do not always live in accord with them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1097184X11432113">
<title>1980s and 1990s: The impact of Hegemonic Masculinity</title>
<p>In many ways the 1980s became the decade of political programs on men, masculinity and fatherhood—but also when the dominant theoretical paradigm began to crumble. The subfield focusing on men as gendered beings is often referred to as <italic>Mansforskning</italic> (Men’s Studies) and dates from the 1980s. During much of this period, Swedish critical research on men and masculinities was intimately interlinked with and influenced by Connell’s theory of hegemonic masculinity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1097184X11432113">3</xref>
</sup> From the mid-1980s there was a greater impact of Anglophone theories and concepts in studies on men and masculinity, especially hegemonic masculinity and multiple masculinities. This can be seen as the second main phase of research on men and masculinities characterized by the influence of, sometimes ambivalence toward, such Anglophone approaches. With the arrival of such (hegemonic) masculinity theory to Sweden, questions of men and masculinity have been further taken up in civil society and government. In the late 1980s, some connections to critical studies on men and masculinities in the Anglophone world became one tendency.</p>
<p>The term, hegemonic masculinity, was diffused in Sweden by Margot Bengtsson and Jonas Frykman in the 1987 report <italic>Om maskulinitet: Mannen som forskningsobjekt</italic> (“About masculinity: The man as an object for research”) commissioned by the government. They related the term to how certain groups of men maneuver economically and politically, thus legitimizing men’s dominating positions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2000</xref>). Bengtsson and Frykman severely critiqued earlier Swedish research on men and masculinity, instead suggesting studies on masculinities, men’s practices, and constructions of forms of hegemony. They also took on a governmental commission to design a research program on societal development and its consequences for men in family and work life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1097184X11432113">Bengtsson and Frykman 1987</xref>). Influenced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1097184X11432113">Carrigan, Connell, and Lee (1985)</xref>, they concluded that Swedish masculinity research until the mid-1980s had offered few useful tools for understanding the dynamics of masculinity and gender relations. The consensus-oriented dualistic framework that, according to the authors, had dominated Swedish masculinity research and policy was seen as a cul-de-sac. Instead they promoted a framework focusing masculinity as a social construct, shaped by power relations intersected by structures of class, ethnicity, and sexuality.</p>
<p>The concept of hegemonic masculinity had a greater impact on Swedish research on men and masculinities than in other Nordic countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2000</xref>). This is partly because Sweden has produced more dissertations on men and masculinities, but also because the gender power aspect fits to some extent with Swedish equality politics and research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1097184X11432113">Folkesson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2004</xref>), even if the meaning of hegemonic masculinity is difficult to specify in this context. Swedish interest in hegemonic masculinity can be understood partly in terms of making visible power relations, dominance, and the hierarchical order between men, while focusing on patriarchal subordination of women and femininity. From the mid-1990s theoretical interest in Connell’s work was revived after a lull in the early 1990s. This was related to the publication and translation of <italic>Masculinities</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1097184X11432113">Connell 1995</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1097184X11432113">Mellström 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-1097184X11432113">Nilsson 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1097184X11432113">Nissen 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1097184X11432113">Ekenstam et al. 1998</xref>). The spread of Connell’s theory in Sweden can be related to how Swedish research became closely connected to British and US research during World War II. Indeed other Anglophone theories and concepts have been imported and frequently used as analytical tools in Swedish studies on men and masculinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg and Saar 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-1097184X11432113">Nordberg, Hellman, and Saar 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>By the late 1990s and early 2000s favored topics included fatherhood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1097184X11432113">Bekkengen 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1097184X11432113">Berg and Johansson 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1097184X11432113">Hagström 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1097184X11432113">Åström 1990</xref>), men in nontraditional occupations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1097184X11432113">Eriksson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1097184X11432113">Havung 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr114-1097184X11432113">Robertsson 2003</xref>), men in organizations and management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr118-1097184X11432113">Wahl 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1097184X11432113">Wahl and Holgersson 2003</xref>), homosociality and obstacles to women entering men’s occupations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1097184X11432113">Lindgren 1992</xref>). Historical research included studies of transformations in men and their emotions toward more disciplined ways of behaving (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1097184X11432113">Ekenstam 1998</xref>), and use of the concept of “unmanliness/manliness” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1097184X11432113">Lilieqvist 1999</xref>), rather than hegemonic masculinity. In 2003, two major edited collections, on <italic>Moulding Masculinities</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1097184X11432113">Ervø and Johansson 2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1097184X11432113">2003b</xref>), were published, resulting from Nordic cooperation in the late 1990s, including both Nordic and Anglophone authors, focusing on embodiment and discussing among many other things, including hegemonic masculinity. To many Anglophone readers, these are still the most comprehensive collections on masculinities published from the Nordic region.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1097184X11432113">
<title>2000s: Beyond Hegemonic Masculinity</title>
<p>Since the late 1990s, there has been discussion on moving beyond Connell’s theory of hegemonic masculinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1097184X11432113">2004</xref>). Swedish studies on men have expanded, and other mainly Anglophone theorists have become influential. This third phase of research in the 2000s might be characterized by diversity and critique, which includes work by a new generation of scholars not embedded in the frameworks of the 1980s. Some contemporary work on men and masculinities stresses insights from queer theory, discourse theory, science and technology studies, postcolonialism, intersectionality, and “third-wave feminism,” in addition to more specific approaches to men and masculinities.</p>
<p>The main contemporary theoretical perspective is grounded in social constructivism, and much research has critically reviewed dominant forms of manliness and explored alternative constructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1097184X11432113">Johansson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1097184X11432113">Johansson and Kuosmanen 2003</xref>). The subfield is often described as grounded in feminist research, but this is sometimes contested in how gender orders within studies of men may exclude women researchers and whether a feminist perspective is promoted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1097184X11432113">Folkesson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1097184X11432113">2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1097184X11432113">2001b</xref>). In recent years, queer theory, poststructuralism and discourse theory (both masculinity as discourse and discourses of masculinity) have had growing impact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1097184X11432113">Andersson 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1097184X11432113">Eriksson 2002</xref>; Ekstrand, 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1097184X11432113">Hammarén 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1097184X11432113">Johansson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1097184X11432113">Jonsson 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-1097184X11432113">Nilsson 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-1097184X11432113">2005b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-1097184X11432113">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-1097184X11432113">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr120-1097184X11432113">Steorn 2006</xref>). Cultural Studies has influenced research on masculinity in relation to ethnicity, education, consumption, and representation. Researchers on young men and boys have drawn on Paul Willis’s work, as well as researchers inspired by Connell, such as Ann Phoenix, Stephen Frosh, and Rob Pattman (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1097184X11432113">Asplund 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1097184X11432113">Holm 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1097184X11432113">Kalat 2008</xref>). Masculinity has been seen as gendered identity achieved in interaction, and as discourses restricting what it is supposed to entail to be a man. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg (2005a, 2007</xref>) has analyzed masculinity as fluid, contradictory assemblages of discourses, as more fruitful than Connell’s approach.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1097184X11432113">4</xref>
</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-1097184X11432113">Nordberg and Mörck (2007)</xref> have criticized Connell for neglecting such issues as dress, aesthetics, amusement, and consumption.</p>
<p>The subfield of study is still not clearly defined and is rather weakly established institutionally. On the other hand, there are courses on men and masculinity in many universities. Relevant ongoing doctoral and postdoctoral researches proceeding are linked to these and other institutions, including this very project, bringing together researchers in Karlstad, Linköping, Stockholm and Uppsala Universities.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1097184X11432113">5</xref>
</sup> This periodization, like many other such classifications, has some weaknesses and should be treated with caution. On the other hand, it does speak to some important temporal and generational shifts—from those attempts to address men and masculinity as a minor offshoot of more general women’s/feminist/gender/sexual politics studies, to those more focused on a specific subfield of studies on men and masculinity within (and sometimes outside) women’s/feminist/gender studies, to approaches not wedded to key Anglophone texts from the previous phase of development but rather drawing on a wider range of influences within feminist theory, including the travelling of theory.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1097184X11432113">6</xref>
</sup> To investigate the place of hegemonic masculinity in Swedish research in more detail, we now consider three specific areas, namely, men, children, and boys’ schooling; violence; and health.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1097184X11432113">
<title>Men, Children, Boys’ Schooling and Young Men</title>
<p>Scholarly output on boys and young men has focused on fatherhood and boys’ schooling, and is a major focus of research in Sweden. These are probably also the sites where the concept of hegemonic masculinity has been most discussed and utilized. Unlike in South Africa where the literature on youth has largely been associated with struggles to overthrow the apartheid state and, more recently, crime and violence, Swedish studies have focused on a relatively well-resourced and stable educational and familial settings. Research has sought to examine the subtle ways in which patriarchal relations have been reproduced even as alternative masculinities and ways of being boys have emerged.</p>
<sec id="section8-1097184X11432113">
<title>Fathers and Children</title>
<p>Following the established <italic>daddy politics</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1097184X11432113">Klinth 2002</xref>), research and debate on fatherhood and fathering has been especially strong. Many commentators agree that “involved fathering” has become incorporated into hegemonic masculinity in Sweden in dominant discourses on being a man. At that point divergence emerges. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1097184X11432113">Bergman and Hobson (2002</xref>, 124) see this incorporation as maintaining patriarchal relations, noting it has not disturbed “the division of labor in the family or gendered inequalities in the labor market.” By contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr111-1097184X11432113">Plantin, Månsson, and Kearney (2003)</xref>, focusing on what men say on their fathering, assert that transformation in hegemonic masculinity represents real change in practice. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1097184X11432113">Johansson and Klinth (2008)</xref>, who deal with what various men say about fathering, make claims implying changes in practice: “the hegemonic structure is changing. To qualify for hegemonic masculinity, it is no longer enough to be rational, goal-means oriented, career-oriented, and disciplined. Today, men must also show their readiness to engage in child care, their child orientation, and their willingness to live up to the ideal of gender equality” (p. 17). This suggests a reformulation of hegemonic masculinity in Sweden.</p>
<p>Some Swedish texts on fatherhood have taken up Connell’s hegemonic masculinity framework to some extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1097184X11432113">Berg and Johansson 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1097184X11432113">Johansson 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1097184X11432113">Bangura Arvidsson 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr113-1097184X11432113">Regnér 2006</xref>). On the other hand, studies on fathering in Sweden have been much based on different traditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1097184X11432113">Mellström 2006</xref>). Drawing upon, among others, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1097184X11432113">Bekkengen (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1097184X11432113">Björnberg and Kollind (2005)</xref>, rather than the concept of hegemonic masculinity, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1097184X11432113">Forsberg (2007)</xref> distinguishes how men talk about parenting from, first, the actual amount men do in practice, and, second, how they do, parenting: “paternal involvement does not necessarily imply gender equality; in fact, there is a tendency that fathers are child-oriented—spend time playing and talking with their children—rather than taking responsibility for childcare and household work.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1097184X11432113">Forsberg 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-1097184X11432113">Pringle (2010)</xref> analyses public policy and academic discourses on oppressive forms of fathers’ practices and their almost exclusive focus on minority ethnic groups. He shows the neglect in attention to the considerable number of fathers in majority ethnic group families engaging in oppressive practices. Pringle does not use the concept of hegemonic masculinity, preferring terminology such as oppressive practices of men.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1097184X11432113">
<title>Boys’ Preschooling and Schooling</title>
<p>In Swedish educational research concept has mainly been used to study boys’ educational achievement, peer cultures, and language use in terms of local often school-based hegemonic masculinities. Preschooling is a part of the education sector, and the relation between state feminism and the governmental gender pedagogy project. In studies of young boys’ preschool practices the concept of hegemonic masculinity is often used to describe normalization of certain ways of being a boy, highlighting power relations and regulating practices and hierarchies constituted between boys, between boys and girls in their daily interactions, and in preschool teachers’ interactions with children. This is mostly used in this context to highlight exclusions and marginalizations of some boys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1097184X11432113">Eidevald 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1097184X11432113">Hellman 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1097184X11432113">2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1097184X11432113">2008b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2005b</xref>). Hegemonic masculinity is presented both as a problematic, normalized and idealized masculinity concept, and as individual/collective practices in which masculinity norms are constituted, learnt, and upheld by ongoing collective boundary marking. This may occur in how some boys and most girls are excluded from play and peer group activities, because they in some way depart from normalized masculinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1097184X11432113">Hellman 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1097184X11432113">2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1097184X11432113">2008b</xref>). Much research on teachers’ practices and boys’ masculinity practices appears to arise from emphasis in the curriculum on contesting gender stereotypes.</p>
<p>The concept of hegemonic masculinity has also been employed during the last decade in Swedish educational policy debates on male pupils’ underachievement. In a public report, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1097184X11432113">Björnsson (2005)</xref> explained boys’ deteriorating test scores as the result of an emerging hegemonic masculinity with an “anti-study culture” (<italic>antipluggkultur</italic>) a central component. In debate on pupils’ national educational results, boys’ position in relation to girls has been discussed as an <italic>effect</italic> of hegemonic masculinity, thus reifying the concept. In the report presenting possible explanations of how it is that boys as a group achieve lower results than girl as a group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1097184X11432113">Björnsson 2005</xref>), Connell’s description of hegemonic masculinity is presented, but the other positions in the hierarchy are omitted. Hegemonic masculinity is described as <italic>outmoded</italic> form of masculinity, connected to the same stereotypical script that Connell emphasized as hegemonic masculinity, with many characteristics in common with the male sex role script in earlier Swedish gender equality debate. In Björnsson’s report there is also some hesitation, however, as there seems to be a divide between the description of hegemonic masculinity in Anglophone research and the practices of Swedish men. The discussion in Björnsson’s report on masculinity as a cultural concept that causes problems for both female and male pupils has been taken up by civil servants and politicians. This has been linked with a new more conservative educational politics, in which rules, rewards, competition between pupils and more authoritarian leadership are emphasized. When hegemonic masculinity is used in educational debates and in shaping implementation of conservative policy directed at male pupils, that part of the concept that connects hegemonic masculinity with legitimation of the male elite is forgotten. The fluidity and historical change in hegemonic masculinity pointed out by Connell is left out; the concept is thereby fixed to a certain historically unchangeable concept; boys are treated as a homogenous group, and variations downplayed. Through the limited application of the concept, female pupils who do not fit well into school and gain low results have been omitted from discussion.</p>
<p>Several studies have followed Björnsson’s argument. In an ethnography of an all-male secondary school class, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1097184X11432113">Högberg (2009)</xref> argues that local hegemonic masculinity is to a great extent a working-class identity, and that talk about cars, girls, and routine critique of theoretical subjects are used in boys’ self-constructions. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr120-1097184X11432113">Wester (2008)</xref>, hegemonic masculinity in schools is connected to rowdiness, anti-studying culture, and “being school smart.” Through social competence and knowledge about school behavioral norms, boys avoid sanctions for their behavior, which, according to Wester, explains their underachievement (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr110-1097184X11432113">Petersson 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>However, some researchers have argued that an anti-studying culture is not necessarily dominant among male pupils and have called for more nuanced analyses of local hegemonic masculinities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1097184X11432113">Berggren 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1097184X11432113">Bergman 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1097184X11432113">Holm 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1097184X11432113">Jonsson 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-1097184X11432113">Nordberg 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg and Saar 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1097184X11432113">Nordberg and Saar (2005)</xref> argue that an anti-studying culture is not as common as often presented among both working-class and middle-class positioned boys. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1097184X11432113">Holm (2008)</xref> suggests that study orientation, maturity, and disassociation from fighting and truancy characterizes both popular white middle-class boys and boys with immigrant background. Educational success is not necessarily part of hegemonic school masculinities, but the aim is to underemphasize studying so that you do not appear a “bookworm” or “swat” (<italic>pluggis</italic>), a category associated with lack of talent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1097184X11432113">Holm 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1097184X11432113">Kalat 2008</xref>). This problematizes uses of hegemonic masculinity that see boys, both middle-class and working-class, as uninterested in school work, and reproduce essentialized notions of hegemonic masculinity. Similarly, while some research shows how boys draw on homophobic and misogynist discourses to construct local hegemonic masculinities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1097184X11432113">Eliasson, Isaksson, and Laflamme 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1097184X11432113">Evaldsson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr107-1097184X11432113">Öqvist 2009</xref>), in his school ethnography of boys in a low-status suburb <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1097184X11432113">Jonsson (2007)</xref> argues that meanings of sexist expressions depend on context. By exploring how boys, through language, sometimes perform normative heterosexual masculinity, and sometimes “the successful pupil,” Jonsson deconstructs “the immigrant man,” which he argues has become a deviant, masculine stereotype needing discipline. This is in effect a critique of hegemonic masculinity seen as marginalized or other.</p>
<p>The concept of hegemonic masculinity is thus used in various ways in Swedish preschool and school studies. Often it is essentialized, fixed to certain unchanging characteristics: hardness, competition, authority, physical strength, suppression of pain and crying, risk taking, distance from girls and that coded feminine. Most studies repeat the description of hegemonic masculinity presented in Swedish and international gender research since the 1960s. Some studies, such as Jonsson, and Nordberg and Saar, use poststructuralism and Butlerian approaches, thus differing to some important extent from Connell’s assumptions, and more in line with the work of Stephen Whitehead, Alan Petersen, and third-wave feminists. Combining hegemonic masculinity and Connell’s masculinity hierarchy with a queer focus on heterosexuality as a regulating norm, they use masculinity positions to present other practices and ways of being a boy that depart from stereotypical, strongly gender-polarized masculinity.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1097184X11432113">
<title>Men and Violence</title>
<p>The problem of men’s violences did not become part of the official gender equality agenda until the mid-1990s, which matches the emergence of antiviolence work with men in South Africa. Up until this time research work had focused much on the gender-segregated labor market and policy, encouraging men to take parental leave. A general pattern is Swedish critical research on men’s violence to women has emerged out of a women-oriented radical feminist theoretical framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1097184X11432113">Steen 2003</xref>, 103). This critical, power-oriented approach to violence covers a wide range of issues: violence toward family pets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1097184X11432113">Holmberg 2004</xref>), relationship breakup processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1097184X11432113">Holmberg and Enander 2004</xref>), complex interconnections between the ending of intimate heterosexual relationships and men’s violence against women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1097184X11432113">Ekbrand 2006</xref>), violence in same-sex couples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1097184X11432113">Holmberg and Stjernqvist 2005</xref>), men’s violence in relation to child custody and contact in cases of separation and divorce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1097184X11432113">Eriksson 2003</xref>), and so-called honor-related violence focusing on victims and cultural meanings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1097184X11432113">Eldén 2003</xref>). Eva Lundgren’s research is often seen as central to knowledge on violence in Sweden. She, among others, points out that men’s violence against women must be interpreted as an expression of gender power hierarchy and a means of upholding it. Different forms of violence, exercised in different forms of arenas and relationships, are understood as interconnected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1097184X11432113">Lundgren 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr118-1097184X11432113">Statens offentliga utredningar (SOU) 2004</xref>, 121). Even though radical feminism has been rather successful in analyses of men’s violence against women over the last 20 years or so, other sociologically oriented and psychological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1097184X11432113">Eliasson 1997</xref>) perspectives have also had strong influence. A key debate has revolved around whether violence is “always” an expression of men’s power over women, challenging knowledge claims around psychological, biological, and social exclusion as explanatory grounds.</p>
<p>However, in Swedish research on gender-based violence, the concept of hegemonic masculinity is rarely used as an analytical framework. Ninni <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1097184X11432113">Carlsson (2009)</xref> explores the dynamics of women addressing sexual abuse in childhood, drawing on feminist perspectives, such as work of Maud Eduards, Maria Eriksson, Liz Kelly, and Lundgren, which offers critical perspectives on men’s practices. However, the concept of hegemonic masculinity is not employed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1097184X11432113">Eriksson’s (2003)</xref> study of violence, largely men’s violence, to children adopts a broad range of feminist/profeminist critical perspectives on men and also makes considerable use of some of Connell’s theoretical frames. However, she tends not to use hegemonic masculinity, instead referring to men’s practices and dominant forms of <italic>manlighet</italic> (“manliness”). Eriksson and Elisabet Näsman (2008), studying children’s participation in family law proceedings where fathers have been violent to mothers, explicitly address masculinity in boys’ experiences. Though drawing on various feminist/profeminist perspectives on men’s practices, they do not use hegemonic masculinity as a concept but rather dominant forms of <italic>pojkaktiget</italic> (“boyness”). Working on man-to-man violence, Veronika <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1097184X11432113">Burcar (2005)</xref> investigates how discursive understandings of masculinity and victimhood clash, and how “victim” is a discursively problematic position for young men. Kjerstin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1097184X11432113">Andersson (2008)</xref> examines young men’s identity constructions in talk on their own violence, using discourse theoretical tools, some from critical studies on men, but not hegemonic masculinity.</p>
<p>Thus, none of these studies theoretically engage with the notion of hegemonic masculinity. A possible explanation for this can be in the connection assumed between violence and hegemonic masculinity as representing an old, obsolete, stereotyped, “nonmodern” concept of masculinity. Thereby violence is excluded from concepts of men and masculinity understood and constructed as “more modern” and gender equal. In other words, violence can be seen as more tightly connected to the male concept highlighted in sex role theory and some versions of hegemonic masculinity.</p>
<p>Even though Swedish research on gender-based violence rarely uses the concept of hegemonic masculinity, there are a few exceptions. The political scientist Maud Eduards writes on the connections between military, peace–war, and men’s violence against women, using hegemonic masculinity as a key concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1097184X11432113">Eduards 2004</xref>, 262). Hegemonic masculinity is represented here though men’s assumed demands and rights, expressed through violence in war, as well as partner violence. She concludes “[w]hat is universal is the ‘culture’ of male violence; that factors such as men’s frustrations, the need to control and that threatened masculinity are ‘permitted’ to express themselves in violence on all levels: on personal, collective (explicit or implicit), national and global levels.” In this vein, hegemonic masculinity becomes an underestimated global problem, with repercussions for women’s conditions, democracy, and world peace. Another example is Anne-Lie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1097184X11432113">Steen’s (2003)</xref> overview of Swedish research on gender-based violence. She finds in hegemonic masculinity a way of broadening understandings of cultural notions of masculinity not reducible to individual men: hegemonic masculinity stands for the dominant notion of how a man should be; and gender equality policy challenges male privileges and questions hegemonic masculinity. In conclusion, while hegemonic masculinity has not been used much in Swedish research on gender-based violence, those who engage with the concept do so in line with radical feminist perspectives, sometimes using the concept to develop a differentiated analysis of cultural notions of masculinity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1097184X11432113">
<title>Men’s Health</title>
<p>In South Africa, gender and health, particularly in the context of the HIV pandemic, was a major sphere for the development of conceptual language relating to men and masculinities. In the case of Sweden, the circumstances were quite different. While there is a lack of substantive research in Sweden on the effects of different masculinities on men’s health, men’s health has gained some attention, for example, in conferences on men’s health engaging researchers and practitioners working with men. With a growing awareness that differences in men’s and women’s health and mortality are not entirely effects of biological dispositions but are also affected by sociocultural gender patterns, health-related behaviors are looked upon as doing masculinity and femininity. The doing of masculinity has generally been looked upon as an undoing of health. This has resulted in studies looking at men’s risk taking, loneliness, and unwillingness to seek help in order to maintain independence as factors influencing men’s health and relations to their bodies. These insights can be discerned in Swedish research on men’s health.</p>
<p>The notion of hegemonic masculinity is, however, little employed in relation to men’s health in Sweden. Two out of very few studies which discuss the concept in relation to men’s health are <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1097184X11432113">Nobis and Sandén (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1097184X11432113">Nobis, Sandén and Elofsson (2007)</xref>. Both studies define hegemonic masculinity as:</p>
<p>the systematic dominance of men and the subordination of women in society, can be viewed as an archetype of a man, other masculinities can also co-exist on a parallel basis. […] The social expectations placed on men in the frame-work of a hegemonic masculinity are that a man should be independent, self-reliant, powerful, strong, tough, robust and invulnerable and seeks predictability of performance.</p>
<p>This definition includes some reference with Connell’s conceptualization of hegemonic masculinity, in terms of men’s dominance over women and as an ideal model for men. However, Nobis and colleagues’ definition does not reflect Connell’s stress on hegemonic masculinity as a flexible concept, which changes to maintain legitimacy. Nobis and Sandén’s definition treats hegemonic masculinity as a set of given traits or characteristics such as “powerful” and “independent,” without discussing how this may change or vary in context and time. In terms of health they point to the potential downsides of hegemonic masculinity, as it may lead men not to take care of their health and not seek counselling, particularly when suffering from illness related to sexuality or genitalia. They conclude in their study of 19- to 34-year-old men that hegemonic masculinity had a significant impact on health. However, Nobis and colleagues also underline that their study points to some new directions on men’s health: the men in their study were able to disassociate from hegemonic patterns by admitting to vulnerability, being concerned for their health, visiting health care when necessary, and practicing self-care.</p>
<p>Another study which discusses the notion of hegemonic masculinity in relation to morbidity is Anna <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1097184X11432113">Månsdotter et al.’s (2009)</xref> study, based on data from Sweden’s 1969 military conscripts. This investigates associations between rankings of masculinity and mortality in the subsequent 34 years. The study found that there was a significant increased relative risk of all-cause mortality among the men who scored lowest on the masculinity ranking. Månsdotter et al. argue this contradicts previous research that points to links between investments in masculinity and mortality, that high masculinity scores and drinking and smoking correlate. They see Connell’s framework of hegemonic masculinity as fruitful for analyzing the results. The way Månsdotter et al. understand Connell’s hegemonic masculinity is, similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1097184X11432113">Nobis and Sandén (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1097184X11432113">Nobis, Sandén and Elofsson (2007)</xref>, a typology of different kinds of masculinities: Connell has defined three key types: hegemonic masculinity represents the highest valued masculinity at any given place and time, which in the Western context usually includes strength, independence, drive, and so on; “complicit masculinity” refers to men who do not achieve hegemonic masculinity but who never- theless experience power and prestige in society from supporting, in principle, these ideals; and “subordinated masculinity” is lowest valued among people in general and is typically signified by pacifists and homosexuals. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1097184X11432113">Månsdotter et al. 2009</xref>, 408)</p>
<p>This interpretation of Connell’s concept bears on this analysis of masculinity and mortality. Hegemonic masculinity is understood to represent one type of man, generally white heterosexual men, in whom characteristics such as “independence, strength, drive, ambition and self-reliance” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1097184X11432113">Månsdotter et al. 2009</xref>, 408) are valued. Complicit masculinity, in turn, is another type of man, and Månsdotter et al. argue that men belonging to this category are more at prone to psychological and physical risk. One conclusion is that hegemonic masculinity may have double effects: on one hand, involving risk taking, on the other, being beneficial, in taking care of one’s body through exercise, for example.</p>
<p>In these studies on men’s health in Sweden, the notion is used and conflated with dominant forms of masculinity but also represents the “most masculine.” In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1097184X11432113">Nobis and colleagues’ (2007, 2008</xref>) studies, the hegemonic is assumed to represent risk taking, reluctance to seek health and medical counseling, and lack of self-care. In contrast, Månsdotter and coauthors see ill-health among men lacking investments in or strong associations with hegemonic masculinity. The imprecise and unclear uses of the concept within these health studies results in rather weak conclusions. Månsdotter’s research on how care for children increases men’s longevity could be an example of specific characteristics of hegemonic masculinity in Sweden, which impact on men’s health.</p>
<p>Swedish research focusing on men and masculinities regarding sexual health and safe sex practices is also noticeably rare. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr115-1097184X11432113">Sandberg (2006)</xref> argues in a study of a clinic for men’s sexual health working with prevention against HIV/AIDS and other sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) that hegemonic masculinity needs to be rethought in the Swedish context. She suggests that hegemonic masculinity does not necessarily equate with a sexually promiscuous and irresponsible man but instead refers to a man who is responsible in sexual relations and oriented toward gender equality. The constitution of hegemonic masculinity, the making of some men desirable in the context of the sexual health clinic, was done by the “othering” of ethnically non-Swedish men and old men by the staff of the clinic. By aligning Swedish middle-aged heterosexual men with discourses of modernity, progressiveness and gender equality, a specific Swedish hegemonic masculinity was constructed in the arena of sexual health. Sandberg stresses the flexibility of hegemonic masculinity in terms of what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1097184X11432113">Connell (1995)</xref> discusses as the currently legitimate answer to the maintenance of patriarchal relations, which in Sweden must be related to gender equality discourses.</p>
<p>There is also a wider debate on the relevance of hegemonic masculinity for studying men and embodiment. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1097184X11432113">Johansson (1998) and Hirdman (2008)</xref> have examined how hegemonic masculinity shapes men’s bodies, producing an idealized male body that regulates boys’ and men’s practices. The athletic hairless fitness body, normalized among many boys and young men in Sweden today, can be seen as a materialization of the characteristics Connell connects to hegemonic masculinity. However, difficulties persist in applying the hegemonic masculinity framework to older men’s bodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1097184X11432113">Hearn and Sandberg 2009)</xref>.</p>
<p>All on all, there seems to be a need for a more sophisticated discussion on what hegemonic masculinity may actually mean in relation to men’s health in the Swedish context. As the gender and health researchers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1097184X11432113">Hammarström and Hensing (2008)</xref> point out, Swedish health researches often refer to studies from Anglophone countries, which they argue have different gender regimes to Sweden. The strong societal impetus for men to take part in child care in Sweden, as reflecting variations and other forms of hegemonic masculinity, may shed light on men’s health over the life course.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1097184X11432113">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>There has been much research on gender carried out in Sweden compared to many other European countries. Swedish research on men and masculinities has strengthened over time, been influenced by various traditions, some non-Anglophone, and usually conducted in Swedish language. Some researchers use approaches to men and masculinities other than that based in hegemonic masculinity, such as well-established Swedish theory on critical sex roles, manliness, gender contracts or the “weak breadwinner model,” and recent international feminist, critical gender, and sexuality theories. In developing such research importing international theory can be positive for researchers in Sweden, especially in becoming part of international debates. There are, however, problems with doing so uncritically, including developing theory insufficiently based on societal or local context.</p>
<p>In Sweden there is a complex mix of approaches to and uses of hegemonic masculinity. Some use hegemonic masculinity mainly as part of a typology (hegemonic, complicit, subordinate, etc.); others link it to how patriarchy is maintained, sometimes connecting it to a Gramscian framework. Some researchers make a rather structuralist analysis based on Connell, often combining it with Hirdman’s framework of societal gender contracts; others focus more on process, often relating to poststructuralist, ethnomethodological, or symbolic interactionist frameworks. The concept of hegemonic masculinity has been used much more in relation to fatherhood and schooling, as well as work and organizations, less so regarding violence and health. In Sweden men’s violence has been largely explored by women researchers. The relative avoidance of men’s violence by men researchers may stem from thinking, of both men researchers and men more generally, that men’s violence connects with a stereotyped and obsolete concept of masculinity, rather than a modern changing concept. This might be surprising, given the country’s reputation for “women friendliness.” Indeed, the Swedish context of strong gender equality discourses must be understood as the context in which hegemonic masculinities in Sweden take shape. This can work in a number of more specific ways.</p>
<p>First, hegemonic masculinity can be seen as <italic>gender stereotype</italic> examined out of the context of legitimation of patriarchy and (elite) male power. When hegemonic masculinity has been used as a gender stereotype in Sweden, the patriarchal dimension has often been excluded. Such analyses emphasize how polarizations between both masculinity and femininity and men and women are constituted and upheld when hegemonic masculinity is made equivalent to strongly gender-polarized concept and practice of masculinity, presented as opposite to “the Swedish gender equal, modern man.” One outcome of this use of hegemonic masculinity is that boys and men practicing more gender-polarized masculinity are positioned as “more masculine” than other men.</p>
<p>Second, the mingling of Swedish gender equality discourses and strongly gender-polarized, stereotypical definitions of hegemonic masculinity that makes some men problematic (e.g., old, immigrant, boys) could be a way of constructing specific “Swedish” hegemonic masculinity/masculinities. In this, hegemonic masculinity is seen as <italic>“Other” than dominant, white middle-class “Swedish,”</italic>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1097184X11432113">7</xref>
</sup> equated with, even marginalized as, outmoded, nonmodern, working-class, failing boys, or minority ethnic masculinities. These first two versions can be brought together in tandem.</p>
<p>A third approach focuses on <italic>hegemonic masculinity as a new concept</italic>
<italic>and practice of</italic>
<italic>masculinity</italic>. This approach highlights how gender equality discourses and changes in gender relations have influenced and changed men’s practices, including hegemonic masculinity. In this version of the concept change, gender equality, modernity and similarities in men and women’s practices are highlighted, and hegemonic masculinity is described as a concept that changes over time. Hegemonic masculinity becomes the most popular, normalized or idealized position for men, opposed to stereotypical characteristics and obsolete masculinity practices. Hegemonic masculinity incorporates (some degree of) gender equality, connected to involved fatherhood, health-conscious masculinity, or Swedish modern masculinity, considered less authoritarian, less violent, more emotional and more gender equality oriented than other and earlier masculinities.</p>
<p>A fourth, more recent variant is to <italic>rethink and reconceptualize hegemonic masculinity</italic> through queer theory, discursive approaches, postcolonialism, STS, as represented by some researchers in the third phase of studies. In this use the concept is decentered and multiple and considered in new forms that extend the category “men” and the male body. Hegemonic masculinity is here often problematized as a modern, heteronormative, and subject-centered concept and refigured into other power-oriented concepts.</p>
<p>Finally, while there has been considerable and variable use of the concept of hegemonic masculinity in Sweden, its intersections with non-Anglophone traditions, recent feminist, critical gender and sexuality theories, and national gender equality policy and rhetoric have been less developed. The national gender context, Swedish/Nordic gender theories, and national gender equality project have all impacted on how hegemonic masculinity has been taken up, discussed, and developed in Sweden. Though the concept has been widely used, and researchers in Sweden have done much research on many aspects of men’s practices and gender equality, hegemonic masculinity has not been applied greatly in studying men and violence. This might be an outcome of relations between understandings of hegemonic masculinity as strongly gender polarized and obsolete practices, and understandings of Swedish middle-class men as more modern and gender equal, than other men. Analyses of how hegemonic masculinity has been used in specific national contexts provide important clues to power relations and specific masculinities practiced in certain national contexts that may otherwise be difficult to grasp. This kind of analysis offers opportunities for new insights on masculinities, men’s practices, and hegemonic masculinity/masculinities in contesting inequality, violence, and problematic practices of men. And this is what makes such contextualized analyses important.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn8-1097184X11432113">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn9-1097184X11432113">
<p>The authors are researchers in the project “Hegemonic Masculinities and Men in Sweden and South Africa: Theorising Power and Change” funded jointly by the South African and the Swedish Research Council, the National Research Foundation (NRF) and Vetenskapsrådet (VR) respectively.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1097184X11432113">
<label>1.</label>
<p>It should be made clear that Swedish critical sex role research was located in the analysis of structural gender power relations and thus is distinct from Anglophone sex role research located in social psychological role theory and criticized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1097184X11432113">Carrigan, Connell, and Lee (1985)</xref> in explicating hegemonic masculinity.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1097184X11432113">
<label>2.</label>
<p>In the early 1970s, the Swedish prime minister contributed to the debate on men and fatherhood. Following his first visit to the United States in 1970 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1097184X11432113">Franklin 2010</xref>, 101), Olof Palme delivered a speech, “The emancipation of men” (Palme, 1971), claiming that a changing male role and men’s active fatherhood are fundamental conditions for the success of Sweden’s dual earner–dual carer policy (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr109-1097184X11432113">Pavlova, c. 2003</xref> for more background information).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1097184X11432113">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Importantly, the very concept of hegemonic masculinity has been used differently by Connell and colleagues in different texts, as a type, set of traits, social process, configuration of practice, and legitimation, and has undergone change over the years (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1097184X11432113">Connell 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1097184X11432113">Carrigan, Connell, and Lee 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1097184X11432113">Connell and Messerschmidt 2005</xref>; also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1097184X11432113">Hearn 2004</xref>), thus meaning that references to it in Sweden also vary.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1097184X11432113">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Discourses and a discursive approach to masculinity are not foregrounded in Connell’s work. Although Connell does not reject a discursive approach, she is critical to a “discourse-only approach,” arguing that “gender relations are also constituted in, and shape, nondiscursive practices.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1097184X11432113">
<label>5.</label>
<p>In addition, in the 2000s two men non-Swedish researchers and one man Swedish researcher who are active internationally in critical studies on men and masculinities have been appointed to professorships in Sweden: Jeff Hearn in Gender Studies, Linköping University; Ulf Mellström in Gender Studies, Karlstad University; and Keith Pringle in Sociology, Uppsala University. All have written on hegemonic masculinity, while developing further theoretical perspectives, such as on hegemony of men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1097184X11432113">Hearn 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1097184X11432113">Egeberg Holmgren and Hearn 2009</xref>), human–technology interfaces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1097184X11432113">Mellström 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1097184X11432113">2004</xref>), and men’s individual and collective practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1097184X11432113">Hearn and Pringle 2006</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1097184X11432113">
<label>6.</label>
<p>This way of analyzing the area has some resemblances to what Tim <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1097184X11432113">Edwards (2006)</xref> identifies as three waves in the field of the critical studies of men: the first with an emphasis on the socially constructed nature of and is rooted in a sociological approach; the second, the profeminist (relatively) structuralist approach; and the third, culturalist, poststructuralist, media-driven approaches.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1097184X11432113">
<label>7.</label>
<p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1097184X11432113">Forsberg (2010)</xref> writes, “White, middle-class men would either argue that they work hard to financially support their family, or that they try their best in sharing household work and childcare relatively equal with their partner. For such men, the hegemonic masculinity figure has become ‘the Other,’ a character distant from their own experiences. <italic>Other</italic> men are violent, oppressive, rowdy and macho, while they are ‘jämställda’ (<italic>gender equal</italic>) partners, and caring, involved fathers. The point I am trying to make here is that masculinity research may actually contribute to patriarchal relations, and Connell’s theory can, ironically, be used to maintain the hegemony of (white, middle-class) men and to conceal power relations.”</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>Kjerstin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Talking Violence, Constructing Identity. Young Men in Institutional Care</source>. <comment>Linköping Studies in Arts and Science No. 444</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asplund</surname>
<given-names>Stig-Börje</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <source>Läsning Som Identitetsskapande Handling. Gemenskapande Och Utbrytningsförsök I Fordonspojkars Litteratursamtal. Karlstad University Studies, nr. 2010:4</source>. <publisher-loc>Karlstad</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karlstads universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Åström</surname>
<given-names>Lissie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <source>Fäder Och Söner. Bland Män I Tre Generationer</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carlsson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maria</surname>
<given-names>Bangura Arvidsson</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Ifrågasatta Fader. Olika Bilder av Fader till Socialt Utsatta Barn</source>. <publisher-loc>Lund</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institution för socialt arbete</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bekkengen</surname>
<given-names>Lisbeth</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <source>Man Får Välja. Om Föräldraskap Och Föräldraledighet I Arbetsliv Och Familjeliv</source>. <publisher-loc>Malmö</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bengtsson</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frykman</surname>
<given-names>Jonas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1987</year>. <source>Om Maskulinitet. Mannen Som Forskningsobjekt</source>. <comment>JÄMFO rapport no 11</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berg</surname>
<given-names>Lars-Erik</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <source>Den Andre Föräldern. Om Deltidspappor Och Deras Barn</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carlssons</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berggren</surname>
<given-names>Carolina</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>“Labour Market Influence on Recruitment to Higher Education: Gender and Class Perspectives.”</article-title> <source>Higher Education</source> <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bergman</surname>
<given-names>Åsa</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Växa upp Med Musik. Ungdomars Musikanvändande I Skolan Och På Fritiden</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Göteborgs universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bergman</surname>
<given-names>Helena</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hobson</surname>
<given-names>Barbara</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>“Compulsory Fatherhood: The Coding of Fatherhood in the Swedish Welfare State.”</article-title> In <source>Making Men into Fathers: Men, Masculinities and Social Politics of Fatherhood</source>, edited by Barbara Hobson, <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bernhardt</surname>
<given-names>Eva</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldscheider</surname>
<given-names>Calvin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldscheider</surname>
<given-names>Frances</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bjerén</surname>
<given-names>Gunilla</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <source>Immigration, Gender, and Family Transitions to Adulthood in Sweden</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, Boulder, New York, Toronto, Plymouth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press of America</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Björnberg</surname>
<given-names>Ulla</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kollind</surname>
<given-names>Anna-Karin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Individualism and Families: Equality, Autonomy and Togetherness</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Björnsson</surname>
<given-names>Mats</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Kön Och Skolframgång: Tolkningar Och Perspektiv</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Myndigheten för skolutveckling</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burcar</surname>
<given-names>Veronika</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Gestaltningar Av Offererfarenheter. Samtal Med Unga Män Som Utsatts för Brott</source>. <publisher-loc>Sociologiska institutionen vid Lunds universitet. Lund</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Sociology, Lund University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carlsson</surname>
<given-names>Ninni</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Avslöjandets Tid. Kvinnors Bearbetning av Sexuella Övergrepp</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Göteborg Univ</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carrigan</surname>
<given-names>Tim</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, R. W. [Raewyn] Connell and John Lee. <year>1985</year>. <article-title>“Towards a new Sociology of Masculinity.”</article-title> <source>Theory and Society</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connell</surname>
<given-names>R. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> [Raewyn]. <year>1983</year>. <source>Which Way Is Up?</source>. <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allen &amp; Unwin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connell</surname>
<given-names>R.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> [Raewyn]. <year>1995</year>. <source>Masculinities</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connell</surname>
<given-names>R.W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> [Raewyn] and James W. Messerschmidt. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>“Hegemonic Masculinity: Rethinking the Concept.”</article-title> <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dahl</surname>
<given-names>Ulrika</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>“Scener Ur Ett Äktenskap: Jämställdhet Och Heteronormativitet.”</article-title> In <source>Queer Sverige</source>, edited by Don Kulick, <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Natur och Kultur</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dahlström</surname>
<given-names>Edmund</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1962</year>. <source>Kvinnors liv och arbete. Svenska Och Norska Studier av Ett Aktuellt Samhällsproblem</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Studieförbundet Näringsliv och samhälle</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eidevald</surname>
<given-names>Christian</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Det finns Inga Tjejbestämmare: Att Förstå Kön Som Position i Förskolans Vardagsrutiner Och Lek</source>. <publisher-loc>Högskolan i Jönköping</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HLK, Encell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eduards</surname>
<given-names>Maud</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>“Våld Utan Gränser: Om Krig Och Hotad Manlighet”</article-title> <comment>[Violence without borders: about war and threatened manliness]</comment>. In <source>Än Män Då?, Kön och Feminism i Sverige Under 150</source> <source>år</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Svanström</surname>
<given-names>Yvonne</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Östberg</surname>
<given-names>Kjell</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Atlas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>Tim</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <source>Cultures of Masculinity</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Linn</surname>
<given-names>Egeberg Holmgren</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeff</surname>
<given-names>Hearn</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>“Framing ‘men in feminism’: Theoretical Locations, Local Contexts and Practical Passings in Men’s Gender Conscious Positionings on Gender Equality and Feminism.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Gender Studies</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekbrand</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2006</year>. <source>Separationer Och Mäns Våld Mot Kvinnor. [<italic>Separations and men’s violence againstwomen</italic>]. <italic>Göteborg Studies in Sociology 28</italic>
</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Göteborg University, Department of Sociology</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekenstam</surname>
<given-names>Claes</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>“En Historia Om Manlig Gråt.”</article-title> In <source>Rädd Att Falla. Studier i Manlighet</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ekenstam</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frykman</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuosmanen</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ljunggren</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nilsson</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Hedemora</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gidlund</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekenstam</surname>
<given-names>Claes</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frykman</surname>
<given-names>Jonas</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuosmanen</surname>
<given-names>Jari</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ljunggren</surname>
<given-names>Jens</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nilsson</surname>
<given-names>Arne</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds.). <year>1998</year>. <source>Rädd att Falla: Studier i Manlighet</source>. <publisher-loc>Hedemora</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gidlund</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekstrand</surname>
<given-names>Per</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Tarzan och Jane”: <italic>Hur män som sjuksköterskor formar sin identitet</italic>
</source>. <publisher-loc>Uppsala</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Education, Uppsala University</publisher-name>..</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eliasson</surname>
<given-names>Mona</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <source>Mäns Våld Mot Kvinnor, en Kunskapsöversikt om Kvinnomisshandel och Våldtäkt, Dominans och Kontroll</source>. <comment>[Men’s violence to women, an overview on knowledge about women’s battering and rape, dominance and control]</comment> <publisher-name>Stockholm</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Natur och Kultur</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eliasson</surname>
<given-names>Miriam</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isaksson</surname>
<given-names>Kerstin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Laflamme</surname>
<given-names>Lucie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>“Verbal Abuse in School. Constructions of Gender Among 14- to 15-year-Olds.”</article-title> <source>Gender &amp; Education</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eldén</surname>
<given-names>Åsa</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Heder På Liv och Död. Våldsamma Berättelser om Rykten, Oskuld och Heder [Life and death honour</source>. <publisher-loc>Violent stories about reputation, virginity and honour] Uppsala</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sociologiska institutionen, Uppsala Universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eriksson</surname>
<given-names>Henrik</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <source>Den Diplomatiska Punkten. Maskulinitet som Kroppsligt Identitetsskapande Projekt i Svensk Sjuksköterskeutbildning</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Acta Universitatis Gothoburgensis</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eriksson</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>I Skuggan av Pappa. Familjerätten och Hanteringen Av Fäders Våld</source> <source>[In the shadow of Daddy</source>. <publisher-loc>Family law and the handling of fathers’ violence]. Stehag</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Förlags AB Gondolin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ervø</surname>
<given-names>Søren</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003a</year>. <source>Among Men. Moulding Masculinities, Vol. 1</source>. <publisher-loc>Hants</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ervø</surname>
<given-names>Søren</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003b</year>. <source>Bending Bodies. Moulding Masculinities, Vol. 2</source>. <publisher-loc>Hants</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Evaldsson</surname>
<given-names>Ann-Carita</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>“Boys’</article-title> <source>Gossip Telling: Staging Identities and Indexing (unacceptable) Masculine Behavior.” <italic>Text</italic>
</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Florin</surname>
<given-names>Christina</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nilsson</surname>
<given-names>Bengt</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <source>Något Som Liknar en Oblodig Revolution: Jämställdhetens Politisering Under 1960-och 70-talen</source>. <publisher-loc>Umeå</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Umeå universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Folkesson</surname>
<given-names>Per</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <source>Nordisk Mansforskning. En Kartläggning</source>. <publisher-loc>Arbetsrapport Karlstads universitet, Institutionen för samhällsvetenskap. Karlstad</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institutionen för samhällsvetenskap, Karlstad University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forsberg</surname>
<given-names>Lucas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>“Negotiating Involved Fatherhood: Household work, Childcare and Spending time with Children.”</article-title> <source>NORMA: Nordic Journal for Masculinity Studies</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forsberg</surname>
<given-names>Lucas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Involved Parenthood. Everyday Lives of Swedish Middle-Class Families</source>. <comment>Linköping Studies in Arts and Science No. 473</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forsberg</surname>
<given-names>Lucas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>“Editorial: Masculinity Studies as Fetish and the need of a Feminist Imagination.”</article-title> <source>NORMA: Nordic Journal for Masculinity Studies</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Franklin</surname>
<given-names>Cary</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>“The Anti-Stereotyping Principle in Constitutional Sex Discrimination Law.”</article-title> <source>New York University Law Review</source> <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frykman</surname>
<given-names>Jonas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1981</year>. <article-title>“Pure &amp; Rational. The Hygienic Vision: A Study of Cultural Transformation in the 1930’s: the new Man.”</article-title> <source>Ethnologia Scandinavica</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hagström</surname>
<given-names>Charlotte</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <source>Man Blir Pappa. Föräldraskap och Maskulinitet I Förändring</source>. <publisher-loc>Lund</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nordic Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hammarén</surname>
<given-names>Nils</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Förorten i Huvudet. Unga Män om Kön och Sexualitet i det nya Sverige</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Atlas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hammarström</surname>
<given-names>Anne</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hensing</surname>
<given-names>Gunnel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Folkhälsofrågor ur Ett Genusperspektiv: Arbetsmarknad, Maskuliniteter, Medikalisering och Könsrelaterat Våld</source>. <publisher-loc>Östersund</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statens folkhälsoinstitut</publisher-name>. http://www.fhi.se/PageFiles/3160/Genusrapport_R2008_8(1).pdf.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Havung</surname>
<given-names>Margareta</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <source>Anpassning till Rådande Ordning. En Studie av Manliga Förskollärare i Förskoleverksamhet. </source>: <publisher-loc>Malmö</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institutionen för pedagogik, Lärarhögskolan</publisher-name>..</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hearn</surname>
<given-names>Jeff</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>“From Hegemonic Masculinity to the Hegemony of Men.”</article-title> <source>Feminist Theory</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hearn</surname>
<given-names>Jeff</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pringle</surname>
<given-names>Keith</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, with members of CROME. <year>2006</year>. <source>European Perspectives on Men and Masculinities: National and Transnational Approaches</source>. <publisher-loc>Houndmills</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hearn</surname>
<given-names>Jeff</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandberg</surname>
<given-names>Linn</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Older Men, Ageing and Power: Masculinities Theory and Alternative Spatialised Theoretical Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Sextant</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Revue du Groupe Interdisciplinaire D’Etudes sur les Femmes et le Genre</publisher-name> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hellman</surname>
<given-names>Anette</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>“Förskolebarns Konstruktion av Maskuliniteter.”</article-title> In <source>Manlighet i Fokus. En bok om Manliga Pedagoger, Pojkar och Maskulinitetsskapanden i Förskola och Skola</source>, edited by Marie Nordberg, <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hellman</surname>
<given-names>Anette</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008a</year>. <article-title>“Sluta Gnälla som en Bäbis och va’ en Stor Kille Nu! Ålder, Kön och Normalitetsskapanden.”</article-title> In <source>Maskulinitet på Schemat-Pojkar, Flickor och Könsskapande i Förskola och Skola</source>, edited by Marie Nordberg, <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hellman</surname>
<given-names>Anette</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008b</year>. <article-title>“Kan Batman Vara Rosa? Färg, Rörelse och röst Som Markörer Då Förskolebarn Gör Kön.”</article-title> In <source>Maskulinitet på Schemat-Pojkar, Flickor och Könsskapande i Förskola och Skola</source>, edited by Marie Nordberg, <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirdman</surname>
<given-names>Anja</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Den Ensamma Fallosen. Mediala Bilder, Pornografi och Kön</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Atlas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirdman</surname>
<given-names>Yvonne</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1988</year>. <article-title>“Genussystemet-Reflexioner Kring Kvinnors Sociala Underordning.”</article-title> <source>Kvinnnovetenskaplig Tidskrift</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Högberg</surname>
<given-names>Ronny</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Motstånd och Konformitet. Om Manliga Yrkeselevers liv och Identitetsskapande i Relation Till Kärnämnena</source>. <publisher-loc>Linköping</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Linköping University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holm</surname>
<given-names>Ann-Sofie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Relationer i Skolan. En Studie av Feminiteter och Maskuliniteter</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Göteborgs universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmberg</surname>
<given-names>Carin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Med Husbondens Röst, Om Våld Mot Djur i Misshandelsrelationer</source> <source>[With his masters voice</source>: <publisher-loc>On violence to animals in violent relations] Ystad</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kabusa böcker</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmberg</surname>
<given-names>Carin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Enander</surname>
<given-names>Viveka</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Varför Går Hon? Om Misshandlade Kvinnors Uppbrottsprocess</source> <comment>[Why does she leave? About maltreated women’s break up process]</comment> <publisher-loc>Ystad</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kabusa böcker</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmberg</surname>
<given-names>Carin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stjernqvist</surname>
<given-names>Ulrica</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Våldsamt Lika och Olika—Om Våld i Samkönade Parrelationer</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centrum för Genusstudier</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holth</surname>
<given-names>Line</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mellström</surname>
<given-names>Ulf</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>“Revisiting Engineering, Masculinity and Technology Studies: Old Structures with new Openings.”</article-title> <comment>Tvärvetenskaplig konferens kring arbetsliv och arbetsmiljö</comment> <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage> <comment>May</comment>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://media.falf.se/2010/05/Mellstrom.pdf">http://media.falf.se/2010/05/Mellstrom.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jalmert</surname>
<given-names>Lars</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1979</year>. <source>Små Barns Sociala Utveckling: Kritisk Granskning av Forskning</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stockholms universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jalmert</surname>
<given-names>Lars</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <source>Den Svenske Mannen</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tiden</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <source>Den Skulpterade Kroppen</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carlsson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <source>Det Första Könet. Mansforskning som Reflexivt Projekt</source>. <publisher-loc>Malmö</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Faderskapets Omvandlingar: Frånvarons Socialpsykologi</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Daidalos</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klinth</surname>
<given-names>Roger</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>“Caring Fathers: The Ideology of Gender Equality and Masculine Positions.”</article-title> <source>Men and Masculinities</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuosmanen</surname>
<given-names>Jari</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Manlighetens Många Ansikten</source>. <publisher-loc>Malmö</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jonsson</surname>
<given-names>Rickard</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <source>Blatte Betyder Kompis. Om Maskulinitet och Språk i en Högstadieskola</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ordfront</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kalat</surname>
<given-names>Anne-Sofie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>“Läxläsning, Provplugg och Social Status–Vad Gör Elitens Söner i Skolan?”</article-title> In <source>Maskulinitet på Schemat–Pojkar, Flickor och Könsskapande i Förskola och Skola</source>, edited by Marie Nordberg, <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klinth</surname>
<given-names>Roger</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>“Mannen och Den Jämställda Familjen: Mannen i Familjen Speglad Genom Utbildningsprogrammen i Svensk Radio och Tv 1946–1971.”</article-title> In <source>Medier och Modernisering: En Antologi om Utbildningsprogram och Samhällsförändring</source>, edited by Bengt Sandin. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stiftelsen Etermedierna i Sverige</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klinth</surname>
<given-names>Roger</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <source>Göra Pappa Med Barn. Den Svenska Pappapolitiken 1960-1995</source>. <publisher-loc>Umeå</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Boréa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klinth</surname>
<given-names>Roger</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <source>Nya Svenska Fader [The new Swedish father]</source>. <publisher-loc>Umeå</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Borea</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lilieqvist</surname>
<given-names>Jonas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>“Från niding till Sprätt.”</article-title> In <source>Manligt och omanligt i ett historiskt perspektiv, edited by A. M. Berggren, 73–94. Stockholm: Forskningsrådsnämnden Rapport</source> <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liljeström</surname>
<given-names>Rita</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1968</year>. <source>Jämställdhetens Villkor: Män och Kvinnor i Dagens Värld</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sveriges Radio</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lindgren</surname>
<given-names>Gerd</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1992</year>. <source>Doktorer, Systrar och Flickor. Om Informell Makt</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carlsson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lundgren</surname>
<given-names>Eva</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. <source>Våldets Normaliseringsprocess</source> <comment>[The process of normalising the violence]</comment> <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Riksorganisationen för Kvinno-och tjejjourer i Sverige</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Månsdotter</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lundin</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Falkstedt</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hemmingsson</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>“The Association Between Masculinity Rank and Mortality Patterns: A Prospective Study based on the Swedish 1969 Conscript Cohort.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mellström</surname>
<given-names>Ulf</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>“‘Maskulinitet och Teknologi. Män och Deras Maskiner’.”</article-title> In <source>Från Symaskin till Cyborg</source>, edited by Elisabet Sundin and Boel Berner, <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nerenius &amp; Santérus</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mellström</surname>
<given-names>Ulf</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>“Patriarchal Machines and Masculine Embodiment.”</article-title> <source>Science, Technology and Human Values</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>460</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mellström</surname>
<given-names>Ulf</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>“Machines and Masculine Subjectivity, Technology as an Integral part of Men’s Life Experiences.”</article-title> <source>Men and Masculinities</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mellström</surname>
<given-names>Ulf</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>“Nytt Faderskap i Skärningspunkten Mellan Produktion Och Reproduktion?”</article-title> <source>Socialvetenskaplig tidskrift</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moberg</surname>
<given-names>Eva</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1961</year>. <article-title>“Kvinnans Villkorliga Frigivning.”</article-title> In <source>Unga liberlaer. Nio inlägg i idédebatten</source>, edited by Hans Hederberg, <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bonnier</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Myrdal</surname>
<given-names>Alva</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, <year>1938</year>. <source>Vart tar Pappa Vägen? 37 Idun</source> <comment>10 september</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Myrdal</surname>
<given-names>Alva</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Myrdal</surname>
<given-names>Gunnar</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1934</year>. <source>Kris i befolkningsfrågan</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bonniers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nilsson</surname>
<given-names>Arne</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <source>Såna &amp; Riktiga Karlar. Om Manlig Homosexualitet i Göteborg Decennierna Kring Andra Världskriget</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Anamma</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nissen</surname>
<given-names>Jörgen</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>“Det är Klart att det är Grabbar som Håller på Med Datorer! Men varför är det Så?”</article-title> In <source>Från symaskin till cyborg</source>, edited by Elisabet Sundin and Boel Berner, <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nerenius &amp; Santérus</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nobis</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandén</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>“Young Men’s Health: A Balance Between Self-Reliance and Vulnerability in the Light of Hegemonic Masculinity.”</article-title> <source>Contemporary Nurse</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nobis</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandén</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elofsson</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>“Masculinity and Urogenital Cancer: Sensitive Issues in Health Care.”</article-title> <source>Contemporary Nurse</source> <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <source>James Bond i Värmland: manlighetsideal som importvara.Ljusgården</source> <source>16:53–70</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Etnologiska Institutionen, Göteborgs Universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>“Hegemonibegreppet och Hegemonier Inom Mansforskningen.”</article-title> In <source>Hegemoni och Mansforskning. Rapport från Nordiska Mansforskningsworkshopen i Karlstad 19-21/3 1999</source>, edited by Per Folkesson, Marie Nordberg, and Goldina Smirthwaite, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Karlstad</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karlstad universitet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2001a</year>. <article-title>“Teori som Importvara: ’Hegemonisk Maskulinitet’–Ett Teoretiskt Axiom i Svensk Genusforskning med Fokus på Män?”</article-title> In <source>Svensk Genusforskning I Världen. Konferensrapport Örebro 3.11-1-12</source> <volume>2000</volume>, edited by Anna Johansson, <fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nationella sekretariatet för genusforskning</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2001b</year>. <article-title>“Hegemonier Inom Mansforskningsfältet.”</article-title> <source>Fronesis</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>“Jämställdhetens Spjutspets. Rollmodeller, Velournissar och Andra Män i Kvinnoyrken.”</article-title> In <source>Manlighetens Många Ansikten: Fäder, Feminister, Frisörer och Andra Män</source>, edited by Thomas Johansson and Jari Kuosmanen, <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Malmö</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>“Forskning om Män och Maskulinitet.”</article-title> <source>Sociologisk Forskning</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005a</year>. <source>Jämställdhetens Spjutspets?: Manliga Arbetstagare i Kvinnoyrken, Jämställdhet, Maskulinitet, Femininitet och Heteronormativitet</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arkipelag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr98-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie. ed.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2005b</year>. <source>Manlighet i Fokus. En bok om Manliga Pedagoger, Pojkar och Maskulinitetsskapanden i Förskola och Skola</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr99-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>“En Riktig Man Gör Karriär … Diskursbrott, Ambivalenser och Mäns Längtan.”</article-title> In <source>Män i Rörelse. Jämställdhet, Förändring och Social Innovation i Norden</source>, edited by Øystein Gullvåg Holter, <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Hedemora</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gidlund</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr100-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie. ed.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. <source>Maskulinitet på Schemat–pojkar, Flickor och Könsskapande i Förskola och Skola</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr101-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hellman</surname>
<given-names>Anette</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saar</surname>
<given-names>Tomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>“Deconstructing the Normative Boy in Pre-School and School and in Masculinity Research.”</article-title> <source>Paper presented at the conference Heterofactory, Norrköping</source> <volume>13-15</volume>
<issue>/6</issue>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr102-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>2007</surname>
<given-names>Magnus Mörck.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>“Maskulinitet och Mode Som Genusvetenskaplig och Etnografisk Utmaning.”</article-title> <source>Tidskrift för genusvetenskap</source> <volume>1-2</volume>:<year>2007</year>:<fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr103-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordberg</surname>
<given-names>Marie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saar</surname>
<given-names>Tomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>“Moralisk Panik Ersätter Kulturanalys.”</article-title> <source>KRUT: Kritisk utbildningstidskrift</source> <volume>120</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr104-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Öqvist</surname>
<given-names>Anna</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Skolvardagens Genusdramaturgi: En Studie av hur Feminiteter och Maskuliniteter görs i år 5 med ett Särskilt Fokus på Benämningar som hora och Kärring</source>. <publisher-loc>Luleå</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Luleå University of Technology</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr105-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Palme</surname>
<given-names>Olof</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1972</year>. <article-title>“The Emancipation of Man.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Social Issues</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr106-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pavlova</surname>
<given-names>Anastasia</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>c. 2003</year>. <source>Shaping Equal Gender Policy in Sweden in 1960s-1970s</source>. <comment>Institute of History, Russian Academy of Sciences, Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rosadoc.be/site/rosa/english/pdf/athena/pavlova.pdf">http://www.rosadoc.be/site/rosa/english/pdf/athena/pavlova.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr107-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Petersson</surname>
<given-names>Monica</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <source>Att Genuszappa på säker Eller Minerad Mark. Hem-och Konsumentkunskap ur ett Könsperspektiv</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Göteborg University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr108-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Plantin</surname>
<given-names>Lars</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Månsson</surname>
<given-names>Sven-Axel</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kearney</surname>
<given-names>Jeremy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>“Talking and doing Fatherhood: On Fatherhood and Masculinity in Sweden and England.”</article-title> <source>Fathering</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr109-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pringle</surname>
<given-names>Keith</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>“Swedish Welfare Responses to Ethnicity: The Case of Children and their Families.”</article-title> <source>European Journal of Social Work</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr110-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Regnér</surname>
<given-names>Margareta</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>“När den goda Viljan Finns: Om Frånvarande Fader i Kontaktfamiljsinsatsen.”</article-title> <source>Socialvetenskaplig tidskrift</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr111-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Robertsson</surname>
<given-names>Hans</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Maskulinitetskonstruktion, Yrkesidentitet, Könssegregering och Jämställdhet</source> <source>[Constructions of masculinity, work identity, gender segregation and equality] <italic>Arbetsliv i Omvandling</italic>
</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arbetslivsinstitutet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr112-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sandberg</surname>
<given-names>Linn</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Man nog för jämställdhet: Man nog för jämställdhet?: en studie av Järva Mansmottagning och omvandlingar av hegemonisk maskulinitet i jämställdhetsdiskursernas tidevarv</article-title>. <comment>D-uppsats i Genusvetenskap, Södertörns högskola</comment>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diva-portal.org/diva/getDocument?urn_nbn_se_sh_diva-535-1__fulltext.pdf">http://www.diva-portal.org/diva/getDocument?urn_nbn_se_sh_diva-535-1__fulltext.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr113-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Statens offentliga utredningar (SOU)</collab>. <year>2001</year>. <source>Välfärdsbokslut för 1990-Talet. Slutbetänkande Från Kommittén Välfärdsbokslut. Statens Offentliga utredningar 2001:79</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fritzes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr114-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Statens offentliga utredningar (SOU)</collab>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Ett Slag i Luften, En Utredning om Myndigheter, Mansvåld och Makt [A punch in the air. An investigation on authorities, men’s violence and power] Eldén, Åsa, Tanja Joelsson, Peter Söderström, Maria Wendt Höjer</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fritzes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr115-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Statistics Sweden (SCB)</collab>. <year>2008</year>. <source>På tal om kvinnor och män: Lathund om jämställdhet</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistics Sweden</publisher-name>..</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr116-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Steen</surname>
<given-names>Anne-Lie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Mäns Våld mot Kvinnor–ett Diskursivt Slagfält</source> <source>[Men’s violence against women–a discursive battlefield]. Research Report No. 131 Department of Sociology</source>. <publisher-loc>Göteborg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Göteborg University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr117-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Steorn</surname>
<given-names>Patrik</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <source>Naknamän. Maskulinitet och Kreativitet i Svensk Bildkultur 1900-1915</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norstedts Akademiska förlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr118-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wahl</surname>
<given-names>Anna. ed.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>1995</year>. <source>Men’s Perceptions of Women and Management</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fritzes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr119-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wahl</surname>
<given-names>Anna</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holgersson</surname>
<given-names>Charlotte</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>“Male Managers’ Reactions to Gender Diversity Activities in Organizations.”</article-title> In <source>Individual Diversity and Psychology in Organizations</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Marilyn</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> Davidson and Sandra L. Fielden, <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr120-1097184X11432113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wester</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Hålla Ordning, Men inte Överordning” Köns-och Maktperspektiv på Uppförandenormer i Svenska Klassrumskulturer</source>. <publisher-loc>Umeå</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Umeå University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>