<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OSS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sposs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Organization Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0170-8406</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3044</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0170840613479235</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0170840613479235</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Role of Ideological Radicalism and Resource Homogeneity in Social Movement Organization Campaigns against Corporations</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>de Bakker</surname><given-names>Frank G. A.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>den Hond</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Brayden</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yaziji</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0170840613479235">IMD, Switzerland</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>Jonathan P.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0170840613479235">Villanova University, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0170840613479235">Jonathan P. Doh, Villanova University, School of Business, Villanova University, 800 Lancaster Ave, Villanova, PA 19085, USA. Email: <email>jonathan.doh@villanova.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>5-6</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Social Movements, Civil Society and Corporations</issue-title><fpage>755</fpage>
<lpage>780</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>There is growing interest in the interactions among different sectors of civil society and the distinct organizational forms—both formal and informal—that occupy and transcend them. At the same time, the complementary nature of social movement theory and institutionalism is increasingly recognized by scholars seeking to understand these interactions, particularly the relational exchanges between social movements and organizations, including business corporations. In this study, we seek to contribute to this emergent literature by proposing a more complete theoretical and practical understanding of how the radicalism of social movement organizations influences the nature of the resource providers upon which they depend and, as a consequence, their overall strategy and tactics. Specifically, we draw on a survey of social movement organizations to explore the notion that ideological radicalism leads to more homogenous resource providers for SMOs in their campaigns against corporations, and that this, in turn, influences their selection of corporate targets and the tactics they use to influence these targets. We find evidence for our intuitions and describe how they may augment existing understanding of the strategies and continued existence of unconventional SMOs.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>campaigns</kwd>
<kwd>ideology</kwd>
<kwd>radicalism</kwd>
<kwd>resource mobilization</kwd>
<kwd>social movements</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0170840613479235" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>On November 17, 2009, Russell Athletics, one of the United States’ leading sportswear companies owned by Fruit of the Loom (itself a Berkshire-Hathaway portfolio company), along with a coalition of student advocacy organizations led by United Students Against Sweatshops (USAS), announced that the company would rehire 1,200 workers in Honduras who had lost their jobs when it closed their factory soon after the workers had unionized. Russell also agreed to provide access for the union to all of its apparel plants in Honduras for union organizing drives in which the company would remain neutral. According to a November 18, 2009, USAS press release, this was an “unprecedented victory for labor rights” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0170840613479235">USAS, 2009</xref>). This example is illustrative of the persistence of relatively small, unconventional and resource-poor social movement organizations and their campaigns against corporations. How can we explain the existence of such organizations when the pressures to conform and the potential benefits of conformity—greater resources, greater legitimacy and acceptance, and organizational longevity—seem so obvious?</p>
<p>A starting point is the emerging literature by scholars that has explored the interactions among different sectors of civil society and the distinct organizational forms—both formal and informal—that occupy and transcend them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0170840613479235">Davis &amp; Thompson, 1994</xref>). The complementary nature of social movement theory and institutionalism is increasingly recognized by scholars seeking to understand these interactions, particularly the relational exchanges between social movements and organizations, including business corporations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0170840613479235">Clemens, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0170840613479235">Clemens &amp; Cook, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond &amp; de Bakker, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0170840613479235">McAdam, McCarthy, &amp; Zald, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0170840613479235">McAdam &amp; Scott, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0170840613479235">Rao, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0170840613479235">Rao, Morrill, &amp; Zald, 2000</xref>). One subset of actors that have been credited with generating pressure for collective challenges to authority in political or social domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0170840613479235">Snow, 2002</xref>) are nongovernmental watchdog or advocacy groups, some of which could be considered as organizational carriers of social movements, known in the sociology literature as social movement organizations (SMOs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0170840613479235">Lipschutz, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0170840613479235">McAdam &amp; Scott, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0170840613479235">Zald &amp; Ash, 1966</xref>).</p>
<p>In examining these SMOs, the social movement literature has focused on how the quantity and type of resources affect organizations’ strategies and tactics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0170840613479235">Gamson, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0170840613479235">Jenkins, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0170840613479235">McCarthy &amp; Zald, 1977</xref>) and how the presence and nature of political opportunity structures, framing, and organizational infrastructures create the conditions for the emergence of social movements and their potential impact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0170840613479235">Jenkins, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0170840613479235">McAdam, McCarthy, &amp; Zald, 1996</xref>). Although both of these traditions have generated valuable insights and deepened understandings of social movements, they have historically focused on how social movements engage governments in their change efforts, most often by lobbying public officials to enable or restrict certain types of activities.</p>
<p>Increasingly, however, SMOs are engaged in direct petitions toward corporations, what has been sometimes termed “private politics,” defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0170840613479235">Baron (2003</xref>, p. 31) as “situations of conflict and their resolution without reliance on the law or government.” Moreover, this research has not fully resolved some of the contradictions inherent in the growth and impact of these SMOs. For example, many of these organizations initially lie outside the ideological mainstream and therefore are unable to access resources available to more mainstream organizations. In the quest for resources, however, some SMOs may be drawn toward more conventional tactics and, as a result, lose some of their distinctive character and the non-pecuniary support upon which they have come to rely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0170840613479235">Sell &amp; Prakash, 2004</xref>). Yet, many relatively small and poorly resourced SMOs have retained and reinforced their core mission and repertoires, and even moved toward ever more radical tactics. This presents us with fundamental questions that we address in this paper: How do we explain the existence and persistence of small, resource-poor and ideologically unconventional social movement organizations (SMOs)? Further, how might their continued dedication to unconventional ideologies be influenced by the nature of their resource providers and how might that persistent commitment to “radicalism” influence their tactics and target selection?</p>
<p>While resource mobilization theory has provided important insights regarding how the quantity and type of resource affects social movement formation, processes, and outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0170840613479235">McAdam et al., 1996</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0170840613479235">Jenkins’ (1983</xref>, p. 549) contention nearly three decades ago that “collective interests are assumed to be relatively unproblematic and to exist prior to mobilization, instead of being socially constructed and created by the mobilization process” remains a shortcoming of much social movement literature.</p>
<p>In this study, we respond, in part, to these gaps in the existing literature by developing a theory that ideological radical SMOs rely on homogenous resource providers, and that their commitment to ideological radicalism influences their choice of tactics and targets. Drawing from a large survey of SMOs campaigning against corporations, we propose that ideological radicalism increases the ideological homogeneity of resource providers and that this, in turn, removes or reduces institutionally defined norms of conformity, thus encouraging the SMO to pursue more contra-institutional tactics and to target corporations it views as representative of broader institutional interests.</p>
<p>We make several contributions in this paper. First, we add to the literature on the strategic considerations of organizations responsible for generating pressure for social change through advocacy toward corporations and explore some of the processes that contribute to their influence and impact. More specifically, we introduce the notion of institutionally circumscribed resource niches and suggest how a single narrow institutional resource niche may provide institutional challengers with an advantage over dominant organizations saddled with the constraints and costs imposed by what we call <italic>institutional multivocality</italic>, i.e., the requirement to meet or “speak to” multiple and sometimes conflicting demands of stakeholders with distinct values, goals, and ideologies. Finally, we show how the integration of institutional and social movement literature can enrich our understanding of contemporary interactions among social movements and organizations.</p>
<p>The paper is organized as follows. First, we review some of the relevant social movement and institutional literatures and illustrate how they can inform the phenomenon of social movement advocacy and campaigning. We identify several remaining research puzzles and develop a series of hypotheses that emerge from our theoretical review and analysis to address these puzzles. We then explore these questions via a survey of SMOs and empirical analysis. Finally, we discuss implications of our findings, identify its limitations, and propose suggestions for future institutional and social movement research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0170840613479235">
<title>SMO Campaigns against Corporations: Ideology, Resources, and Tactics</title>
<p>Social movement theory has evolved substantially in recent years to incorporate new phenomena and to link social movement processes and dynamics to organizational theory. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0170840613479235">Touraine (1988</xref>, p. 26) argues that the term social movement should be reserved for “truly central conflicts” which call into question the social control over historicity, researchers have begun examining the role of organizations in social movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0170840613479235">Davis &amp; Thompson, 1994</xref>) and proposed that some social movements may be viewed as organizations in and of themselves, hence the term social movement organizations (SMOs). Indeed, corporations have become targets of specific social movement campaigns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0170840613479235">della Porta, Kriesi, &amp; Rucht, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0170840613479235">Yaziji &amp; Doh, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>A subset of this literature has integrated the social movement tradition regarding SMO tactics with more contemporary research on activist groups to inform the process and outcome of SMO actions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0170840613479235">King and Soule (2007)</xref>, for example, have explored extra-institutional social movement tactics (protests) and their impact on share prices while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond and de Bakker (2007)</xref> theorized around the different tactics employed by activist groups in relation to their ideology and the particular stage in the process of institutional change. Here we build on and integrate this research to inform our theoretical intuition regarding the relationships among SMO ideology, the structure of resource provision, and SMO target and tactic selection.</p>
<p>Social movement (SM) scholars have historically described the influence toolkit of SM activism by looking at four components (for a summary, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0170840613479235">della Porta &amp; Diani, 1999</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0170840613479235">McAdam et al., 1996</xref>). The first component is “framing processes” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0170840613479235">Benford &amp; Snow, 2000</xref>). Framing is defined as the “conscious strategic efforts by groups of people to fashion shared understandings of the world and of themselves that legitimate and motivate collective action” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0170840613479235">McAdam et al., 1996</xref>, p. 6). The second component is “mobilizing structures,” that is, how the movement (or activist group) has organized itself to draw upon the resources of its members and supporters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0170840613479235">McAdam et al., 1996</xref>, p. 3). The third component is “repertoires” of actions (or contention), which correspond to organizational routines developed over time and used to carry out the goals of the organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0170840613479235">della Porta &amp; Diani, 1999</xref>, pp. 165–192; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0170840613479235">Tilly, 1979</xref>). These repertoires reflect the feasible actions that the organization can undertake, given its current resources and acquired expertise, as well as the cultural biases of the organization and cognitive biases of its members. The fourth component is the “opportunities” or “opportunity structure” provided by the specific environment in which the social movement is embedded and the three other components are used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0170840613479235">della Porta &amp; Diani, 1999</xref>, p. 223; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0170840613479235">McAdam et al., 1996</xref>), enabling certain options as well as excluding others within the organization’s repertoire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0170840613479235">Djelic &amp; Quack, 2003</xref>, p. 18). Relevant to this SM research stream, SM and management scholars have concurrently converged in examination of corporations as targets of specific social movements campaigns, often those involving labor practices, human rights or genetically modified foods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0170840613479235">de Bakker &amp; den Hond, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0170840613479235">della Porta et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0170840613479235">Yaziji &amp; Doh, 2009</xref>) and exploring the connections among organizational ideology and tactics in shaping the nature of SMO campaigns.</p>
<p>A specific, common form of strategic pressure for institutional change is the de-legitimation/deinstitutionalization campaign (hereafter, simply campaign) by SMOs against corporations. These campaigns are efforts by proactive organizations to de-legitimize a particular corporation or identifiable set of corporations and, potentially, weaken or restrict the domain of a particular institution. Well-known examples of such campaigns include those against McDonald’s environmental/sustainability practice, Monsanto’s production of genetically modified products, Nike’s suppliers’ labor practices in Southeast Asia, various pharmaceutical companies’ AIDS drug pricing and patent enforcement in developing countries, Starkist Tuna’s suppliers’ catch methods, and Nestlé’s suppliers’ destruction of rainforests. Perhaps the most cited modern case of such a campaign was the (successful) effort by Greenpeace to force Shell to backtrack from its plans to sink the <italic>Brent Spar</italic> offshore oil rig (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0170840613479235">Giugni, 1998</xref>, p. 373). A critical insight in understanding SMO campaigns against corporations is to recognize that they often have two simultaneous goals—de-legitimation of the targeted firm, and deinstitutionalization of a dominant institutional logic. As den Hond and de Bakker note (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">2007</xref>, p. 902), “Greenpeace clearly indicated that its protest was not only directed against the intended disposal of this particular decommissioned oil storage platform but against the very principle that oil platforms could be sunk into deep-sea ridges; according to Greenpeace, the world’s oceans are not dumping sites.” Hence, a defining feature of these campaigns is that they often operate at both the organizational and the institutional levels and the campaigning organization’s actions are designed to simultaneously de-legitimize the targeted organization and change the institutional structure. Therefore, for our purposes, institutions represent dominant governance or social structures supporting firms or other mainstream organizations.</p>
<p>Our goal is to unite and integrate what have primarily been distinct and disparate constructs. We believe there is a connection among the ideological focus of SMOs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond &amp; de Bakker, 2007</xref>), the nature of their resource providers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0170840613479235">Jenkins &amp; Eckert, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0170840613479235">McAdam, 1982</xref>), and the tactics and targets they select (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond &amp; de Bakker, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0170840613479235">Gamson, 1990</xref>) in which homogeneity of resource providers is independently associated with ideological radicalism of the SMO, and that radicalism affects the operations and strategies of SMOs by removing or reducing institutionally defined norms and providing the SMO greater freedom from institutional constraints in the tactics in which it engages and the targets it selects.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0170840613479235">
<title>Organizational Ideological Radicalism and the Ideological Homogeneity of Resource Providers</title>
<p>An organization’s norms, values, and evaluative judgments can be considered to be the organization’s ideology. While definitions of “ideology” differ, we adopt John Wilson’s non-pejorative and widely referenced definition: “a set of beliefs about the social world and how it operates, containing statements about the rightness of certain social arrangements and what action would be undertaken in light of those statements…An ideology is both a cognitive map of sets of expectations and a scale of values in which standards and imperatives are proclaimed” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0170840613479235">Wilson, 1973</xref>, pp. 91–92).</p>
<p>We define organizational ideological radicalism as the extent to which an organization’s beliefs and values about the focal issue are out of alignment with the dominant institutions of its societal system (which is often coextensive with the state). Thus, radicalism is relative both to the issue and its society. An organization can be ideologically radical in terms of one focal issue, but mainstream in terms of another. For instance, the Animal Liberation Front is ideologically radical in the United States in terms of its values with regards to animal rights, but it is ideologically mainstream or neutral (admittedly not the same thing) with regard to, say, wealth distribution in society, or gender issues. Similarly, radicalism is relative to the reference society. The Socialist Party in the USA is more ideologically radical (relative to the range and distribution of the beliefs and values of the United States at large) than is the Socialist Party in France (relative to the range and distribution of the beliefs and values in France).</p>
<p>Ideological radicalism—consisting of norms, values, and beliefs—is essentially cognitive in nature, with both descriptive (how things are) and normative (how things ought to be) elements. Yet ideological radicalism may also be associated with an emotional component, which we define as <italic>ideological fervor</italic>, that is, the intensity of the sentiment<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0170840613479235">1</xref></sup> toward the focal set of social, economic, or political issues. We can conceive of organizational ideological fervor, with no additional ontological baggage, simply as the mean of individual members’ ideological fervor toward the focal social, economic, or political issues of the organization. (See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0170840613479235">Kelly &amp; Barsade, 2001</xref>, for a defense of group-level emotion constructs.) Examples of ideological fervor in the given context would include antipathy toward particular behavior (e.g., clear-cutting of forests), a particular corporation, an industry or an entire socio-economic system. It could also include positive sentiments regarding, for example, a different distribution of wealth, protected forests, animal welfare, etc.</p>
<p>It is worth clarifying that the organizational or individual pursuit of other-oriented goods does not contradict the economic view of human behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0170840613479235">Arrow, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0170840613479235">Becker, 1974</xref>), and is compatible with the notion that “altruistic” behavior actually yields for the actor various psychological private goods including maintenance of self-esteem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0170840613479235">Baumeister, 1998</xref>), empathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0170840613479235">Batson, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0170840613479235">Clore &amp; Ortney, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0170840613479235">Eisenberg &amp; Fabes, 1991</xref>), a sense of purpose, moral indignation, a sense of duty, guilt avoidance, and desire for social approval. Some set of these psychological drivers likely underlies and contributes to ideological fervor.</p>
<p>The resources that are potentially accessible to an SMO are restricted to those small niches that are controlled by individuals or organizations that share the SMO’s ideology and who support the goals pursued by the SMO. That is, the resource providers to the SMOs—be they volunteers, donors, or employees—are more or less aligned ideologically in terms of the institutional values and objectives that the SMO is working to realize. Given the wide ideological range of possible organizations to which they could contribute, the suppliers of capital and labor to a particular SMO will tend to be relatively homogeneous in their support of the ideological goals of the SMO; after all, if their views diverge from that of the SMO, they could easily direct their resources elsewhere. We posit that <italic>the fact that the SMO is dedicated to undermining a dominant institution, while limiting the pool of available resources, simultaneously ensures that the SMO has a relatively homogeneous set of individuals and organizations upon which it is resource dependent.</italic> There are four reasons why organizational radicalism, while foreclosing support from the vast majority or resources that are available to more mainstream organizations, tends to increase the ideological homogeneity of the resource providers it does manage to attract.</p>
<p>First, the higher the levels of social sanction and political alienation the more radical are an individual’s ideology and political activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0170840613479235">Finifter, 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0170840613479235">Olsen, 1968</xref>). As a result, there will tend to be a higher self-selection mechanism by the individual in choosing to support a radical SMO. They will only help out if they are strongly aligned philosophically with the organization. Second, at the organizational level, because of this social sanction and the fact that they are in the minority, supporters of radical organizations tend to feel they are engaged in a David versus Goliath battle, and they will tend to have a high level of “us-against-them” thinking and engage in groupthink and minimize any <italic>ex ante</italic> philosophical differences among the supporters. In short, they will tend to close ranks in the face of the opposition. Third, at the individual level, supporters will tend to identify with the organization the more radical the organization. An identity is a set of logically connected propositions that a person uses to describe himself/herself to himself/herself or others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0170840613479235">Rowley &amp; Moldoveanu, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0170840613479235">Klandersmans (1984)</xref> used such an approach to argue that SMOs can develop a collective identity that expresses their shared interests and goals. This collective identification provides as a basis for individual commitment and sense of solidarity and minimizes perceived differences in ideologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0170840613479235">Ashforth, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0170840613479235">Ashforth &amp; Mael, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, radical organizations simply tend to be smaller and have fewer resource providers and thus fewer dependencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0170840613479235">Pfeffer &amp; Salancik, 1978</xref>). For example, the moderate environmental organization WWF has a wide range of resource providers—from individuals, to governments, to corporate partners. Managing the resulting required multivocality greatly limits the range of possible action. This can be compared to groups such as the Earth Liberation Front, a radical and underground environmental SMO that only needs to satisfy its volunteer direct action members. This small and narrow range of resource providers will tend to decrease the chance for ideological conflict among the Earth Liberation Front’s resource providers.</p>
<p>Based on these arguments, we propose the following hypothesis:</p>
<list id="list1-0170840613479235" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>Hypothesis 1:</bold> The greater the ideological radicalism of an SMO, the greater will be the institutional homogeneity of its resource providers.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0170840613479235">
<title>Resources, Radicalism, Tactics, and Targets</title>
<p>The resource mobilization school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0170840613479235">McCarthy &amp; Zald, 1977</xref>) proposed that the increasing success of SMs in the 1960s and 1970s could be attributed to the growing professionalism and changing resource base of SMOs such that these new “professional” SMOs resembled more established organizations and drew their resources from external or “conscience” constituencies. One consequence of this process was that professional SMOs were less accountable to their traditional constituencies, came to be viewed as more mainstream organizations, and, according to critics, lost their fundamental character and potentially their efficacy as distinct institutional actors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0170840613479235">McAdam, 1982</xref>). In extending research to more contemporary SMOs, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond and de Bakker (2007)</xref> focused on the nature of SMO ideology and how that ideology influences tactic selection at different points in the deinstitutionalization–reinstitutionalization cycle. They contended that, in comparison to more reformist groups, activists are more focused on the deinstitutionalization (versus reinstitutionalization) process, use tactics aimed at material damage and material and symbolic gain within an alternative field frame, are more likely to challenge proactive firms (whereas reformative groups are more likely to challenge laggard firms and work with proactive firms), and that the efficacy of joint efforts by radical and reformative activist groups in reinstitutionalization is enhanced if radical groups are constrained in applying tactics aimed at material damage. Again, while not addressing the resource issue per se, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond and de Bakker’s (2007)</xref> conceptual assertions offer justification for why more radical SMOs may be inclined to persist in their ideological commitment in both scope of attention (deinstitutionalization) and tactics (material damage/gain), despite pressures to do otherwise.</p>
<p>Tactics can be differentiated by (a) the degree to which tactics use existing political, legal, and regulatory institutions to attain the ends sought, and (b) how broadly accepted the tactics are within the community at large. For instance, lawsuits, lobbying of regulators, and lobbying of politicians are tactics which can be described as “highly institutional” along these dimensions. Press conferences, rallies, and marches might be considered “institutionally neutral” in that they rely less on political, legal, and regulatory institutions, but do not contravene these institutions. Finally, civil disobedience, direct action to disrupt businesses and streets, destruction of property, and violence are all tactics which, generally being illegal, contravene institutions and can be labeled contra-institutional.</p>
<p>Contra-institutional tactics have a number of attributes that make them more attractive as an option for ideologically radical organizations than for ideologically mainstream or moderate organizations. First, these tactics tend to be less resource-demanding. An individual or group of people, with little or no training, capital or networks, can engage in civil disobedience, direct action, and violence. By contrast, political and regulative lobbying, for example, tends to require established networks among institutional players such as politicians and regulators. Radical organizations, at odds with the dominant institutions, might be less inclined to have these networks than mainstream or moderate organizations. To the extent that radical organizations are often relatively resource-poor in terms of capital and networks into the dominant institutions, radical tactics become relatively more attractive.</p>
<p>Positive feedback systems will tend to reinforce this mechanism, as the use of radical tactics may tend to isolate the radical organization from more mainstream sources of capital as well as from key players in the dominant institutions. The mainstream holders of capital and individuals ensconced in institution networks have their own resource dependencies, which are likely also within the dominant institutions, and thus will tend to avoid jeopardizing their own legitimacy within their field by providing support to radical organizations. Mainstream and moderate advocacy organizations will tend to have more access to—and, importantly, reliance on—resources housed within the dominant institutional context, and thus will tend to avoid legitimacy-threatening radical tactics. Radical organizations, being less reliant on these dominant-institution resources, will be free to pursue these radical tactics.</p>
<p>Additionally, radical ideologies may justify and even demand radical tactics more easily than more moderate ideologies. For example, many of the members of People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals take seriously ethical theories that may <italic>demand</italic> radical tactics. Some are ethical utilitarians that believe that we must maximize the welfare of all sentient beings and that an animal’s suffering is as important as a human’s welfare. Others are rights-theorists who believe that if highly mentally handicapped humans have whatever attributes give them rights, then higher animals that share those capacities also have similar rights. Thus, from this perspective, genocides are occurring regularly and whatever means necessary should be employed to stop them. Similarly, internally consistent reasoning may lead some pro-life groups to sanction, even if not publicly, violence against abortion practitioners. Drawing on the theoretical predictions of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond and de Bakker (2007)</xref> and that of observational insights described above, we propose the following:</p>
<list id="list2-0170840613479235" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>Hypothesis 2:</bold> The more radical the SMO, the more it will tend to use contra-institutional tactics.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Hypothesis 3</bold>: The more radical the SMO, the less it will tend to use institution-dependent tactics.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>A component of some campaigns is that they explicitly target an organization that is broadly representative of a widespread industry practice or broader ideological position. We term these initiatives as <italic>institutional proxy campaigns</italic> in which opposing institutions generate a proxy conflict between organizations that strategically interact to promote, sustain, or represent the opposing institutions. So, for example, José Bové’s anti-globalization farmers’ union, the Confédération Paysanne, has physically attacked and destroyed McDonald’s restaurants and Monsanto crops, primarily because these corporations were seen as representatives and vectors of the institutions of laissez-faire free trade and globalization. In the USAS/Russell Athletics conflict described in the Introduction, Russell appears to have been selected as a target, in part, because it could be used as an example for other sportswear companies.</p>
<p>The degree of ideological radicalism within the organization affects the direction of institutional pressure generated by advocacy organizations. Mainstream advocacy organizations, being ideologically in harmony with the dominant institutions of their environments, will tend to be institutionally conservative, resisting institutional change and/or being a source of normative pressure for isomorphism. By contrast, more radical organizations will tend push for institutional change and pushing other organizations away from isomorphism within the dominant institutional paradigm.</p>
<p>The ideological bearing among advocacy organizations will have implications for which corporations they target. Ideologically mainstream organizations will tend to target those organizations that fail to sufficiently conform to dominant institutional standards of appropriate behavior. In a recent example, the local community, led by the advocacy organization Democracy Resource Center, protested when Tyson Foods proposed building chicken feed barns close to a cemetery in Hickman County, Kentucky; the complaint against Tyson was for failing to be sufficiently respectful of the dead.</p>
<p>Generally the goal in such campaigns is to convince the critical players that the target is in violation of either mainstream normative or regulative standards. In the case of alleged normative violations, appeals to emotion or conscience will often be employed. In cases of alleged regulative violations, a more legalistic argument will have to be made in terms of questions of fact and law. Moderate organizations, having the goal of moderate institutional change, will tend more than mainstream organizations to target corporations as a means of highlighting to a broader audience why the dominant institution needs moderate adjustment. A classic example of this type of campaign was the campaign started by Ralph Nader’s book <italic>Unsafe at Any Speed</italic> which primarily targeted GM and its Corvair automobile. As is described on one of Nader’s websites:<disp-quote>
<p>The chief target of the book was General Motors’ “sporty” Corvair, whose faulty rear suspension system made it possible to skid violently and roll over. The corporate negligence that had produced the various Corvair defects, said Nader, was “one of the greatest acts of industrial irresponsibility in the present century.” More generally, Nader’s book documented how Detroit habitually subordinated safety to style and marketing concerns. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nader.org/history/bollier_section_1.html">http://www.nader.org/history/bollier_section_1.html</ext-link>, September 20, 2003)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In such campaigns where the goal is moderate institutional change, the targeted corporation is used as a case-in-point of why common industry practices need to change, because they are out of compliance with either normative or regulative institutional norms or values. A common rhetorical tactic is to extend extreme examples as being representative of a more general phenomenon. Thus, moderate organizations will also tend to target corporations that demonstrate most vividly the implied normative or regulative violations.</p>
<p>Finally, ideologically radical advocacy organizations, interested in fundamental political, economic, or social change, will be more likely than either mainstream or moderate organizations to target corporations, not because they fail to conform to dominant institutional standards, <italic>but precisely because they do</italic>. In such cases, targets will be more likely to be targeted because they are taken as representative of an institution. As in the case of campaigns designed for moderate industry change, targets are often chosen for highlighting the problematic aspect of the institutional system. For example, the McInformation Network’s campaign against McDonald’s is equally explicit about its larger goal in targeting McDonald’s:<disp-quote>
<p>Yes, we appreciate that McDonald’s only sell hamburgers and loads of other corporations are just as bad. But that’s not the point. They have been used as a symbol of all multinationals and big business relentlessly pursuing their profits at the expense of anything that stands in their way. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mcspotlight.org/help.html">http://www.mcspotlight.org/help.html</ext-link>, December, 2002)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Taken together, the above discussion indicates how the degree of ideological radicalism will influence the criteria by which advocacy organizations choose the targets of their campaigns and suggests the following formal hypothesis:</p>
<list id="list3-0170840613479235" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>Hypothesis 4</bold>: In selecting a corporation to target, the more ideologically radical the advocacy organizations, the more heavily it will weigh the degree to which the corporation is seen by the advocacy organization as representative of fundamental political, social, or economic institutions.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0170840613479235">
<title>Research Approach and Findings</title>
<sec id="section6-0170840613479235">
<title>Defining and Identifying Subjects</title>
<p>In this study we constrain the population to “ideologically driven organizations” as opposed to “interest-driven organizations” in order to minimize confounding variables and unobserved heterogeneity in the sample. We define ideologically driven organizations as those organizations in which the primary goal of the organization is an other-oriented good or public good of which very little is captured by the contributors, members, and owners of the organization. This can be contrasted with “interest-driven” organizations, where the primary goal of the organization is the creation of private goods that are distributed among the contributors, members, and owners of the organization.</p>
<p>Examples of ideologically driven advocacy organizations would be People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals (PETA), where improving animal welfare and respecting animal rights are seen as the primary goal of the organization, and Sweatshop Watch, whose main goal is improvement of labor conditions in textile factories in the developing world, and whose members are almost exclusively in the developed world and not employed in textile industries.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0170840613479235">
<title>Variable Definition and Construction</title>
<p>We consider pools of resources as being attached to particular organizations, such that these resources are preferentially available to those organizations that conform to the given institution’s demands. In the prior section, we defined institutional homogeneity of resource providers (or “homogeneity” for ease of reference) as the degree to which resource providers share common institutional norms and values, i.e., the extent to which they are in the same institutional “niche.”</p>
<p>SMOs are, by definition, working against the mainstream values and beliefs of their societies. By being dedicated to institutional change, the agents tend to have a relatively small institutionally circumscribed resource pool from which to draw. Most of the resources in the environment will tend to be withheld from SMOs since most of the individuals and organizations that control these resources will be loath, all things being equal, to provide resources to organizations with which they are at ideological loggerheads. The resources that are potentially accessible to SMOs are restricted to those small niches that are controlled by individuals or organizations that share their ideology and who support the institutional change being pursued by the SMO. The descriptions of SMOs that campaign against corporations are based on interviews, a case study, and a survey.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0170840613479235">
<title>Sample and Data Collection</title>
<p>The sample frame from which we drew consisted of SMOs that describe themselves as having waged campaigns against corporations in the last five years and who were not part of a labor group. (This last criterion was used to avoid confounding interests and ideological motivations.) There is no pre-existing, exhaustive list of such organizations; the formal, legal, and tax status of these organizations varies considerably. The organizations range from well-established 501(c)4 and 501(c)3 organizations in the US (though 501(c)3 organizations are not supposed to engage in lobbying or advocacy) to loosely organized, cell-based organizations engaging in illegal activities and operating underground.</p>
<p>Thus, the first task was to identify the population and sample. Two methods were used in order to increase reliability and coverage through triangulation. The first method was based on a web-based snowballing process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0170840613479235">Erickson, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0170840613479235">Erickson &amp; Nosanchuk, 1983</xref>). Issues of bias in the snowballing process described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0170840613479235">Erickson (1981)</xref> were minimized through 21 separate and unique snowball starting points. The first step was to identify advocacy organizations that were central and prominent in networks of advocacy groups. As a result of numerous interviews and the case study, the first author was quite familiar with some of the most prominent advocacy groups that challenge firms across a wide range of issues including various environmental issues, human rights, developing country labor exploitation, consumer rights, patent issues, pornography, same-sex partner recognition, etc. The list of these core organizations was bolstered through websites such as <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.corpwatch.org">www.corpwatch.org</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.multinationalmonitor.org">www.multinationalmonitor.org</ext-link>, which serve as advocacy group network hubs and information clearinghouses. The next step was to use an Internet software spider which goes to specified web addresses, collects all the URLs (links) within the site, and then follows those URLs and repeats the process through a specified number of iterations. The rationale is that advocacy groups tend to have links to other advocacy organizations.</p>
<p>A spider search was conducted with 21 URLs of groups identified through the qualitative research. This generated a list of 19,356 URLs. After eliminating duplicate URLs, a list of 7,821 unique URLs was generated. Eliminating URLs with “.gov” or “.edu” or “.state” domains (since these were more likely to be government or educational organizations than advocacy organizations) left 6,515 URLs. These 6,515 sites were accessed to determine whether or not they actually <italic>do</italic> campaign against firms, based on the content of the sites. Of the 6,515, we identified 413 that campaign against firms. These include stand-alone organizations as well as branches of larger organizations. For these 413 organizations, we attempted to collect contact information (sometimes organizations would not divulge this) as well as information about the target of the campaign (whether they were in a coalition, etc.). This information was captured in a relational database for later use.</p>
<p>The second method for identifying relevant organizations was to use Lexis-Nexis newspaper searches for the last five years from five major English-language newspapers from across three continents (<italic>Asian Wall Street Journal, Financial Times, New York Times, Seattle Times</italic>, and <italic>The Guardian</italic>). Searches were done on a multitude of combinations of search terms (e.g., “campaign,” “corporation,” “environment,” and “child labor”). We skimmed the resulting articles to identify relevant organizations and campaigns. This method allowed for the identification of the vast majority of those advocacy organizations active in the last five years and whose impact has been sufficient to make the major papers. (By contrast, the snowball method, though less exhaustive, is less subject toward over-sampling of major and influential organizations. The two methods are thus highly complementary.) These organizations were compared to those identified through the web-spider process. This search yielded 110 new organizations that were not in the database from the first web-spider snowball method. We then sought contact information for these groups from various sources including web pages, <italic>The Yearbook of International Organization</italic>s, and telephone directories, and included the information in the database.</p>
<p>Based on the thoroughness of the two methods, the database incorporated a large percentage of advocacy organizations over a certain minimal size and importance, and in the English-speaking world. (The sample collected included NGOs from fifteen countries across five continents and not all of the NGOs operated in English. However, all the surveys were in English and thus we ensured that respondents were sufficiently fluent and comfortable in English to answer the survey. This was done through the phone calls in the following phase of the data collection process.) The next step in the process was contacting the organizations to ask for their participation. This task faced some substantial hurdles that needed to be overcome. First, these organizations tend to be small and poorly funded and do not have the resources to spare to answer lengthy surveys. Second, these organizations have been engaged in campaigns against, most often, much larger and more resource-rich adversaries. There have been a few established cases of corporate interests infiltrating or spying on their NGO adversaries; these few cases are well known in the advocacy NGO community and serve to feed a general distrust of corporate and business interests. The first author’s association with a business school was enough to potentially raise suspicions. Given these hurdles and the relatively small sample frame, it was decided that, rather than mail out surveys, individual calls would be made to each of the organizations to establish a personal rapport and trust, signal how much we valued their participation, and address any concerns they might have.</p>
<p>(It is worth noting that some of the organizations are very radical. Some have slogans such as “Sabotage the war machine!” and “All we are saying is give class war a chance.” The Environmental Liberation Front and the Animal Liberation Front are organized in cells that engage in extensive property destruction. Black Block, which describes itself as “a group of anarchists and anarchist affinity groups,” and engages in destruction of property as a form of direct action, refuses to see itself as an organization at all. Interestingly, while it is likely that these groups were under-sampled in the survey, a few very radical organizations that engage in illegal activity agreed to participate and admitted to engaging in illegal activity.)</p>
<p>We developed a “caller script” which highlighted a number of facts intended to reduce any concerns or suspicions. Callers emphasized that the work was funded in part by the European Union and the European Academy of Business in Society, the background of the first author in ethics and past involvement with various NGOs and the INSEAD Business and Society Forum. Callers also underscored that the results were anonymous, that only the research team and authors would see any non-aggregated data, and that the respondents would receive individualized benchmarked reports in return for their participation. The team then set out calling the 513 organizations using the caller scripts. Multiple attempts were used to reach organizations and to follow up non-respondents.</p>
<p>Of the 513 organizations identified through the two methods, 130 could not be reached and 35 denied challenging firms. A later double-check on these 35 revealed that indeed 31 out of the 35 did not challenge firms, i.e., the original classification and inclusion in the database had been in error. (Twenty-seven of these 35 had been identified through the spider searches and eight had been identified through the Lexis-Nexis searches.) Four organizations that denied campaigning against corporations did, in fact, appear to campaign. They may have denied campaigning because they did not see themselves as really doing so or for tax-status reasons since tax status for advocacy organizations is different from mere information-providing organizations. Of the 348 remaining organizations, 133 completed the survey, a 38% response rate.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the vast majority of nonrespondents appeared relatively willing to answer the survey and said they would try to get to it, but never ended up filling out the survey, even after multiple calls (our standard procedure). This suggests that sensitivity of information was less of an issue than time constraints. Item response rates were generally over 95%. Of the respondents, 34% were executives, 23% were managers, 34% were staff; in 9% of the organizations there were no formal titles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0170840613479235">
<title>Survey Instrument</title>
<p>With a reasonable familiarity of the phenomenon based on the in-depth interviews and the case study, a 107-item survey was developed. This paper draws on a subset of these items. The survey captures data on (a) basic aspects about the organization (size, age, structure, formality in processes, hierarchical structure, and decision-making processes), internal and external resource dependencies, standard tactics it usually employs; (b) organizational ideological radicalism and ideological fervor, employee identification with the organization; and (c) detailed questions about a particular campaign against a firm, including: identification of the corporation, the size of the coalition, if any, involved in the campaign, information on the weight of various motivations behind target selection, willingness at the outset of the campaign to negotiate or compromise with the corporation, confidence at the outset of the campaign of gaining significant concessions from the firm, tactics employed by the advocacy organization, strategic responses used by the firm, the advocacy group’s change in intensity of campaign in response to the corporation’s response, the final response by the corporation, the duration of the campaign, and final outcomes at the firm, industry, and institution levels.</p>
<p>In developing the survey, the first author scanned the literature for useful existing scales for key constructs of ideological radicalism and ideological fervor. Although there are a number of scales on ideology, they were found to mostly be specific to a particular issue, e.g., feminism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0170840613479235">Plutzer, 1988</xref>) or general political leanings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0170840613479235">Barnes &amp; Kaase, 1979</xref>). None were found that focused on the specific constructs under study so original items were developed, most of which were on a seven-point Likert scale.</p>
<p>Second, the survey was pre-tested with five advocacy group executives and two scholars with expertise in survey development. During these interviews, respondents were asked to evaluate the meaningfulness, clarity, and “loadedness” of the items (a potential issue of special import, given the sensitivity of the topic). For more complex questions, in order to improve face validity and check for clarity, interviewees were asked to explain what they interpreted the questions to be asking. On the basis of these interviews, some items were dropped, modified, or added. The survey was then pre-tested with four additional advocacy executives, asking them to identify confusing or unclear questions and check the time needed to complete the survey. A small number of items were cut and modified accordingly. The survey was conducted online. While there were no major technical hitches, a few respondents were unable to complete the survey online and were provided either a copy in Microsoft Word or a hard-copy version.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0170840613479235">
<title>Independent Variables</title>
<p>All variables were subjected to the standard procedure for scale development, and validation. Two of the variables, ideological radicalism and institutionally homogenous resource providers, were subject to exploratory factor analysis and items were evaluated and discarded until strong reliability was achieved. Confirmatory factor analysis was not used because the number of items in each case was relatively small (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0170840613479235">Gatignon, Tushman, Smith, &amp; Anderson, 2003</xref>). The other variables that were built around multiple items were not constructs, but rather sets of possible actions and effects, and hence factor analysis was not an appropriate methodology. The survey items for each of variables listed below are found in the <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-0170840613479235">Appendix</xref>.</p>
<sec id="section11-0170840613479235">
<title>Ideological radicalism</title>
<p>An ideology is both a cognitive map of sets of expectations and a scale of values in which standards and imperatives are proclaimed. Wilson’s definition of ideology—“a set of beliefs about the social world and how it operates, containing statements about the rightness of certain social arrangements and what action would be undertaken in light of those statements”—refers to three main beliefs: beliefs about how the world operates, the moral appropriateness of the current arrangements, and what should be done to bring these two into alignment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0170840613479235">Wilson, 1973</xref>). Thus items were employed which capture, at the organizational level, (a) political, economic and social institutions <italic>beliefs</italic> (relative to the community), (b) social, environmental, economic and political <italic>values</italic> (relative to the community), and (c) beliefs about the importance of various factors as solutions to the focal issues of the organization, where these factors went from better enforcement of existing regulations, through minor and major modifications to the rules, to “fundamental changes to basic aspects of the political, economic, or social system.” Five items were employed to capture the global and partial facets of the construct. All of these items employed a seven-point Likert scale, with a Cronbach coefficient alpha of .90.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0170840613479235">
<title>Dependent Variables</title>
<sec id="section13-0170840613479235">
<title>Institutionally homogenous resource providers</title>
<p>To create this construct, we used three seven-point Likert items that captured the variance of beliefs of resource providers (individual and organizational donors, members, staff, and volunteers) concerning (a) political, social, and economic issues addressed by the organization, (b) the goals of the organization, and (c) the tactics of the organization. The construct has a Cronbach coefficient alpha of .76.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0170840613479235">
<title>Contra-institutional tactics</title>
<p>The measure of the degree to which the organization uses tactics that conflict in some way with institutional expectations was measured as the average of use of four contra-institutional tactics (i.e., boycotts, civil disobedience, direct action, and destruction of property), divided by the average use of all twelve of the tactics provided in the questionnaire (i.e., lawsuits, lobbying of regulators, shareholder resolutions, lobbying of politicians, rallies, publicity stunts, press conferences, leafleting, boycotts, civil disobedience, direct action, and destruction of property). The Cronbach alpha of the four contra-institutional tactics is .82.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0170840613479235">
<title>Institution-dependent tactics</title>
<p>The measure of the degree to which the organization uses tactics that depend on major institutions, in this case, the courts, the legislature and executive, and regulators. It was measured as the average of use of two institution-dependent tactics (i.e., lobbying of regulators and lobbying of politicians), divided by the average use of all twelve of the tactics provided in the questionnaire (i.e., lawsuits, lobbying of regulators, shareholder resolutions, lobbying of politicians, rallies, publicity stunts, press conferences, leafleting, boycotts, civil disobedience, direct action, and destruction of property). The Cronbach alpha of the two institution-dependent tactics is .80.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0170840613479235">
<title>Target selection</title>
<p>Four seven-point Likert scale items concerning firm attributes were used to determine the extent to which firms were targeted for what they represented. (These four items were a subset of a larger set of factors, which were not limited to firm attributes, but also included variables concerning the NGO and its supporters.) The four items—i.e., (1) its prior reputation, (2) its likeliness to respond, (3) how bad its actions were relative to others in its industry, (4) the extent to which it was representative of a broader institution or ideology—were identified through prior qualitative research to be among the most common bases of target selection. We averaged the four values and then divided the value of the fourth item by this average for the statistical analysis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0170840613479235">
<title>Control Variables</title>
<p>The logs of organizational size in terms of employees and volunteers, the log of budget, and the log of organizational age were used as control variables. These variables were selected because the size of the organization—captured in terms of the number of volunteers and paid staff, as well as the budget—would likely impact the effectiveness of the organization. We included organizational age as a control variable because arguments could be made that organizational age will affect the organization’s effectiveness (say, through population selection processes as well as through learning processes).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0170840613479235">
<title>Regression Analyses</title>
<p>We used three different statistical analyses—OLS, 2SLS, and 3SLS—to evaluate the system of equations representing the possible relationships, including potential endogeneity, mediation, and recursiveness of the dependent variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0170840613479235">Baron &amp; Kenny, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0170840613479235">Gatignon et al., 2003</xref>). We defined homogeneity, target, and tactic selection as our endogenous variables; we defined radicalism and the control variables (organization age, headcount, budget) as instruments, i.e., exogenous variables. We then ran the 2SLS and 3SLS regressions. The analyses for both 2SLS and 3SLS were virtually identical. The statistical significance of the variables and models were unchanged and the parameters virtually identical using these different techniques. Thus we report here the results from the 2SLS analysis. In our first regression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0170840613479235">Table 2</xref>), Homogeneity is the dependent variable, and we regress our Radicalism independent variable along with controls on the dependent variable. In our second regression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0170840613479235">Table 3</xref>), Tactic and Target selection are our dependent variables and Radicalism is our independent variable which we regress on the dependent variables, along with controls.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0170840613479235">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0170840613479235">Table 1</xref> shows the mean, standard deviations and Pearson correlations for all the variables. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0170840613479235">Table 2</xref> shows strong support for our argument that ideological radicalism of an SMO and the institutional homogeneity of its resource providers are related. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0170840613479235">Table 3</xref> supports that the more radical the SMO the more it will tend to use contra-institutional tactics and the more heavily it will weigh the degree to which the corporation is seen as representative of fundamental political, social, or economic institutions in choosing a target.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0170840613479235" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Statistics and Correlations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0170840613479235" xlink:href="10.1177_0170840613479235-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">s.d.</th>
<th align="left">1</th>
<th align="left">2</th>
<th align="left">3</th>
<th align="left">4</th>
<th align="left">5</th>
<th align="left">6</th>
<th align="left">7</th>
<th align="left">8</th>
<th align="left">9</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Radicalism</td>
<td>5.11</td>
<td>1.14</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Homogeneity</td>
<td>5.21</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Inst-Depend Tactics</td>
<td>4.27</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>−0.12</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Contra-Inst Tactics</td>
<td>2.11</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Instit. Rep’ness</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Log Org Age</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>−0.03</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>−0.08</td>
<td>−0.07</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. Log Headcount</td>
<td>6.21</td>
<td>1.42</td>
<td>−0.03</td>
<td>−0.03</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8. Log Budget</td>
<td>13.08</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>−0.10</td>
<td>−0.07</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>−0.12</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0170840613479235">
<p>Note: Absolute values of correlations greater than .28 are significant at .01; absolute values of correlations greater than .17 are significant at .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0170840613479235" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results for Hierarchical Regression Analysis for Homogeneity.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0170840613479235" xlink:href="10.1177_0170840613479235-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Radicalism</td>
<td>0.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0170840613479235">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Org Age</td>
<td>0.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HeadCount</td>
<td>−0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Budget</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Adjusted R<sup>2</sup></italic></td>
<td>.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0170840613479235">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>F</italic></td>
<td>3.92</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0170840613479235">
<p>Note: <italic>p</italic> &lt;.05; **<italic>p</italic> &lt;.01; ***<italic>p</italic> &lt;.001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0170840613479235" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of 2OLS Regression Analyses of Tactics and Target Selection on Radicalism.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0170840613479235" xlink:href="10.1177_0170840613479235-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Contra-institutional tactics</th>
<th align="left">Institution-dependent tactics</th>
<th align="left">Target selection: representativeness of institution</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Radicalism</td>
<td>0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">***</xref></td>
<td>0.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Organizational Age</td>
<td>−0.03</td>
<td>0.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HeadCount</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>−0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Budget</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Adjusted R<sup>2</sup></italic></td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>F</italic></td>
<td>5.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">**</xref></td>
<td>2.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">*</xref></td>
<td>2.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0170840613479235">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0170840613479235">
<p>Note: <italic>p</italic> &lt;.05; **<italic>p</italic> &lt;.01; ***<italic>p</italic> &lt;.001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0170840613479235" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion, Limitations, and Suggestions for Future Research</title>
<p>In this section, we review the theoretical contributions of this paper, identify its limitations, and propose some paths for future research, including promising directions concerning the dynamics of social movement organizations and ideologies, resources, and target and tactic selection. We also offer some conjectures about how our research might inform questions surrounding the longevity and sustainability of SMOs and their campaigns.</p>
<sec id="section21-0170840613479235">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>There are a number of limitations to the current study, which also prompt avenues for future inquiry. We first raise and dispel some less serious shortcomings and then consider a more serious limitation that could be addressed through additional research. First, we used a single key informant for each organization. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0170840613479235">Campbell and Fiske (1959)</xref> showed that the bias so introduced is negligible for single informants when these are key informants and the bias can actually be less than with multiple informants. In the current study, most of the informants were highly placed in the organization, had been with the organization for an average of six years of tenure, which represents 50 percent of the age of the average organization.</p>
<p>The problem was further mitigated by using a web-based survey that prevented respondents from revisiting prior questions. This limited the extent to which respondents could generate artificially correlated responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0170840613479235">Stanton, 1998</xref>). The problem of retrospective reporting was also limited to some extent by focusing on current aspects of the organization and campaigns that occurred within the last five years. Nonetheless, it is quite possible that the memories of the respondents were sometimes mistaken. Furthermore, the respondents were asked to select a campaign to discuss; in so doing, there was likely a tendency to select those campaigns which mattered more to the individual and the SMO. It is possible that the campaigns selected were not representative, and may be among the more successful of the campaigns by the SMO.</p>
<p>There was also a bias in the sample selection in two ways. First, only SMOs that campaigned against corporations were included in the sample. By definition, we did not include SMOs that engage exclusively or primarily in cooperative interactions with SMOs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0170840613479235">Doh &amp; Teegen, 2003</xref>). Thus, we must be cautious in generalizing beyond this population. Second, the Lexis-Nexis means of identification of potential respondents biased for more impactful campaigns since less impactful campaigns probably did not make it to the major newspapers. Both of these limitations are real but not too damning if one finds the more narrowly circumscribed population identified to be worthy of study. Nonetheless, a broader sampling would surely have been preferable. We were constrained both by practical limitations as well as a concern that the survey be relevant to all respondents. Too much heterogeneity in the sample would have generated its own problems.</p>
<p>Respondents, on average, reported their confidence in their answers to be quite high (5.5 on a seven-point scale). This adds slightly to our confidence that single respondent and retrospective reporting introduced little bias into the results. A third possible complaint is that the sample size of 133 is not large. However, the methods employed in developing the sample suggest that 133 is a relatively large proportion of the entire population of significant SMOs that have campaigned against corporations in the last five years. The fact that the sample represents a relatively large proportion of the entire population of significant SMOs that have campaigned against corporations together with the fact that many of the results were statistically significant should dispel concern about sample size. Finally, it is worth noting that what we test empirically is what we describe theoretically, but it is not actually what the description of the phenomenon addresses. That is, our hypotheses are tested by comparing different SMOs to one another, whereas the main example, or setting, compares the relative homogeneity of SMOs versus that of corporations. From a theoretical standpoint, this would be expected to result in a more conservative approach since the degree of variance in radicalism among SMOs would likely be less than the degree of variance in radicalism between SMOs on the one hand and corporations on the other. Nonetheless, to capture the phenomenon correctly, it would be nice to also have data on the degree of radicalism and homogeneity in the targeted corporations.</p>
<p>A more significant limitation to the current study is that the same respondents were used as data sources for both the dependent and independent variables and thus correlations could be generated as a function of consistent biases within respondents. This problem is exacerbated by the fact that many of the constructs being measured, such as radicalism and homogeneity, are not readily observable and hence are especially subject to vagaries of perception and interpretation. While common method variance is a serious limitation to this study, researchers are divided as to the significance of these effects. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0170840613479235">Spector (1987)</xref> concluded that the overall effects of common method variance are marginal. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0170840613479235">Crampton and Wagner (1994)</xref> found that the effects of common method variance are not insignificant but are small, while others have found more serious challenges to the validity of findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0170840613479235">Williams, Cote, &amp; Buckley, 1989</xref>). Nonetheless, our results should be considered exploratory.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0170840613479235">
<title>Contributions and Future Research</title>
<p>In his comprehensive review of the resource mobilization school, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0170840613479235">Jenkins (1983</xref>, p. 530) laments that “Traditionally resource mobilization theory has been posed in terms of collective actors struggling for power in an institutional context” and that “Microlevel processes have been ignored or treated as simplifying assumptions for a larger-scale analysis.”</p>
<p>In this paper, we have sought to respond to this challenge by developing a theory of social movement organizational radicalism and some empirically derived insights to suggest that, rather than balancing conflicting resource dependencies, more ideologically radical SMOs tend to have resource dependencies on supporters who are more institutionally homogeneous. This creates greater organizational freedom than that faced by larger organizations that must meet various ideological demands of its multiple and heterogeneous resource providers.</p>
<p>One of our most important contributions is to offer a plausible explanation for why small, resource-poor, unconventional SMOs persist, despite intense pressures toward conformity. The resource mobilization school and its more contemporary commentators have generally concluded that, as SMOs mature, they become increasingly professionalized, even corporatist in nature. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0170840613479235">McCarthy and Zald (1977)</xref> reported that the increasing success of SMs in the 1960s and 1970s was attributable to the growing professionalism and changing resource base of SMOs such that these new “professional” SMOs resembled more established organizations and drew their resources from external or “conscience” constituencies. Yet, one consequence of this process was that professional SMOs were less accountable to their traditional constituencies, came to be viewed as more mainstream organizations, and, according to critics, lost their fundamental character and potentially their efficacy as distinct institutional actors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0170840613479235">McAdam, 1982</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0170840613479235">McAdam (1982)</xref> concluded that the foundation patronage (financial resources) gravitated toward more mainstream organizations which, in turn, led to inter-organizational rivalry and, ultimately, movement decay. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0170840613479235">Jenkins and Eckert (1986)</xref> arrived at similar conclusions, finding that elite patronage had the effect of professionalizing social movements and that this professionalization weakened social movement efficacy and potentially contributes to SM decay, although they were careful to add that movement decay had multiple sources and that, while professionalization may have weakened the more extreme elements of the movement, it did not fundamentally transform their goals or tactics. More recently, scholars have concluded that SMOs take on more conventional organizational strategies in order to “engage in mainstream policy debates with governments or firms” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0170840613479235">Sell &amp; Prakash, 2004</xref>, p. 8) and that as SMOs have become more established social actors, their managerial structures and staffing patterns become more conventional, often drawing inspiration from corporations. Most importantly, their willingness to collaborate (as opposed to engage in conflict) with corporations increases in a commensurate fashion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0170840613479235">Doh &amp; Teegen, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Hence, the SMO literature leaves us with a puzzle as to why and how small, resource-poor and unconventional SMOs persist, with contrary observations and insights as to whether formalization and professionalism results in more sustainable and effective organizations and movements, or whether it undermines and erodes their very constitution and, in so doing, leads to decline and decay. Our study attempts to address this paradox by focusing on how the ideological orientation of the SMO is related to the nature of its resource providers, and how the interaction between ideology and the composition of resources influences the SMO’s willingness to engage in contra-institutional tactics and to aim at high-profile and potentially high-impact targets. Specifically, we have identified one mechanism through which greater institutional homogeneity of an organization’s resource providers tends to accrue to more ideologically radical organizations. The paper suggests how a single narrow institutional resource niche may provide challengers with an advantage over dominant organizations saddled with the constraints and costs imposed by institutional multivocality and that radical organizations, while at a disadvantage relative to more mainstream organizations, gain an advantage through this homogeneity in that it broadens their range of tactical options and arguments in their campaigns for institutional change. Given the relationship among our variables, however, there are clearly other forces that counteract pressures toward conformity that may include path dependence or a cycle of self-reinforcing action and support. This would certainly be a productive avenue for future research.</p>
<p>Our findings also complement those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0170840613479235">Haines (1984)</xref>, who posited that moderate association with radicals might harm, not help, the moderate groups in certain settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0170840613479235">Haines, 1984</xref>). This negative radical flank effect (RFE) suggests that moderates will be hurt by their coexistence with radicals in the same movement field. While we do not explicitly address how the persistence of radical groups influences their more moderate counterparts or the overall movement, our findings do suggest that there is reason to believe that radical and moderate elements can and do coexist within the same overall movement.</p>
<p>There are also broader, higher-level comparisons that might prove enlightening in future research. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0170840613479235">Padgett and Ansell (1993)</xref> identified one way in which organizations or individuals can survive and thrive in contexts in which various constituencies have differing and conflicting demands. The solution was “multivocality,” using action and inaction in circumscribed and inscrutable ways so as to be interpreted favorably by the various constituencies. This dynamic is likely at play whenever an organization must meet multiple conflicting demands. As described in this paper, radical organizations use an entirely different approach for survival and impact. Rather than seeking to meet multiple constituents’ conflicting expectations through rather bland and indecipherable actions and inactions, radical organizations—by their very nature—are required to meet fewer divergent demands of constituents, since their constituents are more ideologically homogeneous. Furthermore, whereas the Medici survived via bland actions, radical organizations—again by their nature as described and examined empirically here—tend to use highly contentious contra-institutional tactics. The Medici and radical SMOs seem to occupy two extremes on a spectrum that might be further developed in future research. Such future research could work to develop an overarching typology linking together survival strategies, internal organization, ideologies, resource dependencies, and behavior of organizations.</p>
<p>With respect to more contemporary political phenomena, in recent years there has been a resurgence of more “fringe” parties in many modern democracies, and our research might be used to partially explain their emergence and impact. For example, fringe parties continue to poll well in systems of proportional representation where voters are able to express their rejection of mainstream parties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0170840613479235">Declair, 1999</xref>). As some mainstream parties tack toward their bases during primaries or first round voting and then back toward the center in general or second rounds, core supporters of fringe parties can depend on the more extreme parties to maintain continuity and consistency in their positions. Similarly, as many NGOs that began their lives as more polarizing organizations have “gravitated toward the mean” as they have responded to some of the pressures documented by the traditional resource mobilization school; others have stayed the course as fringe organizations. For example, Greenpeace, Friends of the Earth, and many other environmental NGOs have become much more moderate as they have matured as organizations. Yet, new environmental NGOs, such as Earth First!, have filled the spaces vacated by the earlier occupants, suggesting a complex dynamic within the social movement space in which the movement of one organization towards the center actually creates a void that entices a newer organization to fill it.</p>
<p>Further, our study should inform studies of the life cycle and the chancing tactics and conformity of SMOs throughout their emergence and institutionalization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0170840613479235">den Hond and de Bakker, (2007)</xref>. In an analysis of the influence of the women’s rights movement on national governments and international institutions, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0170840613479235">Joachim (2003)</xref> proposes that SMO/NGO influence on states undergoes a life cycle in which the SMO concentrates on resource mobilization and ideological development in its early stages of formation, and only later gains actual influence on states. Hence,<disp-quote>
<p>[at the] beginning of the agenda-setting process, the influence of NGOs is rather limited, their frames are highly contested, and structural obstacles outweigh organizational resources. However, over time the influence of NGOs increases. As they establish their own mobilizing structures, they become capable of altering the political opportunity structure in their favor, and their frames gain in acceptance and legitimacy. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0170840613479235">Joachim, 2003</xref>, p. 17)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>These dynamic and reflexive realities would suggest further system- or field-wide study of the phenomenon.</p>
<p>This paper takes a preliminary step toward a more comprehensive theory of the legitimation/de-legitimation dynamics between radical organizations and the broader society in which they interact. Leveraging psycho-social dynamics such as social sanction together with self-selection into radical organizations, groupthink, and identity, we see the members of radical organizations increasingly look inward for their legitimation while the external environment de-legitimizes their radicalism. It is for further research to explore whether it is the case that—as hinted in this paper—the more radical the organization, the more intense will be the external de-legitimation and (resulting) de-legitimation dynamics.</p>
<p>At the institutional level, the study advances our understanding of the micro- and meso-level dynamics underpinning institutional normative pressure and institutional change. While there is a great deal of literature on how organizations manage institutional pressure, institutional pressure itself is often considered diffuse and “impersonal.” In contrast, this paper focuses on the strategic considerations of some of the organizations responsible for institutional pressure.</p>
<p>The phenomenon of SMO campaigns against corporations are highly complex and cross multiple levels of analysis. SMOs are themselves constrained and enabled by the group processes and internal resource dependencies of the organization and its supporters (group level). These group processes within the organization affect the strategic behavior of these SMOs, in terms of tactic and target selection and strategic interactions between the SMO and the targeted firm (organizational and inter-organizational levels). These inter-organizational dynamics that make up the campaign ultimately are judged by third-party individuals who evaluate the various claims made by both the SMO and the targeted firm and who may adjust their beliefs, norm,s and values (individual level) and, thereby, collectively affect the legitimacy and strength of competing institutional frameworks (society level). The process descriptions we provide of these cross-level causal chains are likely closer to the first word than the last word on the topic, but we believe they do provide a good description of the key processes.</p>
<p>Finally, we have developed a generalizable framing of ideological “proxy wars,” which provides a means for understanding a broad range of phenomena from SMO campaigns against corporations, to the current “Occupy Wall Street” phenomenon to geo-political conflict. This leads to the counter-intuitive and theoretically novel proposition that in pluralistic societies, i.e., those with a high degree of institutional heterogeneity, high levels of organizational isomorphism can attract de-legitimation attacks (by those who would wish to promote institutional change) as well as be a source of legitimacy. For example, the data suggests that firms are challenged as much for what they represent as for what they do.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0170840613479235" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this paper we have helped to further specify the strategic considerations of SMOs and how the ideological orientation of those organizations relates to the nature of resources upon which they depend. We introduced and explicated the construct of institutionally circumscribed resource niches and proposed how a single narrow institutional resource niche can influence the target and tactic selection of firms to allow them more latitude than organizations subject to the boundaries and strictures of institutional multivocality.</p>
<p>In addition to contributing to and extending the literature on the relationships among social movements, organizations, and institutions, our research adds to the growing exploration of the dynamic interactions among corporations, civil society organizations, and governments that has gained traction in the mainstream management and international business literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0170840613479235">Doh &amp; Guay, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0170840613479235">Teegen, Doh, &amp; Vachani, 2004</xref>). In particular, we explicate and reveal the micro-processes at work that have resulted in greater numbers, impact, and relevance of SMOs around the world and their growing role in mediating the interactions between business and government (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0170840613479235">Yaziji &amp; Doh, 2009</xref>). These contributions may have both theoretical and practical considerations for scholars, policymakers, and executives interested in gaining a deeper understanding of SMOs and their increasing role in local and global communities and societies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0170840613479235">
<title>Appendix: Survey Items for Key Constructs</title>
<sec id="section24-0170840613479235">
<title>Radicalism</title>
<p>11. Different individuals have different interpretations of how the social, economic, and political system is functioning (e.g., power balances, levels of corruption, etc.).</p>
<p>In comparing your organization to the general attitudes in your community (defined here as the total population, e.g., the town or state or country, from which you draw financial support, volunteers, and staff), how would you classify your organization in terms of how it perceives the functioning of the social, economic, and political system?</p>
<p>1 = The beliefs of the organization are extremely different from those of the community</p>
<p>7 = The beliefs of the organization are identical to those of the community</p>
<p>(Likert 7-point scale)</p>
<p>12. Different individuals and organizations weigh different values—e.g., egalitarianism, environmental protection, social justice, economic growth, protection of rights, etc.—differently.</p>
<p>In comparing your organization to the general attitudes in your community (defined here as the total population, e.g., the town or state or country from which you draw financial support, volunteers, and staff), how would you classify your organization in terms of how it weighs such values?</p>
<p>1 = The values of the organization are extremely different from those of the community</p>
<p>7 = The values of the organization are identical to those of the community</p>
<p>(Likert 7-point scale)</p>
<p>13. According to your organization, how important are the following as solutions to the focal issues of the organization to be found primarily in:</p>
<p>1 = Irrelevant as a solution</p>
<p>7 = Critical as a solution</p>
<p>(Likert 7-point scale)</p>
<list id="list4-0170840613479235" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Better enforcement of existing regulations</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Minor modifications to existing regulations</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fundamental changes to basic aspects of the political, economic, or social system</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Major modifications to the existing regulative framework</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>17. How would you classify your organization on the continuum between “mainstream” and “radical,” in terms of:</p>
<p>1 = Mainstream</p>
<p>7 = Radical</p>
<p>(Likert 7-point scale)</p>
<list id="list5-0170840613479235" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Social and economic priorities</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Beliefs about the political, social, and economic system</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Beliefs about how significant the changes to the system must be in order to move from the current state of affairs to an acceptable state of affairs</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0170840613479235">
<title>Homogeneity</title>
<p>18. To what extent do the various contributors to your organization (individual and organizational donors, members, staff, and volunteers) hold differing beliefs concerning the following:</p>
<p>1 = Contributors hold very conflicting beliefs</p>
<p>7 = Contributors hold identical beliefs</p>
<p>(Likert 7-point scale)</p>
<p>Political, social, and economic issues addressed by the organization?</p>
<list id="list6-0170840613479235" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The goals of the organization</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The tactics of the organization</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>19. To what extent do conflicting beliefs among contributors affect the organization in the following ways:</p>
<p>1 = Not at all</p>
<p>7 = Very much</p>
<p>(Likert 7-point scale)</p>
<list id="list7-0170840613479235" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>There are internal debates about goals of the organization</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>There are internal debates about best tactics</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The risk of alienating various contributors is taken into consideration when determining overall strategies and goals of the organization</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The risk of alienating various contributors affects tactic selection</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0170840613479235">
<title>Target Selection</title>
<p>23. In selecting the firm as a target of the campaign, how important were the following factors?</p>
<p>1 = Not at all</p>
<p>7 = Very much</p>
<list id="list8-0170840613479235" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The likelihood of the targeted firm acceding to the campaign’s demands</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The degree to which the firm’s behavior was worse than others in its industry</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The firm’s reputation was already poor</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The degree to which the firm represents institutions or ideologies (e.g., capitalism, globalization, multinational corporations, abortion, environmental standards, WTO, WIPO, etc.) your organization wanted to target</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0170840613479235">
<title>Tactic Selection</title>
<p>26. To what extent did your organization use the following tactics in this campaign? (There may be overlap among these tactics.)</p>
<p>1 = Not at all</p>
<p>7 = Very much</p>
<list id="list9-0170840613479235" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Lawsuits</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lobbying of regulators</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Shareholder resolutions</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lobbying of politicians</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rallies and marches</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Publicity stunts</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Press conferences</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Leafleting</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Boycotts</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Civil disobedience</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Destruction of property</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Direct action to disrupt businesses, offices, streets</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0170840613479235">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Sentiments are positively or negatively valenced appraisals specific to a given referent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0170840613479235">Frijda, 1994</xref>). That is, the liking or disliking of a particular thing is one’s sentiment toward it. Sentiments differ from diffuse dispositional affect and mood in being directed toward a specific referent; and sentiments are generally seen as longer lasting than emotions, which, while being caused by, or having, a specific object, are more ephemeral. (See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0170840613479235">Kelly &amp; Barsade, 2001</xref>, for a review of various affective factors.)</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Michael Yaziji</bold> is a Professor of Strategy at IMD in Lausanne, Switzerland. He teaches and conducts research in the areas of strategy, nonmarket strategy, stakeholder management, ethics and change management, and governance. He is widely recognized for his research focus on the relationships among corporations, NGOs, and government. His most recent publications include an article on capitalism in <italic>Harvard Business Review</italic> (2008) as well as the book, <italic>NGOs and Corporations: Conflict and Collaboration</italic> (with Jonathan Doh, 2009). Professor Yaziji holds a PhD in management and strategy from INSEAD (2004) and a PhD in analytic philosophy from the University of California (1995).</p>
<p><bold>Jonathan Doh</bold> is the Herbert G. Rammrath Endowed Chair in International Business, founding Director of the Center for Global Leadership, and Professor of Management and Operations at the Villanova School of Business (VSB). His research on multinational strategy, global corporate responsibility, and nongovernmental organizations has been published in <italic>Academy of Management Review, Business Ethics Quarterly, California Management Review, Journal of International Business Studies, Journal of Management Studies, Management Information Systems Quarterly</italic> (MISQ), <italic>Organization Science, Sloan Management Review</italic>, and <italic>Strategic Management Journal</italic>, among others. He is co-editor and/or co-author of seven books, including <italic>NGOs and Corporations: Conflict and Collaboration</italic> (with Michael Yaziji, 2009). He holds a PhD in strategic and international management from George Washington University.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arrow</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>). <article-title>Gifts and exchanges</article-title>. <source>Philosophy and Public Affairs</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ashforth</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>How can you do it? Dirty work and the challenge of constructing a positive identity</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ashforth</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mael</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Social identity theory and the organization</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaase</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <source>Political action: mass participation in five western democracies</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Private politics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economics and Management Strategy</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual and statistical consideration</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Batson</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>The altruism question: toward a social-psychological answer</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The self</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fist</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindzey</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The handbook of social psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>A theory of social interactions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Political Economy</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1093</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benford</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Framing processes and social movements: An overview and assessment</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>). <article-title>Convergent and discriminant validation by the multitrait-multimethod matrix</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Organizational repertoires and institutional change: Women’s groups and the transformation of US politics, 1890–1920</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>755</fpage>–<lpage>798</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Politics and institutionalism: Explaining durability and change</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ortney</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Cognition in emotion: Always, sometimes, never?</article-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nadel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Cognitive neuroscience of emotions</source> (pp. <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crampton</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Percept-percept inflation in microorganizational research: An investigation of prevalence and effect</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A social movement perspective on corporate control</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Bakker</surname><given-names>F. G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>den Hond</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Introducing the politics of stakeholder influence: A review essay</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Society</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeClair</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1999</year>. <source>Politics on the fringe: the people, policies, and organization of the French National Front</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>della Porta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kriesi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rucht</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Social movements in a globalizing world</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>St Martin’s</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>della Porta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Social movements: an introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>den Hond</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Bakker</surname><given-names>F. G. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Ideologically motivated activism: How activist groups influence corporate social change</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>924</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Djelic</surname><given-names>M. L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quack</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Globalization and institutions: redefining the rules of the economic game</source>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edward Elgar</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guay</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Corporate social responsibility, public policy, and NGO activism in Europe and the United States: An institutional-stakeholder perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of Management Studies</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teegen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Globalization and NGOs: transforming business, government, and society</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fabes</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Personality and socialization correlates of vicarious emotional responding</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality &amp; Social Psychology</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Network sampling in practice: Some second steps</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nosanchuk</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Applied network sampling</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finifter</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Dimensions of political alienation</article-title>. <source>American Political Science Review</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frijda</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Varieties of affect: Emotions and episodes, moods, and sentiments</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The nature of emotion: fundamental questions</source> (pp. <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gamson</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>The strategy of social protest</source> (<edition>2nd edition</edition>). <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gatignon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tushman</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>A structural approach to assessing innovation: Construct development of innovation locus, type, and characteristics</article-title>. <source>Management Science</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1103</fpage>–<lpage>1122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giugni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Was it worth the effort? The outcomes and consequences of social movements</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Black radicalization and the funding of civil rights: 1957–1970</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Resource mobilization theory and the study of social movements</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Channeling black insurgency: Elite patronage and professional social movement organizations in the development of the black movement</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>812</fpage>–<lpage>829</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Joachim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Framing issues and seizing opportunities: The UN, NGOs, and women’s rights</article-title>. <source>International Studies Quarterly</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barsade</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Mood and emotions in small groups and work teams</article-title>. <source>Organizational Behavior &amp; Human Decision Processes</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soule</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Social movements as extra-institutional entrepreneurs: The effect of protest on stock price returns</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klandersmans</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Social-psychological expansion of resource-mobilization theory</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lipschutz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Reconstructing world politics: The emergence of global civil society</article-title>. <source>Millennium: Journal of International Studies</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <source>Political process and the development of black insurgency</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chicago University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Social movements</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Smelser</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Handbook of sociology</source> (pp. <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldive</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Comparative perspectives on social movements: political opportunities, mobilizing structures, and cultural framings</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Organizations and movements</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Social movements and organization theory</source> (pp. <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Resource mobilization and social movements</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1212</fpage>–<lpage>1241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>). <article-title>Two categories of political alienation</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Padgett</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ansell</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Robust action and the rise of the Medici, 1400–1434</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>1259</fpage>–<lpage>1319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salancik</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>The external control of organizations: a resource dependence perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford Business Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plutzer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Work life, family life, and women’s support of feminism</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Caveat emptor: The construction of nonprofit consumer watchdog organizations</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>912</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Power plays: How social movements and collective action create new organizational forms</article-title>. <source>Research in Organizational Behavior</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>T. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moldoveanu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>When will stakeholder groups act? An interest- and identity-based model of stakeholder group mobilization</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Using ideas strategically</article-title>. <source>International Studies Quarterly</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Social movements as challenges to authority: Resistance to an emerging conceptual hegemony</article-title>. Working paper. <publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Irvine</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Method variance as an artifact in self-reported affect and perceptions at work: Myth or significant problem?</article-title> <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>An empirical assessment of data collection using the Internet</article-title>. <source>Personnel Psychology</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teegen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vachani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The importance of nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) in global governance and value creation: An international business research agenda</article-title>. <source>Journal of International Business Studies</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Repertoires of contention in America and Britain, 1750–1830</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The dynamics of social movement</source> (pp. <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Winthrop Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Touraine</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>The return of the actor: social theory in post-industrial society</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>USAS</collab> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Press release on Jerzees de Honduras victory</article-title>, <month>November</month> <day>18</day>, <year>2009</year>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://usas.org/2009/11/18/usas-press-release-on-jerzees-de-honduras-victory/">http://usas.org/2009/11/18/usas-press-release-on-jerzees-de-honduras-victory/</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Lack of method variance in self-reported affect and perceptions at work: Reality or artifact?</article-title> <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <source>Introduction to social movements</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yaziji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>NGOs and corporations: conflict and collaboration</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0170840613479235">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zald</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>). <article-title>Social movement organizations: Growth, decay and change</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>