<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TAG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptag</journal-id>
<journal-title>Therapeutic Advances in Gastroenterology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1756-283X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1756-2648</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1756283X12473676</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1756283X12473676</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Colonoscopy and colorectal cancer mortality: both sides of the story</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Neugut</surname><given-names>Alfred I.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1756283X12473676">Columbia University Medical Center, 722 West 168th Street, Room 725, New York, NY 10032, USA</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1756283X12473676">Department of Medicine and the Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, College of Physicians and Surgeons, and Department of Epidemiology, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1756283X12473676"><email>ain1@columbia.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>189</fpage>
<lpage>191</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Screening colonoscopy was first suggested as a potential future colorectal cancer (CRC) screening tool for average risk adults in 1988 in the absence of efficacy data, but with the hope that solid evidence in its support would accumulate in the future [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1756283X12473676">Neugut and Forde, 1988</xref>]. While indirect evidence was published in the ensuing years (e.g. the ability of colonoscopy to detect and remove adenomas), until recently definitive proof of a mortality benefit has been elusive; indeed, whether it is superior to flexible sigmoidoscopy has been questioned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1756283X12473676">Neugut and Lebwohl, 2010</xref>]. Nonetheless, it has become the primary CRC screening modality in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1756283X12473676">Joseph <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>].</p>
<p>It is important to recognize that two criteria are the fundamental cornerstones by which a screening test is evaluated from a public policy perspective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1756283X12473676">Brawley and Kramer, 2005</xref>]. The first is whether the test reduces disease-specific mortality. The second criterion is one that is omnipresent in the evaluation of any intervention in medicine, i.e. that the risk–benefit ratio is worthwhile. Other endpoints are frequently discussed and used as surrogates or alternatives and, when this is done, the evaluation becomes confused. Examples in the case of CRC screening include adenoma detection, yield of CRC found, or the stage distribution of cancers detected. These may all be positive outcomes, and may all suggest that a potential screening test may have promise as a future addition to the menu of options. However, they are not the true criteria by which to establish the efficacy and role of a screening test: the reduction of CRC mortality. Even the reduction of CRC incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1756283X12473676">Brenner <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>], which may seem like the equivalent of CRC mortality, is not a substitute for this endpoint.</p>
<p>The tests that are acceptable for CRC screening, and the preferences among them, have been in evolution. The United States Preventive Services Task Force and a guidance statement from the American College of Physicians list three acceptable tests: fecal occult blood testing (FOBT), sigmoidoscopy, and colonoscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1756283X12473676">U.S. Preventive Services Task Force, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1756283X12473676">Qaseem <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>]. Two of these tests have randomized trial-based evidence for improved mortality: FOBT and sigmoidoscopy. But colonoscopy, which is usually recommended as the premiere screening tool and is the most widely used CRC screening modality in the United States, has had only limited evidence of efficacy.</p>
<p>Over the last 3 years, there has been a plethora of new data regarding the efficacy of colonoscopy in the reduction of CRC mortality. While none are randomized trials (and such trials have only recently been initiated), they shed light on the shortcomings, as well as the potential, of screening colonoscopy as an effective public health intervention.</p>
<p>Colonoscopy earned its popularity in the absence of data showing a reduction of mortality or cancer incidence, and was primarily justified on the basis of a logical argument based on the proven efficacy of sigmoidoscopy; colonoscopy must be superior because it also explores the right side of the colon. Thus, the CRC screening community was taken aback by the first two observational studies of CRC mortality with colonoscopy in 2009 and 2010. While they showed a reduction in overall CRC mortality, this reduction was similar to that of sigmoidoscopy and colonoscopy did not show any benefit on the right side of the colon (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1756283X12473676">Table 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1756283X12473676">Baxter <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1756283X12473676">Singh <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>]. These two studies, performed in Canada rather than the US, were criticized since the bulk of exams were not performed by gastroenterologists, which could have accounted for the lack of efficacy on the right side of the colon. Nevertheless, these results led to the hypothesis, troubling to gastroenterologists as well as the general public which has embraced colonoscopy, that colonoscopy may not be effective in preventing death from proximal colon cancer.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1756283X12473676" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Studies testing for an association between colonoscopy and mortality from colorectal cancer (CRC).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1756283X12473676" xlink:href="10.1177_1756283X12473676-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Study</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Design</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Country</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Deaths from CRC (<italic>n</italic>)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Risk ratio (95% confidence interval)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Overall CRC mortality</th>
<th align="left">Distal CRC mortality</th>
<th align="left">Proximal CRC mortality</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1756283X12473676">Baxter <italic>et al</italic>. [2009]</xref></td>
<td>Case–control</td>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>10,292</td>
<td>0.63 (0.57–0.69)</td>
<td>0.33 (0.28–0.39)</td>
<td>0.99 (0.86–1.14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1756283X12473676">Singh <italic>et al</italic>. [2010]</xref></td>
<td>Cohort</td>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>0.71 (0.61–0.82)</td>
<td>0.53 (0.42–0.67)</td>
<td>0.95 (0.77–1.17)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1756283X12473676">Zauber <italic>et al</italic>. [2012]</xref></td>
<td>Cohort</td>
<td>USA</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>0.47 (0.26–0.80)</td>
<td>Not stated</td>
<td>Not stated</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1756283X12473676">Baxter <italic>et al</italic>. [2012]</xref></td>
<td>Case–control</td>
<td>USA</td>
<td>9458</td>
<td>0.40 (0.37–0.43)</td>
<td>0.24 (0.21–0.27)</td>
<td>0.58 (0.53–0.64)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In parallel with these studies challenging the efficacy of colonoscopy in the proximal colon, came three randomized trials of sigmoidoscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1756283X12473676">Atkin <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1756283X12473676">Segnan <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1756283X12473676">Schoen <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>]. Two of these three studies showed a reduction in mortality of 26% and 31% for CRC mortality overall, mostly limited to the left colon, while the third showed a reduction in incidence, thus reinforcing sigmoidsocopy’s efficacy as a screening tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1756283X12473676">Inadomi, 2012</xref>]. Thus, we reached the conclusion that the available evidence was insufficient to support colonoscopy’s primacy as a CRC screening tool, and we raised the possibility that flexible sigmoidoscopy could rival or even supplant colonoscopy in an era of cost-conscious healthcare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1756283X12473676">Neugut and Lebwohl, 2010</xref>].</p>
<p>However, now the first population-based study of colonoscopy and CRC mortality in the US has been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1756283X12473676">Baxter <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>]. This game-changing case-control study of Medicare recipients by Baxter and colleagues demonstrates a 60% reduction in CRC mortality for colonoscopy, clearly superior to that of sigmoidoscopy. More importantly, while the study does not show the same reduction in mortality on the right and left sides of the colon, it does show good efficacy on both sides (76% reduction in mortality on the left, 42% on the right) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1756283X12473676">Table 1</xref>). This efficacy on the right, not seen in the Canadian studies, is likely due in large part to the fact that 65% of the colonoscopies were performed by gastroenterologists <italic>versus</italic> 31% in one of the Canadian studies. Another study, limited to patients who underwent both colonoscopy and polypectomy, suggested a similar overall mortality reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1756283X12473676">Zauber <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>].</p>
<p>While we do not yet have the results of randomized trials of colonoscopy, which will be available in 15 years, the study by Baxter and colleagues provides high-quality observational evidence that colonoscopy has a clear protective effect on CRC mortality. On the other hand, the evidence for sigmoidoscopy is firmly established on the basis of three randomized trials, the gold standard for efficacy. Extending the use of endoscopic screening to the proximal colon comes at the cost of substantial added invasiveness, risk, logistical effort on the part of the patient, and significant added economic cost. These issues will need to be weighed in conjunction with the putative gain in efficacy.</p>
<p>Cancer screening tests arouse more controversy than almost any area of clinical decision-making. To a large degree, this arises because the scientific evidence often does not support the clinical intuition that leads to the initial widespread adoption of a test before it is proven. Screening colonoscopy has persisted for decades in a similar limbo state, without definitive mortality evidence in its support, and with recent studies questioning its use. The study by Baxter and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1756283X12473676">Baxter <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>] offers the first definitive evidence of superior efficacy, with mortality reduction throughout the colon, making ongoing efforts to promote colonoscopy appropriate.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Dr Neugut and Dr Lebwohl jointly conceived, drafted, and revised this manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>Dr Lebwohl is supported by the National Center for Research Resources, a component of the National Institutes of Health (KL2 RR024157).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest statement</label>
<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest in preparing this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Atkin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kralj-Hans</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wooldrage</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Northover</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Once-only flexible sigmoidoscopy screening in prevention of colorectal cancer: a multicentre randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>375</volume>: <fpage>1624</fpage>–<lpage>1633</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldwasser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paszat</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saskin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rabeneck</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Association of colonoscopy and death from colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–
<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stukel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doria-Rose</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association between colonoscopy and colorectal cancer mortality in a US cohort according to site of cancer and colonoscopist specialty</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2664</fpage>–<lpage>2669</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brawley</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cancer screening in theory and in practice</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang-Claude</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seiler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rickert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Protection from colorectal cancer after colonoscopy: a population-based, case-control study</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Inadomi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Why you should care about screening flexible sigmoidoscopy</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>366</volume>: <fpage>2421</fpage>–<lpage>2422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of colorectal cancer screening among adults–Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System, United States, 2010</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source> <volume>61</volume>(<supplement>Suppl.</supplement>): <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neugut</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Screening colonoscopy: has the time come?</article-title> <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neugut</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Colonoscopy vs sigmoidoscopy screening: getting it right</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>304</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qaseem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Denberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>R.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Screening for colorectal cancer: a guidance statement from the American College of Physicians</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schoen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinsky</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weissfeld</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yokochi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laiyemo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Colorectal-cancer incidence and mortality with screening flexible sigmoidoscopy</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>366</volume>: <fpage>2345</fpage>–<lpage>2357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Segnan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Armaroli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Risio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sciallero</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zappa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Once-only sigmoidoscopy in colorectal cancer screening: follow-up findings of the Italian Randomized Controlled Trial–SCORE</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1310</fpage>–<lpage>1322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kliewer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahmud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The reduction in colorectal cancer mortality after colonoscopy varies by site of the cancer</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1128</fpage>–<lpage>1137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Screening for colorectal cancer: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1756283X12473676">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zauber</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winawer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lansdorp-Vogelaar</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Ballegooijen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hankey</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Colonoscopic polypectomy and long-term prevention of colorectal-cancer deaths</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>366</volume>: <fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>696</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>