<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HEA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphea</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health (London)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Health:</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1363-4593</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7196</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1363459312461823</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1363459312461823</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Review</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Michael H Merson, Robert E Black and Anne J Mills (eds), <italic>Global Health: Diseases, Programs, Systems and Policies</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Regmi</surname><given-names>Krishna</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1363459312461823">University of Bedfordshire, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>319</fpage>
<lpage>320</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Merson</surname><given-names>Michael H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>Robert E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>Anne J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds), <source>Global Health: Diseases, Programs, Systems and Policies</source>, <edition>3rd ed.</edition>, <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <year>2012</year>; <page-count count="936"/> pp.: <isbn>13:9780763785598</isbn>, <price>£56.99</price></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Global health in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1363459312461823">Koplan et al.’s (2009</xref>: 1993) view is considered ‘as a notion (the current state of global health), an objective (a world of healthy people; a condition of global health), or a mix of scholarship, research, and practice (with many questions, issues, skills, and competencies)’ to improve health and achieve equity globally. Merson, Black and Mills’ dense, discursive book addresses most of the global health themes, exploring from diverse (core and cross-cutting) perspectives to support students’, practitioners’ and researchers’ learning in health across the globe. As the meaning of global health is still contested within different professional disciplines, this book has been successful in securing its top ranking within the context of restructuring or reforming health systems in response to new threats, for example poverty, inequality, climate change, broader socio-economic environment and political and ethical tensions globally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1363459312461823">Hunter et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>The breadth and depth of the areas covered is impressive, reflecting 200-plus major health interventions from both rich and poor countries’ health systems. In that respect, this rich textbook would be equally beneficial to academia (undergraduate, postgraduate and academic staff) and to the wider healthcare professional audiences, including medicine, nursing, social science, economics and environment. This is the first textbook that I have ever come across in my professional life to incorporate such a range of paradigms. I enjoyed most of the chapters, as it was well written and accessible, and perhaps the most fascinating chapter for me was Chapter 17, ‘Cooperation in global health’, which challenges the notion of the traditional view. For example, it asserts that health is no longer in the hands of healthcare professionals, but goes beyond those traditional boundaries. I equally argue that it is the right time to think about and choose appropriate working partners to form a global governance to bring lasting change to people’s health and well-being globally. To take <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1363459312461823">Hunter et al.’s (2010</xref>: 13) point, it is the matter of ‘creating the conditions for health’. This I think is a ‘crux’ of current health challenges for all healthcare professionals and practitioners reaching health globally in the 21st century!</p>
<p>This book is divided into 18 chapters that follow typical case studies, examples and exhibits, and each chapter embeds important messages in a conclusion and provides key discussion questions to stimulate students’ theoretical and contextual knowledge, reflecting into the practical contexts. This book is edited by three renowned authors, and 54 internationally established subject experts, offering many new and emerging perspectives, and it makes an important contribution to the field of health sciences globally.</p>
<p>This book stands to face the challenge of current and future health – focusing health, diseases, health systems and health policies in the perspective of the developing world. It has clearly emphasized the importance of interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary action in context. The only query I have about the book is the size of the volume and the cost as it is more than 950 pages in length, and the current cost estimate is £56.99 ($124.95); this might be beyond the capacity of many students and interested academics and practitioners from the developing world. Therefore improvement in formatting, such as volume and cost-cutting measures, for example a low cost edition or an e-book could have further enhanced its accessibility.</p>
<p>Nerveless, this is an excellent book which should be essential reading for all healthcare students (at both undergraduate and postgraduate levels) both nationally and internationally. In addition, the book will possibly be more important to many health practitioners, researchers and scholars. I equally felt that many external development partners, including bilateral and multilateral donors, funders, INGOs, NGOs and charities committed to working to improve the health of needy and poor people would gain great benefit from having this rich and impressive textbook on their work table!</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1363459312461823">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The Public Health System in England</source>. <publisher-loc>Bristol</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1363459312461823">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koplan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Towards a common definition of global health</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>373</volume>(<issue>9676</issue>): <fpage>1993</fpage>–<lpage>1995</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>