<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CNC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcnc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Capital &amp; Class</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0309-8168</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-0980</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0309816813489936</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0309816813489936</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Objective but not detached: Partisanship in industrial relations research</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Darlington</surname><given-names>Ralph</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0309816813489936">University of Salford, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0309816813489936">Riga International School of Economics and Business Administration, Latvia</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0309816813489936">Professor Ralph Darlington, University of Salford, UK. Email: <email>R.R.Darlington@salford.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>285</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Conference of Socialist Economists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article considers whether industrial relations (IR) research is objective, impartial or value-free, and argues that many IR academics in Britain have tended to start from a social-democratic premise which makes them relatively more sympathetic to the interests and objectives of workers and their trade unions than to the business needs of employers and managers. Focusing attention on the partisanship of those who have made a distinctive ‘radical/critical’ contribution to IR scholarship, it advances the argument that IR can, at one and the same time, be <italic>both</italic> partisan <italic>and</italic> objective. Acknowledging the real potential dangers of bias in adopting a methodological approach that states, in the words of C. Wright Mills, ‘I have tried to be objective, but I do not claim to be detached’, it provides a defence of the potential merits of partisanship, provided it is underpinned by rigorous scholarly research.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Bias</kwd>
<kwd>industrial relations</kwd>
<kwd>objectivity</kwd>
<kwd>partisanship</kwd>
<kwd>value-neutrality</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0309816813489936" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0309816813489936">Eric Hobsbawm (1998</xref>: 164) observed that although there has been a great deal of discussion about the nature, or even the possibility, of objectivity in the social sciences, there has been far less discussion about the problem of ‘partisanship’. Certainly this has been true of the academic field of industrial relations (IR). On the one hand, based on the predominant ‘pluralist’ IR paradigm that there are fundamental differences of interest between employees and employers, many IR researchers and theorists have long been concerned with the problem of balancing competing objectives of different stakeholders – to use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0309816813489936">Budd’s (2004)</xref> phrase, ‘balancing equity, efficiency and voice’ – and the advocacy of a normative view of the requirements for improving labour-market institutions, policies and practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0309816813489936">Kochan, 1998</xref>: 37). On the other hand, IR academics have generally also tended to posit a strong belief in the value of critical social science research premised on the notion of academic impartiality and objectivity that is not aligned to the economic or political priorities of either employers or unions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0309816813489936">Bain and Clegg 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0309816813489936">Winchester 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0309816813489936">Berrill, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0309816813489936">Sisson 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0309816813489936">BUIRA 2008</xref>). Although it is in Britain now largely taught in business schools, it could be argued that this differentiates IR from other ‘management’ subjects such as mainstream human resource management (HRM) and professional courses leading to membership of the Chartered Institute for Personnel and Development (CIPD), as well as from shop steward and trade union studies courses. Instead, academic IR is about generating understanding through scholarship that investigates the employment relationship from an impartial vantage point and in a critically questioning fashion towards <italic>all</italic> actors and parties. Such objectivity suggests the exclusion of partisanship (of ‘taking sides’). In the process it also raises the related (albeit not synonymous) issue of whether social research science research generally can, or should, be value-free, or at least value-neutral.</p>
<p>The question of whether partisanship is an unavoidable feature of social science research is especially pertinent for a field of study as potentially value-laden as industrial relations. This article re-examines some classic philosophy of science dilemmas to demonstrate that much industrial relations research, far from being completely impartial or value-free, is often effectively partisan, albeit this is usually not explicitly acknowledged. Focusing on the ‘radical/critical’ contribution to IR scholarship, it goes on to argue that IR can at one and the same time be <italic>both</italic> partisan <italic>and</italic> objective, and provides a defence of partisanship that is underpinned by rigorous scholarly research methodology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0309816813489936">
<title>Objectivity, value neutrality, partisanship and bias</title>
<p>One of the key assumptions during the first half of the 20th century was that social science could mirror the natural sciences and produce ‘objective’ knowledge, which uncovered the true nature of the social world in exactly the same way as scientists had discovered the ‘laws’ of physics, chemistry and biology. The task of the social scientist was to hold up a mirror to society, producing a ‘warts-and-all’ image that may not be acceptable to the viewer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0309816813489936">Rothschild 1982</xref>). It was widely believed that this necessitated a commitment on the part of social scientists to the ideal of ‘value neutrality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0309816813489936">Hammersley 2000</xref>: 1). For some, ‘value-neutrality’ means that research should be wholly independent of all values, and concerned with the pursuit of theoretical or factual knowledge for its own sake; while for others, value-neutrality is treated as a principle (or ideal) that guides the behaviour of researchers, so that whilst not renouncing their values, they must set them aside and not seek to promote them through their research. Defenders of value-neutrality often draw a distinction between the objective <italic>factual evidence</italic> of their research and any subjective <italic>evaluation of its implications and consequences</italic>, drawing no relationship whatsoever between the two.</p>
<p>Yet research can never be value-free, or even completely impartial, because it is simply implausible to suppose that a researcher is not influenced by his or her own established and preconceived values, which reflect a complex cocktail of the person’s political and social beliefs, moulded by their life experiences. It is inevitable that these will feed through into research findings by influencing research focus, the questions asked, the way evidence is selected, the interpretation of facts, and subsequent evaluative analysis. But this raises the question of whether research can ever be <italic>objective</italic> if a researcher is not value-free or impartial, and whether research has to be value-free or impartial in order to be objective. Arguably, ‘objective’ research is objective not because it produces knowledge of phenomena as a direct result of the researcher’s eschewing any personal values, or disavowing any standpoint favourable to one group’s interests as opposed to another. It is objective because it produces knowledge on the basis of research which is scholarly and rigorous in its methodology, in terms of measures such as reliability, validity, representativeness and verification, and which systematically assesses any formulated hypotheses in the light of the evidence, as opposed to ‘biased’ research in which subjective evaluations are expressed independent of such evidence.</p>
<p>‘Partisanship’ is a more difficult term to define, albeit there have been some important sociological contributions on the question. At one end of the spectrum, Howard Becker’s famous article ‘Whose side are we on?’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0309816813489936">1967</xref>) has sometimes mistakenly been interpreted as suggesting that all research should be explicitly partisan, with researchers aligning themselves from the outset with the struggle of particular social or political ‘underdog’ groups, with the aim of producing policy recommendations that serve these groups interests. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0309816813489936">Hammersley (2000</xref>: 60-89) points out that Becker actually argued that researchers cannot avoid becoming more sympathetic to some groups they study than others. This does not mean that they should set out to be partisan <italic>per se</italic>, but that they cannot avoid being viewed as taking sides, because in taking account of society’s underdogs, the research will necessarily be politically partisan <italic>in its effect</italic>, challenging dominant power structures, and thereby contributing to the goal of freedom and equality. Alvin Gouldner, in his equally famous article ‘Anti-Minotaur: The myth of a value-free sociology’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0309816813489936">1962</xref>), argued for what he termed ‘<italic>objective</italic> partisanship’, with research explicitly directed towards serving the goal of social improvement, with a commitment to a particular set of <italic>values</italic> (such as greater equality, democracy and social justice) rather than commitment to any particular social or political <italic>group</italic>. As we shall see, such underlying sentiments probably inform most industrial relations researchers, with partisanship referring to research which is underpinned by values and beliefs that reflect the researchers’ view of a progressive, more equal society, and which therefore lead them to be more sympathetic to the interests of employees than to employers, when studying the employment relationship.</p>
<p>The critical question is whether partisanship and objectivity are mutually exclusive. It follows from what has been said so far that – in common with the conclusions of critical realist (CR) philosophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0309816813489936">Sayer 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0309816813489936">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0309816813489936">Carter and New 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0309816813489936">Fleetwood and Ackroyd 2004</xref>) – while we reject the <italic>objectivist</italic> approach of positivism, with its notion of a completely value-free/impartial and objective social science, we also reject the <italic>subjectivist</italic> position, which assumes (as with postmodernism and social constructivism) that objective knowledge of a ‘real’ social world is not possible, and that all research is necessarily selective, interpretative and biased according to the actors’ and/or researchers’ subjective interpretations, and therefore all versions of events are equally valid. Instead, as the historians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0309816813489936">Carr (1987</xref>: 24) and Evans (1997: 224) have explained, because no ‘fact’ or ‘truth’ can be found outside a context of meaning, interpretation and judgment, it follows that the relationship between researchers and the social phenomena they investigate is mutually interdependent. It is impossible to assign primacy to facts or interpretation; both subject and object are in a continuous process in which the researcher moulds facts to interpretation and interpretation to facts. The researcher brings a distinct ‘perspective’ to an enquiry – a perspective that does not deny the possibility of achieving a degree of objectivity in investigation, but one which equally does not deny the presence and significance of the values and subjectivity of the observer. Hence the need for meta-theories that attempt to account for the interplay of social structures and agency.</p>
<p>While an objective social world <italic>does</italic> largely exist independently of the subjective interpretation of the researcher, since our understanding of it can only be refracted through the partisan interpretation of any individual researcher, some theories, descriptions and accounts of underlying structures and mechanisms that produce empirical events are likely to have greater explanatory power and provide more accurate portrayals than others, even taking into account the scholarly and verifiable methodology that may have been adopted. However, as CR has also insisted, while ‘truth-like’, robust knowledge is accessible, the fact that it is constrained, mediated and contingent also means it is inherently partial, fallible, and provisional.</p>
<p>In contrast to both objectivity and partisanship, ‘bias’ is something that cannot be defended. Bias refers to prejudice or distortion that derives from a conscious tendency on the part of the researcher to produce and interpret data in a way that inclines towards conclusions which are not grounded in verifiable ‘facts’ or sufficient evidence, but which merely reflect the researcher’s own predilections and political sympathies. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0309816813489936">Berrill (1983</xref>: 10) argued, bias goes ‘beyond the reporting of research findings [to] take up political positions or contain polemical expressions such as to lead the readers to doubt the objectivity of the writer’. Thus if the political values of the researcher necessarily shape the nature of research, they should not be allowed to bias conclusions or falsely be presented as validated by research. There <italic>is</italic> a fundamental distinction between factual inferences drawn from strict fidelity to the evidence, and evaluative or prescriptive ones that allow political sympathies to skew the research process. However, once the notion of partisanship is accepted, it is easy to see that the dividing line between ‘objective’ and ‘biased’ research can sometimes be very fine indeed.</p>
<p>We can now turn specifically to the relationship between objectivity and partisanship within the academic field of industrial relations research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0309816813489936">
<title>Partisanship in industrial relations research</title>
<p>Industrial relations research started at the end of the 19th century in Britain and the USA, and had its origin in what was then called the ‘labour problem’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0309816813489936">Kaufman 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0309816813489936">Frege 2008</xref>). The term ‘labour problem’ was revealing because it reflected a concern with maintaining social order: the key objective of the study of industrial relations was to find solutions to these problems and thereby preserve the status quo. In the 1890s, the perceived labour problems in Britain were essentially <italic>management</italic> problems: the spread of unionisation amongst unskilled workers, industrial conflict, unions becoming politically radicalised, and concerns about labour productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0309816813489936">Hyman 1989</xref>: 4). In the USA, despite the fact that labour problems included worker problems such as insecure employment, low pay, child labour and unsafe working conditions, as well as management problems of high labour turnover, ‘idle’ workers, and excessive waste and inefficiency in production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0309816813489936">Kaufman 1993</xref>: 4), underlying much of the discussion of industrial relations was the reformist agenda of ‘saving’ capitalism by making it work better (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0309816813489936">Frege 2008</xref>: 36-8).</p>
<p>This preoccupation with industrial relations problems or industrial relations as a ‘problem’ permeated the academic study of IR, with studies of union democracy, wage-drift, unofficial strikes, restrictive working practices and wage inflation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0309816813489936">Phelps Brown 1983</xref>: 2-11; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0309816813489936">Hyman 1989</xref>: 8; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0309816813489936">McCarthy 1994</xref>). Policy formulation and implementation was of central importance, with eminent academics accepting government appointments. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0309816813489936">Hyman (1975</xref>: ix) observed, research and analysis in industrial relations tended to ‘start from the assumption that stable and orderly relationships between employers and workers are normal and self-evidently desirable. Much of the literature is explicitly designed to advise managers how to maintain a tractable workforce.’</p>
<p>In this respect, Flanders’ famous quote (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0309816813489936">1967</xref>: 32) that ‘the paradox whose truth <italic>managements</italic> have found it difficult to accept, is that they can only <italic>regain control</italic> by sharing it’ (italics added) was particularly revealing. Similarly, the acceptability of the influential Donovan Report’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0309816813489936">1968</xref>) advocacy of the need for institutional reform was precisely because it was seen as serving managerial interests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0309816813489936">Hyman 1989</xref>: 10). Ironically, the alleged decline of the academic field of IR in Britain and the USA has led some writers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0309816813489936">Ackers and Wilkinson 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0309816813489936">Kaufmann 2008</xref>) to suggest a reorientation towards the study of management (and its strategies and influence on industrial relations practices) to make the subject more relevant, away from the supposedly outmoded preoccupation with trade unions, collective bargaining and strikes. But arguably, a ‘managerial turn’ would result in ‘turning Industrial Relations into an intellectual branch of HRM’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0309816813489936">Voskeritsian 2009</xref>: 11).</p>
<p>However, partisanship is more complicated and nuanced than IR academics simply serving managerial interests. Whilst often considering themselves ‘objective’, many British industrial relations academics (for example, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0309816813489936">Hollinshead et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0309816813489936">Blyton and Turnbull 2004</xref>; and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0309816813489936">Williams and Adam-Smith 2010</xref>), far from being completely neutral regarding the interests of employees and employers, have tended to start from a social-democratic or ‘labourist’ premise, and with a deeply held belief in social justice. This has made them relatively more sympathetic to the interests and objectives of workers and their trade unions than to the business needs of employers and managers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0309816813489936">Strauss and Whitfield 1998</xref>: 18), such that academics have often been viewed by employers and politicians as too ‘soft on unions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0309816813489936">McCarthy 1994</xref>: 210).</p>
<p>There are probably two main reasons for this partisanship. At least some leading IR academics in the post-war period had a personal history that came from the political left, or they had been workers who received their formal education as mature students, often at Ruskin College, Oxford (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0309816813489936">Fox 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0309816813489936">Kelly 2000</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0309816813489936">1</xref></sup> But in addition, there have always been solid academic reasons to explain why they favoured workers and trade unions, stemming from the subject’s view of the unequal nature of the employment relationship within which parties have contrasting and at times conflictual priorities and interests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0309816813489936">Fox 1974</xref>). Indeed, it is because the employment relationship is seen as being ‘indeterminate, continuous, exploitative and contradictory’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0309816813489936">Sisson 2008</xref>: 49) that it has naturally encouraged an academic interest in the struggles that take place within and around it. Unilateral management regulation is seen as neither fair nor efficient, while trade unions and collective bargaining are viewed as indispensable means of mitigating the power imbalance. Thus IR could only abandon its traditional sympathy with worker interests by abandoning its traditional view of the unequal nature of the employment relationship.</p>
<p>This should not in any way be taken to suggest that IR academics have been so ‘biased’ in their research that it has compromised their scholarly credibility. In the early 1980s, Warwick University’s prestigious Industrial Relations Research Unit (IRRU), at that time funded by the Social Science Research Council, was accused of being ‘unfairly biased in favour of the unions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0309816813489936">Rothschild 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0309816813489936">Brown 1998</xref>). An inquiry reported only one or two instances in which the IRRU’s publications could be judged to have been less than totally objective (specifically in relation to the government’s 1981 employment legislative proposals), and concluded that ‘the accusation of bias in the published research work (of the Unit) has not been substantiated’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0309816813489936">Berrill 1983</xref>: 17). Nonetheless, the Berrill Report assumed a very traditional approach to partisanship in social science research, reminding all members of the Unit that they should not act in a way that would ‘jeopardise the impartiality and objectivity of the Unit’. Similarly, while the British Universities Industrial Relations Association’s AGM expressed support for the independence of IRRU, its simultaneous request for ‘discretion on the part of the membership’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0309816813489936">Berridge and Goodman 1988</xref>: 166) seemed to implicitly acknowledge the political assumptions and sympathies of some researchers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0309816813489936">
<title>The ‘radical/critical’ approach to industrial relations research</title>
<p>Partisanship is more clearly visible in the work of those who adopt a ‘radical’ or ‘critical’ analysis of the employment relationship. Notable in this respect has been <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0309816813489936">Richard Hyman’s (1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0309816813489936">1989</xref>) advocacy for a ‘political economy of industrial relations’ that examines the employment relationship within its broader <italic>capitalist</italic> totality. From such a vantage point, inequality, exploitative working conditions and social justice figure more prominently than do the problems of how to secure ‘employee engagement’ to managerial goals. Similar partisanship is to be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0309816813489936">Kelly’s (1998)</xref> research, focused on the process of collective worker mobilisation against employers and governments. Moreover, some of the most insightful workplace case studies, such as <italic>Working for Ford</italic> (Beynon 1973), <italic>Girls, Wives and Factory Lives</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0309816813489936">Pollert 1981</xref>), and <italic>Cultures of Solidarity</italic> (Fantasia 1989), have been written by researchers who have done little to mask their overwhelming empathy with worker and trade union organisation and activity in resisting management. Stewart at al.’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0309816813489936">2009</xref>) study of car workers’ struggles against ‘management by stress’, <italic>We Sell Our Time No More</italic>, stands in the same tradition.</p>
<p>Some researchers believe that there should be a direct relationship between their political and social outlook and their research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0309816813489936">Darlington 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0309816813489936">Darlington and Lyddon 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0309816813489936">Foster and Woolfson, 1986</xref>; Fantasia 1989; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0309816813489936">Green 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0309816813489936">1993</xref>). In his <italic>Preface to Strikes</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0309816813489936">Hyman (1972</xref>: 8) justified the adoption of an unequivocal partisan stance:<disp-quote>
<p>It is virtually obligatory for any academic writing on an acutely controversial topic to make ritual genuflections in the direction of objectivity. I am sceptical of such moralistics … My commitment to the traditional humanistic goals of freedom and reason colours the treatment of my subject… I cannot profess neutrality. And since I consider it more illuminating to view conflict as a natural response to specific social and institutional arrangements in industry, rather than as the outcome of human wilfulness and irrationality, my approach to strikes is scarcely orthodox.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Likewise, Ralph Darlington has always made his own partisanship explicit – for example, stating that his study of shop stewards’ organisation on Merseyside was ‘written within the general framework of a revolutionary socialist approach and devoted to assisting those everywhere engaged in the battle to advance the struggle against capital’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0309816813489936">1994</xref>, 10). His study of the strike wave in Britain in 1972 aimed to be ‘a guidebook of militant working class struggle’, such that a future generation could ‘learn from, and hopefully will surpass, that “glorious summer”’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0309816813489936">Darlington and Lyddon 2001</xref>: 230-31). Similarly, those academics associated with the Critical Labour Studies network view work and employment from a radical and labour-focused perspective, exploring the conditions, issues and causes that give rise to conflict, and the nature and dynamics of resistance mounted in opposition to neoliberal capitalism by workers, trade unions and a diverse range of social movements. Labour process theory (LPT) also avows a critical and pro-worker partisanship (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0309816813489936">Thompson and Smith 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Arguably, it is precisely <italic>because of</italic> their partisan perspective that ‘radical/critical’ IR researchers have often made such a distinctive contribution to understanding and documenting the underlying conflictual nature of the employment relationship. In the process, they have generally provided a comparatively more accurate depiction than the equally partisan, albeit inverted, mainstream HRM paradigm adherents, with their exaggerated emphasis on the perceived extent of employee co-operation with management. However, we should note the insightful and valuable contribution being made by the growing numbers associated with critical management studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0309816813489936">Alvesson and Wilmott 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0309816813489936">Tadajewski et al. 2011</xref>), who have in varying degrees pursued open partisanship on the side of those subordinated in the labour process and labour market and/or in support of alternatives to hierarchical, authoritarian and market dominated forms of management.</p>
<p>In adopting such an approach, radical/critical writers have effectively followed in the tradition of C. Wright Mills, who in <italic>The Sociological Imagination</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0309816813489936">1959</xref>) advocated the role of the intellectual as being to create an informed and radical public that would challenge those who currently exercise power, and thereby generate political action to transform society. It is a stance recently reinforced by Burowoy’s call for an <italic>organic public sociology</italic>, underpinned by the ‘sociologist as partisan’ who defends the ‘social and ‘represents humanity’ in an era of ‘market tyranny and state despotism’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0309816813489936">2007</xref>: 55; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0309816813489936">2008</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0309816813489936">Brook and Darlington, 2013</xref>). Despite the fact that critical realism has only received passing attention within the field of IR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0309816813489936">Edwards 2006</xref>), radical/critical scholars would no doubt concur with its view of knowledge as being ‘transformative’ and emancipatory, with ‘epistemic gain’ measured against practical social progress.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0309816813489936">
<title>The limits of partisanship</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0309816813489936">Fantasia (1988</xref>: 247) argued that data collection would have been impossible in his study of wildcat strikes in the US steel-casting foundry, without the trust generated by partisanship, in this case extending to participation both as a worker and a striker. He noted that workers had an understandable mistrust of ‘outsiders’, who they believed would help to advance managerial interests. Without his participation, ‘it is likely that I would have been “frozen out” of the strike community altogether and that I would have had to abandon research on the strike’ (p. 251). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0309816813489936">Green (1990</xref>: 208), whose research on the 1984-5 British miners’ strike has been criticised on the basis that her close association with striking miners compromised her objectivity, argued that ‘my political sympathies facilitated research, because striking miners and their wives were able to report their experiences and opinions freely in an atmosphere of trust’. However, both Fantasia and Green acknowledged that there was a ‘research price’ to be paid for their partisanship, with areas of investigation being closed off. Green (p. 53) noted that her support for the striking miners may have inhibited interviews with working miners, and Fantasia (p. 251) found that ‘my pro-strike stance meant that anti-strike elements (the employer, strikebreakers) could not easily be approached’, and that therefore, ‘while partisanship may be necessary to facilitate research, it also hinders it, and future researchers would do well to consider the costs and benefits beforehand’ (p. 251).</p>
<p>Clearly there <italic>are</italic> some complex issues, dilemmas, and tensions to be navigated in adopting a methodological approach that states, to use the words of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0309816813489936">Wright Mills (1962</xref>: 11), ‘I have tried to be objective, but I do not claim to be detached’. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0309816813489936">Gall (2003</xref>: 320) has pointed out, for Marxist IR academics there are the pitfalls of having a research agenda or perspective which is set by narrow concerns such as the programme of an organisation/current; ‘bending the stick’ too far to support and back up the perspective of a particular organisation or current without the intellectual independence to contradict; and seeking refuge in merely asserting faith over evidence. Yet while the potential for IR researchers to superimpose their own politically-informed perspectives in a way that distorts the evidence <italic>can</italic> be a real one, whether this <italic>actually</italic> occurs can itself be open to debate and contrasting interpretation. <italic>Working for Ford</italic> was condemned by Ford management for its ‘doubtful value as an objective sociological study, on the basis that ‘Beynon comes so much to identify himself with the stewards’, but was defended by stewards and workers as an authentic portrayal of life in a car factory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0309816813489936">Beynon 1984</xref>: 11-15; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0309816813489936">1988</xref>).</p>
<p>While readers of such partisan-influenced studies are not obliged to share the political assumptions underpinning the research, they do have the right to demand that they should not simply be the defence of a political position, but rather an internally well-grounded analysis, interpretation and portrayal of the actual underlying social processes of the employment relationship. Yet ironically, some of the academics who have complained that radical/critical researchers have allowed political commitment to cloud their judgement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0309816813489936">Fielding 2002</xref>) have failed to answer the similar charge that could be levelled against themselves, albeit with different political predilections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0309816813489936">Mcllroy 2010</xref>: 106).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0309816813489936">
<title>Active participants</title>
<p>A separate question is that of whether partisan academic researchers should limit their involvement to research, or become <italic>active participants</italic>, for example, by taking the side of workers and trade unions in struggles against employers by fundraising, writing supportive press articles, addressing union meetings, or signing and publicising statements in support of strikes. For example, more than 100 academics signed a letter published in the <italic>Guardian</italic> (25 March 2010) condemning the ‘macho-management’ of British Airways (BA) and supporting striking BA cabin crew. Ralph Darlington and Gregor Gall addressed a mass meeting of BASSA (Unite) strikers,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0309816813489936">2</xref></sup> whilst Martin Upchurch produced a report, commissioned by the Unite union, which documented ‘an embedded culture of bullying and authoritarianism deliberately engineered from the top echelons of the company’, which was ‘clearly designed to intimidate cabin crew union members’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0309816813489936">2010</xref>: 1). Such initiatives provoked objections from within business schools that academic staff were engaging in ‘biased’ activities linked to the trade union movement. But should it be uncontroversial for academics to support management or companies (even when the ethics of such companies are questionable) through consultancy, management education, training and research, and yet questionable for them to support workers and unions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0309816813489936">Martinez Lucio 2010</xref>)?</p>
<p>While some IR academics support the notion that they should directly relate to, support and even contribute to trade unions and their attempts to revitalise their organisations, there is nothing comparable in Britain to the research-based US journals <italic>New Labor Forum</italic> and <italic>Working USA</italic>, which are broadly aimed at a trade union and worker audience. Nonetheless, in recent years the Critical Labour Studies network has made an explicit and significant contribution, through a series of symposiums and other forums, to facilitating joint dialogue, networking and practical engagement between academic researchers and labour/union and social movement activists. More generally, there are many other individual academics and small research groups producing research and advice for particular union/movement campaigns or initiatives, and through their active engagement helping to break down barriers between scholars and those who constitute the substance of ‘their’ labour process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0309816813489936">Stewart and Martinez Lucio 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Meanwhile, in recent years there has been some debate within the British Universities Industrial Relations Association (BUIRA) as to whether a professional association, established to promote and support the field of IR, should intervene in industrial disputes and other political causes in which some of its members are involved. The issue was highlighted in 2008, when the BUIRA executive vigorously opposed Keele University’s closure of the Centre for Industrial Relations by launching an open letter signed by 435 members and other supporters from across the world, paying for a half-page advertisement in the <italic>Guardian</italic>, and encouraging its members to participate in protest rallies organised by University College Union (UCU). BUIRA subsequently published a statement and book, <italic>What’s the Point of Industrial Relations?</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0309816813489936">Darlington 2009</xref>), which mounted a strong intellectual and policy defence of the academic field of IR, in the process challenging both HRM and the marketisation of higher education. While such a partisan stance received backing from the vast majority of BUIRA members, some prominent IR academics criticised the executive for pushing the Association towards trade union-type activity, which they believed would compromise BUIRA’s professional and academic independence and credibility.</p>
<p>In Britain, these tensions are likely to be exacerbated over the next few years amidst funding cutbacks, the reconfiguration of post-16 education, the threat to academics’ pensions, salaries, jobs and conditions of service, as well as to social science generally and the very notion of education as a ‘public good’. In this respect, if the 2010-12 UCU campaign of one-day strikes over pensions ‘brought home’ in sharp relief the relevance of the subject matter of industrial relations to its academic specialists within higher education, it also underlined the importance of IR academics as <italic>trade unionists</italic> whose partisan ideological and practical intervention is an integral part of their identity and portfolio at work. Moreover, in the context of a higher education system subject to the pressures of research funding, academic journal publications, the Research Excellence Framework (REF), ‘impact’ factors, and career survival and/or advancement, the professional study of industrial relations (as with social sciences generally) is likely to be confronted with ever increasing constraints on the nature of academic inquiry, the process of research, and the presentation and interpretation of evidence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0309816813489936" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Far from being some kind of unwelcome intruder, partisanship is an essential ingredient of research that can produce real insights of value to all. While there <italic>are</italic> real dangers that partisanship <italic>may</italic> lead to biased research, it would be an error to suppose that it necessarily does so, or that the distortions potentially involved are confined to partisanship research. While it may not be easy, it <italic>is</italic> possible for research to be <italic>both</italic> partisan <italic>and</italic> objective. But to ensure partisan research is ‘objective’, it should not only be grounded on scientific research methods, but also involve a self-critical and self-conscious examination of the basic value-commitments that inform research in order to understand how they relate to the enquiry at hand, with the researcher the first to find flaws in his or her own interpretation, so as to avoid the danger of bias. There should be a publicly accessible declaration of, inter alia, membership, affiliation or support for any (social or political) party/movement on the part of the author(s), and the nature/source of any funding that has assisted in the research process. Such an approach would have two benefits: authors would need to strive for transparency in order to avoid any inference that political affiliation or source of funding had introduced bias into their work or flawed the methodology; and readers would be able to make a judgement themselves as to whether and how such factors had deliberately or accidentally influenced the work.</p>
<p>Whatever the nature of partisanship, research, it could be argued, should primarily be about the pursuit of knowledge, and should be judged on the extent to which it increases knowledge, not by whether it is successful in advancing the cause of whatever values or groups to which the researcher is sympathetic. But at the very least, an important and desirable by-product of researching and documenting workers’ collective forms of resistance to employers and governments is that it may make some contribution to attempts by workers and their industrial and political organisations to redress the imbalance of power in the employment relationship, and to create a more equal society.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0309816813489936">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Academics who studied at Ruskin include Alan Fox, Sid Kessler, Bill McCarthy, and Roger Undy. Academics with a left political history include Hugh Clegg, Allan Flanders, Richard Hyman, and John Kelly. Michael Barrett Brown, Ken Coates, Tony Topham and Brian Towers identified with workers through the WEA or extra-mural teaching.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0309816813489936">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Speeches given 3 June 2010. Uploaded to YouTube &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com">www.youtube.com</ext-link>&gt; as ‘Professor Ralph Darlington speaks to BA Cabin Crew @ Bedfont FC‘, and ‘Professor Gall speaks to BA Cabin Crew @ Bedfont FC’.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Ralph Darlington</bold> is a professor of employment relations at the University of Salford. He is the author of <italic>The Dynamics of Workplace Unionism</italic> (Mansell, 1994) and <italic>Syndicalism and the Transition to Communism: An International Comparative Analysis</italic> (second edition, 2013). He is co-author of <italic>Glorious Summer: Class Struggle in Britain, 1972</italic> (Bookmarks, 2001) and editor of <italic>What’s the Point of Industrial Relations? In Defence of Critical Social Science</italic> (BUIRA, 2009).</p>
<p><bold>John Dobson</bold> has published widely on the operation of labour markets in Central and Eastern Europe, and is currently an associated professor at Riga International College of Economics and Business Administration, Latvia. He was previously a senior lecturer in industrial relations at the University of Salford, where he was head of the School of Management (2002-6) and president of the Salford Branch of the University and College Union (UCU) from 2007-9. He also served on the UCU National Executive from 2009-11.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ackers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Industrial relations and the social sciences</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Blyton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiorito</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heery</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>The Sage Handbook of Industrial Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Alvesson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willmott</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) (<year>2003</year>) <source>Studying Management Critically</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>A strategy for industrial relations research in Great Britain</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Whose side are we on?</article-title> <source>Social Problems</source> <volume>14</volume> (<season>Winter</season>): <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>The British Universities Industrial Relations Association: The first 35 years</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berrill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Report of an Investigation into Certain Matters Arising from the Rothschild Report on the Social Science Research Council</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Social Science Research Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Working for Ford</source>. <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Regulating research: Politics and decision making in industrial organisations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bryman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Doing Research in Organisations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blyton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>The Dynamics of Employee Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Basingstoke</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Darlington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Partisan, scholarly and active: Arguments for an organic public sociology of work</article-title>. <source>Work, Employment &amp; Society</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>232</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Employment with a Human Face: Balancing Efficiency, Equity and Voice</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>BUIRA</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>‘What’s the point of Industrial Relations?’</article-title> <source>A Statement by the British Universities Industrial Relations Association</source>, <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>BUIRA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burawoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Response: Public sociology: Populist fad or path to renewal?</article-title> <source>The British Journal of Sociology</source> <volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burawoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The public turn: From the labor process to labor movement</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Funders and research: The vulnerability of the subject</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Researching the World of Work: Strategies and Methods in Studying Industrial Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ILR Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>, <edition>second edition</edition>) <source>What is History?</source> <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>New</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Making Realism Work: Realist Social Theory and Empirical Research</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Darlington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>The Dynamics of Workplace Unionism</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mansell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Darlington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>What’s the Point of Industrial Relations? In Defence of Critical Social Science</source>. <publisher-loc>Salford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>British Universities Industrial Relations Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Darlington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyddon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Glorious Summer: Class Struggle in Britain,1972</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bookmarks</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>Lord</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <source>Royal Commission on Trade Unions and Employers’ Associations 1965-1968</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HMSO</publisher-name>, Cmnd. 3623.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Industrial relations and critical realism: IR’s tacit contribution</article-title>. <source>Warwick Papers in Industrial Relations</source> <volume>80</volume>. <publisher-loc>IRRU</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Warwick</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <source>In Defence of History</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Granta Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fantasia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Cultures of Solidarity: Consciousness, Action and Contemporary American Workers</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>‘New’ labour and the ‘new’ labour history</article-title>. <source>Mitteilungsblatt des Instituts fur soziale Bewegungen</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flanders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <source>Collective Bargaining: Prescription for Change</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Faber and Faber</publisher-name>, reprinted in Flanders A (1970) <italic>Management and Unions: The Theory and Reform of Industrial Relations</italic>. London: Faber and Faber, pp. <fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fleetwood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ackroyd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) (<year>2004</year>) <source>Critical Realist Applications in Organisation and Management Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woolfson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>The Politics of the UCS Work-In: Class Alliances and the Right to Work</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence and Wishart</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <source>Beyond Contract: Work, Power and Trust Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Faber and Faber</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>A Very Late Development: An Autobiography</source>. <publisher-loc>Warwick University</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Industrial Relations Research Unit</publisher-name>, reprinted by BUIRA in 2004.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frege</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The history of industrial relations as a field of study</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Blyton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiorito</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heery</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>The Sage Handbook of Industrial Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Marxism and industrial relations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ackers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Understanding Work and Employment: Industrial Relations in Transition</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>316</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gouldner</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Anti-Minotaur: The myth of a value-free sociology</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>The Enemy Without: Policing and Class Consciousness in the Miners’ Strike</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Taking sides: Partisan research in the 1984-5 miners’ strike</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>May</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Interpreting the Field: Accounts of Ethnography</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammersley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Taking Sides in Social Research: Essays on Partisanship and Bias</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hobsbawm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Partisanship</article-title>. In <source>On History</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Abacus</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>164</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hollinshead</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tailby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Employee Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Harlow</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FT/Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>Strikes</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fontana/Collins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>Industrial Relations: A Marxist Introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>Houndmills</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>The Political Economy of Industrial Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Houndmills</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The Origins and Evolution of the Field of Industrial Relations in the United States</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ILR Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Paradigms in industrial relations: Original, modern and versions in-between</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>314</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Rethinking Industrial Relations: Mobilisation, Collectivism and Long Waves</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Social democracy and anti-communism: Allan Flanders and British industrial relations in the early Post-War period</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mcllroy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>British Trade Unions and Industrial Politics, Volume One: Consensus and Boom, 1945-64</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kochan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>What is distinctive about industrial relations?</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Researching the World of Work: Strategies and Methods in Studying Industrial Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornel University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martinez Lucio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>We need to teach the reality of work and not the fantasy of what we think work consists of</article-title>. <italic>Transforming Management website</italic>, &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tm.mbs.ac.uk">http://tm.mbs.ac.uk</ext-link>&gt;.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The involvement of academics in British industrial relations</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mcllroy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The society for the study of labour history, 1956-1985: Its origins and its heyday</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mcllroy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Making History: Organisations of Labour Historians in Britain Since 1960</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Maney Publishing</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>) <source>The Sociological Imagination</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1962</year>) <source>The Marxists</source>. <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phelps Brown</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>The Origins of Trade Union Power</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarendon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pollert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <source>Girls, Wives, Factory Lives</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>Lord</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>An Enquiry into the Social Science Research Council</source>. Cmnd 8554. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HMSO</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>Method in Social Science: A Realist Approach</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Realism and Social Science</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Industrial relations: Challenges and opportunities</article-title>. <source>Employee Relations</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Putting the record straight: Industrial relations and the employment relationship</article-title>. <source>Warwick Papers in Industrial Relations</source> <volume>88</volume>. <publisher-name>Industrial Relations Research Unit</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wass</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>We Sell Our Time No More: Workers’ Struggles against Lean Production in the British Car Industry</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez Lucio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Collective narratives and politics in the contemporary study of work: The new management practices debate</article-title>. <source>Work, Employment and Society</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Research methods in industrial relations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Researching the World of Work: Strategies and Methods in Studying Industrial Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Tadajewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maclaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) (<year>2001</year>) <source>Key Concepts in Critical Management Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Labour power and labour process: Contesting the marginality of the sociology of work</article-title>. <source>Sociology</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>913</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Upchurch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Creating a Sustainable Work Environment in British Airways: Implications of the 2010 Cabin Crew Dispute</source>. Technical Report, <publisher-name>Middlesex University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Voskeritsian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Richard Hyman, the role of theory and the disciplinary boundaries of industrial relations: A thirty-year retrospective</article-title>. <conf-name>British Journal of Industrial Relations Conference in Honour of Richard Hyman</conf-name>, <conf-loc>LSE</conf-loc>, <conf-date>28-29 May 2009</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adam-Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Contemporary Employment Relations: A Critical Introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0309816813489936">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winchester</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Industrial relations research in Britain</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>100</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>