<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjop</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Psychopharmacol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Psychopharmacology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0269-8811</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7285</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269881112454230</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269881112454230</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Group II metabotropic glutamate receptor type 2 allosteric potentiators prevent sodium lactate-induced panic-like response in panic-vulnerable rats</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Philip L</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0269881112454230">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fitz</surname><given-names>Stephanie D</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0269881112454230">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Engleman</surname><given-names>Eric A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0269881112454230">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>Kjell A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0269881112454230">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Schkeryantz</surname><given-names>Jeffrey M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0269881112454230">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>Anantha</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0269881112454230">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0269881112454230"><label>1</label>Institute of Psychiatric Research, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0269881112454230"><label>2</label>Eli Lilly &amp; Co., Indianapolis, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0269881112454230">Philip L Johnson, 791 Union Dr, Institute of Psychiatric Research, Indianapolis, IN, 46202, USA. Email: <email>philjohn@iupui.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>152</fpage>
<lpage>161</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">British Association for Psychopharmacology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Rats with chronic inhibition of GABA synthesis by infusion of l-allyglycine, a glutamic acid decarboxylase inhibitor, into their dorsomedial/perifornical hypothalamus are anxious and exhibit panic-like cardio-respiratory responses to treatment with intravenous (i.v.) sodium lactate (NaLac) infusions, in a manner similar to what occurs in patients with panic disorder. We previously showed that either NMDA receptor antagonists or metabotropic glutamate receptor type 2/3 receptor agonists can block such a NaLac response, suggesting that a glutamate mechanism is contributing to this panic-like state. Using this animal model of panic, we tested the efficacy of CBiPES and THIIC, which are selective group II metabotropic glutamate type 2 receptor allosteric potentiators (at 10–30mg/kg i.p.), in preventing NaLac-induced panic-like behavioral and cardiovascular responses. The positive control was alprazolam (3mg/kg i.p.), a clinically effective anti-panic benzodiazepine. As predicted, panic-prone rats given a NaLac challenge displayed NaLac-induced panic-like cardiovascular (i.e. tachycardia and hypertensive) responses and “anxiety” (i.e. decreased social interaction time) and “flight” (i.e. increased locomotion) -associated behaviors; however, systemic injection of the panic-prone rats with CBiPES, THIIC or alprazolam prior to the NaLac dose blocked all NaLac-induced panic-like behaviors and cardiovascular responses. These data suggested that in a rat animal model, selective group II metabotropic glutamate type 2 receptor allosteric potentiators show an anti-panic efficacy similar to alprazolam.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>CBiPES</kwd>
<kwd>THIIC</kwd>
<kwd>panic</kwd>
<kwd>anxiety</kwd>
<kwd>alprazolam</kwd>
<kwd>glutamate receptor</kwd>
<kwd>GABA</kwd>
<kwd>hypothalamus</kwd>
<kwd>social interaction</kwd>
<kwd>stress</kwd>
<kwd>pre-clinical study</kwd>
<kwd>sodium lactate</kwd>
<kwd>tachycardia</kwd>
<kwd>hypertension</kwd>
<kwd>anti-panic drugs</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0269881112454230" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Panic disorder is a severe anxiety disorder characterized by recurring “spontaneous” panic attacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0269881112454230">Weissman and Merikangas, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269881112454230">Kessler et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269881112454230">Hirschfeld, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0269881112454230">Katon et al., 2002</xref>) that, although considered spontaneous, can be consistently provoked in the majority of panic disorder patients by using mild interoceptive stimuli such as intravenous (i.v.) infusions of 0.5M sodium lactate (NaLac) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0269881112454230">Liebowitz et al., 1984</xref>) or inhalation of 7% CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269881112454230">Gorman et al., 1994</xref>) as challenges. This suggests that the threshold for some interoceptive stimuli to be able to induce a panic response is reduced in patients with panic disorder, which has led to the hypothesis that the initial pathology in these patients appears to be an alteration somewhere in the central neural pathways that are critical sites for responding to disruptive interoceptive stimuli and regulating normal panic responses.</p>
<p>Although a number of limbic and autonomic regulatory centers have been implicated in the pathophysiology of panic disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269881112454230">Gorman et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 2003</xref>), the dorsomedial hypothalamus (DMH) is one such panic-related site, which not only coordinates autonomic and behavioral responses for a variety of homeostatic mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269881112454230">Bernardis and Bellinger, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269881112454230">DiMicco et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269881112454230">Chou et al., 2003</xref>), but is also an important efferent target of circumventricular organs (CVOs) that are critical for sensing changes in interoceptive-associated plasma parameters such as NaLac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269881112454230">Molosh et al., 2010</xref>). In light of this, Shekhar and colleagues developed an animal model of panic disorder, where chronically disrupting the inhibitory GABAergic activity (where GABA stands for gamma-aminobutyric acid) by infusion of the GABA synthesis inhibitor l-allylglycine (l–AG) into the dorsomedial/perifornical hypothalamus (DMH/PeF) produces rats that have heightened anxiety and display panic-like responses following exposure to i.v. infusions of 0.5 M NaLac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2010</xref>). Consistent with this, panic disorder patients do demonstrate deficits in central GABA concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269881112454230">Goddard et al., 2001</xref>) and a hyperactive hypothalamus during anticipatory anxiety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269881112454230">Boshuisen et al., 2002</xref>). Additionally, benzodiazepine agonists (which enhance GABA activity) attenuate NaLac-induced panic attacks in panic patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0269881112454230">Pohl et al., 1994</xref>), as well as NaLac-induced panic-like responses in panic-prone rats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2010</xref>). Because they are rapid and effective, benzodiazepines have been the most widely used class of drugs for the treatment of acute anxiety since the 1960s, yet there are significant and common side effects, such as sedation, memory impairment and dependence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0269881112454230">Nutt et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269881112454230">Baldwin et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269881112454230">Bandelow et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269881112454230">Cloos and Ferreira, 2009</xref>); therefore, there is a great need for newer, rapidly effective anxiolytic agents without the typical benzodiazepine side effects.</p>
<p>Recent evidence suggests that there is a balance between tonic GABAergic inhibition and the glutamate-mediated excitation within the DMH/PeF that makes rats vulnerable to NaLac-induced panic responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>). Under basal conditions, the activity of DMH neurons is regulated by a tonic GABAergic inhibition of the excitatory glutamatergic drive (Soltis and DiMicco, 1991). However, when the GABAergic inhibitory tone is reduced with l-AG infusions, the glutamate-mediated excitation appears to become prominent, leading to chronic activation and a panic-prone state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>). In light of this, there is increasing recognition that glutamatergic mechanisms may offer a potential avenue for developing new treatment for anxiety problems such as panic disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269881112454230">Gorman, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>In one review, the two Group II metabotropic glutamate receptors (mGluR2/3) are shown to be activated by excess synaptic glutamate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269881112454230">Nicoletti et al., 2010</xref>), while conversely, they negatively modulate presynaptic glutamate neurotransmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0269881112454230">Pin and Duvoisin, 1995</xref>). This suggests that mGluR2/3 potentiators could possibly reduce excessive synaptic glutamate release in panic-prone rats, to reduce panic vulnerability without altering basal glutamate release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2005</xref>). Consistent with this hypothesis, mGluR2/3 agonists do reduce anxiety-associated behaviors in rodents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269881112454230">Monn et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269881112454230">Helton et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0269881112454230">Walker and Davis, 2002</xref>) and also have anxiolytic properties in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269881112454230">Grillon, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0269881112454230">Schoepp et al., 2003</xref>) without any of the benzodiazepine-associated side effects, such as sedation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0269881112454230">Schoepp et al., 2003</xref>). Anxiolytic-like properties have also been observed for several mGluR2 potentiators, including CBiPES (N-(4′-cyano-biphenyl-3-yl)-N-(3-pyridinylmethyl)-(ethanesulfonamide hydrochloride)), which readily reverses stress-induced changes in body temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2005</xref>). Recently, we found evidence of the antidepressant and anxiolytic-like effects of the mGluR2 potentiator designated as THIIC (having the formula N-(4-{[3-hydroxy-4-(2-methylpropanoyl)-2- (trifluoromethyl)phenoxy]methyl}benzyl)-1-methyl-1H-imidazole-4-carboxamide), including the reversal of stress-induced hyperthermia and in decreased marble-burying behavior and efficacy, in the mouse forced swim test and DRL–72 test in the rat, respectively (Fell et al., 2011). Data generated with mGluR2 knockout mice clearly suggest that these effects are mediated via the mGluR2 receptor. Also, in vitro data indicate that mGlu2R2 potentiators suppress glutamate release under conditions of enhanced, but not normal, glutamate release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2005</xref>) indicating that this kind of therapy could be an advantageous approach to stabilizing glutamatergic tone with reduced side effect liability. To further test our excessive glutamate-based hypothesis, in this study panic-prone rats were pretreated with either vehicle, the two mGlu2 potentiators (CBiPES and THIIC), or the benzodiazepine alprazolam prior to exerting a panic provocation with NaLac.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0269881112454230" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods and materials</title>
<sec id="section3-0269881112454230">
<title>Animals and housing conditions</title>
<p>All experiments were conducted on adult male Sprague-Dawley rats (300–350 g), which were purchased from Harlan Laboratories and were housed individually, in plastic cages under standard environmental conditions (22 ºC; 12/12 light/dark cycle; lights on at 7:00 am) for 7–10 days prior to the surgical manipulations. Food and water were provided <italic>ad libitum</italic>. Animal care procedures were conducted in accordance with the <italic>NIH Guidelines for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic> (US National Institute of Health Publication #80–23), revised in 1996, and the guidelines of the IUPUI Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0269881112454230">
<title>Surgical procedures, cardiovascular and locomotor activity assessment, and osmotic minipump infusions</title>
<p>Prior to and during surgery, rats were anesthetized with a nose cone connected to an isoflurane system (MGX Research Machine; Vetamic, Rossville, IN). Rats were surgically fitted with femoral arterial catheters for measurement of mean arterial blood pressure (MAP) and heart rate (HR), and with femoral venous catheters for i.v. infusions, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>Cardiovascular responses (i.e. MAP and HR) were measured by a femoral arterial line connected to a telemetric probe, which contained a pressure transducer (Cat. no. C50–PXT, Data Science International (DSI), St. Paul, MN). The C50–PXT probes also assess general motor activity. DSI Dataquest software was used to monitor and record MAP, HR and general motor activity, which was recorded continuously in the freely-moving conscious rats and were expressed as a 20-min time course. Data reported for each rat are: changes in MAP, HR and motor activity from the average of the baseline (5 min prior to the NaLac infusion, from <italic>t</italic> = −5 min to <italic>t</italic> = −1 min).</p>
<p>After 3 days of recovery, the rats were tested for baseline cardiovascular responses to lactate (see below). Following baseline testing, rats were anesthetized as stated previously and 26 gauge T-shaped cannulae (Cat. no. 3260PG, Plastics One Inc., Roanoake, VA) were directed at the cardio-excitatory regions of the DMH/PeF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0269881112454230">Samuels et al., 2004</xref>), based on coordinates (from bregma: 1.2 mm posterior, +2.1 mm lateral, +9.1 mm ventral; adjusted for approaching at a 10 degree angle toward the midline, with the stereotaxic incisor bar elevated 5 mm above the interaural line) and cemented into place, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 1996</xref>). The 22-gauge side arm was then attached, using PE–60 tubing, to an osmotic minipump (prefilled with l–AG solution) and sutured into place subcutaneously, at the nape of the neck (DURECT Corporation, Model no. 2002). The concentration of the solutions was such that 3.5 nmol/0.5µl per hour of l–AG was continuously infused into the DMH/PeF region, for the remainder of the given experiment.</p>
<p>Previous studies determined that the dose of l–AG that we utilized here reduces local GABA concentrations by approximately 60%, following unilateral infusions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269881112454230">Abshire et al., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 2006</xref>), and was supported by immunohistochemistry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>) and increased anxiety-like behavior (i.e. as measured by the social interaction (SI) test and elevated plus-maze (EPM)), without increasing the cardiorespiratory responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0269881112454230">
<title>Social interaction test to measure anxiety responses</title>
<p>The social interaction (SI) test is a fully validated test of experimental anxiety-like behavior in rats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269881112454230">File, 1980</xref>) and the procedure, as used in our laboratory, has been described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0269881112454230">Sanders and Shekhar, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Katner, 1995</xref>). The apparatus itself consists of a solid wooden box with an open roof approximately 0.9 m long x 0.9 m wide, with walls 0.3 m high. All behavioral tests are videotaped by a camera located above the box. The “experimental” rat and an unfamiliar “partner” rat are both allowed to individually habituate to the box for a 5-min period, 24 h prior to each SI test. During the SI test, the two rats are placed together in the center of the box, so that the total duration (in seconds) of non-aggressive physical contact (grooming, sniffing, crawling over and under, etc.) initiated by the “experimental” rat is quantified over a 5-min period. A baseline SI test was performed 72+ h after i.v. catheterization, but prior to osmotic minipump implantation. Another SI test was performed 5 days following minipump infusions, and also immediately following either saline control or sodium lactate infusions. Videotaped sessions were scored at a later time (by SDF), whom was blind to any drug treatment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0269881112454230">
<title>Experiment 1: Effects on 1–AG infusion into the DMH/PeF on the local tissue concentrations of GABA and glutamate</title>
<p>Adult male rats were made panic-prone by the 5-day unilateral infusions of l–AG into the DMH/PeF, as described above. On day 5, rats were anaesthetized with isoflurane and then decapitated; their brains were removed and frozen in isopentane that was pre-cooled (–50°C) on dry ice; then sectioned coronally at 300 µm thickness on a cryostat, placed on glass slides that were pre-cooled on dry ice prior to the micropunching of tissue from the hypothalamus. Next, the DMH tissue was dissected with a Microtome tissue micropunch (inside diameter = 0.51mm) from the ipsilateral and contralateral DMH, for use in high performance liquid chromotography (HPLC) analysis of the GABA concentrations in order to determine the effectiveness of the l–AG pumps, and of glutamate to determine if this 1–AG pre-treatment led to an increase in glutamate concentrations. Once micropunched, the remaining tissue samples were frozen at −70ºC.</p>
<sec id="section7-0269881112454230">
<title>GABA analysis</title>
<p>During extraction, 500 µl of 0.5M perchloric acid was added to each sample and the samples were left to stand at 4ºC for at least 24 h. Samples were then sonicated on ice for 15 sec and centrifuged at 14,000 x g for 10 min using a microfuge. The supernatant was decanted and alkalized with 36 µl of 10 M NaOH, briefly vortexed, and stored at 4ºC until assayed for GABA content. GABA content in the samples was measured by HPLC with electrochemical detection following o-phthalaldehyde/sulfite derivatization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269881112454230">Bourdelais and Kalivas, 1991</xref>). Briefly, samples were loaded into an autosampler and 20 µl of sample was mixed with 20 µl of derivatizing reagent. After a period for a 5 min reaction, samples were automatically injected onto a C–18 column (cat. no. HR–80, ESA) with a mobile phase of 100 mM monosodium ortho-phosphate and 25% methanol, at a pH of 4.6 and at 40ºC. GABA was detected at E2 set at 50 nA using a Coulochem II coulometric detector with potential settings of: guard cell +700mv, E1 +400mV, and E2 +650mV. Peak areas were calculated and values determined by comparison with a standard curve.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0269881112454230">
<title>Glutamate analysis</title>
<p>Glutamate levels in tissue extracts were measured by HPLC separation and electrochemical detection of the o-phthaldialdehyde (OPA)-mercaptoethanol derivative, using a modification of the method used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269881112454230">Donzanti and Yamamoto (1988)</xref>. Briefly, 10 µl of supernatant from the tissue extract was transferred into assay tubes and placed in an autosampler tray at 4ºC. Ten 10 µl of 10 µM homoserine standard was added to each sample, then the sample was derivitized by the addition and mixing of 20 µl of an OPA/β-mercaptoethanol reagent. At 90 seconds after the addition of the reagent, 10 µl of the sample-reagent mixture was injected onto an HPLC column (3µm, C–18 column, 150 X 2mm). Separations were carried out isocratically, with a mobile phase containing 0.1 M sodium phosphate dibasic (pH 6.75) and 25% methanol, at a flow rate of 410 µl/min and a column temperature of 40ºC. Electrochemical detection was performed by an ESA Coulochem II system with a dual electrode, set at 300 mV on channel 1, to preoxidize undesirable analytes and 600 mV on channel 2 for oxidization of the glutamate derivative. Peak areas were calculated based on standard curves and adjusted for the value of the internal standard.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0269881112454230">
<title>Experiment 2: Systemic injections of CBiPES or alprazolam</title>
<p>5 days following l–AG infusion onset, in a counterbalanced design, sets of six rats each received an intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of either CBiPES, 30mg/kg in 0.2ml/100g volume of 10% DMSO in ddH<sub>2</sub>O; THIIC, 10 or 30 mg/kg; alprazolam 3 mg/kg; Tocris, in 0.2ml/100g of 10% DMSO in ddH<sub>2</sub>O; or control vehicle (0.2ml/100g volume of 10% DMSO in ddH<sub>2</sub>O) 30 min prior to a NaLac challenge.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0269881112454230">
<title>Experiment 3: Systemic injections of THIIC</title>
<p>Five days following onset of l–AG infusion, in a counterbalanced design, sets of six rats each received an i.p. injection of either vehicle control (0.2ml/100g volume DMSO), 10mg/kg THIIC, or 30mg/kg THIIC in 0.2ml/100g volume DMSO, exactly 30 min prior to the NaLac challenge.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0269881112454230">
<title>Histology</title>
<p>Following experiments, all rats were anesthetized and decapitated; their brains were removed and frozen, then sectioned (30µm) and placed on slides; and these were stained with Neutral Red dye for determination of injection cannulae placements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0269881112454230">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>Each dependent variable for in vivo analyses (i.e. SI duration, activity, HR and MAP) was analyzed using a one-way ANOVA with repeated measures with <italic>drug treatment</italic> as the main factor and time in repeated measures, as well. In the presence of significant main effects, between subject post-hoc tests were conducted using a parametric Tukey’s test, and the within-subjects time effects were assessed using a Dunnett’s one-way analysis, with the time just prior to the i.v. infusion used as the control. Each dependent variable for ex-vivo analyses (i.e. GABA and glutamate concentrations) was analyzed using a one-tailed paired <italic>t</italic>-test. Statistical significance was accepted with <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. All statistical analyses were carried out using SPSS 13.0 (SPSS Inc., IL, USA) and Systat 5.02 for Windows (SYSTAT Inc., Evanston, IL, USA), plus all graphs were generated using SigmaPlot 2001 for Windows (SPSS Inc., IL, USA), while the figure-plate illustrations were done using CorelDraw version 12 for Windows.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0269881112454230" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section14-0269881112454230">
<title>Experiment 1: Effects of <italic>1</italic>–AG in the DMH/PeF on local tissue concentrations of GABA and glutamate</title>
<p>Unilateral infusions of a GABA synthesis inhibitor (l–AG) into the DMH/PeF, over 5 days, reduces GABA (<italic>t</italic>(6) = 5.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.001) as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0269881112454230">Figure 1(a)</xref> and increases glutamate (<italic>t</italic>(6) = 2.0, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.05), as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0269881112454230">Figure 1(b)</xref>, as per analysis of 300uM micro-punches obtained from frozen coronal sections of the DMH/PeF ipsilateral to the infusion site, as compared to the contralateral control site, which is indicated by the * symbol (<italic>n</italic> = 7/group).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0269881112454230" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Unilateral infusions of a GABA synthesis inhibitor, l-allylglycine (l–AG), into the DMH/PeF over 5 days: (a) reduces GABA (<italic>t</italic>(6)= 5.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, left graph) and increases (b) glutamate (<italic>t</italic>(6)= 2.0, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, right graph), as assessed in 300uM micro-punches from frozen rat coronal sections of the DMH/PeF ipsilateral to the infusion site, as compared to the contralateral control site, and as indicated by the symbol * (<italic>n</italic> = 7/group; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, in a one-tailed paired <italic>t</italic>-test).</p>
<p>GABA: gamma-aminobutyric acid; DMH/PeF: dorsomedial/perifornical hypothalamus.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269881112454230-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0269881112454230">
<title>Experiment 2: Effects of CBiPES or alprazolam on NaLac-induced anxiety-like social behavior and panic-associated cardio-excitatory responses in panic-prone rats</title>
<sec id="section16-0269881112454230">
<title>Anxiety-associated behavior</title>
<p>An ANOVA with a Tukey’s posthoc test revealed significant differences between the groups (treatment effect F<sub>(3,23)</sub>= 11.8, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.001, <italic>n</italic> = 6/group), as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269881112454230">Figure 2(a)</xref>, where the alprazolam or the CBiPES drug blocked NaLac + l–AG-induced anxiety behavior (i.e. reductions in social interaction times).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0269881112454230" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Systemic injections of the benzodiazepine Alprazolam or CBiPES attenuates lactate-induced changes (from 5 min baseline) in (a) anxiety-associated behavior (reduced SI), (b) tachycardia, and (c) general locomotor activity in rats made panic-prone with chronic reductions of GABA synthesis in the DMH/PeF (i.e. by local l-AG infusion). There was no significant baseline HR or general locomotor activity between groups (see legends on figures with baseline HR +/- SEM).</p>
<p>Gray shaded area represents the duration of intravenous (i.v.) lactate infusions. The a, b and c symbols in Figures (b) and (c) and the * symbol in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269881112454230">Figure 2(b)</xref> indicate between-subject differences using a Tukey’s HSD posthoc test that was protected with an ANOVA. * indicates within-subject time points that are significantly different than at the -5 min pre-lactate infusion time point, using a one-way Dunnett’s posthoc test (<italic>n</italic>= 6,6,6 and 5 for each respective group).</p>
<p>GABA: gamma-aminobutyric acid; DMH/PeF: dorsomedial/perifornical hypothalamus; I-AG: l-allylglycine; Veh: vehicle control; Lac: lactate; Alpr: Alprazolam; CBiPES: (N-(4′-cyano-biphenyl-3-yl)-N-(3-pyridinylmethyl)-(ethanesulfonamide hydrochloride)); HR: heart rate; HSD: honestly significant difference; t: time; Bsln: baseline; BPM: beats per minute; SEM: Standard error of the mean; SI: social interaction.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269881112454230-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0269881112454230">
<title>Cardiovascular activity responses</title>
<p>An overall ANOVA with time as a repeated measure detected a treatment by time interaction for the change in HR (F<sub>(38,266)</sub> = 4.8, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.001), as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269881112454230">Figure 2(b)</xref>, and MAP (F<sub>(38,266)</sub> = 2.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.001, data not shown) when comparing the l–AG + NaLac + vehicle group to the l–AG + NaLac + CBiPES or 20mg groups, when looking at all time-points over the 20 min period. A within-subjects analysis of HR and MAP changes revealed that lactate increased HR (F<sub>(19,100)</sub> = 4.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.002) and MAP (F<sub>(19,100)</sub> = 2.4, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.005) from the baseline, over time, in only the l–AG +NaLac + vehicle-treated rats (see the asterisk on graphs). A radio-telemetry probe battery malfunctioned (evidenced by HR, and MAP data that was outside the physiological range) prior to the CBiPES injection; therefore, there was <italic>n</italic> = 6 for the vehicle group, <italic>n</italic> = 6 for the alprazolam group and <italic>n</italic> = 5 for the CBiPES group. There was no significant difference in baseline (5 min prior to intravenous infusion) MAP (F<sub>(3,22)</sub>= 0.6, <italic>p</italic> = 0.594) between groups (see legends on figures with baseline data +/- SEM); however, an ANOVA with a subsequent Tukey’s posthoc test did reveal that prior to NaLac infusion the baseline HR was significantly lower in the alprazolam-treated rats, as compared to all other groups (F<sub>(3,19)</sub> = 5.2, <italic>p</italic> = 0.009).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0269881112454230">
<title>General motor activity responses</title>
<p>Although a within-group, over time ANOVA did not detect an increase in motor activity from baseline following the lactate challenge (F<sub>(3,20)</sub> = 2.9, <italic>p</italic> = 0.061), between-group analyses detected that the l–AG + NaLac + vehicle group did have higher locomotor activity post NaLac exposure, than the other groups did at the 5–10 min (F<sub>(2,14)</sub> = 13.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and 10–15 min (F<sub>(2,14)</sub> = 4.7, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) interval post NaLac challenge (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269881112454230">Figure 2(c)</xref> for details from subsequent Tukey’s posthoc tests). There were also no significant differences in the baseline (5 min prior to intravenous infusion) activity (F<sub>(3,22)</sub>= 0.4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.721) between groups (see the legends on figures, with baseline data +/- SEM).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0269881112454230">
<title>Experiment 3: Effects of THIIC on NaLac-induced anxiety-like social behavior and panic-associated cardio-excitatory responses in panic-prone rats</title>
<sec id="section20-0269881112454230">
<title>Anxiety-associated behavior</title>
<p>An ANOVA with a Tukey’s post-hoc test revealed that there were significant differences between groups of six individuals, with a treatment effect (F<sub>(2,15)</sub>= 6.2, <italic>p</italic> = 0.004) seen between <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0269881112454230">Figure 1(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3(a)</xref>, where the THIIC drug blocked the NaLac + l–AG -induced anxiety behavior (i.e. there were reductions in social interaction times observed).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0269881112454230" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>(a) Systemic injections of the highest dose of THIIC attenuated NaLac-induced anxiety behavior (as measured by reduced social interaction times) in rats made panic-prone with chronic reductions of GABA synthesis in the DMH/PeF (i.e. local l-AG infusions). The * symbol in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3 (a)</xref> indicates between-subject differences using a Tukey’s posthoc test protected with an ANOVA. (b) Systemic injections of both doses of the THIIC attenuated NaLac-induced tachycardia in rats made panic-prone with chronic reductions of GABA synthesis in the DMH/PeF (i.e. l-AG infusions). (c) NaLac did not elicit an increase in general motor activity. There was no significant baseline HR or general locomotor activity between groups (see figure legends for baseline HR and activity +/- SEM).</p>
<p>Symbols a and b in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3(b)</xref> indicate the between-subject differences, using a Tukey’s posthoc test protected with an ANOVA. The * symbol in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3(b)</xref> indicates within-subject time points that are significantly different that the 1 min pre-NaLac infusion time point, using a one-way Dunnett’s posthoc test.</p>
<p>THIIC: N-(4-{[3-hydroxy-4-(2-methylpropanoyl)-2-(trifluoromethyl)phenoxy]methyl}benzyl)-1-methyl-1H-imidazole-4-carboxamide); NaLac: sodium lactate; GABA: gamma- aminobutyric acid; DMH/PeF: dorsomedial/perifornical hypothalamus; I-AG: l-allyglycine; HR: heart rate; Lac: lactate; Veh: control vehicle; BsIn: baseline; BPM: beats per minute.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269881112454230-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0269881112454230">
<title>Cardiovascular activity responses</title>
<p>An overall ANOVA with time as a repeated measure did not detect a treatment by time interaction (F<sub>(38,266)</sub>= 1.4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.058) or a time effect (F<sub>(19,266)</sub>= 1.1, <italic>p</italic> = 0.356) for the change in HR, when comparing the l–AG + NaLac + vehicle group to the l–AG + NaLac + either 10 or 30mg/kg THIIC groups, if looking at all the time points over the 20-min period. Nor was there an overall within-subject treatment effect seen (F<sub>(2,14)</sub>= 2.7, <italic>p</italic> = 0.100); however, if the analysis for HR is restricted to looking only at the 5-min baseline and post-NaLac time points of 6–15min, then there was a significant treatment x time interaction (F<sub>(28,196)</sub>= 1.9, p = 0.006), as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3(b)</xref>. A within-subject analysis of HR changes revealed that NaLac increased HR from baseline over time in only l–AG + NaLac + vehicle -treated rats (F<sub>(19,95)</sub>= 3.7, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), as is also seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3(b)</xref>. No significant change in MAP (F<sub>(19,380)</sub>= 0.6, <italic>p</italic> = 0.975) was noted (data not shown). A radio-telemetry probe battery malfunctioned (evidenced by HR data that was outside the physiological range) prior to the 10mg/kg THIIC injection; therefore, <italic>n</italic> = 6 rats were in the vehicle group, only <italic>n</italic> = 5 in the 10mg/kg group and <italic>n</italic> = 6 for the 30mg/kg group, for HR. Also, no significant differences in baseline (5 min prior to intravenous infusion) HR (F<sub>(2,17)</sub>= 0.2, <italic>p</italic> = 0.795) nor MAP (F<sub>(2,17)</sub>= 0.3, <italic>p</italic> = 0.773) between groups (see legends on figures, with baseline data +/- SEM).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0269881112454230">
<title>General motor activity responses</title>
<p>No significant change in locomotor activity (F<sub>(9,60)</sub> = 1.4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.223) was noted, as is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269881112454230">Figure 3(c)</xref>. No significant differences in baseline (5 min prior to intravenous infusion) activity (F<sub>(2,17)</sub>= 0.04, <italic>p</italic> = 0.964) between groups occurred, either (see figure legends with baseline data +/- SEM).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0269881112454230">
<title>Osmotic minipump probe placement</title>
<p>All minipump cannulae placements resided in regions of the DMH/PeF and posterior hypothalamus (PH), known to be cardioexcitatory, as is seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0269881112454230">Figure 4</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0269881112454230">Samuels et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 1997</xref>). Although there was some tissue damage at the site of implantation, this damage was minimal and it was observed equally in the control and experimental groups, with the majority of cells in the DMH/PeF/PH still remaining intact, surrounding the infusion site and histologically staining with methyl green (data not shown).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0269881112454230" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>Coronal brain sections of the rat that illustrate the rostrocaudal distribution of unilateral placement of a minipump filled with the glutamic amino acid decarboxylase inhibitor l-allylglycine (l-AG, as represented by circles) from experiments testing the drugs CBiPES and alprazolam, denoted by black circles, and THIIC, denoted by open white circles. Numbers at bottom right of illustrations represent the distance from bregma.</p>
<p>PH: posterior hypothalamus; DMH: dorsomedial hypothalamus; PeF: perifornical hypothalamus; mt: mammillothalamic tract.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269881112454230-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0269881112454230" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Extensive previous studies demonstrate that chronic inhibition of GABA synthesis in the DMH/PeF leads to a panic-prone state in rats. We previously demonstrated that subsequent increases in local glutamatergic activity are in part responsible for this state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>). In this study, we obtained more direct confirmation that blocking of GABA synthesis in the DMH/PeF not only decreased local GABA concentrations, but this decrease in GABA was accompanied by an increase in local glutamate concentrations. This was not surprising, since antagonizing GABA synthesis in the DMH/PeF would decrease the conversion of glutamate to GABA locally, so it is a likely explanation for the increased glutamate tone. We also previously showed that pre-injecting NMDA receptor antagonists into the DMH/PeF (to inhibit the postsynaptic effects of glutamate) does block NaLac-induced panic responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>). Thus, the increase in local glutamatergic tone within the DMH/PeF, as well as other postsynaptic sites, supports the use of a mGluR 2 potentiator such as CBiPES or THIIC in subsequent experiments, to see whether they could reduce the consequences of the excess synaptic glutamate, thus reduce vulnerability to feeling panic. In the present study, we found that the mGluR2 potentiators CBiPES or THIIC, when given as a pre-treatment, were each as effective a pre-treatment as the anti-panic drug benzodiazepine alprazolam in blocking NaLac-induced anxiety-like behavior, as well as panic-like increases in cardioexcitation, suggesting that the mGluR 2 potentiators could possibly become clinically effective antipanic agents in humans. The effective doses used in the present study correlated with potency in other animal models for treatment of anxiety/depression in both the rat and mouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2005</xref>; Fell et al., 2011). Rats that were pre-treated with alprazolam had significantly lower baseline HRs prior to NaLac challenge than those rats given either the control vehicle, CBiPES or THIIC, which suggested that mGluR 2 potentiators may have fewer of the kind of side effects associated with benzodiazepines. These data are consistent with a previous study where pre-treating panic-prone rats with LY354740, an mGluR2/3 agonist, attenuated NaLac-induced panic responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 2000</xref>); however, in addition to limiting the release of glutamate, a review mentions that LY354740 is also known to alter postsynaptic excitability through actions at the group II mGluR3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0269881112454230">Swanson et al., 2005</xref>). Our present findings suggested that blocking the release of glutamate by a presynaptic mechanism through treatment with mGluR2 potentiators may be therapeutic in treating panic disorder. This novel approach would not only be a significant improvement over therapy with benzodiazepines such as alprazolam, but this treatment may potentially have even fewer side-effects than the less selective mGlu2/3 agonists.</p>
<p>The present report adds to a wide variety of preclinical and clinical studies which suggest that panic vulnerability could partially be explained by glutamate-mediated hyperexcitation in brain regions such as the DMH/PeF, or other panic-generating sites such as the amygdala (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0269881112454230">Sajdyk and Shekhar, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0269881112454230">Shekhar et al., 2003</xref>) or the dorsal periaqueductal gray (DPAG), which is proposed to be a critical locus for the “suffocation alarm system” in response to NaLac or hypoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0269881112454230">Schimitel et al., 2012</xref>) and, if hyperactive, could contribute to what Klein terms “false suffocation alarm,” to trigger panic attacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0269881112454230">Klein, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0269881112454230">Schenberg et al., 2001</xref>). In light of this, there is increasing recognition that glutamatergic mechanisms may be a potential avenue to develop for new treatments for anxiety problems such as panic disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269881112454230">Gorman, 2003</xref>). For instance, the noncompetitive NMDA antagonist MK–801 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0269881112454230">Xie and Commissaris, 1992</xref>) and the competitive NMDA antagonist AP–7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0269881112454230">Plaznik et al., 1994</xref>) are both shown to reduce anxiety-like and panic-associated behavior in rats. Still, although these previously reviewed preclinical trials with NMDA receptor antagonists appear to reduce anxiety, human clinical trials with NMDA receptor antagonists (e.g. Dizolcilpine (MK-801), Cerestat (CNS-1102), Selfotel (CGS–19755) and D-CPPene) demonstrated they are not a realistic therapy, in light of their numerous undesired side-effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0269881112454230">Parsons et al., 1999</xref>). The adverse side effects that are most commonly reported are the ability of certain NMDA receptor antagonists to induce psychotomimetic effects (e.g. phencyclidine) and having sedative effects at high doses (e.g. ketamine). These adverse effects are unfortunate, because NMDA antagonists have shown promising therapeutic applications for acute (e.g. stroke and trauma) and chronic (e.g. Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s disease) neurodegeneration disorders, anxiety, depression and chronic pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0269881112454230">Parsons et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>According to a review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0269881112454230">Swanson and Schoepp (2002)</xref>, more recent preclinical research had greater success, by targeting mGluRs to treat anxiety with fewer side effects. The mGluR family of glutamate G-protein-coupled receptors are classified into three major groups, based on molecular structure, function and pharmacology: group I (mGluR 1 and 5), group II (mGluR 2 and 3) and group III (mGluR 4,6–8) receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269881112454230">Nicoletti et al., 2010</xref>). The mGluR 2/3 potentiators such as LY354740 or LY379268 have shown anxiolytic action in several anxiety models, such as: fear induced potentiated startle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269881112454230">Monn et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269881112454230">Helton et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0269881112454230">Walker and Davis, 2002</xref>), elevated plus maze (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269881112454230">Monn et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269881112454230">Helton et al., 1998</xref>), and in addition, LY354740 reduces NaLac-induced panic responses in panic-prone rats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Keim, 2000</xref>). Furthermore, in humans the mGlu2/3 potentiatiors have anxiolytic properties in fear-potentiated startle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269881112454230">Grillon, 2003</xref>) and CO<sub>2</sub>-induced panic attacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0269881112454230">Schoepp et al., 2003</xref>). However, because the mGlu 3 receptors are located postsynaptically and also on glia, it suggests that targeting of mGlu 2 receptors, which are activated by an excess synaptic glutamate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269881112454230">Nicoletti et al., 2010</xref>) to negatively modulate presynaptic glutamate neurotransmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0269881112454230">Pin and Duvoisin, 1995</xref>) would potentially be more selective in reducing an excessive synaptic glutamate release in the DMH/PeF of panic-prone rats, to reduce panic vulnerability without altering the basal glutamate release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2005</xref>). Our current study data clearly show that the mGluR2 potentiators used were as effective as a benzodiazepine in blocking the full spectrum of NaLac-induced panic responses in panic-prone rats. Clinical studies will be needed to determine whether mGluR2 potentiators such as CBiPES or THIIC can effectively treat severe human anxiety disorders, such as panic disorder, with fewer side effects than those associated with other clinically-approved anxiolytics.</p>
<p>The distribution of mGlu 2 receptors may give insight into where CBiPES may exert its panicolytic effects without the adverse side-effects that are associated with NMDA receptor antagonists. The mGluR2 mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0269881112454230">Ohishi et al., 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269881112454230">1993b</xref>) and protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0269881112454230">Neki et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0269881112454230">Petralia et al., 1996</xref>) are present in the hypothalamus and are particularly dense in limbic (e.g. basolateral amygdala) and cortical areas in rats, as well as in the brainstem structures through which NaLac may drive the autonomic (e.g. raphe, reticular nuclei) and respiratory (e.g. lateral parabrachial nucleus) responses in panic-prone rats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2008</xref>). Within the hypothalamus, the mGluR2 mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269881112454230">Gu et al., 2008</xref>) and mGluR2/3 protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0269881112454230">Petralia et al., 1996</xref>) is dense in the zona incerta, which is found dorsal to the DMH/PeF region. Therefore, some of the panicolytic properties of the mGluR 2 potentiators used here could derive from reducing excess glutamate in the DMH/PeF region of panic-prone rats, as well as efferent targets of the DMH/PeF (see the hypothetical illustration in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0269881112454230">Figure 5</xref>). Consistent with this hypothesis, we previously showed that local injections of NMDA glutamate receptor antagonists into the DMH/PeF of panic-prone rats prior to a NaLac challenge blocks the NaLac-induced panic responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>). The anxiolytic effects of NMDA receptor antagonists in the DMH/PeF may be state dependent, because under normal conditions, when the tonic GABAergic inhibition is intact in the DMH/PeF, reducing glutamate excitation with direct injections of glutamate receptor antagonists into the DMH/PeF will increase exploratory behavior, but have no effect on anxiety-related behavior, as is measured by an elevated plus-maze test or Vogel conflict test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269881112454230">Jardim and Guimaraes, 2004</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5-0269881112454230" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><p>Summary schema of glutamatergic and GABAergic input into the DMH/PeF and important efferent brain regions implicated in the regulation of panic-like responses. GABAergic and glutamatergic neurons are represented by circles attached to dashed or solid lines, respectively. Sources of GABA include local interneurons, which are tonically driven by glutamatergic input from mPFC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269881112454230">Bard and Mountcastle, 1948</xref>) as well as efferent brain regions such as the LS and mPOA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269881112454230">Feldblum et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0269881112454230">Risold and Swanson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0269881112454230">Thompson and Swanson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269881112454230">Grob et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269881112454230">Molosh et al., 2010</xref>). Glutamatergic input which excites the DMH/PeF region appears to arise from afferent sites such as CVOs (e.g. MnPO/OVLT and SFO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0269881112454230">Richard and Bourque, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269881112454230">Grob et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269881112454230">Molosh et al., 2010</xref>)). Afferent targets of the DMH/PeF that are implicated in the regulation of panic-like responses are also listed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0269881112454230">Johnson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269881112454230">Chamberlin and Saper, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0269881112454230">Thompson et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0269881112454230">Fontes et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269881112454230">Chen et al., 2004</xref>). The Group II mGluRs 2 and 3 are predominantly expressed presynpatically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0269881112454230">Shigemoto et al., 1997</xref>) and they negatively modulate glutamate neurotransmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0269881112454230">Pin and Duvoisin, 1995</xref>), acting on postsynaptic NMDAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269881112454230">Johnson and Shekhar, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>ACTH: adrenocorticotropic hormone; BNST: bed nucleus of the stria terminalis; CVO: circumventricular organ; DMH/PeF: dorsomedial/perifornical hypothalamus; GABA: gamma-aminobutyric acid; Glu: glutamatergic; GluR2: glutamate receptor 2; IML: intermediolateral cell column of spinal cord; LC: locus coeruleus; LS: lateral septum; mPFC: medial prefrontal cortex; mGluR: metabotropic glutamate receptor; MnPO: median preoptic nucleus; mPOA: medial preoptic area; NaLac: sodium lactate; NMDAR: N-methyl-D-aspartic acid receptor; nTS: nucleus of solitary tract; OVLT: organum vasculosum lamina terminalis; PBN: parabrachial nucleus; PVN: paraventricular hypothalamic nucleus; RVLM: rostroventrolateral medulla; SFO: subfornical organ.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269881112454230-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Alternatively, the panicolytic effects of the CBiPES or THIIC compounds may be due to blocking of the NaLac-induced cardioexcitatory activity, by inhibiting peripheral cardiovascular activity. An argument against this is that beta-blockers, which reduce NaLac-induced cardioexcitatory (HR and MAP) responses in patients with panic disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0269881112454230">Price et al., 1995</xref>) or after the DMH/PeF activation model of panic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Katner, 1995</xref>), do not block self-reported panic responses in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0269881112454230">Price et al., 1995</xref>) nor anxiety-associated behavior in rats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0269881112454230">Shekhar and Katner, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>In conclusion, our present studies confirmed that disrupting GABA synthesis in a panic-generating hypothalamic site (i.e. DMH/PeF) produced panic-prone rats, which also coincided with an increase in local glutamate activity. Furthermore, pre-treating these panic-prone rats with one of the selective group II mGlu receptor agonists like CBiPES, THIIC, or the currently-used benzodiazepine alprazolam did block NaLac-induced panic-like responses, as was indicated by the increased social anxiety, increased locomotor activity and cardio-excitation. These animal study data suggest that mGluR2 potentiators could become a novel anti-panic drug that is as effective as alprazolam, but acts without some of the adverse effects typical of benzodiazepines.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by Eli Lilly &amp; Co. and the NIH (R01 grant number MH52619), awarded to AS; as well as by Anxiety Disorders Association of America (Junior Faculty Research Award) awarded to PLJ, the NIH (Student LRP) awarded to PLJ and the National Alliance for Schizophrenia and Depression (Young Investigators Award) awarded to PLJ.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors declare that there are no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abshire</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hankins</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roehr</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Injection of L-allylglycine into the posterior hypothalamus in rats causes decreases in local GABA which correlate with increases in heart rate</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1171</fpage>–<lpage>1177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nutt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evidence-based guidelines for the pharmacological treatment of anxiety disorders: Recommendations from the British Association for Psychopharmacology</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandelow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zohar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hollander</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry (WFSBP) guidelines for the pharmacological treatment of anxiety, obsessive-compulsive and post-traumatic stress disorders - first revision</article-title>. <source>World J Biol Psychiatry</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mountcastle</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1948</year>) <article-title>Some forebrain mechanisms involved in the expression of rage with special reference to suppression of angry behavior</article-title>. <source>Res Publ Assoc Res Nerv Ment Dis</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernardis</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellinger</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) The dorsomedial hypothalamic nucleus revisited: <year>1998</year> Update. <source>Proc Soc Exp Biol Med</source> <volume>218</volume>: <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boshuisen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ter Horst</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paans</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>rCBF differences between panic disorder patients and control subjects during anticipatory anxiety and rest</article-title>. <source>Biol Psy</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bourdelais</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalivas</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>High sensitivity HPLC assay for GABA in brain dialysis studies</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Meth</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chamberlin</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Topographic organization of respiratory responses to glutamate microstimulation of the parabrachial nucleus in the rat</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>6500</fpage>–<lpage>6510</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Endomorphin 1- and endomorphin 2-like immunoreactive neurons in the hypothalamus send axons to the parabrachial nucleus in the rat</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source> <volume>357</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gooley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Critical role of dorsomedial hypothalamic nucleus in a wide range of behavioral circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>10691</fpage>–<lpage>10702</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cloos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Current use of benzodiazepines in anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Psych</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DiMicco</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaretskaia</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The dorsomedial hypothalamus and the response to stress: Part renaissance, part revolution</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donzanti</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>An improved and rapid HPLC-EC method for the isocratic separation of amino acid neurotransmitters from brain tissue and microdialysis perfusates</article-title>. <source>Life Sci</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>922</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feldblum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erlander</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Different distributions of GAD65 and GAD67 mRNAs suggest that the two glutamate decarboxylases play distinctive functional roles</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Res</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>File</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>The use of social interaction as a method for detecting anxiolytic activity of chlordiazepoxide-like drugs</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Meth</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fontes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tagawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Descending pathways mediating cardiovascular response from dorsomedial hypothalamic nucleus</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>H2891</fpage>–<lpage>H2901</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reductions in occipital cortex GABA levels in panic disorder detected with 1h-magnetic resonance spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psych</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>New molecular targets for antianxiety interventions</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psych</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Neuroanatomical hypothesis of panic disorder, revised</article-title>. <source>Am J Psych</source> <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coplan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Anxiogenic effects of CO2 and hyperventilation in patients with panic disorder</article-title>. <source>Am J Psych</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grillon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Anxiolytic effects of a novel group II metabotropic glutamate receptor agonis (LY354740) in the fear-potentiated startle paradigm in humans</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source> <volume>168</volume>: <fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grob</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trottier</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drolet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the neurochemical content of neuronal populations of the lamina terminalis activated by acute hydromineral challenge</article-title>. <source>Neurosci</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorrain</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Distribution of metabotropic glutamate 2 and 3 receptors in the rat forebrain: Implication in emotional responses and central disinhibition</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source> <volume>1197</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Helton</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tizzano</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monn</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Anxiolytic and side-effect profile of LY354740: A potent, highly selective, orally active agonist for group II metabotropic glutamate receptors</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hirschfeld</surname><given-names>RMA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Panic disorder: Diagnosis, epidemiology, and clinical course</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psych</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jardim</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guimaraes</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Role of glutamate ionotropic receptors in the dorsomedial hypothalamic nucleus on anxiety and locomotor behavior</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Metabotropic glutamate 2 receptor potentiators: Receptor modulation, frequency-dependent synaptic activity, and efficacy in preclinical anxiety and psychosis model(s)</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacol</source> <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Panic-prone state induced in rats with GABA dysfunction in the dorsomedial hypothalamus is mediated by NMDA receptors</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>7093</fpage>–<lpage>7104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Truitt</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitz</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Neural pathways underlying lactate-induced panic</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>2093</fpage>–<lpage>2107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Truitt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitz</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A key role for orexin in panic anxiety</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katon</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roy-Byrne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cost-effectiveness and cost offset of a collaborative care intervention for primary care patients with panic disorder</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psych</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1098</fpage>–<lpage>1104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGonagle</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Lifetime and 12-month prevalence of DSM-III-R psychiatric disorders in the United States</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psych</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>False suffocation alarms, spontaneous panics, and related conditions</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psych</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liebowitz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Biological accompaniments of lactate-induced panic</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacol Bull</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Molosh</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitz</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Changes in central sodium and not osmolarity or lactate induce panic-like responses in a model of panic disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacol</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1333</fpage>–<lpage>1347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monn</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valli</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Design, synthesis, and pharmacological characterization of (+)-2-aminobicyclo[3.1.0]hexane-2,6-dicarboxylic acid (LY354740): A potent, selective, and orally active group 2 metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist possessing anticonvulsant and anxiolytic properties</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Pre- and postsynaptic localization of a metabotropic glutamate receptor, mGluR2, in the rat brain: An immunohistochemical study with a monoclonal antibody</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source> <volume>202</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bockaert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collingridge</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Metabotropic glutamate receptors: From the workbench to the bedside</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1017</fpage>–<lpage>1041</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nutt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ballenger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Generalized anxiety disorder: Comorbidity, comparative biology and treatment</article-title>. <source>Int J Neuropsychopharmacol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shigemoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1993a</year>) <article-title>Distribution of the messenger RNA for a metabotropic glutamate receptor, mGluR2, in the central nervous system of the rat</article-title>. <source>Neurosci</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1018</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shigemoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1993b</year>) <article-title>Distribution of the mRNA for a metabotropic glutamate receptor (mGluR3)</article-title> <publisher-loc>in the rat brain</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>An in situ hybridization study</publisher-name>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source> <volume>335</volume>: <fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danysz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quack</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Memantine is a clinically well tolerated N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA)</article-title> <publisher-loc>receptor antagonist</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>A review of preclinical data</publisher-name>. <source>Neuropharmacol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>767</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petralia</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niedzielski</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The metabotropic glutamate receptors, mGluR2 and mGluR3, show unique postsynaptic, presynaptic and glial localizations</article-title>. <source>Neurosci</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duvoisin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The metabotropic glutamate receptors: Structure and functions</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacol</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plaznik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palejko</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Effects of antagonists at the NMDA receptor complex in two models of anxiety</article-title>. <source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bechou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Lactate-induced anxiety after imapramine and diazepam treatment</article-title>. <source>Anxiety</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Pharmacological challenges in anxiety disorders</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Psychopharmacology: The fourth generation of progression</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1323</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Synaptic activation of rat supraoptic neurons by osmotic stimulation of the <italic>organum vasculosum lamina terminalis</italic></article-title>. <source>Neuroendocrinol</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Risold</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Connections of the rat lateral septal complex</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Rev</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sajdyk</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Sodium lactate elicits anxiety in rats after repeated GABA receptor blockade in the basolateral amygdala</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source> <volume>394</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaretsky</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiMicco</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dorsomedial hypothalamic sites where disinhibition evokes tachycardia correlate with location of raphe-projecting neurons</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source> <volume>287</volume>: <fpage>R472</fpage>–<lpage>R478</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Regulation of anxiety by GABAA receptors in the rat amygdala</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>–<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schenberg</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bittencourt</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sudre</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Modeling panic attacks</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schimitel</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Almeida</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pitol</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evidence of a suffocation alarm system within the periaqueductal gray matter of the rat</article-title>. <source>Neurosci</source> <volume>200</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schoepp</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>LY354740, an mGlu2/3 receptor agonist as a novel approach to treat anxiety/stress</article-title>. <source>Stress</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sajdyk</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Angiotensin-II is a putative neurotransmitter in lactate-induced panic-like responses in rats with disruption of GABAergic inhibition in the dorsomedial hypothalamus</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>9205</fpage>–<lpage>9215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Dorsomedial hypothalamic GABA regulates anxiety in the social interaction test</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The circumventricular organs form a potential neural pathway for lactate sensitivity: Implications for panic disorder</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>9726</fpage>–<lpage>9735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>LY354740, a potent group II metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist prevents lactate-induced panic-like response in panic-prone rats</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1139</fpage>–<lpage>1146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Dorsomedial hypothalamic GABA dysfunction produces physiological arousal following sodium lactate infusions</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sajdyk</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gehlert</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The amygdala, panic disorder, and cardiovascular responses</article-title>. <source>Ann NY Acad Sci</source> <volume>985</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shigemoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Differential presynaptic localization of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes in the rat hippocampus</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>7503</fpage>–<lpage>7522</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bures</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Metabotropic glutamate receptors as novel targets for anxiety and stress disorders</article-title>. <source>Nature Rev</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schoepp</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The group II metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist (-)-2-oxa-4-aminobicyclo[3.1.0.]hexane-4,6-dicarboxylate (LY379268) and clozapine reverse phencyclidine-induced behaviors in monoamine-depleted rats</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source> <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>927</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canteras</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Organization of projections from the dorsomedial nucleus of the hypothalamus: A PHA-L study in the rat</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source> <volume>376</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Organization of inputs to the dorsomedial nucleus of the hypothalamus: A reexamination with Fluorogold and PHAL in the rat</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Rev</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The role of amygdala glutamate receptors in fear learning, fear-potentiated startle, and extinction</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merikangas</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The epidemiology of anxiety and panic disorders: An update</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psych</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0269881112454230">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Commissaris</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Anxiolytic-like effects of the noncompetitive NMDA antagonist MK 801</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>