<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SEX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsex</journal-id>
<journal-title>Sexualities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1363-4607</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7382</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1363460711433751</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1363460711433751</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘God forgives the sin but not the scandal’: Coming out in a transnational context – between sexual freedom and cultural isolation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Aguila</surname><given-names>Ernesto Vasquez del</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1363460711433751"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1363460711433751">University College Dublin, Ireland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1363460711433751">Ernesto Vasquez del Aguila, University College Dublin, School of Social Justice, James Joyce Library Building, Belfield, Dublin, 4, Ireland Email: <email>ernesto.vasquezdelaguila@ucd.ie</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>207</fpage>
<lpage>224</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Migration opens new possibilities for sexual freedom for gay and bisexually active men. However, ‘coming out’ carries real and potentially negative implications for immigrant men. Based on ethnographic research over more than four years in New York, this article examines the multiple strategies that Peruvian immigrants perform to fulfil their dreams of sexual freedom, while avoiding rejection and isolation from their relatives and compatriots. It shows different ‘forms’ of coming out or not coming out. Gay men and their families act out their scripts of ‘knowing’, ‘not knowing’ and ‘pretending not to know’, and play by the ‘rules of the game’.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Coming out</kwd>
<kwd>gay immigrants</kwd>
<kwd>masculine capital</kwd>
<kwd><italic>secreto a voces</italic> (open secrets)</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1363460711433751" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Over the course of four years, I conducted ethnographic fieldwork among Peruvian immigrant men who work and reside in New York City and surrounding areas. During the period 2003–2007, I followed the lives of 27 men, aged between 19 and 42 years, conducting life history interviews and participant observation. Informants come from diverse social strata, age, migrant status, and sexual orientation. In this article, I use these men’s stories as a case study to illustrate the complexities of gay and bisexually active immigrant men’s strategies when faced with stigma and homophobia.</p>
<p>Homoerotic sexual practices are not necessarily labelled as ‘homosexual sex’, and categories such as heterosexual, homosexual and bisexual are not necessarily appropriate for all or even most cultural contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1363460711433751">Vance 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1363460711433751">Weeks, 2007</xref>). Studies have shown that in different cultural contexts men who have sex with men hide their homoerotic practices as a survival strategy or ‘coping mechanism’ to confront stigma and homophobia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1363460711433751">Campbell, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1363460711433751">Moodie and Ndatshe, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1363460711433751">Phellas 2002</xref>). Several scholars have demonstrated how many Latin American and Latino men who have sex with men (MSM)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1363460711433751">1</xref></sup> do not associate their sexual behaviour with a gay identity, and despite their homoerotic sexual experiences, these men continue identifying themselves as heterosexual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460711433751">Carrillo, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1363460711433751">Lancaster, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1363460711433751">Parker, 1999</xref>). In this cultural context, gay or homosexual identities are feared and rejected because of the potential hostility, violence and stigma, Male homosexual behaviour in Latin America is generally clandestine, tacitly accepted or ignored by family members and social networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1363460711433751">Alonso and Koreck, 1999</xref>). It must be noted that important social transformation has been taking place across Latin American societies, from social movements and the mobilization of gay rights activists to changes in the everyday lives of LGBT individuals who are becoming more visible and accepted within their communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460711433751">Carrillo, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1363460711433751">Padilla, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1363460711433751">Parker, 1999</xref>). Like in many places around the globe, however, homophobia and discrimination still constrain the lives of LGBT individuals.</p>
<p>Gay masculinities are part of a ‘subordinate’ masculinity because gay men ‘fail’ to embody the expectations of ‘hegemonic’ masculinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1363460711433751">Connell, 2000</xref>). Not all gay men are part of a ‘subordinate’ masculinity, however. Even though there is not necessarily an association between sexual preferences and ‘masculine/feminine’ attitudes (i.e. ‘masculine’ and ‘feminine’ men can adopt both insertive and receptive roles during anal sex), gay men who exhibit ‘feminine’ behaviour are associated with ‘passive’ homosexuality and are the ones who embody subordinated masculinities, while those who perform as ‘straight gays’, increase their masculine capital,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1363460711433751">2</xref></sup> dilute ‘doubts’ about their homosexuality, and ‘defend’ themselves against discrimination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1363460711433751">Vasquez del Aguila, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Within Latin American societies, heterosexuality is at the centre of masculinity; hence these men are seen as lacking masculinity. Compulsory heterosexuality and the display of masculine capital define who is ultimately considered a man and who is not. A ‘real’ Latin American man should be heterosexual and demonstrate ‘masculine’ behaviour. Further, hierarchies of gender and sexuality equates masculinity with the act of penetration, so those men who are penetrated, or are suspected of being penetrated, are at the bottom of the male gender and sexual hierarchy. In this hierarchical system, the pasivo (‘bottom’) partner carries the stigma of homosexuality, while the activo (‘top’) keeps his masculinity and sexuality ‘intact’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1363460711433751">Cantu, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1363460711433751">Lancaster, 2002</xref>). Scholars such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1363460711433751">Parker (1999)</xref> in Brazil, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460711433751">Carrillo (2002)</xref> in Mexico have found that these rigid sexual dichotomies co-exist with global notions of gayness and ‘versatility’ and men who have sex with men must negotiate between different systems of signification in interpreting their sexual practices and identities.</p>
<p>Peruvian immigrant men in New York who have sex with men embrace different identities throughout their passage within different social contexts from the Peruvian communities to the gay communities in the USA. Most of these men maintain their sexual identity as ‘heterosexuals’ within their national communities in order to avoid rejection by their families and communities, while others develop ‘strategies’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1363460711433751">3</xref></sup> to negotiate with cultural norms that allow them to play by the ‘rules of the game’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1363460711433751">Bourdieu, 1990</xref>). In this game of <italic>secreto a voces</italic> (open secrets), gay men and their families perform their scripts in order not to question the social order of heterosexuality. ‘Silences’, secrecy and discretion shape these immigrant men’s sexual lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1363460711433751">Alonso and Koreck, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1363460711433751">Caceres and Rosasco, 2000</xref>). This article illustrates the different strategies that Peruvian immigrant men who engage in homosexual behaviours have to deploy to reconcile their sexual identities, and manage the disclosure of their homosexual desires to their social networks both in Peru and in the USA.</p>
<p>Sexual migration addresses the importance of sexuality in the process of migration. For many gay men and men who have sex with men, internal and international migration is often the only strategy available in the face of stigma and discrimination from their families and communities. The decision to migrate might involve the desire to build or continue a romantic relationship or may be connected to hopes of exploring sexual desires in a more open and tolerant environment (Carrillo, 2004; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1363460711433751">Howe et al., 2008</xref>).</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-1363460711433751"><title>Negotiating identities in a transnational context</title>
<p>The Peruvian racial and social class hierarchy shapes the perception of who is considered ‘gay’ and who is consider to be a ‘maricón’ (‘faggot’). In this scenario, <italic>blancos</italic> (white middle class) are more likely to be associated with the gay culture and gay identities, while <italic>cholos</italic> (working class people with indigenous features) are the <italic>cholos maricas</italic> (cholo faggots). Beto,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1363460711433751">4</xref></sup> a <italic>blanco</italic> gay man, and Jose, a <italic>cholo</italic> gay, show the racialized nature of gender and sexuality in Peruvian society. For Beto, a very discreet gay man, <italic>cholo</italic> gay men are the ‘ugly’ face of homosexuality. Jose, who experiences racial and social class discrimination in Lima, recounts how race and class shape the perception of sexual identities as gay or <italic>cabro/maricón</italic> (faggot):<disp-quote>
<p>The problem is the <italic>cholo maricas</italic>. These ugly <italic>cholos</italic> are scandalous, they ruin everything. Because of them, <italic>normal</italic> people think all gays are feminine, ugly and scandalous. (Beto)</p>
<p>If you are <italic>blanquito</italic> (white), live in Miraflores, study in the Pacific [University], you are not <italic>maricón</italic>, you are gay … in Peru <italic>maricones</italic> are only the <italic>cholos</italic>, if you are poor and <italic>cholito</italic>, you are not gay. (Jose)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>As a consequence of almost three centuries of Spanish colonization, Latin American countries such as Peru produced a hierarchical racial system that represents <italic>blanco</italic> (white) people as the hegemonic and desired race, while relegating other ethnic and racial groups to subordinate positions. Peruvian transnational immigrants recreate their cultural and social backgrounds in their new places of residence and reproduce these racial and class tensions between <italic>blancos</italic> and <italic>cholos</italic> (indigenous). Gender and sexuality intersects with race and social class creating these hierarchies among gay men.</p>
<p>Embracing an openly gay identity is a very difficult process for most Peruvians, not only in their country of origin but also in the USA, where they often have family members and compatriots. The following five sections show the different strategies that gay and bisexually active Peruvian men deploy to avoid the discrimination associated with a gay identity.</p>
<sec id="sec3-1363460711433751"><title><italic>Caletas</italic>: A performance of masculine capital</title>
<p>In general terms, <italic>caleta</italic> in Peru alludes to any discreet or secret behaviour, not necessarily related to sexuality. When applied to homosexuality, <italic>caleta</italic> designates a man who has homoerotic experiences in total secrecy and discretion. <italic>Caleta</italic> also refers to ‘masculine’ performances that make it unlikely that men with homosexual experiences will be ‘discovered’. The term <italic>caleta</italic> can be a noun or an adjective: denotes a man with a public heterosexual identity; performance of masculine capital such as his ways of walking and speaking, proficiency in ‘male’ sports, display and control of emotions, among other masculine gestures; and a secret homosexual life. <italic>Caleta</italic> men do not want to be <italic>quemados</italic> (‘burned’) by being associated with openly gay men and seeing their sexual reputation ruined. Secrecy, discretion, and ‘masculine’ presentation of self protect them from being associated with the<italic> mundo de ambiente</italic> (gay scene).</p>
<p>The term <italic>caleta</italic> can be a positive label that many men with homosexual experiences embrace as a ‘private identity’. It does not question these men’s public sexual and gender identity as ‘heterosexuals’ and ‘masculine’ men. They are not gay men; they are just ‘playing around’ with other men.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1363460711433751">5</xref></sup> <italic>Caleta</italic> men do not frequent gay bars or gay scenes; they engage in sexual activities mainly through the internet and anonymous encounters.</p>
<p>Victor and Ricardo are technically bisexual men in the USA but identify themselves as heterosexuals. They have sexual encounters with women and also they develop ‘very discreet’ sexual relations with other men. Victor and Ricardo show changes in their sexual practices in the USA in comparison with Peru.</p>
<p>For Victor, his homoerotic experiences in Peru and in the USA are part of a ‘game’ with no emotional attachments. He wants to keep hidden his sexual experiences with men, because he is a ‘responsible man’ who wants to live outside the ‘scandals’ and ‘frivolity’ of the gay scene. Victor is seeing a woman in New York and another one in New Jersey. Parallel to these experiences with women, Victor has regular sexual encounters with a white Peruvian gay man. For the first time in his life, Victor does not avoid the possibility of establishing a long term ‘friendship’ with a ‘discreet’ male lover:<disp-quote>
<p>I don’t want to ruin my life … I don’t want to have a relationship … I don’t want to be looking all the time for someone new either; I want a very discreet friend … he [male lover] is someone whom I can trust, have fun with. (Victor)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Ricardo is more open than Victor to changes in his sexual life in New York in comparison to Lima. He also self-identifies as a heterosexual man with a girlfriend in Lima, and even though he still explains his homosexual experiences as part of his ‘hyper desire for sex’, after three years living in the USA he questions for the first time his sexual identity. Ricardo recognizes that he ‘might be bisexual’, owing to his sexual preferences for men and women, but he emphasizes that this identity only works in the USA. In Peru he will be a <italic>caleta</italic>:<disp-quote>
<p>Since I was an adolescent I was always <italic>arrecho</italic> (horny), I like sex, women, men … no problem [laughs]. I know for many people here, I am bisexual, [but] in Peru I am just super <italic>caleta</italic>, I am not a faggot or gay … I might be bisexual<italic>.</italic> (Ricardo)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>In the case of Gabriel, he experienced the opposite process: from being relatively openly gay in New York, to a life as <italic>caleta</italic> in Lima. Gabriel had to return to Lima after two years living in New Jersey to take care of his mother who was very ill. It was a very difficult decision for Gabriel; he wanted to take care of his mother in Lima, but he knew he would lose his job and also his American visa. Gabriel has been in Lima for more than a year, and after his mother died, he is trying to come back to the USA but he has been denied a visa. Gabriel lives in a working-class area of Lima, and most of his friends are heterosexuals who ignore his sexual orientation. He came out to his best friend as ‘bisexual’. Gabriel has some gay friends outside his neighbourhood with whom he goes occasionally to gay discos. These gay men live also as <italic>caletas</italic> in their own neighbourhood and frequent the gay scene very discreetly. For Gabriel, the departure gate at JFK airport was the ‘door to the closet’ in the homophobic environment of Lima:<disp-quote>
<p>I was living as a gay there [New York], most of my friends were gay, people at my work knew about me … in Lima I had to become <italic>caleta</italic> again. I can’t tell my family or friends about my sexuality, they won’t understand … in this homophobic city being <italic>caleta</italic> is the only way to survive … I told my best friend that I am bisexual … JFK [airport] was the door of my closet. (Gabriel)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Gay men, who are more publicly open about their sexuality, are particularly critical of <italic>caleta</italic> men, for many of these men the term <italic>caleta</italic> has the negative connotation of repressed gay men living in the ‘closet’, so afraid of ‘being discovered’ that they even discriminate against openly gay men to protect their heterosexual reputation:<disp-quote>
<p>My friends and I call <italic>caletas</italic> the ‘macho men’. This kind of man is very masculine, the ‘macho of America’, plays soccer during weekends, has a nice girlfriend or wife, gets drunk with his straight <italic>patas</italic> (buddies), but after soccer he goes in secret and has sex with gay people. He enjoys that, but then when he comes back to his straight world, he discriminates against other gay men, even though he is like us. (Walter)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Sometimes the experience of migration can offer new possibilities for sexual freedom and more progressive views about sexual diversity. But the new place can be as oppressive as their country of origin. The decision to come out to their families and other compatriots is extremely complex, and the fact that most of these immigrant men hide their sexual lives should be understood that being openly gay for them could imply the immediate separation from their families and other compatriots who are their fundamental support system in terms of work, social life, accommodation, comfort, community, language, assistance navigating bureaucracy, when living abroad. For some of them, the dream of ‘sexual freedom’ in New York is only possible for white Americans; for most of my informants, secrecy about their sexuality continues to be part of their lives. They have to continue living as <italic>caletas</italic>:<disp-quote>
<p>Any gay Peruvian will tell you the same, there is no way to be openly gay here [in the USA]. Many people think because ‘this is New York, people are more liberal’. All that discourse only applies to white Americans. If you are Peruvian, Latino or Chinese, the situation is not really different from your own country. Your <italic>paisanos</italic> (compatriots) are here, they are not going to tolerate you being totally gay … and you don’t want to lose them. You need to be very discreet, very <italic>caleta</italic>, you know. (Francisco)</p></disp-quote></p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-1363460711433751"><title>Two separate worlds: ‘Being gay and heterosexual’</title>
<p>In contrast to the <italic>caleta</italic> man who keeps his homoerotic experiences totally hidden, there are other men who negotiate two identities: a public heterosexual identity with their families and compatriots, and a gay identity with a small group of friends, usually gay, with whom they socialize away from where they live. In this sense, for these men ‘being out’ is not synonymous with total disclosure but having a space where they can be ‘out’ without jeopardizing their bonds with their families and compatriots.</p>
<p>Most of my gay informants experience this situation. They have a small group of gay friends, but they do not participate in social activities related to the LGBT community. The fear of being rejected by their compatriots and families creates borders that they do not cross, such as participating in gay parades or being seen with openly gay and ‘feminine’ men in public.</p>
<p>Walter arrived in Virginia and stayed with a friend he met online. Leaving Peru was a liberating experience for him, and he decided to ‘start a new life’ in the USA as a gay man. Walter contacted through the internet some Peruvians in Virginia, and was welcomed into the Peruvian community. Consistent with his desire to be honest about his sexuality, Walter came out to his new Peruvian friends. Their reaction was very disappointing for Walter. Some of them openly rejected him and tried to ‘change’ his behaviour, while others simply stopped inviting him. Walter was isolated. After moving to New York, he knew that this time he would do things ‘correctly’; he learned his lesson. Walter contacted Peruvians in New Jersey and New York to whom he identifies himself as a heterosexual man, while living a discreet gay life with his gay friends in New York:<disp-quote>
<p>I learned my lesson there [Virginia], I was naïve thinking that Peruvians will change in the USA, that I can be honest and start a new life here being openly gay … here I have new [Peruvian] friends, they invite me to their parties … I am a straight guy for them … no reason to repeat my mistake from Virginia … I can live freely with my gay friends. No need to bother with the rest of the Peruvians, they won’t understand. (Walter)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Dario has been living with his parents in New Jersey for more than six years. They are an older couple and Dario looks after them. Dario has a group of Latino and Peruvian gay friends with whom he frequents gay bars in New York City. Dario also has heterosexual friends with whom he socializes in New Jersey. His family and friends in New Jersey do not know about his group of gay friends. Dario lives in the basement of his parent’s place, who continue looking for ‘the perfect Peruvian girlfriend’ for him. Two years ago Dario started dating Johnny, a Colombian gay man, and after a year together, Johnny moved into Dario’s parents’ house. Dario convinced his parents of the economic advantage of sharing his room with his ‘friend’, as a way to earn extra money for the household. Dario and Johnny are very careful in not showing signs of their relationship in front of Dario’s parents and friends in New Jersey. Dario feels supported by the understanding of his Latino boyfriend, an understanding which he considers would be impossible from an American boyfriend. In the house of Dario’s parents, the young gay couple’s bedroom has two beds:<disp-quote>
<p>My uncle found a job for me. I work with his boss, friends and other Peruvians. I have a debt to them, without their help, I wouldn’t be here. I can’t just be selfish and ruin everything and say, ‘you know, I am gay, fuck you and your values’. I have to respect them; I need to be grateful to them … I can’t create a scandal. If they suspect or know about me is one thing, but being known as gay would be a shame, that I don’t want to bring that upon them. (Dario)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Marcelo, 27 and Tony, 30 illustrate the pressure that gay Peruvian men experience reconciling their ‘two worlds’. Marcelo and Tony have been together for more than six years. They moved to New York four years ago, and told their families in Peru that because of the cost of living in New York, they are sharing an apartment. So for both families, Marcelo and Tony are roommates. They always have a spare room ready to be shown to unexpected visitors as Tony’s bedroom. Their secret is carefully kept by their gay friends. Two years ago Marcelo and Tony travelled to a small town outside Lima where a young seminarian, a classmate of Marcelo from school, conducted a ceremony that symbolized the couple’s union. There were no legal documents or any official religious blessing. Nobody from Marcelo’s or Tony’s families was at the ceremony, which was held in secrecy owing to both men’s fears of being discovered and rejected by their families. The couple did not need to ask their small group of gay friends to keep the secret. They have an implicit pact among them to protect each other.</p>
<p>The constant flow of communications between the Peruvian immigrant communities in New Jersey and New York and Peru can represent a real threat for some of these men who maintain a publicly heterosexual life in Peru. Miguel came out to one of his heterosexual cousins in New Jersey, who helps him keep his homosexual life hidden from their families in New Jersey. Marcelo is afraid that his relatives in the USA can disseminate news of his sexual life to his parents in Peru:<disp-quote>
<p>I told my cousin [in the USA] about me, he was very cool … the rest of my family here doesn’t know about me … I trust him … he knows that if people here know about me, they will tell my parents in Lima. He even covers my back when I have a date with some guy … he tells his straight friends that I have a girlfriend in New York … you know, just in case they have doubts about me. (Marcelo)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Discretion and caution are fundamental parts of gay Peruvian immigrant men’s friendships in the USA. The best sign of love, loyalty and trust among gay friends is to keep the secret within the boundaries of the group. There is a tacit agreement among these gay men. Revealing the other’s sexuality will jeopardize their own situation; hence, indiscreet individuals who reveal the <italic>secreto</italic> (the secret) betray the tacit rules of the group. Discretion and caution is the best way of protection, not only for them, but also for their families in Peru and in the USA:<disp-quote>
<p>If someone reveals the other’s sexuality, he is also putting himself at risk of being discovered … it’s a mutual protection among us … for us and for our families. (Roberto)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Men who engage in homosexual behaviour live on the border between two worlds one that knows their secret and one that ignores it. The limits between these two worlds are flexible and many times permeable; hence these men have to build strategies to keep the tension unresolved.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-1363460711433751"><title>Coming out as bisexual: ‘Half coming out’</title>
<p>To cope with potential discrimination and rejection, some of these gay Peruvian men have a ‘half coming out’ as ‘bisexual’ men. Because homosexuality is so feared and stigmatized in the Peruvian context, these men prefer to tell their families that they are bisexuals. A bisexual identity and the fact that these men are still interested in women keep alive their families’ ‘hope’ for a future ‘reconversion’ to a heterosexual life. For some of these gay men, a bisexual identity serves as ‘strategy’ to gain some time, so their families can get accustomed to their sexual lives. For others, a bisexual identity can be the only way to confront their families without breaking the relationship.</p>
<p>In the case of Matías, embracing a bisexual identity helped him to confront his distressed mother; he wanted to be honest with her without causing the pain of the stereotypes associated with gay men. Jerry’s father was ‘devastated’, fearing having a gay son, so Jerry had a ‘half coming out’ and comforted his father with a ‘not-so-threatening’ bisexual identity:<disp-quote>
<p>My father eventually confronted me and asked me if I was gay … I was 26 years old. I could feel he was devastated even to ask, so I told him that I also liked girls, that I was bisexual. It was a real comfort for him; there was still hope for me, it was a half coming out [laughs]. (Jerry)</p></disp-quote>Jerry also illustrates a common situation for many gay Peruvian immigrants. He has to perform multiple identities in different scenarios. He is ‘bisexual’ with his parents in Peru, remains heterosexual to the rest of his family and compatriots in New Jersey, and lives a gay life with his small group of gay friends in New York City, where he works and mainly socializes.</p>
<p>Francisco eloquently explains the ‘advantages’ of the bisexual identity instead of the gay one. In this context, there is a suspicion that an openly gay person is a <italic>pasivo</italic> (receiver), thus being someone who took the ‘one-way’ journey to passive homosexuality, while bisexuals remain ‘masculine’ and their ability to penetrate other people is still intact:<disp-quote>
<p>The ‘good thing’ about bisexuality is that people think that you still are able to fuck someone, that you are not the <italic>maricón</italic> who opens his leg and is sodomized like a woman. If you are bisexual, you are ‘saved’, you are still a man; you didn’t take the ‘one-way journey’ of being totally <italic>maricón</italic>. (Francisco)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>However, like <italic>caletas</italic>, bisexual men can also be heavily criticized as gay men with cowardly, disloyal and distrustful behaviour. Antonio provides a rich description of labels to describe ‘bisexually active’ men: <italic>entendidos</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1363460711433751">6</xref></sup> (the ones who ‘know the gay scene’), <italic>turistas sexuales</italic> (sexual tourists), and <italic>curiosos</italic> (curious). These bisexually active men have different approaches to homosexual experiences and gay men should know how to interact and what to expect from them:<disp-quote>
<p>You have the <italic>entendidos</italic>, they are very normal men, you know, masculine, with a girlfriend, but they have no issues having sex with men also … then you have the <italic>turistas sexuales</italic>, these ones are just passing, you know, like a tourist, they are not going to stay with you, just enjoy the moment with them because after sex they will go back to their women … then there are the <italic>curiosos</italic>, these ones are more open to experimenting with sex with men, trying something different … maybe they will like it and become bisexuals or even gay, maybe they will return to be straights … you should know their type so you won’t get tricked. (Antonio)</p></disp-quote></p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-1363460711433751"><title>The institutionalization of<italic> secreto a voces</italic></title>
<p>Another way through which Peruvians deal with homosexuality is the institutionalization of <italic>secreto a voces</italic> (open secrets). For these gay men, their families and social networks share the secret and perform their expected scripts as a valid strategy to avoid opening a ‘sensitive topic’. As with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1363460711433751">Miller (1989)</xref>, open secrets represent an unarticulated knowledge framed by the boundaries between what is considered public and private. In this cultural scene, all the actors choose to keep the <italic>secreto</italic>. They pretend not to know something that is in the public domain. These open secrets are also active performances of non-disclosure: about what to know and especially how to act out the script of ‘what <italic>not</italic> to know’ about someone’s sexual life:<disp-quote>
<p>I know that my parents know about me, my sister told me that they know, that my mother still cries about that, but [my parents] behave as if they don’t know, and I also pretend I don’t know that they know [laughs], I know, it seems crazy but this is the way it works for everybody, it’s a <italic>secreto a voces</italic>. (Francisco)</p>
<p>I am certain that some of my friends know about my sexuality because one of them told the rest about me. But these friends prefer to behave as if they don’t know, they are still making jokes about me being a womanizer, it’s an innocent joke, they want me to be comfortable, I don’t want to confront them and they also prefer not to know the truth. I do my part and they do the same. We all work to keep up appearances. (John)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>In the case of Ronny, 39, his parents in Peru justify their oldest son’s bachelorhood with his hard work and busy life in New York. As he recounts, he does not need to hide his sexuality; his parents create the ‘answers’ to avoid the feared reality. Ronny came out to his maternal uncle in the USA, who also creates excuses to justify his nephew’s suspicious bachelorhood. However, as Ronny recognizes, this script is just a performance; ‘everybody knows the truth’. The script is only to keep up appearances. For Ronny and some other gay men, the strategy of <italic>secreto a voces</italic> allows him to communicate his secret without explicitly revealing it. It is a way to filter information while at the same time acting as if nothing has changed. For these men, this strategy can constitute a relief from the rejection of an explicit coming out.</p>
<p>Even though Ulises never showed interest in women, and he is confident his parents already know about his sexuality, he thinks they prefer to ‘ignore the evidence’ and act out the script of not knowing, which distanced the relationship between Ulises and his family:<disp-quote>
<p>If you never bring a girlfriend to your place, if you never talk and boast about girls or never look at women’s asses in the streets, you know, your family notices that … My parents prefer ‘not to know’ … There was a time when I was afraid of every call from Peru … to talk about everything but nothing personal, just avoiding to touch T-H-E issue … instead of enjoying my conversations with them, it was like the same anxiety I used to live with in Lima … little by little I became more distant from them, there was always an excuse for not calling them. (Ulises)</p></disp-quote></p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-1363460711433751"><title>‘Full coming out’: Never easy … never ends</title>
<p>For those who fully came out to their family, the process is usually difficult, and sometimes causes separation from family and compatriots. These gay men’s stories display some similarities, but also show differences in their own processes and in their parents’ initial reactions and subsequent coping strategies with their sons’ sexualities.</p>
<p>In the case of Antonio, he came out in Peru before migrating to the USA, and his disclosure involved a serious family crisis that only ended when he finally migrated to the USA and was not jeopardizing the family name or honour in front of the neighbours:<disp-quote>
<p>I truly believe that they felt comfortable only when I finally left Peru. People wouldn’t any longer talk about me; my family name was preserved when the faggot in the family left home. (Antonio)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Tito moved to the USA with his parents when he was three years old. They are American residents and have stable jobs that allow them to live a relatively comfortable life in New Jersey. Tito was 21 years old when he came out to his parents. They were very shocked and asked Tito not to mention the situation again. They did not want to ever discuss Tito’s sexuality. Tito could not live with this situation and left his parents’ home, and moved to New York where he shares an apartment with two American friends. Since then, Tito has not gone back to visit his parents. He has lost contact with his father, but he continues to see his mother when she comes to visit him in New York. For Tito, leaving New Jersey and his family environment was a liberating decision; in New York he can live an openly gay life. The price was very high, however:<disp-quote>
<p>My [American] friends don’t understand my parents, they think that because they are living for so long in the USA, they could be more tolerant about my sexuality [but] they are not alone; they spend their lives with other Peruvians and relatives. For these people homosexuality is still a big issue. I know that my father would tolerate my sexuality if I kept it a secret, you know the saying … ‘God forgives the sin but not the scandal’. But I couldn’t live pretending nothing happened, not even mentioning the topic … I wanted them to know about my sexuality and to live it openly. I just wanted to live honestly … It was my decision, I don’t regret it. [New] Jersey would kill me; here [in New York] I can be honest with myself. (Tito)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>When Michael, a second generation Peruvian in the USA, came out to his parents, his father planned to send Michael back to Peru in a desperate attempt at ‘reconversion’ to heterosexuality. Michael’s father thought that Peru was a safer environment as compared to the ‘excessive liberalism’ of American society:<disp-quote>
<p>Coming out is never easy. My father couldn't take it. He said that it was because over here in the USA everything was so different and libertine. He wanted to send me back to Peru. He even went online and tried to book a flight for my return to Peru, but my mom knocked some sense into him and eventually he didn't continue. My mom just cried a bit, but over the course of a year she accepted it … I guess my father thought that sending me to Peru would somehow change me and help me back to the straight world. (Michael)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Even for these gay men who have the possibility of living their sexuality openly, coming out is ‘never easy’; and it represents a process that ‘never ends’, as there is always someone ‘new’ to reveal their sexuality to:<disp-quote>
<p>The worst thing about coming out is that there is always a new person to tell you are gay, someone new from your job, an old friend who didn’t know, someone in your family … it really never ends! (Facundo)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Love and romance can be more threatening and more strongly rejected than homosexual behaviour. When Facundo came out as a gay man to his parents, they were quite calm; it was the revelation of their son being in love and in a relationship with his boyfriend that really shocked them. Facundo’s parents have been living for more than 20 years in the USA; imagining their youngest son in a romantic relationship with another man was something they were not prepared to hear:<disp-quote>
<p>The real issue wasn’t me being gay or telling them that I was having sex with men; the real drama came when I said that I was in love and had a boyfriend; that was the real bomb for them … being in love with another men. (Facundo)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Roberto moved to the USA when he was a child, and his parents have been living here for more than 20 years. In contrast to Tito and Michael, Roberto negotiated an implicit pact with his parents after he came out to them. Roberto’s parents do not talk about their son’s sexuality. Roberto can even bring his boyfriends to his parents’ house as long as he respects certain rules such as not showing any affection in front of the rest of the family and introducing his boyfriend to the rest of the family as a ‘friend’ or ‘roommate’:<disp-quote>
<p>I lived here [in the USA] my entire life, my parents are here for more than 20 years, but still they are Peruvians, you know. My mother was very supportive; she said she always knew, that mothers could feel everything about their children. My father was silent, skeptical, but hugged me and said I will always be his son and nobody will ever treat me with disrespect … I bring my boyfriends to any family parties … we have an implicit agreement, I don’t show affection for my boyfriend in front of them, and if there is any relative in the house, my boyfriend is always a ‘friend’ or ‘roommate’. My parents really think that this way they protect me from discrimination by my other relatives. (Roberto)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Roberto is aware of the performances and scripts he is expected to perform to fulfil the implicit pact with his parents. Roberto knows that his extended family and compatriots ‘know’ about him, and the only reason that he is not discriminated against is because of his parents’ wealthy economic position within the Peruvian immigrant community. As he relates it, if he were a <italic>pobre cholito</italic> (poor indigenous person), the situation would be different for him:<disp-quote>
<p>Peruvians here respect my parents, they help other people, collaborate with the community … I am certainly sure that because people respect them, nobody bothers me. They ‘know’ about me, but treat me with respect. If I were a <italic>pobre cholito,</italic> they would destroy me. I would be the <italic>marica peruchita</italic> (indigenous Peruvian faggot) to make fun of. (Roberto)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Racial discrimination was one of the major reasons Rafael, a working-class man with indigenous features, decided to leave Peru. Rafael also experienced sexual oppression as a gay man. Rafael did not have the ‘privileges’ of white middle-class gay men from Lima; he lived in a working-class neighbourhood where gay men face constant violence and discrimination, and there is no possibility to embrace a gay identity. After a great effort, Rafael finally got a tourist visa and travelled to the USA. For him, the USA was the place where his indigenous features would not represent a barrier to economic improvement, and it was also the place for sexual freedom. However, Rafael did not have the same network of support as Roberto, and he experienced community rejection. He was the <italic>cholito maricón</italic> (indigenous faggot) that Peruvian immigrants rejected. Coming out was a learning process for Rafael. After arriving in New York, he started an openly gay life, and displayed a gay identity in front of the Peruvian immigrants in New York and New Jersey. However, Rafael’s compatriots did not receive his honesty with the openness he expected. He again felt the rejection that originally forced him to leave Peru and so decided to build a new life outside the Peruvian immigrant community. After years of hard work, Rafael got a good job and started a relationship with an American man. They both live together and socialize mainly with Americans.</p>
<p>Coming out to his family in Peru was not part of Rafael’s plan, but when his American boyfriend and he were planning to travel to Lima together, Rafael had to find the right <italic>justo medio</italic> (balance) to respond to his boyfriend’s request for honesty and openness about their relationship, but at the same time not to confront his parents’ values towards homosexuality. Rafael had to pass the ‘test of love’ in two directions: love for his boyfriend, by telling his family about their relationship; and also demonstrate love for his parents, by not disclosing the ‘secret’ to the rest of the relatives and neighbours in Peru and instead presenting his boyfriend as a friend:<disp-quote>
<p>I had to find the <italic>justo medio</italic> to keep everybody happy. [In Peru] it doesn’t matter that everybody knew we were a couple; the important thing was to play the game, don’t make my family feel uncomfortable, and don’t tell my boyfriend that everybody was calling him my ‘friend’. (Rafael)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The rules of the <italic>secreto a voces</italic> include gestures of love, protection and consideration for the loved ones. Rafael is very comfortable living as an openly gay man with his boyfriend in New York. Rafael also knows that his family in Lima faces a less tolerant environment for sexual diversity. As a gesture of love for his parents in Peru, Rafael will play the game of <italic>secreto a voces</italic>:<disp-quote>
<p>I have a life here [in New York]. It took me my entire life to be where I am and I don’t want to move back and be in the closet again. Every time I visit my parents in Peru, I don’t like that they are conflicted, that people might discover that I am gay here, or that I can’t be too open and tell more people about myself. I love them, they do their best to keep the secret there, and it would be unfair for me to destroy everything they believe in. I don’t live there; they would suffer if I opened my gayness to everybody. I am happy here and they have the right to be happy there too. (Rafael)</p></disp-quote></p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec8-1363460711433751" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The widespread assumption that Latin American men who have sex with men exhibit a ‘double standard’ in their sexual lives could be deconstructed by understanding how many times this apparent double discourse is the only way to deal with homophobia, family shame, the potential loss of social capital and community support. Gay men and men who have sex with men have the right to decide when and to whom to come out to about their sexual identities and sexual practices. Being <italic>caleta</italic> by displaying masculine capital is often the only option for many men who fear homophobia and rejection. Others embrace a less threatening identity as ‘bisexuals’ as a strategy to relieve the fear of a gay identity. Even gay men who consider themselves ‘out of the closet’ can, in fact, be open only to a small group of people, and live their sexual lives hidden from their families and the rest of their compatriots. Most of them have developed parallel social identities: they are ‘gay’ within their very discreet network of gay friends, and ‘heterosexual’ with their families, friends, and other compatriots in Peru and in the USA.</p>
<p>There is also an institutionalization of <italic>secreto a voces</italic> (open secrets) through public performances about these men’s sexual lives. Discretion and secrecy act as an implicit agreement among gay men and their families in order to protect themselves from the stigma of having a gay relative. The<italic> secreto a voces</italic> represents a fundamental aspect in the lives and identities of gay men and men who have sex with men. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1363460711433751">Pecheny (2003)</xref> identifies two complementary aspects of the <italic>secreto</italic>: a passive form of discretion through <italic>simulación</italic> (simulation) and an active way to keep discretion through <italic>simulacro</italic> (rehearsal). Both forms are used to prevent discrimination against stigmatized individuals.</p>
<p>The <italic>secreto a voces</italic> constitutes a contradictory strategy that protects gay men and their families from discrimination in societies such as in Latin America. For some, the <italic>secreto</italic> is a sign of love, care and consideration, performing scripts that maintain the tension between the known and unknown. For others, this <italic>secreto a voces</italic> and its protective measures are a heavy weight to carry and can be associated with sexual oppression. For still others, this <italic>secreto</italic> is a comfortable strategy for not dealing with the sexual rights of sexual minorities and helps to maintain homosexuality as being invisible. What all these forms have in common is its palatable nature that helps to preserve the limits between the public and the private worlds.</p>
<p>There is also an aspect of resistance and contestation in this strategy. In some cases, gay men have the desire to communicate their sexual lives to others, which involves trust and the expectation of support and care. In other cases, this strategy serves to ‘solve’ tensions through filtering the <italic>secreto</italic>. This paradoxical aspect of the <italic>secreto</italic> shows the complexities of a cultural phenomenon that challenges the boundaries of heteronormativity and creates spaces for resistance by gay men and men who have sex with men in Latin America.</p>
<p>The paradox between the public and private worlds and between the stigma associated with homosexuality and the apparent tolerance of <italic>secreto a voces</italic> can be explained with a cultural idiom that reconciles this contradiction: ‘God forgives the sin but not the scandal’. Considering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1363460711433751">Foucault’s (1989)</xref> assertion that what most bothers people about gayness is the ‘gay lifestyle’ rather than the actual (homosexual) sexual acts, the institutionalization of <italic>secreto a voces</italic> configures a complex mechanism by which individuals pay more attention to the display of masculine capital and public performances of heterosexuality than the actual homosexual lives of their family members. What individuals do with their sexual lives can be ignored if it remains secret or at least discreet. Everybody plays the game of ‘not knowing the secret’. Doing so ensures that the heterosexual social order remains unquestioned. This cultural mechanism of ‘turning a blind eye’ seeks to preserve family honour, and ‘protects’ families and their presumed gay family members from the stigma and ‘scandal’ of publicly acknowledging a gay family member. God or Peruvian society, ‘forgives the sin if there is no scandal’ associated to homosexual acts.</p>
<p>Global changes have influenced all aspects of daily life, including sexual life, playing a fundamental role in the configuration of sexualities, sexual cultures and gay communities in places such as Latin America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1363460711433751">Altman, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1363460711433751">Parker, 1999</xref>). Migration opens new possibilities for sexual freedom for men who have sex with men and for gay men. However, migration can also increase the vulnerability of some of these men, and the new place can be as oppressive as their country of origin. Migration does not necessarily shift the patterns of disclosure because of the nature of transnationalism that creates proximity between Peru and the USA. This can constitute a real fear for gay immigrants who had the dream of sexual freedom in a distant land. ‘Coming out’ can bring relief and support; elicit discrimination and violence, as well as rejection and isolation from their families and compatriots, which can jeopardize these men’s lives. For these men, coming out is never easy … and never ends.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes><title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1363460711433751"><label>1</label><p>Diverse authors address the complexity and paradoxes inherent to the ‘MSM’ category to label ‘bisexually active’ men. On the one hand, this category has invaluable importance in the fight against the HIV/AIDS epidemic, but on the other hand it reduces the spectrum of these men’s sexual desires, self-representation, and overlooks their sexual interactions with women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1363460711433751">Diaz, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1363460711433751">Muñoz-Laboy, 2004</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-1363460711433751"><label>2</label><p>I define masculine capital as a form of cultural capital that provides men with the necessary ‘masculine’ skills and cultural competence to achieve legitimacy and social recognition as respected men. This masculine capital goes beyond life skills that boys and girls should acquire as part of their development, but rather includes the acquisition of certain manners; body postures; sexual expertise; ability in sports, such as soccer; control and display of emotions; among others. These ‘masculine’ performances prepare men to display manhood and fulfil the social expectations of men in society. In this way, masculine capital is learned and acquired through repeated mechanisms and techniques to police masculine behaviours, and it also varies with factors such as social class and age. Men have to learn how to reproduce this capital in culturally appropriate ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1363460711433751">Vasquez del Aguila, 2008</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-1363460711433751"><label>3</label><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1363460711433751">Bourdieu (1990)</xref> argues that instead of following rules imposed on them, individuals are oriented by ‘strategies’ to negotiate with cultural norms. These strategies imply individuals’ understandings of the ‘practical sense of things’ and the sense of knowing the ‘rules of the game’. Individuals have cultural knowledge of the particular scene, but they also exercise ‘agency’ to negotiate, maintain and also change the rules of social relations.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-1363460711433751"><label>4</label><p>In order to protect my informants’ confidentiality, all their names used in this article are pseudonyms.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-1363460711433751"><label>5</label><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460711433751">Carrillo (2002)</xref> describes Mexican men who conceal their homoerotic experiences from society, how these men remain ‘normal men’ by respecting, at least publicly, social expectations of ‘masculine’ behaviour.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6-1363460711433751"><label>6</label><p><italic>Entendido</italic> literally means a person who knows or understands. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1363460711433751">Parker (1999)</xref> describes the <italic>entendido</italic> subculture in Brazil. These men, who are either interested only in men, or in men and women, and regardless of their sexual role in homosexual encounters, know the ‘rules of the game’ in the ‘gay market’. In the Peruvian <italic>mundo the ambiente</italic> (gay scene), <italic>entendidos</italic> are individuals who identify as heterosexuals but are also ‘open’ to homoerotic experiences.</p></fn></fn-group></notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koreck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Silences: ‘Hispanics', AIDS, and sexual practices</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggleton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Culture, Society and Sexuality: A Reader</source>. <publisher-loc>London and Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UCL Press</publisher-name>. <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Global gaze/global gays</article-title>. <source>GLQ: A Journal of Lesbian and Gay Studies</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourdieu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>The Logic of Practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosasco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Secreto a Voces: Homoerotismo Masculino en Lima: Culturas, Identidades y Salud Sexual</source>. <publisher-loc>Lima</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UPCH/REDESS Jóvenes</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Migrancy, masculine identities and AIDS: The psychosocial context of HIV transmission on the South African gold mines</article-title>. <source>Social Sciences and Medicine</source> <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Sexuality of Migration. Border Crossing and Mexican Immigrant Men</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Night is Young: Sexuality in Mexico in the Time of AIDS</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Carrillo H (2004) Sexual migration, cross-cultural sexual encounters, and sexual health. <italic>Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy</italic> 1(3): 58–70</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>The Men and the Boys</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Latino Gay Men and HIV</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sexual choice, sexual act</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lotringer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Foucault Live. Collected Interviews, 1961–1984</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Semiotext(e)</publisher-name>. <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaraysky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorentzen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Transgender sex workers and sexual transmigration between Guadalajara and San Francisco</article-title>. <source>Latin American Perspectives</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>158</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Subject honor, object shame</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Savran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>The Masculinity Studies Reader</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishers</publisher-name>. <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>The Novel and the Police</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>California University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moodie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndatshe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Going for Gold: Men, Mines, and Migration</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muñoz-Laboy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Beyond ‘MSM': Sexual desire among bisexually-active Latino men in New York City</article-title>. <source>Sexualities</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Caribbean Pleasure Industry. Tourism Sexuality, and AIDS in the Dominican Republic</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Beneath the Equator. Cultures of Desire, Male Homosexuality, and Emerging Gay Communities in Brazil</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pecheny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Identidades Discretas</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Arfuch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Identidades, Sujetos y Subjetividades: Narrativas de la Diferencia</source>. <publisher-loc>Buenos Aires</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prometeo</publisher-name>. <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phellas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Construction of Sexual and Cultural Identities. Greek-Cypriot Men in Britain</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Anthropology rediscovers sexuality: A theoretical comment</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggleton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Culture, Society and Sexuality: A Reader</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>. <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasquez del Aguila</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Being a man in a transnational world: Masculinity and sexuality among Peruvian immigrants in New York City</source>. <publisher-loc>PhD dissertation. Columbia University</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York City</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1363460711433751"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Discourse, desire and sexual deviance: Some problems in a history of homosexuality</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggleton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Culture, Society and Sexuality. A Reader</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>. <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<notes><p><bold>Ernesto Vasquez del Aguila</bold> earned his PhD in medical anthropology from Columbia University, New York. He has published studies on sexual and reproductive rights; the health of sexual minorities; non-discrimination; masculinity; and sexuality. He is a lecturer and researcher in the School of Social Justice, University College Dublin, Ireland, where he teaches a course on masculinities and global health inequalities.</p></notes>
</back>
</article>