<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AES</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaes</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Aesthet Surg J</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Aesthetic Surgery Journal</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">1090-820X</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1527-330X</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1090820X12471830</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1090820X12471830</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Reviews</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Book Review: The Art of Aesthetic Surgery: Principles and Techniques</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thorne</surname>
                  <given-names>Charles H.</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>MD</degrees>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff1-1090820X12471830">Dr Thorne is Associate Professor, Department of Plastic Surgery, New York University School of Medicine, New York, New York</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>2</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>33</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <fpage>NP5</fpage>
         <lpage>NP6</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nahai</surname>
                  <given-names>Foad</given-names>
               </name>
            </person-group>. <source>The Art of Aesthetic Surgery: Principles and Techniques</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> 
            <publisher-loc>St Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Quality Medical Publishing</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. ISBN-10: <isbn>1576263118</isbn>
         </product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2012 The American Society for Aesthetic Plastic Surgery, Inc.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="society">American Society for Aesthetic Plastic Surgery, Inc.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <graphic alt-version="no" id="img1-1090820X12471830" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1090820X12471830-img1.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
      <sec id="section1-1090820X12471830">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Only 6 years after the first edition was published, Dr Nahai has produced the second edition of <italic>The Art of Aesthetic Surgery</italic>, the only truly comprehensive textbook of cosmetic surgery in the world. Not content with a cursory or empty sequel to a monumentally successful first edition, he has provided the plastic surgery community with an edition that is, in every way, bigger and better than its predecessor.</p>
         <p>The book has been expanded from 2 to 3 volumes and from 1786 to 3187 pages. The additions (39 new chapters) are timely and appropriate given the direction in which the field has evolved in recent years. The text is accompanied by 7 DVDs containing videos of procedures in almost all of the anatomic areas. There are approximately 115 contributing authors, of whom 65 are new to this edition.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section2-1090820X12471830">
         <title>Strengths</title>
         <p>In short, Foad Nahai has done it again. Both the new chapters in this book and the rewritten previous chapters reflect the trends in our subspecialty toward less invasive procedures and the appreciation of volume replacement in the face, the development of new technologies and injectable products, the explosion of breast and body contouring procedures (including fat grafting to the breast and contouring for massive weight loss patients), and the recent increased focus on patient safety in our plastic surgery organizations.</p>
         <p>Although we have come to expect attractive books from publisher Karen Berger and her colleagues at QMP, this book is even more appealing and easy to read than the first edition. The large font and large images are familiar and relaxing, but the print, at least in the edition I reviewed, is crisper and darker. Unlike most textbooks, in which one is tempted to peek ahead to find out how many pages a chapter contains and then trudge through them, this book is actually addictive and hard to put down.</p>
         <p>As impressive as the content and the appearance are, however, the personal nature of the text is what is most striking. The contributors have done their part, providing well-written and well-illustrated chapters, but the editor’s fingerprints are on virtually every page. Each anatomic section begins with a “Clinical Decision Making” chapter, and almost all of these were written by Dr Nahai himself. Three decades of clinical experience has enabled him to sprinkle pearls of wisdom throughout the entire text. Like any multiauthored textbook, there is some variability in style, length, and quality of the chapters, but because Dr Nahai (and Ms Berger’s staff) has actually read, edited, and integrated the content into a cohesive whole, there is much less variability than in most such tomes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section3-1090820X12471830">
         <title>Summary</title>
         <p>For the young surgeon starting a practice, the seasoned surgeon changing the focus of his or her practice to cosmetic surgery, or the veteran aesthetic surgeon, the second edition of <italic>The Art of Aesthetic Surgery</italic> will likely be the most referenced text on the office shelf. No other book provides comparable scope and depth, and this text is worth every penny.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section4-1090820X12471830">
         <title>Rating</title>
         <graphic alt-version="no" id="img2-1090820X12471830" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1090820X12471830-img2.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
         <p>To purchase this book, visit: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qmp.com/product_dtl_20.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.qmp.com/product_dtl_20.htm</ext-link>
         </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <fn fn-type="conflict">
            <label>Disclosures</label>
            <p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and publication of this article.</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>