<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ADB</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spadb</journal-id>
<journal-title>Adaptive Behavior</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1059-7123</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2633</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059712312462248</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1059712312462248</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Self-organized flocking with a mobile robot swarm: a novel motion control method</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>Eliseo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1059712312462248">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1059712312462248">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>Ali Emre</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1059712312462248">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Huepe</surname><given-names>Cristián</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1059712312462248">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Stranieri</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1059712312462248">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinciroli</surname><given-names>Carlo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1059712312462248">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1059712312462248">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1059712312462248"><label>1</label>IRIDIA, CoDE, Université Libre de Bruxelles, Brussels, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1059712312462248"><label>2</label>Laboratory of Socioecology and Social Evolution, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1059712312462248"><label>3</label>Mechatronics Department, Türk Hava Kurumu University, Etimesgut/Ankara,Turkey</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1059712312462248"><label>4</label>CHuepe Labs Inc., Chicago IL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1059712312462248">Eliseo Ferrante, Laboratory of Socioecology and Social Evolution, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, 59 Naamsestraat - bus 2466, B-3000 Leuven, Belgium. Email: <email>eliseo.ferrante@bio.kuleuven.be</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>460</fpage>
<lpage>477</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Society of Adaptive Behavior</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In flocking, a swarm of robots moves cohesively in a common direction. Traditionally, flocking is realized using two main control rules: proximal control, which controls the cohesion of the swarm using local range-and bearing information about neighboring robots; and alignment control, which allows the robots to align in a common direction and uses more elaborate sensing mechanisms to obtain the orientation of neighboring robots. So far, limited attention has been given to motion control, used to translate the output of these two control rules into robot motion. In this paper, we propose a novel motion control method: magnitude-dependent motion control (MDMC). Through simulations and real robot experiments, we show that, with MDMC, flocking in a random direction is possible without the need for alignment control and for robots having a preferred direction of travel. MDMC has the advantage to be implementable on very simple robots that lack the capability to detect the orientation of their neighbors. In addition, we introduce a small proportion of robots informed about a desired direction of travel. We compare MDMC with a motion control method used in previous robotics literature, which we call magnitude-independent motion control (MIMC), and we show that the swarms can travel longer distances in the desired direction when using MDMC instead of MIMC. Finally, we systematically study flocking under various conditions: with or without alignment control, with or without informed robots, with MDMC or with MIMC.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Flocking</kwd>
<kwd>swarm robotics</kwd>
<kwd>swarm intelligence</kwd>
<kwd>coordinated motion</kwd>
<kwd>self-organization</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1059712312462248" sec-type="intro">
<title>1 Introduction</title>
<p>Flocking, also referred to as self-organized flocking, is a collective behavior that is widely observed in nature. It can be defined as the cohesive and ordered motion of a group of individuals in a common direction. Examples can be seen in many animal species, from locusts to birds and quadrupeds.</p>
<p>One of the first computer models of the flocking behavior was proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1059712312462248">Reynolds (1987)</xref>. In the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1059712312462248">Reynolds (1987)</xref>, the behavior of each individual of the swarm is determined by three components: attraction, repulsion and alignment. The attraction component allows the individual to be attracted to its neighbors to keep the group together. The repulsion component allows the individual to stay away from its neighbors to avoid collisions. The alignment component allows the individual to match its heading direction to an average of the heading of its neighbors, thus making all individuals point in the same direction. Note that these three components had already been introduced in a previous flocking model by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1059712312462248">Suzuki and Sakai (1973)</xref>.</p>
<p>Reynolds’ model can be considered as a seminal work that inspired much subsequent literature. In the majority of these later works, none of the individuals composing the swarm has a preferred direction of motion. This literature includes works in biology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1059712312462248">Couzin, Krause, James, Ruxton, &amp; Franks, 2002</xref>), statistical physics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059712312462248">Vicsek, Czirok, Ben-Jacob, Cohen, &amp; Shochet, 1995</xref>) and robotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, GökÇe, &amp; Şahin, 2008</xref>). Another part of the literature followed the seminal work of Couzin, Krause, Franks, and Levin (2005), who introduced the notions of informed individuals, which have a preferred direction of motion or goal direction, and non-informed individuals, which are not aware of the goal direction.</p>
<p>In robotics, all works use rules of attraction and repulsion that are similar to those studied by Reynolds. However, only some works use the alignment rule. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref> developed a flocking method consisting of proximal control, which encodes the attraction and repulsion rules, and alignment control, which encodes the alignment rule. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref> achieved a flocking behavior on autonomous robots that, for the first time, did not require external computation or communication devices. They did not consider informed robots, but these were later introduced in a subsequent study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059712312462248">Çelikkanat and Şahin (2010)</xref>. Other works achieved alignment either by using global information or simulated sensors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1059712312462248">Hayes &amp; Dormiani-Tabatabaei, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059712312462248">Holland, Woods, Nardi, &amp; Clark, 2005</xref>) or by making all or most of the robots aware of the desired goal direction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059712312462248">Matarić, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059712312462248">Spears, Spears, Hamann, &amp; Heil, 2004</xref>). When the knowledge of the goal direction is widely available in the swarm, the alignment of all robots in the same direction results merely from this global information rather than from a self-organization process.</p>
<p>In this paper, we take a perspective that is different from what is found in the literature. We propose magnitude-dependent motion control (MDMC), a method that, together with proximal control, achieves flocking with minimal components. By minimal we mean that, differently from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref>, alignment control is not needed; differently from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1059712312462248">Hayes and Dormiani-Tabatabaei (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059712312462248">Holland et al. (2005)</xref>, external hardware is not needed; differently from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059712312462248">Matarić (1994)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059712312462248">Spears et al. (2004)</xref>, information about the goal direction is not needed. Our method achieves ordered and cohesive flocking using very simple robot hardware: robots only need to be non-holonomic and to sense their neighbors’ range and bearing. Using this method, large swarms composed of hundreds or thousands of even very simple robots (such as nano-robots, aerial robots or robots used for extra-planetary missions) could be used to explore large environments. Furthermore, we believe that our model is simple but powerful enough to be used as a reference model for biology, for studying the movement of very simple animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1059712312462248">Simpson, Sword, Lorch, &amp; Couzin, 2006</xref>) or cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1059712312462248">Szabó et al., 2006</xref>) and, in the context of statistical physics, for studying the principles underlying swarms of active particles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059712312462248">Vicsek et al., 1995</xref>; Romanczuk, Couzin, &amp; L.Schimansky-Geier, 2009).</p>
<p>The contribution of this paper is twofold. First, we introduce MDMC, a method capable of achieving self-organized flocking without alignment control and without informed robots. Second, we systematically study self-organized flocking by performing extensive simulations and validating our results with real robot experiments. The study is conducted with and without alignment control, with and without informed robots, with MDMC and with <italic>magnitude-independent motion control</italic> (MIMC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al., 2008</xref>). We show that MDMC always outperforms MIMC when alignment control is not used, both with and without informed robots.</p>
<p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we introduce the flocking and the motion control methods. In Section 3, we explain how the model has been implemented on the utilized robotics platform. In Section 4, we describe the metrics, the simulation and the real robot experimental setup. In Sections 5 and 6, we present the results obtained without and with informed robots, respectively. In Section 7, we discuss related works within robotics literature and we also survey some related works in statistical physics. Finally, in Section 8 we conclude and we discuss possible future work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1059712312462248">
<title>2 Self-organized flocking</title>
<p>In this section we describe the method we use to achieve flocking. The method is made of different components: proximal control, alignment control and motion control. Motion control is, in turn, realized either with the novel MDMC or with MIMC.</p>
<p>The overall flocking method is defined as follows. We assume that the robot under consideration, the focal robot, computes a flocking control vector denoted by <bold>f</bold>. The expression of the flocking control vector, in the most complete form that we call Model 1, is</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1059712312462248">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <bold>p</bold> is the proximal control vector, encoding the attraction and repulsion rules, <bold>a</bold> is the alignment control vector, encoding the alignment rule, and <bold>g</bold> is the goal direction vector, encoding the goal following behavior used only by the informed robots. In this study we will also consider the following models:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1059712312462248">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1059712312462248">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula4-1059712312462248">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math4-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq4.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>In Section 4, we explain how these models are utilized.</p>
<sec id="section3-1059712312462248">
<title>2.1 Proximal control</title>
<p>The proximal control part of the method is common to all four models. The main idea of proximal control is that, in order to achieve cohesive flocking, a robot needs to keep a certain distance from its neighbors. The proximal control vector encodes the attraction and repulsion rules: a robot tends to move closer to its neighbors when their distance is greater than the desired distance and tends to move away from them when their distance is smaller than the desired distance.</p>
<p>Proximal control assumes that the focal robot is able to sense the range and bearing of its neighboring robots within a maximum interaction distance <inline-formula id="inline-formula1-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math5-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The proximal control vector <bold>p</bold> is computed as</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula5-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math6-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq5.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula2-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math7-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is a vector expressed in the complex plane; <inline-formula id="inline-formula3-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math8-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the number of neighboring robots perceived by the focal robot within range <inline-formula id="inline-formula4-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math9-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>; and <inline-formula id="inline-formula5-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math10-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula6-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math11-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> denote, respectively, the relative range and bearing of the <italic>i</italic>th neighboring robot, expressed in the body-fixed reference frame of the focal robot.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1059712312462248">1</xref></sup> The magnitude of the vector, <inline-formula id="inline-formula7-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math12-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, is computed as</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula6-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math13-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∂</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∂</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq6.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>In words, <inline-formula id="inline-formula8-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math14-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is defined as the negative derivative of the virtual potential function <inline-formula id="inline-formula9-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math15-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. A virtual potential function is often used in swarm robotics and statistical physics to model social interaction between robots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059712312462248">Spears et al., 2004</xref>) or between particles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1059712312462248">Gregoire, Chate, &amp; Tu, 2003</xref>). In our study, we use a generalized version of the Lennard–Jones potential function:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula7-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math16-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq7.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>Parameter ϵ determines the depth of the potential function; that is, the minimum of the potential function located at <inline-formula id="inline-formula10-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math17-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>des</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is <inline-formula id="inline-formula11-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math18-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. We generalized the standard Lennard–Jones potential used in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1059712312462248">Hettiarachchi and Spears (2009)</xref> in order to have the flexibility to choose the exponent α, which determines the steepness of the function. Originally, Lennard–Jones set <inline-formula id="inline-formula12-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math19-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. In this paper, as summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1059712312462248">Table 1</xref>, we use <inline-formula id="inline-formula13-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math20-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, which corresponds to a lower steepness, as this value was found to achieve better performance in experiments with real robots.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Parameter values or range of values used in the controller and in simulations. The values in <bold>bold</bold> are the nominal values, that is, the values used in experiments when the effect of another parameter is explored</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Parameter</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="left">Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic></td>
<td>Number of robots</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula14-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math21-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>50</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>500</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1000</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ρ</td>
<td>Proportion of informed robots</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula15-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math22-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo mathvariant="bold">.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>05</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>15</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>U</italic></td>
<td>Maximum forward speed</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula16-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math23-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>005</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> m/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ω</td>
<td>Maximum angular speed</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula17-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math24-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>π</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> rad/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula18-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math25-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
<td>MDMC linear gain</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula19-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math26-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> m/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula20-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math27-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
<td>MDMC angular gain</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula21-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math28-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>06</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> rad/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula22-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math29-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
<td>MIMC angular gain</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula23-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math30-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>25</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> rad/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>l</italic></td>
<td>Inter-wheel distance</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula24-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math31-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>14</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>α</td>
<td>Steepness of potential function</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ϵ</td>
<td>Strength of potential function</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula25-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math32-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula26-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math33-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>des</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
<td>Desired inter-robot distance</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula27-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math34-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>45</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula28-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math35-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
<td>Maximum interaction range of proximal control</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula29-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math36-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>des</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>81</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula30-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math37-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
<td>Maximum interaction range of alignment control</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula31-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math38-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>σ</td>
<td>Amount of noise</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula32-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math39-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>T</italic></td>
<td>Duration of experiments</td>
<td>2500 s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>R</italic></td>
<td>Number of runs per setting</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Finally, regarding the maximum interaction distance <inline-formula id="inline-formula33-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math40-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, in general it can be less than or equal to the maximum sensing range of the sensor. In this study, in order for the proposed model to work in the absence of alignment control and informed robots, we found that <inline-formula id="inline-formula34-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math41-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> must be chosen so that, when the swarm reaches a stable formation, interactions among robots are limited to the first neighbors only in the Voronoi sense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1059712312462248">Voronoi, 1908</xref>). In order to achieve this without having to compute the Voronoi tessellation, we set <inline-formula id="inline-formula35-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math42-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>·</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, that is, the maximum interaction range is less than twice the desired distance <inline-formula id="inline-formula36-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math43-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> between two robots.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1059712312462248">
<title>2.2 Alignment control</title>
<p>The main idea of alignment control is that a robot computes the average orientation of its neighbors and adjusts its own orientation accordingly.</p>
<p>The method used for alignment control uses the following equation:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula8-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math44-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∥</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>∥</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq8.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula37-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math45-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the orientation of the focal robot, <inline-formula id="inline-formula38-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math46-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the number of neighbors within a range <inline-formula id="inline-formula39-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math47-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> of the focal robot, <inline-formula id="inline-formula40-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math48-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> are the orientation of the neighbors expressed in the body-fixed reference frame of the focal robot and <inline-formula id="inline-formula41-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math49-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∥</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>·</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>∥</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes the length of a vector. The focal robot calculates its alignment control vector as the average orientation of the <inline-formula id="inline-formula42-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math50-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> neighboring robots and of its own orientation (which we label as <inline-formula id="inline-formula43-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math51-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1059712312462248">
<title>2.3 Motion control</title>
<p>Motion control is used to convert the flocking control vector <bold>f</bold> into the forward speed <italic>u</italic> and the angular speed ω of the robot that is assumed to be non-holonomic. In the following, we describe the two motion control methods considered in this paper.</p>
<sec id="section6-1059712312462248">
<title>2.3.1 Magnitude-dependent motion control (MDMC)</title>
<p>MDMC is the novel contribution of this paper. In MDMC, the forward and angular speed of the robot depend on both the magnitude and the direction of the flocking control vector. Therefore, the method uses all of the information contained in this vector.</p>
<p>We define MDMC as follows. Let <inline-formula id="inline-formula44-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math52-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula45-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math53-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> denote the projection of the flocking control vector (<bold>f</bold>) on the <italic>x</italic>- and <italic>y</italic>-axis of the body-fixed reference frame, respectively. The forward speed <italic>u</italic> is directly proportional to the <italic>x</italic> component of the vector, pointing in the same direction as the robot’s orientation. The angular speed ω, instead, is directly proportional to the <italic>y</italic> component of the vector, pointing in the direction perpendicular to the robot’s orientation. The corresponding equations are</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula9-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math54-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula9-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq9.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula10-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math55-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula10-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq10.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>U</italic> is a forward biasing speed, and <inline-formula id="inline-formula46-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math56-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula47-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math57-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> are the linear and angular gains, respectively.</p>
<p>The rationale for this method is as follows: the larger the <italic>x</italic>-component of the flocking control vector, the faster we want the robot to move forward; the larger the <italic>y</italic>-component of the flocking control vector, the faster we want the robot to turn. Note that, with MDMC, robots can in principle move also backwards, but they have a propension to move forward due to the presence of the <inline-formula id="inline-formula48-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math58-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> term in the equation for the forward speed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1059712312462248">
<title>2.3.2 Magnitude-independent motion control (MIMC)</title>
<p>MIMC was introduced for the first time by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref> and later used in subsequent work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059712312462248">Çelikkanat and Şahin (2010)</xref>. In MIMC, the forward and angular speed of the robot only partially depend on the information contained in the flocking control vector. By ‘partially’ we mean that, for calculating the speeds, only the direction of the flocking control vector is taken into account, while the magnitude is discarded.</p>
<p>Let <bold>o</bold> be the unit vector matching the orientation of the focal robot (it points forward along the <inline-formula id="inline-formula49-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math59-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>axis of the body-fixed reference frame). The forward velocity and the angular velocities are computed as</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula11-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math60-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mtable align="left">
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd columnalign="center">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">o</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>·</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">o</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>·</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>≥</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd columnalign="center" columnspan="1">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>otherwise</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>;</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula11-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq11.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula12-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math61-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>∠</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">o</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>∠</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">f</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula12-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq12.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula50-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math62-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the angular gain and · denotes the dot product of two vectors.</p>
<p>The rationale for the method is as follows. The robot modulates its forward speed according to the angular difference between the flocking control vector and its orientation. When the two directions are aligned, the robot moves at maximum speed <italic>U</italic>. When the angular difference is equal to or larger than <inline-formula id="inline-formula51-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math63-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>90</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∘</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the robot does not move forward but rotates on the spot. In between these two cases, the forward speed is interpolated between 0 and <italic>U</italic> according to the dot product between the flocking control vector and the robot’s orientation. The angular speed is instead proportional to the angular difference between the flocking control vector and the robot’s orientation. Note that, with MIMC, the robots are not able to move backwards.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1059712312462248">
<title>3 Self-organized flocking with mobile robots</title>
<p>The mobile robot we use is the foot-bot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1059712312462248">Bonani et al., 2010</xref>), shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1059712312462248">Figure 1a</xref>. The foot-bot is commonly used for swarm robotics experiments and was developed during the Swarmanoid project<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1059712312462248">2</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1059712312462248">Dorigo et al., in press</xref>)</p>
<fig id="fig1-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>(a) The foot-bot with its used sensors and actuators. (b) The arena as seen by the overhead camera used for tracking: on the left-hand side we created a light source by placing four lamps; a cardboard hat with a directional marker is placed on each foot-bot, in order to detect its orientation to compute the required metrics; the glowing robots are informed about the desired goal direction (this example is taken from experiments with informed robots). Note that LEDs and cardboard hats are used for debugging, visualization and measurement purposes only, but are never utilized by the controller.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section9-1059712312462248">
<title>3.1 The hardware</title>
<p>We utilized the following sensors and actuators: (i) A light sensor, used to measure the intensity and the direction of the light in the environment. (ii) A range and bearing system (RAB), used to measure the range and the bearing of the other robots. (iii) Two wheel actuators, used to control independently the speed of the left and the right wheels of the robot.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1059712312462248">
<title>3.2 The simulator</title>
<p>We used the ARGoS<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1059712312462248">3</xref></sup> simulator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059712312462248">Pinciroli et al., 2011</xref>) to execute physics-based simulations of the robot dynamics when real-robot experiments are not possible or practical. ARGoS is an open-source, plug-in based simulator in which custom-made physics engines and robots with any desired degree of accuracy can be added. We used a custom-made 2D kinematic physics engine and a realistic model of the foot-bot that simulates very accurately all of the sensors and actuators. Another feature of ARGoS is the possibility to cross-compile controllers both in simulation and on the real robots. This allowed us to seamlessly port the same controller studied in simulation to the real robots.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1059712312462248">
<title>3.3 Flocking implementation</title>
<p>The method described in Section 2 is implemented both on simulated and on real robots as follows. Proximal control is achieved by using the RAB to measure the relative range and bearing <inline-formula id="inline-formula52-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math64-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula53-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math65-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> of the <italic>i</italic>th neighbor. Since robots are not able to measure the orientation of their neighbors directly, we achieve alignment control by using a method similar to that in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref>. A light source, placed in a fixed position in the environment, is used to define a reference frame common to all robots. Each aligning robot measures its orientation <inline-formula id="inline-formula54-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math66-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> with respect to this reference frame by using its on-board light sensor. It then communicates <inline-formula id="inline-formula55-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math67-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> to its neighbors by using the communication unit present in the RAB. The result is equivalent to having neighbors that are able to sense each others’ orientations. Only the informed robots are given the goal direction, expressed with respect to the fixed light source.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1059712312462248">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>To achieve motion control, we first limit the forward speed to the interval <inline-formula id="inline-formula56-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math68-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, and the angular speed to the interval <inline-formula id="inline-formula57-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math69-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. We then use the differential drive model used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref> to convert the forward speed <italic>u</italic> and the angular speed ω into the linear speeds of the left (<inline-formula id="inline-formula58-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math70-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) and right (<inline-formula id="inline-formula59-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math71-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) wheel:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula13-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math72-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula13-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq13.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula14-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math73-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula14-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq14.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>l</italic> is the distance between the wheels. Note that, in MIMC and MDMC, we fix the maximum attainable speeds to the same values. This is done for two reasons: first, in order to be able to properly compare the performance of the two methods; second, in order to have numerically stable simulation results with the control time-step used (<inline-formula id="inline-formula60-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math74-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s), which requires limiting both speeds to low values.</p>
<p>We summarize the values of the parameters used in our experiments in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1059712312462248">Table 1</xref> (simulation and controller parameters) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1059712312462248">Table 2</xref> (real robot). Note that the parameters used for the controller in simulation are the same as those used in the real robot experiments.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Parameter values or range of values used for the real-robots experiments. All of the parameters related to the controllers were omitted in this table, since they are the same as in simulation (refer to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1059712312462248">Table 1</xref>)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Parameter</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="left">Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic></td>
<td>Number of robots</td>
<td><italic>8</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ρ</td>
<td>Proportion of informed robots</td>
<td><inline-formula id="inline-formula61-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math75-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>25</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>T</italic></td>
<td>Duration of experiments</td>
<td>300 s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>R</italic></td>
<td>Number of runs per setting</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1059712312462248">
<title>4 Experimental setup</title>
<p>In this section, we introduce the tools and the settings used in the experiments. First, we define the metrics used to assess the performance. Then, we describe the experimental setup used in the simulations and with the real robots.</p>
<sec id="section13-1059712312462248">
<title>4.1 Metrics</title>
<p>We are interested in having a cohesive swarm of robots that aligns in a common direction in a short time. In the experiments with informed robots, we want this direction to be the desired goal direction, and we want the swarm to travel as far as possible in this direction. We use order (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059712312462248">Vicsek et al., 1995</xref>) and accuracy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1059712312462248">Couzin et al., 2005</xref>) as metrics to measure the degree of success in achieving these objectives. In addition, we also measure the steady-state value that is reached for a given metric and how long it takes for the swarm to reach such value. We call these metrics steady-state value and settling time respectively. Finally, we also measure the effective traveled distance in the desired goal direction.</p>
<p><bold>Order</bold>: The order metric ψ measures the degree of agreement of the orientations of the robots in the swarm. We first define the vectorial sum of the headings of all <italic>N</italic> robots as</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula15-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math76-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">b</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula15-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq15.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>The order is then defined as</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula16-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math77-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>∥</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">b</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>∥</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula16-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq16.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>When the robots have a common heading, then <inline-formula id="inline-formula62-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math78-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>; when they point in different directions, then <inline-formula id="inline-formula63-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math79-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.</p>
<p><bold>Accuracy</bold>: The accuracy metric δ is used to measure how close to the goal direction the robots are moving. The accuracy metric is defined in the <inline-formula id="inline-formula64-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math80-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> interval in order to be consistent with the order metric and follows the same definition as the one provided in previous flocking studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059712312462248">Çelikkanat &amp; Şahin, 2010</xref>):</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula17-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math81-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>cos</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>∠</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">b</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>∠</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula17-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq17.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula65-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math82-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∠</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">b</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the direction of <bold>b</bold> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula66-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math83-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∠</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the desired goal direction. Robots with a common heading and also moving in the goal direction will thus have <inline-formula id="inline-formula67-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math84-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula68-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math85-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Conversely, when <inline-formula id="inline-formula69-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math86-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, they are moving in a direction which is opposite to the goal direction, even if they are well aligned. Note that, when the swarm is not aligned, the value of the accuracy is <inline-formula id="inline-formula70-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math87-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, since <inline-formula id="inline-formula71-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math88-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> nullifies the contribution of the cosine term.</p>
<p><bold>Steady-state value</bold>: The steady-state value is the asymptotic value reached by either order or accuracy during an experiment. After the system reaches a steady state, we compute the steady-state value as the average value of the metric in the last 100 simulated seconds:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula18-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math89-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula18-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq18.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula72-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math90-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> denotes either the order ψ or the accuracy δ at time <italic>t</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Settling time</bold>: The settling time is the time needed to reach a steady state in order or in accuracy. More precisely, the settling time <inline-formula id="inline-formula73-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math91-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is defined as the time for which <inline-formula id="inline-formula74-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math92-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∀</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≥</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> we have <inline-formula id="inline-formula75-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math93-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>≥</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>95</mml:mn>
<mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>μ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. In other words, <inline-formula id="inline-formula76-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math94-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the time at which and after which the considered metric stays above the 95% of the steady state of the considered metric μ.</p>
<p><bold>Effective traveled distance</bold>: The effective traveled distance is the distance, in meters, traveled in the desired goal direction. It is computed as the total distance traveled projected onto the goal direction <italic>g</italic>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula19-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="block" id="math95-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>·</mml:mo>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula19-1059712312462248" xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-eq19.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>Here, <inline-formula id="inline-formula77-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math96-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula78-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math97-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> are the position vectors of the center of mass of the swarm at time <inline-formula id="inline-formula79-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math98-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula80-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math99-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, respectively; <bold>g</bold> is the goal direction, and · denotes the dot product of two vectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1059712312462248">
<title>4.2 Experimental setup in simulation</title>
<p>We compared the proposed MDMC with MIMC, the motion control method used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref> and by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059712312462248">Çelikkanat &amp; Şahin, 2010</xref>). The experiments can be divided into two sets. In the first set, no robot is informed about any desired goal direction. In the second set, we select a proportion ρ of robots and we inform them about the goal direction <bold>g</bold>. All of the other robots remain uninformed during the entire experiment. The informed robots and the goal direction are randomly selected at the beginning of each run. In all cases, we performed experiments with and without alignment control.</p>
<p>The models described in Section 2 are utilized in the following way. In experiments without informed robots and without alignment control, all robots use Model 2 (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1059712312462248">Equation (2)</xref>). In experiments without informed robots and with alignment control, all of the robots use Model 4 (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-1059712312462248">Equation (4)</xref>). In experiments with informed robots and without alignment control, informed robots use Model 3 (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1059712312462248">Equation (3)</xref>), whereas the rest of the swarm uses Model 2. Finally, in experiments with informed robots and with alignment control, informed robots use Model 1 (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1059712312462248">Equation (1)</xref>) and the rest of the swarm uses Model 4.</p>
<p>We study both the transient and the steady-state behavior of the system. When analyzing the transient behavior, we report the time evolution of the median value of the order or of the accuracy metrics, with the corresponding error bars showing the values at the 25% and the 75% percentile scores (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059712312462248">Figure 2</xref> for an example). When analyzing the steady-state behavior, we report the box-plot of the distribution of the steady-state values and of the settling times. In experiments with informed robots, we also report the box-plot of the distribution of the effective traveled distances.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>MDMC versus MIMC in simulation experiments without informed robots. Time evolution of the order metric for (a) 100 robots without alignment control, (b) 100 robots with alignment control, (c) 1000 robots without alignment control and (d) 1000 robots with alignment control. The line denotes the median of the distribution obtained over <inline-formula id="inline-formula81-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math100-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> runs whereas the error bars represent the interval between the 25% and the 75% quartiles of the distribution.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In all experiments, we add noise to several components of our system: to the proximal control vector <bold>p</bold>, to the alignment control vector <bold>a</bold>, and to the goal direction vector <bold>g</bold>. We consider noise only in the bearing, as commonly done in flocking studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059712312462248">Vicsek et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al., 2008</xref>), and we introduce it by adding to the bearing a random variable homogeneously distributed in the range <inline-formula id="inline-formula82-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math101-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>π</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>π</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. For each experimental setting, we execute <italic>R</italic> independent runs.</p>
<p>At the beginning of each run, <italic>N</italic> mobile robots are placed within a circle at random positions and orientations. The radius of the circle is chosen so that the mean density of the initial configuration is kept fixed at five robots per square meter, independently of the number of robots <italic>N</italic>. In the experiments with informed robots or with aligning robots, a light source is also placed at a fixed position in the arena, in such a way to be seen by all robots that use it as a global reference frame.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1059712312462248">
<title>4.3 Experimental setup with real robots</title>
<p>In order to validate the results obtained in simulation with MDMC, we perform experiments on real robots. Eight foot-bots are placed in the arena depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1059712312462248">Figure 1b</xref>. The robots are placed within a circle at the center of the arena at the beginning of each run, each with a random orientation. A light source is placed at the left-hand side of the arena. To measure order and accuracy over time, we built a custom-made tracking system. We place cardboard hats with a directional marker on top of each robot.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1059712312462248">5</xref></sup> This marker is detected by an overhead camera placed on one side of the arena, at an height of about 3 meters and pointing towards the floor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1059712312462248">Figure 1b</xref> was taken by this camera). We recorded a movie for each experiment and we analysed each video off-line using the Halcon software.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1059712312462248">6</xref></sup> The analysis of each video produced a file containing, for each frame, the orientation of all robots.</p>
<p>We conduct two sets of experiments as we did in simulation: without and with informed robots. All parameters are kept the same as in the simulations. We only change the number of robots and the duration of the experiments in order to comply with arena-size constraints. We consider a proportion of 25% informed robots. The parameters used with real robots are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1059712312462248">Table 2</xref>. All other parameters are the same as used in simulation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1059712312462248">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>For each of the two sets of experiments, and for each of the two motion control methods, we execute 10 runs and report the median values of the metrics together with their first and third quartiles.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1059712312462248" sec-type="results">
<title>5 Results without informed robots</title>
<p>In this section, we report results obtained without informed robots, that is, <inline-formula id="inline-formula83-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math102-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. We first analyze the transient and the steady-state behavior of the system in simulation, and then we report the results obtained with real robots.</p>
<sec id="section17-1059712312462248">
<title>5.1 Simulations</title>
<p><bold>Transient behavior</bold>: Transient behavior:. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059712312462248">Figure 2</xref> shows the transient behavior of the system in a medium-sized (<inline-formula id="inline-formula84-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math103-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) and in a large (<inline-formula id="inline-formula85-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math104-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1000</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) swarm. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059712312462248">Figure 2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059712312462248">(c)</xref> show the results obtained without alignment control (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1059712312462248">Equation (2)</xref>). As we can see, the swarm reaches an ordered state only when using MDMC. The ordered state is reached within 700 simulated seconds in the medium-sized swarm and within 1500 simulated seconds in large swarms. When MIMC is used, the swarm remains disordered during the entire experiment. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059712312462248">Figure 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059712312462248">(d)</xref> show the results obtained with alignment control. In this case, the alignment state is reached with both motion control methods, and the response of the system is much faster than without alignment control. The performance of MDMC and MIMC are comparable: the system self-organizes in less than 200 seconds in medium-sized swarms and in less than 400 seconds in large swarms.</p>
<p><bold>Steady state and settling time without using alignment control</bold>:<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3</xref> shows the steady-state behavior of the system for different swarm sizes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3a</xref> shows box-plots of the distributions of the asymptotic values of order reached without alignment control. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3b</xref> shows box-plots of the distributions of the settling times without alignment control.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>MDMC versus MIMC in simulations with no informed robots and without alignment control. Box-plots of the distribution of (a) steady-state values and (b) settling times of the order metric for different swarm sizes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>An important result of this paper is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3a</xref>: by using MDMC, the system achieves an ordered state without the need of alignment control for all swarm sizes. The use of MDMC is critical for achieving this result. In fact, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3a</xref>, the system never reaches the ordered state when using MIMC.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3a</xref> also displays points indicating results that were considered as outliers. These are of two different types. Some correspond to cases where the system is trying to self-organize but is too slow to reach its stationary state within the maximum run time of <inline-formula id="inline-formula86-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math105-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2500</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s, and can be easily identified by looking at the time series. The others correspond to cases in which the swarm, instead of achieving aligned motion, converged to a rotating state with fixed center of mass, low order (<inline-formula id="inline-formula87-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math106-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) and high angular rotation. A video of a rotating state can be found in our supplementary material page (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>). For the purpose of our current study, we consider these as outliers and focus on the convergence to parallel states. Convergence to a rotating state is rare, becomes less probable if more robots are used, and can be easily suppressed by imposing minor constraints to the robot dynamics. Its analysis goes beyond the scope of this paper and will be presented in a parallel study.</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1059712312462248">Figure 3b</xref> we report the settling time needed to reach the ordered state. The settling time obtained with MDMC increases with increasing swarm sizes, as expected. We also noticed some outliers in the distribution of settling times for MDMC. These correspond to runs where the systems first self-organizes in the rotating solution, and only later, due to noise, reorganizes in the ordered solution. Settling times for MIMC are not reported as the system does not converge to a steady state in the allotted time (2500 s).</p>
<p><bold>Steady state and settling time when using alignment control</bold>: Additional results reported in the supplementary material page (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>) show that the system reaches the ordered state for any swarm size and any motion control method when alignment control is used. This is consistent with previous studies in flocking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al., 2008</xref>) and, additionally, it shows that MDMC can also be implemented together with alignment control. In addition, for both methods the medians of the settling times increase with increasing swarm sizes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1059712312462248">
<title>5.2 Real robots</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1059712312462248">Figure 4</xref> shows the results obtained with MDMC using real robots. Results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1059712312462248">Figure 4a</xref> show that, when alignment control is not used, the system reaches reasonable levels of order also with the real robots. The difference in performance when compared with the simulations can be attributed to the different nature and amount of noise on the real robots, which is very difficult to replicate in simulation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1059712312462248">Figure 4b</xref> shows that, when alignment control is used, results are less noisy. This is because alignment control uses a communication device, the RAB, that is noise-free. Its only source of noise comes from orientation measurements via the light sensor, which appears to be very precise. Results with no alignment control also exhibit much larger fluctuations of the order versus time than those with alignment control. Finally, note that both in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1059712312462248">Figure 4a</xref> and in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1059712312462248">Figure 4b</xref> the order becomes constant at <inline-formula id="inline-formula88-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math107-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>280</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s and at <inline-formula id="inline-formula89-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math108-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>180</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s, respectively. This is because by time <inline-formula id="inline-formula90-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math109-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>280</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s (respectively, <inline-formula id="inline-formula91-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math110-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>180</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s) all experiments had been stopped due to the robots having reached the borders of the arena.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results with no informed robots using MDMC in the real-robots experiments. Time evolution of the order metric for eight robots (a) without alignment control and (b) with alignment control. The line denotes the median of the distribution obtained over <inline-formula id="inline-formula92-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math111-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> runs whereas the error bars span the interval between the 25% and the 75% quartiles of the distribution.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1059712312462248">
<title>6 Results with informed robots</title>
<p>In this section, we report results obtained with informed robots. Analogously to the experiments in Section 5, we analyze the transient and the steady-state behavior of the system in simulation, and then we report the results obtained with real robots.</p>
<sec id="section20-1059712312462248">
<title>6.1 Simulations</title>
<p><bold>Transient behavior</bold>:<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1059712312462248">Figure 5</xref> shows the transient behavior of the system for <inline-formula id="inline-formula93-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math112-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="inline-formula94-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math113-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1000</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and a proportion of informed robots <inline-formula id="inline-formula95-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math114-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1059712312462248">Figure 5a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1059712312462248">5c</xref> show results obtained without alignment control. For this case, the swarm reaches a value of accuracy close to 1 only when using MDMC. This value is reached within 1000 s and 1500 s for swarms with <inline-formula id="inline-formula96-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math115-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula97-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math116-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1000</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> robots, respectively. When using MIMC, accuracy of the system remains <inline-formula id="inline-formula98-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math117-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. As explained in Section 4.1, this is the value obtained when the order metric is close to 0. In other words, when using MIMC without alignment control, the system is not able to reach an ordered state if the proportion of informed robots is small (<inline-formula id="inline-formula99-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math118-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>). Complete results that include also the value of the order metric are reported in our supplementary material page (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>). However, as we will show later, if the proportion of informed robots is increased, the system self-organizes also with MIMC. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1059712312462248">Figure 5b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1059712312462248">5d</xref> show the results obtained with alignment control. In this case, a proportion <inline-formula id="inline-formula100-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math119-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> of informed robots is enough to reach high levels of accuracy for both MIMC and MDMC. Furthermore, MIMC seems to have better performance in terms of convergence time.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>MDMC versus MIMC in simulations with a proportion of <inline-formula id="inline-formula101-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math120-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> informed robots. Time evolution of the accuracy metric for (a) 100 robots without alignment control, (b) 100 robots with alignment control, (c) 1000 robots without alignment control and (d) 1000 robots with alignment control. The line denotes the median of the distribution obtained over <inline-formula id="inline-formula102-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math121-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> runs whereas the error bars represent the interval spanned between the 25% and the 75% quartiles of the distribution.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><bold>Steady state and settling time of accuracy without using alignment control</bold>:<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1059712312462248">Figure 6</xref> shows the steady-state behavior of the system for different swarm sizes, with <inline-formula id="inline-formula103-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math122-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and without alignment control. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1059712312462248">Figure 6a</xref> shows the distribution of the asymptotic value of the accuracy metric. As we can see, MDMC dominates MIMC in all three cases. In facts, the system does not reach an ordered state when MIMC is used. This makes the accuracy metric settle approximately at <inline-formula id="inline-formula104-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math123-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≈</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1059712312462248">Figure 6b</xref>, we see that the distribution of settling times for MDMC has 1000 s as median value.</p>
<fig id="fig6-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>MDMC versus MIMC in simulations with a proportion of <inline-formula id="inline-formula105-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math124-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> informed robots without alignment control. Box-plots of the distribution of (a) steady-state values and (b) settling times of the accuracy metric for different swarm sizes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><bold>Steady state and settling time of accuracy when using alignment control</bold>: Additional results reported in the supplementary material page (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>) show that, when alignment control is used, the steady-state values of the accuracy are almost always close to 1. The few outliers that are observed are due to the fact that, in rare cases, the system splits into two groups. The median settling time, as well as its spread, increases with increasing swarm sizes, and increases more with MDMC than with MIMC.</p>
<p><bold>Impact of the proportion of informed robots</bold>:<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1059712312462248">Figure 7</xref> reports the results of the study conducted with fixed swarm size <inline-formula id="inline-formula106-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math125-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and various proportions of informed robots. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1059712312462248">Figure 7a</xref> shows that, when alignment control is not used, MDMC dominates MIMC in terms of accuracy only for <inline-formula id="inline-formula107-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math126-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. In the other cases, the two methods achieve very similar performance level. However, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1059712312462248">Figure 8</xref> and explained below, this apparent equivalence between MDMC and MIMC in accuracy does not result in an equivalence in the effective traveled distance. Finally, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1059712312462248">Figure 7b</xref> shows that the system converges faster with MDMC than with MIMC in the <inline-formula id="inline-formula108-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math127-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> case, and that the opposite is true for the other cases.</p>
<fig id="fig7-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>MDMC versus MIMC in simulations with informed robots, no alignment control, a swarm size of <inline-formula id="inline-formula109-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math128-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> robots and <inline-formula id="inline-formula110-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math129-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">{</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>05</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>15</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">}</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Box-plots of the distribution of (a) steady-state values and (b) settling times of the accuracy metric for different proportions of informed robots.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig8-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>MDMC versus MIMC in simulations with informed robots and no alignment control. Box-plots of the distribution of effective traveled distance for (a) different swarm sizes (<inline-formula id="inline-formula111-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math130-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) and (b) different proportions of informed robots (<inline-formula id="inline-formula112-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math131-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Additional experiments performed with alignment control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>) show that the system achieves very good performance levels in all cases. However, MDMC converges slower than MIMC when the proportion of informed robots is low.</p>
<p><bold>Effective traveled distance</bold>:<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1059712312462248">Figure 8</xref> shows the box-plots of the distribution of the effective traveled distance for different swarm sizes (fixing <inline-formula id="inline-formula113-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math132-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>01</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) and of the proportion of informed robots (fixing <inline-formula id="inline-formula114-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math133-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>). When alignment control is not used, MDMC consistently outperforms MIMC for any swarm size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1059712312462248">Figure 8a</xref>). This was already known since, unless when the swarm is small, the system cannot order or achieve high accuracy values when using MIMC. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1059712312462248">Figure 8b</xref> shows that MDMC also consistently outperforms MIMC for any proportion of informed robots. Although the system can self-organize and achieve a high level of accuracy for a larger proportion of informed robots, MDMC still has the advantage of being able to let the swarm travel farther in the desired direction of motion.</p>
<p>Additional experiments performed using alignment control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>) show that the swarm is able to travel in the desired goal direction for all swarm sizes. We note that MIMC performs slightly better than MDMC with alignment control, although the latter is still competitive. Finally, we also observe that the two methods perform almost equally for a large proportion of informed robots.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1059712312462248">
<title>6.2 Real robots</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1059712312462248">Figure 9</xref> shows the results obtained with MDMC using real robots. The results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1059712312462248">Figure 9a</xref> show that, without alignment control, the system reaches reasonable levels of accuracy. The difference in performance when compared with simulation could be due to the different way in which noise affects the system, since our simulation does not attempt to model the noise realistically. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1059712312462248">Figure 9b</xref> shows that, surprisingly, MDMC performs worse in real robots with alignment control. In fact, in a group of eight real robots with two informed robots, the range and bearing communication device made the swarm agree on a common, random direction very quickly. When this happened, the interactions between informed and non-informed robots were not strong enough to let the swarm change its direction to the desired heading. Furthermore, the swarm, due to noise, continuously changed its direction, which may explain the increase in the spread and the decrease of the median of the distribution after <inline-formula id="inline-formula115-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math134-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> s. By contrast, when alignment control is not used, the swarm never agrees on a common direction. Hence, the movement of the swarm is almost completely driven by the interaction between the informed and the non-informed robots, that in this case is enough to make the swarm move in the desired direction of motion.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1059712312462248" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results with informed robots using MDMC in real-robots experiments. Time evolution of the accuracy metric for a group of eight robots and two informed robots (a) without alignment control and (b) with alignment control. The line denotes the median of the distribution obtained over <inline-formula id="inline-formula116-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math135-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> runs whereas the error bars represent the interval spanned between the 25% and the 75% quartiles of the distribution.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1059712312462248-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1059712312462248" sec-type="discussion">
<title>7 Related work and discussion</title>
<p>In this section, we review the literature on flocking. We first discuss previous works in robotics, highlighting the novelties of the current paper. We then discuss the most representative work on flocking in statistical physics, comparing the two different perspectives.</p>
<sec id="section23-1059712312462248">
<title>7.1 Robotics</title>
<p>In robotics, flocking has been studied for the last two decades. We focus here on works where the method is either directly tested on real robots or at least it has the potential to be readily applied to real robots. We classify the literature according to two categories. In the first, we include works that use alignment control; in the second, those that do not use it.</p>
<sec id="section24-1059712312462248">
<title>7.1.1 Robotics studies with alignment control</title>
<p>We divide studies where alignment control is used into two categories. In the first, we place studies that relied on external hardware beyond what robots have on-board. In the second, we place studies using on-board hardware only.</p>
<p>In works belonging to the first category, authors have either estimated the relative orientation of the robots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1059712312462248">Hayes &amp; Dormiani-Tabatabaei, 2002</xref>) or emulated an orientation sensing device using an external computer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059712312462248">Holland et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1059712312462248">Hayes and Dormiani-Tabatabaei (2002)</xref> proposed a flocking method based on collision avoidance and velocity matching where all measurements were emulated via an external computer and broadcast to the robots. Robots compute the position and the velocity of the center of mass of their neighbors, in order to maintain cohesion and to align in the same direction. Furthermore, each robot is informed about the direction to a goal area. Emulated external sensing was also used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059712312462248">Holland et al. (2005)</xref>, who developed a method based on Reynolds’ rules for unmanned aerial vehicles.</p>
<p>In the works that fall within the second category, a local communication unit is always used to implement alignment control. In the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1059712312462248">Campo, Nouyan, Birattari, GroΒ, and Dorigo (2006)</xref>, robots have to transport an object to a given location. This work is one of the pioneering studies of coordinated motion with purely on-board local communication, implemented via an LED ring and an omnidirectional camera.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref> proposed a method based on proximal control and alignment control that achieves ordered motion in a random direction. Proximal control and alignment control ware implemented using proximity sensors and a virtual heading sensor (VHS), respectively. The VHS combines a digital compass and a communication unit: each robot measures its orientation and broadcasts it. In this way, the orientation of a robot is sensed ‘virtually’ by its neighbors. In a follow-up study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1059712312462248">Gökçe and Şahin (2010)</xref> introduced a goal-following behavior and studied the effect that a noisy goal direction has on the swarm motion. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059712312462248">Çelikkanat and Şahin (2010)</xref>, inspired by the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1059712312462248">Couzin et al. (2005)</xref>, provided a goal direction to some of the robots and showed that these are enough to guide a large swarm.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Mathews, Birattari, and Dorigo (2010)</xref> proposed a communication strategy that uses the same range and bearing sensor considered in this paper. The authors achieved good flocking performance in environments where the goal direction changes over time. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1059712312462248">Stranieri et al. (2011)</xref> studied self-organized flocking in a heterogeneous swarm of robots, where some of the robots use alignment control, and the rest of the swarm only uses proximal control. Under these conditions, the swarm can still organize and move in a common random direction. Recently, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Stranieri, et al. (2012)</xref>, a self-adaptive communication strategy was proposed to deal with flocking in situations with two conflicting goal directions with different priorities. The authors showed that the swarm can always follow the highest priority goal direction without splitting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1059712312462248">
<title>7.1.2 Robotics studies without alignment control</title>
<p>In this category, we place studies that do not use alignment control. Instead, alignment to a given direction is typically induced by introducing a large majority of robots that are informed about a goal direction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059712312462248">Matarić, 1994</xref>) or light-source direction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059712312462248">Spears et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059712312462248">Matarić (1994)</xref> proposed a flocking method based on a set of ‘basis behaviors’: safe-wandering, aggregation, dispersion and goal-following. The robots sense obstacles in the environment, localize themselves with respect to a set of stationary beacons and broadcast their position. Robots moved cohesively in a goal direction known to all robots.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1059712312462248">Kelly and Keating (1996)</xref> proposed a flocking method based on a leader-following behavior. They used an active infrared sensing system to sense the range and bearing of other robots and a radio-frequency system for dynamically electing the leader. Multiple informed robots could co-exist in the swarm and, in their presence, the swarm was able to split to overcome obstacles.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1059712312462248">Baldassarre, Nolfi, and Parisi (2003)</xref> used artificial evolution to evolve a flocking behavior with a group of four simulated robots. The robots were equipped with proximity and light sensors. They used the former to perceive each others’ relative position and orientation, and used the latter to perceive a common goal direction.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1059712312462248">Nembrini, Winfield, and Melhuish (2002)</xref> proposed a minimalistic method to achieve flocking using only a local communication device and a sensor able to detect obstacles and beacons. Some robots were informed about a goal direction and signaled their status using their beacon. They achieved a swarming behavior where robots dynamically disconnect and reconnect to the swarm.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059712312462248">Spears et al. (2004)</xref> proposed a flocking method based on attraction/repulsion and viscous forces. The robots form a regular lattice structure using the range and bearing of their neighbors and move in a goal direction given by a light source perceived by the majority of the robots.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1059712312462248">Moslinger, Schmickl, and Crailsheim (2009)</xref> proposed a method for minimalistic flocking based on attraction and repulsion zones with different threshold levels. By adjusting these levels, they achieved flocking with a small group of robots in a constrained environment. In this work, as in our study, no robots used neither goal direction nor alignment information. However, the flocking behavior was limited since the group could not stay cohesive all of the time.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1059712312462248">Monteiro and Bicho (2010)</xref> developed a control method based on leader–follower dynamics to move a swarm in formation towards a target. The location of the target is known to some informed robots, assumed to be identifiable within the swarm.</p>
<p>Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1059712312462248">Tarcai et al. (2011)</xref> studied a system composed of very simple remote-controlled (RC) boats subject to inelastic, natural collisions between each other. They placed the boats in a toroidal pool and observed that the swarm organizes in a clockwise or counter-clockwise motion after a certain amount of time. They also studied the effect of adding informed boats into the system. This work can be considered of hybrid nature, between robotics and statistical physics, but is only analyzed here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-1059712312462248">
<title>7.1.3 Discussion</title>
<p>The main contribution of this paper is to propose a motion control method that achieves flocking without alignment control and without informed robots. Therefore, the unique characteristic of this work with respect to the literature analyzed above is that we explicitly study motion control, which has received little or no attention at all.</p>
<p>Since our method can achieve flocking even in absence of alignment control, it is unique when compared with the literature discussed in Section 7.1.1. When comparing with the studies discussed in Section 7.1.2 where alignment control was not used, our study presents the following differences. Our analysis considers only a few informed individuals or no informed individuals, while almost all of the previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059712312462248">Matarić, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1059712312462248">Kelly &amp; Keating, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1059712312462248">Nembrini et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1059712312462248">Baldassarre et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059712312462248">Spears et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1059712312462248">Monteiro &amp; Bicho, 2010</xref>) included a large proportion of informed robots, to help the system reach an ordered state. The rest of the studies either achieved sub-optimal performance in swarm cohesion when compared with our work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1059712312462248">Moslinger et al., 2009</xref>) (the swarm was splitting and rejoining very often in a bounded arena) or analyzed a system under very specific environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1059712312462248">Tarcai et al., 2011</xref>). To the best of the authors’ knowledge, our work is the first to achieve both ordered and cohesive flocking performance in an environment with no constraints on the boundary conditions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-1059712312462248">
<title>7.2 Statistical physics</title>
<p>In statistical physics, flocking is studied with the aim of searching for a theory of self-propelled collective motion applicable to a wide range of systems. Often, the approach is to consider simple models, such as point-particle systems in which actuation or sensing noise plays a role similar to that of temperature in standard physical systems. The resulting dynamics are analyzed using tools from non-equilibrium statistical physics.</p>
<p>Here, we describe briefly some of the most representative statistical physics flocking studies. We classify them into two groups: with and without explicit alignment rules. A complete survey can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1059712312462248">Vicsek and Zafiris (2010)</xref>.</p>
<sec id="section28-1059712312462248">
<title>7.2.1 Statistical physics models with alignment</title>
<p>The first flocking model developed within statistical physics was SDP (self-driven particles) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059712312462248">Vicsek et al., 1995</xref>). In SDP, particles advance at constant speed and use an alignment rule: at every time step, each particle’s orientation is set to the average orientation of its neighbors plus a noise component. The model includes neither attraction nor repulsion. The authors found that a phase transition separates the ordered state (particles moving in a common direction) from the disordered state (particles with random orientation). The transition is reached by either varying the amount of noise or the particle density.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1059712312462248">Gregoire et al. (2003)</xref> extended the SDP model by adding the attraction and repulsion rules. Noise is introduced by adding a small randomly oriented vector to the particles’ heading. As in the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059712312462248">Vicsek et al. (1995)</xref>, the authors observed a transition between an ordered and a disordered state at a critical noise value. The details of this transition appear to be different, and this issue is still a matter of debate.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1059712312462248">Aldana and Huepe (2003)</xref> considered the vectorial network model (VNM), in which individuals do not move in space but are nodes of a network. Each node has an associated orientation that evolves following an SDP model where neighbors are nodes directly connected through a link. The authors found that an order–disorder transition equivalent to that in the SDP model could be obtained only when long-range interactions are present. The VNM was extended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1059712312462248">Turgut, Huepe, Çelikkanat, Gökçe, and Şahin (2008)</xref> to analyze the self-organized flocking of robots that follow the method proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059712312462248">Turgut, Çelikkanat, et al. (2008)</xref>.</p>
<p>Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1059712312462248">Cucker and Huepe (2008)</xref> introduced informed individuals and studied theoretically the behavior of the swarm. They considered a Laplacian model, where each particle tries to minimize the difference between its velocity and that of its neighbors, that are defined according to an adjacency matrix.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-1059712312462248">
<title>7.2.2 Statistical physics models without alignment</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1059712312462248">Szabó et al. (2006)</xref> proposed one of the first models that achieved ordered motion using locally interacting particles and no explicit alignment rule. The goal was to fit experimental data they gathered on the dynamics of collectively migrating tissue cells. The authors observed an order–disorder phase transition occurring at critical mean density of particles. Their model has many similarities with MDMC. For example, particles interact through attraction–repulsion forces and move forward with non-constant speed. An important difference, however, is that in their model each particle is not constrained to only translate parallel to its orientation but can also advance sideways. Owing to this difference, their model is not directly applicable to standard non-holonomic mobile robots, which are constrained in their movements by their wheels. Similar results to those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1059712312462248">Szabó et al. (2006)</xref> were also obtained by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1059712312462248">Erdmann and Mikhailov (2005)</xref>, who considered particle motion in two dimensions and later extended the model to three dimensions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1059712312462248">Streer, Erdmann, &amp; Schimansky-Geier, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1059712312462248">Grossman, Aranson, and Jacob (2008)</xref> considered a system composed of particles that interact only through inelastic collisions on a 2D plane with reflecting circular boundary conditions. They observed complex phenomena such as ordered motion, vortices and chaos. They then studied the system in elliptic-shaped arenas, showing that more complex dynamical patterns, such as particles moving together in sub-groups, could be observed.</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1059712312462248">Romanczuk et al. (2009)</xref>, the authors considered particles with asymmetric non-isotropic interactions. Their model represents ‘escape–pursuit’ dynamics. A particle is attracted to particles in the front (pursuit) and is repelled from particles on the back (escape). Here again, the authors find ordered phases displaying collective motion for high levels of the mean density. At low densities, collective motion is only achieved for specific combinations of the parameters that determine the escape–pursuit dynamics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-1059712312462248">
<title>7.2.3 Discussion</title>
<p>The above review allows us to speculate on the key mechanisms required for a method to make a swarm self-organize to a flocking state with no alignment rule and informed robots. For this to happen, we have observed in simulation videos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059712312462248">Ferrante, Turgut, Huepe, et al., 2012</xref>) that robots must first oscillate in place while turning to adjust their orientation. This process produces small coherent aligned regions that gradually grow until they span the whole group, which then starts moving. We have observed that, in cases where the system fails to self-organize, robots oscillate and turn in place, without creating coherently moving regions. By combining these observations with our survey of successful and unsuccessful methods, we formulate here hypotheses on the conditions required for a method to achieve collective motion.</p>
<p>A first component that we believe is required to reach an ordered flocking state is continuous angular dynamics. In most statistical physics models, the orientation relaxes in a single time step to the direction dictated by the model, leading to discrete jumps from one angle to the next. These jumps often leave robots pointing in directions that are still not fully coherent with their neighbors’, which may have switched to a very different heading on the same time step. Instead, in models that successfully order (such as MDMC and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1059712312462248">Szabó et al. (2006))</xref> each robot adjusts its angular velocity (and not its angle) at each time step, while the angle relaxes in a continuous manner. These smooth dynamics allow the system to gradually reconfigure as it converges towards the ordered state.</p>
<p>Another component we believe is essential is the dampening of the rotational and translational dynamics as the robot approaches a stable, locally ordered state. In MIMC, this condition is not satisfied, and robots close to a stable local configuration still have high angular velocities, as the angle between the flocking vector and the orientation vector is never zero. A similar situation arises if the forward component of the robot speed is made constant by setting <inline-formula id="inline-formula117-1059712312462248">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math136-1059712312462248">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> in the definition of the MDMC model. In this case, high relative velocities between neighbors remain possible when close to a stable configuration.</p>
<p>The two conditions described above are satisfied by MDMC and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1059712312462248">Szabó et al. (2006)</xref>. However, a rigorous confirmation of whether these conditions are indeed necessary can only be achieved through a detailed theoretical study, which is currently ongoing.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-1059712312462248" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>8 Conclusions and future work</title>
<p>In this paper, we have presented a novel motion control method to achieve flocking that can be implemented on robots with limited hardware requirements. Only the relative distance and bearing to neighboring robots are needed to execute the attraction–repulsion dynamics that leads to flocking. Furthermore, to implement MDMC robots do not need to sense each others orientation to perform alignment control, as required by the Reynolds model. The proposed method could thus make possible, in the future, the production of a very large swarm of robots able to perform flocking at a substantially lower cost due to the relatively simple hardware required.</p>
<p>We have performed experiments using both a realistic simulator and real robots. We showed that, with MDMC, self-organized collective motion in a random direction can be achieved. Also, MDMC can be implemented including informed robots that have a desired goal direction to be followed, and only a small proportion of such robots is needed to lead a large swarm in the goal direction. Furthermore, MDMC without alignment control and with informed robots allows the swarm to travel farther in the goal direction, when compared with the MIMC method, which was used as a reference. Finally, we carried out a systematic study where we measured and compared the performance of the two methods in various settings: with and without alignment control and with and without informed robots.</p>
<p>This work presents several opportunities for future studies and/or applications. From a theoretical standpoint, we are conducting a more rigorous analysis of the proposed motion control method. We are studying why the proposed model has the properties shown here while others do not. We are also analyzing under which conditions the swarm exhibits the rotating motion on the spot that was mentioned in the results section.</p>
<p>From the point of view of possible applications, the method could be applied to different types of robots, requiring only relatively simple hardware.</p>
<p>An additional possible research direction would be to extend the proposed method to flocking in three-dimensional space. These results could be applied to aerial and submarine swarms, where often communication and long-range sensing are very difficult to achieve.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1059712312462248">
<label>1</label>
<p>The body-fixed reference frame is fixed to the center of a robot, its x-axis points to the front of the robot and its y-axis is coincident with the rotation axis of the wheels.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1059712312462248">
<label>2</label>
<p>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.swarmanoid.org/">http://www.swarmanoid.org/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1059712312462248">
<label>3</label>
<p>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iridia.ulb.ac.be/argos/">http://iridia.ulb.ac.be/argos/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1059712312462248">
<label>4</label>
<p>Note that non-informed robots that do not use alignment control do not need the light sensor. Therefore, the light was not used in experiments without informed robots and without alignment control.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1059712312462248">
<label>5</label>
<p>Note that such hats are used for tracking purposes only and are not detectable by the robots themselves.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1059712312462248">
<label>6</label>
<p>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.halcon.de/">http://www.halcon.de/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was partially supported by the European Union through the ERC Advanced Grant ‘E-SWARM: Engineering Swarm Intelligence Systems’ (contract 246939) and the Future and Emerging Technologies project ASCENS and by the Vlaanderen Research Foundation Flanders (Flemish Community of Belgium) through the H2Swarm project. Cristián Huepe acknowledges support from the US National Science Foundation (grant number PHY-0848755). Marco Dorigo acknowledges support from the F.R.S.-FNRS of Belgium’s French Community, of which he is a Research Director.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>About the Authors</title>
<p><bold>Eliseo Ferrante</bold> has received a B.Sc. in computer science engineering from Politecnico di Milano in 2004, Italy, a M.Sc. in computer science engineering from Politecnico di Milano in 2007, Italy, and a M.Sc. in computer science from University of Illinois at Chicago, USA, in 2007. He is working as a research associate at the department of biology at KULeuven, Belgium, and is also a Ph.D. student at Université Libre de Bruxelles, Belgium, under the supervision of Professor Marco Dorigo.</p>
<p><bold>Ali Emre Turgut</bold> has received a B.Sc. in mechanical engineering from Middle East Technical University, Turkey, in 1996, a M.Sc. in mechanical engineering from Middle East Technical University, Turkey, in 2000 and Ph.D. in mechanical engineering from Middle East Technical University at Kovan Research Laboratory, Turkey, in 2008. He worked as a post-doctoral researcher at Université Libre de Bruxelles, IRIDIA, Belgium and as a research associate at the department of biology at KULeuven, Belgium during 2008–2012.</p>
<p><bold>Cristián Huepe</bold> is an unaffiliated research scientist based in Chicago and a visiting scholar at the Northwestern University Institute on Complex Systems (NICO). He received his Ph.D. in physics from University of Paris 7 and École Normale Supérieure de Paris in 1999 and his B.Sc. in physics from Universidad de Chile in 1994. He was a postdoctoral researcher at University of Chicago from 2000 to 2002 and at Northwestern University from 2002 to 2005. His research has spanned various fields in nonlinear dynamics, statistical physics and complex systems, including superfluidity, Bose–Einstein condensation, complex networks and collective motion. In 2006 he started CHuepe Labs Inc., an independent research organization that has been funded by grants from the US National Science Foundation.</p>
<p><bold>Alessandro Stranieri</bold> has received a M.Sc. in computer engineering from Politecnico di Milano (Italy) in 2009. While studying for his Masters he focused his studies on artificial intelligence and robotics. Since 2010, he has been pursuing his Ph.D. at the IRIDIA laboratory of the Université Libre de Bruxelles (Belgium) under the supervision of Professor Marco Dorigo. The main area of his research is swarm robotics and in particular he focuses on the use of vision in multi-robot systems for exploration and environment mapping.</p>
<p><bold>Carlo Pinciroli</bold> is a Ph.D. student at IRIDIA, CoDE, Université Libre de Bruxelles in Belgium. Before joining IRIDIA, in 2005 he obtained a Masters degree in computer engineering at Politecnico di Milano, Milan, Italy and a second Masters degree in computer science at University of Illinois at Chicago, IL, USA. In 2007 he also obtained a Diplôme d’études approfondiés from the Université Libre de Bruxelles. The focus of his research is computer simulation and swarm robotics.</p>
<p><bold>Marco Dorigo</bold> is a research director of the F.R.S–FNRS, the Belgian National Fund for Scientific Research, and of IRIDIA, the artificial intelligence laboratory of the Université Libre de Bruxelles. He is the inventor of the ant colony optimization metaheuristic. His current research interests include swarm intelligence and swarm robotics. He is the editor-in-chief of <italic>Swarm Intelligence</italic>, and an associate editor or member of the editorial board of many journals on computational intelligence and adaptive systems. He is a fellow of the IEEE and of the ECCAI. In 1996 he was awarded the Italian prize for artificial intelligence, in 2003 the Marie Curie excellence award, in 2005 the Dr A. De Leeuw-Damry-Bourlart award in applied sciences, in 2007 the Cajastur international prize for soft computing, and in 2010 an ERC advanced grant.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aldana</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huepe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Phase transitions in self-driven many-particle systems and related non-equilibrium models: a network approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Physics</source>, <volume>112</volume> (<issue>1-21</issue>), <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldassarre</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nolfi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Evolving mobile robots able to display collective behaviors</article-title>. <source>Artificial Life</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Longchamp</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magnenat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rétornaz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burnier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roulet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The MarXbot, a miniature mobile robot opening new perspectives for the collective-robotic research</article-title>. In <conf-name>2010 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2010)</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>4187</fpage>–<lpage>4193</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nouyan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birattari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groß</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Negotiation of goal direction for cooperative transport</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gambardella</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birattari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stützle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Ant colony optimization and swarm intelligence (ants) 2006</source> (<volume>Vol. 4150</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Çelikkanat</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Şahin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Steering self-organized robot flocks through externally guided individuals</article-title>. <source>Neural Computing and Applications</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruxton</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Collective Memory and Spatial Sorting in Animal Groups</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source>, <volume>218</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effective leadership and decision-making in animal groups on the move</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>433</volume>, <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cucker</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huepe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Flocking with informed agents</article-title>. <source>MathematicS in Action</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Floreano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gambardella</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mondada</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nolfi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baaboura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>in press</year>). <article-title>Swarmanoid: a novel concept for the study of heterogeneous robotic swarms</article-title>. <source>IEEE Robotics &amp; Automation Magazine</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mikhailov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Noise-induced transition from translational to rotational motion of swarms</article-title>. <source>Physical Review E</source>, <volume>71</volume>(<issue>051904</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huepe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stranieri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinciroli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Self-organized flocking with a mobile robot swarm: a novel motion control method. Complete data</source>. (Supplementary information page at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iridia.ulb.ac.be/supp/IridiaSupp2012-007/">http://iridia.ulb.ac.be/supp/IridiaSupp2012-007/</ext-link>)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birattari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Flocking in stationary and non-stationary environments: A novel communication strategy for heading alignment</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cotta</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kocc Iodziej</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Parallel problem solving from nature – ppsn xi</source> (<volume>Vol. 6239</volume>, pp. <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>A E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stranieri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinciroli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birattari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>A self-adaptive communication strategy for flocking in stationary and non-stationary environments</source> (No. TR/IRIDIA/2012-002). <publisher-loc>Brussels, Belgium</publisher-loc>. (Technical report/IRIDIA/2012-002. IRIDIA, Université Libre de Bruxelles, Belgium)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gökçe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Şahin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The pros and cons of flocking in the long-range “migration” of mobile robot swarms</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Computer Science</source>, <volume>411</volume>, (<issue>21</issue>), <fpage>2140</fpage>–<lpage>2154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gregoire</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chate</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Moving and staying together without a leader</article-title>. <source>Physica D</source>, <volume>181</volume>(<issue>3-4</issue>), <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aranson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Emergence of agent swarm migration and vortex formation through inelastic collisions</article-title>. <source>New Journal of Physics</source>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>023036</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dormiani-Tabatabaei</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Self-organized flocking with agent failure: Off-line optimization and demonstration with real robots</article-title>. In <source>Proc. of the ieee int. conf. on robotics and automation</source> (p. <fpage>3900</fpage>–<lpage>3905</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hettiarachchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Distributed adaptive swarm for obstacle avoidance</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Intelligent Computing and Cybernetics</source>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Beyond swarm intelligence: the ultraswarm</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proc.of the ieee swarm intelligence symposium</conf-name> (p. <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Flocking by the fusion of sonar and active infrared sensors on physical autonomous robots</article-title>. In <source>Proc. of the third int. conf. on mechatronics and machine vision in practice</source> (p. <fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matarić</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Interaction and intelligent behavior</source>. Unpublished doctoral dissertation, <publisher-loc>MIT, MA</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bicho</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Attractor dynamics approach to formation control: theory and application</article-title>. <source>Autonomous Robots</source>, <volume>29</volume> (<issue>3–4</issue>), <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moslinger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmickl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crailsheim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A minimalistic flocking algorithm for swarm robots</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kampis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szathmáry</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <conf-name>European conference of artificial life (ecal 2009)</conf-name> (p. <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nembrini</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>A. F. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melhuish</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Minimalist coherent swarming of wireless networked autonomous mobile robots</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>From Animals to Animats</source> (<volume>Vol. 7</volume>, p. <fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>382</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinciroli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trianni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Grady</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brutschy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>ARGoS: a modular, multi-engine simulator for heterogeneous swarm robotics</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of the IEEE/RSJ international conference on intelligent robots and systems (IROS 2011)</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>5027</fpage>–<lpage>5034</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Los Alamitos, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Flocks, herds and schools: A distributed behavioral model</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <conf-name>Siggraph ’87: Proc. of the 14th annual conference on computer graphics and interactive techniques</conf-name> (p. <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACM Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Romanczuk</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schimansky-Geier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Collective motion due to individual escape and pursuit response</article-title>. <source>Physical Review Letters</source>, <volume>102</volume> (<issue>010602</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sword</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorch</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Cannibal crickets on a forced</article-title> <month>march</month> <article-title>for protein and salt</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>, <volume>103</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>4152</fpage>-<lpage>4156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heil</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Distributed, physics-based control of swarms of vehicles</article-title>. <source>Autonomous Robots</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stranieri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trianni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinciroli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birattari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Self-Organized flocking with a heterogeneous mobile robot swarm</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of the european conference on artificial life 2001</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>789</fpage>–<lpage>796</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Streer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schimansky-Geier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Swarming in three dimensions</article-title>. <source>Physical Review E</source>, <volume>78</volume> (<issue>031927</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Movement of a group of animals</article-title>. <source>Biophysics</source>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>281–282</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szöllösi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gönci</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jurànyi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Selmeczi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Phase transition in the collective migration of tissue cells: Experiment and model</article-title>. <source>Physical Review E</source>, <volume>74</volume> (<issue>061908</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tarcai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Virgh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>bel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vrkonyi</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vsrhelyi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Patterns, transitions and the role of leaders in the collective dynamics of a simple robotic flock</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment</source>, <volume>2011</volume> (<issue>04</issue>), <fpage>P04010</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Çelikkanat</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gökçe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Şahin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Self-organized flocking in mobile robot swarms</article-title>. <source>Swarm Intelligence</source>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huepe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Çelikkanat</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gökçe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Şahin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Modeling phase transition in self-organized mobile robot flocks</article-title>. In (<volume>Vol. 5217</volume>, pp. <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czirok</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ben-Jacob</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shochet</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Novel type of phase transition in a system of self-driven particles</article-title>. <source>Physical Review Letters</source>, <volume>75</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1226</fpage>–<lpage>1229</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zafiris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Collective motion</source>. (arXiv:1010.5017v2)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1059712312462248">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Voronoi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1908</year>). <article-title>Nouvelles applications des paramètres continus à la théorie des formes quadratiques</article-title>. <source>Journal für die Reine und Angewandte Mathematik</source>, <volume>133</volume>(<issue>97-178</issue>), <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>