<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppie</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part E: Journal of Process Mechanical Engineering</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4089</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-3009</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954408912452222</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954408912452222</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Thermomechanical analysis of the drum of a steam generator using the finite element method</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Avelino</surname><given-names>Juan Carlos Prince</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954408912452222">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Chacon</surname><given-names>Guillermo Efren Ovando</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954408912452222">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954408912452222"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
    <name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>Alberto Servín</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954408912452222">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lamadrid</surname><given-names>Gilberto Ochoa</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954408912452222">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
    <name><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>Rodolfo Muñoz</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0954408912452222">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954408912452222"><label>1</label>Instituto Tecnológico de Veracruz, M. A. de Quevedo, Veracruz, Ver, México</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0954408912452222"><label>2</label>Instituto de Investigaciones Eléctricas, Calle Reforma, Cuernavaca, Morelos, México</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954408912452222">GE Ovando, Instituto Tecnológico de Veracruz, M. A. de Quevedo 2779, Veracruz, Ver, México. Email: <email>ovachag@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>157</fpage>
<lpage>165</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In electric power plants, the boiler drum has the function of generating steam for its later use in the turbines. Because of the steam inside the drum, this component is subjected to high temperatures and pressure during the startup of the boiler, causing temperature gradients through the wall of the drum generating thermal stresses coupled with the mechanical stresses induced by the steam pressure. The thermomechanical analysis of the drum presented here was carried out by means of the finite element method and using actual measurements of the starting-up process of a power plant boiler up to the drum temperature is stabilized. The simulation includes the temperature distribution through the wall of the drum and the effect of temperature gradients in the thick walls up to the temperature steady state is reached. In addition the drum stresses caused by the vapor pressure coupled with those generated by the temperature distribution in the wall of the drum were also analyzed. Finally, the simulation of the performance of the drum for a long period to evaluate deformations caused by creep is also presented, since the operation of the boiler has the conditions that can cause this phenomenon.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Boiler drum</kwd>
<kwd>operating conditions</kwd>
<kwd>simulation</kwd>
<kwd>material analysis</kwd>
<kwd>creep</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954408912452222" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The rapid growth of modern technology in the field of electrical power plants as well as the development of more powerful machines have put in the limit the mechanical capabilities of the materials that are currently available. The reliability and safety of the whole power system depends greatly on the way in which the main power unit components like the steam turbine and the boiler are operated. The operating conditions of these devices are usually very complex and involve many unsteady mechanical and thermal loads that determine the stress states of the particular components. The increase in the efficiency of the steam generators and the functioning of each of its components are important points of interest for the continuing improvement in the processes of electric power generation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954408912452222">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954408912452222">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>The reliability of the steam generator should be considered in terms of the durability of its main components like the drum that has the task of delivering high quality steam to the pipe lines for its subsequent overheated and use in the turbine for electricity generation. The dependability of the boiler components are connected with the material properties and the consequent material behavior and deterioration process throughout the operational period of a power plant.</p>
<p>The finite element method (FEM) can be employed, to carry out the simulation of thermo-mechanical analysis of a variety of components and processes and it is an auxiliary tool in the area of mechanical design with extensive industrial applications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954408912452222">3</xref></sup> There is a variety of FEM software codes with different capabilities that can be used; however, having a FEM code is not enough for the solution of an industry problem; it also requires knowledge about the physical phenomena and the appropriate geometry for obtaining robust and reliable results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954408912452222">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954408912452222">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>An important issue in the operation of a power plant is the analysis of the startup of its components. The thermal stress evolution in the steam drum during startup of a heat recovery steam generator was analyzed in Kim et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954408912452222">6</xref></sup> The drum was modeled as a cylinder which inside is filled with water/steam mixture, the longitudinal strain developed by the stress was uniform and the temperature is assumed to vary only in the radial direction and with respect to time. This analysis showed the importance of the gas bypass in managing the thermal stress evolution of the steam drum. Two mathematical and simulation models were developed in Bracco<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954408912452222">7</xref></sup> to evaluate the thermomechanical stress distribution inside the metal part of a steam drum installed into a recovery steam generator of a combined cycle power plant. The first simulation was characterized by a static structure while the second one was more flexible, due to its vectorial structure. The steam drum temperature and thermomechanical stress calculation were done by finite difference approach. The structural integrity by analyzing the thermomechanical behavior of the nozzle header of a steam generator, developed for an integral reactor, under the operating conditions was investigated in Kim et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0954408912452222">8</xref></sup> A finite element analysis was performed to evaluate the temperature distribution and the stress state, while a test loop were designed to carry out thermal transient experiments. The temperatures obtained from the finite element analysis showed differences of up to 30% from those measured by the experiment. Strain values obtained from the experiment showed greater differences in magnitude than the temperature distribution.</p>
<p>The purpose of the present work is to investigate the influence of the starting-up condition of a power system on the thermal stress and creep phenomenon of a steam drum, where conditions and geometry are taken from a real steam generator of Federal Commission of Electricity (CFE), in Mexico.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954408912452222">9</xref></sup> This is a case of thick-wall pressure vessels subject to temperature which has diverse applications in the industry not only for the analysis of the behavior of the material that constitute the drum presented here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954408912452222"><title>Modeling the problem</title>
<p>In the modeling, as a preliminary study, the material properties of the boiler drum are not considered temperature dependent and, this model can be improved in a future work by taking the mechanical properties as a function of the temperature (the yield strength, the tensile strength and modulus of elasticity decreases at high temperatures, while the ductility generally increases).</p>
<p>The boiler drum is manufactured with carbon steel SA-515 Grade 70 (yield strength <italic>S</italic><sub>Y</sub> = 230 MPa, tensile strength <italic>S</italic><sub>max</sub> = 483 MPa) which is recommended according to the ASME Boiler and Pressure Vessel Code. Its thermal conductivity is 47.5 W/m-<sup>o</sup>C, modulus of elasticity <italic>E</italic> = 202 GPa, Poisson’s ratio ν<sub> </sub>= 0.3 and a coefficient of thermal expansion of 11.52 m/m-<sup>o</sup>C. This drum has a length of 15 m with a cylindrical shape in the main body (13.08 m from end to end) and the end plates of hemispherical form, both parts with internal and external radius of 0.84 m and 0.96 m, respectively (uniform thickness of 0.12 m). The nozzles are manufactured of carbon steel ASTM SA106 C, with similar thermomechanical properties of the SA-515 Grade 70 steel, and they are not included in the present analysis.</p>
<p>As with any container under pressure and temperature changes, three stresses can occur: tangential (<italic>S</italic><sub>T</sub>), radial (<italic>S</italic><sub>r</sub>) and longitudinal (<italic>S</italic><sub>l</sub>). In the present analysis the stress with the highest value is the tangential stress and therefore it will be the only one to be considered. For example the radial stress, that would be one that would follow in magnitude, would get a value of the internal pressure of the drum (<italic>S</italic><sub>r</sub> = <italic>p</italic>) and this steam pressure is of one order of magnitude lower than the tangential stress.</p>
<sec id="sec3-0954408912452222"><title>Operating conditions</title>
<p>In the steam generation two processes can be distinguished, the transitory or starting-point and the steady one. During the steam generator start-up, the components are heated-up due to the increase of steam temperature. The temperature gradient occurring within the components depend of steam temperature and pressure, and influences directly the stress level. Throughout the start-up period, when the fluid inside the drum increases its pressure and temperature until the operating conditions are reached, high variations of loads take place which entail higher failure risk. It is precisely the starting process on which there is an interest for modeling. Also the modeling of the drum performance for an extended period to evaluate deformations caused by creep is also presented, since the operation of the boiler has the conditions that can cause this phenomenon. During the startup period of the drum analyzed here, the generated steam increases its temperature and pressure up to <italic>T</italic> = 350 ℃ and <italic>p</italic> = 16.5 MPa, respectively, when the steady state is reached at around 22,500 s, as shown in their corresponding Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954408912452222">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954408912452222">2</xref> based on collected start-up curves of similar boilers of CFE.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954408912452222">9</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig1-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>History profile of the boiler drum temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>History profile of the boiler drum pressure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954408912452222"><title>Heat conduction equation</title>
<p>Heat conduction is very important to modern technology; a particular case is the area of thermal stresses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954408912452222">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954408912452222">11</xref></sup> The temperature distribution in solids can be determined from the solution of the conduction equation subject to the appropriate initial and boundary conditions. The specification of high temperatures, and of heat flux, in regions of material in which heat conduction occurs gives rise to analyses of temperature distributions, heat flows, and conditions of thermal stressing. In the specific case of the steam drum it is necessary to know the temperature distribution as well as the thermal history of these until reaching the steady state. For a material of constant thermal conductivity, the heat conduction is governed by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0954408912452222"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0954408912452222" xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>which is known as the heat diffusion equation. In equation (1), <italic>T</italic> denotes the temperature, <inline-formula id="ilm1-0954408912452222"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∇</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the Laplacian of the temperature, <italic>t</italic> is the time and α is the thermal diffusivity of the material.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954408912452222"><title>Initial and boundary conditions</title>
<p>To obtain the complete solution of a particular physical situation, the initial and boundary conditions must be completely specified. For the present analysis as an initial condition a uniform temperature of 30 ℃ was specified in the drum. For the boundary condition inside the drum the history profile of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954408912452222">Figure 1</xref> was imposed (<italic>T<sub>ri</sub></italic> = <italic>T</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)), taken from operational data. As a boundary condition at the outer surface of the drum a temperature gradient equal to zero was applied <inline-formula id="ilm2-0954408912452222"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. For the mechanical stress due to pressure the history profile of the boiler drum pressure of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954408912452222">Figure 2</xref> was imposed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954408912452222"><title>Thermal stresses</title>
<p>The general equation for calculating the stresses of thermal origin is<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954408912452222">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954408912452222">13</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0954408912452222"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>TH</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ave</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0954408912452222" xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>where <italic>S<sub>T</sub><sub>H</sub></italic> is the thermal stress, <italic>β</italic> the thermal expansion coefficient, <italic>E</italic> the elasticity modulus, <italic>T<sub>ave</sub></italic> the average temperature of the metal in the zone of interest and ν is Poisson’s ratio.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954408912452222"><title>Mechanical stresses</title>
<p>To calculate analytically the maximum tangential stress of a thick wall cylinder subject to pressure, the following equation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954408912452222">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954408912452222">14</xref></sup> is applied
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0954408912452222"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ma</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0954408912452222" xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Being <italic>k = r</italic><sub>1</sub>/<italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub>, where <italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> are the corresponding inner and outer radius of the wall drum, <italic>S</italic> is the main stress, and <italic>p</italic> internal pressure. Equation (3) is based on Lame’s theory for a thick cylinder subject to internal pressure <italic>p</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0954408912452222"><title>Deformation by creep</title>
<p>The creep equation used (modified hardening time) is the option number 6 that the ANSYS®<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954408912452222">15</xref></sup> library provides for this type of modeling
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0954408912452222"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math4-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>AS</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0954408912452222" xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Here <inline-formula id="ilm3-0954408912452222"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0954408912452222"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the transient equivalent deformation by creep, <italic>A</italic> is a creep constant<italic>, m,</italic> and <italic>n</italic> are creep exponents, <italic>S</italic> is the applied stress (maximum tangential stress), and <italic>t</italic> is time. Equation (4) represents the first stage of creep when the cylinder has a steady deformation and the other two stages of creep are not modeled in the present work (an explanation of this assumption is found in the section of Results).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954408912452222"><title>Computational procedure</title>
<p>For the simulation of the thermomechanical states of the boiler drum, based on the model proposed in the previous section, the computational FEM software ANSYS®<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954408912452222">15</xref></sup> was employed.</p>
<p>Only half of the drum was modeled due to its geometrical symmetry. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954408912452222">Table 1</xref> presents a comparison of the analytical results using equation (3) and results from the FEM simulation using ANSYS®,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954408912452222">15</xref></sup> showing an accuracy higher than 99%. The results of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954408912452222">Table 1</xref> are given for tangential and radial stresses, the latter being the same value as the pressure inside the dome. Once the validation was done, four stages of the simulation were conducted.
<table-wrap id="table1-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Comparison of analytical and FEM simulation results for maximum tangential and radial stresses.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954408912452222" xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Type of FEM element</th>
<th colspan="2">Tangential stress (MPa)</th>
<th colspan="2">Radial stress (MPa)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Analytical result</td>
<td>FEM simulation</td>
<td>Analytical result</td>
<td>FEM simulation</td>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Solid95 th2</td>
<td>124.6</td>
<td>124.53</td>
<td>−16.5</td>
<td>−16.34</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0954408912452222">
<p>FEM: finite element method.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>For the first stage of the simulation a CAD design software, SOLIDWORKS, was used to generate a more convenient form the geometry of the drum for its subsequent use with the FEM code. Details are listed below:
<list id="list1-0954408912452222" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The three-dimensional geometry is generated from actual data and provided plans of a 300 MW boiler.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Symmetry in the middle of the drum was used, drawing only the holes and removing of the nozzles.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>For the second stage, simulation of the transient heat transfer and thermal stresses caused by temperature gradients in the wall of the drum, the steps are as follows:
<list id="list2-0954408912452222" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Setting of material properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954408912452222">16</xref></sup> (thermal conductivity, elastic modulus, Poisson’s ratio, coefficient of thermal expansion, density, etc.).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Applying of boundary conditions from the temperature profile (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954408912452222">Figure 2</xref>) in the inner part of the drum for the transient heat transfer process through the wall for generating the temperature distribution in the boiler drum.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Application of initial and boundary conditions from the temperature distribution output file as structural loads for the transient structural process simulation to obtain the stress distribution due to the temperature effects through the wall.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The third stage, simulation of the transient process for obtaining thermomechanical stresses due to both thermal expansion and internal pressure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figure 3</xref>) has the following steps:
<list id="list3-0954408912452222" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Analytical calculation of the maximum tangential and radial stresses of a thick wall cylinder subject to pressure.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Material properties are set and initial and boundary conditions from applying the temperature distribution with the simultaneous application of the pressure profile (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figure 3</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Transient structural process and generation of the output file of the stress distribution due to thermal expansion and internal pressure.</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig3-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Main thermal stresses (<italic>S</italic>1), caused solely by temperature gradients, in the internal (_I), middle (_M) and external (_E) sections of the drum, and temperature (T), as functions of time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>For the fourth stage, simulation of creep, the steps are:
<list id="list4-0954408912452222" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Meshing of the drum in finite elements for the first stage of the creep process.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Settings of material properties, creep constants and exponents.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Creep process simulation due to a constant load (steady internal pressure) for an extended period of time to generate structural stresses through the wall of the drum.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0954408912452222" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<p>The results of the simulations of the present analysis provide an overview of the behavior of the drum and its manufactured material for the prescribed operating conditions. History profile of the stresses caused by thermal expansion through the wall thickness are plotted together with the history temperature in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figure 3</xref>; the left and right vertical axes correspond to stress and temperature, respectively. The stresses caused by both thermal expansion and internal pressure through the wall thickness of the drum as well as the temperature history are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954408912452222">Figure 4</xref>.
<fig id="fig4-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Main thermomechanical stresses (<italic>S</italic>1), caused by both temperature gradients and internal pressure, in the internal (_I), middle (_M) and external (_E) sections of the drum and temperature (T), as functions of time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Distribution of the main stresses (<italic>S</italic>1), in MPa, generated mainly by the internal pressure in comparison with the non-stressed non-deformed state of the drum.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</p>
<p>These graphs show the behavior in the vicinity of the steam inlet hole. The horizontal axis corresponds to time, while the left and right vertical axes correspond to stress and temperature, respectively. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figures 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954408912452222">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954408912452222">8</xref>, <italic>S1</italic> denotes the main stress (tangential stress caused by only temperature gradient or both temperature gradient and internal pressure), <italic>T</italic> is the temperature and <italic>E</italic>, <italic>M</italic> and <italic>I</italic> correspond to the external, middle and inner part of the drum wall, respectively. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figure 3</xref> shows that as the steam temperature increases quickly during startup, the inner surface of the drum is subjected to thermal deformations of compression (<italic>S1_I</italic>). The compressive deformation on the inner surface occurs because the inside is heated faster than the remnant of the wall drum, the thermal expansion of the hotter surface is restricted by the rest of the section, resulting in compression stresses in the interior of the surface. As the operating temperature is reached, the heating rate decreases and the temperature through the thickness, begins to balance and as a consequence the thermal stresses and deformations dissipate,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954408912452222">17</xref></sup> at approximately 7500 s.
<fig id="fig6-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Distribution of the main stresses (<italic>S</italic>1), in MPa, generated in the middle section of the drill holes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Main deformation by creep (EPCR1) in the internal (_I), middle (_M) and external (_E) sections of the drum as functions of time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig8-0954408912452222" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Main stress by creep (<italic>S</italic>1) in the internal (_I), middle (_M) and external (_E) sections of the drum as functions of time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954408912452222-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954408912452222">Figure 4</xref> shows that the stresses due to thermal expansion dissipate while those caused by the pressure remain, at around 7500 s, being more pronounced in the vicinity of the vertical holes. It is remarkable the influence of the internal pressure in the generation of stresses in the drum. It can be noted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figure 3</xref> that, at approximately 7500 s, the thermal stresses on the outside surface are about 54 MPa, while in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954408912452222">Figure 4</xref>, for the same time, the thermomechanical stresses on the outside surface are approximately of 94 MPa. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figure 3</xref> also shows that internal thermal stresses from the initial time up to 7500 s are compressive stresses of up to 9 MPa, whereas in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954408912452222">Figure 4</xref>, where internal pressure is involved, during the first 5000 s, these stresses are of compressive type and thermal stresses dominate, but at approximately 7500 s they shift to tension stresses and reach a value of 30 MPa due to the internal pressure.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954408912452222">Figure 5</xref>, corresponding to the third stage of the simulation, shows the overall image of the drum with the distribution of main stresses (<italic>S</italic>1) throughout the body in comparison with the non-deformed image. These stresses are the so-called tangential, which are the most significant of the three main stresses; these go from a range of 17.8 MPa on the external surface of the hemispherical section to up to 169 MPa in the middle part of the drill holes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954408912452222">Figure 6</xref>).
</p>
<p>The results of the simulation given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954408912452222">Figures 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954408912452222">6</xref> show that the main stress (tangential) during the startup period of the boiler achieve values below the yield strength of the material (<italic>S</italic><sub>y</sub>) of which the drum is manufactured (SA-515 Grade 70), where a factor of safety (FS) of approximately 1.4 is obtained (based on the highest value of the main stress) and therefore there is reliability on the boiler drum during the startup process of the power plant.</p>
<p>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954408912452222">7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954408912452222">8</xref>, corresponding to stage 4 of the simulation, show the strain and stress history profiles for the creep process, after steady state is reached in about 8 h, for an extended period of 80,000 h. In the phenomenon of creep, there are 3 phases that are presented in the material, given the conditions of temperature it was decided to only simulate the first phase of this phenomenon.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954408912452222">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0954408912452222">18</xref></sup> It is noted that in the simulation of creep, the deformations presented are caused only by the action of a constant load maintained for a prolonged period of time, the pressure inside the drum.
</p>
<p>For the present study the first stage of creep is sufficient to describe the creep phenomenon. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954408912452222">Figure 7</xref> shows that the strain behavior has a stiff slope during the first 5000 h, approximately, and after that time the slope of the strain starts to decrease which is characteristic for the first stage of creep. The maximum deformation for creep was presented in the inner surface of the boiler drum while the minimum deformation for creep was located in the external surface.</p>
<p>Similar to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954408912452222">Figure 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954408912452222">Figure 8</xref> shows that the stress by creep increases with a constant rate during the first 5000 h, approximately, reaching its maximum value, which is kept constant for a much longer time. This behavior is also characteristic during the first stage of creep. Also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954408912452222">Figure 8</xref> shows that the stress by creep degradation in the internal and external surface of the drum are below <italic>S</italic><sub>y</sub> while the middle part of the drum achieves a value higher than <italic>S</italic><sub>Y</sub> but lower than <italic>S</italic><sub>max</sub>, being able to cause internal cracks which are common in these pressure vessels. Hence it is recommended regular inspections with non-destructive testing in the dome of the boiler.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0954408912452222" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Thermomechanical analysis of a boiler drum for a power generation plant has been carried out. The problem was modeled by means of the conduction equation, thermal and inner pressure stress theory, and the appropriate initial and boundary conditions were applied, specifically from the operational curves for temperature and pressure of the steam. A commercial computer program based on the FEM properly registered the transient solution of the stresses as well as performance of the drum for a long period to estimate deformations caused by the first stage of creep.</p>
<p>The proposed model and simulation can give an acceptable behavior of the drum for the described characteristics. The simulation shows the significant influence of operation conditions, especially during start-ups, on the stress level and in consequence on the lifetime of the boiler drum. It is undoubted that this methodology can have a wide variety of applications, not only for the industry of energy generation. The developed strategy allows carrying out simulations for different material and operational conditions with relative facility. Although the methodology of the creep process only considers the load by pressure, the results are acceptable within the proposed limits. It is concluded that based on these processes deeper research can be carried out in the future, for example by taking the mechanical properties as temperature dependent or fatigue analysis, with the purpose of being able to estimate the damage accumulated and visualizing the remaining life of the equipment.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We are grateful for grammar revision from Andy and Emi Prince.</p></ack>
<sec id="sec12-0954408912452222"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research was supported by DGEST, CONACYT and PROMEP.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954408912452222"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Yee, RK. Fitness-for-service and remaining useful life assessment of a steam drum. In: <italic>ASME Pressure Vessel and Piping Conference</italic>, Cleveland, Ohio, July 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954408912452222"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Singer JG. <italic>Combustion fossil power systems: A reference book on fuel burning and steam generation</italic>. Connecticut: Combustion Engineering, Inc., 1981</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954408912452222"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zienkiewicz</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Finite element method. vol. 1. The basis</source>, <edition>5th edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954408912452222"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megyesy</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Pressure vessel handbook</source>, <publisher-loc>Oklahoma</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PV Publishing Inc.</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954408912452222"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroño</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>León</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thermomechanical analysis of piercing mandrel for the production of seamless steel tubes</article-title>. <source><italic>In:</italic> Proc IMechE, Part E: J Process Mechanical Engineering</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>217</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954408912452222"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of thermal stress evolution in the drum during start-up of a heat recovery steam generator</article-title>. <source>Appl Therm Eng</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>992</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954408912452222"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bracco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Simulation models of steam drums based on the heat transfer equations</article-title>. <source>Appl Math Sci</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>3687</fpage>–<lpage>3712</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954408912452222"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Thermo-mechanical simulation for nozzle header of once-through steam generator by experiment and finite element method</article-title>. <source>Int J Presssure Vessel Piping</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954408912452222"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modelado de Caldera de una planta termo-eléctrica de 300 MW para el simulador de rodado de Turbina</article-title>. <source>Instituto de Investigaciones Eléctricas, Boletín IIE</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954408912452222"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Heat conduction and mass diffusion</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954408912452222"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yener</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Heat conduction</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Taylor and Francis</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954408912452222"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Pisarenko GS, Yákovlev AP and Matvéev VV. <italic>Manual de resistencia de materiales</italic>. Moscú: MIR, 1985</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954408912452222"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timoshenko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Strength of materials Part II: Advanced theory and problems</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>D. Van Nostrand Company, Inc.</publisher-name>, <year>1965</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954408912452222"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timo</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Design philosophy and thermal stresses considerations of large fossil steam turbines</source>, <publisher-loc>Fitchburg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>General Electric Company</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954408912452222"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>ANSYS Release 7.0 Documentation, 2003, ANSYS, Inc</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954408912452222"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>American Society of Mechanical Engineers. <italic>ASME boiler and pressure vessel code, Section II materials</italic>. New York: ASME, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0954408912452222"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakoneczny</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Life assessment of high temperature headers</source>, <publisher-loc>Ohio</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Babcock and Wilcox</publisher-name>, <year>1995</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0954408912452222"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>González</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Metalurgia mecánica</source>, <publisher-loc>México</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Limusa</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>