<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AUT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaut</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Autism</journal-id>
<journal-title>Autism</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1362-3613</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7005</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1362361312442790</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1362361312442790</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of autism spectrum disorder symptomatology and related behavioural characteristics in individuals with Down syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>Jo</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1362361312442790">Cerebra Centre for Neurodevelopmental Disorders, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK and Institute of Psychiatry, King’s College London, London, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1362361312442790">Cerebra Centre for Neurodevelopmental Disorders, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-1362361312442790">Cerebra Centre for Neurodevelopmental Disorders, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff4-1362361312442790">Cerebra Centre for Neurodevelopmental Disorders, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1362361312442790">Dr Jo Moss, Cerebra Centre for Neurodevelopmental Disorders, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK. Email: <email>j.f.moss@bham.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>390</fpage>
<lpage>404</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The National Autistic Society, SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We evaluated the proportion of individuals with Down syndrome (DS: N = 108) who met criteria for autism spectrum disorder (ASD) on the Social Communication Questionnaire and the severity of ASD-related symptomatology in this group. The proportions of individuals with DS meeting the cut-off for ASD and autism in this sample were 19% and 8%, respectively. We then evaluated the behavioural profile of individuals with DS who scored above cut-off for ASD (DS+ASD; N = 17) compared with those with DS-only (N = 17) and individuals with idiopathic ASD (N = 17), matched for adaptive behaviour skills and ASD symptom severity (ASD group only). Individuals in the DS+ASD and ASD-only groups showed more stereotyped behaviour, repetitive language, overactivity and self-injury than the DS-only group (p &lt; .001). Individuals in the DS+ASD and DS-only groups appeared less withdrawn from their surroundings than those with ASD (p &lt; .004). These findings indicate differences in the behavioural and cognitive profile of individuals with DS+ASD compared with those with DS-only, when controlling for adaptive behaviour skills. Individuals with DS+ASD show broad similarities with individuals with idiopathic ASD with regard to ASD and behavioural characteristics but may also show some areas of subtle difference from this group.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Down syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
<kwd>repetitive behaviour</kwd>
<kwd>challenging behaviour</kwd>
<kwd>mood</kwd>
<kwd>behavioural phenotype</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1362361312442790" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In recent years, there has been increasing interest into the association between autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and a range of genetic disorders. The presence of ASD or autistic like characteristics have now been reported in a large number of genetic syndromes, including: Angelman, Cohen, Williams, Fragile X, Rett, Cornelia de Lange, 22q11 deletion and Prader Willi syndromes and tuberous sclerosis complex (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1362361312442790">Fombonne, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1362361312442790">Gillberg and Coleman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1362361312442790">Moss and Howlin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1362361312442790">Moss, Howlin and Oliver, 2011</xref>). Recent advances in genetic technologies have resulted in further expansion of this list to include a number of microdeletion syndromes, such as 8p23 deletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1362361312442790">Fisch et al., 2010</xref>), 3q29 deletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1362361312442790">Quintero-Rivera et al., 2010</xref>) and 9p partial duplication syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1362361312442790">Abu-Amero et al., 2010</xref>) which are considered, by some researchers, to be key to developing our understanding of the causes of ASD.</p>
<p>The study of the association between ASD and genetic syndromes has raised considerable debate within the ASD and behavioural phenotypes fields. Although it is acknowledged that recognition and accurate identification of ASD characteristics among individuals with genetically determined syndromes is important for providing appropriate educational and behaviour management programmes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1362361312442790">Howlin et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1362361312442790">Moss and Howlin, 2009</xref>), a number of conceptual and methodological issues have consistently been raised. At the forefront of this debate is the question regarding the role of intellectual disability (ID) in the association between genetic syndromes and ASD. Identification of ASD-like characteristics in individuals with severe and profound levels of ID and those with complex behavioural and cognitive profiles is particularly difficult (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1362361312442790">Moss and Howlin, 2009</xref>). Many of the core diagnostic features of ASD are developmentally weighted and consequently an individual may meet certain diagnostic criteria because they have not yet reached the developmental level required for that behaviour to be achieved. Moreover, the clinical tools that have been developed to aid the diagnosis of ASD are generally not designed to be able to distinguish between these very subtle differences and complex patterns of behaviour and thus may have more limited sensitivity and specificity when applied to individuals with genetic syndromes associated with ID (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1362361312442790">Moss et al., 2011</xref>). Careful attention should be paid to the role of ID when evaluating the strength of association between ASD and a specific genetic syndrome.</p>
<p>Caution is also required when considering the level at which to interpret research and clinical findings within this population. Although the prevalence of ASD symptomatology has been shown to be heightened in a range of syndromes, evaluation of the specific ASD symptomatology associated with a given syndrome group has often identified profiles of ASD-related behaviour that are different from that observed in individuals with idiopathic ASD. Among others, this has been the case in Fragile X, Rett, Cornelia de Lange and Angelman syndromes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1362361312442790">Hall et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1362361312442790">Moss et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1362361312442790">Mount et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1362361312442790">Trillingsgaard and Østergaard, 2004</xref>). These findings clearly have important implications for the conceptualization of the triad of impairments within genetic syndromes and highlight the importance of using detailed behavioural description, beyond the level of clinical cut-off scores, to illustrate accurately the profile of ASD phenomenology in genetic syndromes. These findings also emphasize the need for appropriate comparison groups when evaluating ASD symptomatology in genetic syndrome groups. Single syndrome description is no longer sufficient to accurately evaluate the strength and nature of association between a given genetic syndrome and ASD symptomatology. Comparison of genetic syndrome groups with individuals with idiopathic ASD and careful attention to degree of ID is required to further progress research in this field.</p>
<p>One syndrome in which an interesting association with ASD has begun to emerge in recent years is Down syndrome (DS). DS is the most common chromosomal cause of ID, occurring in approximately 10.3 in 10,000 live births (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1362361312442790">Bell et al., 2003</xref>). Typically, DS is caused by the presence of a full or partial trisomy of chromosome 21, although occasionally an unbalanced translocation involving chromosome 21 has been identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1362361312442790">Dykens et al., 2000</xref>). Intellectual disability in DS ranges from mild to severe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Previously, ASD in individuals with DS has been considered to be relatively rare. However, several case studies of individuals with DS who met ASD criteria have now been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1362361312442790">Bregman and Volkmar, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1362361312442790">Ghaziuddin et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1362361312442790">Howlin et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1362361312442790">Wakabayashi, 1979</xref>) and, more recently, studies that have used standardized, ASD-specific assessments have indicated that co-morbidity may be more common than previously thought, with prevalence rates ranging from 5% to 39% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1362361312442790">DiGuiseppi, et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1362361312442790">Ghaziuddin et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1362361312442790">Gillberg et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362361312442790">Hepburn et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1362361312442790">Kent et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1362361312442790">Lowenthal et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1362361312442790">Lund, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1362361312442790">Reilly, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1362361312442790">Starr et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1362361312442790">Turk and Graham, 1997</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362361312442790">Hepburn et al. (2008)</xref> suggest that the presentation of the triad of impairments in DS may be atypical, with fewer impairments in the domain of social relatedness. Higher rates of impaired social skills have also been reported in family members of individuals with DS and ASD than in those of with individuals with DS without ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1362361312442790">Lowenthal et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1362361312442790">Reilly, 2009</xref>), indicating a potentially heightened susceptibility for the broader autism phenotype in families of children with DS and ASD.</p>
<p>Recent research has focused on what might distinguish individuals with DS and ASD from those with ‘typical DS’ and findings indicate that there may be differences between these two subgroups. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al. (2005)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1362361312442790">Carter et al. (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. (2009)</xref> have reported that those with ASD and DS have a greater degree of ID than those with DS who do not meet ASD criteria. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. (2009)</xref> propose that the presence of ASD-like impairments in those with DS and ASD is not solely accounted for by the greater degree of ID. In addition, higher rates of behaviour difficulties, including stereotyped behaviours, hyperactivity and inappropriate speech have been reported in individuals with DS and ASD relative to those with DS-only (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1362361312442790">Carter et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. 2009</xref>). However, none of these studies have used matched comparison groups to evaluate whether these differences in behavioural profile are accounted for by the greater degree of ID and whether this behaviour profile is similar to that observed in individuals with idiopathic ASD who show similar levels of ASD symptomatology.</p>
<p>This is the first study to evaluate the profile of ASD symptomatology, repetitive behaviour, hyperactivity and mood in individuals with DS who score above the cut-off for ASD on the Social Communication Questionnaire (SCQ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1362361312442790">Rutter et al., 2003</xref>) compared with a contrast group of individuals with DS matched for chronological age and estimates of ID who do not score above the cut-off for ASD and individuals with idiopathic ASD (also matched for severity of ASD symptomatology). In this study we address the following research questions:</p>
<list id="list1-1362361312442790" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>What is the prevalence of ASD symptomatology in individuals with DS?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What is the profile of ASD symptomatology, hyperactivity, challenging behaviour, mood and repetitive behaviour in individuals with DS who score above the SCQ cut-off for ASD compared with individuals with DS who do not score highly on the SCQ and individuals with idiopathic ASD who are matched on estimates of ID and ASD symptom severity (ASD group only)?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1362361312442790" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>This study was conducted as part of a larger project comparing aspects of the behavioural phenotypes of individuals with a range of genetic syndromes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1362361312442790">Arron et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1362361312442790">Burbidge et al, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1362361312442790">Moss et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1362361312442790">Oliver et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section3-1362361312442790">
<title>Participants</title>
<sec id="section4-1362361312442790">
<title>This study was conducted in two stages</title>
<p><italic>Stage 1: Investigation of the prevalence and phenomenology of ASD symptomatology in a sample of 108 individuals with DS</italic>. Participants were recruited via the UK Down Syndrome Association. Five hundred families caring for people with DS were contacted and invited to participate. One-hundred-and-forty-four (28.8%) individuals returned questionnaires. Participants were included if information regarding participant’s date of birth and diagnosis of DS from a professional (physician, clinical geneticist, paediatrician or other) was present, if at least 75% of the SCQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1362361312442790">Rutter et al., 2003</xref>) had been completed and if the participant with DS was at least 4 years of age. Eleven participants (7.6%) were excluded from the study because they did not provide information regarding age or date of birth, 12 (8.3%) were excluded because they did not have a confirmed diagnosis and 13 (9.0%) were excluded because they had not completed at least 75% of the SCQ. This left a total sample of 108 participants.</p>
<p><italic>Stage 2: Investigation of the behaviour profile of individuals with DS who score above the cut-off for ASD on the SCQ (DS+ASD</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1362361312442790">1</xref></sup><italic>) compared with individuals with DS who do not meet this criteria (DS-only) and individuals with idiopathic ASD (ASD-only)</italic>. Participants with DS meeting the suggested cut-off for ASD on the SCQ who could be matched to those with DS who did not score above this cut-off and those with idiopathic ASD were selected into the DS +ASD group (N = 17; 4 participants with DS who met the ASD cut-off were excluded as they could not be matched to individuals in the contrast groups). Seventeen participants with DS who did not score above the ASD cut-off on the SCQ were selected into the DS-only group based on matching criteria of ± 2 points on the self help subscale of the Wessex questionnaire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1362361312442790">Kushlick et al., 1973</xref>). For the purposes of analysis, a comparison group of 17 individuals with idiopathic ASD were selected from a larger participant sample that had been collected as part of a large study of individuals with ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1362361312442790">Richards et al., in press</xref>). Participants with ASD were included in the study if information regarding diagnosis of ASD by a relevant professional (paediatrician, GP, psychiatrist, clinical psychologist or educational psychologist) was present and they scored above the ASD cut-off on the SCQ. The ASD group were matched to the DS+ASD group using the SCQ total score (± 2 points on total score<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1362361312442790">2</xref></sup>) and estimates of ID (± 2 points on the self help subscale of the Wessex questionnaire; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1362361312442790">Kushlick et al., 1973</xref>). Participant characteristics for the total DS sample, the DS+ASD and DS-only subsamples and the ASD comparison group are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1362361312442790">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1362361312442790" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Age, gender, ability, mobility and speech characteristics for the total DS group, DS+ASD subsample group, DS-only subsample and ASD group.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1362361312442790" xlink:href="10.1177_1362361312442790-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">DS total group</th>
<th align="left">DS-only</th>
<th align="left">DS+ASD</th>
<th align="left">ASD group</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>N</td>
<td/>
<td>108</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>Mean (SD)</td>
<td>22.16 (12.51)</td>
<td>20.53 (11.72)</td>
<td>21.14 (11.79)</td>
<td>13.65 (8.90)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>range</td>
<td>4.00 – 62.00</td>
<td>5.00–43.00</td>
<td>4.00–39.00</td>
<td>4.00–32.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td>% male (N)</td>
<td>42.59 (46)</td>
<td>35.29 (6)</td>
<td>47.06 (8)</td>
<td>70.01 (12)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total self help score</td>
<td>Mean (SD)</td>
<td>7.87 (1.41)</td>
<td>7.53 (1.62)</td>
<td>6.71 (1.76)</td>
<td>6.88 (1.65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>range</td>
<td>4.00–9.00</td>
<td>5.00–9.00</td>
<td>4.00–9.00</td>
<td>4.00–9.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mobility</td>
<td>% mobile (N)</td>
<td>96.30 (104)</td>
<td>94.12 (16)</td>
<td>88.2 (15)</td>
<td>88.24 (15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Speech</td>
<td>% verbal (N)</td>
<td>93.52 (101)</td>
<td>88.24 (15)</td>
<td>70.59 (12)</td>
<td>76.47 (13)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1362361312442790">
<title>Measures</title>
<p><italic>Demographic Information</italic>. The demographic questionnaire provided information regarding date of birth, gender, mobility (able to walk unaided), verbal ability (more than 30 signs/words) and diagnostic status (whether or not a diagnosis had been made, the precise diagnosis made, when and by whom).</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of autism spectrum disorder symptomatology:</italic> The SCQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1362361312442790">Rutter et al., 2003</xref>) was used to screen for the presence of ASD symptomatology in individuals of all age groups. The measure consists of 40 items that comprise three subscales: communication, social interaction and repetitive and stereotyped patterns of behaviours. The authors suggest a cut-off point for ASD of 15. This score was found to differentiate individuals with Pervasive Developmental Disorders from other diagnoses (excluding those with ID) with a specificity of .80 and a sensitivity of .96 and differentiated individuals with autism from individuals with ID with a specificity of .67 and a sensitivity of .96. A higher cut-off point of 22 or more is required to differentiate individuals with autism from other Pervasive Developmental Disorders with a sensitivity of .75 and a specificity of .60. The SCQ has also been shown to have good concurrent validity with the Autism Diagnostic Interview and with the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1362361312442790">Berument et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1362361312442790">Bishop and Norbury, 2002</xref>). Internal consistency is also good (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1362361312442790">Berument et al., 1999</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1362361312442790">Howlin and Karpf (2004)</xref> report good internal consistency and concurrent validity with the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule and the Autism Diagnostic Interview in individuals with Cohen syndrome and propose that this supports the validity of using this screening tool for evaluating ASD symptomatology in individuals with genetic syndromes.</p>
<p><italic>Estimates of ability, hyperactivity, repetitive behaviour, mood and challenging behaviour:</italic> Full details of these assessments are provided in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1362361312442790">Arron et al. (2011)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1362361312442790">Burbidge et al. (2010)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1362361312442790">Hyman, Oliver and Hall (2002)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1362361312442790">Moss et al. (2009)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1362361312442790">Oliver et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1362361312442790">Ross &amp; Oliver (2003)</xref>.</p>
<p>The Wessex questionnaire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1362361312442790">Kushlick et al., 1973</xref>) is an informant-based measure of adaptive behaviour for children and adults with ID and was used as an estimate of degree of ID. It is an informant questionnaire designed to assess social and physical abilities in children and adults with ID. Subscales include continence, mobility, self help skills, speech and literacy and information on vision and hearing is also included. The Wessex scale has good inter-rater reliability at subscale level for both children and adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1362361312442790">Kushlick <italic>et al</italic>., 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1362361312442790">Palmer and Jenkins, 1982</xref>).</p>
<p>The Mood Interest and Pleasure Questionnaire-Short (MIPQ-S; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1362361312442790">Ross &amp; Oliver, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1362361312442790">Oliver et al., 2011</xref>) is a 12-item informant questionnaire used to assess two constructs related to depression, mood, and interest and pleasure. It is designed for use with people with ID including those with severe or profound intellectual disabilities. There are two subscales: Mood, and Interest and Pleasure. The MIPQ-S shows good internal consistency (Cronbach’s alpha coefficients: total = .88, Mood = .79, Interest and Pleasure = .87), test-retest (.97) and inter-rater reliability (.85).</p>
<p>The Activity Questionnaire (TAQ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1362361312442790">Burbidge et al., 2010</xref>) is an 18-item informant questionnaire designed to evaluate hyperactivity and impulsivity and is appropriate for use with people with ID including those with severe or profound ID. Item-level inter-rater reliability ranges from .31 to .75 (mean .56) and test-retest reliability ranges from .60 to .90 (mean .75). Inter-rater and test-retest reliability indices for subscales and total score exceed .70.</p>
<p>The Challenging Behaviour Questionnaire (CBQ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1362361312442790">Hyman et al., 2002</xref>) was used to evaluate the presence or absence of self-injury, physical aggression, verbal aggression, destruction of property and inappropriate vocalizations over the last month. Previous examination of the psychometric properties of the questionnaire has demonstrated good inter-rater reliability with reliability coefficients ranging from .61 to .89 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1362361312442790">Hyman et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The Repetitive Behaviour Questionnaire (RBQ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1362361312442790">Moss et al., 2009</xref>) was used to assess the frequency of a range of repetitive behaviours. There are five subscales: stereotyped behaviour, compulsive behaviour, restricted preferences, insistence on sameness, and repetitive use of language. The RBQ is an informant questionnaire for use with children and adults with a range of intellectual abilities. Examination of the psychometric properties of the RBQ indicates that item-level inter-rater and test-retest reliability and validity are good (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1362361312442790">Moss et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1362361312442790">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Questionnaires were distributed to families and carers of individuals with DS and individuals with ASD via the relevant family support groups that were local to the research bases in Birmingham and London.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1362361312442790">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>All data were tested for normality using Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests. Non-parametric tests were used where data were not normally distributed.</p>
<p><italic>Stage 1 analysis</italic>. The proportion of individuals with DS scoring above the cut-offs for ASD and Autism on the SCQ were assessed using the total sample of individuals with DS (N = 108). Independent t tests and chi-squared tests (for categorical data) were conducted to evaluate differences in chronological age, self help skills, verbal ability and mobility between individuals who scored above and below these cut-off scores.</p>
<p><italic>Stage 2 analysis</italic>. One way ANOVAs (or Kruskal-Wallis tests where data were not normally distributed) and chi-squared tests for categorical data (or Fisher’s exact where required) were conducted to determine differences between the DS+ASD, DS-only and ASD-only groups with regard to chronological age, self help skills, verbal ability and mobility. Differences between the three groups (DS+ASD, DS, ASD) on measures of mood, repetitive behaviour, levels of hyperactivity and impulsivity and challenging behaviour were also conducted in this way at both subscale and item level. Post hoc differences were investigated using Scheffé post hoc tests (or pairwise Mann-Whitney U tests). A conservative p value of ≤ .01 was used for all main analysis, and Bonferroni corrected p values were used for item-level analysis owing to the number of comparisons. All post hoc tests used a significance level of p &lt; .05.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1362361312442790" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section9-1362361312442790">
<title>Stage 1 analysis: Prevalence of ASD symptomatology in DS</title>
<p>Twenty-one participants in the total DS sample (N = 108) scored above the cut-off for ASD on the SCQ (cut-off score 15; 19.4%). Of these, nine participants scored above the more stringent cut-off for autism (cut-off score 22; 8.3%). Those who scored above the cut-off for autism and/or ASD did not differ significantly from those with DS who did not score above these criteria on chronological age (autism cut-off vs. not: t(97) =.63, p = .53; ASD cut-off vs. not: t(97)=.75, p = .46) or gender (autism cut-off vs. not: Fisher’s exact; p = .49; number of males meeting autism cut-off = 5 (55.6%); ASD cut-off vs. not: χ<sup>2</sup>(1) =1.02; p = .35; N males meeting ASD cut-off = 11 (52.4%)) but did have significantly lower self help skills (above autism cut-off vs. not: t(105) = 4.50, p &lt; .001; above ASD cut-off vs. not: t(105) = 4.01, p &lt; .001) and lower levels of verbal ability (above autism cut-off vs. not: Fisher’s exact, p &lt; .001; above ASD cut-off vs. not: Fisher’s exact, p = .002). Those scoring above the cut-off for ASD were also less mobile than those who did not meet this criteria (Fisher’s exact, p = .02).</p>
<p>A comparison between individuals with DS who met the cut-off for autism and those who met the ASD cut-off only showed no differences in chronological age (t(17) = .25, p = .80). A difference in self help scores between these groups approached significance (t(18) = 2.15, p = .05), with those scoring above cut-off for ASD showing greater self help skills than those scoring above cut-off for autism.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1362361312442790">
<title>Stage 2 analysis: Profile of autism spectrum symptomatology, hyperactivity, repetitive behaviour, mood and challenging behaviour</title>
<p>For the next stage of analysis, participants were matched on estimates of ID (±2 points; measured by the Wessex self help score) and SCQ total score (ASD group only; ± 2 points). Accordingly, participants did not differ significantly on self help scores (F(50,2) = 1.13; p = .33) and the DS+ASD and ASD-only groups did not differ on SCQ total score (t(32) = .02; p = .98). There were also no significant differences between the groups on chronological age (F(50,2) = 2.45; p = .10), verbal ability (&gt;30 words/signs; Fisher’s exact = 1.65, p = .58), mobility (walks unaided; Fisher’s exact = 1.65, p = .58) and gender (χ<sup>2</sup>(2) = 4.39; p = .15). Details of participant characteristics can be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1362361312442790">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1362361312442790">Table 2</xref> describes the profiles of ASD symptomatology, hyperactivity, repetitive behaviour, mood and challenging behaviour across the three participant groups.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1362361312442790" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Mean scores and percentage displayed on subscales of MIPQ, RBQ, TAQ and CBQ for DS, DS + ASD and ASD groups.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1362361312442790" xlink:href="10.1177_1362361312442790-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measure</th>
<th align="left">Subscale</th>
<th align="left">DS, mean (SD)</th>
<th align="left">DS + ASD, mean (SD)</th>
<th align="left">ASD, mean (SD)</th>
<th align="left">χ² /F</th>
<th align="left">df</th>
<th align="left">p</th>
<th align="left">Post hoc analyses (Scheffe/ Mann-Whitney U)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>SCQ</td>
<td>Communication</td>
<td>3.58 (2.03)</td>
<td>7.31 (2.27)</td>
<td>7.24 (1.82)</td>
<td>17.71</td>
<td>49,2</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Restricted and repetitive behaviour</td>
<td>1.24 (.97)</td>
<td>3.97 (2.33)</td>
<td>5.00 (1.73)</td>
<td>20.47</td>
<td>50,2</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Reciprocal social interaction</td>
<td>2.74 (1.74)</td>
<td>9.94 (2.59</td>
<td>8.94 (3.88)</td>
<td>31.35</td>
<td>50,2</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MIPQ</td>
<td>Mood</td>
<td>21.60 (2.48)</td>
<td>20.35 (2.74)</td>
<td>19.29 (2.31)</td>
<td>3.58</td>
<td>50,2</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Interest and pleasure</td>
<td>19.12 (3.67)</td>
<td>16.35 (5.15)</td>
<td>12.53 (4.37)</td>
<td>9.44</td>
<td>50,2</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS&gt; ASD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RBQ</td>
<td>Stereotyped behaviour</td>
<td>1.56 (3.16)</td>
<td>7.00 (4.56)</td>
<td>6.19 (5.00)</td>
<td>17.06</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD &gt; DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Compulsive behaviour</td>
<td>4.74 (6.48)</td>
<td>7.47 (8.97)</td>
<td>8.53 (5.64)</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>48,2</td>
<td>.323</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Insistence on sameness</td>
<td>1.94 (2.98)</td>
<td>2.94 (3.25)</td>
<td>4.06 (2.16)</td>
<td>2.32</td>
<td>49,2</td>
<td>.110</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Restricted preferences<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1362361312442790">*</xref></td>
<td>3.14 (2.63)</td>
<td>4.42 (3.58)</td>
<td>4.85 (2.64)</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>38,2</td>
<td>.308</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Repetitive use of language<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1362361312442790">*</xref></td>
<td>1.64 (1.65)</td>
<td>5.50 (4.50)</td>
<td>4.62 (3.10)</td>
<td>5.23</td>
<td>38,2</td>
<td>.010</td>
<td>DS+ASD&gt; DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TAQ</td>
<td>Impulsivity</td>
<td>7.82 (6.37)</td>
<td>11.26 (6.86)</td>
<td>16.60 (5.80)</td>
<td>5.83</td>
<td>49,2</td>
<td>.005</td>
<td>ASD &gt; DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Overactivity</td>
<td>5.47 (5.95)</td>
<td>13.06 (10.71)</td>
<td>15.59 (11.97)</td>
<td>5.19</td>
<td>50,2</td>
<td>.009</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD &gt; DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Impulsive speech<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1362361312442790">*</xref></td>
<td>3.07 (3.53)</td>
<td>3.91 (4.13)</td>
<td>6.39 (3.64)</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>38,2</td>
<td>.132</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CBQ</td>
<td>Aggression (% showing behaviour)</td>
<td>23.53</td>
<td>43.75</td>
<td>58.82</td>
<td>4.38</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>.112</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Self-injurious behaviour (% showing behaviour)</td>
<td>5.88</td>
<td>37.50</td>
<td>52.94</td>
<td>8.98</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>.011</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Property destruction (% showing behaviour)</td>
<td>11.76</td>
<td>13.33</td>
<td>47.06</td>
<td>6.38</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>.039</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1362361312442790">
<label>*</label>
<p>Subscale calculated only for verbal participants.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>To investigate the profile of ASD phenomenology in DS, the scores on the SCQ subscales were compared across the three groups. The DS-only group scored significantly lower than both the DS+ASD and ASD-only groups on all domains of the SCQ (all p values ≤ .001), whereas no significant differences were identified between the DS+ASD and ASD-only groups on any of the SCQ domains (all p values &gt; .20), suggesting no differences between these groups with regard to the profile of domain scores on this measure.</p>
<p>Scores on assessments of hyperactivity, repetitive behaviour, mood and challenging behaviour were compared at subscale and item level across the three matched participant groups. Analysis at subscale level revealed that the DS-only group showed significantly higher levels of interest and pleasure than the ASD-only group. The DS + ASD and ASD-only groups engaged in significantly more stereotyped behaviour and showed greater levels of overactivity than the DS-only group. The DS+ASD group also showed significantly more repetitive language than the DS-only group. The ASD-only group was significantly more impulsive than the DS-only group. There were no significant differences between the groups on measures of compulsive behaviour, insistence on sameness, restricted preferences, aggression or property destruction. Self-injurious behaviour was more frequent in the DS+ASD and ASD-only groups compared with the DS-only group.</p>
<p>Item-level analysis showed significant differences between the groups on the frequency of hand stereotypies (DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS), repetitive phrases (DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS), echolalia (DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS), positive vocalizations (DS&gt;DS+ASD, ASD), flat affect (DS&gt;ASD), interest in surroundings (DS, DS+ASD&gt; ASD), expressing enjoyment in activities (DS &gt;ASD) and preference to be moving around (DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS). See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1362361312442790">Table 3</xref> for a description of item-level scores. For conciseness, only group scores on items on which there were significant differences are reported.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1362361312442790" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Median scores and interquartile range on items of the MIPQ, RBQ and TAQ in which significant differences were identified.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1362361312442790" xlink:href="10.1177_1362361312442790-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measure</th>
<th align="left">Item</th>
<th align="left">DS median (interquartile range)</th>
<th align="left">DS + ASD median (interquartile range)</th>
<th align="left">ASD median (interquartile range)</th>
<th align="left">χ²</th>
<th align="left">p value</th>
<th align="left">Post hoc</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>RBQ</td>
<td>Hand stereotypies</td>
<td>0.00 (0.00)</td>
<td>1.50 (4.00)</td>
<td>3.00 (1.50)</td>
<td>18.92</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Repetitive phrases</td>
<td>0.00 (0.00)</td>
<td>0.00 (3.75)</td>
<td>1.00 (3.00)</td>
<td>11.49</td>
<td>.003</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Echolalia</td>
<td>0.00 (0.00)</td>
<td>3.00 (4.00)</td>
<td>2.00 (3.00)</td>
<td>12.81</td>
<td>.002</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MIPQ</td>
<td>Positive vocalizations</td>
<td>3.00 (0.50)</td>
<td>3.00 (1.00)</td>
<td>1.00 (1.50)</td>
<td>14.01</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>DS&gt;DS+ASD, ASD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Flat affect <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1362361312442790">*</xref></td>
<td>4.00 (0.00)</td>
<td>3.50 (1.00)</td>
<td>3.00 (0.00)</td>
<td>15.22</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>DS&gt;ASD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Interested in surroundings</td>
<td>4.00 0.50)</td>
<td>4.00 (1.00)</td>
<td>3.00 (1.00)</td>
<td>14.43</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>DS+ASD, DS &gt;ASD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Enjoyment in activities</td>
<td>3.00 (1.00)</td>
<td>3.00 (2.75)</td>
<td>2.00 (1.50)</td>
<td>16.10</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>DS&gt;ASD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TAQ</td>
<td>Prefers to be moving around</td>
<td>0.00 (1.00)</td>
<td>1.00 (3.00)</td>
<td>3.00 (2.50)</td>
<td>12.76</td>
<td>.002</td>
<td>DS+ASD, ASD&gt;DS</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1362361312442790">
<label>*</label>
<p>this item is reverse scored, thus a higher score in this item denotes less flat affect.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1362361312442790" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study we assessed the prevalence of ASD symptomatology in a large group of individuals with DS. Following this analysis, the profile of ASD symptomatology, repetitive behaviour, hyperactivity and mood in individuals with DS who met the cut-off for ASD on the SCQ (DS+ASD) was evaluated relative to two matched contrast groups of individuals with DS who did not meet these criteria (DS-only; matched on estimates of adaptive behaviour) and individuals with idiopathic ASD (ASD-only; matched on estimates of adaptive behaviour and severity of ASD symptomatology). This is the first study to have evaluated the behavioural profile of individuals with DS+ASD relative to others with DS who do not meet these criteria and individuals with idiopathic ASD, using matched comparison groups to control for differences in adaptive behaviour skills. Furthermore, this is the first study to consider whether the presentation of ASD symptomatology and the behavioural profile of those with DS+ASD are similar to that of individuals with idiopathic ASD who are matched for ASD symptom severity.</p>
<sec id="section12-1362361312442790">
<title>Prevalence and profile of ASD symptomatology in DS</title>
<p>Of the total DS sample (108), the proportion of individuals with DS who met the cut-off for ASD and autism was 19% (N = 21) and 8% (N = 9), respectively. These figures are broadly consistent with the majority of previous prevalence estimates reported within the DS population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362361312442790">Hepburn et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1362361312442790">Kent et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1362361312442790">Lowenthal et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1362361312442790">Lund, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1362361312442790">Turk and Graham, 1997</xref>). However, they are higher than that reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1362361312442790">Gillberg et al. (1986)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1362361312442790">Ghaziuddin et al. (1992)</xref> (both 5%) and lower than that reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1362361312442790">Starr et al., 2005</xref> (39%). This variability is likely to reflect differences in assessment measures, sample characteristics and changes in diagnostic criteria over time.</p>
<p>Although some previous case reports and studies of individuals with DS+ASD have indicated a male bias in individuals with DS+ASD (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1362361312442790">Reilly 2009</xref> for a review), this was not identified in the current study. The proportion of males with DS meeting the cut-off for ASD and autism was 52% (N = 11) and 55.6% (N = 5), respectively. These figures are consistent with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1362361312442790">Kent et al. (1999)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1362361312442790">Rasmussen et al. (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1362361312442790">Lowenthal et al. (2007)</xref>.</p>
<p>Further analysis indicated that individuals with DS who met the cut-off for ASD/autism on the SCQ had lower levels of self help skills, were less mobile and had fewer verbal abilities than the total sample of individuals with DS who did not score above the SCQ cut-off. These findings are consistent with reports from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al. (2005)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1362361312442790">Carter et al. (2007)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362361312442790">Hepburn et al. (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. (2009)</xref>. A comparison of individuals with DS scoring above the cut-off for ASD with those meeting the more stringent criteria for autism was limited by the small sample size but indicated that those scoring above the cut-off for ASD only were more able than those who scored above the cut-off for autism. This difference approached significance (p = .05). Given that the ability to assess ASD symptomatology becomes more difficult as the severity of the ID increases, it is not clear whether the association between DS and ASD simply reflects a lack of specificity of autism-specific measures to accurately screen individuals with more severe ID. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. (2009)</xref> argue that this association is unlikely to be accounted for solely by degree of ID.</p>
<p>To evaluate the role of ID further, we considered the scores within the domains of the SCQ across three groups of participants (DS+ASD, DS-only, ASD-only) who were matched on estimates of adaptive behaviour and SCQ scores (ASD-only group). Individuals in the DS+ASD group scored significantly higher than the DS-only group on all three domains of the SCQ, and showed a similar profile of scores on these domains to individuals with ASD-only. These findings indicate that the DS+ASD group demonstrated impairments across all domains of ASD symptomatology, with similar levels of severity to individuals with idiopathic ASD. This is in contrast to reports of an atypical presentation, as has been identified in toddlers with DS who met criteria for ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1362361312442790">Hepburn et al., 2008</xref>) and several other genetic syndromes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1362361312442790">Moss and Howlin, 2009</xref>). Although the similarities between the DS+ASD and ASD-only group are perhaps not surprising, given that these groups were matched on total SCQ scores, it indicates that the <italic>presentation</italic> of ASD symptomatology and the contribution of each domain score towards the total SCQ score is similar in those with DS who meet the cut-off for ASD on the SCQ and those with idiopathic ASD. These findings are consistent with that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al. (2005)</xref> who also report impairments within all domains of the triad.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1362361312442790">
<title>Profile of hyperactivity, repetitive behaviour, challenging behaviour and mood</title>
<p>Previous studies have reported that those with DS and ASD are different from those with ‘typical’ DS, showing higher rates of behaviour difficulties, including hyperactivity, stereotyped behaviour and inappropriate speech (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1362361312442790">Carter et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. 2009</xref>). In this study, we evaluated whether these differences were evident when adaptive behaviour was controlled for, and whether this behaviour profile was also evident in individuals with idiopathic ASD. Similar to previous findings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1362361312442790">Capone et al. (2005)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1362361312442790">Carter et al. (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1362361312442790">Molloy et al. (2009)</xref>, our results indicated that individuals in the DS+ASD group showed significantly more stereotyped behaviour (specifically hand stereotypies), repetitive use of language (including repetitive phrases and echolalia) and overactivity than those in the DS-only group. No differences between the DS+ASD and DS-only groups were identified with regard to impulsivity, although the ASD-only group showed significantly more impulsivity than the DS-only group. Interestingly, the repetitive interests, rituals, preference for routine and attachment to objects previously reported in some of the single case studies of individuals with DS+ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1362361312442790">Ghaziuddin et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1362361312442790">Howlin et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1362361312442790">Kent et al., 1998</xref>) were not highlighted in this study as being particularly prominent in this group relative to individuals with DS only.</p>
<p>This study extended previous findings to evaluate levels of mood and challenging behaviour (self-injurious behaviour, physical aggression and destruction of property) in individuals with DS+ASD relative to those with DS-only and ASD-only. The analysis indicated that individuals with DS-only had higher levels of interest and pleasure than those with ASD-only. Item-level analysis of this questionnaire indicated that <italic>both</italic> the DS-only and DS+ASD groups showed significantly more interest in their surroundings than the ASD-only group, whereas the DS+ASD and ASD-only groups showed fewer positive vocalizations than the DS-only group. In addition, the DS-only group showed significantly less flat affect and expressed greater enjoyment in activities than the ASD-only group. Self-injury was significantly more likely to occur in individuals with DS+ASD and ASD-only relative to those with DS-only. No other differences in challenging behaviour were observed.</p>
<p>Overall, these results support previous findings showing differences between individuals with DS-only and those with DS+ASD. Specifically, individuals with DS who meet the cut-off for ASD on the SCQ show greater levels of stereotyped behaviour, repetitive language, self-injurious behaviour and overactivity and fewer positive vocalizations than those with DS-only. These differences are not accounted for by degree of ID. Furthermore, the DS+ASD group show a similar profile of ASD symptomatology and a similar behavioural profile to those with idiopathic ASD. Again, this does not seem to be accounted for by degree of ID. However, the DS+ASD group are reported to be less withdrawn from their environment than those with idiopathic ASD, suggesting some subtle differences between these groups with regard to the quality of the social impairments. It is well established that the DS population, as a whole, experience significantly fewer behaviour difficulties than other individuals with ID (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1362361312442790">Dykens et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1362361312442790">Reilly, 2009</xref>) and this has been suggested by some to indicate that DS is, in some way, protective of such difficulties. The findings from this study suggest that this apparent ‘protection’ may be reduced by the presence of ASD symptomatology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1362361312442790">
<title>Limitations of the study</title>
<p>The findings from the current study should be considered alongside a number of limitations. The presence of ASD symptomatology was identified through the use of an informant screening tool, the SCQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1362361312442790">Rutter et al., 2003</xref>). Consequently, there is a limit to what we are able to infer regarding the prevalence of ASD within this DS sample. Scoring highly on the SCQ alone is not sufficient to indicate a diagnosis and further detailed observation and interview is required for diagnosis. However, previous studies have reported very good convergent validity for the SCQ and other ‘gold standard’ diagnostic assessments of ASD, suggesting that this measure provides a very good indicator of ASD symptomatology. Reliance on the Wessex self help scale to provide an estimate of adaptive behaviour skills is a further limitation of the study. In future studies, direct assessments of ID and adaptive skills such as the Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1362361312442790">Sparrow et al., 2005</xref>) would provide a more accurate account of degree of ID. However, it is important to note that the Wessex scale, although brief, has been reported to show good reliability (Kushlick et al., 1982; Palmer and Jenkins, 1979). Furthermore, this is the first study to consider the role of ID, in any way, when evaluating the association between ASD and DS. Given the difficulties in identifying ASD in individuals with ID this is clearly an important confounding variable to take into account. The overall response rate of the DS group was relatively low (28.8%) and this is likely to be due to the fact that this syndrome group has been extensively researched and thus may reflect participant fatigue. Although this may have introduced some bias in the sample, the study was presented to families as a project evaluating the characteristics of DS and this is likely to have avoided a bias towards more severely affected individuals. The sample size of the three matched participants groups was small and this may have resulted in limited statistical power. However, the size of the samples was largely driven by the proportion of individuals with DS who met the cut-off for ASD. Furthermore, inclusion of matched comparison groups addresses the threat to internal validity and enables more precise characterization of the behavioural profile of individuals with DS+ASD. One potential drawback of the matched DS-only group is that our analyses identified that those individuals with DS who scored above cut-off for ASD on the SCQ had significantly lower levels of ability than the total DS sample. This confounder was accounted for in the subsequent matched groups comparisons, although it may suggest that the individuals selected into the matched DS-only group were those who were less able and therefore may not be representative of the wider DS population. However, the fact that our findings are consistent with those reported in previous studies, where matched comparison groups have not been used, suggests that our findings are valid. Finally, diagnosis of DS was not confirmed by genetic karyotyping in this study. Given the age range of the sample (4–62 yrs) it is unlikely that this information would be available for a significant proportion of individuals and thus reliance upon a confirmed clinical diagnosis, which is highly accurate in this syndrome, was considered to be sufficient.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1362361312442790" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Consistent with previous findings, we identified the proportion of individuals meeting cut-off scores for ASD and autism in a sample of 108 individuals with DS to be 19% and 8%, respectively. Individuals with DS+ASD showed a different profile of behaviour difficulties from that of individuals with DS-only, which was not accounted for by level of adaptive behaviour skills. This provides support for previous reports that have suggested that individuals with DS and ASD comprise a subgroup of individuals with DS. Individuals with DS+ASD performed similarly to individuals with ASD on a range of measures; however, this was not always the case, suggesting that individuals with DS+ASD may show some areas of subtle difference from those with idiopathic ASD. Further detailed study of these subgroups using larger samples and direct assessments is required to progress our understanding of the association between ASD and DS.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are grateful to the Down syndrome Association UK, the National Autistic Society and Research Autism UK for their help with participant recruitment, to Dawn Adams and Laura O’Farrell for their help with data collection and data entry and to all of the families who took part in this study.</p>
</ack>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1362361312442790">
<label>1.</label>
<p>‘DS+ASD’ is used here and throughout to describe participants scoring above the cut-off on the SCQ for ASD; it does not imply that these individuals have a confirmed diagnosis of co-morbid ASD.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1362361312442790">
<label>2.</label>
<p>It was important to match the DS+ASD and ASD only groups according to SCQ scores to ensure that any difference in the profile of ASD symptomatology and other behavioural characteristics could clearly be attributed to group membership rather than differences in the severity of ASD symptomatology of the two groups.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abu-Amero</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hellani</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salih</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seidahmed</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elmalik</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zidan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bosley</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A de novo marker chromosome derived from 9p in a patient with 9p partial duplication syndrome and autism features: genotype-phenotype correlation</article-title>. <source>BMC Medical Genetics</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>135</fpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burbidge</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Delineation of behavioural phenotypes in genetic syndromes. Prevalence, phenomenology and correlates of self-injurious and aggressive behaviour</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Down’s syndrome: occurrence and outcome in the north of England, 1985–99</article-title>. <source>Paediatric and Perinatal Epidemiology</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berument</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickles</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Autism Screening Questionnaire: Diagnostic validity</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>175</volume>, <fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norbury</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Exploring the borderlands of autistic disorder and specific language impairment: a study using standardized diagnostic instruments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>917</fpage>–<lpage>929</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bregman</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Case Study Autistic Social Dysfunction and Down Syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burbidge</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trusler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furniss</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The association between repetitive behaviours, impulsivity and hyperactivity in people with intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1078</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Capone</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grados</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernad-Ripoll</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Down Syndrome and Comorbid Autism-Spectrum Disorder: Characterization Using the Aberrant Behavior Checklist</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Medical Genetics</source>, <volume>134A</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capone</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Autistic-spectrum disorders in down syndrome: Further delineation and distinction from other behavioral abnormalities</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Medical Genetics Part B: Neuropsychiatric Genetics</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DiGuiseppi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fidler</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartway</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruttenber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rovinson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Screening for autism spectrum disorders in children with down syndrome population prevalence and screening test characteristics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>– <lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dykens</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hodapp</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Genetics and Mental Retardation Syndromes</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paul H Brookes Publishing Co</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisch</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grossfeld</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Youngblom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simensen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Autism, intellectual disability and molecular-genetic aspects associated with subtelomeric rearrangements</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>886</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fombonne</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The epidemiology of autism: a review</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>769</fpage>–<lpage>786</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ghaziuddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>L. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghaziuddin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Autism in Down’s syndrome: presentation and diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillberg</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>The Biology of the Autistic Syndromes</source>. (<edition>3 ed.</edition>) <publisher-name>McKeith press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillberg</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grufman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Themner</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Psychiatric disorders in mildly and severely mentally retarded urban children and adolescents: epidemiological aspects</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>149</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lightbody</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rezvani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Autism in Fragile X Syndrome: a category mistake?</article-title> <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>921</fpage>–<lpage>933</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Philofsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fidler</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Autism symptoms in toddlers with Down syndrome: a descriptive study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karpf</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Using the Social Communication Questionnaire to identify ‘autistic spectrum’ disorders associated with other genetic conditions: findings from a study of individuals with Cohen syndrome</article-title>. <source>Autism</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The recognition of autism in children with Down syndrome: implications for intervention and some speculations about pathology</article-title>. <source>Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>398</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Self-injurious behavior, self-restraint and compulsive behaviors in Cornelia de Lange syndrome</article-title>. <source>American Journal on Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Comorbidity of autistic spectrum disorder in children with Down syndrome</article-title>. <source>Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Autism in Down’s syndrome: Three case reports</article-title>. <source>Autism</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kushlick</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blunden</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>A method for rating behavior characteristics for use in large scale studies of mental handicap</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>466</fpage> – <lpage>478</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowenthal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartzman</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brunoni</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mercadante</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of pervasive developmental disorders in Down’s syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1394</fpage>–<lpage>1395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Psychiatric aspects of Down’s syndrome</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinsman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Differences in the clinical presentation of Trisomy 21 with and without autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Invited Annotation - Autism spectrum disorders in genetic syndromes: Implications for diagnosis, intervention and understanding the wider ASD population</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>872</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The assessment and presentation of Autism Spectrum Disorder and associated characteristics in individuals with severe intellectual disability and genetic syndromes</article-title>. <source>The Oxford Handbook of Intellectual Disability and Development</source>. Editors: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Burack</surname><given-names>Jake</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hodapp</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iarocci</surname><given-names>Grace</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zigler</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burbidge</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>).<article-title>The prevalence and phenomenology of repetitive behavior in genetic syndromes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of autism spectrum phenomenology in Cornelia de Lange and Cri du Chat syndromes</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mount</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cass</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003a</year>). <article-title>Towards a behavioral phenotype for Rett syndrome</article-title>. <source>American Journal on Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burbidge</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (In Press). <article-title>Delineation of behavioral phenotypes in genetic syndromes. Comparison of autism spectrum disorder, affect and hyperactivity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The ‘Wessex’ behaviour rating system for metnally handicapped people: Reliability study</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Mental Subnormality</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quintero-Rivera</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharifi-Hannauer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez-Agosto</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Autistic and Psychiatric Findings Associated With the 3q29 Microdeletion Syndrome: Case Report and Review</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Medical Genetics Part A</source>, <volume>152a</volume>, <fpage>2459</fpage>–<lpage>2467</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Börjesson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wentz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillberg</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Autistic disorders in Down syndrome: Background factors and clinical correlates</article-title>. <source>Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>750</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (In press). <article-title>Self-injurious behaviour in individuals with autism spectrum disorder and intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Autism spectrum disorders in Down syndrome: A review</article-title>. <source>Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>829</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Preliminary analysis of the psychometric properties of the Mood, Interest and Pleasure Questionnaire (MIPQ) for adults with severe and profound learning disabilities</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berument</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The Social Communication Questionnaire</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Western Psychological Services</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales, Second Edition</source>. <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Assessment</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berument</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomlins</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papanikolaou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Brief report: autism in individuals with Down syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trillingsaard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ostergaard</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Autism in Angelman syndrome: an exploration of comorbidity</article-title>. <source>Autism: International Journal of Research and Practice</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Fragile X syndrome and autistic features</article-title>. <source>Autism: International Journal of Research and Practice</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1362361312442790">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wakabayashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Case of infantile-autism associated with Down’s Syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>