<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="EN">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TJX</journal-id>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptjx</journal-id>
            <journal-title>Theology</journal-title>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">0040-571X</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">2044-2696</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040571X13475404d</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040571X13475404d</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Book Reviews</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Jeremy Schipper, <italic>Disability and Isaiah’s Suffering
                        Servant</italic></article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Heskett</surname>
                        <given-names>Randall</given-names>
                    </name>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="aff1-0040571X13475404">Boulder University, Boulder, Colorado</aff>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>116</volume>
            <issue>3</issue>
            <fpage>209</fpage>
            <lpage>210</lpage>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge</copyright-holder>
            </permissions>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="sec1-0040571X13475404">
            <title>Jeremy Schipper, <bold><italic>Disability and Isaiah’s Suffering
                        Servant</italic></bold>, Biblical Refigurations, Oxford University Press:
                Oxford, 2011; 208 pp.: 9780199594856, £45.00 (£22.50)/$65.00
                (hbk); 9780199594863, £14.99/$27.95 (pbk)</title>
            <p>In his book, <italic>Disability and Isaiah’s Suffering Servant</italic>,
                Jeremy Schipper raises an important question that scholarship has tended to ignore
                regarding the subject of disability, when interpreting the Scriptures. He claims
                that, although disability imagery is ubiquitous in the Hebrew Bible, characters with
                disabilities are not much in evidence, and tries to establish the Suffering Servant
                in Isaiah 53 as a biblical character with disabilities, aiming to show that
                disability language is lost in translation. He claims there are physical and social
                implications from an injured, killed, recovered and prisoner Servant. Arguing that
                disability language is lost in typology, Schipper makes no distinction between
                typology and metaphor within the ‘literal sense’ of Scripture.
                Reference to blind and deaf imagery may not speak of disability, since Isaiah 6 uses
                this metaphor to describe Judah’s unwillingness to hear the prophetic word,
                and blindness and deafness in Isaiah 40—55 refer to Isaiah 6 and not
                ‘literal’ reference to disabilities. Whether or not such an argument
                is correct, Schipper shows how narrow traditional interpretations are when
                considering the Servant or other biblical characters.</p>
            <p>Admirable as his project is, Schipper overlooks the extensive nature of
                twentieth-century scholarship, not to mention work on the formation of Isaiah,
                medieval rabbinic exegesis and recent works about the role of the Servant. While his
                Targumic treatment underscores that early Judaism did not foresee a suffering
                messiah, more extensive research is needed before addressing this commendable topic.
                Overlooking how Isaiah 40—66 was trisected into three equal parts,
                developing the Servant from collective (40—48) to individual (49—57)
                and ‘servants’ (58—66), Schipper imposes a
                ‘collective reference’ on Isaiah 52.13—53.12 while ignoring
                scholarship that demonstrates how the first three Servant Songs have a different
                meaning from the fourth song. He also overlooks the ‘functional
                ambiguity’ of the fourth song, which allows for a variety of
                interpretations. His section on messianism is quite weak and shows little awareness
                of this subject, including my <italic>Messianism within the Scriptural Scroll of
                    Isaiah</italic> (2007). Schipper needs to move beyond pre-biblical levels of
                Deutero-Isaiah to the later scriptural form of the book when later editors reshaped
                Deutero-Isaiah into a greater corpus.</p>
            <p>Inviting biblical readers into new hermeneutical horizons, Schiffer’s work
                will cause scholars to step back and re-examine disabilities but it requires more
                advanced research. This thoughtful, compassionate and imaginative work warns
                biblical scholars against closing their hearts to other interpretive options. It is
                accessible to both scholars and general readers but betrays how topical study or
                themes cannot be imposed on biblical literature.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
</article>