<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PEN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppen</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0148-6071</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2444</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0148607111413896</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0148607111413896</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Communications</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Use of Prealbumin and C-Reactive Protein for Monitoring Nutrition Support in Adult Patients Receiving Enteral Nutrition in an Urban Medical Center</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Cassie Jo</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS, RD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sowa</surname><given-names>Diane</given-names></name>
<degrees>MBA, LDN, RD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>Kathryn S.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, LDN, RD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kinnare</surname><given-names>Kelly</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS, RD, LDN, CNSD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS, RD, LDN, CNSD</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0148607111413896">Rush University Medical Center, Chicago, Illinois. Statistical adviser: Kwasny M, CsD, Rush University Medical Center, Chicago, Illinois</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0148607111413896">Cassie Jo Davis, MS, RD, Essentia Health St. Mary’s Medical Center, Nutrition Services Department, 502 E. 2nd Street, Duluth, MN 55805; e-mail: <email>cjodavis@yahoo.com</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>197</fpage>
<lpage>204</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>27</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Background</italic>: Serum prealbumin (PAB) is commonly used to assess protein status and is often used to monitor the response to nutrition support. However, during inflammation, the liver synthesizes acute-phase proteins such as C-reactive protein (CRP) at the expense of PAB. <italic>Objective</italic>: The purpose of this retrospective study was to determine whether changes in PAB reflect the delivery of adequate nutrients or changes in inflammatory status in hospitalized adults (≥18 years) receiving enteral nutrition (n = 154). <italic>Methods</italic>: Protein and energy intake were compared to changes in PAB, assessed at baseline and twice weekly. C-reactive protein was assessed when PAB was &lt;18 mg/dL to determine the presence and severity of inflammation. <italic>Results</italic>: In a sample of mostly critically ill patients, there was no significant difference in change in PAB for those receiving ≥60% of calorie needs (2.74 ± 9.50 mg/dL) compared to &lt;60% of calorie needs (2.48 ± 9.36 mg/dL; <italic>P</italic> = .86). Changes in PAB correlated only with changes in CRP (<italic>r</italic> = -0.544, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). In a subgroup analysis of 62 patients with repeated measures of PAB and CRP, PAB increased significantly only in the bottom 2 tertiles for calorie delivery and the lowest tertile for protein delivery. <italic>Conclusions</italic>: These results indicate that PAB may not be a sensitive marker for evaluating the adequacy of nutrition support in critically ill patients with inflammation. Only change in CRP was able to significantly predict changes in PAB, suggesting that an improvement in inflammation, rather than nutrient intake, was responsible for the increases in PAB levels.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>prealbumin</kwd>
<kwd>enteral nutrition</kwd>
<kwd>inflammation</kwd>
<kwd>C-reactive protein</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0148607111413896">
<title>Clinical Relevancy Statement</title>
<p>The results of this study are clinically relevant to the practice of using prealbumin to determine the adequacy of nutrition support. The results suggest that clinicians should not rely on change in prealbumin as a marker for adequate nutrient delivery, as it may be more likely to reflect changes in inflammatory status, particularly in the critically ill patient.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0148607111413896" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The prevalence of malnutrition is reported to be between 13% and 78% among hospitalized adults.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0148607111413896">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0148607111413896">3</xref></sup> Malnutrition is associated with an increased risk of infection, a longer length of hospital stay, and increased morbidity and mortality.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0148607111413896">1</xref></sup> Interruption in the delivery of enteral nutrition (EN) for tests and procedures may lead to an increased risk of malnutrition in hospitalized patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111413896">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0148607111413896">10</xref></sup> The delivery of adequate nutrients can help prevent or reverse the effects of malnutrition. However, accurate methods are needed to monitor the adequacy of nutrition support. To assess nutrition status, many clinicians use a combination of objective measures, such as weight, weight loss, arm circumference, skinfold measures, lab values, and subjective measures such as subjective global assessment and diet history. Many of the measures used are subject to error and can be influenced by conditions such as edema, obesity, and loss of skin turgor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0148607111413896">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Serum prealbumin (PAB) is often used to help assess adequacy of nutrition support in preference to other serum proteins such as albumin, given its shorter half-life of 2.5 days.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111413896">12</xref></sup> However, caution should be taken when interpreting PAB in the hospitalized patient, especially in the critically ill population. Prealbumin is increased with severe renal failure, corticosteroid use, and oral contraceptive use. Serum concentrations decrease with liver disease, hepatitis, dialysis, hyperthyroidism, pregnancy, and significant hyperglycemia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111413896">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111413896">14</xref></sup> In addition, as a negative acute-phase protein, PAB synthesis decreases with inflammation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111413896">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111413896">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>C-reactive protein (CRP) is a marker for inflammation that changes rapidly in the presence of inflammation, having a half-life of approximately 19 hours.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111413896">14</xref></sup> CRP is often used in conjunction with PAB to assess whether the changes in PAB are reflective of adequate nutrition support or changes in inflammation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111413896">14</xref></sup> It should be noted that although CRP generally rises with the presence and severity of inflammation and decreases as inflammation subsides, it has limitations to its use and interpretation. People respond differently to similar inflammatory conditions, and CRP levels vary widely in both healthy individuals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0148607111413896">15</xref></sup> and in infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0148607111413896">16</xref></sup> CRP levels are known to be elevated among patients with chronic inflammatory conditions, including periodontal disease, arthritis, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, renal failure, metabolic syndrome, and obesity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0148607111413896">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>Much of the existing research on PAB as a marker for adequate nutrient delivery occurred prior to the current understanding of the inflammatory process, and indicators of inflammation were seldom measured.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0148607111413896">18</xref></sup> The identification of a sensitive and objective marker will help clinicians monitor the adequacy of nutrition support. However, many experts disagree as to whether any serum protein can be used for this purpose.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0148607111413896">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0148607111413896">24</xref></sup> Small sample sizes, short study duration, lack of inflammatory markers measured, and poor monitoring of intake are just some of the limitations of earlier studies.</p>
<p>The purpose of this retrospective study was to determine whether changes in PAB are reflective of the delivery of adequate calories and protein or of changes in CRP and inflammatory status. The specific objectives were to determine the average calorie and protein intake in patients receiving EN in relation to the EN prescription, examine the relation between protein and calorie intake and changes in PAB levels, and determine whether CRP concentration influences the relation between PAB and nutrient intake. The major hypothesis was, with adequate protein and energy intake, PAB will be within normal range, regardless of the level of CRP in patients receiving EN.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0148607111413896" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section4-0148607111413896">
<title>Participants and Setting</title>
<p>This study was a retrospective review of data collected between July and November 2008 as part of an academic urban medical center Food and Nutrition Services Department quality improvement initiative. Approval for the study was obtained from the Institutional Review Board for Human Subjects. All adult patients (18 years or older) requiring EN were eligible for inclusion, with the exception of patients admitted to the psychiatric or maternity units. Patients were excluded from analysis if they received EN for &lt;3 days, had &lt;2 measures of PAB, or received parenteral nutrition (PN) or an oral diet while receiving EN.</p>
<p>Patients who received PN were excluded under the assumption that many of these patients would be receiving a nutrient prescription meeting &lt;100% of needs due to more cautious advancement secondary to the risk of refeeding syndrome, volume restrictions, or limitations associated with the use of a peripheral line. Patients who received an oral diet were excluded because of the difficulty obtaining accurate calorie and protein intake records.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0148607111413896">
<title>Data Collection and Procedures</title>
<p>Upon receipt of an EN consult, a registered dietitian (RD) recorded demographic data, including age, ethnicity, gender, diagnoses, and past medical and surgical history. Each patient was assigned a unique study number. The RD performed a nutrition risk assessment on each patient. Nutrition risk was defined as weight &lt;85% ideal body weight (IBW), body mass index (BMI) &lt;18.5, or unintentional weight loss of 10% or greater in 6 months. Within 72 hours of study enrollment, patients received an indirect calorimetry measurement using the Ultima (MedGraphics, St Paul, MN) metabolic cart to determine measured resting energy expenditure (MREE). In the event that indirect calorimetry was not completed (ie, patients receiving supplemental oxygen, patients with a fraction of inspired oxygen [FiO<sub>2</sub>] ≥60%, or patients with chest tubes) or if the indirect calorimetry measurement was invalid (ie, coefficient of variation &gt;10%, respiratory quotient out of physiological range of &lt;0.67 or &gt;1.3),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0148607111413896">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0148607111413896">26</xref></sup> the estimated goal calorie requirement was used.</p>
<p>A dosing weight (DW) was determined based on the patient’s percent IBW, with an adjusted weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0148607111413896">27</xref></sup> used for patients who were &gt;120% IBW. Calorie requirements were calculated per protocol using a range of 30–35 calories per kilogram based on the patients’ DW and individualized to patients’ needs. The EN protocol called for a calorie range of 30–35 calories per kilogram as part of a more aggressive feeding strategy to achieve adequate nutrient delivery after completion of internal studies that revealed patients were receiving on average 60% of the EN prescription. Protein needs were calculated based on the patient’s weight and clinical condition. The protein prescription ranged from 0.9–2.5 g per kilogram actual or adjusted body weight. The RD determined the appropriate formula and calculated goal rate and EN infusion schedule. EN was initiated per protocol at 20 mL/h and advanced by 20-mL/h increments as tolerated every 4 hours until the goal rate was achieved.</p>
<p>The RD checked the Kangaroo ePump (Kendall, Mansfield, MA) enteral feeding pump daily and recorded the volume of EN infused over the previous 24 hours, unless criteria for study discharge occurred, which included (1) discontinuation of EN order, (2) death, (3) either PN or an oral diet was ordered, or (4) patient was on EN &gt;30 days. Total calories and protein delivered during the previous 24 hours were calculated based on the volume infused. Health risk scores, including Braden Score, number and stage of wounds, Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation (APACHE) II score, and Glascow Coma score were obtained and recorded upon admit. The medical record was checked daily and data collected for medications (propofol, corticosteroids, and multivitamins), protein modulars, labs (albumin, PAB, and CRP), reasons why EN was held, and infections. Calories from propofol, as well as calories and protein from protein modulars, were calculated and added to the total calories and protein delivered during the previous 24 hours. Tube feeding complications that were documented included gastric residual volume, aspiration, diarrhea, nausea and vomiting, and constipation.</p>
<p>Prealbumin levels were obtained within 24 hours of starting EN and every Tuesday and Friday. CRP values were obtained if PAB levels were &lt;18 mg/dL to assess the presence and severity of inflammation. A PAB of &lt;18 mg/dL was considered suboptimal,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0148607111413896">13</xref></sup> and a CRP of ≥10 mg/L was considered indicative of the inflammatory response.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0148607111413896">28</xref></sup> Turbidimetric immunoassays (Architect c8000; Abbott Laboratories, Diagnostics Division, Abbott Park, IL) were used to determine PAB and CRP levels. All data were verified against electronic records, and patient data sheets were returned to the RD for final review. Data were collected for up to 30 days of EN support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0148607111413896">
<title>Statistical Methods</title>
<p>All data were coded and entered into SPSS for Windows (version 15.0, 2006; SPSS, Inc, an IBM Company, Chicago, IL). All tests were run at a 2-tailed significance level of α = 0.05. Bonferroni corrections were used for all post hoc multiple comparisons. Normally distributed variables are presented as mean ± standard deviation, and nonnormally distributed variables are presented as median and interquartile range (IQR). Calorie and protein intake were analyzed as the percent delivered of prescribed:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0148607111413896">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0148607111413896">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Calories</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>protein delivered</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Prescribed</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>%</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>delivered of prescribed</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0148607111413896" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111413896-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>Pearson’s correlation coefficients were determined to check for correlations between change in PAB and percent calories and protein delivered. Patients were split into 2 groups based on the delivery of adequate calories and protein, defined as ≥60% of prescribed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0148607111413896">29</xref></sup> Independent <italic>t</italic> tests were used to determine whether there was a difference in the change in PAB based on adequate calorie and protein delivery. Patients were also split into tertiles of percent calories or percent protein delivered, and a 1-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to detect any differences in change in PAB. Two multiple linear regression models were fit to the ability of either percent calories delivered or percent protein delivered, adjusting for change in CRP to predict changes in PAB. Preliminary analyses were conducted to ensure no violation of the assumptions of normality, linearity, multicollinearity, and homoscedasticity.</p>
<p>A subgroup of 62 patients with 3 or more repeated measures of PAB and 2 or more measures of CRP was split into tertiles of percent calories or percent protein delivered. Wilcoxon signed rank tests with Bonferroni adjustments were used to detect within-group differences over 3 time points in PAB, CRP, percent of calories delivered, and percent of protein delivered. Multivariate tests from analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) were used to detect differences in the pattern of change in PAB over the tertiles of percent calories and percent protein delivered while controlling for change in CRP.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0148607111413896" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section8-0148607111413896">
<title>Study Sample</title>
<p>Three hundred charts were reviewed and assessed for inclusion in this study. In total, 146 patients were excluded from analysis: 54 (37%) had none or 1 PAB value, 52 (36%) received &lt;3 days of EN, 7 (5%) were repeated admissions, 7 (5%) received an oral diet or PN, 20 had incomplete data (14%), and 6 (4%) had a wrong medical record number recorded. A total of 154 patients were included in the final data set for analysis.</p>
<p>The study sample comprised mostly older (mean age 60.4 years) African American (44%) overweight or obese (57%) adults. Most patients were critically ill, with 85.7% (n = 132) having spent some time in a medical, surgical, or neuro–intensive care unit (ICU) during their hospital stay and a mean APACHE II score of 17.4 ± 5.8 for ICU patients (n = 85). The average ICU length of stay (LOS) was 13.2 ± 10.7 days, and the average hospital LOS was 18.9 ± 12.2 days. Patients received EN for an average of 12.4 ± 6.6 days. The most common reasons for requirement of EN were intubation (52.1%), decreased mental status (19.2%), and dysphagia (11.0%). Steroids were used among 55 patients (36.7%). Demographic characteristic and diagnoses are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0148607111413896">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0148607111413896" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline Characteristics, Diagnoses, and Length of Stay of Enterally Fed Adults Admitted to a Large Urban Medical Center</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0148607111413896" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111413896-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristic</th>
<th align="center">Mean ± SD</th>
<th align="center">No.</th>
<th align="center">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age, y (n = 154)</td>
<td>60.4 ± 16.6</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Gender (n = 154)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td/>
<td>75</td>
<td>48.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td/>
<td>79</td>
<td>51.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Race/ethnicity (n = 148)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td/>
<td>65</td>
<td>43.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td/>
<td>55</td>
<td>37.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td/>
<td>26</td>
<td>17.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td/>
<td>2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BMI (n = 154)</td>
<td>26.8 ± 6.4</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Underweight (BMI   &lt;18.5)</td>
<td/>
<td>12</td>
<td>7.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Normal (BMI 18.5–24.9)</td>
<td/>
<td>54</td>
<td>35.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Overweight (BMI 25–29.9)</td>
<td/>
<td>44</td>
<td>28.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Obese (BMI ≥30)</td>
<td/>
<td>44</td>
<td>28.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Primary diagnosis (n = 149)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Stroke/neurological</td>
<td/>
<td>68</td>
<td>45.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cancer</td>
<td/>
<td>19</td>
<td>12.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gastrointestinal disorder</td>
<td/>
<td>9</td>
<td>6.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Heart disease</td>
<td/>
<td>5</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td/>
<td>48</td>
<td>32.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Secondary diagnosis (n = 113)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0148607111413896">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hypertension</td>
<td/>
<td>74</td>
<td>38.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td/>
<td>33</td>
<td>17.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Heart disease</td>
<td/>
<td>24</td>
<td>12.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Renal</td>
<td/>
<td>11</td>
<td>5.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cancer</td>
<td/>
<td>8</td>
<td>4.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td/>
<td>42</td>
<td>21.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Infections<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup> (n = 141)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></td>
<td/>
<td>89</td>
<td>63.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Steroids<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0148607111413896">d</xref></sup> (n = 150)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></td>
<td/>
<td>55</td>
<td>36.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LOS (n = 154)</td>
<td>18.9 ± 12.2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICU LOS (n = 132)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>13.2 ± 10.7</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0148607111413896">
<p>BMI, body mass index, calculated as kg/m<sup>2</sup>; ICU, intensive care unit; LOS, hospital length of stay in days.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0148607111413896">
<label>a</label>
<p>Sample size for characteristics varies due to missing values.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0148607111413896">
<label>b</label>
<p>Up to 2 secondary diagnoses were recorded per patient; total recorded = 192.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0148607111413896">
<label>c</label>
<p>Recorded as positive if there was a positive culture at any point during the study period; included urinary, blood stream, aerobic, and/or sputum cultures.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0148607111413896">
<label>d</label>
<p>Recorded as positive if steroids used at any point during the study period.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0148607111413896">
<title>Nutrients Delivered vs Prescribed</title>
<p>It has been well established that patients receiving EN often do not receive their full nutrient prescription.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111413896">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0148607111413896">10</xref></sup> In this study, the EN prescription was based on estimated or measured needs. Metabolic cart studies were completed on 39 (25.3%) patients. The average EN prescription was 1966 ± 353 kcal/d and 109.8 ± 31.4 g protein/d. The average EN prescription by gender and the percent of calories and protein delivered are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0148607111413896">Table 2</xref>. Overall, an average of 57.3% ± 0.2% and 56.1% ± 0.2% of the calorie and protein prescription was delivered, respectively. A total of 70 (45.5%) patients received ≥60% of their prescribed calorie needs, and 65 (42.2%) received ≥60% of their prescribed protein needs.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0148607111413896" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Average Enteral Nutrition Prescription and Actual Intake in Male and Female Patients</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0148607111413896" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111413896-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Enteral Prescription<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></th>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Adequate Intake<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0148607111413896">b</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center">Total</th>
<th align="center">Per kg</th>
<th align="center">Percent Delivered</th>
<th align="center">No.</th>
<th align="center">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Male (n = 75)</td>
<td>Calories</td>
<td>2129 ± 348<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>29.2 ± 3.3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0148607111413896">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>56.4 ± 21.7<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0148607111413896">e</xref></sup></td>
<td>36</td>
<td>48.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Protein</td>
<td>121.9 ± 30.9<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0148607111413896">f</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.7 ± 0.3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0148607111413896">g</xref></sup></td>
<td>53.4 ± 22.0<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn13-0148607111413896">h</xref></sup></td>
<td>28</td>
<td>37.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female (n = 79)</td>
<td>Calories</td>
<td>1812 ± 284<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>31.0 ± 2.9<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0148607111413896">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>58.1 ± 19.6<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0148607111413896">e</xref></sup></td>
<td>34</td>
<td>43.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Protein</td>
<td>98.2 ± 27.4<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0148607111413896">f</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.7 ± 0.4<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0148607111413896">g</xref></sup></td>
<td>58.8 ± 22.8<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0148607111413896">h</xref></sup></td>
<td>37</td>
<td>46.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total (n = 154)</td>
<td>Calories</td>
<td>1966 ± 353<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>30.1 ± 3.2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0148607111413896">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>57.3 ± 0.2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0148607111413896">e</xref></sup></td>
<td>70</td>
<td>45.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Protein</td>
<td>109.8 ± 31.4<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0148607111413896">f</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.6 ± 0.3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0148607111413896">g</xref></sup></td>
<td>56.1 ± 0.2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0148607111413896">h</xref></sup></td>
<td>65</td>
<td>42.2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0148607111413896">
<label>a</label>
<p>Data presented at mean ± standard deviation.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0148607111413896">
<label>b</label>
<p>Adequate intake defined as ≥60% of estimated or measured needs.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0148607111413896">
<label>c</label>
<p>Total calories prescribed (kcal/d).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-0148607111413896">
<label>d</label>
<p>Calories prescribed as kcal/kg dosing weight.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn10-0148607111413896">
<label>e</label>
<p>Calories delivered as a percent of prescribed.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn11-0148607111413896">
<label>f</label>
<p>Total protein prescribed (g/d).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn12-0148607111413896">
<label>g</label>
<p>Protein prescribed as g/kg dosing weight.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn13-0148607111413896">
<label>h</label>
<p>Protein delivered as a percent of prescribed.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0148607111413896">
<title>Reasons for EN Held</title>
<p>EN infusions may be held, or initiation delayed, for a variety of reasons, reducing the achievement of adequate nutrition support. EN was started on the first day of admission or within 1 day of the patient becoming nil per os (NPO) in 94 (61.4%) patients (mean 0.87 ± 1.33 days). For 740 (39%) feeding days, of a total of 1909 feeding days, at least one reason was given for stopping the EN infusion. The RD was asked to provide a reason any time the infusion was interrupted or if a patient received &lt;750 kcal/d. There were 284 EN feeding days for which the patient received &lt;750 kcal. Of these, 219 (77%) had a reason recorded for EN cessation time. The most common reasons for stopping EN or for delivery of &lt;750 kcal were surgery (31%); tests (11%); EN complication, including gastric residual volume, aspiration, diarrhea, nausea and vomiting, and constipation (11%); EN just started (and not yet advanced to goal) (11%); and “other” (such as tube occluded or out, medication administration, patient unstable, and forgot to turn on pump) (20%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0148607111413896">
<title>Relation Among Prealbumin, Nutrient Delivery, and Inflammation</title>
<p>Clinicians often expect to see an increase in PAB as nutrient delivery increases, but the presence of inflammation may make changes in PAB difficult to interpret. In this study, there was a significant increase in PAB between the first measure (13.5 (8.8, 18.3) mg/dL) and the last measure (16.5 (12.0, 23.0) mg/dL); <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001, n = 154. There was a significant decrease in CRP between the first (72.9 (38.5, 137.9) mg/L) and last (52.2 (19.6, 103.0) mg/L) measures; <italic>P</italic> = .009, n = 94. The mean time between the first and last PAB measure was 8.6 ± 6.26 days (range, 1–28). CRP was usually measured when PAB was &lt;18 mg/dL, resulting in fewer measures of CRP than PAB. Twenty-three patients (14.9%) had no measures of CRP, 37 (24.0%) had a single measure, and 94 (61.0%) had 2 or more repeated measures.</p>
<p>Change in PAB did not correlate with percent calories delivered or percent protein delivered. The sample was split into 2 groups based on those who received above (n = 70) and below (n = 84) an average of 60% of prescribed calorie needs. The sample was similarly split by patients who received above (n = 65) and below (n = 89) an average of 60% of prescribed protein needs. The percent of needs delivered was calculated between the first and last PAB measure (mean 8.6 ± 6.26 days). The 60% cutoff was chosen based on evidence that the delivery of 60%−70% of calorie and protein needs can help reduce LOS, ventilator time, and infectious complications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0148607111413896">29</xref></sup> There was no significant difference in change from first to last PAB for those receiving ≥60% of calorie needs (2.74 ± 9.50 mg/dL) compared to &lt;60% of calorie needs (2.48 ± 9.36 mg/dL); <italic>P</italic> = .86. For those who achieved adequate protein intake, there was a nonsignificant trend toward a greater increase in PAB (4.12 ± 8.05 mg/dL) compared to those who did not achieve adequate protein intake (1.48 ± 10.16 mg/dL); <italic>P</italic> = .09.</p>
<p>A 1-way ANOVA was conducted to explore the relation of calorie intake to change in PAB, not accounting for inflammation. Patients were divided into tertiles of percent calories delivered. The first tertile (n = 52) received 4%−50% of calorie needs, the second tertile (n = 54) received 51%−68% of calorie needs, and the third tertile (n = 48) received 69%−114% of calorie needs. Patients who received &gt;100% of calorie needs were typically those who received propofol for sedation, which contributes an additional 1.l kcal/mL propofol. There was no significant difference in change in PAB among the 3 tertiles of percent calories delivered: <italic>F</italic>(2, 151) = 1.005, <italic>P</italic> = .37. A 1-way ANOVA was also conducted based on tertiles of percent protein delivered. The first tertile (n = 54) received 4%−48% of protein needs, the second tertile (n = 52) received 49%−65% of protein needs, and the third teritle (n = 48) received 66%−143% of protein needs. No significant differences were found across groups: <italic>F</italic>(2, 151) = 1.906, <italic>P</italic> = .15.</p>
<p>CRP was then entered into the analysis to account for the presence or absence of inflammation. Change in CRP was negatively correlated with change in PAB (<italic>r</italic> = -0.544, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Two multiple linear regression models were fit to assess the ability of either percent calories delivered or percent protein delivered to predict changes in PAB while adjusting for CRP. Only change in CRP was able to significantly predict change in PAB levels, explaining 29.6% of the variance (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.296) in change in PAB consistently, adjusting for either percent calories delivered (<italic>B</italic> = -0.051, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) or percent protein delivered (<italic>B</italic> = -0.051, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<p>In the subgroup analysis of 62 patients with repeated measures of PAB and CRP, data were analyzed over 3 consecutive measures of PAB to detect differences in the pattern of change in PAB over tertiles of percent calories and percent protein delivered while controlling for change in CRP. CRP levels were measured at the same time as at least 2 of the 3 PAB measures. There was a significant difference in pattern of change in PAB based on tertiles of percent calories delivered (<italic>P</italic> = .017) and in a separate model with tertiles of percent protein delivered (<italic>P</italic> = .046) based on multivariate tests from ANCOVA. The lowest tertile of both percent calories and percent protein delivered had the largest increase in PAB over time. A summary of the univariate change in PAB, CRP, percent calories delivered, percent protein delivered, and measures of PAB from general linear models adjusted for change in CRP is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0148607111413896">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0148607111413896">4</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0148607111413896" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Median Prealbumin, C-Reactive Protein, and Percent Calories Delivered at 3 Time Points in 62 Enterally Fed Adults With Repeated Measures of Prealbumin and C-Reactive Protein<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn15-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0148607111413896" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111413896-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">kcal Tertile</th>
<th align="center">Measure</th>
<th align="center">Time 1</th>
<th align="center">Time 2</th>
<th align="center">Time 3</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 (n = 19)</td>
<td>PAB</td>
<td>12.0 (7.0, 14.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>12.0 (11.0, 14.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>17.0 (13.0, 24.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CRP</td>
<td>87.3 (38.5, 153.6)</td>
<td>57.8 (17.9, 98.2)</td>
<td>38.9 (13.0, 71.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adjusted PAB</td>
<td>11.1 ± 1.1</td>
<td>13.6 ± 1.2</td>
<td>18.5 ± 1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%kcal</td>
<td>15.0 (2.5, 45.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
<td>24.0 (9.0, 47.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>44.0 (34.0, 60.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%Pro</td>
<td>7.0 (0.5, 27.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
<td>27.0 (10.0, 47.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>43.0 (36.0, 60.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Days</td>
<td>0.9 ± 1.5<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn16-0148607111413896">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.3 ± 1.3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn17-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.4 ± 0.9<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn17-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 (n = 25)</td>
<td>PAB</td>
<td>9.0 (8.0, 13.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>11.0 (9.5, 16.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
<td>12.0 (11.0, 17.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CRP</td>
<td>82.8 (67.5, 152.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>58.1 (31.8, 121.1)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>60.2 (25.6, 100.2)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adjusted PAB</td>
<td>10.4 ± 1.0</td>
<td>12.2 ± 1.1</td>
<td>12.7 ± 1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%kcal</td>
<td>27.5 (12.0, 60.3)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>53.0 (39.5, 73.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>56.0 (48.5, 78.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%Pro</td>
<td>24.0 (3.3, 54.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>54.0 (39.0, 72.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>56.0 (44.5, 77.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Days</td>
<td>2.2 ± 3.0</td>
<td>3.8 ± 1.1</td>
<td>3.6 ± 1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 (n = 28)</td>
<td>PAB</td>
<td>12.5 (6.8, 16.0)</td>
<td>14.0 (9.8, 16.0)</td>
<td>14.0 (10.8, 18.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CRP</td>
<td>63.3 (27.0, 140.9)</td>
<td>46.2 (13.7, 138.4)</td>
<td>71.1 (22.4, 128.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adjusted PAB</td>
<td>12.0 ± 1.1</td>
<td>13.5 ± 1.3</td>
<td>15.2 ± 1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%kcal</td>
<td>29.5 (10.3, 76.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>71.0 (44.5, 87.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
<td>86.0 (78.0, 92.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%Pro</td>
<td>28.0 (11.3, 67.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>70.0 (43.5, 88.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
<td>83.0 (71.0, 90.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Days</td>
<td>2.3 ± 3.1</td>
<td>3.6 ± 1.3</td>
<td>3.2 ± 0.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn14-0148607111413896">
<p>Values with the same superscript letters (<sup>xy</sup>) do not differ significantly from one another; Wilcoxon signed rank tests at Bonferroni adjusted ∝ &lt;0.017. Adjusted PAB, prealbumin adjusted for change in CRP, mg/dL, presented as mean ± standard error, from analysis of covariance; CRP, C-reactive protein, mg/L, presented as median (interquartile range [IQR]); %kcal, median (IQR) calories delivered as a percent of prescribed (value at time 1 represents median percent calories delivered between EN initiation and time 1); PAB, prealbumin, mg/dL, presented as median (IQR); %Pro, median (IQR) protein delivered as a percent of prescribed (value at time 1 represents median percent protein delivered between EN initiation and time 1).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn15-0148607111413896">
<label>a</label>
<p>Subjects had at least 3 consecutive measures of prealbumin and 2 measures of C-reactive protein. Labs were drawn within 24 hours of enteral nutrition (EN) initiation and every Tuesday and Friday.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn16-0148607111413896">
<label>b</label>
<p>Mean number of days from EN initiation to prealbumin time 1; mean ± SD.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn17-0148607111413896">
<label>c</label>
<p>Mean number of days between prealbumin draws; mean ± SD.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0148607111413896" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Median Prealbumin, C-Reactive Protein, and Percent Protein Delivered at 3 Time Points in 62 Enterally Fed Adults With Repeated Measures of Prealbumin and C-Reactive Protein<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn19-0148607111413896">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0148607111413896" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111413896-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Protein Tertile</th>
<th align="center">Measure</th>
<th align="center">Time 1</th>
<th align="center">Time 1</th>
<th align="center">Time 1</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 (n = 20)</td>
<td>PAB</td>
<td>11.5 (7.0, 13.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>12.0 (10.3, 13.8)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>15.0 (11.0, 23.8)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CRP</td>
<td>124.8 (38.0, 153.1)</td>
<td>61.7 (18.6, 105.4)</td>
<td>40.4 (13.3, 83.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adjusted PAB</td>
<td>10.4 ± 1.1</td>
<td>12.6 ± 1.2</td>
<td>17.0 ± 1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%kcal</td>
<td>11.0 (2.5, 45.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
<td>26.0 (9.8, 42.8)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>46.0 (35.0, 52.8)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%Pro</td>
<td>5.0, (0.0, 27.5)</td>
<td>22.0 (10.0, 43.8)</td>
<td>42.0 (28.5, 53.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Days</td>
<td>0.8 ± 1.4<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn20-0148607111413896">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.1 ± 1.3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn21-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.5 ± 0.9<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn21-0148607111413896">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 (n = 21)</td>
<td>PAB</td>
<td>13.0 (8.0, 15.5)</td>
<td>13.0 (11.0, 16.0)</td>
<td>14.0 (11.0, 17.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CRP</td>
<td>75.0 (62.9, 130.9)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>50.4 (24.9, 112.1)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>47.3 (22.7, 82.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adjusted PAB</td>
<td>12.1 ± 1.1</td>
<td>13.9 ± 1.2</td>
<td>14.0 ± 1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%kcal</td>
<td>31.0 (15.0, 72.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>53.0 (39.5, 74.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>55.0 (44.5, 75.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%Pro</td>
<td>25.0 (15.0, 55.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>51.0 (39.0, 74.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>55.0 (44.5, 75.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">xy</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Days</td>
<td>2.9 ± 3.7</td>
<td>4.1 ± 0.9</td>
<td>3.6 ± 1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 (n = 21)</td>
<td>PAB</td>
<td>10.0 (6.5, 14.5)</td>
<td>11.0 (9.0, 11.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>14.0 (10.5, 19.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CRP</td>
<td>80.9 (44.1, 142.9)</td>
<td>56.3 (20.0, 139.2)</td>
<td>85.7 (30.5, 123.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adjusted PAB</td>
<td>10.7 ± 1.1</td>
<td>12.6 ± 1.2</td>
<td>14.7 ± 1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%kcal</td>
<td>27.0 (5.0, 55.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>70.0 (47.5, 81.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>83.0 (78.0, 92.0)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">z</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>%Pro</td>
<td>26.0 (5.5, 65.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">x</xref></sup></td>
<td>65.0 (46.0, 89.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">y</xref></sup></td>
<td>83.0 (75.5, 92.5)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0148607111413896">z</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Days</td>
<td>1.8 ± 2.1</td>
<td>3.6 ± 1.3</td>
<td>3.1 ± 0.7</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn18-0148607111413896">
<p>Values with the same superscript letters (<sup>xyz</sup>) do not differ significantly from one another; Wilcoxon signed rank tests at Bonferroni adjusted ∝ &lt;0.017. Adjusted PAB, prealbumin adjusted for change in CRP, mg/dL, presented as mean ± standard error, from analysis of covariance; CRP, C-reactive protein, mg/L, presented as median (interquartile range [IQR]); %kcal, median (IQR) calories delivered as a percent of prescribed (value at time 1 represents median percent calories delivered between EN initiation and time 1); PAB, prealbumin, mg/dL, presented as median (IQR); %Pro, median (IQR) protein delivered as a percent of prescribed (value at time 1 represents median percent protein delivered between EN initiation and time 1).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn19-0148607111413896">
<label>a</label>
<p>Subjects had at least 3 consecutive measures of prealbumin and 2 measures of C-reactive protein. Labs were drawn within 24 hours of enteral nutrition (EN) initiation and every Tuesday and Friday.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn20-0148607111413896">
<label>b</label>
<p>Mean number of days from EN initiation to prealbumin time 1; mean ± SD.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn21-0148607111413896">
<label>c</label>
<p>Mean number of days between prealbumin draws; mean ± SD.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Independent samples <italic>t</italic> tests were used to determine whether there was a difference in the change in PAB in patients on steroids (n = 55) vs those not on steroids (n = 95). There was a significantly greater increase in PAB in patients who were on steroids (7.04 ± 8.68 mg/dL) vs those who were not (0.16 ± 9.03 mg/dL); <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001. Patients on steroids had a decreasing CRP (−48.8 ± 127.7 mg/L), whereas those not on steroids had little to no change in CRP (2.67 ± 64.77 mg/L); <italic>P</italic> = .03. <italic>t</italic> tests were also used to compare changes in PAB between patients with (n = 89) and without (n = 40) confirmed infections, as well as between patients above (n = 91) and below age 60 (n = 63). There were no significant differences in either analysis.</p>
<p>Of 11 patients included in the analysis who had a renal diagnosis, 6 received hemodialysis. Those with a renal diagnosis had a decrease in PAB (−2.09 ± 8.02 mg/dL), whereas those with no renal diagnosis had an increase in PAB (2.91 ± 9.41 mg/dL); <italic>P</italic> = .02. There was no significant difference in change in CRP between those with or without a renal diagnosis (<italic>P</italic> = .150).</p>
<p>Although most patients were overweight or obese, there was no difference in either baseline CRP (<italic>P</italic> = .996) or change in CRP (<italic>P</italic> = .173) among obese vs nonobese patients. This may be attributed to the presence of other inflammatory conditions having a greater impact than obesity on CRP values.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0148607111413896" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The results of this study differed from many earlier studies, most likely because much of the earlier research did not assess inflammation. Two earlier studies by Tuten et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0148607111413896">19</xref></sup> and Sawicky et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0148607111413896">20</xref></sup> reported a significant increase in PAB over the course of 7 days of EN or PN. Patients received a calorie intake of 100%−140% of estimated needs in the study by Tuten et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0148607111413896">19</xref></sup> and 70% of patients received &gt;100% of estimated calorie needs in the study by Sawicky et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0148607111413896">20</xref></sup> However, neither measured inflammatory markers, so it was unclear whether the increased PAB was related to adequate calorie delivery or a reduction in inflammation. In a retrospective study by Boosalis et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0148607111413896">21</xref></sup> 27 head-injured patients who were well nourished prior to injury had elevated CRP levels that trended downward throughout the 16-day study period. Prealbumin concentrations improved during the 16-day period but lagged several days behind achievement of goal calorie and protein intake.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0148607111413896">21</xref></sup></p>
<p>In a randomized controlled trial by Bauer et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0148607111413896">22</xref></sup> there was a significantly greater increase in PAB in the treatment group, who received 25 kcal/kg, vs the control group, who received 15 kcal/kg (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), after 7 days of EN and PN support. CRP levels decreased throughout the study, but the decreases were not significantly different between groups.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0148607111413896">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>Researchers have suggested that with the delivery of adequate calories and protein, low PAB levels should increase during the course of nutrition support.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0148607111413896">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0148607111413896">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0148607111413896">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0148607111413896">24</xref></sup> However, patients receiving EN often do not receive 100% of their calorie and protein needs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111413896">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0148607111413896">10</xref></sup> In the current study, the delivery of 60% of estimated needs for calories and protein was selected as the cutoff to determine adequate delivery based on evidence that the delivery of 60%−70% of calorie and protein needs can improve outcomes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0148607111413896">29</xref></sup></p>
<p>Most patients in the current study did not achieve “adequate” calorie or protein intake. Only 70 (45.5%) patients achieved an intake of ≥60% of calorie needs, and 65 (42.2%) achieved ≥60% of protein needs. Patients received an average of 57.3% ± 0.2% and 56.1% ± 0.2% of their calorie and protein needs, respectively, which is comparable to previous research reporting the delivery of energy requirements ranging from 52%−75%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111413896">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0148607111413896">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0148607111413896">8</xref></sup> Reasons for EN cessation in the current study were also similar to other studies, with tests and procedures among the top contributors for time that EN was held.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111413896">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0148607111413896">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0148607111413896">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>The results of the current study contradicted the hypothesis that PAB is a good marker for monitoring the adequacy of nutrition support. There was no correlation between change in PAB levels and percent of calorie or protein needs delivered. The only value that correlated significantly to change in PAB was change in CRP. Although there was a significant increase in median PAB levels between the first and last PAB measure, there were no significant differences in change in PAB based on adequacy of intake (≥60% vs &lt;60%) of calories or protein or when the sample was split into tertiles of percent calories or protein delivered. This suggests that other factors may have been driving the increase in PAB over time.</p>
<p>To explore this further, 2 multiple linear regression models were fit to assess the ability of either percent calories delivered or percent protein delivered to predict changes in PAB, adjusting for change in CRP. Change in CRP explained 29.6% of the variance in change in PAB consistently, adjusting for either percent calories delivered (<italic>B</italic> = -0.051, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) or percent protein delivered (<italic>B</italic> = -0.051, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). In a subgroup analysis of 62 patients with repeated measures of PAB and CRP, there was a significant difference in the pattern of change in PAB by tertiles of percent calories delivered (<italic>P</italic> = .017) and percent protein delivered (<italic>P</italic> = .046). Prealbumin increased significantly between measures 1 and 3 only in the bottom 2 tertiles for calorie delivery and only the lowest tertile for protein delivery. CRP, however, did not change significantly in any of the groups that had increasing PAB between measures 1 and 3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0148607111413896">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0148607111413896">4</xref>). The lack of significance for change in CRP may be due to the high level of variability in this measure and the small subgroup sample size. Change in CRP was the only variable that was able to significantly predict changes in PAB levels, suggesting that a change in inflammatory status, rather than nutrient intake, was responsible for the increases seen in PAB levels.</p>
<p>These results were similar to that of a study in older adult men receiving oral nutrition. Dennis et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0148607111413896">23</xref></sup> found that inflammation had a stronger effect on changes in PAB than did calorie or protein intake. In this study, changes in CRP accounted for 41% of the variance in change in PAB (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and protein intake accounted for only 6% of the variance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0148607111413896">23</xref></sup> Dennis et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0148607111413896">23</xref></sup> suggested that PAB was strongly influenced by inflammation and should not be used in place of a more in-depth nutrition assessment.</p>
<p>The greater increase in PAB in patients who were on steroids vs those who were not can likely be attributed to the anti-inflammatory effects of steroids. Patients on steroids also had a significantly greater decrease in change in CRP.</p>
<p>The limitations of this study should be considered when interpreting the results and making conclusions. Because data were collected in all adult care units, many clinicians were involved in data collection. With multiple clinicians collecting data, there were some inconsistencies that occasionally resulted in missing data, most of which was demographic information. A thorough recheck of the data was conducted before the data were analyzed to attempt to fill in any missing information.</p>
<p>Fewer metabolic cart studies were completed than anticipated, and a wide range of calorie and protein prescriptions was used to individualize patients’ nutrient needs. Indirect calorimetry is regarded as the gold standard for determining calorie needs in the clinical setting but cannot be completed in certain patients (ie, those receiving supplemental oxygen, patients with an FiO<sub>2</sub> ≥60%, or patients with chest tubes).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0148607111413896">25</xref></sup> Other factors that may have impeded the number of metabolic cart studies obtained include the time needed to warm up, calibrate, and run the test; having only 1 cart available for use among 3 ICUs; and the concern for patient agitation influencing the results of the study.</p>
<p>In attempting to capture a larger population, the researchers included patients with renal diagnoses. Renal failure and dialysis affect PAB levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111413896">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111413896">14</xref></sup> and may have affected the results of this study. Dialysis was likely a contributing factor to the differences in change in PAB in those with and without a renal diagnosis. However, only 7.6% of the study population had a documented renal diagnosis, with 3.9% receiving hemodialysis.</p>
<p>Another consideration is that the EN protocol required CRP to be measured only when PAB levels were low, meaning that potentially useful data may be missing. In addition, the researchers attempted to include patients from a variety of hospital units, but most of the patients who were started on EN during the study period were critically ill and spent at least some of their time in an ICU. Therefore, study results may be limited to similar populations. More research is needed to determine whether PAB may be useful in assessing adequate calorie and protein delivery among stable patients with low levels of inflammation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0148607111413896" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Data from this retrospective study support that PAB may not be an accurate marker for the adequacy of nutrition support in critically ill patients in the presence of inflammation. Pearson’s correlation coefficients, <italic>t</italic> test analysis, ANOVA, and multiple linear regression tests provided evidence that changes in PAB do not reflect the delivery of adequate calories and protein in the presence of an inflammatory condition. Changes in PAB correlated only with changes in inflammatory status, as measured by CRP. Others have suggested that serum proteins, including PAB, may be better used as markers for severity of disease or injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111413896">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0148607111413896">18</xref></sup> Until a more reliable marker for monitoring the adequacy of nutrition support can be identified, clinicians should use their skills in subjective global assessment and clinical judgment to determine whether a nutrition prescription should be adjusted to meet the needs of patients on nutrition support.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Financial disclosure: none declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0148607111413896">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kubrak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Malnutrition in acute care patients: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs Stud</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1036</fpage>-<lpage>1054</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0148607111413896">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tessier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Still hungry in hospital: identifying malnutrition in acute hospital admissions</article-title>. <source>Q J Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0148607111413896">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rocandio Pablo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arroyo Izaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ansotegui Alday</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of nutritional status on hospital admission: nutritional scores</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>824</fpage>-<lpage>831</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0148607111413896">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elpern</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stutz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gurka</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skipper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes associated with enteral tube feedings in a medical intensive care unit</article-title>. <source>Am J Crit Care</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>227</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0148607111413896">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Binnekade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tepaske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruynzeel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathus-Vliegen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Hann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Daily enteral feeding practice on the ICU: attainment of goals and interfering factors</article-title>. <source>Crit Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>R218</fpage>-<lpage>R225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0148607111413896">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Jonghe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Appere-De-Vechi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A prospective survey of nutritional support practices in intensive care unit patients: what is prescribed? What is delivered?</article-title> <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0148607111413896">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Batson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A study of problems associated with the delivery of enteral feed in critically ill patients in five ICUs in the UK</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0148607111413896">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClave</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Enteral tube feeding in the intensive care unit: factors impeding adequate delivery</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1252</fpage>-<lpage>1256</lpage>.</citation>
</ref> <ref id="bibr9-0148607111413896">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Leary-Kelley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puntillo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stotts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nutritional adequacy in patients receiving mechanical ventilation who are enterally fed</article-title>. <source>Am J Crit Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0148607111413896">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Improving Enteral Nutrition Delivery: Assessing Calorie Recommendations</source> [<comment>master’s thesis</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rush University</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0148607111413896">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerrior</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pomp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Use of retinol-binding protein and prealbumin as indicators of the response to nutrition therapy</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>684</fpage>-<lpage>687</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0148607111413896">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Principles of Nutritional Assessment</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0148607111413896">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Nutritional Assessment</source>. <edition>4th ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0148607111413896">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Banh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Serum proteins as markers of nutrition: what are we treating?</article-title> <source>Practical Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0148607111413896">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gleeson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cripps</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>C-reactive protein: A critical review</article-title>. <source>Pathology</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0148607111413896">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vuagnat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Safar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fagon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis and follow-up of infections in intensive care patients: value of C-reactive protein compared with other clinical and biological markers</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>-<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0148607111413896">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation as the key interface of the medical and nutrition universes: a proactive examination of the future of clinical nutrition and medicine</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>463</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0148607111413896">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hepatic proteins and nutrition assessment</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>1258</fpage>-<lpage>1264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0148607111413896">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tuten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wogt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dasse</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leider</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Utilization of prealbumin as a nutritional parameter</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>-<lpage>711</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0148607111413896">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sawicky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nippo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adequate energy intake and improved prealbumin concentration as indicators of the response to total parenteral nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Amer Diet Assoc</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1266</fpage>-<lpage>1268</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0148607111413896">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boosalis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sevine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship of visceral proteins to nutritional status in chronic and acute stress</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>-<lpage>747</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0148607111413896">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nace</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raffy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaconnet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Parenteral with enteral nutrition in the critically ill</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>893</fpage>-<lpage>900</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0148607111413896">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberson</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Changes in prealbumin, nutrient intake, and systemic inflammation in elderly recuperative care patients</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1270</fpage>-<lpage>1275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0148607111413896">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bourry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caldani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of nutritional proteins during the parenteral nutrition of cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Lab Sci</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>-<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0148607111413896">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Indirect calorimetry: A practical guide for clinicians</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0148607111413896">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClave</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McClain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snider</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Should indirect calorimetry be used as part of nutritional assessment?</article-title> <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0148607111413896">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karkeck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adjusted body weight for obesity</article-title>. <source>American Dietetic Association Renal Practice Group Newsletter</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0148607111413896">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gabay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute-phase proteins and other systemic responses to inflammation</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>340</volume>:<fpage>448</fpage>-<lpage>454</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0148607111413896">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kattelmann</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hise</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Compher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary evidence for a medical nutrition therapy protocol: enteral feedings for critically ill patients</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1226</fpage>-<lpage>1241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>