<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RAC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprac</journal-id>
<journal-title>Race &amp; Class</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0306-3968</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3125</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0306396811425994</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0306396811425994</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mary Dines: 1927–2011</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>Jenny</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>53</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>3</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Institute of Race Relations</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institute of Race Relations</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>January–March 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>We have lost one of our greatest fighters for racial justice and human rights, and, because she was so self-effacing, because she lacked personal ambition, because she refused the blandishments of power, not one national newspaper in the UK has seen fit to publish an obituary of one of the most remarkable women of her generation.</p>
<p>Apocryphal stories about Mary abound. There was the time when would-be immigrants from the Indian subcontinent in the late 1960s and early 1970s arrived at Heathrow with just two words of English; ‘Mummy Dines to airport information’ would echo over the tannoy. There was the time Mary found herself on the same plane as Enoch Powell. She marched down the aisle to challenge and abuse him, as he sat helplessly pinned in by his seatbelt. The time she impersonated a Home Office official and phoned an overseas embassy to have deportees returned to the UK immediately because of a supposed oversight. And they were. The time when, because of the Dublin Treaty, families with young babies were being constantly returned and re-returned on the cross-Channel ferry to France. Mary took a baby’s soiled nappies and left them on the doorstep of the home secretary’s house. The time she and her daughter decided to renounce British citizenship and take Pakistani citizenship instead, in protest at British racism. The stories are endless and, in fact, Mary did most of the telling of them, not because of any ego (she had none), but because of her keen sense of fun. After the telling of each one of her direct-action-style pranks, she would throw back her head and give a loud, raucous, throaty laugh.</p>
<p>Despite Mary being both a natural anti-racist and committed internationalist, there was something about the way she fought that was quintessentially English. She was nothing if not direct, practical. She did not have time for long ideological debates (although she was always on the Left and served as a Labour councillor in Haringey, until she left the party in disgust after it passed the shameful Immigration Act to keep out British passport-holding Kenyan Asians in 1968). She wanted to get things done, laws changed, people assisted, rights established. And her devotion to achieving these aims was unrivalled.</p>
<p>Employed by the London Council for Social Service during the 1960s, she became a member of the pressure group Campaign Against Racial Discrimination (CARD). As CARD began to break up, she, along with Vishnu Sharma (of the Indian Workers’ Association) and Oxford don Michael Dummett, decided, in the late 1960s, that there was a need for an organisation to provide welfare support and immigration advice to newly arriving communities from the ‘new Commonwealth’, who were being totally neglected by social and welfare services and discriminated against at every turn. They established the Joint Council for the Welfare of Immigrants (JCWI), an affiliation of a host of groups, including the Pakistani Welfare Associations, the Indian Workers’ Associations and the West Indian Standing Conference. The JCWI, where Mary and Vishnu were to work, sent someone to Heathrow to help those refused entry. It was first based at Toynbee Hall in Tower Hamlets, later in Pentonville Road in King’s Cross, and is currently still hard at work in Old Street. (In 1972, when the Institute of Race Relations, which publishes this journal, had undergone a palace revolution, lost all its funding and was about to be thrown onto the streets, it was Mary who negotiated with a large national charity to sublet us office and warehouse space that could take the organisation and its then huge library.)</p>
<p>There were precisely two solicitors and one barrister in the whole country, at the time, who had any knowledge of immigration law. All the rest of the cases were dealt with by JCWI – its hard-pressed staff working all hours and days from downtrodden, dingy offices. It was Mary and her colleagues who not only handled thousands of cases, but campaigned on issues in the courts and the media, persuading lawyers, in the process, that there was indeed a need to understand immigration law and even training them in representation and appeals. Mary was there behind the scenes during every crisis, whether it was the resettlement of thousands of Asians expelled from Uganda by Amin in 1972 or the defence of Italian worker/organiser Franco Caprino, one of the first to be threatened with deportation under the ‘not conducive to the public good’ clause of the 1971 Immigration Act.</p>
<p>From 1976–1979, she was general secretary of the international charity War on Want, where her concerns about injustice broadened from individual plights to group rights. Apart from the courageous stand she took in defending the organisation against the Right and the Charity Commissioners, when staff and board members were under attack for making a donation to the Grunwick strike fund, she is remembered for the way she took War on Want in a new political direction: to address the structures that perpetuated poverty and oppression worldwide. It was at War on Want that Mary became involved in supporting the liberation movement of the people of Eritrea, a passion of hers for the rest of her life. She was to visit the country many times, and wrote and campaigned in the UK for its freedom. In 1976, using her connections with larger charities such as Oxfam, Christian Aid and Cafod, she helped set up the Eritrean Relief Association and, in the late 1980s, helped found and house the Eritrean Community in the UK – both organisations still flourishing today.</p>
<p>Mary’s support for peoples seeking self-determination extended when, with the support of David Astor (publisher and philanthropist), she set up Rights and Justice after leaving War on Want. She then took on a whole host of causes close to her heart, including those of the oppressed Tamils of Sri Lanka and the Kurds. In 1986, Mary helped to set up the Kurdish Workers’ Association and, later, an All-Party Parliamentary Kurdistan Group. Asylum Aid was established in 1990 as a casework organisation to complement the work of Rights and Justice.</p>
<p>What an amazing legacy of organisations and campaigns for one person to leave us! But this was an exceptional woman. She hated those in power who abused their positions, she was often irked by others in her fields of work, such as lawyers or NGOs whom she felt did not pull their full weight for their clients. But, for lame dogs (or, literally, cats), she had all the time and all the gentleness in the world. The last three pieces of music played at Mary’s funeral on 29 June 2011 summed her up: she was indeed a mixture of ‘The Pastoral’, ‘The Red Flag’ and ‘We Shall Overcome’.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>JENNY BOURNE</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>