<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">specl</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1468-7984</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2919</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468798411417377</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1468798411417377</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ants, apples and the ABCs: The use of commercial phonics programmes in prior-to-school children’s services</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>Stacey</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1468798411417377"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1468798411417377">Macquarie University, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Torr</surname><given-names>Jane</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1468798411417377">Macquarie University, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cologon</surname><given-names>Kathy</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1468798411417377">Macquarie University, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1468798411417377">Stacey Campbell, Balaclava Road, Macquarie University, North Ryde 2109, NSW, Australia Email: <email>stacey.campbell@mq.edu.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>367</fpage>
<lpage>388</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Commercial phonics programmes (e.g. Jolly Phonics and Letterland) are becoming widely used in the early years of school. These programmes claim to use a systematic explicit approach, considered as the preferred method of phonics instruction for teaching alphabetic code-breaking skills in Australia and the UK in the first years of school (Department of Education, Science and Training, 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1468798411417377">Rose, 2006</xref>). However, little is known about the extent to which they are being used in prior-to-school settings, and the reasons behind decisions to use them. This study surveyed 283 early childhood staff in Sydney, Australia and found that commercial phonics programmes were being used in 36% of the early childhood settings surveyed. Staff with early childhood university qualifications and staff working in not-for-profit service types were less likely to use a commercial phonics programme than staff without university qualifications and staff working in for-profit services. Staff with less than 10 years’ experience were also more likely to use a commercial phonics programme. The rationale behind decisions determining whether or not staff used the programmes ranged from pragmatic reasons, such as parent pressure or higher management decisions, to pedagogical reasons, such as teacher beliefs about how children learn to read and write. The practices staff engage in to teach phonics are explored.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>early childhood</kwd>
<kwd>emergent literacy</kwd>
<kwd>phonics programmes</kwd>
<kwd>literacy development</kwd>
<kwd>teacher beliefs</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1468798411417377" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The role of explicit phonics instruction in teaching reading is a subject ofmuch debate in the media and in the research literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1468798411417377">Cambourne, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1468798411417377">Department of Education, Science and Training, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1468798411417377">Devine, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1468798411417377">Dombey, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1468798411417377">Ferrari, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1468798411417377">Goouch and Lambirth, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1468798411417377">Savage, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1468798411417377">Soler and Openshaw, 2007</xref>). Although exact numbers are not available, itappears that commercial phonics programmes that follow a systematic explicit approach to teaching phonics are being widely used in the early years of school. Anecdotal evidence suggests that such programmes are also being used in prior-to-school settings, with children aged five years and younger.</p>
<p>While many commercial phonics programmes make strong claims for theirefficacy in fostering young children’s literacy development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1468798411417377">Letterland International, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1468798411417377">Lloyd, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1468798411417377">Manson and Wendon, 2007</xref>), there is little empirical evidence to support these claims, especially for children in the prior-to-school years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1468798411417377">Soler and Openshaw, 2007</xref>). Furthermore, the methods of instruction recommended by some commercial phonics programmes do not necessarily resonate with practices that are regarded as developmentally appropriate for fostering young children’s language and literacy development. Explicit phonics instruction, conducted in a style whereby young children aged three to five years are grouped together to recite, chant and review phonemes and graphemes (which is the method employed by many commercial phonics programmes) is questionable in terms of pedagogical appropriateness for preschoolers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1468798411417377">Neuman and Roskos, 2005</xref>). This specific method of teaching phonics, which is direct, adult initiated and programmed for large-group learning, challenges the pedagogical practices of many early childhood teachers, who subscribe to an emergent literacy learning perspective. According to this perspective, literacy-rich play is important as it enables children to make connections with print through meaningful experiences such as sharing books, dramatic play, songs, nursery rhymes and language play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1468798411417377">Morrow and Tracey, 1997</xref>). In this way, speaking, listening, reading and writing are integrated and supported through social contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1468798411417377">Beecher and Arthur, 2001</xref>). According to this perspective, children learn phonics through play, exploration and interaction with others, rather than through explicit instruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468798411417377">Snow, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Anecdotal reports indicate that many early childhood staff are currently using more explicit methods of teaching literacy to children under five, including commercial phonics programmes such as Letterland, Jolly Phonics and Ants inthe Apple. Little is known about how widely commercial phonics programmes are being used by staff in prior-to-school settings, including preschool (which usually operates during school semesters with shorter hours) and long-day care (which generally operates year round, 10 hours per day), nor the reasons for their adoption by early childhood staff. This study aims to explore to what extent, and why, commercial phonics programmes are being used with children aged five years and younger in early childhood services.</p>
<p>The production of commercial phonics programmes is a growing industry, and the adoption of commercial programmes is on the rise, not only in the USAbut also in English-speaking countries worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1468798411417377">Reeves, 2010</xref>). Furthermore, there are considerable commercial interests involved in producing commercial programmes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1468798411417377">Goouch, 2007</xref>). Such programmes typically include a range of products, including flash cards, books, videos and DVDs, teacher instruction and parent manuals, newsletters, magazines and websites. Many phonics programmes are heavily promoted internationally. The cost of commercial phonics programmes ranges from AU$200 to AU$2,000, depending on what programme components are purchased. Some components are recommended as essential while others are optional. These programmes often promise a complete and easy way to develop the skills necessary to be able to read, for example the Letterland website claims that ‘we publish everything you need to help your child become a happy, confident and successful reader’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1468798411417377">Letterland International, 2009</xref>). Jolly Phonics products state that the programme ‘teaches the letter sounds in an enjoyable, multisensory way, and enables children to use them to read and write words’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1468798411417377">Jolly Learning, 2005</xref>). In some countries, such as the USA, teachers are under pressure to comply witha range of mandates in preparing children to meet educational standards, and as a consequence commercially produced programmes have been developed that claim to meet both state and federal educational standards and that also claim to be based on scientific research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468798411417377">Fang Fu and Lamme, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Commercial phonics programmes are generally based on a systematic explicit approach to phonics instruction, typically instructing children in how to make grapheme-phoneme correspondences. Some commercial phonics programmes may also include explicit instruction in phonemic awareness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468798411417377">Ehri and Nunes, 2002</xref>). Commercial phonics programmes cover around 90 phonics rules, whereas children need to understand over 500 spelling and sound relationships in order to become proficient readers by late elementary school level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1468798411417377">Snow and Juel, 2005</xref>). Essentially, this suggests that some commercial phonics programmes are not intended by their producers to be a total solution to teaching children how to read, but may be seen as a resource that can be integrated into existing reading programmes.</p>
<p>Commercial phonics programmes may also employ a synthetic phonics approach, which is similar to systematic explicit phonics. With synthetic phonics children learn isolated phonemic, phonological and alphabetic skills, rather than learning phonics when engaged in a wider range of activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1468798411417377">Cunningham and Cunningham, 2002</xref>). Children are introduced to individual letters first and are then taught to build on them to form words. When children are introduced to a word they are encouraged to synthesize the sounds represented by letters to produce the word (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1468798411417377">Johnston and Watson, 2005</xref>). The first texts that children encounter through these systems are constructed to restrict the graphemes and phonemes to those previously introduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1468798411417377">Cunningham and Cunningham, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>One of the difficulties faced when attempting to develop a commercial phonics programme is that the English language is complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1468798411417377">Wyse and Goswami, 2008</xref>). It is different from many other alphabetic languages such as German, Finnish, Italian and Spanish, where synthetic phonics instruction is considered effective. This is because these languages use a less complex syllabic structure and there is a one-to-one mapping of phonemes to graphemes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1468798411417377">Seymour, Aro and Erskine, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1468798411417377">Wyse and Goswami, 2008</xref>). The English language, however, is characterized by the phonological complexity of its syllable structure and inconsistent spelling systems. This means that direct instructionhas to incorporate more than instruction at the phoneme-grapheme level(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1468798411417377">Wyse and Goswami, 2008</xref>). Another difficulty is that commercially produced programmes do not always provide substantial professional development, other than the essential and initial training that teachers need to implement the programme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1468798411417377">Wren, 2002</xref>). Furthermore, training in the use of commercial programmes is often conducted by the publishers of the programmes, whose primary interest is in promoting their own programmes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468798411417377">Fang et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Schools often purchase commercial reading programmes in the hope that the product will help resolve student literacy issues; however, the programmes are generally designed to address only one aspect of reading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1468798411417377">Wren, 2002</xref>). They tend to focus on reading sub-skills such as phoneme-grapheme correspondence without addressing all areas of literacy development such as vocabulary, comprehension and discourse structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1468798411417377">Duncan-Owens, 2009</xref>). Furthermore, the effectiveness of commercial reading programmes is difficult to evaluate because programme developers often commission their own research where results have not always been put through a process of peer evaluation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1468798411417377">Duncan-Owens, 2009</xref>). Some commercial programmes, when correctly implemented, have been shown to lead to an increase in reading scores, especially with lower-performing schools in the USA; however, there is no one commercial reading programme that has been shown to be successful with all children and all teachers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1468798411417377">Wren, 2002</xref>). The results from some studies focusing on the use of a commercial phonics programme, in particular the Clackmannanshire study, have been questioned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468798411417377">Ellis, 2007</xref>). Other studies have shown that there were no long-term academic gains by children who had more didactic academically-directed preschool experiences than children who were taught from a more child-initiated curriculum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1468798411417377">Marcon, 2002</xref>). Furthermore, research has suggested that the most effective settings are possibly ones that have a balanced approach between an open framework, free-play opportunities and group work involving direct instruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1468798411417377">Siraj-Blatchford and Sylva, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Research on explicit phonics instruction through the use of commercial phonics programmes has been limited to research with children aged five years and over. Little research has investigated the use of phonics programmes with children under five. The Rose Report in the UK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1468798411417377">Rose, 2006</xref>) claimed that it is appropriate to begin a systematic phonics instruction programme with children aged five and above; however, this claim is difficult to support withevidence as the majority of studies in the Rose Report were carried out with children aged six and older (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1468798411417377">Wyse and Styles, 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1468798411417377">Wyse and Styles (2007)</xref> state that the claim regarding the appropriateness of this type of instruction with five-year-old children is not supported by evidence and is ‘arguably one of the most controversial recommendations of the Rose Report’ (p.37). In response to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1468798411417377">Wyse and Styles (2007)</xref>, it was argued that ‘to be fair they should also point out there is no evidence to show that children under 5 years will not benefit either’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468798411417377">Brooks, 2007</xref>: 170).</p>
<p>The current paper aims to determine the following:
<list id="list1-1468798411417377" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The extent to which commercial phonics programmes are being used in different types of prior-to-school children’s services.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The relationship between the use of commercial phonics programmes and staff qualifications and experience.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The reasons given by early childhood staff for using commercial phonics programmes.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Early childhood staff practices relating to the teaching of phonics in the prior-to-school years.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1468798411417377" sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title>
<sec id="sec3-1468798411417377"><title>Survey design</title>
<p>This study used postal surveys to obtain feedback from early childhood staff working with children aged three to five years in Sydney, Australia. The survey was developed following a review of recent research investigating the beliefs and attitudes of early childhood staff about emergent literacy development. The survey was designed to investigate self-reported early childhood staff practices (e.g. <italic>I use a commercial phonics programme to teach letters and sounds only</italic>) and early childhood staff beliefs (e.g. <italic>One of the ways children learn about letters and sounds is by sharing picture books with adults</italic>) about literacy in early childhood.</p>
<p>The survey included a range of data collection methods to enhance the potential to understand the perspectives and views of the participants. These were as follows.</p>
<p><italic>Likert scale.</italic> There were 24 statements that required participants to respond on a five-point Likert scale ranging from ‘strongly disagree’ to ‘strongly agree’. The statements included general phonics teaching (e.g. <italic>I do much incidental teaching about letters and sounds in the course of everyday activities</italic>), general literacy teaching (e.g. <italic>I don’t teach the alphabet in a structured way, but I do teach letter awareness indirectly, e.g. name card</italic>s) and specific statements related to the use of commercial phonics programmes (e.g. <italic>I follow the commercial phonics program’s suggested sequence of letter introduction</italic>).</p>
<p><italic>Questions requiring short answers.</italic> Two short-answer questions were asked in the survey: one requiring a yes/no response as to whether the participant uses a commercial phonics programme, and one asking participants to give reasons for using or not using one.</p>
<p><italic>Demographic questions.</italic> Demographic data were also collected on the participants’ backgrounds including the type of service in which they worked, theage groups of children with whom they worked, their years of service in the early childhood field and their level of qualifications.</p>
<p><italic>Open-ended section.</italic> An open-ended section was included at the end of the survey. Here participants were invited to share any ideas or comments.</p>
<p><italic>Invitation to participate in an interview.</italic> An additional section invited participants to take part in an interview to discuss their views on phonics instruction and its role in early childhood literacy programmes.</p>
<p>Once a final draft of the survey was completed, the survey was trialed withfour academics who were also practising early childhood teachers with expertise in this area. Following their feedback, further changes were made to the survey, and it was then posted with reply-paid envelopes to a wide range of early childhood centres with varied demographic profiles across the Sydney metropolitan area. Survey responses were anonymous (see Appendix).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1468798411417377" sec-type="subjects"><title>Participants</title>
<p>Of the 900 surveys distributed, 31.4% (<italic>N</italic> = 283) were returned, all of which were usable. Respondents included university-qualified early childhood teachers, early childhood educators who had a diploma or certificate qualification from a government technical and further education college (TAFE) or aprivate vocational education and training college (VET), and staff who had no early childhood qualifications. Survey respondents were employed in for-profit, not-for-profit and school-based preschools, and long-day care centres.</p>
<p>Within Australia, the terminology used to refer to children’s services variesconsiderably from state to state. In New South Wales, where this study was conducted, the following terms are used. The term ‘long-day care centre’ refers to centres that cater to children from six weeks to five years of age. Such centres are open for 48 weeks a year for approximately 10 hours per day. The term ‘preschool’ refers to centres for children aged three to five years, which open during school hours only. The term ‘preparatory class’ or ‘prep’ refers to programmes for three- to five-year-old children thatare attached to either government primary schools or independent schools. Prep services, like preschools, follow the same hours and vacations as the school to which they are attached.</p>
<p>Funding arrangements for children’s services vary across service types. For-profit centres are usually long-day care services that are owned by private operators. Corporate long-day care services are for profit and run by companies listed on the Australian Stock Exchange. Local government- and community-based services are either preschools or long-day care settings. They are not for profit. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1468798411417377">Table 1</xref> shows participants’ qualifications and the type of service in which they were employed.
<table-wrap id="table1-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Participant response rate by qualification and service type</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Qualifications <italic>n</italic> = 283</th>
<th colspan="2">Long-day care<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Preschool<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Prep<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Other<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Total<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Early childhood university qualifications</td>
<td>104</td>
<td>(50)</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>(45)</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>(4)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>(1)</td>
<td>210</td>
<td>(74)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Early childhood TAFE/diploma qualifications</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>(72)</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>(26)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>(2)</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>(22)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>No formal qualifications</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>(100)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>(1)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>(63)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>(25)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>(12)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>(3)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>It can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1468798411417377">Table 1</xref> that 74% (<italic>n</italic> = 210) of respondents were university qualified with a bachelor’s or master’s degree in early childhood, and 22% (<italic>n</italic> = 64) of respondents had a TAFE or VET diploma or advanced diploma in children’s services. There were 3% (<italic>n</italic> = 8) of respondents who hadanother qualification, for example a bachelor’s degree in primary or secondary education. The high proportion of university-qualified early childhood teachers who responded to this survey is possibly due to the fact that the survey was targeted at staff working with three- to five-year-old children, and in New South Wales, regulations require that there be at least one university-qualified early childhood teacher in centres with over 29 children. This teacher commonly works with the three- to five-year-old children.</p>
<p>The majority of respondents were employed in long-day care services. This could be because there are more long-day care services in Australia than preschools or school-based prep settings.</p>
<p>When the proportion of survey respondents working in each service type is compared with the total proportion of different service types operating in New South Wales, it can be seen that the proportion of respondents working in preschools (40%) is greater than the state average (27%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1468798411417377">Baruch and Holtom, 2008</xref>). There were fewer long-day care centres in this study (56%) compared with the total for New South Wales (68%). Responses from staff working in prep settings (4%) are equivalent to the state average (5%). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1468798411417377">Figure 1</xref> depicts a comparison between total service types operating in New South Wales and the proportion of service types represented in this study.
<fig id="fig1-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Survey responses compared to New South Wales services types Source of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1468798411417377">New South Wales Service types data: National Childcare Accreditation Council, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468798411417377">New South Wales Department of Community Services, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1468798411417377">New South Wales Department of Education and Training, 2009</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1468798411417377" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>The results were analysed using Pearson <italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic> (SPSS version 17.5) to determine the extent to which commercial phonics programmes are being used in relation to service types, staff qualifications and staff experience, and the reasons for their use.</p>
<sec id="sec6-1468798411417377"><title>The extent to which commercial phonics programmes are being used</title>
<p>Of the 283 survey responses, 36% (<italic>n</italic> = 103) of staff reported that they currently use a commercial phonics programme (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1468798411417377">Table 2</xref>). This suggests that commercial phonics programmes are currently being used in approximately one third of early childhood settings in metropolitan Sydney.
<table-wrap id="table2-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Use of commercial phonics programmes in different types of early childhood setting</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Service type <italic>n</italic> = 283</th>
<th colspan="2">Yes<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">No<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Long-day care</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>(43)</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>(57)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Preschool</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>(26)</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>(74)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Government school prep</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>(55)</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>(45)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>103</td>
<td>(36)</td>
<td>180</td>
<td>(64)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Of those who responded to the survey, 57% (<italic>n</italic> = 161) reported that they have used a commercial phonics programme at some point either now or in the past.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1468798411417377"><title>Types of early childhood services using commercial phonics programmes</title>
<p>Results showed that significantly more staff employed in long-day care services used a commercial phonics programme compared with those employed inpreschools (<italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic>(4, <italic>n</italic> = 270) = 7.916, <italic>p</italic> = .005) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1468798411417377">Table 2</xref>). As noted above, in Australia there are more long-day care services than preschool or school prep services.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1468798411417377"><title>Ownership of service type currently using commercial phonics programmes</title>
<p>Results indicate that not-for-profit early childhood services are significantlyless likely to use a commercial phonics programme (79%, <italic>n</italic> = 115) than for-profit services (42%, <italic>n</italic> = 42) (<italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic>(6, <italic>n</italic> = 274) = 14.105, <italic>p</italic> = .001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1468798411417377">Table 3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table3-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Ownership of service type and the use of commercial phonics programmes</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Ownership type (<italic>n</italic> = 283)</th>
<th colspan="2">Use CPP<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Do not use CPP<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Not for profit</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>(21)</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>(79)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>For profit</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>(58)</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>(42)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>School based</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>(34)</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>(66)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>(67)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>(33)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>103</td>
<td>(36)</td>
<td>180</td>
<td>(64)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>It should be noted that the majority of respondents to this survey were employed in a not-for-profit service. However, in Australia, the early childhood prior-to-school sector is predominantly for-profit managed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1468798411417377">Brennan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1468798411417377">Wannan, 2006</xref>). There were also more respondents to this survey from preschool-based services even though these make up only 25% of all early childhood services in New South Wales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1468798411417377">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1468798411417377"><title>Staff qualifications and the use of commercial phonics programmes</title>
<p>The results indicate that early childhood staff with university qualifications aresignificantly less likely to use a commercial phonics programme than staffwith a TAFE diploma qualification (<italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic>(4, <italic>n</italic> = 274) = 6.70, <italic>p</italic> = .010) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1468798411417377">Table 4</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table4-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Staff qualifications and the use of commercial phonics programmes</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Early childhood qualification (<italic>n</italic> = 274)</th>
<th colspan="2">Use<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Do not use<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Total<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>University degree</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>(32)</td>
<td>142</td>
<td>(68)</td>
<td>210</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>TAFE/diploma</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>(50)</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>(50)</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Other or none</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>(33)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>(67)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1468798411417377"><title>Teaching experience and the use of commercial phonics programmes</title>
<p>Early childhood staff with less than 10 years’ experience were significantly more likely to use a commercial phonics programme than staff who had over 15 years’ experience (<italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic>(6, <italic>n</italic> = 274) = 14.105, <italic>p</italic> = .001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1468798411417377">Table 5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table5-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Use of commercial phonics programmes by years of teaching experience</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table5.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Years of service (<italic>n</italic> = 274)</th>
<th colspan="2">Yes<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">No<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Total<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>0–9 years</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>(47)</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>(53)</td>
<td>127</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>10–14 years</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>(30)</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>(70)</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>15+ years</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>(24)</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>(76)</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Not indicated</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>(55)</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>(45)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(100)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1468798411417377"><title>Early childhood staff decisions as to why they use a commercial phonics programme</title>
<p>The results indicate that early childhood staff are more likely to use a commercial phonics programme for pragmatic or external reasons (57%, <italic>n</italic> = 73) than for pedagogical or personal reasons (43%, <italic>n</italic> = 56). Some staff provided more than one reason for their decision (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1468798411417377">Table 6</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table6-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>Reasons given as to why staff use a commercial phonics programmes</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table6.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">(<italic>n</italic> = 129)</th>
<th colspan="2">External/pragmatic<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Pedagogical<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Already in use when they started</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>(16)</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>The local school uses it</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>(14)</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Higher management decision</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>(13)</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Recommendation by others</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(7)</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Parent request</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>(5)</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>In-service recommendation</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>(2)</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Total external/pragmatic</bold></td>
<td><bold>73</bold></td>
<td><bold>(57)</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Children’s interest and enjoyment</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>20</td>
<td>(15)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal preference for using a programme</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>15</td>
<td>(12)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Used it previously in another service and liked it</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>11</td>
<td>(9)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Feel that it supports school readiness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>7</td>
<td>(5)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Because the programme is based on research</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>3</td>
<td>(2)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Total pedagogical</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><bold>56</bold></td>
<td><bold>(43)</bold></td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1468798411417377"><title>Early childhood staff practices relating to the teaching of phonics</title>
<p>Results show that 83% (<italic>n</italic> = 230) of early childhood staff reported that theybelieve it is appropriate to teach phonics in the prior-to-school years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1468798411417377">Table 7</xref>). Responses to survey items relating to teaching practices are set out below.
<table-wrap id="table7-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 7.</label><caption><p>Staff practices relating to the teaching of phonics</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table7.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Statement item</th>
<th rowspan="2">Response statement</th>
<th colspan="2">Yes<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">No<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Unsure<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>%</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>I plan and teach with a balance of picture book reading, play-based writing and letter-sound introduction (<italic>n</italic> = 279)</td>
<td>265</td>
<td>(95)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(3)</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>(2)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>I do much incidental teaching about letters and sounds in the course of everyday activities (<italic>n</italic> = 279)</td>
<td>262</td>
<td>(94)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>(5)</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>(1)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>I don’t teach the alphabet in a structured way, but I do letter awareness indirectly, e.g. name cards (<italic>n</italic> = 279)</td>
<td>227</td>
<td>(81)</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>(17)</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>(2)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Children need to have formal pre-reading instruction (<italic>n</italic> = 274)</td>
<td>101</td>
<td>(37)</td>
<td>138</td>
<td>(50)</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>(13)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>I teach the letters of the alphabet on a formal basis, e.g. formal as in a separate group experience (<italic>n</italic> = 270)</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>(35)</td>
<td>165</td>
<td>(61)</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>(4)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>It is not appropriate to teach letters and sounds in my context as they will learn them at school (<italic>n</italic> = 279)</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>(12)</td>
<td>230</td>
<td>(83)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>(5)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The results show that the majority of early childhood staff reported that they teach phonics in a manner that is less structured than the methods typically employed by commercial phonics programmes. The vast majority of staff (95%) reported that they plan and teach phonics with a balance of picture book reading, play-based writing and letter sound introduction, 94% reported that they teach phonics during everyday activities and 81% reported teaching letter awareness indirectly, for example through the use of children’s names on cards (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1468798411417377">Table 7</xref>).</p>
<p>Some early childhood staff reported using methods that are relatively more structured, with 37% agreeing that children need to have formal pre-reading instruction and 35% teaching letters of the alphabet on a formal basis, for example in separate group experiences specifically for this purpose (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1468798411417377">Table 7</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1468798411417377"><title>Early childhood staff who are currently using a commercial phonics programme</title>
<p>In this section we focus solely on the responses of participants who stated that they are using a commercial phonics programme (<italic>n = </italic>103). This section determines how staff use commercial phonics programmes.</p>
<p>The results suggest that although early childhood staff are using a commercial phonics programme, they are adapting programmes in a range of ways that theyfeel are relevant for the service, children and their own beliefs. For example, 74% of staff reported that they only used components they felt were relevant forthe children and 40% reported that they followed the commercial phonicsprogramme’s suggested sequence of letter introduction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table8-1468798411417377">Table 8</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table8-1468798411417377" position="float"><label>Table 8.</label><caption><p>Early childhood staff who are currently using a commercial phonics programme</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table8-1468798411417377" xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-table8.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Statement item</th>
<th rowspan="2">Response statement</th>
<th colspan="2">Yes<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">No<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Unsure<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>(%)</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>(%)</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>(%)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>12b</td>
<td>I have a commercial phonics programme but only use parts of the programme because: I have chosen to use only components I feel are relevant for these children (<italic>n</italic> = 101)</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>(74)</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>(17)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(9)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>I use all the major parts of the commercial phonics programme to teach letters and sounds (<italic>n</italic> = 102)</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>(55)</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>(36)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(9)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>I follow the commercial phonic programme’s suggested sequence of letter introduction (<italic>n</italic> = 102)</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>(40)</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>(44)</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>(15)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>I use a commercial phonics programme to teach letters and sounds only (<italic>n</italic> = 101)</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>(40)</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>(51)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>(9)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>12a</td>
<td>I have a commercial phonics programme but only use parts of the programme because I only have access to parts of the programme (<italic>n</italic> = 86)</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>(17)</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>(47)</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>(36)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1468798411417377"><p>Note: Some of the totals differ from 103 as some of the respondents did not answer all questions.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1468798411417377" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>This study provides evidence to suggest that commercial phonics programmes are currently being used in over a third of prior-to-school settings with children aged three to five years in the Sydney region. Furthermore, the use of these programmes appears to be related to a range of factors including staff qualifications, staff experience, type of setting and funding of setting. Proportionally, long-day care centres are more likely to use commercial phonics programmes than preschools, and for-profit centres are more likely to use such programmes than community-based centres. Staff with TAFE diplomas are more likely than university-qualified teachers to use these programmes. Finally, less experienced staff are more likely to use the programmes than staff with over 15 years’ experience. This latter finding may be due to the fact that university pre-service teacher training has varied over time; however, the implications of this finding are unclear. In summary, this study provides evidence of an emerging profile of where these programmes are most likely to be used: long-day care, for-profit centres with less qualified and less experienced staff.</p>
<p>Given the reservations about the pedagogical appropriateness and value of using commercial phonics programmes with three- to five-year-old children, and the growth of the multinational companies that produce the programmes, it is timely to investigate further the reasons why early childhood staff usethese programmes. The results of this study suggest that educators often use the programmes for pragmatic reasons, such as the fact that they are already in use in their centre or the local primary school. Some staff cited more personal reasons, such as children’s perceived interest and enjoyment and their own preference. Only three educators noted pedagogical reasons, in the form of school-readiness programmes for preschool children. A more detailed understanding of why staff decide to use commercial phonics programmes is important and will be the subject of future research.</p>
<p>The results from this study found that it was more likely for a prior-to-school service that is run for profit to use a commercial phonics programme than a not-for-profit service. In Australia, over three-quarters of long-day care centres are run as for-profit services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1468798411417377">Meagher, 2007</xref>). Such centres may offer a readily ‘visible’ commercially produced literacy programme for potential and existing parents, as well as regarding this as a beneficial programme for less qualified and experienced staff. Many for-profit services are part of larger corporate organizations whose key drivers are to generate profit and minimize costs of staffing, through providing standardized programmes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1468798411417377">Wannan, 2006</xref>). By implementing a homogenous literacy programme, through the useof a commercial phonics programme across all settings, they provide a ‘uniform’ one-fits-all approach, thus demonstrating or creating a sense of consistency of all the staff in their service, regardless of qualification levels. This will enable for-profit services to demonstrate to parents that they are providing a literacy programme for children.</p>
<p>This study found that early childhood teachers with a university qualification were less likely to use a commercial phonics programme than staff with atechnical or private college certificate or diploma. Possible reasons are that early childhood teachers may be more informed theoretically and more confident in planning and programming for individual children than less qualified staff.</p>
<p>The results of this study also found that a majority of early childhood staff reported that they believed it was appropriate to teach phonics in the prior-to-school years. Although some staff are following a more structured approach to teaching phonics, by including a commercial phonics programme, they adapt the programme when they consider it appropriate to do so.</p>
<sec id="sec15-1468798411417377"><title>Limitations</title>
<p>Like all surveys, this study has both strengths and limitations. The findings are important in establishing that there is widespread use of commercial phonics programmes in prior-to-school settings, especially in for-profit services and amongst less experienced and qualified staff. Yet the actual beliefs, motivations and reasons for using or not using these resources are difficult to establish viasurvey methods alone. Furthermore, the survey was sent only to Sydney metropolitan services, so the situation in rural and remote areas, and among different cultural groups, cannot be determined from this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-1468798411417377"><title>Directions for future research</title>
<p>This study has implications for early childhood teacher preparation programmes, professional development of staff, the implementation of the first Australian National Early Years Learning Framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1468798411417377">Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations, 2009</xref>) and the underlying beliefs about what is considered important in early childhood programmes. Future research will explore in more depth the reasons why early childhood staff may or may not use commercial phonics programmes. Underpinning these decisions are beliefs about what literacy is and how it is learnt.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We gratefully acknowledge and thank all the dedicated early childhood staff who tooktime out of their busy days to participate in this survey and the academics whoprovided feedback on the survey. We also thank the reviewers for their helpful feedback and advice.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baruch</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtom</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>‘Survey Response Rate Levels and Trends in Organizational Research’</article-title>. <source>Human Relations</source> <volume>61</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1139</fpage>–<lpage>1160</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Play and Literacy in Children’s Worlds</source>, <publisher-loc>Newtown, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Primary English Teaching Association</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Home and Away: The Policy Context in Australia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Child Care: A Better Policy Framework for Australia</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Sydney Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>‘Rationality and Phonics: A Comment on Wyse and Styles (2007)’</article-title>. <source>Literacy</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Cambourne B (2009) ‘The Sound and the Fury about Making Sense of Written Words’, <italic>The Sydney Morning Herald</italic>, 30 March, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.smh.com.au/national/the-sound-and-the-fury-about-making-sense-of-written-words-20090329-9fm8.html">http://www.smh.com.au/national/the-sound-and-the-fury-about-making-sense-of-written-words-20090329-9fm8.html</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>What We Know about How to Teach Phonics</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Farstrup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>What Research Has to Say about Reading Instruction</source>, <publisher-loc>Newark, DE</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Reading Association</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations (2009) <italic>Early Years Learning Framework</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.deewr.gov.au/EarlyChildhood/Policy_Agenda/Quality/Pages/EarlyYearsLearningFramework.aspx">http://www.deewr.gov.au/EarlyChildhood/Policy_Agenda/Quality/Pages/EarlyYearsLearningFramework.aspx</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Department of Education, Science and Training</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Teaching Reading: Report and Recommendations: National Inquiry into the Teaching of Literacy</source>, <publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Devine M (2009) ‘The Crazy Politics of Learning to Read’, <italic>The Sydney Morning Herald</italic>, 21 March, p.11</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dombey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>‘Towards a Balanced Approach to Phonics Teaching’</article-title>. <source>Literacy</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan-Owens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>‘Scripted Reading Programs: Fishing for Success’</article-title>. <source>Principal</source> <volume>88</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehri</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Role of Phonemic Awareness in Learning to Read’</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Farstrup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>What Research Has to Say About Reading Instruction</source>, <publisher-loc>Newark, DE</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Reading Association</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>‘Policy and Research: Lessons from the Clackmannanshire Synthetic Phonics Initiative’</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamme</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>‘From Scripted Instruction to Teacher Empowerment: Supporting Literacy Teachers to Make Pedagogical Transitions’</article-title>. <source>Literacy</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Ferrari J (2010) ‘Syllabus Confused on Place of Phonics’, <italic>The Australian</italic>, 7 June, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/nation/syllabus-confused-on-place-of-phonics/story-e6frg6nf-1225876211439">http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/nation/syllabus-confused-on-place-of-phonics/story-e6frg6nf-1225876211439</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goouch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Understanding Educational Discourse: Attending to Multiple Voices</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Goouch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambirth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Understanding Phonics and the Teaching of Reading: Critical Perspectives</source>, <publisher-loc>Maidenhead, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goouch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambirth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Introduction: Sound and Fury</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Goouch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambirth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Understanding Phonics and the Teaching of Reading: Critical Perspectives</source>, <publisher-loc>Maidenhead, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Johnston RS and Watson J E (2005) ‘The Effects of Synthetic Phonics Teaching on Reading and Spelling Attainment: A Seven Year Longitudinal Study’, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2005/02/20688/52449">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2005/02/20688/52449</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Jolly Learning (2005) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jollylearning.co.uk">http://www.jollylearning.co.uk</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Letterland International (2009) <italic>Letterland Child-Friendly Phonics</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.letterland.com">http://www.letterland.com</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>The Phonics Handbook: In Print Letters</source>, <edition>3rd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Chigwell, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jolly Learning</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Letterland Early Years Handbook</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Letterland International</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Marcon RA (2002) ‘Moving Up the Grades: Relationship between Preschool Model and Later School Success’, <italic>Early Childhood Research and Practice</italic> 4(1), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecrp.uiuc.edu/v4n1/marcon.html">http://ecrp.uiuc.edu/v4n1/marcon.html</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>‘Contested, Corporatised and Confused? Australian Attitudes to Child Care’</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Kids Count: Better Early Childhood Education and Care in Australia</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>‘Strategies Used for Phonics Instruction in Early Childhood Classrooms’</article-title>. <source>Reading Teacher</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Childcare Accreditation Council</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>QIAS Service Progress Statistics</source>, <publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Government</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>‘Whatever Happened to Developmentally Appropriate Practice in Early Literacy?’</article-title>. <source>Young Children</source> <volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>New South Wales Department of Community Services</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Annual Report 05/06 Preschool Funding Report</source>, <publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Government</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>New South Wales Department of Education and Training (2009) <italic>NSW Public Schools</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.schools.nsw.edu.au/gotoschool/preschool/adjusting.php">http://www.schools.nsw.edu.au/gotoschool/preschool/adjusting.php</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>‘Teacher Learning by Script’</article-title>. <source>Language Teaching Research</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Independent Review of the Teaching of Early Reading</source>, <publisher-loc>Nottingham, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department for Education and Skills</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Sound it Out! Phonics in a Comprehensive Reading Program</source>, <edition>3rd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erskine</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>‘Foundation Literacy Acquisition in European Orthographies’</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychology</source> <volume>94</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siraj-Blatchford</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sylva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>‘Researching Pedagogy in English Pre-Schools’</article-title>. <source>British Educational Research Journal</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>What Counts as Literacy in Early Childhood?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Blackwell Handbook of Early Childhood Development</source>, <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Juel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Teaching Children to Read: What Do We Know about How to Do It?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Snowling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulme</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>The Science of Reading: A Handbook</source>, <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Openshaw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>‘“To Be or Not To Be?”: The Politics of Teaching Phonics in England and New Zealand’</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wannan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Getting the Basics Right – Goals that Would Deliver a Good National Children’s Service System</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Kids Count: Better Early Childhood Education and Care in Australia</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Wren S (2002) ‘Ten Myths of Reading Instruction’, <italic>SEDL Letter, Putting Reading First</italic> XIV(3), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sedl.org/pubs/sedl-letter/v14n03/2.html">http://www.sedl.org/pubs/sedl-letter/v14n03/2.html</ext-link> (consulted July 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>‘Synthetic Phonics and the Teaching of Reading’</article-title>. <source>British Educational Research Journal</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>710</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1468798411417377"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Styles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>‘Synthetic Phonics and the Teaching of Reading: The Debate Surrounding England’s “Rose Report”’</article-title>. <source>Literacy</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1468798411417377"><title>Appendix</title>
<p>The beliefs of early childhood staff about children learning alphabetic literacy Survey
<fig id="img1-1468798411417377" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-img1.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="img2-1468798411417377" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-img2.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="img3-1468798411417377" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-img3.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="img4-1468798411417377" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468798411417377-img4.tif"/></fig>
</p></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>