<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Contemp Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Contemporary Sociology: A Journal of Reviews</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0094-3061</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-8638</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0094306113491549pp</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0094306113491549pp</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Street Therapists: Race, Affect, and Neoliberal Personhood in Latino Newark</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Mindiola</surname><given-names>Tatcho</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0094306113491549">University of Houston</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0094306113491549"><email>tmindiola@uh.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>606</fpage>
<lpage>608</lpage>
<product>
<source>Street Therapists: Race, Affect, and Neoliberal Personhood in Latino Newark</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramos-Zayas</surname><given-names>Ana Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>. <page-count count="448"/>pp. <price>$30.00</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780226703626</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>Street Therapists</italic> presents an innovative and sophisticated way of analyzing race relations. It is also a book that is not totally easy to read because of its complex writing style and its voluminous and detailed analysis of day-to-day interactions. Ana Ramos-Zayas analyzes the ethnographic information she gathered over a period of several years in the Ironbound and North Broadway area of Newark, New Jersey where Brazilians, Puerto Ricans, African Americans, Portuguese, and other Latino immigrants live. The largest group in Newark is African American and they have governed the city since 1970. They loom large over the narratives of race relations in the city and often as the beginning and end of race talk as a reference point. The author uses several ideas to analyze her information and it is these that are emphasized here.</p>
<p><bold>Street therapist:</bold> People who live in multiracial areas of cities like Newark must become “street therapists” if they are to navigate their day-to-day lives and this means engaging in racial learning. This involves observing, interpreting, and analyzing the everyday behaviors, body language, and emotions of others who are not like them. This is especially true for Latino immigrants who do not have experience or extensive knowledge about race relations in the United States.</p>
<p><bold>Emotional commonsense</bold>: The main concern of the book is how race relations are emotionally assessed. Emotions are an integral part of our everyday lives and they involve feelings and active manifestation. We feel our emotions physically and subjectively, and there is a great deal of variation in the intensity of our feelings. They operate in ways that are not completely understood because they are semi-conscious and deeply internalized, and they serve as unrefined sources of action. Emotions manifest themselves through our verbal interactions with others and we convey them not only through words but also with body language. We also gather emotional information from our day-to-day encounters and they teach us things about ourselves and others, if we listen. We not only feel and provide evidence of our emotions but we also project them onto others. Consider for example some of the emotions attributed to different groups in the Ironbound and North Broadway: African Americans are aggressive, have attitude, and always complain; Brazilian women know how to live and are more sensual and in touch with their femininity than other women; Puerto Ricans lack self-esteem and do not take advantage of their opportunities; whites are cold, and cultureless; Portuguese want to be seen as white but not like white Americans. Knowing which emotions make commonsense to use or avoid as one goes about his or her life makes for good street therapists. Emotions are also projected upon places. Newark for example is perceived to be an aggressive city, filled with angry African Americans, a reputation that developed from the 1976 riots in which African Americans rioted for six days. When Cory Booker (an Ivy League-educated African American) was elected mayor in 2006, he brought a different emotional tone to the fore. He ran on a platform of safety, development, and transparency—and he spoke of taking personal responsibility for one’s actions. He was from an upper middle-class family, but after he was elected he chose to live in the projects not only to better understand his constituents but also to illustrate that it was more safe than portrayed. He was a vegetarian and was reported to have been influenced by Buddhist philosophy. Booker’s message and persona stressed an emotional narrative of “overall emotional adequacy, quasi-spiritual values, and appropriate affect” (p. 59). He brought a softer emotional tone.</p>
<p><bold>Cartography of racial democracy:</bold> Cartography refers to the art of map making and it is used as a metaphor for the many cognitive maps that we have embedded in our minds about reality. The maps served as guides, codes, and orientations. Latinos, especially the immigrants, have a race relations map referred to by academics as racial democracy, which is more complicated and nuanced than the conceptions held by African American and others in the United States. The idea of racial democracy originated in Brazil where miscegenation among the European, Indian, and African populations was so extensive that it produced a people so thoroughly mixed and of so many different colors/hues that Brazilians claim not to view or judge each other through the lens of race because everyone in Brazil is said to have people in their families who are of many different shades of black, brown, and white. Hence there is a democratic relationship between all of the different skin pigments in Brazil. The emotions of this ideology have erotic undertones of closeness and acceptance, and are thought to be of a higher order, especially when juxtaposed with the rigid racial ideology of segregation and avoidance in the United States and its cold calculations. As might be expected, Brazilian immigrants rely upon and apply their notions of racial democracy when trying to make sense of race relations in the Ironbound and North Broadway areas. On the one hand, Brazilians repeatedly claim they do not see other racial groups through the American lens of black and white but only through their own ideology of the insignificance of color and race which they believe is a superior view. Yet their assertions of racial invisibility and their awareness of and hesitation to speak about African Americans are so constant as to reveal a hypersensitivity to racial differences. It also has the effect of Brazilians perceiving racial inequality as a function of character flaws rather than of structural arrangements that reflect racial preferences and power.</p>
<p><bold>Neoliberal personhood:</bold> Neoliberalism refers to private capital being used to revitalize inner cities—and Newark is no exception. These efforts involve governments providing incentives to lure private capital to blighted areas. The efforts invariably stress and use the technology of safety and security. Some of these revitalization efforts involve the promotion of ethnic culture. In the Ironbound for example, the Portuguese enclave predominates. In the aftermath of the riots, many ethnic groups (Italian, Jewish) fled the city but the Portuguese stayed and took over a dilapidated area and began to perpetuate their culture and images of their homeland by opening cafes, restaurants, bars, shops, and markets in the Iberian style. Other immigrants followed and over time it became an attractive area that was promoted as part of the new Newark. The emotions aspect is a “sensual feel” that appeals to the senses. It is not clear if the revitalization was a deliberated effort to lure private capital, but the area is nevertheless used to promote a visual and emotional appeal to affluent whites, tourists, and other consumers of cultural diversity. The point is that investment capital decides which ethnic cultures are palatable to be promoted to a larger predominately white clientele. Some cultures are deemed more acceptable and hence more profitable than others. Equally important is the particular kind of personhood that is sought and emphasized by this form of capital, especially in the area of employment in the service sector. It is one that stresses emotions associated with personal responsibility, manners, respect, and family values, shame, and aggression. This likewise includes and excludes others.</p>
<p>These ideas are used to amplify and dwell in the emotions behind a variety of topics including, but not limited to, the politics of worth among Puerto Ricans and the idea that Puerto Rican youth gain worth only by enlisting in the Armed Services and dying for the country; the relationship between Brazilians and African Americans and the belief that African Americans are trying to appropriate Brazilian culture; the notion that African American men prefer Puerto Rican women much to the chagrin of African American women; and how Puerto Ricans are perceived as delinquent citizens and South Americans as super citizens. Indeed, the topics, ideas, and detailed discussions are numerous and can overwhelm. Yet, <italic>Street Therapists</italic> is not only a must read, it is one that needs to be studied, for it is a gem of insights into the emotions of race relations in a multiracial setting.</p>
</body>
</article>