<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ARP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sparp</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Review of Public Administration</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0275-0740</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3357</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0275074012450942</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0275074012450942</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Recognizing and Responding to Retirement Obligations</article-title>
<subtitle>Other Postemployment Benefits in Florida Cities and Counties</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Matkin</surname><given-names>David S. T.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0275074012450942">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Krivosheyev</surname><given-names>Alex Y.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0275074012450942">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0275074012450942"><label>1</label>Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0275074012450942">David S. T. Matkin, Florida State University, 658 Bellamy Building, P.O. Box 3062250, Tallahassee, FL 32306-2250, USA. Email: <email>dmatkin@fsu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>558</fpage>
<lpage>580</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>With the implementation of recent accounting standards (GASB 43 and 45), local governments began reporting their liabilities and funding levels for postemployment benefits other than pensions—so-called OPEBs. In this article we pose three questions: (a) What factors affect the size of a government’s OPEB liability? (b) How did the OPEB standards affect the way governments manage their OPEB plans? and (c) What factors explain government responds to the OPEB standards? We draw data directly from audited financial reports in Florida counties and cities to examine those questions. Our results suggest that benefit policies, personnel characteristics, and actuarial cost methods are the most influential factors in determining a size of a government’s OPEB liability. Our results also provide evidence that many governments responded to the OPEB standards by reducing their benefits and changing their funding approaches. We show preliminary evidence of differences in governments that changed their policies or funding approaches with those that continued the status quo.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>administrative reform</kwd>
<kwd>financial transparency</kwd>
<kwd>retirement benefits</kwd>
<kwd>accounting standards</kwd>
<kwd>financial management</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Given the aging American workforce and widespread concern about the financial health of many public-employee pension funds, the management and sustainability of public retirement systems has become one of the most prominent and controversial policy issues in state and local government. A recent national poll (CNN, 2011) illustrates that Americans are widely divided over whether pensions and other retirement benefits for government workers should be increased (15%), kept the same (33%), decreased a little (26%), decreased a lot (21%), or eliminated (5%).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0275074012450942">1</xref></sup> There is also evidence that opposition to public retirement benefits is on the rise. Recent surveys in California, for example, show a 10-percentage point increase in the number of individuals who believe public pensions are too generous—from approximately 32% of respondents in 2010 to 42% in 2011 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0275074012450942">Christie, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Concerns about public sector retirement plans are not only a matter of public opinion. Several recent studies demonstrate that many state and local retirement systems are significantly underfunded (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0275074012450942">Biggs, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0275074012450942">Center for State and Local Government Excellence [CSLGE], 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0275074012450942">Coggburn &amp; Kearney, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0275074012450942">General Accountability Office [GAO], 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0275074012450942">Novy-Marx &amp; Raux, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0275074012450942">PEW, 2010</xref>), suggesting that numerous government officials face unavoidable and difficult decisions to increase the funding for their retirement plans and/or reduce their retirement benefits. The underfunding problem is further complicated by the recent economic downturn, the resulting decline in both governmental revenues and the value of retirement assets, and the subsequent need to increase retirement contributions at a time when many governments need to cut back on services. The problem is also challenging because efforts to reduce or reorganize retirement benefits nearly always face significant opposition from influential groups such as public-safety and teacher unions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0275074012450942">Hiltzik, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0275074012450942">Riordan &amp; Rubalcava, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0275074012450942">Walsh, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Most of the scholarly and popular attention on public retirement systems has focused on the condition of public pensions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0275074012450942">Cohen, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0275074012450942">Jensen, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0275074012450942">Lowenstein, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0275074012450942">Whoriskey, 2011</xref>), and public sector observers have largely overlooked evidence that many governments also carry large obligations associated with other retirement benefits such as postemployment subsidies for health care insurance, vision and dental care insurance, and life insurance (so-called “other postemployment benefits” or OPEBs).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0275074012450942">2</xref></sup> This omission is problematic because OPEBs comprise a significant portion of many state and local governments’ unfunded retirement liabilities. According to a recent report by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0275074012450942">PEW Center on the States (2010)</xref>, more than half of the so-called “trillion-dollar gap” in state retirement liabilities is attributable to underfunded OPEB plans. As health care costs continue to rise, some observers speculate that the OPEB portion of public retirement liabilities may increase at a faster rate than the pension portion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0275074012450942">The Kaiser Family Foundation, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>An important reason public pension plans are more widely discussed and analyzed than OPEBs is that, until recently, there was little transparency on the size of OPEB liabilities. In 2004, however, the Governmental Accounting Standards Board (GASB) issued accounting standards (GASB Statements Nos. 43 and 45, referred to in this article as “the OPEB standards”)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0275074012450942">3</xref></sup> that require state and local governments to report their OPEB liabilities and related funding activity to satisfy generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP). Since the majority of state and local governments are legally required to be GAAP compliant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0275074012450942">GASB 2008</xref>) and many others are compelled into GAAP compliance by external stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0275074012450942">Carpenter &amp; Feroz, 2007</xref>), most state and local governments in the United States have or will implement the OPEB standards.</p>
<p>Given the recentness of these new transparency requirements, little is empirically known about OPEB plans in state and local governments. Noted exceptions include <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0275074012450942">Coggburn and Kearney’s (2010)</xref> examination of the funding levels of state pension and OPEB plans and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0275074012450942">Coe and Rivenbark’s (2010)</xref> look at actuarial and accounting practices in the implementation of OPEB standards in North Carolina. We still know little, however, about the management and influence of OPEB policies, costs, and liabilities in public organizations. In response to that knowledge gap, this study uses observations of OPEB conditions in Florida cities and counties to explore answers to the following questions: (a) What factors are associated with the size of OPEB liabilities? (b) How did the OPEB standards affect the way governments manage their OPEB plans? and (c) What factors explain government responses to the OPEB standards?</p>
<p>This article proceeds as follows. The next section briefly overviews the development and implementation of the OPEB standards. That is followed by a discussion of our research questions, variable selection, and hypotheses. Then, the data and analysis are described. The article closes with a review of our findings and conclusions.</p>
<sec id="section1-0275074012450942">
<title>The Development of the OPEB Standards</title>
<p>Prior to the implementation of GASB Statements nos. 43 and 45 (the OPEB standards), nearly all state and local governments used a pay-as-you-go approach to recognizing and funding their OPEB obligations. This means that OPEB costs were recognized, and paid, when the benefits were received by retirees (i.e., insurance premiums paid on behalf of, or reimbursed to, qualified retirees) and not when employees earned the benefits. That approach contradicts the fundamentals of accrual accounting because it fails to recognize the cost of retirement benefits during the time period when benefits are earned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0275074012450942">Herbert, Williams, Burge, &amp; Baliga, 1989</xref>). It also contradicts principles of intergenerational equity because it allows taxpayers to shift some of the costs of delivering public services (i.e., compensation for public employees) onto future generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0275074012450942">Frederickson, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0275074012450942">Sneed &amp; Sneed, 1997</xref>). It also creates an incentive for public officials to increase the generosity of OPEBs since the full cost of increasing retirement benefit is not recognized for many years—contributing to a condition known as fiscal illusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0275074012450942">Wagner, 1976</xref>).</p>
<p>The GASB began its formal examination into the benefits and feasibility of OPEB standards in 1988, a few years after the organization was established. The GASB issued its first exposure draft<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0275074012450942">4</xref></sup> on OPEBs in 1989.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0275074012450942">5</xref></sup> The exposure draft led to GASB Statement No. 12 in 1990, which directed state and local governments to provide descriptive information in their financial statements on their OPEB policies and annual costs. As the GASB continued to study OPEBs, they issued an interim standard in 1994, Statement No. 26, which directed defined-benefit pension plans with retiree health care plans to disclose their health care related holdings, contributions, and outlays. Statement Nos. 12 and 26, however, did not set standards for reporting on OPEB liabilities.</p>
<p>After nearly two decades of study and deliberation, GASB issued two exposure drafts in February 2003 that outlined proposed standards for measuring, recognizing, and displaying OPEB liabilities. Following a period of public comment and the release of a revised exposure draft, GASB issued Statements No. 43 in April 2004 and No. 45 in June 2004.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0275074012450942">6</xref></sup> The OPEB standards established multiple expectations for the proper reporting of OPEB conditions in state and local governments. Among the standards’ most salient requirements are criteria for measuring, recognizing, and displaying information on OPEB liabilities, assets, unfunded liabilities, actuarial methods, benefit policies, funding policies, annual obligations, and contributions toward those annual obligations.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0275074012450942">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>The OPEB standards were then implemented over 3 years beginning in fiscal year 2007 or 2008 depending on the last day of the fiscal year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0275074012450942">GASB, 2004</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0275074012450942">8</xref></sup> Readers who want more information on the process of measuring and reporting OPEB liabilities in state and local governments are referred to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0275074012450942">Coe and Rivenbark (2010)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0275074012450942">
<title>Research Questions and Hypotheses</title>
<p>This study explores three basic questions about OPEBs:</p>
<list id="list1-0275074012450942" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Research Question 1</italic>: What factors are associated with the size of OPEB liabilities?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Research Question 2</italic>: How did the OPEB accounting standards affect the way governments manage their OPEB plans?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Research Question 3</italic>: What factors explain government responses to the new standards?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>This section presents our conceptual approach to each of these research questions, describes the rationale behind the selection of variables to identify answers to the questions, and identifies hypothesized relationships.</p>
<sec id="section3-0275074012450942">
<title>What Factors Explain the Size of OPEB Liabilities?</title>
<p>OPEB liabilities are affected by a variety of direct and indirect factors. Direct factors include (a) the generosity of benefit policies, (b) the number of participants who qualify for the benefits, and (c) the actuarial methods and assumptions used to calculate the OPEB liability. Indirect factors include political, organizational, and community characteristics of sponsoring governments. Because the calculation of OPEB liabilities is fully determined by direct factors, indirect factors only affect the size of OPEB liabilities through their influence on direct factors and cannot have an independent effect on OPEB liabilities. The analysis of indirect factors cannot be adequately addressed in this article. Rather, we focus on evaluating the effect of direct factors and anticipate that our findings will guide further research into the relative effect of indirect factors on the size of OPEB liabilities.</p>
<sec id="section4-0275074012450942">
<title>Benefit policies</title>
<p>There are two types of benefit policies that create OPEB liabilities.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0275074012450942">9</xref></sup> <italic>First</italic>, OPEBs often subsidize retirees’ insurance premiums with either fixed-dollar subsidies in monthly or annual disbursements (i.e., annuitized benefits)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0275074012450942">10</xref></sup> or subsidies that cover a percentage of retirees’ insurance premiums, usually with minimum and maximum benefit levels based on the number of years of qualified service performed.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0275074012450942">11</xref></sup> Because both approaches directly subsidize retiree insurance premiums, they are called <italic>explicit benefits</italic>. As subsidy levels increase, explicit benefits can create substantive costs that are associated with larger liabilities.</p>
<p><italic>Second</italic>, many plans permit retirees to purchase the same insurance coverage that is provided to current employees and at the premium rates that are charged for current employees’ coverage. This increases the cost of insurance premiums because age-adjusted premium rates for retirees are usually much higher than age-adjusted premiums for employed individuals, and when the two age-adjusted groups are pooled together, the result is a blended rate that increases a sponsor’s insurance premiums. The difference between the age-adjusted rate for current employees and the blended rate is called an <italic>implicit benefit</italic>.</p>
<p>The liabilities created by implicit benefits are nearly always much smaller than those created by explicit benefits. Due to limitations in the disclosure of plan details by OPEB sponsors in their audited financial statements, our analysis is limited to using a dichotomous variable to indicate the presence of either explicit or implicit benefits. We expect the difference to be substantively and statistically significant. As such, <italic>we hypothesize that the presence of explicit OPEBs is positively associated with the size of OPEB liabilities</italic>.</p>
<p>While we are not able to directly measure the generosity of OPEB plans in our study, it is widely believed that government officials treat retirement benefits and salaries as interchangeable components of total compensation. If that assumption is true, average salary levels should be negatively associated with the generosity of OPEB policies and, thereby, OPEB liabilities. <italic>We hypothesize, therefore, that employee salaries are negatively associated with OPEB liabilities</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0275074012450942">
<title>Number of participants</title>
<p>All else being equal, governments that increase access to retirement benefits to more participants will have higher OPEB costs and thereby higher liabilities. There are three classifications of plan participants: <italic>active</italic> participants are individuals who qualify for retirement benefits and are still providing service (usually as employees) to the OPEB plan’s sponsor; <italic>terminated</italic> participants are individuals who qualify to receive retirement benefits at a future date but no longer provide service to the OPEB plan’s sponsor; and, <italic>retired</italic> participants are individuals who have begun to receive retirement benefits. Unfortunately, many of the financial reports examined in this study do not provide information on the number and type of participants in their OPEB plan(s). In response, we use three measures to account for the number of participants.</p>
<p>The first measure is the number of full-time equivalents (FTEs) in the sponsoring government. <italic>We hypothesize that the number of FTEs is positively associated with OPEB liabilities</italic>.</p>
<p>The number of active participants, of course, is likely to be different from the number of FTEs. This is because FTEs include part-time employees who may not qualify for OPEBs. Also, FTEs do not count elected officials who may qualify for OPEBs. And, FTEs do not recognize vesting requirements that reduce the number of workers who qualify for OPEBs. We include control variables, discussed below, to account for possible bias in personnel policies and benefit qualifications that are associated with governmental size and with whether a plan sponsor is a city or county government.</p>
<p>The FTE variable also does not capture the number of terminated and retired participants in the OPEB plan. The number of retired participants should increase when personnel policies allow employees to qualify for full retirement at younger ages. Also, the number of terminated participants should increase as vesting periods are shortened. As a class of employees, public-safety workers often have shorter vesting periods and younger retirement age requirements. Governments with more public-safety FTEs, therefore, may have higher OPEB liabilities. They may also have higher OPEB liabilities if benefit policies provide more generous benefits to public safety workers. <italic>We hypothesize, therefore, that the percentage of FTE’s in police and fire departments is positively associated with OPEB liabilities</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0275074012450942">
<title>Actuarial cost methods and assumptions</title>
<p>Because OPEB liabilities are based on the projected costs of future benefits and the present value of those future benefits, they are not precisely calculated but are estimated using methods of actuarial valuation. There are two important components of an actuarial valuation: the selection of an actuarial cost method and the selection of assumptions about the growth in health care costs, the survival rate of participants, and the time value of money (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0275074012450942">Peng, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The OPEB standards permit six different actuarial cost methods. All but one of the plans in this study used either the entry-age normal actuarial cost method or the unit-credit actuarial cost method. The high incidence of those two methods in OPEB plans is not surprising given their common use in public pension plans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0275074012450942">Peng, 2009</xref>). The two approaches differ in how they recognize OPEB liabilities and their contribution requirements over participants’ years of service. The entry-age normal method produces larger liabilities than the unit-credit method until participants get close to retirement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0275074012450942">Novy-Marx &amp; Rauh, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0275074012450942">Peng, 2009</xref>). We include an indicator variable in our analysis to estimate the effect of using entry-age normal or unit-credit cost methods and <italic>hypothesize that OPEBs plans that use an entry-age normal actuarial method will have higher liabilities than those that use the unit-credit cost method</italic>.</p>
<p>In addition to the selection of cost methods, professional actuaries use several assumptions to estimate OPEB costs and liabilities. Actuarial assumptions do not change the actual cost of paying for benefits in the future but they do affect the forecasted value of those costs and the present value of those projections. Our analysis focuses on two key assumptions that are commonly reported: the assumed rate of return that is used to discount forecasted costs into their present values and the assumed growth rates of health insurance costs.</p>
<p>The governing boards of OPEB plans, in consultation with their contracted professional actuaries, set the actuarial assumptions. While the membership of pension boards is known to generally include representatives from their sponsoring governments, plan participants, and/or the general public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0275074012450942">Peng, 2009</xref>), little is known about the membership of OPEB boards. In Florida, most municipal and county OPEB plans are under the purview of city and county councils, who have significant short-term incentives to minimize actuarial liabilities and annual OPEB costs by using optimistic actuarial assumptions, though more research is needed into the antecedents and effects of OPEB board membership characteristics.</p>
<p>It is important to note that the nature of benefit policies and personnel characteristics is different from that of actuarial assumptions because, in most cases, the former is the culmination of decisions made prior to the issuance of the current OPEB standards and the latter is in direct response to the accounting standards. Assumptions, therefore, can be used as mechanisms to affect the reported size of OPEB liabilities without changing the substantive benefits. In fact, one of the primary criticisms of the OPEB standards is a concern that forecasting future OPEB costs and investment returns are prohibitively challenging and, as such, plan managers have an incentive to select actuarial assumptions that are overly optimistic, resulting in lower OPEB liabilities than may be justified by more objective analysis.</p>
<p>This concern is well established in studies of OPEB reporting in the private sector (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0275074012450942">Chung, Jacob, &amp; Neuwirth, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0275074012450942">Hann, Lu &amp; Subramanyan, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0275074012450942">Pearson, Jerris, &amp; Brooks, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0275074012450942">Rizzo, 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0275074012450942">Fogarty and Grant (1995)</xref>, for example, demonstrate that the relationship between actuaries and accountants creates an opportunity for collusion between actuaries and their clients to generate favorable financial statements. Also, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0275074012450942">Miner (1994)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0275074012450942">Akresh and Sher (1999)</xref> provide evidence that actuarial methods often fail to deliver an accurate measurement of OPEB liabilities and that much of the problem is in the selection of overly generous rates of return, which lower the present value of future costs (i.e., the OPEB liability).</p>
<p>The OPEB standards were designed to anticipate these concerns and only permit the use of long-term rates of return on the funded portion of the OPEB liability and require lower rates of return on the unfunded portion. This reduces some of the opportunity for manipulation that is found in the actuarial assumptions of pension plans; however, even within a range of short-term rates of return, there is an opportunity to make optimistic assumptions.</p>
<p>We obtained the actuarial assumption data from governments’ audited financial reports and <italic>hypothesize that more optimistic actuarial assumptions—measured as higher assumed rates of return and lower assumed near-term (called “initial”) and long-term (called “ultimate”) growth rates in health care costs—are associated with lower OPEB liabilities</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0275074012450942">
<title>Control variables</title>
<p>We also include four control variables to account for other factors that may directly affect the size of OPEB liabilities. The first variable is a dichotomous indicator of whether the government is a city or a county. This variable helps to control for differences in retirement systems, personnel characteristics, and other conditions between municipal and county governments. The second variable is a measure of the population size of the government.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0275074012450942">12</xref></sup> Marlowe finds that OPEB liabilities may be skewed toward larger cities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0275074012450942">2007</xref>). This variable helps to control for differences in economies of scale in the provision of health care benefits, personnel characteristics, the sophistication of administrative professionals, and other conditions associated with population size. The third and fourth control variables are dichotomous indicators of the reporting year, which help to control for variation in OPEB liabilities that may be associated with the three implementation phases of the accounting standards and opportunities for organizational learning and benefit changes over time.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0275074012450942">
<title>How Did Governments Respond to the OPEB Standards?</title>
<p>There are several ways that plan sponsors may have responded to the issuance of the OPEB standards. This study focuses on the two<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0275074012450942">13</xref></sup> most commonly anticipated responses (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0275074012450942">Chase &amp; Calkins-McGettigan, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0275074012450942">Keating &amp; Berman, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0275074012450942">Pickens, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0275074012450942">Wisniewski, 2005</xref>): the decision to change the way OPEB liabilities are funded and the decision to change benefit policies.</p>
<sec id="section9-0275074012450942">
<title>Funding the liability</title>
<p>Prior to the issuance of the OPEB standards, the most common approach to funding OPEB plans was to “pay-as-you-go.” This was the approach used by all the governments in this study prior to 2004. The pay-as-you-go approach involves paying for retirement benefits out of budgetary resources as retirees receive those benefits. This approach produces an unfunded actuarial liability because plan sponsors are obligated to provide benefits at a future date but they do not set aside resources to make those future payments. Government officials may choose to increase their funding above the pay-as-you-go level to reduce their unfunded liabilities. The OPEB standards, however, do not require governments to reduce their unfunded liabilities, only to report them.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0275074012450942">14</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0275074012450942">
<title>Change benefit policies</title>
<p>We also looked to see if governments changed their OPEB policies after the issuance and during the implementation of the OPEB standards. The standards require governments to disclose basic descriptive information on their OPEB policies, and we looked for reported changes to those policies in the financial reports. Potential changes to OPEB policies include closing the plan to new workers, changing the formula used to calculate the anticipated OPEB subsidy, or changing the number of people who qualify for benefits (e.g., increasing vesting periods, increasing retirement ages, and constraining beneficiary provisions). We expected most of the policy changes to reduce the generosity of benefits and thereby reduce OPEB liabilities.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0275074012450942">
<title>What Factors Explain Government Responses?</title>
<p>Much is known about the various factors that affect administrative and political decisions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0275074012450942">March, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0275074012450942">Pfeffer &amp; Salancik, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0275074012450942">Selznick, 1949</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0275074012450942">Simon, 1945</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0275074012450942">Weick, 1979</xref>). We use a simplified decision framework to examine responses to the OPEB standards. Three conditions are expected to affect government responses to the OPEB standards. These include (a) whether the OPEB liability was recognized as a <italic>problem</italic>, (b) the influence of internal and external <italic>stakeholders</italic>, and (c) whether governments had the <italic>ability</italic> to respond.</p>
<sec id="section12-0275074012450942">
<title>Problem recognition</title>
<p>If public officials do not recognize OPEB liabilities as substantive problems, they are unlikely to change their OPEB plans in response to the new standards. Two important sources of perceived importance are (a) the magnitude of the problem and (b) philosophical agreement with the OPEB standards.</p>
<p>Officials in governments with relatively small OPEB costs and actuarial liabilities are more likely to view those liabilities as minor concerns. We expect, therefore, <italic>governments that changed their OPEB policies and/or their funding approach will have larger OPEB liabilities than those that did not change</italic>. It is important to note that the size of OPEB liabilities is not a simple measure of financial costs, it represents the number of plan participants, the age profile of those participants (both active and retired),<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0275074012450942">15</xref></sup> and the generosity of plan benefits.</p>
<p>Some critics of the OPEB standards claim that future health care costs cannot be accurately calculated and should not, therefore, be considered measureable liabilities, and others claim that their benefit policies can be substantively changed in the future, which may significantly reduce or eliminate their liability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0275074012450942">Patton &amp; Bauer, 2008</xref>). Opposition to the OPEB standards may examine why some government officials have not changed their OPEB policies or funding strategies since the standards were issued. Unfortunately, we do not have individual-level data and cannot directly examine this proposition. Further research is needed to assess the relationship between perceptions of the legitimacy of OPEB standards and governmental responses.</p>
<p>Given the complexity of accounting standards and actuarial valuations, cities and counties with professional executives may be more likely to be concerned with unfunded OPEB liabilities. We expect <italic>a higher proportion of council-manager governments among those that changed their OPEB policies and/or their funding approach</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0275074012450942">
<title>Influential stakeholders</title>
<p>Given the technical nature of OPEBs and accounting standards, the number of interested and influential stakeholder groups is likely to be limited.</p>
<p>Credit raters and bond investors are commonly viewed as important external stakeholders. Governments with higher credit ratings, those seeking to influence a change in their credit ratings, and those that are preparing to issue bonds may be more likely to fund their OPEB liabilities or change their benefit policies. Of course, the relationship between credit ratings and OPEB responses isn’t necessarily straightforward, since a higher credit rating also suggests an increased ability to fund OPEB liabilities and previous research suggests that bond investors may have already factored the size of OPEB liabilities into the pricing of municipal bonds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0275074012450942">Marlowe, 2007</xref>). Based on published reports by the three major credit rating agencies, we know that they are monitoring the disclosure of OPEB liabilities, but there is no evidence that the rating agencies have taken any clear action toward governments with larger unfunded OPEB liabilities. <italic>We compare, therefore, whether governments that changed their OPEB policies and/or their funding approach have higher credit ratings than those that did not make changes</italic>.</p>
<p>Government employees are another potentially influential stakeholder group. Government employees may be likely to cooperate with benefit reductions if those changes are clearly necessary to maintain the sustainability of a benefit plan; however, employee groups are more likely to provide strong opposition to benefit reductions. Governments with employee unions may be especially effective in preventing benefit reductions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0275074012450942">Marlow &amp; Orzechowksi, 1996</xref>). <italic>We expect that governments that changed their OPEB policies will not have union representation as often as those that did not change their policies</italic>.</p>
<p>Other influential stakeholders include state regulators, public policy think tanks, media outlets, tax-payer interest groups, and advocates for public employees, who may pressure governments to lower their unfunded OPEB liabilities or to preserve benefits. In Florida, the state does not regulate the management of OPEBs in local governments beyond requiring implicit benefits as a minimum benefit level, and there were no prominent state-level public interest groups or media outlets that drew public attention to the topic during the fiscal years analyzed in this study.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-0275074012450942">16</xref></sup> And, while it is difficult to identify citizen groups that are likely to support or oppose changes to OPEB policies and funding approaches, the conservative or liberal political ideology may be predictive of relative pressure to reduce employee benefits or prefund OPEB liabilities. <italic>We compare, therefore, whether governments that changed their OPEB policies or funding approaches have a larger percentage of Republican residents</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0275074012450942">
<title>Ability to change</title>
<p>If public officials do not have the ability to increase OPEB funding or to reduce the generosity of benefits, they are not likely change the management of their OPEB plans, even when OPEB liabilities are recognized as a significant problem and when they are under significant pressure by stakeholders to change their approach.</p>
<p>One aspect of the ability to change is whether the government has sufficient financial resources to increase its funding commitments beyond the minimum “pay-as-you-go” level. <italic>We expect that governments that change their funding approach will be in better financial condition than those that maintain a pay-as-you-go strategy</italic>. There are many ways to measure fiscal condition. Researchers often use socioeconomic indicators, such as poverty levels, median household income, and unemployment, to measure governments’ financial condition. We opt for measures of financial condition that use information from governmental financial statements, such as (a) high ratios of short-term assets to short-term liabilities, (b) positive variances in revenue forecasts, and (c) low ratios of long-term liabilities to total assets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0275074012450942">Clark, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0275074012450942">Finkler, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0275074012450942">Wang, Dennis, &amp; Tu, 2007</xref>). To the extent that socioeconomic factors are expected to influence how government officials approach their OPEB policies and funding strategies, we take the position that the conceptual link goes through the influence of socioeconomic conditions on governmental liquidity, revenue scarcity, debt levels, and similar measures.</p>
<p>Another aspect of the ability to change is whether state and local laws constrain the range of opportunities that are available to government officials who wish to change their OPEB policies, for example, by requiring OPEB changes to be part of collective bargaining negotiations. These considerations are more likely to affect the ability to change OPEB policies than funding approaches. During the time period of this study, there were no legal provisions to prohibit or permit OPEB changes in Florida.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0275074012450942" sec-type="methods">
<title>Data and Method</title>
<p>To answer our research questions, we examined OPEB plans in Florida cities and counties. Our sample includes all of the 66 counties<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-0275074012450942">17</xref></sup> and 100 largest cities (those with populations greater than 20,000) in the state. We collected data from several sources. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0275074012450942">Table 1</xref> for a summary of our variables and their sources.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0275074012450942" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Statistics.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0275074012450942" xlink:href="10.1177_0275074012450942-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="center">Mean</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">Min</th>
<th align="center">Max</th>
<th align="center">Description</th>
<th align="center">Sources</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Liability (ln)</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>16.31</td>
<td>2.07</td>
<td>9.95</td>
<td>20.09</td>
<td>Natural log of actuarially accrued OPEB liability</td>
<td>Government CAFRS from Fiscal Years 2008 – 2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Explicit benefit</td>
<td>350</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0 = <italic>Implicit benefit only</italic></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1 = <italic>Explicit benefit provided</italic></td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Pay (ln)</td>
<td>311</td>
<td>10.69</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>7.15</td>
<td>12.24</td>
<td>Natural log of covered payroll per FTE</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FTEs (ln)</td>
<td>338</td>
<td>6.82</td>
<td>1.17</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>10.75</td>
<td>Natural log of count of full-time equivalent (FTE) employees</td>
<td>2007 census of governments</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percent police</td>
<td>338</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Percentage of FTEs that are police dept. employees</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percent fire</td>
<td>338</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Percenteag of FTEs that are fire dept. employees</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Actuarial method</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0 = <italic>Entry-age method</italic></td>
<td>Government CAFRS from fiscal years 2008 – 2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1 = <italic>Unit-credit method</italic></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Discount assumption</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>4.77</td>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8.5</td>
<td>Assumed rate of return</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Health care (initial) assumption</td>
<td>343</td>
<td>9.52</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>Initial health care growth rate assumption</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Health care (ultimate) assumption</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>5.12</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>Ultimate health care growth rate assumption</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Government type</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0 = <italic>County</italic></td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1 = <italic>City</italic></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population (ln)</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>11.73</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>9.03</td>
<td>14.73</td>
<td>Natural log of population</td>
<td>2010 U.S. Census</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2008</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates that Fiscal Year 2008</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2009</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates that Fiscal Year 2009</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2010</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates Fiscal Year 2010</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Political form</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates that &gt;70% of council is elected by district and mayor is CAO</td>
<td>Data collected by departmental survey</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Adapted political</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates that &lt;70% of council is elected by district and mayor is CAO</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Adapted administrative</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates that &gt;70% of council is elected by district and manager is CAO</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Administrative form</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicates that &lt;70% of council is elected by district and manager is CAO</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aaa</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of Aaa credit rating</td>
<td>Moody’s investor service and Standard &amp; Poor’s rating services<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0275074012450942">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aa</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of Aa credit rating</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>A</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of A credit rating</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baa</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of if Baa credit rating</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Police union</td>
<td>350</td>
<td>.76</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of police union</td>
<td>Florida’s public employee relations commission—certification report</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fire union</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of fire union</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>General union</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Indicator of general employee union</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percent Republican</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>34.6</td>
<td>9.4</td>
<td>8.59</td>
<td>59.23</td>
<td>% of jurisdictions' registered voters identified as Republicans</td>
<td>Florida division of elections, November 2008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liquidity</td>
<td>351</td>
<td>7.6</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td>31.74</td>
<td>Current assets / current liabilities</td>
<td>Government CAFRS from fiscal years 2008 –2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Leverage</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>.97</td>
<td>Noncurrent liabilities / Total assets</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Revenue variance</td>
<td>352</td>
<td>−.00</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.43</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>(Actual revenue minus budgeted revenue) / budgeted revenue</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0275074012450942">
<label>a.</label>
<p>Standard deviation provides little information for dummy variables. The mean values for dummy variables represents the proportion of observations with the value of “1”.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0275074012450942">
<label>b.</label>
<p>Moody’s notation used for credit ratings though some ratings are from S&amp;P (Aaa = AAA), (Aa = AA), (A = A), (Baa = BBB).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section16-0275074012450942">
<title>Data</title>
<p>Information on OPEB plans (i.e., liability size, benefit characteristics, covered payrolls, actuarial information, policy changes, and funding activity) was collected from governments’ comprehensive annual financial statements (CAFRs) for each of the three phases of the OPEB standards’ implementation: fiscal years 2008, 2009, and 2010. As of this writing, CAFRs from fiscal year 2011 are unavailable.</p>
<p>In fiscal year 2008, 33% of the 100 cities in our study and 47% of the 66 counties reported OPEB liabilities in their CAFRs. Those numbers increased in fiscal year 2009 to 91% of cities and 71% of counties. There was a slight increase in 2010 to 95% of cities and 83% of counties. Of the 16 governments that did not report their OPEB liabilities in fiscal year 2010, one has not published its CAFR and the others either made no mention of their OPEB plans, stated that their OPEB liabilities are not material, or stated that they have not conducted an actuarial valuation of their liability. In fiscal year 2010, the median population of governments that did not report their OPEB information is 24,153, compared to 73,090 in reporting governments. This suggests that OPEB reporting is less prevalent among smaller governments and efforts to collect OPEB information on Florida cities that are smaller than 20,000 (our sample’s cutoff) are not likely to produce an abundance of additional information on OPEB liabilities and governmental responses.</p>
<p>Our unit of analysis is individual OPEB plans. Ninety-nine percent of the reporting cities have a single OPEB plan that covers all of their employees. One city has separate plans for its general and police employees. Eighty-seven percent of reporting counties have a single OPEB plan for their employees. Three counties have two OPEB plans, three counties have three OPEB plans, and one county has seven separate OPEB plans.</p>
<p>The OPEB standards require that CAFRs report material changes to OPEB policies. We conducted content analysis of the CAFRs to identify those changes. We looked for changes from 2003 (the year prior to the implementation of the OPEB standards) to 2010 (the most current year of available financial statements) and coded the dates of the changes and captured descriptive information on the substantive effect of each change.</p>
<p>We also used the CAFRs to collect and calculate three measures of the fiscal condition of the sponsoring governments. The first is a liquidity measure [current assets / current liability]. Higher values indicate the availability of more resources to meet short-term obligations. The second is a revenue variance measure [(actual general fund revenue – budgeted general fund revenue) / budgeted general fund revenue]. Positive values indicate the availability of revenue that was not previously anticipated and negative values indicate less revenue than planned. The third is a leverage measure [long-term liabilities / total assets]. Higher values signal higher levels of existing long-term debt.</p>
<p>We obtained data on the number of full-time equivalent workers in each government from the 2007 Census of Governments. We selected data from the 2007 Census of Governments over the Public Employment and Payroll Census for each fiscal year because the former includes data on all governments and the latter only includes counties with populations greater than 100,000 and cities with populations greater than 75,000.</p>
<p>We gathered population data from the 2010 U.S. Census. We selected the 2010 Census over the American Community Survey data because it is a more accurate count and is closely proximate to the time period studied, which was a period of low mobility in Florida.</p>
<p>We obtained form-of-government information from an internal departmental study. Researchers used government documents and web sites to identify (a) whether governments’ chief administrative officer (CAO) is an elected mayor or appointed city manager and (b) the number of council members who are elected at-large and the number elected by district. We also identified if the government used a commission form of government. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0275074012450942">Frederickson, Johnson, and Wood (2004)</xref>, we categorized local governments as “political” if they have a mayoral CAO and more than 70% of their council members are elected by district; “adapted political” if they have a mayoral CAO and less than 70% of their city council is elected by district; “adapted administrative” if they have a city manager CAO and more than 70% of their council members are elected by district; and “administrative” if they have a city manager CAO and less than 70% of their city council is elected by district.</p>
<p>We identified credit ratings from Moody’s Investor Service and Standard &amp; Poor’s Rating Services, as published on their web site in January 2011. We coded the ratings using an ordinal scale (from strongest to weakest, using Moody’s notation): Aaa, Aa, A, or Baa. Credit rating agencies do not provide a rating for all governments, and the different agencies sometimes conflict in their rating, though usually not between the ordinal classification used in this study. We limited our selection of credit ratings to general obligation ratings.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-0275074012450942">18</xref></sup> We used the following preference order in coding governments’ credit ratings: Moody’s senior taxable rating, Standard &amp; Poor’s issuer credit rating, Standard &amp; Poor’s most recent general obligation debt. We note that our study includes ratings at one point in time, though we do not expect this to bias our results because general obligation ratings tend to be stable and there is no evidence, as yet, that credit ratings have changed because of how governments manage their OPEB liabilities. More research is needed, however, into the relative affect of OPEB liabilities (especially unfunded liabilities) on rating changes.</p>
<p>We collected union data from Florida’s Public Employee Relations Commission. We identified whether jurisdictions had certified police unions, firefighter unions, and general employee unions.</p>
<p>Given that this is a single-state analysis, there are a few Florida-specific conditions that may influence the generalizability of our findings to other states. First, Florida statutes mandate that all local governments provide an implicit health care benefit to their employees. More than half of the governments in this study provide an explicit benefit, but we cannot know how many of the governments in our study that have implicit benefit plans would not have an OPEB plan at all if it was permitted by state law. Second, while the state of Florida provides regulatory oversight of local government pension plans and actuarial assumptions, they provide no oversight of OPEB plans. City and county officials in states that regulate or oversee local government OPEB plans may have responded differently to the OPEB standards. Third, all Florida counties participate in the Florida Retirement System (FRS)—a statewide retirement systems and the principal pension system for state, county, and school district workers. Very few Florida cities participate in FRS. FRS provides an explicit OPEB, called the Health Insurance Subsidy (HIS), to qualified retirees. This means that governments that participate in FRS and provide an explicit benefit are providing a subsidy benefit in addition to the one provided by the HIS. One may expect that FRS participating governments would be less likely to provide explicit benefits, but 54% of the counties in our study provide explicit benefits, which is even more than the 39% of cities that provide explicit benefits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0275074012450942">
<title>Method</title>
<p>We use OLS regression to estimate the effect of our independent variables (benefit type, salary levels, number and type of employees, actuarial methods and assumptions, population size, government type, and observed year) on the size of governments’ OPEB liabilities. We selected OLS because it is the best linear unbiased estimator of true population values when regression assumptions are reasonable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0275074012450942">Lewis-Beck, 1980</xref>). We assume a linear relationship between the independent variables and the dependent variables within the observed range of observations. We produced residual-versus-fitted plots of the regression estimates to examine the distribution of the error term and find support for assuming that the expected value of the error term is zero. We cluster the standard errors on an OPEB plan identifier over the 3 years of pooled observations, which addresses concerns of bias due to heteroskedasticity. We also include indicator variables for each year to control for year effects.</p>
<p>The observed values of OPEB liabilities are right-skewed; though OLS does not require a normally distributed dependent variable (only a normally distributed error term), we use their log-transformed values in our analysis to improve the interpretation of the estimators. Our measures of payroll, the number of employees, and population are also log transformed. The other variables resembled normality and do not warrant transformation.</p>
<p>We test six variations of the model using different sample specifications: one that includes all of the OPEB plans, one that excludes sponsors with multiple OPEB plans, one that only includes city sponsored plans, one that only includes county sponsored plans, one that only includes plans that provide explicit benefits, and one that only includes plans that provide implicit benefits.</p>
<p>We analyze governmental responses to the OPEB standards (Research Questions 2 and 3) with descriptive and nonparametric statistics. First, we count the number and types of policy changes that occurred in each year following the issuance of the OPEB. Second, we examine differences in the various characteristics of OPEB plans and sponsoring governments based on the type of benefits (i.e., implicit and explicit) and the type of observed change (i.e., funding approach and/or policy change).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-0275074012450942">19</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0275074012450942">
<title>Analysis</title>
<sec id="section19-0275074012450942">
<title>OLS Estimates of OPEB Liability</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0275074012450942">Table 2</xref> presents our regression results. With the exception of the sample that only included plans with explicit benefits, the model fit statistics are consistent and strong, with <italic>R</italic>-squared values that indicate our independent variables accounting for about 75% to 80% of the variation in the dependent variable. The fit of the explicit benefit sample is not as good (an <italic>R</italic>-squared value of .528), indicating that the model is not as well specified. Additional information on differences in benefit provisions across explicit-benefit plans (which is not uniformly available in the CAFRs) would likely explain more of the variation and improve the model fit.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0275074012450942" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>What Explains the Size of Actuarially Accrued Liabilities?</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0275074012450942" xlink:href="10.1177_0275074012450942-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="center">All Plans</th>
<th align="center">Single Plan Governments</th>
<th align="center">Counties only</th>
<th align="center">Cities only</th>
<th align="center">Implicit only</th>
<th align="center">Explicit only</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Explicit benefit</td>
<td><bold>1.24 (5.76)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.16 (5.29)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.27 (5.31)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.25 (3.82)</bold></td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pay (ln)</td>
<td><bold>1.06 (3.50)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.09 (3.04)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.27 (3.50)</bold></td>
<td><bold>.88 (2.96)</bold></td>
<td><bold>.94 (3.39)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.49 (3.05)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FTE (ln)</td>
<td><bold>1.22 (7.41)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.66 (9.91)</bold></td>
<td><bold>.52 (5.13)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.97 (9.57)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.62 (9.70)</bold></td>
<td><bold>.83 (4.97)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percent police</td>
<td><bold>.86 (1.80)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.14 (1.86)</bold></td>
<td>−.11(−0.28)</td>
<td>−.34(−.26)</td>
<td>.69 (.98)</td>
<td>.09 (.15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percent fire</td>
<td>.15 (1.04)</td>
<td>−.59(−.39)</td>
<td>.32 (.56)</td>
<td>−1.14(−.73)</td>
<td>−.72(−.49)</td>
<td>−.55(−0.50)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Actuarial method</td>
<td>−<bold>.42(−2.16)</bold></td>
<td>−<bold>.46(−2.17)</bold></td>
<td>−.03(−.13)</td>
<td>−<bold>.52(−2.23)</bold></td>
<td>−22(−1.01)</td>
<td>−<bold>.52(−1.75)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Return assumption</td>
<td>−.09(−1.04)</td>
<td>−.09(−1.10)</td>
<td>−<bold>.23(−2.18)</bold></td>
<td>−.06(−.60)</td>
<td>−<bold>.25(−2.43)</bold></td>
<td>−.03(−.33)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Health care (initial) assumption</td>
<td>.08 (.91)</td>
<td>.09 (1.02)</td>
<td>.13 (1.00)</td>
<td>.04 (.45)</td>
<td>−.05(−0.52)</td>
<td>.22 (1.63)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Health care (ultimate) assumption</td>
<td>−.21(−1.55)</td>
<td>−.17(−1.35)</td>
<td>−.12(−.70)</td>
<td>−.09(−.62)</td>
<td>−.17(−1.35)</td>
<td>−.19(−.80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Government type</td>
<td>.37 (1.58)</td>
<td>.35 (1.47)</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>.18 (.73)</td>
<td>.55 (1.47)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population (ln)</td>
<td>−.08(−.47)</td>
<td>−<bold>.61(−3.04)</bold></td>
<td><bold>.31 (2.84)</bold></td>
<td>−<bold>57(−2.13)</bold></td>
<td>−.28(−1.50)</td>
<td>.13 (.70)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2009</td>
<td>−.09(−.95)</td>
<td>−.16(−1.47)</td>
<td>−.08(−.85)</td>
<td>−.04(−.29)</td>
<td>−.13(−.92)</td>
<td>−.01(−.04)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2010</td>
<td>−.18(−1.61)</td>
<td>−<bold>.27(−2.23)</bold></td>
<td>−.18(−1.42)</td>
<td>−.12 (.46)</td>
<td>−<bold>.25(−1.77)</bold></td>
<td>.00 (.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−2.30(−.84)</td>
<td>.15 (.04)</td>
<td>−4.62(−1.38)</td>
<td>.49 (.15)</td>
<td>.62 (.25)</td>
<td>−7.09(−1.46)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>N</td>
<td>301</td>
<td>268</td>
<td>129</td>
<td>172</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>153</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>R</italic>-Squared</td>
<td>.744</td>
<td>.756</td>
<td>.760</td>
<td>.796</td>
<td>.767</td>
<td>.528</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0275074012450942">
<p>Note: DV: Actuarially Accrued Liability (ln). OLS estimation with clustered standard errors on OPEB plans. <italic>t</italic>-scores in parentheses. Bolded values have <italic>p</italic> values less than .10</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>As hypothesized, the presence of explicit benefits is statistically and substantively significant. This finding is robust across all six of the sample specifications. Plans that provide explicit benefits are expected to have OPEB liabilities that are 245% larger, on average, than those that only provide implicit benefits (based on the “all plans” sample coefficient). The difference between OPEB liabilities in implicit and explicit benefit plans is also demonstrated by comparing the size of OPEB liabilities as a percentage of the plans’ covered payroll. OPEB liabilities are 28% of payroll in governments with implicit benefits and 102% in governments with explicit benefits (median values).</p>
<p>The number of FTEs is positively associated with the size of the OPEB liability, as hypothesized. A 1% increase in FTEs relates to a 1.22% increase in OPEB liabilities (based on the “all plans” sample coefficient). That equates to a US$660,000 increase in OPEB liabilities, on average, which is a little less than 1% of the average payroll in our sample. The statistical significance of this relationship is consistent in each of the sample specifications, though the size of the estimated effect varies.</p>
<p>Contrary to our expectations, the measure of employee pay (covered payroll / FTEs) is positively associated with OPEB liabilities. A 1% increase in employee pay is associated with a 1.06% increase in OPEB liabilities (based on the “all plans” sample coefficient). The substantive effect is similar to that of the FTE parameter discussed above. This suggests that salary increases are complemented by OPEB increases and that there is not a trade off between the two forms of compensation. Rather, it may be that government officials who are able to increase the employee salaries (e.g., wealthier jurisdictions) are also able to increase retirement benefits or that government officials who have to increase employee salaries (e.g., those in competitive labor markets) also have to increase retirement benefits to attract and retain qualified workers. This finding was robust across the six sample specifications and deserves further study.</p>
<p>We find some support for our hypothesis that the proportion of public safety employees is associated with OPEB liabilities. A higher percentage of police workers is related to higher OPEB liabilities in the samples that included the most number of plans. A 1-percentage point increase in the number of police workers is associated with a 1.36% increase in OPEB liabilities (based on the “all plans” sample coefficient). The substantive effect is similar to that of the FTE parameter discussed above. There is no relationship, however, between the percentage of police workers in the other four sample specifications and no relationship between the percentage of firefighters in any of the six sample specifications.</p>
<p>As we hypothesized, the entry-age method for calculating the OPEB liability is associated with larger liabilities than the unit-cost method. Plans that use the entry-age method have liabilities that are 34% higher, on average, than those that use the unit-cost method. This finding was significant and consistent in nearly all the sample specifications. The difference between OPEB liabilities in governments that use entry-age and unit-cost actuarial methods is also demonstrated by comparing the size of OPEB liabilities as a percentage of the plans’ covered payroll. OPEB liabilities are 54% of payroll in governments that use the unit-cost method and 76% in governments that use the entry-age cost method (median values).</p>
<p>As expected, the assumed rate of return was negatively related to the size of OPEB liabilities. However, the parameter estimates were only significant in two of the sample specifications. This may be partly due to the relatively low variation in the observed rates of returns in our sample, which would increase the standard errors and thereby reduce the likelihood of statistical significance. Forty percent of the plans in our sample have an assumed rate of 4% and 80% have an assumed rate between 4% and 5%.</p>
<p>The parameter estimates for the other actuarial assumptions in our model were not found to be statistically different from zero. The parameter for the initial health care assumption was positive, as hypothesized, for all but one of the sample specifications. Surprisingly, however, the ultimate health care assumption was negatively associated with the size of OPEB liabilities in all of the six sample specifications (though not significantly different for zero). This suggests endogeneity in the selection of ultimate health care growth rates. The trustees of OPEB plans with particularly high liabilities may be more likely to assume especially low ultimate health care growth assumptions to lower their reported liabilities.</p>
<p>It is a mathematical fact that, ceteris paribus, more conservative actuarial assumptions will produce lower OPEB liabilities in individual OPEB plans. Our findings suggest, however, that when comparing plans, one should be cautious in assuming that the difference in their liability size is because of actuarial assumptions. It is more likely that the differences are associated with the nature of their benefits, the government’s compensation practices, and the number of workers that qualify for benefits. Our findings also show that this is consistent whether one is talking about counties or cities and about plans with explicit or implicit benefits.</p>
<p>The city/county control variable was not significant. The population control variable was statistically significant in three of the sample specifications but the estimates were not consistent. This suggests a need to further understand how population size may relate to the types of retirement benefit plans in local governments. The control variables for year effects were also insignificant in most of the sample specifications. This suggests that the average size of OPEB liabilities did not significantly change over the three implementation phases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0275074012450942">
<title>Policy Changes From 2003 to 2010</title>
<p>Of the 72 plans that provide an explicit benefit during the time period between the issuance and implementation of the OPEB standards, 33 did not change their benefits, 33 decreased their benefits, 6 increased their benefits, and 17 changed their funding approach.</p>
<p>The incidence of benefit reductions has a bimodal distribution (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0275074012450942">Table 3</xref>). One group of benefit reductions occurred around 2005 and 2006, shortly after the OPEB standards were issued and before sponsoring governments needed to publish their OPEB liabilities on their financial statements. Another group of benefit reductions occurred in 2008-2010, the years when the OPEB standards were implemented. While these results do not prove that changes were in direct response to the OPEB standards, the timing of these changes provides evidence that government decision makers responded to the issuance and implementation of the standards.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0275074012450942" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Changes in OPEB Policies From Fiscal Years 2003 to 2010.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0275074012450942" xlink:href="10.1177_0275074012450942-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">2003</th>
<th align="center">2004</th>
<th align="center">2005</th>
<th align="center">2006</th>
<th align="center">2007</th>
<th align="center">2008</th>
<th align="center">2009</th>
<th align="center">2010</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Created New Explicit Benefit</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Increase Value of Benefits</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Plan Increases Totals</bold></td>
<td/>
<td><bold>1</bold></td>
<td><bold>1</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><bold>1</bold></td>
<td><bold>2</bold></td>
<td><bold>1</bold></td>
<td><bold>6</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">2003</th>
<th align="center">2004</th>
<th align="center">2005</th>
<th align="center">2006</th>
<th align="center">2007</th>
<th align="center">2008</th>
<th align="center">2009</th>
<th align="center">2010</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Qualifications Made More Restrictive</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reduce Size of Defined-Benefit</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Switch from Percent-Benefit to Defined-Benefit Value</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reduce Size of Percent-Benefit</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Capped Benefit at the Current Level</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Explicit Benefit to Defined Contribution</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Closed Explicit Benefit</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>Plan Reduction Totals</bold></td>
<td><bold>2</bold></td>
<td><bold>2</bold></td>
<td><bold>6</bold></td>
<td><bold>4</bold></td>
<td><bold>1</bold></td>
<td><bold>3</bold></td>
<td><bold>9</bold></td>
<td><bold>6</bold></td>
<td><bold>33</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The most common type of benefit reduction (13 of the 33 reductions) was to eliminate the explicit benefit for future employees. In six plans, the maximum percentage of an OPEB subsidy was reduced for retirees that receive defined-percentage benefits. In five plans, the benefit policy was switched from a defined-percentage approach to a defined-value approach, which reduces the sponsors’ exposure to the risk of escalating health care costs. In four plans, officials capped the dollar value of future defined-percentage benefits at the value of current insurance premiums. In two plans, officials dropped their defined benefit plan in favor of a defined contribution plan for future employees (i.e., health care savings plan). In two plans, the qualifications for receiving an explicit benefit were made more restrictive. Lastly, in one plan, officials decreased the size of its defined-benefit subsidy.</p>
<p>In most situations, the benefit reductions only applied to future employees. Also, some of the reductions did not apply to all employee classifications equally (e.g., general, police, firefighters). As a result, significant equity concerns are likely to exist for many years in a lot of the governments that changed their benefit policies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0275074012450942">
<title>Comparing the Different Responses</title>
<p>Our results provide evidence that governments that responded differently to the OPEB standards also differ on some of our measures of problem salience, stakeholder influence, and the ability to change (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0275074012450942">Table 4</xref>). Specifically, we found notable differences in the median size of their OPEB liabilities, credit ratings, and financial conditions. Those differences are discussed below; however, these findings should be considered preliminary because there is a high level of variation within each response category and, given the small sample size, further evidence is needed to provide a more conclusive understanding of why governments differed in their responses.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0275074012450942" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Reduce Benefits and/or Fund the Liability.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0275074012450942" xlink:href="10.1177_0275074012450942-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Implicit benefit plans<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Explicit benefit plans<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristics</th>
<th align="center">No change</th>
<th align="center">Funding change</th>
<th align="center">No change</th>
<th align="center">Policy change</th>
<th align="center">Funding change</th>
<th align="center">Policy &amp; funding change</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Number of observations</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Liability<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liability</td>
<td>US$3.3 million</td>
<td>US$.5 million</td>
<td>US$23.6 million</td>
<td>US$23.6 million</td>
<td>US$14.2 million</td>
<td>US$72.4 million</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liability/FTE</td>
<td>US$6,715</td>
<td>US$1,082</td>
<td>US$27,332</td>
<td>US$22,074</td>
<td>US$9,828</td>
<td>US$49,867</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liability/Population</td>
<td>US$56</td>
<td>US$9</td>
<td>US$124</td>
<td>US$173</td>
<td>US$68</td>
<td>US$621</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Form of government<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0275074012450942">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Political</td>
<td>2%</td>
<td>40%</td>
<td>4%</td>
<td>10%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>30%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Political adapted</td>
<td>2%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Administrative adapted</td>
<td>37%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>33%</td>
<td>40%</td>
<td>43%</td>
<td>10%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Administrative</td>
<td>51%</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>52%</td>
<td>50%</td>
<td>57%</td>
<td>60%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Commission</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>4%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Credit rating<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0275074012450942">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aaa</td>
<td>8%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>5%</td>
<td>29%</td>
<td>0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aa</td>
<td>36%</td>
<td>100%</td>
<td>43%</td>
<td>50%</td>
<td>71%</td>
<td>90%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A</td>
<td>8%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>18%</td>
<td>15%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baa</td>
<td>2%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>5%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No rating</td>
<td>45%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>32%</td>
<td>25%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>10%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Unions<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0275074012450942">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Police union</td>
<td>70%</td>
<td>45%</td>
<td>75%</td>
<td>75%</td>
<td>86%</td>
<td>100%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fire union</td>
<td>61%</td>
<td>44%</td>
<td>53%</td>
<td>53%</td>
<td>57%</td>
<td>100%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>General union</td>
<td>36%</td>
<td>55%</td>
<td>46%</td>
<td>46%</td>
<td>26%</td>
<td>50%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Party affiliation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>32%</td>
<td>30%</td>
<td>31%</td>
<td>38%</td>
<td>44%</td>
<td>28%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Financial condition<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0275074012450942">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liquidity</td>
<td>7.3</td>
<td>9.5</td>
<td>6.4</td>
<td>7.5</td>
<td>5.2</td>
<td>5.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Leverage</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Revenue variance</td>
<td>.015</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>–.013</td>
<td>–.006</td>
<td>–.002</td>
<td>.018</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0275074012450942">
<p>Note: Data are from FY2010 and do not differ substantively with data from FY2009. Implicit benefit plans with policy changes are not shown because that condition is not possible in Florida because statuary provisions require implicit benefits as a minimum benefit.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0275074012450942">
<label>a.</label>
<p>Median Values.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0275074012450942">
<label>b.</label>
<p>Percentage of those within each response category with identified characteristics (totals 100% for Form of Government and Credit Ratings).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>We did not find meaningful differences associated with forms of governments, union representation, or party affiliation. The failure to find a difference associated with union representation may be partly associated with the common decision to only change benefits for future employees, which reduces opposition from current employees.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most notable finding is that among plans with explicit benefits, the median size of OPEB liabilities is higher, by approximately three times, for those plans that changed their benefits policies and their funding strategies. This difference holds if we use per FTE or per population measures of the OPEB liability. This finding suggests that particularly high liabilities elicited the most comprehensive responses, supporting the problem recognition perspective on the factors that stimulated changes.</p>
<p>However, there is significant variation in the size of the liabilities within each response category, and <italic>t</italic> tests of mean differences, to test whether governments that changed their response had higher OPEB liabilities than governments that did not make a change, only indicate statistical differences in the mean values of the “no change” response with the “policy &amp; funding change” (<italic>p</italic> value is .041) and “policy change” (<italic>p</italic> value is .072) in one-sided <italic>t</italic> tests.</p>
<p>Plans that only changed their funding approach had the lowest liabilities among those with either explicit or implicit benefits. This may indicate that officials in governments with particularly low liabilities view the problem as more easily solved through funding the liability and that officials in governments with medium-sized OPEB liabilities either change their policies or do not make any substantive changes. Test of means differences, however, do not show statistical differences.</p>
<p>While governments with higher credit ratings (Aaa or Aa) were represented in nearly every response category, they were particularly common among plans that changed their funding approach. None of the plans that changed their funding approach had A or Baa credit ratings and nearly all of them had a credit rating. This finding is consistent for plans with explicit or implicit benefits and supports claims that funding responses are attempts to maintain strong credit ratings, suggesting a direct or indirect influence by the credit market on government responses to OPEB liabilities that depends on governments’ credit quality. Another explanation for this finding, however, is that governments with higher credit ratings tend to be in better financial condition and, therefore, better able to fund their liability. More research is needed to better understand this apparent relationship.</p>
<p>Plans that changed their funding approaches also have different financial conditions compared to those that did not change their funding approach.</p>
<p>Among implicit-benefit plans, those that changed their funding approach had higher median liquidity and revenue-variance measures. This finding supports expectations that governments in better financial condition are more likely to fund their OPEB liabilities and those without sufficient resources will continue to use the pay-as-you-go approach. However, the variation in the liquidity ratios is high and means-difference tests do not indicate a statistical difference in their means. Another item of caution is that while the median liquidity and revenue-variance measures are notably different, those governments that did not change their funding approach still appear to be highly liquid and received more revenue than expected. This may mean there is a financial-condition threshold that is important to reach before government officials change their funding approach.</p>
<p>Among plans with explicit benefits, sponsors that changed their funding approaches had lower median liquidity levels and higher median revenue-variance measures than those that did not change their funding approach (means-difference tests are not significant). This may suggest that these governments reduced their available cash or increased their short-term obligations to fund their OPEB liability. This is opposite to the finding in implicit plans. More research is needed into the revenue sources that were tapped to fund OPEB liabilities.</p>
<p>Interestingly, plans that changed policies and funding approaches had the highest leverage measures of all the response categories (one-tailed <italic>p</italic> value is .12 between “policy &amp; funding change” and “no change”). This may be partially associated with higher OPEB liabilities, but since OPEB liabilities only recently began to be recognized on government balance sheets and will be recognized over as many as 30 years, it is more likely that this indicates that governments with particularly high OPEB liabilities tend to have higher long-term liabilities and may suggest that the size of governments’ OPEB liabilities are good indicators of their propensity to incur long-term debt.</p>
<p>Our mixed findings on the relationship between financial conditions and governmental responses to OPEB liabilities is not surprising given that much of the recent literature on state and local financial conditions argue that financial condition is a multidimensional, nonlinear, heterogeneous, and politically contextual construct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0275074012450942">Hendrick, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0275074012450942">Sohl, Peddle, Thurmaier, Wood, &amp; Kuhn, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0275074012450942">Justice &amp; Scorsone, 2012</xref>). A minimal level of fiscal health is certainly necessary for organizational survival and basic functionality, but beyond that minimal level, the effects of additional fiscal slack may be limited.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-0275074012450942">20</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0275074012450942" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>While the sustainability and cost of public pensions has become an increasingly important policy issue, recent studies demonstrate that other postemployment benefits (OPEBs), especially health care insurance subsidies, comprise a significant portion of the total retirement liabilities in state and local governments. In this article, we seek to expand our empirical understanding of OPEBs by studying Florida cities and counties to identify factors that affect the size of OPEB liabilities and to explore how governments responded to GASB’s recently issued OPEB standards that require state and local governments to measure and report those liabilities to be compliant with generally accepted accounting principles.</p>
<p>Our findings indicate a strong relationship between OPEB liabilities and the type of benefit policies provided to retired employees. We also find a positive association between OPEB liabilities and both the size of government workforces and, surprisingly, average employee salaries. OPEB liabilities are also found to be associated with the actuarial methods used to calculate the liabilities, but we find little support for expectations that variation in actuarial assumptions explains substantive differences in OPEB liabilities.</p>
<p>We also find that many governments reduced the generosity of their OPEB benefits in recent years. Some of those reductions occurred when the accounting standards were issued and others during the standards’ implementation period. The most common form of benefit reduction was the elimination of explicit benefits for new employees. Several governments also began to fund their OPEB liabilities. We find preliminary evidence that those governments that changed their benefit policies and/or funding approaches at the time of the OPEB standards’ implementation have higher OPEB liabilities and higher credit ratings than governments that did not change. We also find mixed evidence on the relationship between financial conditions and how government officials responded to the OPEB standards.</p>
<p>While this study provides new empirical information on OPEBs in local governments, the findings also stimulates a number additional questions about the technical management of public retirement systems and the normative foundations and unintended effects of “good” governance in public organizations.</p>
<p>Future research could improve our understanding of public sector retirement systems by examining the relationship between pensions, OPEBs, and other forms of compensation in public organizations. While there is value in studies of specific components of compensation systems, these benefits do not operate in isolation and must also be understood as a whole. It is also necessary to understand the relationship between retirement obligations and other long-term obligations in government. For example, are the sizes of governments’ unfunded pension and OPEB liabilities predictive of a general inclination to shift the burdens of current services onto future taxpayers? And, related, is the motivation to increase retirement benefits and obligations a necessity of a competitive labor market the result of administrative and political ignorance, and/or evidence of organizational capture by public employees? Why do some governments adopt policies that lead to large unfunded liabilities while others eschew debt? Why should governments continue to provide these benefits when they have been largely abandoned in the private sector?</p>
<p>Another important future line of research is to expand our understanding of efforts to improve “good” fiscal governance, including transparency and reporting requirements. If the OPEB standards exposed information that was not previously known by public administrators or elected officials, policy and funding changes may be seen as efforts to correct previous wrongs. However, many administrators probably knew that they had large unfunded OPEB liabilities. They may have used the OPEB standards to pressure elected officials into making more responsible financial decisions. The latter closely matches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0275074012450942">Carl Friedrich’s (1940)</xref> view of responsible professionalism but is contrary to classical notions of neutral competence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0275074012450942">Goodnow, 1900</xref>). How do we define “good” fiscal management?</p>
<p>The findings also point to new equity concerns in public sector retirement systems. Concerns for intergenerational equity persist, but given that many policy changes only affect future employees, how will disparities in compensation systems affect job satisfaction and organizational culture? How will disparities affect the ability to attract and retain quality employees? As public sector workers continue to age, understanding OPEBs, as well as pensions, will be an increasingly important area of research in public administration and policy.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors acknowledge and thank the LeRoy Collins Institute at Florida State University for its support.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<label>Author’s Note</label>
<p>Earlier versions of this article were presented at the 2010 Annual Conference of the Association for Budgeting and Financial Management and the 1st Global Conference on Transparency Research in 2011 at Rutgers University-Newark.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: A grant from the Jesse Ball DuPont Fund to the LeRoy Collins Institute supported the collection of the data that is used in this paper.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0275074012450942">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The poll (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0275074012450942">CNN, 2011</xref>) also shows that support for public retirement benefits is split on partisan grounds as 60% of self-identified Democrats stated that retirement benefits should be increased or kept the same but 59% of self-identified Republicans stated that benefit levels should be reduced a little or a lot.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0275074012450942">
<label>2.</label>
<p>For most governments, the subsidy for health care insurance is, by far, the most costly component and makes up the largest share, if not nearly all, of their OPEB liability.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0275074012450942">
<label>3.</label><p>The Financial Accounting Standards Board (FASB), which oversees the development of accounting standards for private firms, established similar OPEB standards in the 1990s and has revised those standards several times over the past 20 years.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0275074012450942">
<label>4.</label><p>The purpose of exposure drafts is to reveal proposed accounting standards to users and preparers of financial reports and to those familiar with accounting practices to obtain feedback on the expected impact of proposed standards. Those comments are used to revise standards or to direct further analysis before issuing official statements that establish generally accepted accounting principles.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0275074012450942">
<label>5.</label><p>The Financial Accounting Standards Board (FASB) was in the process of considering an OPEB standard for private sector entities since the late 1970s, and FASB No. 81, released in 1984, was substantively similar to GASB No. 12.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0275074012450942">
<label>6.</label><p>GASB statement No. 43 outlines reporting requirements on state and local government entities with OPEB trust funds. GASB statement No. 45 outlines standards for measuring, recognizing, and displaying OPEB liabilities, funding progress, and annual costs for all state and local government entities.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0275074012450942">
<label>7.</label>
<p>After issuing the OPEB standards, GASB released technical bulletins in 2004, 2006, and 2008 to further clarify the standards and published a Guide to Implementation of GASB Statements Nos. 43 and 45 on Other Postemployment Benefits in August 2005 to explain the scope and breadth of the statements, to distinguish OPEBs from other types of retirement benefits, and to clarify actuarial measurement procedures.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0275074012450942">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Governments in Phase 1 implemented the standards no later than the first fiscal year beginning after December 15, 2006, which was fiscal year 2007 for governments with fiscal years that end in the last 2 weeks of December (i.e., those that match the calendar year) but was fiscal year 2008 for the majority of state and local governments. Governments in Phase 2 began no later than the first fiscal year after December 15, 2007, which, for most, was fiscal year 2009. And, Phase 3 governments began reporting their OPEB liabilities no later than the first fiscal year after December 15, 2008, which, for most, was fiscal year 2010.</p>
<p>A government’s inclusion in the first, second, or third phase depended on the size of its revenues in the first fiscal year ending after June 15, 1999. The first phase included governments with revenues of US$100 million or more. The second phase included governments with revenues between US$10 million and US$100 million. And, the third phase included governments with revenues that were less than US$10 million.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0275074012450942">
<label>9.</label>
<p>A third type of benefit policy is the use of health care savings plans similar to defined-contribution pension plans, where sponsors contribute into saving accounts that are the property of their employees who can then access the funds on retirement to pay for qualified expenses. This option does not create an actuarial liability and is therefore not included in our study.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0275074012450942">
<label>10.</label>
<p>A common example is a US$5 per month health care insurance subsidy for every year of qualified service up to a maximum of US$150 per month after 30 years.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0275074012450942">
<label>11.</label>
<p>For example, retirees with 10 years of service may receive subsidies that cover 25% of their insurance premiums and employees with 30 years of service may receive 80% subsidies.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0275074012450942">
<label>12.</label>
<p>We also considered a measure of population change (2000 to 2010). The absolute value of population change did not substantively alter parameter estimates and did not have an independent effect on OPEB liabilities. The percentage change measure of population growth provided especially high values of growth for smaller governments and therefore was negatively associated with OPEB liabilities. This is likely because less populated governments tend to employ fewer people and have smaller OPEB liabilities and not because population growth lowers your OPEB liability. We, therefore, did not include population growth measures in our model.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0275074012450942">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Other potential responses that are not examined in this study include changes to the way government officials negotiate compensation benefits with their employees and decisions to engage credit rating agencies or other stakeholder groups to address anticipated effects of the OPEB disclosures.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0275074012450942">
<label>14.</label>
<p>There are two primary approaches to funding OPEB liabilities. First, governments can deposit assets into an OPEB trust, which are managed by trustees on behalf of plan participants. Second, governments can transfer their assets into savings accounts, such as treasury accounts, and designate those assets for future OPEB payments. Some governments have also funded their OPEB liability by issuing issue taxable bonds and invest the proceeds into OPEB trusts or designated funds.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0275074012450942">
<label>15.</label>
<p>As active participants near retirement, their retirement liabilities increase (though the rate of the increase depends on the actuarial cost methods used). As retired participants age, their expected future benefit and associated liability decreases (though the rate of the decrease depends on survival assumptions). Information on the age profiles of plan participants is not provided in the OPEB information reported in government annual financial reports.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-0275074012450942">
<label>16.</label>
<p>The LeRoy Collins Institute released the only known Florida-based study on OPEBs in February 2011. That report received attention from many Florida news outlets, especially in communities with large unfunded OPEB liabilities. If that report had a direct effect on OPEB policies or funding activity, however, the effect is not likely until FY 2012 at the earliest.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-0275074012450942">
<label>17.</label>
<p>While there are technically 67 counties in Florida, Duval County is consolidated with the city of Jacksonville and is coded as a city.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-0275074012450942">
<label>18.</label><p>Ratings for revenue bonds were not included because those ratings are significantly influenced by the credit quality of the revenue source that is dedicated to servicing the debt. As such, a single government can have several revenue bonds that each has a different rating. In contrast, general obligation bonds are viewed as the credit quality of the underlying government.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-0275074012450942">
<label>19.</label>
<p>Future research will hopefully build on these findings by using regression analysis to evaluate the effect of various factors on government responses to the accounting standards. That analysis is not performed here because of the number of plans in some of the response categories is too small to provide robust estimates.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-0275074012450942">
<label>20.</label>
<p>As an example, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0275074012450942">Marlowe’s (2011)</xref> study on the relationship between fiscal slack and credit ratings.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>David S. T. Matkin</bold> is an assistant professor at the Reubin O’D. Askew School of Public Administration and Policy at Florida State University and a research fellow at the LeRoy Collins Institute at Florida State University. His research focuses on public financial management in U.S. local governments. David’s current work is concentrated on understanding municipal retirement plans in Florida.</p>
<p><bold>Alex Y. Krivosheyev</bold> is a recent MPA graduate of the Reubin O’D. Askew School of Public Administration and Policy at Florida State University. Alex currently works as a statistical consultant for the Florida Office of State Courts Administrator.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Akresh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Year-end strategies for pension &amp; OPEB obligations and expense</article-title>. <source>Journal of Corporate Accounting &amp; Finance</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Biggs</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>An options pricing method for calculating the market price of public sector pension liabilities</article-title>. <source>Public Budgeting &amp; Finance</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>94</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feroz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Institutional theory and accounting rule choice: An analysis of four U.S. state governments’ decision to adopt generally accepted accounting principles</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Organizations, and Society</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>565</fpage>-<lpage>596</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Center for State and Local Government Excellence</collab>. (<year>2011</year>, <month>January</month>). <source>State and local pensions: An overview of funding issues and challenges</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calkins-McGettigan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Survey: Approaches vary among Virginia governments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accountancy</source>, <volume>206</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>60</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neuwirth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>, <month>June</month> <day>1</day>). <article-title>Changes in actuarial assumptions/plan designs after FASB 106</article-title>. <source>CPA Journal</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>56</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Municipal fiscal strain: Indicators and causes</article-title>. <source>Government Finance Review</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>CNN Opinion Research Poll</collab> (<year>2011</year>, <month>March</month> <day>11-13</day>). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://i2.cdn.turner.com/cnn/2011/images/03/31/rel4m.pdf">http://i2.cdn.turner.com/cnn/2011/images/03/31/rel4m.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coe</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rivenbark</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Implementing GASB 45: Recommended best practices in local government</article-title>. <source>Public Budgeting &amp; Finance</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coggburn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Trouble keeping promises? An analysis of underfunding in state retiree benefits</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>70</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>February</month> <day>22</day>). <article-title>Played for pension fools</article-title>. <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>A13</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>March</month> <day>17</day>). <article-title>California voters souring on public pensions: Survey</article-title>. <source>Reuters</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/03/17/us-economy-california-pensions-survey-idUSTRE72G3KF20110317">http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/03/17/us-economy-california-pensions-survey-idUSTRE72G3KF20110317</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finkler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Financial management for public, health, and not-for-profit organizations</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Impact of the actuarial profession on financial reporting</article-title>. <source>Accounting Horizons</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frederickson</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Can public officials correctly be said to have obligations to future generations?</article-title> <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>-<lpage>464</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frederickson</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>The adapted city: Institutional dynamics and structural change</source>. <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M.E. Sharpe</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1940</year>). <article-title>Public policy and the nature of administrative responsibility</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Public policy: A yearbook of the graduate school of public administration</source> (pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>General Accountability Office</collab>. (<year>2009</year>, <month>November</month>). <source>Report to chairman, special committee on aging, U.S. Senate: State and local government retiree health benefits</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodnow</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1900</year>). <source>Politics and administration</source> (Technical Bulletin 2004-2). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MacMillan. Governmental Accounting Standards Board</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Government Accounting Standards Board</collab>. (<year>2008</year>, <month>March</month>). <source>Research brief: State and local government use of generally accepted accounting principles for general purpose external financial reporting</source>. <publisher-loc>Norwalk, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subramanyan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Uniformity versus flexibility: Evidence from pricing of the pension obligation</article-title>. <source>Accounting Review</source>, <volume>82</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hendrick</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Managing the fiscal metropolis</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Responses to OPEB proposal</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accountancy</source>, <volume>168</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hiltzik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>May</month> <day>15</day>). <article-title>Some truths about public pensions</article-title>. <source>Los Angeles Times</source>, p. <fpage>B1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>January</month> <day>7</day>). <article-title>San Diego ahead in pension reform—City considers 401(k)-style system</article-title>. <source>The Bond Buyer</source>, p. <fpage>9</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scorsone</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Measuring and predicting local government fiscal stress</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scorsone</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of local government fiscal health</source> (pp., <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>) <publisher-loc>Burlington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>The Kaiser Family Foundation and Health Research and Educational Trust</collab>. (<year>2003</year>, <month>September</month>). <source>Employer health beneﬁts: 2003 Annual Survey</source>. <publisher-loc>Menlo Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Unfunded public employee health care benefits and GASB No. 45</article-title>. <source>Accounting Horizons</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis-Beck</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <source>Applied regression: An introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>, <month>June</month> <day>27</day>). <article-title>The next crisis: Public pension funds</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>, Magazine Section, p. <fpage>MM9</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>March</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>A primer on decision making: How decisions happen</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marlow</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orzechowski</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Public sector unions and public sector spending</article-title>. <source>Public Choice</source>, <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marlowe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Much ado about nothing? The size and credit quality implications of municipal and other postemployment benefit liabilities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Budgeting &amp; Finance</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marlowe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Beyond 5 percent: Optimal municipal slack resources and credit ratings</article-title>. <source>Public Budgeting and Finance</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Ask a benefit actuary: New approach is needed to compute plan liability</article-title>. <source>Business Insurance</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Novy-Marx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rauh</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Public pension promises: How big are they and what are they worth?</article-title> <source>Journal of Finance</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>1211</fpage>-<lpage>1249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>, <month>January/February</month> <day>28-31</day>). <article-title>The GASB OPEB Standards: To comply or not to comply</article-title>. <source>Today’s CPA</source>, <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jerris</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Accounting for OPEBs: Does better accounting serve the public interest?</article-title> <source>Journal of Applied Business Research</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>State and local pension fund management</source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Auerbach</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Pew Center on the States</collab>. (<year>2010</year>, <month>February</month>). <source>The trillion dollar gap: Underfunded state retirement systems and the roads to reform</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salancik</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>The external control of organizations: A resource dependence perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper &amp; Row</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pickens</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Managing the Challenges of OPEB</article-title>. <source>Government Finance Review</source>, <volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>42</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riordan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubalcava</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>, <month>September</month> <day>16</day>). <article-title>How Pensions Can Get Out of the Red</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>A33</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Future cost versus market value: The great debate over pension valuation</article-title>. <source>Government Finance Review</source>, <volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Selznick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1949</year>). <source>TVA and the grass roots: A study in the sociology of formal organization</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1945</year>) <source>Administrative behavior: A study of decision-making processes in administrative organization</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MacMillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sneed</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sneed</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The intergenerational consequence of retiree healthcare premiums: What is the evidence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Budgeting, Accounting &amp; Financial Management</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>285</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sohl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peddle</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thurmaier</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>Measuring the financial position of municipalities: Numbers do not speak for themselves</article-title>. <source>Public Budgeting and Finance</source>, <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>74</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Revenue structure, fiscal illusion, and budgetary choice</article-title>. <source>Public Choice</source>, <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>March</month> <day>11</day>). <article-title>The burden of pensions on states</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>B1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Measuring fiscal condition: A study of U.S. states</article-title>. <source>Public Budgeting and Finance</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whoriskey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>March</month> <day>4</day>). <article-title>The big pension math question</article-title>. <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>A14</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Potential state government practices impact of the new GASB accounting standard for retiree health benefits</article-title>. <source>Public Budgeting &amp; Finance</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0275074012450942">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weick</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <source>The social psychology of organizing</source>. <publisher-loc>Reading, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Addison-Wesley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>