<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmsj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mult Scler</journal-id>
<journal-title>Multiple Sclerosis Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1352-4585</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0970</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458512440604</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1352458512440604</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Controversies in Multiple Sclerosis</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Do not treat from CIS onset: evaluate disease course and prognosis first – Yes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bunyan</surname><given-names>Reem F</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458512440604">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>Sean J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1352458512440604">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1352458512440604"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology, Neurosciences Center, King Fahad Specialist Hospital Dammam, Saudi Arabia</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1352458512440604"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1352458512440604">Sean Pittock, Neurology, Mayo Clinic, College of Medicine, 200 First St. SW, Rochester, MN 55905, USA Email: <email>pittock.sean@mayo.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>391</fpage>
<lpage>393</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>As physicians how do we counsel our patients with clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) when they ask, ‘what is the benefit of injecting disease-modifying agents (DMAs) over many years? What disability will they prevent in my future?’ In this debate, we will provide three core points supporting the concept that a watchful waiting approach (annual neurological evaluation and magnetic resonance imaging of the head (with gadolinium) at least for the first few years after diagnosis) for most patients with CIS represents appropriate medical care.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>disease-modifying therapies</kwd>
<kwd>beta-interferon</kwd>
<kwd>demyelination</kwd>
<kwd>multiple sclerosis</kwd>
<kwd>outcome measurement</kwd>
<kwd>glatiramer acetate</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1352458512440604" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>As physicians how do we counsel our patients with clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) when they ask, ‘what is the benefit of injecting disease-modifying agents (DMAs) over many years? What disability will they prevent in my future?’? In this debate, we will provide three core points supporting the concept that a watchful waiting approach (annual neurological evaluation and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the head (with gadolinium) at least for the first few years after diagnosis) for most patients with CIS represents appropriate medical care. Our three core points are:</p>
<list id="list1-1352458512440604" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>1) The natural history of CIS is favorable for most.</bold></p>
<p>Many patients (25–55%) with CIS never develop clinically definite multiple sclerosis (CDMS), and most have a good or excellent outcome over 20 years.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>2) There is no proven clinical benefit of DMAs on long-term disability in CIS, and if a benefit does exist it is likely small.</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>3) High costs (without proven efficacy) represent significant economic burden for patients and payers.</bold></p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1352458512440604">
<title>The natural history of CIS is favorable for most</title>
<p>Three large prospective natural history studies reported a cumulative probability of developing CDMS of between 38–59% at 10 years after CIS. For CIS patients with a normal baseline MRI, around 80% will not have any further demyelinating episodes at 20 year follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1352458512440604">1</xref></sup> For those with an abnormal baseline MRI, around 20% will have no further episodes at 20 years. Fisniku reported that for those patients with CIS who do indeed convert to CDMS a significant proportion (approximately 40%) have a benign course.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1352458512440604">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>Since most high-risk (abnormal baseline MRI scans) patients with CIS convert to CDMS early (within a few years), even these patients may benefit from a brief early watchful waiting period, allowing identification of those likely to develop CDMS and have an active disease course; this would minimize over-treatment of patients never destined to develop CDMS or worsening disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1352458512440604">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Those familiar with the new 2010 MS diagnostic criteria should note that many high-risk CIS patients would now be reclassified as MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458512440604">3</xref></sup> This would further shift those patients who continue to be classified as CIS towards an even more favorable long-term outcome.</p>
<p>In contrast to the points discussed in core point 1, some might argue that since it is not possible to accurately predict early those patients who will remain classified as CIS and those who will convert to CDMS, a ‘treat all early’ approach is required. However, do DMAs benefit patients with CIS, and if they are used is there any harm in delaying treatment by a few years?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1352458512440604">
<title>There is no proven clinical benefit of DMAs on long-term disability in CIS, and if a benefit does exist it is likely small</title>
<p>Large randomized controlled trials (RCT) of DMAs in MS and CIS have focused mainly on relapse behavior and surrogate markers of ‘activity’ including MRI variables (more easily accessible outcomes in the short term) rather then disability. Interpretation and presentation of these data have emphasized relative risk reductions and their highly significant <italic>p</italic>-values rather than the magnitude of clinical benefit (numbers needed to treat (NNT) and absolute risk reductions).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1352458512440604">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>All four RCTs have shown a statistically significant benefit on MRI outcomes and a reduction in the rate of conversion to CDMS within 2–3 years of CIS (NNT 6 [BENEFIT], 7 [CHAMPS] and 5.5 [PreCISe]), but the benefits were modest.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458512440604">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458512440604">6</xref></sup> These data may be enough to persuade some patients to commit to DMAs, and their request for early treatment with a DMA should be respected within the ‘shared decision-making’ model. For other patients, the data raise a more important question: does delaying the second attack or reducing MRI lesions reduce long-term disability?</p>
<p>In CIS, only the BENEFIT study was designed primarily to address whether early treatment with interferon beta-1b was better then delayed treatment at prevention of disability. Although the initial 3-year follow-up analysis revealed a highly statistically significant benefit of early compared with delayed treatment, the magnitude of clinical benefit was small: 12 patients need to be treated early to avoid one patient having an increase in Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score of one point or more.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1352458512440604">4</xref></sup> This benefit was not observed in patients with limited clinical signs or less than nine T2-weighted lesions on MRI. Most concerning, however, given the current treat-all approach in the USA, is the fact that the small benefit seen at 3 years was lost by the end of the 5-year observational period.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458512440604">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458512440604">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Furthermore in the BENEFIT study (as was observed in the CHAMPIONS 10-year extension study) the NNT at the 5-year point to prevent one patient converting to CDMS had increased to nine (with absolute risk reduction of 11%) from seven (absolute risk reduction 14%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458512440604">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458512440604">7</xref></sup> Thus despite delaying development of CDMS in some patients, no long-term benefit on disability was observed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458512440604">7</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1352458512440604">
<title>High costs (without proven efficacy) represent significant economic burden for patients and payers</title>
<p>A recent analysis of DMAs for treating MS reported that, on average, a patient with MS on DMA for 10 years would gain about 2 quality-adjusted months, and the cost far exceeded $800,000 per quality-adjusted life year.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1352458512440604">8</xref></sup> This is considered an order of magnitude greater then the cost effectiveness of commonly accepted therapies for other chronic illness.</p>
<p>The use of DMAs for CIS likely would have an even less favorable cost–benefit ratio. In fact, the potential cost of treating all new cases of CIS in the USA for a single year based on an incidence rate of 6/100,000 is half a billion dollars. Since therapy is ongoing (and potentially lifelong), the true cost is many multiples of this. This high cost at a time of finite healthcare resources, coupled with the parenteral administration and often bothersome side effects, requires ‘concrete’ and ‘clinically relevant’ evidence that DMA for CIS have some long-term disability benefit. This evidence, as outlined above, does not exist.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="section5-1352458512440604">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1352458512440604">
<title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>Dr Bunyan – nothing to disclose. Dr Pittock is a named inventor on patents (#12/678,350 filed 2010 and #12/573,942 filed 2008) that relate to functional AQP4/NMO-IgG assays and NMO-IgG as a cancer marker; receives research support from Alexion Pharmaceuticals, Inc, the Guthy Jackson Charitable Foundation, and the National Institutes of Health.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1352458512440604">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abou Zeid</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinically isolated syndromes</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lucchinetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hohlfeld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Multiple Sclerosis 3: Blue Books of Neurology</source>. <publisher-name>Saunders Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>, pp. <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1352458512440604">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisniku</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brex</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Disability and T2 MRI lesions: a 20-year follow-up of patients with relapse onset of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1352458512440604">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Polman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic criteria for multiple sclerosis: 2010 revisions to the McDonald criteria</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1352458512440604">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interferon beta in multiple sclerosis: how much BENEFIT?</article-title> <source>Lancet</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>370</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1352458512440604">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kappos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term effect of early treatment with interferon beta-1b after a first clinical event suggestive of multiple sclerosis: 5-year active treatment extension of the phase 3 BENEFIT trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>997</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1352458512440604">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Comi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodegher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of glatiramer acetate on conversion to clinically definite multiple sclerosis in patients with clinically isolated syndrome (PreCISe study): a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>374</volume>: <fpage>1503</fpage>–<lpage>1511</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1352458512440604">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Uncertain BENEFIT of early interferon beta-1b treatment</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>970</fpage>–<lpage>971</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1352458512440604">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bajorska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chappel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cost-effectiveness of disease-modifying therapy for multiple sclerosis: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>