<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spfas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Foot &amp; Ankle Specialist</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1938-6400</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-7636</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1938640012441926</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1938640012441926</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Change . . .</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Berlet</surname><given-names>Gregory C.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>90</fpage>
<lpage>90</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Ron Epstein, a key member of the visionary team behind FAS, has left to pursue other interests.</p>
<p>I am a member of a team, and I rely on the team, I defer to it and sacrifice for it, because the team, not the individual, is the ultimate champion.</p>
<attrib>—Mia Hamm</attrib>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>For those of you who know me, soccer has played a big role in our family for many years. Our two girls play most days of the week and maintain a busy travel schedule competing with the top clubs in the country. Their journey is much more than just a sport competition but rather a stage on which to develop their personalities and character.</p>
<p>This year will see my eldest heading to the College of Charleston to learn and join the Division I Women’s Soccer team. Exciting but a tough milestone for us as our first daughter is leaving the house. As we get ready for this transition we are also thoughtful to celebrate the successes along the way.</p>
<p>At <italic>FAS</italic> we have also seen a transition. Ron Epstein, a key member of the visionary team behind <italic>FAS</italic>, has left to pursue other interests. Ron and I have had bimonthly chats for several years. We talked about <italic>FAS</italic> as we built the editorial team, production team, and content to where you see it today. We also shared our family stories and became good friends. Ron put much more into this journal than conventional business practices would justify but he believed in the vision. For his vision, time, friendship, and mentoring I will be forever grateful.</p>
<p>We also say good bye to Sarah Carrera. Those who have interacted with the editorial team will know Sarah by her calm yet encouraging tone when deadlines were due or the article content needed some specific editing to reach the standards for publication. Sarah, we thank you, wish you well in your new pursuits, and hope you take great pride in what you helped create.</p>
<p>We are pleased to be joined by Melissa Stevens, who, as Publishing Editor, will assume the reigns of <italic>Foot and Ankle Specialist</italic>. On behalf of our <italic>FAS</italic> production team (Erin Nelson, Jesse Soll, Lowell, and I), we welcome you and are eager to help you create your own stamp on this journal.</p>
<p>The team we sacrifice for here is <italic>Foot and Ankle Specialist</italic>. We are proud of our heritage and look forward to 2012. Thank you to all who help us make <italic>FAS</italic> a different and effective medium for communication in the foot and ankle arena.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Gregory C. Berlet, MD<break/>
<italic>Editor</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>