<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LEC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splec</journal-id>
<journal-title>Local Economy: The Journal of the Local Economy Policy Unit</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0269-0942</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1470-9325</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269094212474241</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269094212474241</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Features</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Working with communities-of-place: Complexities of empowerment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Skerratt</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0269094212474241"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0269094212474241">SRUC, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>Artur</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-0269094212474241">SRUC, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Skerratt</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0269094212474241">Sarah Skerratt, Economy and Environment Research Group, Scotland’s Rural College (SRUC), King’s Buildings, Edinburgh, EH9 3JG, UK. Email: <email>sarah.skerratt@sruc.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Localism: Identifying complexities and ways forward for research and practice</issue-title>
<fpage>320</fpage>
<lpage>338</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">London South Bank University</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Recent legislative and other policy-related developments seek to enhance local agenda-setting through empowered communities. However, community <italic>development</italic> is separated from community <italic>empowerment</italic>, thus implicitly supporting a more uncritical perspective of empowerment processes. In this article we: (1) focus on communities who do not engage; (2) identify in-community sub-groups and differences as the norm rather than exception; (3) recognise the backwards and forwards motion of community development processes; (4) identify the fluidity of in-community interests and powers; and (5) recognise differences between individual and community-level aspirations. We use evidence from a development project which targets communities that do not engage. Based on interviews with the project manager, project officer, and 155 community members, we conclude that: demoting capacity-building betrays an intrinsic and naïve belief in self-fulfilling processes of community empowerment, rather than acknowledgement of complexities; there is a need, therefore, to remain sceptical in order that analyses are sensitive to complexities of empowerment.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>community empowerment</kwd>
<kwd>community engagement</kwd>
<kwd>community resilience</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0269094212474241"><title>The language of community empowerment in policy in Scotland</title>
<p>Increasingly within Scotland, there has been a shift towards the use of aspirational language concerning sustainable development of Scotland’s communities, with a key focus on empowerment and resilience. This is evident primarily within the National Performance Framework (NPF), the core of the Scottish Government’s Economic Strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0269094212474241">Scottish Government, 2007</xref>): ‘We have strong, resilient and supportive communities where people take responsibility for their own actions and how they affect others’ (Outcome 11).</p>
<p>Further, the Scottish Community Empowerment Action Plan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269094212474241">Scottish Government, 2009</xref>: 8) describes a ‘process where people work together to make change happen in their communities by having more power and influence over what matters to them’. This ‘invigorating democracy’ is considered achievable because:<disp-quote>
<p>Scotland’s communities are a rich source of talent and creative potential and the process of community empowerment helps to unlock that potential. It stimulates and harnesses the energy of local people to come up with creative and successful solutions to local challenges. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269094212474241">Scottish Government, 2009</xref>: 6)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>A second significant development is the proposed Community Empowerment and Renewal Bill (CERB) which aims to ‘strengthen opportunities for communities to take independent action to achieve their own goals and aspirations’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269094212474241">Scottish Government, 2009</xref>: 5). Under the heading ‘Involving all our communities’ (pp. 6–7), we read that capacity building for communities is important. However, it is not being addressed within the CERB; rather, it sits within the remit of Community Learning and Development (CLD) in the Strategic Guidance (2012) developed for Community Planning Partnerships (CPPs). Critically, this document remains as <italic>Guidance</italic> rather than <italic>legislation</italic> whereby:<disp-quote>
<p>We <italic>expect</italic> local authorities to provide clear leadership and direction, and to drive the action needed to ensure we maximise the contribution of CLD partners in the reform of public services … The implementation of this guidance <italic>must</italic> be led by CPPs, with support from Government bodies such as Education Scotland and with national and local Third Sector partners. It <italic>should</italic> form an integral part of public service reform, ensuring that Community Planning provides the vehicle to deliver better outcomes in partnership with communities. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0269094212474241">Scottish Government, 2009</xref>: 1; emphases added)</p></disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0269094212474241"><title>Why such language and distinctions matter</title>
<p>Such distinctions are critical because capacity building, or development, is now separated from empowerment, and is demoted to Guidance rather than being part of the legislative remit. This stance echoes the dominant, largely uncritical assumption which persists around community empowerment: that it takes place largely in a spontaneous, self-regulating, inclusive and organic way. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269094212474241">Edwards (2009</xref>: 50) states that what he terms ‘civil society revivalists’:<disp-quote>
<p>insist that voluntary social interaction produces high and generalised levels of trust and cooperation, which in turn are essential for democracy and social progress. Their key hypothesis is that communities, networks and associations are ‘micro-climates’ in which skills are learned, values and loyalties are developed, and caring and cooperation – instead of competition and violence – become the rational ways to behave.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Other similarly uncritical takes on community-level empowerment processes include Asset Based Community Development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269094212474241">Kretzmann and McKnight, 1993</xref>) which has the primary focus on a community developing its assets, rather than focusing on any deficits or conflicts. Other such examples of civil society and empowerment processes include Puttnam’s work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0269094212474241">Putnam, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0269094212474241">Putnam et al., 1993</xref>) on social capital (increasingly critiqued, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0269094212474241">Portes, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0269094212474241">Svendsen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0269094212474241">Svendsen and Svendsen, 2000</xref>), and Oldenburg’s work on the ‘Great Good Place’ (1999, 2001).</p>
<p>This unrelentingly positive approach raises concerns for some commentators. In a specifically rural community context, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0269094212474241">Shortall (2004</xref>: 110) is unequivocal: ‘ … the social capital debate gives renewed impetus to a romantic, naïve view of rural communities, where civic harmony and inclusion triumphs and there is little room for power struggles, exclusionary tactics by privileged groups, or ideological conflicts’. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist (2009</xref>: 1, 6, 130) stresses that:<disp-quote>
<p>it is important to remember that references to community values and identities have also been used to generate conflict and to resist change … Within communities, diversity can be enriching and dynamic, but it also needs careful attention, particularly where inequalities and incompatibilities generate unease and misunderstanding … People’s sense of ‘community’ … reflects real experience and emotions, encompassing the negative aspects of human relationships, as well as rose-tinted notions of belonging, trust and loyalty.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269094212474241">Hayward et al. (2004</xref>: 95) similarly write of ‘the uncritical use of development rhetoric such as “capacity building”, “empowerment” and “participation”’ in a rural development context, and the need therefore to reflect on the ‘problematic nature of some of these assumptions’.</p>
<p>This ‘problematic nature’ is seen to matter because otherwise the focus simply on empowerment, rather than development and capacity-building, omits the complexities inherent within communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269094212474241">Henderson and Versceg, 2010</xref>: 87). It also means that there is an expectation that short-term empowerment projects will produce community-wide empowerment outcomes, whereas experiences show that longer-term interventions are required which are: ‘sensitive to differences within communities; manage tensions and expectations; and include a variety of ways for people to contribute their ideas’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist, 2009</xref>: 32). This has implications for inclusion and democratic representation, rather than simply going at the pace of the most articulate and project-literate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist, 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269094212474241">Shucksmith (2000</xref>: 212) also makes this key point in relation to the LEADER programme across Europe, where he states that ‘it is the most privileged who are able to mobilize and win funding in a short time-scale, since they already have a greater capacity to act’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0269094212474241"><title>What does the wider literature tell about the importance of understanding community-level complexities?</title>
<sec id="sec4-0269094212474241"><title>Communities who do not engage or participate</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0269094212474241">Shortall (2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0269094212474241">2008</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269094212474241">Shucksmith (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0269094212474241">2010</xref>) have highlighted the need to examine capacity at local community level for inclusive development, civic engagement and governance processes which ensure that community participation in development does not favour only the articulate, well networked and vocal – or what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0269094212474241">Taylor (2003</xref>: 229) calls the ‘committee-literate’. This is because: ‘More marginalized groups are less able to participate or engage with the programme, and are less likely to be empowered unless explicit attention is given to their inclusion’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269094212474241">Shucksmith, 2000</xref>: 215)</p>
<p>Significantly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269094212474241">Aiken et al. (2011)</xref> also found that the availability of skills to engage (and take over and develop an asset) depended on where the asset was situated: ‘more affluent areas … benefited from the availability of people locally who had a range of professional skills, but these skills might not be available in more disadvantaged areas’ (p. 61). This potential disparity between communities’ capacities is also highlighted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269094212474241">Dobson (2011</xref>: 2), who states that: ‘the paradox of localism is that it offers opportunities for the innovator and experimenter, but allows other to fall behind’. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0269094212474241">Skerratt and Hall (2012</xref>: 675) also note that: ‘human, social and political capitals, like all capitals, are likely to be unequally distributed’, thus affecting abilities to take over and develop assets.</p>
<p>Before jumping to a normative stance that ‘to participate’ is <italic>the</italic> indicator of a ‘healthy, vibrant’ community with high levels of empowerment, we must highlight that: ‘non-participation may well be a rational survival strategy among populations that have other priorities and tactics for coping with long-term disadvantage’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist, 2009</xref>: 32). Further, ‘non-participation (in rural development) can represent a valid and legitimate choice and often one made from a position of power’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0269094212474241">Shortall, 2008</xref>: 452), particularly where rural citizens are already participating in their civic networks which enhance community’s social capital (p. 455).</p>
<p>So, in our research evidence presented below, we are not proposing that to participate is by definition ‘good’ and not to participate is by definition ‘bad’ or ‘dysfunctional’. Rather, we are saying that within the research community, researchers have concerns about non-participation either as evidence of social exclusion, and/or due to its normative associations. Consequently, accuracy about modes of non-participation is required.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0269094212474241"><title>In-community sub-groups and potential differences as the norm</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269094212474241">Edwards (2009</xref>: 50) expresses his concerns relating to the romanticised notion of communities: ‘So far so good – until the <italic>genie of difference</italic> is introduced into the equation … ’ (emphasis added). As argued, not only do different sub-groups exist, but they have unequal capacities to act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269094212474241">Shucksmith, 2000</xref>), and are defined by complicated patterns with ‘different perceptions, interests, resources and amounts of influence’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269094212474241">Crona and Bodin, 2006</xref>: 1–2). This diversity has implications for the efficacy of community development in practice, since a key part is: ‘identifying central and potentially influential actors’ within place-based communities, as well as those who remain outside the influential circle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269094212474241">Crona and Bodin, 2006</xref>: 1–2).</p>
<p>Further, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist (2009</xref>: 145) notes that: ‘People tend to associate with people who are like themselves, and this dimension of networking militates against inclusion and equality of opportunity’. Despite concerns, there are some researchers who outline the benefits of multiple sub-groups in communities-of-place, since such differences (or what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269094212474241">Hirschi (2010)</xref> calls ‘fragmentation’) are important in enhancing the <italic>sustainability</italic> of rural community development initiatives, even if they may be counterproductive in <italic>earlier</italic> stages. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0269094212474241">Newman and Dale (2005</xref>: 1) argue that: ‘Diversity … is critical to a community’s ability to move beyond adaptive management to proactively maintain and enhance resiliency’.</p>
<p>Finally, researchers recognise that these sub-groups and affiliations are not static, but fluid, ebbing and flowing due to particular circumstances or potential change in local environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0269094212474241">Maguire and Cartwright, 2008</xref>). Such sub-groups are thus embedded in the local heuristic system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269094212474241">High and Nemes, 2007</xref>: 105) and are highly specific to context and shared histories. Understanding this temporal component is therefore important.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0269094212474241"><title>The backwards and forwards motion of community development processes</title>
<p>Temporality also appears as a dimension when considering processes of development. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269094212474241">Henderson and Versceg (2010</xref>: 96) note: ‘Community development … in reality … is usually full of turmoil, false starts, victories and confusion … ’. Many researchers and practitioners agree that rural community development is <italic>non-linear</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269094212474241">Cleaver 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269094212474241">Hegney et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269094212474241">McIntosh et al., 2008</xref>), contrasting with linear processes anticipated by funders and in policy fields.</p>
<p>Further, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269094212474241">Khotari (2001</xref>: 147) states that: ‘participatory development techniques do not easily accommodate chance happenings, or unplanned or irregular occurrences’. Echoing this, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269094212474241">Cleaver (2004</xref>: 275–276) states that: ‘in considering the time-space dimensions of participation, we should be concerned with the possibility of stoppages and reversals in the transformatory direction, and also with the inherent limitations of ad hoc, infrequent collective action’. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269094212474241">Cheers and Luloff (2001)</xref> also note the ‘episodic’ nature of participation in practice, stating that it often ‘intensif[ies] in response to particular issues, problems, interests and challenges, especially perceived crises’ (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269094212474241">Hayward et al., 2004</xref>: 105). Research therefore needs to be designed to pick up these nuances.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0269094212474241"><title>The entrenchment and/or fluidity of interests and powers</title>
<p>As noted, there is an understanding that differences within communities can be directly linked with existing power-structures and exclusive/inclusive behaviours. These may pre-date and sometimes outlast, development efforts, with a number of authors’ analyses of community social relations querying the extent to which hierarchies, social strata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269094212474241">Gray, 2005</xref>) and associated norms on the ground can change as a result of community development projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269094212474241">Brennan and Lullof, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269094212474241">Brunori and Rossi, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269094212474241">Clark et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0269094212474241">Healey et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0269094212474241">Magnani and Struffi, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0269094212474241">Woods et al., 2006</xref>); and do change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269094212474241">Clark et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269094212474241">Day, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0269094212474241">Paniagua, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269094212474241">Mackleworth and Caric (2010)</xref> found that the ‘gatekeepers’ involved in sustainable development initiatives behaved according to local accepted power structures that pre-dated sustainable development projects. Such projects were seen as a threat to the status quo of established relationships and leadership, particularly in more isolated communities (pp. 476–477). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0269094212474241">Sorensen and Epps (1996</xref>: 124) highlighted how the ‘culture of rural Australia’ meant that people were bound by ‘fairly rigid formalities’ relating to traditions of seniority, respect, dominance of landed interests, suspicion of outsiders, and ‘divisions between town and bush’. Authors point to the disempowering as well as empowering aspects of such intra-community relations, and variously debate ‘empowering for whom’ (Crona and Bodin, 2010; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269094212474241">Hayward et al., 2004</xref>). Who is empowered, and disempowered, through ‘community empowerment’, therefore needs to be explored rather than assumed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0269094212474241"><title>The differentiation between individual and community-level lives and aspirations</title>
<p>Research pointing to non-participation, to sub-groups within communities of place, and to the fluidity or otherwise of in-community power relations, also throws light onto an emerging theme: that there are differences between individual and community aspirations and lives. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269094212474241">Henderson and Versceg (2010</xref>: 19) capture this tension when they observe the need for ‘a more modern interpretation of community (which) synthesises two seemingly contradictory yet very basic human needs: belonging and freedom’. This appears to point to a need for a more ‘personalised’ approach to understanding communities, with the ‘person-in-community/ies’ as the unit of analysis, rather than ‘the community’. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269094212474241">Cleaver (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269094212474241">2004</xref>) has pointed to the ‘non-project lives’ of people in rural communities (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269094212474241">Gray, 2005</xref>), which directly inform how hierarchies are collectively operationalised in community settings:<disp-quote>
<p>many interactions between people also take place outside formal organisations … Interactions of daily life may be more important in shaping co-operation than public negotiations … People may indirectly affect outcomes without direct participation. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269094212474241">Cleaver, 2001</xref>: 42, 54)</p></disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0269094212474241"><title>Exploring these themes through empirical research</title>
<sec id="sec10-0269094212474241"><title>Introduction to Capacity for Change</title>
<p>Capacity for Change (C4C), one of the Dumfries and Galloway LEADER Programmes,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0269094212474241">1</xref></sup> deliberately seeks to address capacity raising and community resilience <italic>with communities who have not engaged</italic>. C4C is a two-year programme (2011–2013) that involves LEADER staff working with communities that they consider to be ‘less-resourced’ and who have not engaged with LEADER or with other funding streams in any significant way. The focus of the programme is on villages located in Dumfries and Galloway which is a mostly rural region in south-west of Scotland (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0269094212474241">Figure 1</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0269094212474241">2</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig1-0269094212474241" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Geographical location of the C4C programme<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0269094212474241">3</xref></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269094212474241-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>LEADER staff engage in activities and processes that identify and build on a community’s existing capacity, working with communities to identify their preferred direction(s) and approach(es), rather than focusing on project delivery. Our role as researchers is to monitor and evaluate C4C throughout its implementation, from pre-planning through to post-completion. Our aim is to assess the contribution of C4C to community resilience, with the ultimate aim being to develop a framework which will help identify social and economic outcomes associated with C4C-type project investments.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0269094212474241"><title>Analytical methods and approaches</title>
<sec id="sec12-0269094212474241"><title>Using the framework of community resilience</title>
<p>The focus of the C4C project is on enhancing the capacity and resilience of rural communities. Despite increasing interest in <italic>community resilience</italic>, defining and measuring the concept is complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0269094212474241">Pendall et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0269094212474241">Wilson 2012</xref>). In general, resilience could be seen as the capacity of a system ‘to absorb disturbance and re-organise while undergoing change so as to still retain essentially the same function, structure, identity, and feedbacks’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269094212474241">Folke, 2006</xref>: 259). Community resilience, on the other hand, is perceived to be:<disp-quote>
<p>the existence, development, and <bold>engagement</bold> of community resources <bold>by community members</bold> to thrive in an environment characterized by change, uncertainty, unpredictability, and surprise. Members of resilient communities intentionally develop <bold>personal and collective capacity</bold> that they engage to respond to and influence change, to sustain and renew the community and to develop new trajectories for the communities’ future. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269094212474241">Magis 2010</xref>: 402)</p></disp-quote>Consequently, empowerment seems to be an important component of the concept of resilience because, in order to develop community resilience, community members have to be able to actively engage in building the capacity to thrive in an environment characterized by change. Therefore empowered communities, as suggested, are more likely to possess the ability to anticipate, and adapt to, stresses and changes and to transform into more desirable states.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0269094212474241"><title>Analytical framework</title>
<p>Existing evidence presents community resilience as a multidimensional concept with different <italic>scales/levels</italic> of resilience (including individual and community) and different <italic>thematic aspects</italic> associated with social and economic resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0269094212474241">Steinerowski and Markantoni, 2012</xref>) leading us to develop a model consisting of four resiliency outcomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269094212474241">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig id="fig2-0269094212474241" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Components of resilience.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269094212474241-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>In order to prepare for implementing the model empirically and measuring resilience in the communities-of-place, the development of this analytical framework was followed up with three consecutive stages:
<list id="list1-0269094212474241" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Stage 1 – ‘unpacked’ the four identified components of resilience and verified how social and economic resilience at both individual and community levels are described, defined and measured. The process required rigorous review of existing international evidence and enabled recognition of themes and elements in the four resiliency categories.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Stage 2 <bold>–</bold> consisted of a scoping-study in villages of Dumfries and Galloway. The aim was to validate and to ‘challenge’ findings from Stage 1. A number of focus groups were organised in local villages, plus researchers visited communities that were perceived (by the C4C project team) as thriving with active citizens, and other ‘less successful’ places in which a number of services have been withdrawn over the recent years and where local people have not significantly engaged in community development projects.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Stage 3 – as a result of Stages 1 and 2, we created a <italic>hybrid evaluation model</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269094212474241">High and Nemes, 2007</xref>) which underpinned Stage 3 <bold><italic>–</italic></bold> where we then identified parallel areas and themes within the four resiliency dimensions<italic>.</italic></p></list-item>
</list>Based on Stages 1, 2 and 3, the most appropriate themes for capturing resilience were identified and used to develop research questions that explored social and economic resiliency outcomes at individual and community levels.</p>
<p>The research questions were designed to enable respondents to give answers using a scale from zero (i.e. very negative) to 10 (i.e. very positive). For each of the four categories, a combination of responses is used to determine the level of resilience. Within each category, all criteria are weighted equally and present a mean of collected scores. To gain richer data about resilience, a number of qualitative questions were added to the model – to understand responses better and provide in-depth information and examples about case study communities (thus helping to answer <italic>what, why</italic> and <italic>how</italic> questions). The questionnaire was pre-tested; content and phrasing were revised to improve the clarity of the questionnaire and minimise bias in the responses.</p>
<p>In order to measure change over time, the study takes a longitudinal approach with data collection before the initiation of the C4C programme and consecutively after its completion (2013–2015). In this article we present data from the initial stage of the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0269094212474241"><title>Data sources</title>
<p>The data presented below are based on two sources (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0269094212474241">Table 1</xref>); first, interviews with the C4C project manager and project officer, enabling us to capture observations and decisions of experienced community development workers actively involved in the programme; second, data from 155 face-to-face, semi-structured interviews with C4C community members identified through snowball sampling which aimed to consist of people with diversified socio-demographic characteristics (thus capturing a wide range of perspectives on community life) from six small villages (i.e. around 500 inhabitants). The six villages were perceived, by the C4C project manager and officer, to be ‘disadvantaged’ and less resourced – which have not engaged with LEADER or other major funding streams in a significant way. Less-resourced communities were defined in this project as communities which have lost some or the majority of local services over recent years. Quantitative data were analysed using earlier developed model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269094212474241">Figure 2</xref>) and qualitative analysis was mainly inductive conducted through a thematic analysis identifying any recurrent patterns. All interviewees were ensured of anonymity in research outputs.
<table-wrap id="table1-0269094212474241" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Data matrix.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0269094212474241" xlink:href="10.1177_0269094212474241-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Theme</th>
<th colspan="3">Data source</th>
</tr>
<tr><th>Interviews with project manager and project officer</th>
<th>Qualitative information from interviews with C4C community members</th>
<th>Quantitative information from the C4C interviews and analytical framework</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Theme 1 – Communities who never engage</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Theme 2 – Sub-groups as the norm</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>X</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Theme 3 – Backwards and forwards movements</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>X</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Theme 4 – Powers</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>X</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Theme 5 – Individual and community levels</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
<td>V</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0269094212474241"><p>V – empirical data evidence supporting discussed themes.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0269094212474241"><p>X – findings which will emerge through a longitudinal study.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0269094212474241"><title>Findings</title>
<sec id="sec16-0269094212474241"><title>Communities who have not engaged</title>
<p>The need for working with communities who never engage with local funding streams was articulated by the local project manager:<disp-quote>
<p>The first thing was that we identified that there were some communities that never approached LEADER … they didn’t seem to have any ideas for a need for funding … We started to plot on a map of locations where we have funded projects and it was quite obvious that there were geographic corridors within Dumfries and Galloway where there seem to be lack of community activity.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Analysis of previously funded LEADER projects in Dumfries and Galloway identified that particular communities regularly apply for external grants to run community projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0269094212474241">Skerratt, 2012</xref>). This could in itself be perceived as positive: certain communities are already empowered and capable of generating community project ideas, developing grant applications and finding match funding. If successful, those communities can secure resources and develop their villages. This, however, leaves other (possibly less capable or less empowered) communities without the support and opportunities for development. Hence, strong, proactive and entrepreneurial communities become even stronger while communities less capable of generating community project ideas do not access essential support, potentially becoming weaker (which is against the ethos of rural development agencies).</p>
<p>Interestingly however, evidence indicates that offering help without being necessarily asked for it might be misinterpreted:<disp-quote>
<p>It is important that the first step comes from a community. It’s not us going to a village and selecting them. In Village 1 people said: ‘you’ve selected us so there must be something wrong about the village so do something about it’. This is not how it works … It is important that the first step after initial or baseline information comes from the community. (Project Officer)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>One village which was offered C4C support did not express interest in the programme and was characterised by ‘lack of enthusiasm and community determination’. The project officer highlighted that lack of engagement made it impossible to successfully run the project:<disp-quote>
<p>Village 2 didn’t really grasp the potential of C4C. It was perceived just as a funding stream despite us trying to reassure that it’s not necessarily about the money, it’s about the process and getting village together and working towards common good.. Once we familiarised them with the C4C concept, we mentioned that it’s their project that they need to develop it and take forward, it became quite clear that majority of community couldn’t be mobilised to get behind it. We tried second time and (...) they were going to discuss it and they didn’t want to put their time to develop this.</p></disp-quote>Respondents claimed that:<disp-quote>
<p>these days people are too busy with work, they don’t have time for community projects. (Community Member 3)</p></disp-quote>and that:<disp-quote>
<p>they will use local facilities and take advantage of community projects but they won’t invest any of their time to help us. (Community Member 8)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Based on project officer observations, in order for a community to benefit from a development project, its members need to be engaged in designing and running it:<disp-quote>
<p>It should come from communities to make it a sustainable project or something with a sustainable outcome and my role as a C4C project officer is to draw out some ideas and get things started and it’s not that we’re dictating things … it’s about them coming and exploring this.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>C4C village interviewees indicated that, at the community level, community members do have opportunities to engage in community life and a range of community initiatives, with information about local events being distributed through door-to-door leaflets, online mailing systems, local information boards as well as through word of mouth. The major challenge to wider community participation is, however, reported to be lack of time. Some respondents claimed that they would get involved in participative activates tailored to their interests but no commitment to organising or maintaining such ‘community interest groups’ was observed. In one of the villages, for example, despite setting up a community garden, few people decided to support the initiative. Further, a number of interviewees claimed that negative previous experience (such as failure of existing projects due to disagreements between community members) discourages them from being engaged in a community life. Thus, historical events and internal community relationships also appear to be a reason for non-engagement. Lack of engagement from local people was described by interviewees as a barrier to creating new community projects and for the potential failure of existing initiatives.</p>
<p>The quantitative findings presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0269094212474241">Figure 3</xref> confirm a relatively high level of encouragement to participate in community life across all villages. The data show that the extent to which the communities <italic>succeed</italic> in developing and improving their villages is, however, lower in five out of six villages.
<fig id="fig3-0269094212474241" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Levels of encouragement to participate in community life and the extent to which communities succeed in developing their villages (where 0 is very negative and 10 is very positive).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0269094212474241-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-0269094212474241"><title>In-community sub-groups and potential differences are the norm rather than the exception</title>
<p>Communities consist of a number of different groups of people with different perceptions and different vision. Our data show that different points of view can cause disagreements and that these can appear at any time and in relation to any area of community/village life. For instance, when exploring approaches to new business development, some interviewees emphasised that new business ventures could change the dynamics within villages, bringing undesirable changes; this group of people appreciated ‘peace and safety’, perceiving their village as a ‘residential’ rather than ‘business’ area. Other interviewees stressed that community members should encourage new business creation, claiming that these are essential in building a sustainable village. Different groups of people have different needs and, consequently, promote different community initiatives. Possibly, rather than abnormality, differences in between community sub-groups could be perceived as something that is natural. Our evidence shows that the lack of communication, lack of dialogue and misinterpretation of other ideas can lead to conflict and disagreements.</p>
<p>As noted by the C4C project officer, some sub-groups are more vocal in expressing their views and priorities for community development. Opinions of other less powerful groups might not therefore be well articulated. Yet, a need for democratic community structures was noted:<disp-quote>
<p>Social structure of the village was already established and people didn’t really challenge this … It was left to a few individuals to get on with things and everybody was fine with it. Now people are talking to each other and the committees realise that they don’t necessarily know what’s in the best interest for the whole village.. Key individuals came along and incorporated other views and opened up to the community. (Project Officer)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The data show that the ‘social structures’ within communities can change and that C4C, although sometimes challenging, initiated a process of including views of wider groups within a community.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-0269094212474241"><title>The backwards and forwards motions of community development processes</title>
<p>Our data show that implementing and running community projects is neither straightforward, linear nor of one pattern. The C4C project officer stated that each community is different and it is important to use appropriate strategies to engage communities. It was emphasised that there are periods in which a community might progress their projects and then, on other occasions, slow down or even reverse achieved progress. Consequently, it is necessary to constantly oversee project activities and resolve any problems in their initial stage:<disp-quote>
<p>I was disappointed as I’ve spoken to people about C4C and I got positive feedback and all of a sudden it turned around.. It’s been a rollercoaster … now it’s positive – they’re very focused and constructive so it has changed quite a lot. (Project Officer)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Interestingly, data from qualitative interviews with C4C community members reveal a high community spirit during moments of crisis when, for example, community members face a threat of losing an existing service (e.g. local school) or mobilise around an issue of shared concern (such as the development of a local waste dump). These two examples originate from communities that were described by the C4C project officer as those that are least participative across all C4C locations. Thus, it seems that moments of ‘crisis’ that bring anxiety and worry to the majority of community members, and that a visible rapid change or shock to their life helps to gather people together. These present backwards and forwards motions of community processes during which communities may appear ‘inactive’ and, when needed, become mobilised and active.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec19-0269094212474241"><title>The entrenchment and/or fluidity of interests and powers at community level</title>
<p>In the C4C programme we observe fluidity of interests and powers at community level. Frequently, as noted by many respondents, there are ‘the usual suspects’ or ‘natural community leaders’ who take decisions on behalf of the communities, appear to resolve problems and actively participate in life in the village. Although interviewees recognise that this in itself it could be perceived as positive, some felt that new ideas that emerge from those people who usually do not engage in community life are not welcomed. These can, potentially, lead to disagreements amongst community members or lack of democratic community engagement. Evidence from the research indicates that sometimes, due to different points of view, community projects are hindered in their embryonic stage. Interviewees claimed that those who experience this are less likely to participate in the future.</p>
<p>Our findings indicate that, sometimes, the engagement of key individuals or community leaders might not only be insufficient but destructive. It is likely that certain structures of power or ‘partial empowerment’ disempowers communities as a whole.<disp-quote>
<p>In terms of challenges, I certainly underestimated the power structures in Village 1… It was taken forward by one very active group or committee in the village and it was perceived as theirs.. it’s their obligation or responsibility to do this and now somebody else is coming in! (Project Officer)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Thus, it appears that it is not just about engagement and empowerment but about a particular type of process – one that is inclusive and considers wider interests of communities and not only individuals within it. The C4C project manager and project officer highlighted that those who hold the power in a community might be both supportive and very destructive.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec20-0269094212474241"><title>The differences between individual and community-level lives and aspirations</title>
<p>According to the LEADER team, and as highlighted in earlier interview quotes, some natural differences exist between individual and community-level lives and aspirations. It is important to bring the two together and, in some communities, evidence of joint working was identified:<disp-quote>
<p>In Village 3 the driving force at the moment are people from the community council who are really keen to make a positive change to the village but we’ve also managed to get few other people coming in to widen our scope a bit. In terms of Village 4, people agree that they would like to bring two parts of the village together – people from both parts of the village expresses their commitment to the project. (Project Officer)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Based on qualitative findings from interviews with C4C community members, a need to create better links between individuals within a community was identified:<disp-quote>
<p>there is nothing in the village so people don’t meet and don’t talk to each other. We don’t have a shop, we don’t have a pub … everything is closed now … we need a place where we could meet, get together again and think about how to improve things in our village. (Community Member 23)</p></disp-quote>Respondents indicated that there are limited opportunities for socialising and this has a negative impact on [what we as researchers might interpret as] the community cohesion and community integrity. For instance, in one of the villages a number of services have been withdrawn including local pubs, local church and local shops. These places, in addition to their primary functions, reportedly played an important part in enhancing inter-connectivity of the communities, creating invisible ‘glue’ which helped communities function well. Our evidence shows that lack of community meeting places can also lead to differences between individuals and community-levels vision. Thus, although interviewees referred to challenges of limited access to services such as a medical centre, the post office and public transport, they emphasised a need for creating a cafe/meeting point for local people. Thus, establishing meeting places, connecting paths and other means of creating spaces for connection in the villages were identified as important C4C projects.</p>
<p>Finally, based on the C4C analytical framework (as presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0269094212474241">Figure 2</xref>), the findings presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0269094212474241">Table 2</xref> help to highlight the differences between individual and community-level of resilience, economic and social aspects of <italic>individual</italic> resilience received higher scores than their <italic>community</italic> equivalents.
<table-wrap id="table2-0269094212474241" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Levels of individual and community resilience across six communities.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0269094212474241" xlink:href="10.1177_0269094212474241-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Individual</th>
<th>Community</th>
<th>Average scores</th>
<th>Difference between individual and community scores</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td rowspan="6">Social</td>
<td>Village 1 – 6.43</td>
<td>6.41</td>
<td>6.42</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 2 – 7.63</td>
<td>6.8</td>
<td>7.21</td>
<td>0.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 3 – 7.37</td>
<td>5.84</td>
<td>6.59</td>
<td>1.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 4 – 7.63</td>
<td>5.01</td>
<td>6.32</td>
<td>2.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 5 – 7.58</td>
<td>6.12</td>
<td>6.85</td>
<td>1.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 6 – 8.15</td>
<td>6.25</td>
<td>7.20</td>
<td>1.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="6">Economic</td>
<td>Village 1 – 3.96</td>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.81</td>
<td>0.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 2 – 4.31</td>
<td>3.96</td>
<td>4.13</td>
<td>0.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 3 – 5.00</td>
<td>5.74</td>
<td>5.37</td>
<td>−0.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 4 – 5.43</td>
<td>4.23</td>
<td>4.83</td>
<td>1.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 5 – 5.01</td>
<td>4.97</td>
<td>4.99</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 6 – 5.74</td>
<td>5.56</td>
<td>5.65</td>
<td>0.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="6">Average scores</td>
<td>Village 1 – 5.20</td>
<td>5.04</td>
<td><bold>5.12</bold></td>
<td rowspan="6"><bold>Overall resilience</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 2 – 5.97</td>
<td>5.38</td>
<td><bold>5.67</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 3 – 6.19</td>
<td>5.79</td>
<td><bold>5.99</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 4 – 6.53</td>
<td>4.62</td>
<td><bold>5.58</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 5 – 6.30</td>
<td>5.54</td>
<td><bold>5.92</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 6 – 6.94</td>
<td>5.91</td>
<td><bold>6.43</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="6">Difference between economic  and social scores</td>
<td>Village 1 – 2.47</td>
<td>2.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 2 – 3.32</td>
<td>2.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 3 – 2.37</td>
<td>0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 4 – 2.20</td>
<td>0.78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 5 – 2.57</td>
<td>1.15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Village 6 – 2.41</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>This means that individuals evaluate their personal circumstances as better than those that exist at a community level. For instance, despite limited local economic resources, individuals from communities draw on available external resources (e.g. job opportunities, services and products) in order to increase personal economic resilience. This could indicate that although empowerment happens or exists at the individual level, it does not necessarily translate into community empowerment. This illustrates potential differences between perceptions, expectations and aspirations of individuals as compared with the entire community. Further, low perception of resilience at community level could suggest low levels of social capital, weak links between community groups or lack of social cohesion. This refers to the findings from the qualitative interviews in which respondents admitted that bringing people together and encouraging them to work together to achieve common good would be beneficial for local citizens. Lack of engagement might be a reason of these relatively low scores in social community resilience.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec21-0269094212474241" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="sec22-0269094212474241"><title>Non-engagement</title>
<p>According to the wider literature, the push towards empowerment (without development) takes insufficient account of the complexities of community processes, particularly amongst those who do not engage – either through choice or through exclusion. Our findings show that the ‘geographic corridors’ of non-engagement were felt, by the LEADER team, to be part of their remit, and that the C4C project was concerned with creating the right environment within which communities could choose whether or not to engage. Villagers themselves point to the fact that there are opportunities to engage in community activities, but that lack of time and previous negative experiences are barriers to development and reasons for failure of initiatives. These findings seem to support those critical of the ‘civil society revivalists’, as well as supporting the research highlighting the choice <italic>not</italic> to participate as being legitimate and making sense in a local context.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec23-0269094212474241"><title>Sub-groups</title>
<p>The wider literature also points to the fact that sub-groups are part of the normal make-up of communities-of-place; what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269094212474241">Edwards (2009</xref>: 50) calls the ‘genie of difference’. Such sub-groups are fluid, have unequal capacities to act, different levels of influence, can be elitist yet can nonetheless enhance the sustainability of community initiatives. Our findings showed groups who prioritise different aspects of village life: peace and safety, or business development and entrepreneurship. Interviewees highlight that it is disagreement and lack of dialogue that leads to misinterpretation on these issues; the C4C project officer also noted that widening the range of voices being represented from sub-groups leads to different views being incorporated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec24-0269094212474241"><title>Non-linear processes</title>
<p>The review of literature showed how community development is full of false-starts, chance happenings, irregular occurrences and reversals, and as such is non-linear. It is also episodic, particularly in response to perceived crises. These observations are reflected in our fieldwork findings, where the C4C project officer outlined how the processes move forward, then slow down or even ‘reverse’. The episodic nature of development is reflected in the villager interviews, where coming together over specific issues was observed, followed by a dissolving of development activity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec25-0269094212474241"><title>In-community power relations</title>
<p>A key point to emerge from the literature is the existence of power relations which may pre-date, and sometimes outlast, development initiatives, having implications for who is actually empowered within a supposed ‘community empowerment’ project. Such themes are echoed in our findings. Interviewees noted ‘the usual suspects’ and the ‘natural community leaders’, whilst also stating that views from ‘others’ in the community were not typically welcomed, and led to a lack of desire to participate in the future. Interviewees highlighted how those with power might either be supportive or destructive.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec26-0269094212474241"><title>Individuals and communities</title>
<p>In the literature, distinction is made between individual-level and community-level aspirations, views and priorities. The ‘non-project lives’ of people were highlighted, as was the fact that not all in-community relations and encounters are productive or ‘positive’ (in a developmental sense). From our findings, we can see how the project officer sought to bring individuals together, to ‘widen the scope’ and to involve people in developing a ‘village approach’. Interviewees in the villages described how locations for socialising and simply bumping into each other (such as shops, local pubs or church) had declined, and interestingly many of the C4C projects focus on creating shared spaces or physical connections between parts of the village. Further, from the quantitative data, it was also possible to observe a distinction between self-reported <italic>individual</italic> economic and social aspects of resilience which were reported as higher than perceptions of <italic>community</italic> resilience.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec27-0269094212474241" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>We began our article by outlining the increased (policy) momentum towards community empowerment, which appears to at worst side-line, or at best demote, capacity building and development which in fact enable such empowerment to take place. Such a process betrays, in our view, an intrinsic and naïve belief in the self-fulfilling processes of community empowerment. In order to query this increasingly dominant stance, we have sought to identify, through exploring a project designed to enhance capacity and resilience, the ‘noise in the system’.</p>
<p>Rather than supporting the ‘civil society revivalist’ stance, our findings, and the wider literature we have reviewed, stands closer to what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269094212474241">Edwards (2009</xref>: 92–96) has termed the ‘School of Sceptics’, whereby: ‘a more dispassionate stance will allow analysts to consider all facets … and prevent turning the ensuing literature into an unmitigated celebration of community’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0269094212474241">Portes 1999</xref>: 22, cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0269094212474241">Shucksmith, 2000</xref>: 211). This is because, as we have seen: ‘The reality of community life encompasses many different identities and allegiances … that characterise people’s real lives, their histories, current preoccupations, enthusiasms and future aspirations’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269094212474241">Gilchrist, 2009</xref>: 6). What this means is that we do not seek, as researchers, to ‘return to some imaginary past where people were nicer to their neighbours and the land flowed with milk, honey and social capital’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269094212474241">Edwards, 2009</xref>: 107). We have sought instead to build our research, deliberately, around the <italic>complexities of empowerment</italic>, rather than either trying to fit such complexities in retrospectively, or keep them out because they do not fit our neat categorisations.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>This research was undertaken as part of the Scottish Government’s Strategic Research Programme ‘Governance and decision-making for community empowerment’ 2011–2016. We would also like to thank the LEADER team managing the C4C project and interviewees in the villages.</p></ack>
<sec id="sec28-0269094212474241">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-0269094212474241"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dumgal.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=7166">http://www.dumgal.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=7166</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-0269094212474241"><label>2</label><p>According to Scottish Government 6-fold Urban/Rural classification: 21.9% of D&amp;G population lives in remote rural; 25.0% in accessible rural; 7.6% in small towns; 17.3% in accessible small towns; 28.1% in other urban areas. In the region, there are no people living in large urban areas.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-0269094212474241"><label>3</label><p>Source: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dumgal.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=4372">http://www.dumgal.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=4372</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Aiken M, Cairns B, Taylor M, et al. (2011) <italic>Community Organisations Controlling Assets: A Better Understanding</italic>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.jrf.org.uk/publications/community-organisationscontrolling-assets">www.jrf.org.uk/publications/community-organisationscontrolling-assets</ext-link> (accessed 10 July 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Luloff</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Exploring rural community agency differences in Ireland and Pennsylvania</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunori</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Differentiating countryside: Social representations and governance patterns in rural areas with high social density: The case of Chianti, Italy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Luloff</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Rural community development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lockie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Rurality Bites: The Social and Environmental Transformation of Rural Australia</source>, <publisher-loc>Annandale, NSW</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Rural governance, community empowerment and the new institutionalism: A case study of the Isle of Wight</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleaver</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Institutions, agency and the limitations of participatory approaches to development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khotari</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Participation, the New Tyranny?</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleaver</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The social embeddedness of agency and decision-making</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Participation: From Tyranny to Transformation?</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Crona B and Bodin O (2006) What you know is who you know? Communication patterns among resource users as a prerequisite for co-management. <italic>Ecology and Society</italic> 11(2): Art 7</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Working with the grain? Towards sustainable rural and community development</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Dobson J (2011) Community asset ownership: Progress, diversity and risks? Joseph Rowntree Foundation Community Assets Seminar Series. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.jrf.org.uk/sites/files/jrf/Community-Asset-Ownership.pdf">www.jrf.org.uk/sites/files/jrf/Community-Asset-Ownership.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 5 June 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Civil Society</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Resilience: The emergence of a perspective for social-ecological systems analyses</article-title>. <source>Global Environmental Change</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Well-Connected Community: A Networking Approach to Community Development</source>, <publisher-loc>Bristol</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Challenges for individual and collective action</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cocklin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dibden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Sustainability and Change in Rural Australia</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of New South Wales Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Still left out in the cold: Problematising participatory research and development</article-title>. <source>Sociologia Ruralis</source>. <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Healey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Magalhaes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Madanipour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>(<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Place, identity and local politics: Analysing initiatives in deliberative governance</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hajer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenaar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Deliberative Policy Analysis: Understanding Governance in the Network Society</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hegney D, Ross H, Baker P et al. (2008) <italic>Building Resilience in Rural Communities: A Toolkit.</italic> Universities of Queensland and Southern Queensland. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://learningforsustainability.net/pubs/Building_Resilience_in_Rural_Communities_Toolkit.pdf">http://learningforsustainability.net/pubs/Building_Resilience_in_Rural_Communities_Toolkit.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 8 January 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercseg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Community Development and Civil Society: Making Connections in a European Context</source>, <publisher-loc>Bristol</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>High</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Social learning in LEADER: Exogenous, endogenous and hybrid evaluation in rural development</article-title>. <source>Sociologia Ruralis</source>. <volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirschi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Strengthening regional cohesion: Collaborative networks and sustainable development in Swiss rural areas</article-title>. <source>Ecology and Society</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khotari</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Power, knowledge and social control in participatory development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khotari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Participation, the New Tyranny?</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kretzmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Building Communities from the Inside Out: A Path Toward Finding and Mobilizing a Community’s Assets</source>, <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACTA</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>McIntosh A, Stayner R, Carrington K et al. (2008) <italic>Resilience in Rural Communities: Literature Review</italic>. Armidale, NSW: University of New England. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.une.edu.au/bcss/research/carss/pdf/lit-review-resilience-in-rural-communities.pdf">http://www.une.edu.au/bcss/research/carss/pdf/lit-review-resilience-in-rural-communities.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 8 January 2013)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackleworth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caric</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gatekeepers of island communities: Exploring the pillars of sustainable development</article-title>. <source>Journal of Environmental Development and Sustainability</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Community resilience: An indicator of social sustainability</article-title>. <source>Society &amp; Natural Resources</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Struffi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Translation sociology and social capital in rural development initiatives. A case study from the Italian Alps</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Assessing a Community’s Capacity to Manage Change: A Resilience Approach to Social Assessment</source>, <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Government Bureau of Rural Sciences</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Newman LL and Dale A (2005) Network structure, diversity, and proactive resilience building: A response to Tompkins and Adger. <italic>Ecology and Society</italic> 10(1): r2. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol10/iss1/resp2/">http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol10/iss1/resp2/</ext-link> (accessed 14 January 2013)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>The Great Good Place: Cafes, Coffee Shops, Bookstores, Bars, Hair Salons, and Other Hangouts at the Heart of a Community</source>, <publisher-loc>Emeryville, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Marlowe and Co</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Celebrating the Third Place: Inspiring Stories about the Great Good Places at the Heart of Our Communities</source>, <publisher-loc>Emeryville, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Avalon Travel</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paniagua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The politics of place: Official, intermediate and community discourses in depopulated rural areas of Central Spain. The case of the Riaza river valley (Segovia, Spain)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pendall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Resilience and regions: Building understanding of the metaphor</article-title>. <source>Cambridge Journal of Regions, Economy and Society</source>. <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Social capital: Its origins and applications in modern sociology</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>. <volume>24</volume>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Immigration theory for a new century: Some problems and opportunities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hirschman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasinitz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWind</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>The Handbook of International Migration: The American Experience</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Bowling Alone: The Collapse and Revival of American Community</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Making Democracy Work: Civic Traditions in Modern Italy</source>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Scottish Government (2007) <italic>The Government Economic Strategy</italic>. Scottish Government. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Resource/Doc/202993/0054092.pdf">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Resource/Doc/202993/0054092.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 29 March 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Scottish Government (2009) <italic>Scottish Community Empowerment Action Plan</italic>. Scottish Government. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Resource/Doc/264771/0079288.pdf">http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Resource/Doc/264771/0079288.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 23 May 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shortall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Social or economic goals, civil inclusion or exclusion? An analysis of rural development theory and practice</article-title>. <source>Sociologia Ruralis</source>. <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shortall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Are rural development programmes socially inclusive? Social inclusion, civic engagement, participation, and social capital: Exploring the differences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shucksmith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Endogenous development, social capital and social inclusion: Perspectives from LEADER in the UK</article-title>. <source>Sociologia Ruralis</source>. <volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shucksmith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Disintegrated rural development? Neo-endogenous rural development, planning and place-shaping in diffused power contexts</article-title>. <source>Sociologia Ruralis</source>. <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skerratt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The need to shift rural community development from projects towards resilience: International implications of findings in Scotland</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sjoblom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (eds) <source>Sustainability and Short-term Policies: Improving Governance in Spatial Policy Interventions</source>, <publisher-loc>Farnham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skerratt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Management of community-owned facilities post acquisition: Brokerage for shared learning</article-title>. <source>Local Economy</source>. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Epps</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Leadership and local development: Dimensions of leadership in four central Queensland towns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rural Studies</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Steinerowski A and Markantoni M (2012) Exploring rural community resilience in Scotland: What does it mean, and can it be identified? <italic>XIII World congress of rural sociology</italic>, 29 July–4 August 2012, Lisbon, Portugal</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svendsen</surname><given-names>GLH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Studying social capital in situ: A qualitative approach</article-title>. <source>Theory and Society</source>. <volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svendsen</surname><given-names>GLH</given-names></name><name><surname>Svendsen</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Measuring social capital: The Danish co-operative dairy movement</article-title>. <source>Sociologia Ruralis</source>. <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Public Policy in the Community</source>, <publisher-loc>Basingstoke</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Community Resilience and Environmental Transitions</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0269094212474241"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Leadership in place: Elites, institutions and agency in British rural community governance</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cheshire</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>(2006) <italic>Rural Governance: International Perspectives.</italic> Routledge Studies in Human Geography</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>