<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GCQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgcq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Gifted Child Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0016-9862</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1934-9041</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986212444122</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0016986212444122</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Statistical Methods Used in Gifted Education Journals, 2006-2010</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Warne</surname><given-names>Russell T.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0016986212444122">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lazo</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0016986212444122">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>Tammy</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0016986212444122">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>Nicola</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0016986212444122">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0016986212444122"><label>1</label>Utah Valley University, Orem, UT, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0016986212444122"><label>2</label>Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0016986212444122">Russell T. Warne, Department of Behavioral Science, Utah Valley University, Mail Code 115, 800 W. University Parkway, Orem, UT 84058, USA Email: <email>rwarne@uvu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>134</fpage>
<lpage>149</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 National Association for Gifted Children</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">National Association for Gifted Children</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article describes the statistical methods used in quantitative and mixed methods articles between 2006 and 2010 in five gifted education research journals. Results indicate that the most commonly used statistical methods are means (85.9% of articles), standard deviations (77.8%), Pearson’s <italic>r</italic> (47.8%), χ<sup>2</sup> (32.2%), ANOVA (30.7%), <italic>t</italic> tests (30.0%), and MANOVA (23.0%). Approximately half (53.3%) of the articles included reliability reports for the data at hand; Cronbach’s alpha was the most commonly reported measure of reliability (41.5%). Some discussions of best statistical practice and implications for the field of gifted education are included.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>statistical analyses</kwd>
<kwd>methodology</kwd>
<kwd>reliability</kwd>
<kwd>quantitative methods</kwd>
<kwd>literature review</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>From time to time, it is necessary for those in a scientific field to take stock of the recent research in order to assess its content and to better direct future studies. Researchers in the field of gifted education seem to be particularly disposed to this internal assessment in recent years. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0016986212444122">Dai, Swanson, and Cheng (2011)</xref> analyzed more than 1,200 empirical studies, published over the course of 12 years, to determine the strength of the link between theory and research and to identify major trends in research among researchers of the gifted. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986212444122">Coleman, Guo, and Dabbs (2007)</xref> examined 124 nominally qualitative studies published in gifted education journals between 1985 and 2003. Surprisingly, the authors found that only 40—just under one third—were fully consistent with the qualitative paradigm.</p>
<p>Another review of gifted education articles was performed by Parker and her colleagues in which they analyzed articles published in four major gifted education journals between 2001 and 2006 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0016986212444122">Parker, Jordan, Kirk, Aspiranti, &amp; Bain, 2010</xref>). They found that almost half of the articles (46%) were narratives (e.g., a description of a successful gifted program). The next largest group of articles was quantitative research reports, which comprised 35% of published work. About 16% of articles were qualitative in nature and 3% fell into multiple categories. The authors also found that, of the quantitative research articles, most were nonexperimental group comparisons or correlational studies.</p>
<p>A fundamental recent review of gifted education research was conducted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986212444122">Matthews et al. (2008)</xref>, in which they evaluated the reporting of effect sizes in five gifted education journals from 1996 to 2005. In their study, Matthews et al. found that effect size reporting had been increasing in recent years. Nevertheless, effect sizes were never reported in more than 60% of quantitative articles in a given year. This proportion may continue to increase because in 2006 the then-new editors of the <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics</italic> began requiring authors to report effect sizes for studies, where appropriate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986212444122">Matthews et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0016986212444122">McCoach &amp; Siegle, 2009</xref>). Since the publication of their assessment of effect size reporting, other researchers have written works aimed at gifted education researchers in strong support of reporting effect sizes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0016986212444122">Fidler, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0016986212444122">Gentry &amp; Peters, 2009</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section1-0016986212444122">
<title>Current Review of Literature</title>
<p>In this article, we undertook a similar review of published journal articles in gifted education to determine (a) which statistical methods are used in gifted education research, (b) whether some statistical methods are more common in certain journals, and (c) whether there are discernible trends in the use of various statistical methods over time. In a way, this review is an extension of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986212444122">Matthews et al. (2008)</xref> article. Instead of concentrating solely on effect sizes, however, we have considered all types of statistical procedures to better understand the current state of the field’s use of statistics.</p>
<p>Reviews of statistical procedures are published periodically. The earliest we have been able to find was by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0016986212444122">Edgington (1964)</xref>, who examined statistical methods used in six leading psychology journals from 1948 to 1962. Edgington found that, in that time, the use of analysis of variance (ANOVA) increased sharply—from 11% to 55%—and the use of the <italic>t</italic> test declined from 51% to 19%. Correlational methods decreased somewhat from 42% to 24%, whereas nonparametric and factor analysis methods increased roughly fivefold. In a follow-up article published a decade later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0016986212444122">Edgington (1974)</xref> found that the use of ANOVA had continued to increase until it was found in 71% of articles, whereas the <italic>t</italic> test continued its decline and was found in only 12% of articles published in 1972. Nonparametric methods declined in the early 1970s, whereas the use of other methods stayed approximately constant.</p>
<p>After Edgington’s efforts, other authors began to examine the statistical methods used in other journals in education and psychology. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0016986212444122">Willson (1980)</xref> examined research techniques published from 1969 to 1978 in the <italic>American Educational Research Journal</italic>. Similar to Edgington’s results, Willson found that ANOVA was the most common statistical technique, although in his review it was found in only 56% of articles. For Willson, Pearson’s <italic>r</italic> correlation was also the second most common technique, followed by multiple regression.</p>
<p>More recent reviews have found that the use of classical statistics such as ANOVA and correlation has declined, likely due to the explosion of statistical techniques and the ease of access to personal computers, which make performing complex statistical procedures much easier than they were in Edgington’s time. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0016986212444122">Bangert and Baumberger (2005)</xref>, for example, found that correlation was the most common statistical method used in the <italic>Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</italic> between 1990 and 2001, yet correlations were found in only 12% of articles. Multiple regression was the second most common method and was found in 8% of articles. MANOVA/MANCOVA, which occurred in 7% of research studies, was the third most common method. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0016986212444122">Kieffer, Reese, and Thompson (2001)</xref> evaluated articles from the <italic>American Educational Research Journal</italic> and <italic>Journal of Counseling Psychology</italic> from 1988 and 1997 and found that the most common methods were (in descending order) ANOVA, correlation, multiple regression, factor analysis, and MANOVA.</p>
<p>These and other reviews of statistical procedures were themselves reviewed and combined into one large review of techniques published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0016986212444122">Skidmore and Thompson (2010)</xref>, which spanned 12,012 articles published between 1948 and 2001. The authors found that the use of statistical procedures tends to wax and wane with time and that there is rarely a constant upward or downward trend for any particular statistical method. For example, in education articles, the use of factor analysis was increasing during the 1960s and 1970s, but decreased in the 1980s before increasing again in the 1990s. Skidmore and Thompson also found a large degree of variability in the use of any particular statistical technique from year to year. Despite these caveats, it was apparent that factor analysis was increasing in use in psychology and that the use of <italic>t</italic> tests was in decline in both education and psychology.</p>
<p>Conducting reviews of methodological techniques is an important exercise for a variety of reasons. First, such reviews help researchers in a specific field learn what methodological training is necessary for a person to understand the quantitative research conducted in that field. Second, reviews shed light on subtle methodological trends that may be occurring in a field over the span of years. Finally, statistical reviews permit researchers to evaluate how well their field compares with the accepted standards of statistical reporting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0016986212444122" sec-type="methods">
<title>Procedures</title>
<p>Before examining the statistical methods used in articles, it was necessary for us to establish what was important to code. For guidance, we turned to several sources. The first was previous reviews of statistical methods in education and psychology (i.e., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0016986212444122">Bangert &amp; Baumburger, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0016986212444122">Baumberger &amp; Bangert, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0016986212444122">Edgington, 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0016986212444122">1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0016986212444122">Elmore &amp; Woehlke, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0016986212444122">Kieffer et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0016986212444122">Skidmore &amp; Thompson, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0016986212444122">Willson, 1980</xref>). We also consulted published standards of statistical reporting from the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0016986212444122">American Psychological Association (2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0016986212444122">APA Publications and Communications Board Working Group on Journal Article Reporting Standards, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0016986212444122">Wilkinson &amp; the Task Force on Statistical Inference, 1999</xref>) and the American Educational Research Association (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0016986212444122">AERA; 2006</xref>). Finally, we consulted works on meta-analysis, which often provide important insight on the type of information that should be reported in original articles (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986212444122">Cooper, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0016986212444122">Lipsey &amp; Wilson, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Because it would be exceptionally difficult (and unwieldy) to code all the information suggested in the previous sources, we focused on statistical methods (including effect sizes) and reliability. For the statistical methods, we recorded every statistical procedure that the original article’s author(s) carried out during the course of the study. Statistical methods were not recorded if they were mentioned during the course of the author’s literature review or if they were merely suggested in the discussion or conclusion sections.</p>
<p>Because many statistical procedures used in gifted education research are interrelated through the General Linear Model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0016986212444122">Cohen, 1968a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2006</xref>), it is possible to code some in multiple categories. For example, a regression with a dichotomous dependent variable could be coded as “logistic regression” or “multinomial regression” because subjecting the same data to both procedures would produce identical results. In coding statistical procedures, we always classified a method under the most specific name possible. Readers should also note that a particular statistical method was only classified once. For example, this regression with a dichotomous dependent variable was only classified as “logistic regression.” However, many authors used multiple statistical procedures within the same article; all these were coded as being used in the same article. Finally, if a statistical method was used more than once in a particular article, it was counted once in our results.</p>
<p>A wide variety of reliability information could potentially be coded during the review of statistical procedures. However, we decided to focus on a few of the most important aspects of reliability, namely, whether the authors reported reliability information for their own data and the type of reliability statistic reported. We believed that recording whether the authors reported their own reliability information was important because previous research had shown that the practice of reliability induction—where a researcher takes a reliability statistic from one sample and applies it to another—is distressingly common (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0016986212444122">Deditius-Island &amp; Caruso, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0016986212444122">Kieffer &amp; Reese, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0016986212444122">Shields &amp; Caruso, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0016986212444122">Vacha-Haase, Kogan, &amp; Thompson, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0016986212444122">Warne (2011)</xref> called reliability induction “inherently erroneous” (p. 675) and said that the practice was “as logically defensible as would be an attempt to take the mean from one sample and apply it to data collected from a completely different sample” (p. 676). We attempted to code instances of reliability induction, but found that the judgments were too subjective and that there was little agreement among coders. Therefore, we instead recorded whether the author(s) of an article made it clear that the reliability statistics they reported applied to the data at hand (and not some other sample, such as the standardization sample from the test manual).</p>
<p>We examined articles from five major journals that frequently publish research on giftedness and gifted education. The journals were (in alphabetical order) <italic>Gifted Child Quarterly</italic> (<italic>GCQ</italic>), <italic>High Ability Studies</italic> (<italic>HAS</italic>), the <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics</italic> (<italic>JAA</italic>; this journal was called <italic>Journal of Secondary Gifted Education</italic> until late 2006), the <italic>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</italic> (<italic>JEG</italic>), and <italic>Roeper Review</italic> (<italic>RR</italic>). All articles published between 2006 and 2010 in these journals were included in the study. The articles were divided among the four authors and each article was read independently by two of the authors of this study. The two coders then met and discussed the results. When differences occurred, the original article was always consulted and agreement reached. The first author is a quantitative psychologist and the other three authors mastered the most common univariate and multivariate statistical methods and passed a rigorous course on structural equation modeling (SEM).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0016986212444122" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0016986212444122">Table 1</xref> shows that in total we reviewed 697 articles. Of these, we determined that 234 (33.6%) were quantitative research reports—a proportion very similar to what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0016986212444122">Parker et al. (2010)</xref> found in their review of gifted education articles from 2001 to 2006. Ninety-nine articles (14.2%) were qualitative research reports and 36 (5.2%) were reports from mixed methods research projects. The remaining 328 articles (47.1%) were not research reports at all (i.e., editorials, theoretical pieces, and other nonresearch articles). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0016986212444122">Table 1</xref> also shows the number and percentage of each article type that was published in each journal and each year. Only quantitative and mixed methods articles were analyzed further. The results of the analyses are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0016986212444122">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0016986212444122">3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0016986212444122" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Number and Types of Articles Published in Gifted Education Journals, Organized by Journal and Year, 2006-2010</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0016986212444122" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986212444122-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Journal</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Article Types</th>
<th align="center"><italic>GCQ</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>HAS</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>JAA</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>JEG</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>RR</italic></th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>154</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>214</td>
<td>697</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quantitative</td>
<td>67 (43.5%)</td>
<td>38 (46.9%)</td>
<td>51 (36.4%)</td>
<td>41 (38.0%)</td>
<td>37 (17.3%)</td>
<td>234 (33.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Qualitative</td>
<td>19 (12.3%)</td>
<td>9 (11.1%)</td>
<td>26 (18.6%)</td>
<td>26 (24.1%)</td>
<td>19 (8.9%)</td>
<td>99 (14.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mixed</td>
<td>9 (5.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.2%)</td>
<td>13 (9.3%)</td>
<td>7 (6.5%)</td>
<td>6 (2.8%)</td>
<td>36 (5.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Literature review</td>
<td>1 (0.6%)</td>
<td>3 (3.7%)</td>
<td>3 (2.1%)</td>
<td>9 (8.3%)</td>
<td>4 (1.9%)</td>
<td>20 (2.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Theoretical</td>
<td>9 (5.8%)</td>
<td>6 (7.4%)</td>
<td>7 (5.0%)</td>
<td>8 (7.4%)</td>
<td>45 (21.0%)</td>
<td>75 (10.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>50 (32.5%)</td>
<td>25 (30.9%)</td>
<td>40 (28.6%)</td>
<td>17 (15.7%)</td>
<td>99 (46.3%)</td>
<td>231 (33.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Year</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Article Types</th>
<th align="center">2006</th>
<th align="center">2007</th>
<th align="center">2008</th>
<th align="center">2009</th>
<th align="center">2010</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>147</td>
<td>153</td>
<td>136</td>
<td>137</td>
<td>124</td>
<td>697</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quantitative</td>
<td>45 (30.6%)</td>
<td>48 (31.4%)</td>
<td>51 (37.5%)</td>
<td>49 (35.8%)</td>
<td>41 (33.1%)</td>
<td>234 (33.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Qualitative</td>
<td>21 (14.3%)</td>
<td>19 (12.4%)</td>
<td>18 (13.2%)</td>
<td>11 (8.0%)</td>
<td>30 (24.2%)</td>
<td>99 (14.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mixed</td>
<td>7 (4.8%)</td>
<td>5 (3.3%)</td>
<td>5 (3.7%)</td>
<td>8 (5.8%)</td>
<td>11 (8.9%)</td>
<td>36 (5.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Literature review</td>
<td>5 (3.4%)</td>
<td>5 (3.3%)</td>
<td>1 (0.7%)</td>
<td>4 (2.9%)</td>
<td>5 (8.8%)</td>
<td>20 (2.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Theoretical</td>
<td>16 (10.9%)</td>
<td>18 (11.8%)</td>
<td>17 (12.5%)</td>
<td>18 (13.1%)</td>
<td>6 (10.5%)</td>
<td>75 (10.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>53 (36.1%)</td>
<td>57 (37.3%)</td>
<td>42 (30.9%)</td>
<td>48 (35.0%)</td>
<td>31 (54.4%)</td>
<td>231 (33.1%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0016986212444122">
<p><italic>Note. GCQ</italic> = <italic>Gifted Child Quarterly; HAS</italic> = <italic>High Ability Studies; JAA</italic> = <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics; JEG</italic> = <italic>Journal for the Education of the Gifted; RR</italic> = <italic>Roeper Review</italic>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0016986212444122" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Statistical Methods Used in Gifted Education Journals, 2006-2010, Organized by Journal</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0016986212444122" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986212444122-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Journal</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Method</th>
<th align="center"><italic>GCQ</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>HAS</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>JAA</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>JEG</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>RR</italic></th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Descriptive statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Means</td>
<td>64 (84.2%)</td>
<td>37 (94.9%)</td>
<td>55 (85.9%)</td>
<td>42 (87.5%)</td>
<td>34 (79.1%)</td>
<td>232 (85.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic>s</td>
<td>60 (78.9%)</td>
<td>35 (89.7%)</td>
<td>46 (71.9%)</td>
<td>38 (79.2%)</td>
<td>31 (72.1%)</td>
<td>210 (77.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Basic inferential statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>t</italic> tests</td>
<td>22 (28.9%)</td>
<td>14 (35.9%)</td>
<td>20 (31.3%)</td>
<td>14 (29.2%)</td>
<td>11 (25.6%)</td>
<td>81 (30.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ANOVA</td>
<td>21 (27.6%)</td>
<td>15 (38.5%)</td>
<td>18 (28.1%)</td>
<td>14 (29.2%)</td>
<td>15 (34.9%)</td>
<td>83 (30.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ANCOVA</td>
<td>4 (5.3%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>2 (3.1%)</td>
<td>2 (4.2%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>11 (3.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> MANOVA</td>
<td>17 (22.4%)</td>
<td>11 (28.2%)</td>
<td>12 (18.8%)</td>
<td>10 (17.2%)</td>
<td>12 (27.9%)</td>
<td>62 (23.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> MANCOVA</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Discriminant analysis</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>2 (4.2%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>7 (10.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Correlation/regression</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Pearson’s <italic>r</italic></td>
<td>38 (50.0%)</td>
<td>22 (56.4%)</td>
<td>26 (40.6%)</td>
<td>23 (47.9%)</td>
<td>20 (46.5%)</td>
<td>129 (47.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Spearman’s rho</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (4.2%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>5 (18.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Phi</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Point–biserial correlation</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>5 (1.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tetrachoric correlation</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kendall’s tau</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Canonical correlation</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>2 (3.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Partial correlation</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multiple regression</td>
<td>8 (10.5%)</td>
<td>7 (17.9%)</td>
<td>17 (26.6%)</td>
<td>3 (6.3%)</td>
<td>5 (11.6%)</td>
<td>40 (14.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Stepwise regression</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (7.7%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>6 (2.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Logistic regression</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6 (9.4%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>7 (2.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ordinal regression</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multinomial logistic regression</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tobit regression</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> HLM</td>
<td>4 (5.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (6.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8 (3.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Logistic HLM</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Data reduction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> EFA</td>
<td>6 (7.9%)</td>
<td>2 (5.1%)</td>
<td>2 (3.1%)</td>
<td>4 (8.3%)</td>
<td>4 (9.3%)</td>
<td>18 (6.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PCA</td>
<td>6 (7.9%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>4 (6.3%)</td>
<td>4 (8.3%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>17 (6.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>3 (7.7%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Complex statistical methods</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Path analysis</td>
<td>3 (3.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> CFA/measure model</td>
<td>7 (9.2%)</td>
<td>6 (15.4%)</td>
<td>6 (9.4%)</td>
<td>3 (6.3%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>24 (8.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Structural model</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>2 (5.1%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>5 (1.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Test of invariance</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (4.2%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5 (1.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Nonparametric statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chi-square</td>
<td>27 (35.5%)</td>
<td>15 (38.5%)</td>
<td>18 (28.1%)</td>
<td>9 (18.8%)</td>
<td>18 (41.9%)</td>
<td>87 (32.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic></td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>3 (6.3%)</td>
<td>7 (2.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kolmogorov–Smirov test</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kruskall–Wallis test</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Log likelihood</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fisher’s exact test</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (5.1%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kendall’s <italic>W</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Wilcoxon signed ranks</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>3 (7.0%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cramér’s <italic>V</italic></td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (4.7%)</td>
<td>2 (4.2%)</td>
<td>4 (9.3%)</td>
<td>11 (4.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cluster analysis</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Reliability</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Reliability report for own data</td>
<td>41 (53.9%)</td>
<td>22 (56.4%)</td>
<td>33 (51.6%)</td>
<td>24 (50.0%)</td>
<td>24 (55.9%)</td>
<td>144 (53.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cronbach’s alpha</td>
<td>29 (38.2%)</td>
<td>17 (43.6%)</td>
<td>29 (45.3%)</td>
<td>20 (41.7%)</td>
<td>17 (39.5%)</td>
<td>112 (41.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Test–retest</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>4 (10.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (6.3%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>11 (4.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">(continued)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> % agreement between raters</td>
<td>5 (6.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>8 (3.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cohen’s Kappa</td>
<td>4 (5.3%)</td>
<td>4 (10.3%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>2 (4.2%)</td>
<td>2 (4.7%)</td>
<td>13 (4.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation between ratings</td>
<td>3 (3.9%)</td>
<td>3 (7.7%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>3 (5.2%)</td>
<td>7 (16.3%)</td>
<td>17 (6.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown interrater reliability method</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.7%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alt/parallel forms</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Split half (no correction)</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Split half (with correction)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard error of measurement</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> IRT-based reliability measure</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Conditional standard error of measurement</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Miscellaneous procedures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Replication</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ICC</td>
<td>7 (9.2%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5 (7.8%)</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>13 (4.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Box’s <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>3 (3.9%)</td>
<td>1 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (6.3%)</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>8 (3.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Bayesian stats</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>2 (5.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Power analysis</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.1%)</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ROC</td>
<td>2 (2.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mahalanobis distance</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Design effect</td>
<td>1 (1.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multicollinearity diagnostics</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>1 (2.1%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> BIC</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (2.3%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0016986212444122">
<p><italic>Note. GCQ</italic> = <italic>Gifted Child Quarterly; HAS</italic> = <italic>High Ability Studies; JAA</italic> = <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics; JEG</italic> = <italic>Journal for the Education of the Gifted; RR</italic> = <italic>Roeper Review</italic>; CFA = confirmatory factor analysis; PCA = principal components analysis; HLM = hierarchical linear modeling; IRT = item response theory; ICC = intraclass correlation coefficient; ROC = receiver operating characteristic curve; BIC = Bayesian information criterion; EFA = exploratory factor analysis; ANOVA = analysis of variance; ANCOVA = analysis of covariance; MANOVA = multivariate analysis of variance; MANCOVA = multivariate analysis of covariance. The following miscellaneous statistical methods were used only once: sensitivity/specificity values (<italic>GCQ</italic>), likelihood ratio (<italic>GCQ</italic>), correct classification rates (<italic>GCQ</italic>), Tobit regression (<italic>GCQ</italic>), simulated data generation (<italic>GCQ</italic>), unspecified nonparametric correlation (<italic>HAS</italic>), difference in correlation (<italic>HAS</italic>), self-organizing map (<italic>HAS</italic>), Huynh–Feldt correction (<italic>HAS</italic>), Puri and Sen’s <italic>L</italic> statistic (<italic>HAS</italic>), IRT-based statistics (<italic>HAS</italic>), latency and amplitude (<italic>HAS</italic>), Monte Carlo bootstrapping (<italic>HAS</italic>), Mardia’s coefficient (<italic>HAS</italic>), probability ratio (<italic>HAS</italic>), Fisher’s <italic>r</italic>-to-<italic>z</italic> transformation (<italic>JAA</italic>), reliability change index (<italic>JAA</italic>), test of heteroscedasticity (<italic>JAA</italic>), test of autocorrelation (<italic>JAA</italic>), EM single imputation (<italic>JAA</italic>), Shapiro–Wilk test (<italic>JAA</italic>), test of homogeneity of slopes (<italic>JEG</italic>), <italic>Q</italic> factor analysis (<italic>RR</italic>), Hotelling’s multivariate <italic>T</italic> (<italic>RR</italic>), false discovery method (<italic>RR</italic>), Grizzle–Starmer–Koch method (<italic>RR</italic>), and latent class analysis (<italic>RR</italic>).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0016986212444122" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Statistical Methods Used in Gifted Education Journals, 2006-2010, Organized by Year</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0016986212444122" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986212444122-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Year</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Method</th>
<th align="center">2006</th>
<th align="center">2007</th>
<th align="center">2008</th>
<th align="center">2009</th>
<th align="center">2010</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Descriptive statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Means</td>
<td>42 (80.8%)</td>
<td>43 (81.1%)</td>
<td>52 (92.9%)</td>
<td>50 (87.7%)</td>
<td>45 (86.5%)</td>
<td>232 (85.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic>s</td>
<td>38 (73.1%)</td>
<td>40 (75.5%)</td>
<td>48 (85.7%)</td>
<td>44 (77.2%)</td>
<td>40 (76.9%)</td>
<td>210 (77.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Basic inferential statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>t</italic> tests</td>
<td>18 (34.6%)</td>
<td>20 (37.7%)</td>
<td>16 (28.6%)</td>
<td>14 (24.6%)</td>
<td>13 (25.0%)</td>
<td>81 (30.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ANOVA</td>
<td>16 (30.8%)</td>
<td>18 (34.0%)</td>
<td>20 (35.7%)</td>
<td>18 (31.6%)</td>
<td>11 (21.1%)</td>
<td>83 (30.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ANCOVA</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (7.5%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (7.0%)</td>
<td>3 (5.8%)</td>
<td>11 (3.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> MANOVA</td>
<td>10 (19.2%)</td>
<td>19 (35.8%)</td>
<td>12 (21.4%)</td>
<td>13 (22.8%)</td>
<td>8 (15.4%)</td>
<td>62 (16.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> MANCOVA</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Discriminant analysis</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>2 (3.5%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>7 (10.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Correlation/regression</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Pearson’s <italic>r</italic></td>
<td>21 (40.4%)</td>
<td>29 (54.7%)</td>
<td>29 (51.8%)</td>
<td>24 (42.1%)</td>
<td>26 (50.0%)</td>
<td>129 (47.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Spearman’s rho</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.5%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5 (18.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Phi</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Point–biserial correlation</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5 (8.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5 (1.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tetrachoric correlation</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kendall’s tau</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Canonical correlation</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (5.4%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Partial correlation</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multiple regress</td>
<td>4 (7.7%)</td>
<td>13 (24.5%)</td>
<td>8 (14.3%)</td>
<td>7 (12.3%)</td>
<td>8 (15.4%)</td>
<td>40 (14.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Stepwise regress</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>3 (5.7%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>6 (2.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Logistic regress</td>
<td>3 (5.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>2 (3.5%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>7 (2.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ordinal regression</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multinominal logistic regression</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tobit regression</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> HLM</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>4 (7.7%)</td>
<td>8 (3.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Logistic HLM</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Data reduction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> EFA</td>
<td>3 (5.8%)</td>
<td>7 (13.2%)</td>
<td>3 (5.4%)</td>
<td>3 (5.3%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>18 (6.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PCA</td>
<td>3 (5.8%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>3 (5.4%)</td>
<td>5 (8.8%)</td>
<td>4 (7.7%)</td>
<td>17 (6.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Complex statistical methods</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Path analysis</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multilevel path analysis</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> CFA/measurement model</td>
<td>4 (7.7%)</td>
<td>3 (5.7%)</td>
<td>3 (5.4%)</td>
<td>7 (12.3%)</td>
<td>7 (13.4%)</td>
<td>24 (8.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Structural model</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>2 (3.5%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5 (1.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Test of invariance</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (5.8%)</td>
<td>5 (1.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Nonparametric statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chi-square</td>
<td>13 (25.0%)</td>
<td>18 (34.0%)</td>
<td>17 (30.4%)</td>
<td>20 (35.1%)</td>
<td>19 (36.5%)</td>
<td>87 (32.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic></td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4 (7.0%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>7 (2.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kolmogorov–Smirov test</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Log likelihood</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kruskall–Wallis test</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fisher’s exact test</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kendall’s <italic>W</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Wilcoxon signed ranks</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.5%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cramér’s <italic>V</italic></td>
<td>2 (3.9%)</td>
<td>2 (9.4%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>4 (7.0%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>11 (4.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cluster analysis</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Reliability</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Reliability report for own data</td>
<td>25 (48.1%)</td>
<td>34 (64.2%)</td>
<td>32 (57.1%)</td>
<td>31 (54.4%)</td>
<td>22 (42.3%)</td>
<td>144 (53.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cronbach’s alpha</td>
<td>16 (30.8%)</td>
<td>27 (50.9%)</td>
<td>29 (51.8%)</td>
<td>25 (43.9%)</td>
<td>15 (28.8%)</td>
<td>112 (41.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Test–retest</td>
<td>2 (3.9%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>4 (7.7%)</td>
<td>11 (4.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> % agreement between raters</td>
<td>2 (3.9%)</td>
<td>3 (5.7%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>8 (3.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cohen’s Kappa</td>
<td>2 (3.9%)</td>
<td>3 (5.7%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (5.3%)</td>
<td>5 (9.6%)</td>
<td>13 (4.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Correlation between ratings</td>
<td>7 (13.5%)</td>
<td>3 (5.7%)</td>
<td>4 (7.1%)</td>
<td>3 (5.3%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>17 (6.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown interrater reliability method</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alt/parallel forms</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Split half (no correction)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Split half (with correction)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard error of measurement</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> IRT-based reliability measure</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Conditional standard error of measurement</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (0.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Miscellaneous procedures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Replication procedures</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ICC</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (5.7%)</td>
<td>2 (3.6%)</td>
<td>3 (5.3%)</td>
<td>5 (9.6%)</td>
<td>13 (4.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Box’s <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>2 (3.9%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>3 (5.4%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8 (3.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Bayesian stats</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>2 (3.8%)</td>
<td>4 (1.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Power analysis</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (5.4%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (1.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ROC</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mahalanobis distance</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Design effect</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multicollinearity diagnostics</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> BIC</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1 (1.8%)</td>
<td>1 (1.9%)</td>
<td>2 (0.7%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0016986212444122">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. CFA = confirmatory factor analysis; PCA = principal components analysis; HLM = hierarchical linear modeling; IRT = item response theory; ICC = intraclass correlation coefficient; ROC = receiver operating characteristic curve; BIC = Bayesian information criterion; EFA = exploratory factor analysis; ANOVA = analysis of variance; ANCOVA = analysis of covariance; MANOVA = multivariate analysis of variance; MANCOVA = multivariate analysis of covariance. The following miscellaneous statistical methods were used only once: sensitivity/specificity values (2008), likelihood ratio (2008), correct classification rates (2008), Tobit regression (2010), simulated data generation (2010), unspecified nonparametric correlation (2009), difference in correlation (2006), self-organizing map (2006), Huynh–Feldt correction (2007), Puri and Sen’s <italic>L</italic> statistic (2007), IRT-based statistics (2010), latency and amplitude (2008), Monte Carlo bootstrapping (2009), Mardia’s coefficient (2009), probability ratio (2010), Fisher’s <italic>r</italic>-to-<italic>z</italic> transformation (2007), reliability change index (2008), test of heteroscedasticity (2008), test of autocorrelation (2008), EM single imputation (2008), Shapiro–Wilk test (2010), test of homogeneity of slopes (2010), <italic>Q</italic> factor analysis (2010), Hotelling’s multivariate <italic>T</italic> (2006), false discovery method (2006), Grizzle–Starmer–Koch method (2007), and latent class analysis (2010).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section4-0016986212444122">
<title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
<p>The vast majority of authors of quantitative and mixed methods articles reported descriptive statistics for their data. Means were reported for 85.9% of articles and standard deviations for 77.8% of articles. We never found an instance where a standard deviation was reported without an accompanying mean. However, means were often reported by themselves without accompanying standard deviations. This is largely recognized as poor practice (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2006</xref>) and makes articles harder to include in meta-analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986212444122">Cooper, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0016986212444122">
<title>t Tests and -OVA Methods</title>
<p>The simplest parametric inferential statistic is the <italic>t</italic> test, which examines whether the means of two groups are statistically different. We found that <italic>t</italic> tests were quite common in the gifted education literature and occurred in a total of 30.0% of articles. The next simplest parametric inferential statistic is ANOVA, which compares multiple group means to determine if one or more are statistically significantly different from the other(s). ANOVA was slightly more popular than <italic>t</italic> tests among gifted education researchers, with 30.7% of articles using ANOVA. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA)—which is the same as an ANOVA, except with a covariate included in the statistical model, was found in a total of 11 articles (3.9%) and was therefore not very common.</p>
<p>The multivariate extensions of ANOVA and ANCOVA—called multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) and multivariate analysis of covariance (MANCOVA)—were less common than their univariate counterparts. MANOVA was used in 23.0% articles; MANCOVA was found in only two articles (0.7%).</p>
<p>Often statistically significant -OVA methods are followed up by post hoc tests to determine exactly where the difference(s) in groups lie (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0016986212444122">Bray &amp; Maxwell, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0016986212444122">Stevens, 2002</xref>). For ANOVA and ANCOVA, the most common post hoc tests were the Tukey test (11 articles), post hoc <italic>t</italic> tests (9 articles), and the Scheffé test (3 articles). Dunnett’s <italic>t</italic> and the Student–Newman–Lewis post hoc tests were each found in a single article. Authors of six articles indicated that they ran post hoc tests after their ANOVA or ANCOVA, yet did not specify which post hoc test(s) were performed.</p>
<p>By far the most common post hoc statistical test for MANOVA or MANCOVA was a series of ANOVAs, which occurred in 31 articles—almost half of all articles that used MANOVA or MANCOVA. The other specified post hoc tests after MANOVA or MANCOVA were Tukey’s test (6 articles), discriminant analysis (5 articles), ANCOVA (2 articles), <italic>t</italic> tests (2 articles), the Games–Howell test (1 article), and the Roy–Bargman test (1 article). Authors of six articles that conducted multivariate null hypothesis statistical significance testing did not specify which post hoc test(s) they conducted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0016986212444122">
<title>Correlational and Regression Procedures</title>
<p>The most basic correlational procedure is Pearson’s <italic>r</italic>, which examines the statistical relationship between two interval or ratio scaled variables. This technique was the most common statistical method we found in the gifted literature, after means and standard deviations—making an appearance in 47.8% of all quantitative or mixed methods articles. Other correlational techniques were much less common; Cramér’s V was found in 11 articles (4.1%), Spearman’s ρ and the point–biserial correlation were each found in five articles (1.9%), and the phi correlation was found in three articles (1.1%). Kendall’s tau and the tetrachoric correlation were each found in a single article (0.4%).</p>
<p>Multiple regression—an extension of Pearson’s <italic>r</italic> applied to situations with multiple independent variables—was a commonly found regression procedure and appeared in 40 articles (14.9%). Similar to the situation with correlational procedures, other regression procedures were comparatively rare: logistic regression was found in seven articles (2.6%), canonical correlation appeared in four articles (1.5%), stepwise regression was found in six articles (2.2%), ordinal regression was found in two articles (0.7%), and multinomial logistic regression was found in a single article (0.4%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0016986212444122">
<title>Complex Statistical Methods</title>
<p>With the increased access to personal computers in the past few decades, the methodological literature has exploded with new techniques, reevaluations of old techniques, and new procedures to make existing statistical techniques easier to implement. This increased access to statistical methods has had an impact on gifted education research.</p>
<sec id="section8-0016986212444122">
<title>Hierarchical linear modeling</title>
<p>Hierarchical linear modeling (HLM) is a technique that compensates for situations where data are clustered into groups, such as in a clustered sampling plan (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0016986212444122">Ferron et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0016986212444122">Hox, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0016986212444122">McCoach, 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0016986212444122">2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0016986212444122">McCoach &amp; Adelson, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0016986212444122">Raudenbush &amp; Bryk, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0016986212444122">Warne et al., in press</xref>). HLM is not commonly found in the gifted education literature; the method was only used in eight articles (3.0%)—all of which were published in <italic>GCQ</italic> or <italic>JAA</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0016986212444122">
<title>Data reduction methods</title>
<p>Data reduction methods are designed to create new synthetic variables that summarize a set of observed variables in a more parsimonious manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2004</xref>). There are two main types of data reduction, exploratory factor analysis (EFA) and principal components analysis (PCA), which largely produce similar results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0016986212444122">O’Connor, 2000</xref>). We found that the gifted education research community favors both methods approximately equally well: EFA was used in 18 articles (6.7%), and PCA was used in 17 articles (6.3%). Authors of four articles used some type of data reduction method but were not clear about which type of data reduction method was used.</p>
<p>Whether one chooses to perform an EFA or a PCA, a variety of subjective decisions come into play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986212444122">Costello &amp; Osborne, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2004</xref>). One of the initial judgments is to choose a rotation method to produce interpretable results. We found that varimax rotation was the most common method used in gifted education and was found in 20 articles. The next most common methods specified were oblimin (6 articles), promax (5 articles), direct oblimin (2 articles), and quartimax (1 article). In eight articles the author(s) did not specify their rotation method.</p>
<p>Quantitative methodologists generally agree that the most important decision that someone makes when conducting an EFA or PCA is the number of factors to retain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986212444122">Costello &amp; Osborne, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0016986212444122">Larsen &amp; Warne, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0016986212444122">Zwick &amp; Velicer, 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0016986212444122">1986</xref>). Given the importance of the factor retention methods, we were disappointed to find that gifted education researchers did not specify the method of retaining the number of factors in their EFA or PCA in 18 articles. This surpassed even the most commonly specified method for determining the number of factors—the Guttman rule (also called the K1 rule, or eigenvalues-greater-than-one rule), which was used in 16 articles. The other factor retention methods used were the scree test (15 articles), the variance accounted by the number of factors (8 articles), the Kaiser–Meyer–Olkin test of sampling adequacy (5 articles), a priori theory (4 articles), parallel analysis (4 articles), Bartlett’s test of sphericity (3 articles), and visual inspection of the item loadings (1 article). It is important to note that some authors used more than one factor retention method when making their decision.</p>
<p>A result of EFA or PCA is the factor loading matrix and—in the case of nonorthogonal rotation methods—a structure matrix. We found that 23 articles that used a data reduction method reported a loading matrix; only 5 structure matrices were reported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0016986212444122">
<title>Path analysis</title>
<p>We found that path analysis was a rarely used statistical method in the recent gifted education literature. Only four articles (1.5%) from the past 5 years were found to have used path analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0016986212444122">
<title>Latent variable methods</title>
<p>Latent variable methods are statistical methods that use observed data to hypothesize relationships among variables—some of which are not directly observable. For the purposes of this review, we defined three types of latent variable models: confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and measurement models, structural models, and tests of invariance. CFA may be one of the most common advanced statistical methods used in gifted education, and CFA/measurement models appeared in 24 articles (8.9%). Structural models were less common, being found in only 5 articles (1.9%) from the past 5 years. Tests of invariance—which often use SEM and CFA—were conducted in 5 articles (1.9%).</p>
<p>Like data reduction methods, CFA, SEM, and tests of invariance require researchers to report a substantial amount of details in order for their procedures to be properly evaluated. One reporting requirement is for researchers to report a covariance matrix of all observed variables in a model or a correlation matrix with accompanying means and standard deviations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986212444122">Kline, 2005</xref>). Authors of only nine articles met this reporting requirement.</p> <p>Leading authorities on SEM (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0016986212444122">Kaplan, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986212444122">Kline, 2005</xref>) recommend that users report the estimation method used by their statistical software package when working with latent variable models. We found that the most common identification method was maximum likelihood (ML; 9 articles), followed by weighted least squares mean/variance adjusted (2 articles), and robust ML (1 article). In the majority of articles that used a latent variable model—17 out of 29—the estimation method was not reported.</p>
<p>One critical assumption of latent variable methods when using ML estimation is multivariate normality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0016986212444122">Kaplan, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986212444122">Kline, 2005</xref>). Therefore, it is expected that researchers who use ML estimation for their latent variable methods either check their data for violations of the normality assumption or use methods that compensate for a lack of normality. Authors of only eight articles using latent variable models reported these procedures.</p>
<p>Of the 29 articles that used latent variable models, results (i.e., factor loadings and other estimated parameters) were only reported for 18 articles. Of these, 17 were standardized results and 1 had unstandardized results.</p>
<p>Finally, researchers who use latent variable models have a wide variety of fit statistics with which they can evaluate how closely their observed data fit their latent variable models (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0016986212444122">Sun, 2005</xref>, for an excellent introduction to fit statistics). The most common fit statistic reported was the comparative fit index (CFI), which was found in 24 articles. The χ<sup>2</sup> and root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) were tied as the second most commonly reported fit statistic, each appearing in 23 articles. Other reported fit statistics were the standardized root mean square residual (SRMR; 12 articles), goodness-of-fit index (GFI; 11 articles), nonnormed fit index (NNFI; 7 articles), expected cross-validation index (ECVI; 5 articles), Tucker–Lewis index (TLI; 4 articles), adjusted goodness-of-fit index (AGFI; 3 articles), normed fit index (NFI; 2 articles), root mean residual (RMR; 2 articles), the Satorra–Benter adjusted χ<sup>2</sup> (2 articles), weighted root mean residual (WRMR; 2 articles), relative fit index (RFI; 1 article), robust CFI (1 article), and the robust RMSEA (1 article).</p>
<p>Finally, some authors who use latent variable models are interested in modifying their models to better fit their data. Although there are many methods for doing this, the most empirical approach is to use modification indices to guide the decision of where to add paths on the model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986212444122">Kline, 2005</xref>). Modification indices were used in four articles (1.5%) in the 5 years of gifted education research that we investigated.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0016986212444122">
<title>Nonparametric Statistics</title>
<p>Most of the statistical methods that we have mentioned so far are parametric methods based on assumptions of normality and associated probability distributions. Nonparametric statistics, on the other hand, do not require these assumptions and are appropriate for a wider variety of research situations, despite not being as common as traditional parametric statistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0016986212444122">Agresti, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0016986212444122">Heiman, 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>The most common nonparametric null hypothesis statistical significance testing method was the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test, which was found in 7 articles (2.6%). Other nonparametric tests used in the gifted education research were Fisher’s exact test (4 articles; 1.5%), the Wilcoxon signed ranks test (4 articles; 1.5%), cluster analysis (4 articles; 1.5%), the Kolmogorov–Smirov test (3 articles; 1.1%), and the Kruskall–Wallis, log likelihood, and Kendall’s <italic>W</italic> tests, all of which appeared in a single article (0.4%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0016986212444122">
<title>Reliability</title>
<p>Recent authoritative publications have dictated that researchers should report the reliability statistics from the data at hand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0016986212444122">AERA, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0016986212444122">Wilkinson &amp; the Task Force on Statistical Inference, 1999</xref>). We found that authors of 144 articles (53.3%) unambiguously reported reliability data from their own sample. By far the most common measure of reliability was measures of internal consistency reliability (Cronbach’s alpha or KR20 statistics), which were reported in 112 articles (41.5% of all quantitative or mixed methods articles reported). The widespread use of Cronbach’s alpha in gifted education research is also found in the general psychological literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0016986212444122">Hogan, Benjamin, &amp; Brezinski, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Interrater reliability measures were the next most common type of reliability data reported. Correlations between ratings were the most common (17 articles; 6.3%) type of interrater reliability data, with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0016986212444122">Cohen’s (1968b)</xref> kappa (13 articles; 4.8%), percentage of agreement (8 articles; 3.0%), and unknown interrater reliability measures (2 articles; 0.7%) also appearing in the literature.</p>
<p>Other types of reliability data were less commonly reported. Authors of 11 articles (4.1%) reported test–retest reliability coefficients. Split-half correlations were reported for four articles (1.5%), with two of those correlations being corrected by the Spearman–Brown prophecy formula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0016986212444122">Brown, 1910</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0016986212444122">Spearman, 1910</xref>). The standard error of measurement was reported in three articles (1.1%). Item response theory–based statistics of reliability were reported in two articles (0.7%), and parallel forms reliability and the conditional standard error of measurement were reported in one article (0.4%) each.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0016986212444122">
<title>Miscellaneous Statistical Procedures</title>
<p>There were a variety of other statistical procedures that did not easily fit into other categories used thus far in this article. The most common miscellaneous statistics reported were intraclass correlations (13 articles; 4.8%), Box’s <italic>M</italic> (8 articles; 3.0%), Levene’s test of homogeneity of variances (6 articles; 2.2%), replication procedures (4 articles; 1.5%), Bayesian statistics (4 articles; 1.5%), and power analysis (3 articles; 1.1%). Two articles (0.7%) reported the use of the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve, Mahalanobis distance, design effect, multicollinearity diagnostics, and Bayesian information criterion (BIC). Statistical procedures that were used in only one article are listed in the footnotes of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0016986212444122">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0016986212444122">3</xref>. It is important to note that some of these miscellaneous statistical procedures are used in conjunction with some of the other methods described elsewhere in this article. For example, Levene’s test is often used to examine the homogeneity of variances assumption in an ANOVA or a <italic>t</italic> test.</p>
<sec id="section15-0016986212444122">
<title>p Values</title>
<p>Another miscellaneous reporting standard we examined was the frequency of exact <italic>p</italic> values being reported. We counted how many articles reported at least one exact <italic>p</italic> value and how many articles reported at least one inexact <italic>p</italic> value. Based on guidelines from APA (2010), “exact <italic>p</italic> values” were defined as <italic>p</italic> values that were equal to a specific number, and not just a range (i.e., <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01 was defined as an inexact <italic>p</italic>). The exceptions to this guideline were those permitted in the APA manual, namely, if <italic>p</italic> is less than .001, or if in a table it would be inefficient and cumbersome to include exact <italic>p</italic> values for all reported statistics (such as in a correlation table). These situations were counted as “exact <italic>p</italic> values.” We found that overall 78.9% of articles reported at least one exact <italic>p</italic> value, whereas 61.1% of articles reported at least one inexact <italic>p</italic> value. As these percentages indicate, there were many authors that reported a mix of exact and inexact <italic>p</italic> values.</p>
<p>We also counted the number of articles stating that <italic>p</italic> was equal or less than zero. Reported values of <italic>p</italic> = .000 or <italic>p</italic> &lt; .000 are impossible. Our review of gifted education articles indicated that 33 articles—12.2%—reported a <italic>p</italic> value of zero or less. Interestingly enough, between 2006 and 2010, authors of articles in the <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics</italic> never reported an impossible <italic>p</italic> value.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0016986212444122">
<title>Effect Sizes</title>
<p>One of the major developments in the past 25 years in educational and psychological research is the increased reporting of effect sizes. The shift in the thinking of psychological researchers about effect sizes can be seen in the changes in APA’s instructions to authors on the topic. In 1994, the fourth edition of APA’s style manual gave an “encouragement” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0016986212444122">1994</xref>, p. 18) to authors to report effect sizes. Five years later, the members of the APA Task Force on Statistical Inference said that authors should “always present effect sizes for primary outcomes” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0016986212444122">Wilkinson &amp; the Task Force on Statistical Inference, 1999</xref>, p. 599). By <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0016986212444122">2001</xref>, the fifth edition of the APA manual stated, “For the reader to fully understand the importance of your findings, it is <italic>almost always necessary</italic> to include some index of effect size” (p. 25, italics added). The current edition of the APA manual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0016986212444122">2010</xref>) included very similar language to that found in the 2001 manual. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0016986212444122">AERA (2006)</xref> has recently published recommendations to use effect sizes in quantitative research, although the instructions from AERA are not as strongly worded as those from APA.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0016986212444122">Table 4</xref> shows that the most commonly reported effect size in the gifted education literature we reviewed was η<sup>2</sup>, which was found in 86 articles (31.9%). There were two other widely popular effect sizes in the gifted education literature: Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> (75 articles; 27.8%) and <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>/<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> (60 articles; 22.2%). No other effect size was reported in more than 10 articles between 2006 and 2010. The details of effect size reporting are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0016986212444122">Table 4</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0016986212444122" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Effect Sizes Reported in Gifted Education Journals, 2006-2010, Organized by Journal and Year</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0016986212444122" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986212444122-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Journal</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Effect Size</th>
<th align="center"><italic>GCQ</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>HAS</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>JAA</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>JEG</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>RR</italic></th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>/<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>19</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>η<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>24</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cohen’s <italic>d</italic></td>
<td>20</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pseudo-<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0016986212444122">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Odds ratio</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Variance explained</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hedges’s <italic>g</italic></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ω<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>w</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unspecified effect size</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Year</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Effect Size</th>
<th align="center">2006</th>
<th align="center">2007</th>
<th align="center">2008</th>
<th align="center">2009</th>
<th align="center">2010</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>/<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>10</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>η<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>11</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cohen’s <italic>d</italic></td>
<td>17</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pseudo-<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>10<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0016986212444122">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Odds ratio</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Variance explained</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hedges’s <italic>g</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ω<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>w</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unspecified effect size</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0016986212444122">
<p>Note. <italic>GCQ</italic> = <italic>Gifted Child Quarterly; HAS</italic> = <italic>High Ability Studies; JAA</italic> = <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics; JEG</italic> = <italic>Journal for the Education of the Gifted; RR</italic> = <italic>Roeper Review</italic>. The following effect sizes were used only once: nonparametric <italic>D</italic> (<italic>HAS</italic>, 2009), Δ (<italic>HAS</italic>, 2006), ξ<sup>2</sup> (<italic>RR</italic>, 2006), τ (<italic>RR</italic>, 2006), and the percentage of subjects classified correctly (<italic>RR</italic>, 2006).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0016986212444122">
<label>a.</label>
<p>Includes pseudo-<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values calculated from both logistic regression and hierarchical linear modeling methods.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Overall, 68.1% of all quantitative and mixed methods published articles reported at least one effect size. This is a remarkable increase compared with Matthews et al.’s (2008) review in which they found that effect size reporting did not exceed 60% in any year between 1996 and 2005 for any gifted education journal. At least half of all quantitative and mixed methods articles in all the journals reported effect sizes, and for <italic>JAA</italic> the proportion exceeded three quarters (76.6%). Moreover, our estimates are rather conservative because we calculated this percentage based on <italic>all</italic> quantitative and mixed methods articles, whereas Matthews et al. eliminated articles that they decided did not need effect sizes reported. Had we done the same, these percentages would surely have increased.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0016986212444122" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this article, we examined the statistical methods used in gifted education journals. As <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0016986212444122">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0016986212444122">3</xref> show, classical parametric statistics methods are found overwhelmingly in quantitative and mixed methods articles published in gifted education journals. Overall, this trend is consistent with other recent reviews of statistical methods used in education and psychology journals (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0016986212444122">Bangert &amp; Baumberger, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0016986212444122">Baumberger &amp; Bangert, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0016986212444122">Kieffer et al., 2001</xref>). Compared with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0016986212444122">Skidmore and Thompson’s (2010)</xref> aggregate examination of the use of statistical methods in the 1990s, gifted education researchers seem to rely more on <italic>t</italic> tests and Pearson’s <italic>r</italic> correlation than other fields of education. Compared with authors of articles in psychology journals, gifted education authors use multiple regression less often, and ANOVA and <italic>t</italic> tests more often.</p>
<sec id="section18-0016986212444122">
<title>Differences Among Journals</title>
<p>The choice of statistical method seems to be mostly independent of where the article is published. There are a few exceptions to this general trend, though. <italic>JAA</italic> seems to be the venue of choice for authors who use more advanced statistical methods. For example, multiple regression was used in more than one quarter of <italic>JAA</italic> articles, where <italic>HAS</italic>—the journal that published articles using multiple regression at the second highest rate—did so in just 17.7% of articles. <italic>JAA</italic> also published all the articles in gifted education that used logistic regression between 2006 and 2010. However, <italic>GCQ</italic> also published a large share of articles that used advanced statistical methods, such as HLM and path analysis. It is also important to note that <italic>GCQ</italic> and <italic>RR</italic> also published noticeably more articles that used a χ<sup>2</sup> statistical significance test than the other journals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0016986212444122">
<title>Trends in Statistical Methods</title>
<p>The only major trend that we observed and found noteworthy was a decline in the use of <italic>t</italic> tests in recent years. In 2006 and 2007, <italic>t</italic> tests appeared in 34.6% and 37.7% of articles, respectively. In 2008, 2009, and 2010, though, <italic>t</italic> tests were used in 28.6%, 24.6%, and 25.0% of quantitative and mixed methods articles. It would be interesting to follow up on this study in the future and determine whether this trend continues.</p>
<p>We believe that there were two problems with identifying trends in the use of statistical methods. First, because we only examined 5 years of published articles, it is possible that not enough time has passed for identifiable trends to emerge. Second, very few articles used advanced and nonparametric methods, which made even minor fluctuations produce apparently large changes in their frequency of use. For example, HLM was used in a total of eight articles between 2006 and 2010; none of those articles were published in 2007 and half of those articles were published in 2010. It is not clear right now whether HLM was more frequently used in later years because it is actually becoming more common, or whether the relatively rare use of HLM means that from time to time a year will occur when a slightly higher number of HLM articles are published.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0016986212444122">
<title>Other Findings</title>
<p>As we conducted this study, we noticed several tendencies among the researchers who produced quantitative articles in gifted education. One of the most noticeable was how they report effect sizes. Although we are impressed that more gifted education researchers are reporting effect sizes, we question whether researchers understand the effect sizes they are reporting. Dozens of authors, for example, merely cited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0016986212444122">Cohen’s (1988)</xref> benchmarks and labeled their effect sizes as “large,” “medium,” or “small” and provided no further interpretation. However, Cohen himself stated several times in his landmark 1988 book (e.g., pp. 12, 25, 79, 113, 147, 184, 224, 285, 413, 478, 532) that his benchmarks should only be used when there was little or no previous research on the topic at hand and should not apply to all social science research situations. Moreover, the “large” effects can be trivial and “small” effects can be critically important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0016986212444122">Gentry &amp; Peters, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0016986212444122">Durlak (2009)</xref> elaborated on these points, saying:
<disp-quote><p>Now that thousands of studies and meta-analyses have been conducted in the social sciences, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0016986212444122">Cohen’s (1988)</xref> general conventions do not automatically apply. Moreover, assuming that “large” effects are always more important than “small” or “medium” ones is unjustified. It is not only the magnitude of effect that is important, but also its practical or clinical value that must be considered. (pp. 922-923)</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In light of these ideas, we urge researchers in gifted education to stop using Cohen’s benchmarks, unless there is no previous research on their topic, and to instead provide interpretations and judgments of the meaning of their effect sizes. This will bring researchers’ practices in line with modern quantitative psychologists’ recommendations for interpreting effect sizes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986212444122">Cooper, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0016986212444122">Durlak, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0016986212444122">Gentry &amp; Peters, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>We are also concerned with the post hoc tests that gifted education researchers use after determining that their ANOVA or MANOVA tests are statistically significant. Despite how common the -OVA methods are found in gifted education research, we have serious doubts about whether many researchers understand how to interpret such statistical tests, especially MANOVA and MANCOVA. General practice is to follow a statistically significant ANOVA or ANCOVA with a specifically designed post hoc test, such as Tukey’s or Scheffé’s test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0016986212444122">Heiman, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0016986212444122">Thompson, 2006</xref>). Yet in nine articles authors followed their statistically significant ANOVA or ANCOVA with <italic>t</italic> tests, often with an accompanying Bonferroni correction. We believe that conducting a series of post hoc <italic>t</italic> tests defeats the purpose of the original ANOVA. Similarly, following a MANOVA or MANCOVA with a post hoc ANOVA—which was the most common post hoc technique in the articles we examined—instead of the recommended discriminant analysis (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0016986212444122">Bray &amp; Maxwell, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0016986212444122">Thompson, Diamond, McWilliam, Snyder, &amp; Snyder, 2005</xref>) often sidesteps the issue of whether the groups are equal on <italic>combinations</italic> of dependent variables, which is the main purpose of conducting an MANOVA in the first place.</p>
<p>We also believe that some gifted education researchers have misconceptions about <italic>p</italic> values obtained from null hypothesis statistical significance tests. As stated above, <italic>p</italic> values equal to 0 or less were reported in 12.2% of articles. However, this is an impossible statistical result because <italic>p</italic> is a probability value, which must always be positive (hence, <italic>p</italic> being less than 0 is impossible). Moreover, a <italic>p</italic> value of zero would imply that the sample does not belong to the population to which the researcher wishes to generalize, and therefore, the statistical test should not be conducted at all. We think that there is no excuse for such a basic error in reporting quantitative results. On the other hand, we applaud the editors of <italic>JAA</italic> for their vigilance in preventing a single impossible <italic>p</italic> value from being reported.</p>
<p>The results that we found from analyzing the decisions made by authors who used data reduction methods also gives us cause to pause. The results of the review indicated that varimax rotation method was used most frequently in gifted education articles and that the most common factor retention method named was the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0016986212444122">Guttman (1954)</xref> rule, where all factors with an eigenvalue greater than one are retained. Although varimax rotation has its place, it requires factors to be completely uncorrelated—an unrealistic assumption in many situations in education and psychology. Also, the Guttman rule has been long established as one of the least accurate guides for determining how many factors to retain in an EFA or PCA (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0016986212444122">Hakstian, Rogers, &amp; Catell, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0016986212444122">Velicer, Eaton, &amp; Fava, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0016986212444122">Zwick &amp; Velicer, 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0016986212444122">1986</xref>). We believe that the fact that both these methods are the default settings on SPSS is not a coincidence and may indicate that some researchers who use data reduction methods like EFA and PCA do not understand how to make the subjective decisions required to properly conduct these statistical analyses.</p>
<p>Finally, we were disappointed in the appearance of six articles with stepwise regression in the gifted education literature. Stepwise regression is a notoriously poor statistical method with pervasive, intrinsic problems (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0016986212444122">Huberty, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0016986212444122">Thompson, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0016986212444122">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0016986212444122">2006</xref>). In fact, stepwise regression is so problematic that there is even one published article titled, “Why Won’t Stepwise Methods Die?” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0016986212444122">Thompson, 1989</xref>). Stepwise methods are problematic for three main reasons: they use the wrong degrees of freedom when calculating <italic>F</italic>
<sub>obs</sub> (and therefore artificially drive down <italic>p</italic> values), capitalize on sampling error, and do not produce the best <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> possible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0016986212444122">Thompson, 1995</xref>). We strongly urge researchers in gifted education to completely abandon stepwise regression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0016986212444122">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>We believe that this summary of statistical methods used in gifted education articles has several important implications for the field. First, this article can give guidance to those who train the next generation of gifted education researchers and practitioners in choosing which statistical methods their graduate students should master to understand the field’s literature. After conducting this research study, we believe that a professional in the field should be able to master classical parametric methods (i.e., <italic>t</italic> tests, ANOVA, correlation, regression) and basic multivariate methods—especially MANOVA, which was found in almost one quarter of articles. Based on our experience and education, this sequence of statistics would likely take three semesters, or about a year and a half. However, it has been found that in psychology, only doctoral students in quantitative psychology are typically required to take this many statistics courses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0016986212444122">Aiken, West, &amp; Millsap, 2008</xref>). Therefore, the typical graduate of a doctoral program in psychology is not able to comprehend or evaluate large portions of the quantitative research that is being published in leading gifted education journals. Although we were not able to find similar information for education or gifted education programs, we doubt that three semesters of statistics is a common requirement for education doctoral students.</p>
<p>Another implication that arises from this article is the editorial policies of the journals we examined. To our knowledge, only <italic>JAA</italic> requires authors to report effect sizes where appropriate; it is also likely an editorial policy at <italic>JAA</italic> that <italic>p</italic> values never be reported as 0 or as being less than 0. We suggest that the editors of the other journals that we reviewed adopt these policies and that all journal editors in gifted education examine their statistical editorial policies to encourage better statistical reporting practices. We also suggest that journal editors be savvy in a wide variety of statistics so that they can fulfill their role as gatekeepers of the published literature and determine whether statistical methods are being used and reported correctly.</p>
<p>We also believe that this article raises further questions about where research in gifted education is headed. Although there are no clear trends in the use rate of multivariate statistics, we believe that the notable percentages of articles using advanced statistical methods like SEM, HLM, and others indicates that at least a portion of the research community is embracing these methods. We believe that this is a positive development because there are some research questions that can only be answered through the use of complex methods. Although there may be a certain elegance in a correlation or a <italic>t</italic> test of two group means, reality is messy and complex and sometimes that reality requires statistical methods that are similarly complex to understand it. We hope that more researchers will embrace complex statistical methods so that the psychological and social phenomena that accompany giftedness may be better understood in the future.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0016986212444122">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>As with all research, there are some limitations to our statistical review of the literature. First, despite our efforts to give our coding system as much integrity and quality as possible, it was inevitable that the real world of published literature would not conform seamlessly to our coding system. This unavoidably led to some subjective judgment in the classification of articles and in interpreting the authors’ descriptions of their methodological and statistical procedures. For example, we were often forced to make a subjective judgment about whether the authors were reporting the reliability information for their own data. Although we consulted test manuals and previous research that used the same psychometric instrument, it was sometimes necessary to decide whether it was likely or probable that the authors were reporting their own reliability data. We believe that by having two different people read each article and requiring agreement on all aspects of the coding that our subjective judgments are justified.</p>
<p>Second, if other researchers were to conduct a similar review of statistical methods, they would likely produce different results. Indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0016986212444122">Skidmore and Thompson (2010)</xref> found that occasionally in other reviews of statistical methods the same volumes of journals would be analyzed by different authors who produced different results. Nevertheless, we believe that having two coders improved our results and that any other analyses of the same volumes of the journals would produce similar findings.</p>
<p>An anonymous reviewer brought to our attention a final limitation of this study, which stems from the fact that statistical methods are merely tools in the research process. With rare exceptions (e.g., stepwise regression), we do not believe that any statistical methods are <italic>good</italic> or <italic>bad</italic>. Rather, statistical methods should be used if they are appropriate for the research question at hand and if the data meet the required assumptions. This investigation of statistical methods was inherently acontextual and we made few judgments about whether these methods were being used appropriately. As stated earlier, complex statistical methods are sometimes necessary to answer complex research questions; similarly, sometimes even the simplest statistical methods may be the best option for testing theories or hypotheses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0016986212444122" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Overall, this review of the literature indicates that gifted education researchers share some similarities in their use of statistical methods with researchers in other areas of psychology and education. Broadly speaking, gifted education researchers favor classical parametric methods over other statistical tools for analyzing their data. However, a notably large portion of articles used multivariate methods— especially MANOVA. We hope that our findings and our discussion of the results will spur a methodological conversation among quantitative researchers that will help researchers conduct better research and gain greater insight into giftedness.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>The second, third, and fourth authors all contributed to the study equally; they are listed alphabetically.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article:</p>
<p>Partial funding for this research was provided by the Lohman/Heep Fellowship at Texas A&amp;M University.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Russell T. Warne</bold>, PhD, is an assistant professor of psychology in the Department of Behavioral Science at Utah Valley University, where he teaches courses in statistics, social science research methods, and psychometrics. He is the winner of the 2009 and 2010 awards for best doctoral-level research in progress from the National Association for Gifted Children. He has previously been published in <italic>Gifted Child Quarterly, Review of General Psychology, American Journal of Health Behavior</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Advanced Academics</italic>, and more. His research interests are in measurement, quantitative methods, giftedness, and intelligence.</p>
<p><bold>Maria Lazo</bold> is a doctoral student in the Educational Psychology Department with a specialization in cognition, creativity, instruction, and development at Texas A&amp;M University. She is also a graduate assistant with the Texas A&amp;M Center for Teaching Excellence. Her research interests include intelligence testing, issues in teacher preparation, creative thinking, and identifying disparities in gifted education. More specifically, her work examines the verbal/ nonverbal intelligence gaps in gifted children from poverty, along with determining how faculty members promote creative thinking in higher education.</p>
<p><bold>Tammy Ramos</bold> is a doctoral student in the Educational Psychology Department, specializing in Educational Technology, at Texas A&amp;M University. She is also a graduate assistant for Technology Services (Instructional Technology Group) in the College of Education and Human Development, working with various instructional development projects. Her research interests focus on self-regulation within the online learning environment, concentrating on the preparation of virtual students, and their academic success within this setting.</p>
<p><bold>Nicola Ritter</bold> is a doctoral student in the Educational Psychology Department, specializing in educational technology, at Texas A&amp;M University. She holds a certificate in Education &amp; Social Sciences Advanced Research Methods with emphasis in advanced behavioral measurement and item response theory. She is also a graduate research assistant with the Department of Student Life Studies. Her primary research interests are focused on adaptive learning systems, methodological issues in educational technology, and technology adoption.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aiken</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Millsap</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Doctoral training in statistics, measurement, and methodology in psychology: Replication and extension of Aiken, West, Sechrest, and Reno’s (1990) survey of PhD programs in North America</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:10.1037/0003-066X.63.1.32<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0003-066X.63.1.32</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agresti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>An introduction to categorical data analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>American Educational Research Association</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Standards for reporting on empirical social science research in AERA publications</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:10.3102/0013189x035006033<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3102/0013189x035006033</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychological Association</collab>. (<year>1994</year>). <source>Publication manual of the American Psychological Association</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychological Association</collab>. (<year>2001</year>). <source>Publication manual of the American Psychological Association</source> (<edition>5th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychological Association</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Publication manual of the American Psychological Association</source> (<edition>6th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>APA Publications and Communications Board Working Group on Journal Article Reporting Standards</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Reporting standards for research in psychology: Why do we need them? What might they be?</article-title> <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>839</fpage>-<lpage>851</lpage>. doi:10.1037/0003-066x.63.9.839<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0003-066x.63.9.839</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bangert</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumberger</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Research and statistical techniques used in the <italic>Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</italic>: 1990-2001</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</source>, <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>480</fpage>-<lpage>487</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumberger</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bangert</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Research designs and statistical techniques used in the <italic>Journal of Learning Disabilities</italic>, 1989-1993</article-title>. <source>Journal of Learning Disabilities</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>313</fpage>-<lpage>316</lpage>. doi:10.1177/002221949602900310<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002221949602900310</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Multivariate analysis of variance</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1910</year>). <article-title>Some experimental results in the correlation of mental abilities</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychology</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>296</fpage>-<lpage>322</lpage>. doi:10.1111/j.2044-8295-1910.tb00207.x<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8295-1910.tb00207.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968a</year>). <article-title>Multiple regression as a general data-analytic system</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>426</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>. doi:10.1037/h0026714<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0026714</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968b</year>). <article-title>Weighted kappa: Nominal scale agreement with provision for scaled disagreement or partial credit</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>. doi:10.1037/h0026256<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0026256</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dabbs</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The state of qualitative research in gifted education as published in American journals: An analysis and critique</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Quarterly</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0016986206296656<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986206296656</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Research synthesis and meta-analysis</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Best practices in exploratory factor analysis: Four recommendations for getting the most from your analysis</article-title>. <source>Practical Assessment, Research &amp; Evaluation</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>State of research on giftedness and gifted education: A survey of empirical studies published during 1998-2010 (April)</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Quarterly</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0016986210397831<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986210397831</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deditius-Island</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>An examination of the reliability of scores from Zuckerman’s Sensation Seeking Scales, Form V</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>728</fpage>-<lpage>734</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0013164402062004012<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164402062004012</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Durlak</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>How to select, calculate and interpret effect sizes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pediatric Psychology</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>917</fpage>-<lpage>928</lpage>. doi:10.1093/jpepsy/jsp004<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpepsy/jsp004</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edgington</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>). <article-title>A tabulation of inferential statistics used in psychology journals</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:10.1037/h0039177<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0039177</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edgington</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>A new tabulation of statistical procedures used in APA journals</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:10.1037/h0035846<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0035846</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elmore</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woehlke</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Statistical methods employed in <italic>American Educational Research Journal, Educational Researcher</italic>, and <italic>Review of Educational Research</italic> from 1978 to 1987</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:10.3102/0013189X017009019<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3102/0013189X017009019</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ferron</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogarty</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dedrick</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niles</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kromrey</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Reporting results from multilevel analyses</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>O’Connell</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Multilevel modeling of educational data</source> (pp. <fpage>391</fpage>-<lpage>426</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Charlotte, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Information Age</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fidler</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Statistical significance, result worthiness and evidence: What lessons are there for giftedness education in other disciplines?</article-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subotnik</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Methodologies for conducting research on giftedness</source> (pp. <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effect sizes in gifted education research</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Quarterly</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0016986209334976<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986209334976</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1954</year>). <article-title>Some necessary conditions for common-factor analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychometrika</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:10.1007/BF02289162<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02289162</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hakstian</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cattell</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The behavior of number-of-factors rules with simulated data</article-title>. <source>Multivariate Behavioral Research</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:10.1207/s15327906mbr1702_3<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15327906mbr1702_3</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Behavioral sciences STAT</source>. <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth Cengage Learning</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brezinski</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Reliability methods: A note on the frequency of use of various types</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>523</fpage>-<lpage>531</lpage>. doi:10.1177/00131640021970691<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00131640021970691</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Multilevel analysis: Techniques and applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huberty</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Problems with stepwise methods—better alternatives</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Advances in social science methodology</source> (<volume>Vol. 1</volume>, pp. <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Greenwich, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Structural equation modeling: Foundations and extensions</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A reliability generalization study of the Geriatric Depression Scale</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>969</fpage>-<lpage>994</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0013164402238085<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164402238085</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Statistical techniques employed in <italic>AERJ</italic> and <italic>JCP</italic> articles from 1988 to 1997: A methodological review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Education</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>. doi:10.1080/00220970109599489<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00220970109599489</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Principles and practice of structural equation modeling</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warne</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Estimating confidence intervals for eigenvalues in exploratory factor analysis</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>871</fpage>-<lpage>876</lpage>. doi:10.3758/BRM.42.3.871<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BRM.42.3.871</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lipsey</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Practical meta-analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Worrell</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Evaluating the state of a field: Effect size reporting in gifted education</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Education</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:10.3200/JEXE.77.1.55-68<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3200/JEXE.77.1.55-68</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010a</year>). <article-title>Dealing with dependence (Part II): A gentle introduction to hierarchical linear modeling</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Quarterly</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>256</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0016986210373475<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986210373475</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>Hierarchical linear modeling</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>R. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The reviewer’s guide to quantitative methods in the social sciences</source> (pp. <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adelson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Dealing with dependence (Part I): Understanding the effects of clustered data</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Quarterly</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0016986210363076<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986210363076</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The first word: A letter from the co-editors: Effect sizes—An explanation of <italic>JAA</italic> editorial policy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Academics</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1932202X0902000201<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1932202X0902000201</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>SPSS and SAS programs for determining the number of components using parallel analysis and Velicer’s MAP test</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &amp; Computers</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>396</fpage>-<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:10.3758/BF03200807<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03200807</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aspiranti</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Publications in four gifted education journals from 2001 to 2006: An analysis of article types and authorship characteristics</article-title>. <source>Roeper Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raudenbush</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryk</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Hierarchical linear models: Applications and data analysis methods</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>A reliability induction and reliability generalization study of the Cage Questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>254</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0013164403261814<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164403261814</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Statistical techniques used in published articles: A historical review of reviews</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>777</fpage>-<lpage>795</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0013164410379320<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164410379320</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spearman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1910</year>). <article-title>Correlation calculated from faulty data</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychology</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>295</lpage>. doi:10.111/j.2044-8295.1910.tb00206.x<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.111/j.2044-8295.1910.tb00206.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Applied multivariate statistics for the social sciences</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Assessing goodness of fit in confirmatory factor analysis</article-title>. <source>Measurement and Evaluation in Counseling and Development</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>-<lpage>256</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Why won’t stepwise methods die?</article-title> <source>Measurement and Evaluation in Counseling and Development</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Stepwise regression and stepwise discriminant analysis need not apply here: A guidelines editorial</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>534</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0013164495055004001<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164495055004001</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Significance, effect sizes, stepwise methods, and other issues: Strong arguments move the field</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Education</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:10.1080/00220970109599499<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00220970109599499</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Foundations of behavioral statistics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Evaluating the quality of evidence from correlational research for evidence-based practice</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vacha-Haase</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kogan</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Sample compositions and variabilities in published studies versus those in test manuals: Validity of score reliability inductions</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>522</lpage>. doi:10.1177/00131640021970682<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00131640021970682</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Velicer</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Construct explication through factor or component analysis: A review and evaluation of alternative procedures for determining the number of factors or components</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Goffin</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Helmes</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Problems and solutions in human assessment: Honoring Douglas N. Jackson at seventy</source> (pp. <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic/Plenum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warne</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A reliability generalization of the Overexcitability Questionnaire–Two (OEQII)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Academics</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>671</fpage>-<lpage>692</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1932202X11424881<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1932202X11424881</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warne</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKyer</surname><given-names>E. L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Condie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diep</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murano</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<comment>in press</comment>). <article-title>Dealing with data dependence using hierarchical linear modeling</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nutrition Education and Behavior</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <collab>&amp; the Task Force on Statistical Inference</collab>. (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Statistical methods in psychology journals: Guidelines and explanations</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>594</fpage>-<lpage>604</lpage>. doi:10.1037/0003-066X.54.8.594<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0003-066X.54.8.594</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Research techniques in <italic>AERJ</italic> articles: 1969 to 1978</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:10.3102/0013189X009006005<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3102/0013189X009006005</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zwick</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Velicer</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Factors influencing four rules for determining the number of components to retain</article-title>. <source>Multivariate Behavioral Research</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>269</lpage>. doi:10.1207/s15327906mbr1702_5<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15327906mbr1702_5</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0016986212444122">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zwick</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Velicer</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Comparison of five rules for determining the number of components to retain</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>-<lpage>442</lpage>. doi:10.1037/0033-2909.99.3.432<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.99.3.432</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>