<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Industrial Relations</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1856</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1472-9296</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022185612466625c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022185612466625c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Greg Bamber, Russell Lansbury and Nick Wailes (eds) <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations: Globalisation and Change</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0022185612466625c">James Cook University, Australia</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>55</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>161</fpage>
<lpage>163</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Australian Labour and Employment Relations Association (ALERA), SAGE Publications Ltd, Los Angeles, London, New Delhi, Singapore and Washington DC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">ALERA</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0022185612466625c"><title>Greg Bamber, Russell Lansbury and Nick Wailes (eds) <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations: Globalisation and Change</italic>. Crows Nest, NSW: Allen and Unwin, 2011, xxix + 418 pp., AU$55.00 (pbk).</title>
<p>The fifth edition of <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations</italic> (the first was published in 1987) is more than an update of the fourth edition, as were the second and fourth editions more than updates of the first and third. Each remains a labour studies resource in its own right. Greg Bamber, Russell Lansbury and Nick Wailes have added 17 new authors of the country studies and three countries – Denmark, India and China – to their fifth edition (gone is Sweden), in which they categorise the country studies within a new conceptual framework. Unlike in the fourth edition, there is no concluding chapter to ‘review and synthesise’ the development of employment relations of the country chapters.</p>
<p>Although, according to its editors, <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations</italic> is an ‘extensively prescribed’ text in its field, it remains uncluttered by the teaching and learning paraphernalia that has inundated course textbooks and trivialised their authors’ scholarship. Its learning objectives are succinctly put in Thomas Kochan’s foreword: ‘Understanding these developments [the renewal in the field of international and comparative employment relations arising from national, international and global transformations] increases the range of options from which managers, union leaders and government policy-makers can choose in shaping their own employment practices’ (p. viii), that is, both intellectual (‘understanding’) and practical (‘shaping’) purposes. In their introduction, Bamber et al. provide three reasons for studying international and comparative industrial relations: to acquire knowledge of employment relations in different countries; to use models to improve understanding; and the most important, as also for Roy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0022185612466625c">Bean (1994)</xref>, whose pioneer work they reference, for its ‘potential to provide theoretical insight into the factors and variables that shape the relationships between employers and employees’ (p. 4).</p>
<p>Following a reappraisal of the theoretical and conceptual underpinnings of their earlier editions – which included ‘Type I’ and ‘Type II’ national typologies (first edition), strategic choice, convergence and divergence (second edition), workplace relations (third edition), and internationalisation and globalisation (fourth edition) – the editors revisit diversity in the form of varieties of capitalism, concluding, after acknowledging the criticisms of the approach, ‘that a modified form of its approach, one that is less deterministic … provides a promising basis for the advancement of international and comparative employment relations’ (p. 25). The varieties are liberal market economies (the USA, UK, Canada and Australia, in this text) and coordinated market economies (Denmark, Germany and Japan, and perhaps Korea, in this text). The editors further categorise the national economies by geo-culture, stage of development and market type: the liberal and coordinated market economies (as above); the European developed economies; the Asian developed economies (Japan and South Korea); and the Asian emerging economies (China and India).</p>
<p>Most of the individual country chapters of <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations</italic> follow a common structure of historical and legal context of employment relations, the parties, employment relations processes, current issues and future trends, and a chronology. The chapter on Britain (by Mick Marchington, Jeremy Waddington and Andrew Timming) mostly avoids the broader concept of ‘employment relations’, which its authors claim ‘has become blurred and fragmented due to the growth of networks … due to privatisation and to increases in subcontracting’, and keeps to ‘industrial relations’ (p. 37). The chapter on the USA deals with the implications of the schism in the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) that saw the formation in 2005 of the Change to Win Coalition (Harry Katz and Alexander Colvin), but Canada (Mark Thompson and Daphne Taras), unlike the USA and other developed market economies, shows few signs of structural change. Following a sequence of legislated reform of industrial relations beginning with the Industrial Relations Act of 1988, and since the fourth edition, Australia (by Lansbury and Wailes) has experienced a pro-employer Workplace Relations Amendment (Work Choices) Act in 2005, and a partial reversal of Work Choices with a Fair Work Act in 2009.</p>
<p>Of the four Continental European countries included in the book, Janine Goetschy and Annette Jobert are pessimistic about the prospects for social dialogue in France, and Berndt Keller and Anja Kirsch claim to be witnessing the decline of the German model and something of a convergence towards the Anglo-American one. Lucio Baccaro and Valeria Pulignano explain how the <italic>evento storico</italic> of the tripartite agreement in Italy in 1993 has been implemented in such a way that wages have lagged inflation, and in spite of the Italian unions’ mobilising capacity, they are ‘on their way to becoming a marginal labour market actor’ because of their declining membership (p. 147). Denmark (Jorgen Steen Madsen, Jesper Due and Soren Kaj Andersen) is included because of its novel, even ‘model’, employment relations (p. 2), and the chapter’s author foresees that if ‘the unions, particularly in the LO [<italic>Landsorganisationen I Danmark</italic>], can stem their loss of members in the coming years, there will also be a future for the Danish model’ (p. 248).</p>
<p>Japan has been in every edition of the book and South Korea was added in 1998, on the grounds that it had joined the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). Hiromasa Suzuki and Katsuyuki Kubo attribute the ‘considerable’ changes in Japan’s employment relations to ‘the relative decline of the predominance of the Japanese economy in the world’ since the 1990s; the ‘increasing globalisation of Japanese firms’ sustained by plants in China; ‘the shift towards a service economy’ (such that two-thirds of employment is in the tertiary sector); and an ageing population, which is more rapid than in most developed countries. They lament that ‘the weight of [industrial] disputes has shifted from the collective to the individual’ (pp. 252–280). Japan has seen an increase in ‘atypical employment’ – part-time, fixed-term and temporary workers – in recent years, and Korea (Byoung-Hoon Lee) in the size of its ‘non-standard labour force’. Discrimination against non-standard workers and a decrease in decent jobs, Lee claims, has served to polarise Korea’s labour market.</p>
<p>The Asian newcomers to <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations</italic> are China (Fang Lee Cooke) and India (CS Venkata Ratnam and Anil Verma). For those who find accounts of Chinese employment relations enigmatic, Cooke’s chapter provides an informative, insightful, analytical and as comprehensive an account of current development as a single chapter will allow. Among the developments discussed in this chapter are China’s bureaucratic complexity, the localisation of regulations and an increase in employer lobbying. Venkata Ratnam (who sadly died before this edition was published) and Verma offer an industrial relations-oriented chapter on employment relations in India, reflecting the fact that in spite of the reforms of the 1990s and subsequent liberalisation and globalisation, labour policy has focused on the small proportion (7%) of workers in India in the organised sector.</p>
<p>Especially for those of us who present employment relations in scholarly forums and in lecture halls, but also for policymakers and practitioners, <italic>International and Comparative Employment Relations</italic>, as have been its earlier editions, is an indispensable foundation text to be consulted before taking up more specialised country studies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0022185612466625c"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Comparative Industrial Relations: An Introduction to Cross-national Perspectives</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>