<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptso</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Teach Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Teaching Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0092-055X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-862X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092055X11420401</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0092055X11420401</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Film Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Plunder: The Crime of Our Time</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Scanlan</surname><given-names>Stephen J.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0092055X11420401">Ohio University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>83</lpage>
<product>
<source>Plunder: The Crime of Our Time</source>. <comment>59 minutes</comment>. <year>2010</year>. <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>Danny</given-names></name>
</person-group>, filmmaker. <article-title>Media Education Foundation</article-title>. <comment>60 Masonic Street, Northampton, MA 01060</comment>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediaed.org">www.mediaed.org</ext-link>. Institutional purchase: <price>$250.00</price>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It is probably the most significant yet least understood crisis to have occurred in the young lives of average college students today. Sociology faculty themselves are likely to struggle as well to grasp the entirety of the situation unless acquainted with it through their teaching or research expertise. With little help available from the news media in disentangling what has been described in the film as “the greatest nonviolent crime against humanity in history,” there is a great need for awareness and comprehension. What is of so dire concern? According to Danny Schefter in the documentary <italic>Plunder: The Crime of Our Time</italic>, it is the deception, fraud, schemes, and predatory practices behind the current global economic crisis. His film is an attempt to simplify and explain the causes and consequences of the crisis, raise awareness among an uninformed public, and ultimately call for action to obtain justice.</p>
<p>Schefter wishes to shift the public dialogue and perspective on the current fiscal crisis in his film. Putting the catastrophe in the context of what he believes to be a perception of free market capitalism viewed in quasi-religious terms by the general public, <italic>Plunder</italic> seeks to reframe Wall Street from being viewed as a financial center to a crime scene instead that beckons investigation and demands repair. The film explores the economic predation, absence of regulation, blind faith in the market, and lack of media scrutiny argued to have caused the economic collapse and related consequences such as lost homes from the foreclosure crisis, looted pension funds, and increased unemployment and poverty. Referring to the economic crisis in the United States as “financial AIDS” that has infected the entire world, <italic>Plunder</italic> emphasizes the increased class polarization and the ongoing transfer of wealth from the poor, persons of color, and a decimated middle class to an increasingly empowered wealthy elite class who has benefitted from the crisis.</p>
<p>Building off of Schefter’s own work as an author and social critic and also relying on former Wall Street insiders and investigative reporters interested in the crisis, <italic>Plunder</italic> is well researched and clearly articulated in its arguments. The approach to the film is clearly organized around the interconnections of three circles at the root of the crisis (a “three ring circus,” so to speak): 1) the real estate and banking industry and their fraudulent, predatory lending practices and subprime mortgages; 2) Wall Street and commercial investment firms and “scrutinizers” who purchased, bundled, and resold fraudulent mortgages; and 3) the insurance industry that guaranteed protection of what ultimately are junk packages and toxic assets. Others implicated in this process include failure of government policy makers and regulators, lack of resources for proper law enforcement and prosecution, and the absence of vigorous investigation and criticism by the news media which in many ways was complicit in the process. In breaking down the crisis with regard to both the institutional actors and the individual players empowered to make the decisions within these structures <italic>Plunder</italic> argues effectively as to how “rogue economics” and a Wall Street that has hijacked the economy have brought the broken system to near meltdown and while the future remains uncertain.</p>
<p>One of the greatest strengths of the film is its ability to simplify and explain economic terms and processes in an informative and critical way (as with hedge funds or subprime lending, for example) that at the same time evokes a desire to want to learn more about how such processes are even possible and what can be done to fix them. <italic>Plunder</italic> makes clear the numerous sociopolitical dynamics at work in the economy and their implications. Most appealing to sociology students is the film’s relevance to concepts such as class structure, corporate and white collar crime, media–society relations, power, and social inequality among others. In addition, although certainly not overly “theoretical” in its approach or presentation (which some may view as a weakness), the connections to classical sociological perspectives are quite evident and students will appreciate being able to apply such core concepts to the realities of the present situation and events. The film’s discussion and critique of the U.S. government’s bailout of Wall Street, for example, and the resulting class war like no other ever seen before between the haves and have-nots is one such case.</p>
<p>Another strength of the film is its ability to humanize what in reality are seemingly distant structural processes. <italic>Plunder</italic> not only relies on the expertise of those intimately involved in the system of manipulation, such as convicted white collar criminal Sam Antar (e.g., “The white collar criminal has no legal constraints. You subpoena documents we destroy documents. You subpoena witnesses, we lie. So you are at a disadvantage when it comes to the white collar criminal.”), but also involves those affected by such manipulation. Activism by and on behalf of those victimized by the crisis is interwoven throughout the film, thus giving it a sense of urgency because of the effects it has had on ordinary citizens. Whether describing someone who has lost her or his home from predatory lending or others whose retirement pensions have been squeezed dry, <italic>Plunder</italic> puts a face on the consequences of the economic crisis and gives it a voice for change as seen in street protests and heard in songs critiquing the crisis. In this regard Schefter intends for the film to be a call for action in search of economic and social justice for those harmed and punishment for those who caused the mess (a “jailout instead of a bailout”).</p>
<p>On this note and with regard to potential shortcomings of the film, as is the case with many documentary films seeking to not only inform “the masses” but also inspire them to action (in the case here even invoking the question of needing “pitch forks and protests” to demand change), <italic>Plunder</italic> certainly has its biases and a point of view it wishes to emphasize and promote as “right.” This should not be a surprise at a time when media outlets on both the left and right “preach to the converted” without little meaningful dialogue between them. Although not necessarily a weakness in the film, those seeking a more balanced approach to the current economic crisis may be disappointed in the presentation and lack of alternative perspectives and should therefore prepare accordingly. Furthermore, with regard to the quality of filmmaking itself, although this work is shot and edited well and uses good writing to support its objectives and purpose, those used to the panache of Michael Moore as seen in films such as <italic>Capitalism: A Love Story</italic> (which takes on related arguments and concerns as <italic>Plunder</italic>) may be disappointed. This should not be taken as a failing on behalf of Schefter to make a solid film, however, but instead speaks to the quality and consistency of Moore to produce outstanding work (and with a filmmaking budget to match).</p>
<p>The film is most suitable for the undergraduate classroom, and there are a number of courses to which it could be adapted, including consumerism, criminology, and deviance (especially corporate and/or white collar crime specifically); economic sociology; law and society; organizations; political sociology; social problems; social stratification; and theory among others. Introductory sociology is also possible with perhaps greater effort required of the faculty member to ensure understanding of the complexities of the crisis and the connections to its multiple sociological themes. By using preparatory and follow-up readings, assignments, and in-class discussion and exercises, instructors will find the film to be an important teaching tool that will help students gain a basic understanding of the structural factors, power dynamics, and individual decision making leading to the fiscal collapse. Sociologists wishing to engage public dialogue on the topics of interest would also find <italic>Plunder</italic> a useful component of a film series in a community center or university setting addressing current issues, something the filmmaker would certainly endorse.</p>
<p>In sum, complete with its own soundtrack of musical commentary that is mixed into the film, <italic>Plunder</italic> is engaging in its presentation and informative in its content and criticism. I envision the film being useful for teaching sociology on a variety of fronts and ultimately helping to provide a basic understanding of this important issue whose effects will be felt for years to come.</p>
</body>
</article>