<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Criminology &amp; Criminal Justice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1748-8958</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1748-8966</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1748895812474550</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1748895812474550</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: International and Comparative Criminal Justice and Urban Governance: Convergence and Divergence in Global, National and Local Settings</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Millie</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1748895812474550">Cardiff University, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Policing in a time of contraction and constraint: Re-imagining the role and function of contemporary policing</issue-title>
<fpage>232</fpage>
<lpage>239</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.)<source>International and Comparative Criminal Justice and Urban Governance: Convergence and Divergence in Global, National and Local Settings</source>, <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>; <page-count count="634"/> pp.: <isbn>9780521116442</isbn>, <price>£90</price> (hbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This new edited book by Adam Crawford, the result of an international conference held in 2008, offers a treasure trove of thoughtful and up-to-date reflections on the changing scene of international and comparative criminal justice. The volume is divided into three parts dealing with international criminal justice, comparative policies and comparative crime control and urban governance. It opens with a lengthy introduction by the editor which sets out the challenges to comparative criminal justice and provides succinct summaries of the contributions to the book. The first section, on international criminal justice, includes contributions by luminaries such as Findlay on locating criminal communities within international criminal justice; Parmentier, Valiñas and Weitekamp on war crimes; and Van Zyl Smit and Snacken on the European Court of Human Rights. The second section, on comparative penal policies, includes further reflections about comparative punitiveness from leading contributors to this debate such as Cavadino and Dignan, Lacey, Pratt and Karstedt among others. The last section discusses comparative crime control and urban governance and includes contributions by insightful scholars such as Aas, Boutellier, Body-Gendrot, Valverde and Crawford himself.</p>
<p>As is true of most conference books, while almost all the chapters make valuable contributions in their own right, the difficulty lies in making the whole more than the sum of its parts. The notes on the back of the book tell us that:<disp-quote>
<p>the emergence of new international justice institutions such as the International Criminal Court, the greater movement of people and goods across national borders and the transfer of criminal justice policies between different jurisdictions all present novel challenges to criminal justice systems as well as our understandings of criminal justice.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>We learn that this collection provides the conceptual parameters to three key themes: (1) the growing internationalization of criminal justice and its implications; (2) the comparative study of penal policies; and (3) the interface between local and international trends in urban governance and crime control. Choosing leading writers who are aware of each other’s work does make for some valuable overlap in both topic and argument. But even Crawford, in his useful synoptic introduction, admits that the collection is made up of only ‘loosely connected parts’ (p. 17). Some of the most important questions raised by the way this volume is organized have to do with the relationship between comparative and international criminal justice. How far should the themes discussed be assumed to be dealing with interrelated questions? Above all, should the study of international criminal justice, already the centre of considerable literature in its own right, be allowed to go its own way?</p>
<p>An issue that runs throughout the book concerns the alleged displacement of criminal justice from the nation state level to, on the one hand, the transnational international and regional level (section one), and on the other hand, to the local level, for example to policy making about towns or parts of them (section three). But having three sections dealing respectively with the supra-national, the national and the local risks reproducing such distinctions rather than calling them into question. In particular, it remains unclear in most of the essays (Valverde and Aas being obvious exceptions) how (and how far) studies of comparative criminal justice can and should emancipate themselves from ‘nation state thinking’ or thinking of society as ‘a container’. Can we use the same theoretical vocabulary for each of these levels, speaking for example of the fortress mentality of states and of individuals in gated communities, and of the ‘exclusion’ of individuals from societies and of states from the ‘family’ of nations? Supra-national and local competition with the State may have different implications for comparative research. Actions taken at the international and transnational level are typically intended to produce more <italic>similarities</italic> in criminal justice responses. So the comparative researcher is likely to be interested in showing how far differences nonetheless persist or are even accentuated. On the other hand, if nation states lose ground to more local developments we would expect internal <italic>differences</italic> to increase.</p>
<p>Many scholars insist that the nation state is losing its centrality and autonomy in dealing with crime, just as it is in other areas of social policy. State sovereignty in matters of criminal justice appears to be challenged by the likes of international courts, human rights conventions, multinational private security enterprises, cross border policing, policy networks and flows and technologies of global surveillance. The State is not only an enforcer of criminal law. It can also be a victim and/or a perpetrator of crimes. At the extreme, failed states pose a threat because their implosion takes place in situations of violent ethnic and other conflicts. Regional powers try to take advantage of such weaknesses, international diasporas can fuel these conflicts and multinational corporations engage directly for their own advantage with both elites and regional leaders. Such states are unable to meet the aspirations and expectations of their people with regard to security, welfare and healthcare. The failure of state institutions to restrict exploitation and rent-seeking among elites leads to grand corruption and the misuse of resources. And many forms of trafficking and environmental crime, involving organized crime and terrorism, have their origins in such states.</p>
<p>On the other hand, even if we accept that the State is losing its centrality it does not follow that what happens in the field of criminal justice necessarily follows the same logic. The nation-state persists as a key site where the insecurities and uncertainties brought about by (economic) globalization are expected to be ‘resolved’. It may ‘act out’ in responding to some crime problems precisely because it has lost power elsewhere. In addition, the relationship between the transnational and the national is not all one way. States can and do use ostensibly transnational powers for local purposes. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1748895812474550">Sheptycki (2002)</xref> has shown, even the world of ‘high policing’ is less often engaged in a strenuous life and death struggle with transnational organized crime than in developing a more technologically advanced response to traditional ‘high volume crime’. Many of the contributions to the first section of this collection raise the question of how far supposedly international laws or institutions in fact really reflect or are applied in national interests (commonly those of the United States).</p>
<p>Another way of thinking about the links between the sections in this book is to ask why it has a separate section (the second) that is explicitly devoted to comparison. If comparison is no more than a methodology then it is surely relevant to all three sections. Alternatively, if the growth of transnational or global connections has changed the way that comparisons must be made, what is the justification of the country-based discussions in section two? Many authors have in fact come to the conclusion that country to country comparisons have lost much of their value. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1748895812474550">Aas (2007)</xref>, in her book on crime and globalization, devotes little energy to comparing individual countries and instead seeks to show us the complex processes by which the ‘global’ and ‘the local’ are intertwined. For her, ‘one can no longer study, for example, Italy, by simply looking at what happens inside its territory, but rather need to acknowledge the effects that distant conflicts and developments have on national crime and security concerns and vice versa’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1748895812474550">2007</xref>: 286). In her contribution here she tells us how Italy’s use of naval patrols to discourage illegal immigration from Africa has important knock-on effects for other countries in Europe, including those in Scandinavia. Recent events add a bitter postscript. Whereas Italy in turn relied on agreements with Colonel Gaddafi in Libya whereby he used his detention centres to help prevent potential immigrants from entering Europe, this ended when Gaddafi himself became the enemy and western countries sent in aircraft to support opposition to his regime whereby he was overthrown and killed.</p>
<p>Arguably, too, many of the issues discussed in Crawford’s volume could have been better dealt with as differentiated sub-disciplines. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1748895812474550">Friedrichs (2011)</xref> for example, would parcel out these questions to comparative criminology, transnational criminology, international and global criminology. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1748895812474550">Pakes (2010</xref>: 18–19), on the other hand, wonders whether the comparative approach should still be seen as the key methodology whereas globalization would only point to the ‘object of study’ concerning the ‘what’ not the ‘how’, describing something taking place in the world, such as the trafficking of illegal goods or people. But he recognizes that the term ‘globalizing criminology’ can also be used as if it related to methodology. He therefore draws a further distinction between two senses of global criminology that, he says, are ‘subject to conceptual confusion’. ‘Strong’ global criminology, he claims, should probably take the world as its unit of analysis. It might address questions such as the relation between climate change and civil unrest, transgressions and control. Here, ‘global’ denotes object. In contrast, globalized criminology frequently refers to relationships: those who advocate it frequently argue that we need to take the interconnectedness of the world into account.</p>
<p>The chapters of this collection that seek to explain the responses to crime in countries such as France or Canada assume that it still makes sense to link criminal justice outcomes to domestic differences between states. Is there anything uniquely ‘French’ about ‘the French response to urban insecurity’? Body-Gendrot, in her chapter, argues that the (over)surveillance of Arab youth in France is linked to wider questions of geopolitics as nuanced by France’s colonial and post-colonial history. Certainly, researchers exploring other transnational practices are increasingly abandoning the unit of the nation-state to focus on flows, nodes and ‘scapes’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1748895812474550">Appadurai, 1996</xref>). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1748895812474550">Sassen (2000)</xref> points out, ‘information’ is not rooted in any given place but ‘global cities’ are found in given places and need to be serviced by people, often legal and illegal immigrants, who have to be kept from contesting their poor conditions. Yet, in the field of criminal justice and security it would be wrong to go too far in playing down the significance of national units, and nation-based policies, interests and cultural propensities. As Aas also tells us, Frontex, the cross-European naval force for curbing immigration, is still waiting for the boats it was promised by Italy. And the student of criminal justice in Italy may be surprised to find that little importance is attached to studies of recidivism there.</p>
<p>It can also be important to address the question of how elites and others in given societies see themselves in relation to others. This requires what might be called ‘second-order comparison’ by which we try to grasp what people know (or think they know) about how things are done elsewhere and how they react to this. As is well known, Finland’s relatively low prison population has been explained as a result of the country’s elites seeking to bring their country into line with others in Scandinavia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1748895812474550">Lappi-Seppala, 2007</xref>). In this collection, the essays on Canada both stress the extent to which elites in this country go to distinguish its approach to criminal justice from the USA, despite considerable similarities in matters of political economy. Likewise, McAra’s discussion of the impact of multi-level governance on crime control and punishment assumes that Scotland’s reactions to crime depend on its relationship to England and English criminal justice policies to the extent that she see it as a paradox that moves towards independence have led to more rather than less use of imprisonment.</p>
<p>Though the title of this collection refers to convergence and divergence as the key theme, for many of the contributors, the interest in variation is less a search for explanations than a concern with the serious ethical and political questions it poses. Much current discussion in comparative criminal justice (and criminology more generally), involves the search to find ways to reduce excessive ‘punitiveness’ (at least as far as conventional crime is concerned). The premise is that changes in crime rates are not a good explanation for recent rises in punitiveness. Countries with more crime do not necessarily have more people in prison, and, over time, a rise in crime rates can be associated with a reduction in imprisonment, while a period of reducing crime rates (as recently) can be accompanied by a rise in prison rates. But, as some of the chapters in this collection demonstrate, discussions of punishment without crime can sometimes seem like Hamlet without the Prince. Scandinavian countries are generally presented as important exceptions to growing punitiveness (though the thesis of their exceptionalness is not uncontroversial). This is attributed in one way or another to their being welfare-oriented social democracies. But to claim that these rates are exceptionally low presupposes that their crime rates are the same as those in the USA and other neo-liberal societies. Is this really the case and, if so, why? While there are a variety of ways by which neo-liberal policies might be thought to give rise <italic>both</italic> to higher rates of punitiveness and to higher crime rates, why social democracy does not also lead to lower levels of crime is left obscure.</p>
<p>As this suggests, there is also evidence in some of the chapters of the ‘evil causes evil’ fallacy as applied to criminal justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1748895812474550">Nelken, 2010a</xref>). But, ‘bad’ outcomes, such as increasing prison numbers, may not in all cases be the result of ‘bad’ causes, such as neo- liberalism and its creation of greater social inequalities. Prison numbers may also rise because of more concern for victims, campaigns to deal with crimes against women, prison building programmes intended to avoid prison overcrowding, and so on. More importantly, what can have good effects in some contexts may have bad ones in others. The neo-liberal countries discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1748895812474550">Cavadino and Dignan (2006)</xref> which have <italic>higher</italic> overall prison populations also have <italic>lower</italic> proportions of immigrants in prison than the Conservative Corporatist countries of Western Europe. Protecting workers from exploitation by market forces may indeed help reduce the level of imprisonment for citizens but also make it harder for immigrants to enter the labour market.</p>
<p>Most of the contributions to the first section focusing on international criminal justice raise policy and normative questions. Who and what lies behind the drive to greater international criminal justice? How far are the institutions of international criminal justice made in the image of US justice, and how far is it possible for strong states including the United States to place themselves outside its reach? The debates over the ‘ends’ or goals of domestic criminal justice find new relevance in discussions of international criminal justice. Is retribution as an aim more or less plausible at this level, does ‘deterrence’ have less (or more?) applicability in what are often both over-determined and unpredictable eruptions of inhuman behaviour? Findlay argues that international criminal justice needs to be better targeted at the needs or wishes of victim communities. But would this bring it into conflict with indigenous dispute remedies? Brants, in her contribution, worries whether a focus on the victim could go wrong (in terms of justifying populism) as it has in many western democracies. Parmentier’s description of his empirical findings in ex-Yugoslavia depicts victims that are convinced that prosecution can stop recurrence, and eager for restitution but reluctant to forgive.</p>
<p>States can often be in collusion with serious criminal actors. And international financial institutions should themselves be seen as part of the problem as much as the solution to global social threats. Arguably, the larger consequences for the fabric of social trust where ‘authorities’ engage in criminal conduct are even greater than those that follow from the toleration of white-collar and corporate crime. The magnitude of the crimes committed in the Second World War and other wars, or the savagery of colonialism, suggests that disproportionately little effort has been put into the prevention and pursuit of these acts as compared to more conventional crimes. On the other hand, globalization may be the bearer of good as well as bad consequences. As Muncie has put it, economic globalism may speak of the import, largely US inspired, of neo-liberal conceptions of the free market and community responsibilization backed by an authoritarian state. However, legal globalism, largely UN inspired, unveils a contrary vision of universal human rights delivered through social democracies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1748895812474550">Muncie, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Relating the discussions of penal response in the first and the second sections raises the question whether ‘what people want’ counts (or should count) more or less at the international than at the national level. In domestic contexts, so-called ‘populist punitivism’ is often seen as the key to unnecessarily high levels of prison use. On the other hand, it is often assumed, even by the most critical criminological writers, that whereas for domestic criminal justice issues we have to beware of ‘moral panics’ that exaggerate crimes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1748895812474550">Cohen, 1972</xref>), at the international level, especially in dealing with crimes by the State, the problem is often the existence of ‘denial’ and consequent impunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1748895812474550">Cohen, 2001</xref>). But, in practice, there can also be ‘moral panics’ involved in responding to international crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1748895812474550">Findlay, 2008</xref>) as well as in transnational crusades such as those against corruption or human trafficking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1748895812474550">Nelken, 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1748895812474550">2010c</xref>).</p>
<p>Working out the normative implications of the various parts of the book is further complicated, however, by the fragmentation of criminal justice debates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1748895812474550">Roberts, 2007</xref>). Many comparative criminal justice scholars have urged the relative merits of the accusatorial system over its rivals (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1748895812474550">Vogler, 2005</xref>). And the accusatorial system is in fact continuing to win adherents more widely, for example in Latin America. But, as the debate over comparative punitiveness shows, countries with accusatorial systems tend to have higher proportions of people in prison than those within the continental European system. Does this mean that systems that are better for accused individuals may have systematic negative affects overall on offenders as a class? How does this relate to the famous and provocative claim by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1748895812474550">Schlesinger (1976)</xref> that the accusatorial system is better if you are guilty but the inquisitorial better if you are innocent? The countries with relatively high prison rates that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1748895812474550">Cavadino and Dignan (2006)</xref> identify as being influenced by neo-liberalism all also use the accusatorial system. Is this just a spurious correlation? Assuming that many (most?) of those processed through the courts are factually guilty should this not mean that the accusatorial system should produce less convictions? Are there deep-lying reasons linked to the role of ‘the State’ and ‘the community’ which can help us understand why criminal procedures produce such different outcomes?</p>
<p>As this sampling of issues suggests, a collection dealing with changes in responses to crime at the international, national and sub-national levels raises many more questions than it can possibly resolve. And this may be seen as one of its merits. For example, insofar as criminal justice is linked to a society’s traditions and cultures when should diversity be protected for its own sake, how should this be done and where should such protection stop? Is Scandinavia really an appropriate criminal justice model for Asia and Africa? Or the USA for Japan? This book and the current literature in general provide little assistance with such questions. Certainly if the crucial issue is stopping transnational criminals taking advantage of differences in criminal justice systems (especially in their criminal procedures or levels of sentences) diversity will be presented as an obstacle to be overcome rather than as a virtue (or a resource). On the other hand, it is not obvious that harmonization between criminal justice systems can be limited to what is needed to stem transnational crimes while leaving other aspects of the different systems unaffected. The increasing resort to standardization through and in the name of technical standards, only (perhaps deliberately?) obscures these difficult issues.</p>
<p>As in the domestic sphere, so with international and transnational criminal justice, there are problems in separating the domain of criminal justice from social justice more generally. Helping individuals who want to immigrate into fortress Europe would seem a positive move, but what if this reduces the availability of skilled people in the countries from which they depart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1748895812474550">Kapstein, 2006</xref>)? A dilemma faced by those fighting against global social problems is how far it is possible ‘to do justice in an unjust world’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1748895812474550">Nelken, 2010c</xref>: 479). Criminalizing trafficking for sexual and labour exploitation from poorer to richer countries (also known as the ‘new slavery’) seems as near to an absolute imperative as one can get. But could it be relevant if at least some of those trafficked prefer the opportunities available in their countries of arrival to the grim conditions they left behind at home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1748895812474550">Davies, 2009</xref>)?</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aas</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Globalization and Crime</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Appadurai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Modernity at Large: Cultural Dimensions of Globalization</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cavadino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dignan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Penal Systems: A Comparative Approach</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>Folk Devils and Moral Panics</source>. <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>States of Denial: Knowing about Atrocities and Suffering</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>My Name Is Not Natasha: How Albanian Women in France Use Trafficking to Overcome Social Exclusion</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Findlay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Governing through Globalised Crime</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global criminology and comparative criminology as complementary projects</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Globalisation and Comparative Criminal Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kapstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Economic Justice in an Unfair World</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lappi-Seppala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Penal policy in Scandinavia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Tonry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Crime and Justice Vol. 36: Crime, Punishment and Politics in Comparative Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muncie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>On globalisation and exceptionalism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Globalisation and Comparative Criminal Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010a</year>) <source>Comparative Criminal Justice: Making Sense of Difference</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010b</year>) <article-title>Corruption and human rights: An afterword</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nelen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Corruption &amp; Human Rights: Interdisciplinary Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Antwerp</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Intersentia</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010c</year>) <article-title>Human trafficking and legal culture</article-title>. <source>Israel Law Review</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pakes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The comparative method in globalised criminology</article-title>. <source>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Criminology</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Comparative law for international criminal justice</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Orucu</surname><given-names>E and</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelken</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Comparative Law: A Handbook</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hart</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sassen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The global city: Strategic site/new frontier</article-title>. <source>American Studies</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2/3</issue>): <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Comparative criminal procedure: A plea for utilizing foreign experience</article-title>. <source>Buffalo Law Review</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheptycki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>In Search of Transnational Policing</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1748895812474550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>A World View of Criminal Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>