<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaje</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Journal of Evaluation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1098-2140</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1557-0878</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1098214011424201</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1098214011424201</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Using Social Network Analysis to Predict Early Collaboration Within Health Advocacy Coalitions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Honeycutt</surname>
<given-names>Todd C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098214011424201">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Strong</surname>
<given-names>Debra A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098214011424201">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1098214011424201"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1098214011424201"><label>1</label>Mathematica Policy Research, Princeton, NJ, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1098214011424201">Debra A. Strong, Mathematica Policy Research, P.O. Box 2393, Princeton, NJ 08543, USA Email: <email>dstrong@mathematica-mpr.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>221</fpage>
<lpage>239</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Evaluation Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Within coalitions of consumer advocates formed to advance health insurance coverage expansions, engaging in united advocacy activities soon after formation might be an important precursor to attaining coalition effectiveness in shaping policy. In this article, the authors apply social network analysis (SNA) to examine how organizational characteristics and interorganizational relationships related to early collaboration on advocacy activities within advocacy coalitions. All interorganizational relationships the authors assessed were significantly associated with early collaboration in advocacy activities, with communication most associated with the differences in collaboration observed across coalitions. Among organizational characteristics, having more resources—as measured by the number of recent policy maker contacts and being the organization that directly received the grant—were statistically significant. Their findings suggest that even organizations that have not worked together before can become engaged in collaborative activities at a relatively early stage. They also show that SNA techniques can usefully be applied to advocacy evaluations.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>social network analysis</kwd>
<kwd>interorganization evaluation</kwd>
<kwd>coalition evaluation</kwd>
<kwd>advocacy evaluation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Social network analysis (SNA) provides tools to help evaluate coalitions by showing their structure and the processes among members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1098214011424201">Provan, Veazie, Staten, &amp; Teufel-Shone, 2005</xref>). In this article, we apply SNA to examine the relationships among organization members within 12 coalitions formed to conduct state-level advocacy for health insurance coverage reform. SNA is used in an exploratory manner to assess how collaboration on advocacy activities within the coalitions is related to organizational characteristics and interorganizational relationships of members at an early stage of a coalition’s existence—specifically, during the first year of grant funding. Collaborative advocacy activities include making joint decisions and jointly attending legislative hearings or one-on-one meetings with policy makers. Engaging in these activities early on may be important precursors of attaining coalition effectiveness in shaping policy and may be especially important in a fast-moving policy environment. The analysis is part of a larger evaluation of the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation’s Consumer Voices for Coverage (CVC) initiative, which funded 12 state-level consumer health advocacy coalitions to promote public policies targeted to achieve meaningful increases in coverage at the state or federal level and to enhance the role that consumer advocates play in shaping comprehensive health reform.</p>
<p>In the following sections we briefly describe the CVC project, the reasons SNA was used for the evaluation, and the research questions to be addressed by the evaluation. Data sources and methods are then presented, followed by findings. We conclude with a discussion of the findings, the strengths and limitations of the analysis, and the implications of the results.</p>
<sec id="section2-1098214011424201">
<title>Program and Description</title>
<p>The mission of the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation is to improve the health of all Americans and health care provided to them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1098214011424201">Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 2011</xref>). Developing policies and programs to expand health coverage has been a goal of the Foundation since its founding in 1972. In 2007, several states seemed on the verge of adopting comprehensive programs to provide health insurance coverage to their residents. To help bring these public policy changes to fruition, the Foundation launched a program aimed at building integrated health care advocacy networks in selected states. This strategy was based on a study showing that such networks could be effective in changing state health policy, if they possessed specific advocacy capacities, which the program was designed to enhance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098214011424201">Community Catalyst, 2006</xref>). The Foundation made 3-year grants to 12 state-level coalitions composed of a single grantee organization and a leadership team made up of partner organizations representing a range of consumer groups acting on behalf of, among others, children, older adults, immigrant and ethnic minority groups, disease groups, and labor unions, as well as organizations that focus on broad progressive issues, legal issues, public policy, and consumer rights. Each coalition varied in the composition of the organizations that were involved with its leadership team.</p>
<p>The theory of change behind the program was that, with funds and technical assistance resources provided by the Foundation, these coalitions would add other needed partners, build their advocacy capacities, and undertake activities to achieve their public policy goals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1098214011424201">Figure 1</xref>
).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Consumer Voices for Coverage theory of change.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig1-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1098214011424201">
<title>Evaluation Approach</title>
<p>For the evaluation, the Foundation wanted to learn, for each coalition, (a) how it was structured and operated, (b) whether its advocacy capacity increased over the life of the initiative, and (c) whether and how it influenced state health policy. To address these questions, Mathematica Policy Research developed a mixed-methods evaluation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1098214011424201">Doyle, Brady, &amp; Byrn, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1098214011424201">Johnson &amp; Onwuegbuzie, 2004</xref>). We used SNA to examine the membership, structure, and operations of each coalition at the beginning of the grant and how they changed over time. This analysis uses the 2008 baseline data, and subsequent analyses will use the follow-up survey data collected in 2010.</p>
<p>Although traditional evaluation methods focus on descriptive characteristics of coalitions (e.g., how many organizations are involved in a coalition and the length of time they are involved), SNA emphasizes the relationships among organizations, such as which members are working together and the quality of their relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1098214011424201">Provan et al., 2005</xref>). In addition to broader research on interorganization relationships (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1098214011424201">Crowe, 2007</xref>), a growing body of literature uses SNA to understand organizational participation in coalitions and interorganization collaborations on topics as diverse as children’s health insurance initiatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1098214011424201">Valente, Coronges, Stevens, &amp; Cousineau, 2008</xref>), community-level Alzheimer’s initiatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1098214011424201">Lemieux-Charles et al., 2005</xref>), chronic disease initiatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1098214011424201">Provan, Nakama, Veazie, Teufel-Shone, &amp; Huddleston, 2003</xref>), health insurance plans aimed at addressing disparity issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1098214011424201">Gold, Doreian, &amp; Taylor, 2008</xref>), school-level violence prevention programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098214011424201">Cross, Dickman, Newman-Gonchar, &amp; Fagan, 2009</xref>), and state-level tobacco control partnerships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1098214011424201">Harris, Luke, Burke, &amp; Mueller, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1098214011424201">Krauss, Mueller, &amp; Luke, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>For this study, we take a broad interpretation of SNA. At one level, we use an analytical perspective that focuses on the relationships between organizations to help understand the decisions that organizations make regarding the activities they undertake with other members of the coalition. At another level, we use the aggregate number of relationships within the coalition to describe each coalition, make comparisons across coalitions, and identify network-level associations. Both views are relevant and appropriate for understanding networks, particularly among organizations, though the relationships between organizations might better account for behaviors among actors within a network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1098214011424201">Mizruchi &amp; Marquis, 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1098214011424201">
<title>Research Questions</title>
<p>Measuring the effectiveness of advocacy is difficult because the ultimate policy outcomes might be observed only years after the coalition begins and too late to influence how the program operates. However, the literature suggests that active participation and collaboration among coalition members might be related to long-term outcomes by indicating whether the coalition brings organizations and community members together to work on a common goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098214011424201">Cross et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1098214011424201">Mitchell &amp; Shortell, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1098214011424201">Zakocs &amp; Edwards, 2006</xref>). To evaluate CVC, we are extending these uses of SNA in order to measure the level of participation within coalitions devoted to advocacy and to identify factors that predict participation in such coalitions. Specifically, we test whether the levels of resources possessed by member organizations and their levels of interorganizational relationships are significantly associated with collaborative advocacy and compare these levels across coalitions. The first three research questions focus on members within a coalition; the fourth considers the coalitions themselves:<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Are organizations with more resources (measured in terms of health coverage policy experience, contacts with policy makers, financial resources, and degree of focus on health care) more likely to be identified in collaborative advocacy activities than those with less resources?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Related to the first question, do member organizations report more collaborative advocacy activities with the grantee, as might be expected from its role in receiving funding and organizing the coalition, than with other coalition members?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Are organizations more likely to report collaborative advocacy activities with organizations with which they have other types of relationships (having worked together before, high frequency of recent communications outside of coalition meetings, and shared values on health coverage)?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Are those coalitions that contain a higher proportion of organizations with more interorganizational relationships (as defined in the third question) more likely to have more collaborative activities among their members in their first year of operation than those coalitions with a lower proportion?</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1098214011424201">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section6-1098214011424201">
<title>Sample and Data Collection</title>
<p>To collect data for the analysis, in the first year of the grant (2008) we surveyed all organizations belonging to the coalitions. The survey, which was customized for each coalition, collected information about the organization, such as its constituency and size, and its relationships and activities with all other organizations in the coalition. Surveys were sent to grantees and leadership team members based on a roster of individuals representing participant organizations that was provided by the grantee. We included these individuals since they would be most knowledgeable about the coalition, their organization’s involvement with it, and other organizations in the coalition. An organization could have had more than one person involved in the coalition, and in six instances two individuals from the same organization responded to the survey. In these cases, we used data from only one respondent, choosing the most knowledgeable respondent (the CVC project director) when such a person could be identified, and a randomly selected respondent in the other five cases.</p>
<p>Of the 130 organizations belonging to the 12 CVC coalitions, we received complete data from representatives of 96, for an overall organization response rate of 74%. The number of organizations on each team ranged from 4 in Colorado to 25 in Illinois, and the response rate varied by coalition, from 50% in New Jersey to 89% in Oregon (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1098214011424201">Table 1</xref>
). Across all coalitions, we had complete data on 866 pairs of organizations. (For each two organizations, A and B, we have organization A’s perspective on its connections with organization B [hereafter referred to as the “alter organization”] and also organization B’s perspective on its connections with organization A.) Although we are less certain about overall levels of relationships for the three coalitions whose response rate was less than 70%, the analysis focuses on complete data from each coalition (i.e., the organizational pairs that both responded to the survey)—we exclude data about alter organizations that did not themselves respond. Nonrespondents may be less involved in and less committed to the coalition. Respondents reported fewer connections (from 8 to 23 percentage points) with nonrespondents than with respondents, and fewer union and public policy organizations, as well as nonadvocacy organizations, responded to the survey than other types of organizations (data not shown). Excluding nonrespondents therefore introduces the possibility of response bias. A reduced model that included alter organizations that did not respond, but omitted reciprocity and alter organizational characteristics because they were not available for those organizations, resulted in similar findings between collaborative activities and interorganizational relationships.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Number of Organizations, Organization Pairs, and Survey Response Rates, by Coalition</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Coalition</th>
<th>Total Organizations</th>
<th>Total Organization Respondents</th>
<th>Total Organization Pairs</th>
<th>Survey Response Rate (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CA</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>272</td>
<td>85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CO</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IL</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MD</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ME</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MN</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NJ</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NY</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OH</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OR</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>89</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PA</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WA</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>130</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>866</td>
<td>74</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 96 organizations. The table shows, for each coalition, the number of organizations, the number that responded to the survey and had complete data, the number of organization pairs included in the analysis, and the survey response rate.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1098214011424201">
<title>Outcome Variables</title>
<p>The outcome examined for this analysis is collaborative advocacy activities—activities performed jointly with other members within a coalition. Respondents were asked to identify the organizations with which they had participated in two specific collaborative activities over the past 6 months: (a) making coordinated decisions about health coverage issues or policies with the organization and (b) meeting with a policy maker or attending a public meeting or hearing with the organization. Although these measures are considered coalition outputs, we note that they may or may not be related specifically to the coalition. Some or all of these activities could be the product of the organizations’ involvement in another coalition or of their relationship before the grant program began.</p>
<p>Rather than examining each activity separately, we created a composite measure of the total number of collaborative advocacy activities that a respondent organization reported with the alter organization. The highest score is 2, indicating that a respondent reported both activities with the alter organization; a score of 1 shows that a respondent indicated only one activity with the alter organization; and a score of 0 indicates that no activities with the alter organization were reported by the respondent. Using a composite measure in this way enables us to minimize the risk of multiple comparisons and also reduces the probability of committing a Type I error.</p>
<p>Respondents more often identified either zero or two advocacy activities with alter organizations, reporting no activities 38% of the time and two activities 36% of the time (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1098214011424201">Table 2</xref>
). However, there was sizable range across the coalitions. For example, in all of the New York organization pairs, the respondent reported both collaborative advocacy activities with alter organizations; in Ohio, the corresponding percentage was 15%. Respondents reported a mean of 1.0 activities with alter organizations, though the averages ranged from 0.6 activities per organization in Ohio to 2.0 activities per organization in New York.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Number of Collaborative Advocacy Activities, by Coalition</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="2">
</th>
<th colspan="4">Collaborative Advocacy Activities</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Coalition</th>
<th>
</th>
<th>Zero</th>
<th>One</th>
<th>Two</th>
<th>Mean</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">CA</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>102</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>77</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(37.5)</td>
<td>(34.2)</td>
<td>(28.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">CO</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(16.7)</td>
<td>(33.3)</td>
<td>(50.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">IL</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>77</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(45.6)</td>
<td>(12.1)</td>
<td>(42.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">MD</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>6</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(53.3)</td>
<td>(26.7)</td>
<td>(20.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">ME</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>17</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(28.6)</td>
<td>(31.0)</td>
<td>(40.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">MN</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>10</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(8.3)</td>
<td>(8.3)</td>
<td>(83.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">NJ</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>6</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(50.0)</td>
<td>(30.0)</td>
<td>(20.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">NY</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>42</td>
<td rowspan="2">2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(0.0)</td>
<td>(0.0)</td>
<td>(100.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">OH</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>20</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(59.1)</td>
<td>(25.8)</td>
<td>(15.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">OR</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>19</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(14.3)</td>
<td>(51.8)</td>
<td>(33.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">PA</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>28</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(28.6)</td>
<td>(4.8)</td>
<td>(66.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">WA</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>9</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(15.0)</td>
<td>(40.0)</td>
<td>(45.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Total</td>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>331</td>
<td>221</td>
<td>314</td>
<td rowspan="2">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%</td>
<td>(38.2)</td>
<td>(25.5)</td>
<td>(36.3)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 866 organization pairs. The table shows, for each coalition, the number of collaborative advocacy activities reported by respondents with other coalition organizations and the mean number of collaborative advocacy activities reported per organization. Percentages may not total to 100% due to rounding.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1098214011424201">
<title>Explanatory Variables</title>
<p>The explanatory variables in our models represent (a) characteristics of coalition member organizations—specifically advocacy-related resources such as experience in health coverage, financial resources, or contacts with policy makers; and (b) coalition-specific interorganizational relationships among member organizations.</p>
<sec id="section9-1098214011424201">
<title>Characteristics</title>
<p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1098214011424201">Table 3</xref>
 shows the years of experience in health coverage policy, size, health policy focus, and grantee status of the coalition member organizations that responded to the survey. Most organizations (66%) had been involved in health care issues for 10 or more years before joining the coalition. We categorized an organization’s size according to its reported annual budget, in quartiles: less than $400,000, $400,000 to $999,999, $1,000,000 to $2,999,999, and $3,000,000 or more. Few organizations reported that health policy was their primary or only policy focus; most organizations (69%) reported that health policy was one of several policy areas. (For size and health policy focus, we included a missing category in our models to account for the organizations that did not respond to these questions.)</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Coalition Member Organizations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>
<italic>N</italic>
</th>
<th>%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Years of experience in health coverage issues</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fewer than 2 years</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2–5 years</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 6–9 years</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 10 or more years</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Size (annual budget)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Missing</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than $400,000</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> $400,000 to $999,999</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> $1,000,000 to $2,999,999</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> $3,000,000 or more</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Health policy focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Missing</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> One of several policy areas</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Most important of many policy areas</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Only policy area</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coalition grantee</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 96 organizations. Percentages may not total to 100% due to rounding.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The survey asked about the number of contacts with policy makers and their staff members “who most influence health coverage issues facing your state, including those from administrative agencies, legislative bodies, executive offices, or the judiciary” in the previous 6 months. Respondents could list up to 10 such individuals. The average number of policy maker contacts that organizations reported was 5.8, with a range from 0 to 10. For analysis, we used a sum of the number of policy maker contacts that an organization reported.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1098214011424201">1</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1098214011424201">
<title>Interorganizational relationships</title>
<p>Survey respondents from each organization were asked to describe their relationships with other organizations in the coalition, using commonly asked social network questions, based on measures proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1098214011424201">van de Ven and Ferry (1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1098214011424201">Table 4</xref>
). Respondents were first asked whether their organization had worked with each organization in the coalition prior to receipt of the CVC grant. Of the 866 unique pairs of organizations, 70% reported having worked together before the grant.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Interorganization Relationships Across All Pairs of Coalition Member Organizations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>
<italic>N</italic>
</th>
<th>%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Worked together before</td>
<td>604</td>
<td>70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Communication</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Every week or almost every week</td>
<td>234</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Every month or almost every month</td>
<td>230</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> A few times over the past 6 months</td>
<td>183</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No contact</td>
<td>154</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Don’t know/missing</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Share values</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> To a great extent</td>
<td>525</td>
<td>61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> To some extent</td>
<td>179</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> To no extent</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Can’t assess/missing</td>
<td>162</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 866 organization pairs. The table shows the number and percentage of organization pairs that had worked together before, the frequency of communication, and the extent to which health coverage values were shared. Percentages may not total to 100% due to rounding.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Frequency of communication was then addressed. Respondents were asked, since receiving the CVC grant and <italic>not counting formal coalition meetings</italic>, how frequently people from their organization had been in contact about health coverage issues with other organizations in the coalition. Possible responses included everyday or almost everyday, every week or almost every week, every month or almost every month, a few times over the past 6 months, no contact, and don’t know. Because few organizations reported daily contact with any organization, we combined the first two categories. We also combined “don’t know” (<italic>N</italic> = 29) and missing (<italic>N</italic> = 36) responses, because these responses are qualitatively similar; the lack of a positive response suggests no communication. The most common levels of communication were contact every week or almost every week and contact every month or almost every month, both of which were reported in 27% of organization pairs. In about one quarter of organization pairs, there was either no contact (18%) or the respondent did not know or did not respond (8%).</p>
<p>A third question asked to what extent coalition members shared the values of the respondent organization on health coverage issues. Possible answers were to a great extent, to some extent, not at all, and can’t assess. For a majority (61%) of organization pairs, the respondent organization reported sharing the same values on health coverage issues to a great extent with the alter organization. No respondents reported that any alter organization did not share values at all. We combined those respondents with missing data (<italic>N</italic> = 21) with the “can’t assess” responses (<italic>N</italic> = 141). This reflects an assumption that data were most likely missing because the respondent was either not aware of the other organization, did not have sufficient information to make an assessment, or was reluctant to make such an assessment.</p>
<p>We used these three measures for a cross-site analysis of how interorganizational relationships affected collaborative advocacy. However, we also wanted to examine how these relationships influenced the overall level of shared advocacy within each coalition. The aggregate level of interorganizational relationships (also measured by the proportions of the three relevant variables reported by members of each coalition) varied (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1098214011424201">Table 5</xref>
). Coalition members in Minnesota, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania had the least history of working together before the grant. At the other end of the spectrum, all organizations in Washington and almost all those in Maine had worked together. In Colorado, all organizations were in at least monthly contact with each other; in Maryland, about one fourth of organizations were. For the third variable, the table shows the proportion of organization pairs with values shared to a great extent and the proportion that could not be assessed or had missing data. All organizations in Minnesota and most in Washington reported sharing values with each other to a great extent; the proportion of organizations in Pennsylvania that shared values to a great extent was half the level in those two coalitions.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Interorganization Relationships by, Coalition</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Coalition</th>
<th>Worked Together Before (%)</th>
<th>Communication: At Least Monthly (%)</th>
<th>Communication: Don’t Know/Missing (%)</th>
<th>Shared Values: to a Great Extent (%)</th>
<th>Shared Values: Can’t Assess/Missing (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CA</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CO</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IL</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MD</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ME</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MN</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NJ</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NY</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OH</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OR</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PA</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WA</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Median</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 12 coalitions. The table shows the percentage among a coalition’s organization members about which one organization reported a relationship with other organizations. “Worked together before” indicates the extent to which an organization reported prior experience working with another organization before the CVC grant began. “Communication: At least monthly” shows the proportion of organizations for which communication in the previous 6 months was every month or almost every month or more frequent. “Communication: Dont’ know/missing” shows the proportion of organization pairs for which the respondent either could not assess the measure or left the measure blank for other organizations. “Shared values to a great extent” shows the proportion of organization pairs for which the respondent believed that the two organizations shared the same health coverage values to a great extent. “Shared values: Can’t assess/missing” is the proportion of organization pairs for which the respondent either could not assess the measure or left the measure blank.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1098214011424201">
<title>Analytical Approach</title>
<p>For the analysis, ordered logistic regression models were used to predict the number of collaborative advocacy activities reported by a respondent with an alter organization within their coalition. Ordered logistic regression models (also known as proportional odds models) are commonly used to predict categorical outcomes that are ordinal, that is, where one category represents more of a factor than another category (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1098214011424201">Agresti, 1996</xref>). As with logistic regression, the estimates can be interpreted as odds ratios by exponentiating the value; we present the estimates, the standard errors, and the adjusted odds ratios in our results tables. We focus on the characteristics of the organization about which activities are reported (the alter organization), because we are interested in the influence from the perspective of those organizations to which other organizations are drawn. Broadly, this approach examines an organization’s popularity or in-degree (the number of times that an organization is identified by others; Wasserman &amp; Faust, 1996).</p>
<p>A traditional ordered logistic regression model would result in biased standard errors for these data because it does not account for the interdependent nature of the data. For instance, reports about relationships with alter organizations are likely correlated across alter organizations as well as across respondents. In addition, the assessment by two organizations of their relationships with each other might be correlated if the relationship is reciprocated; that is, if an organization reports an advocacy activity with an alter organization, the alter organization might be likely to report the same relationship. Moreover, respondents within a coalition may have a tendency to report in a similar way. We adjust for this nonindependence using a p2 ordered logistic regression format (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1098214011424201">van Duijn, Snijders, &amp; Zijlstra, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1098214011424201">Zijlstra, van Duijn, &amp; Snijders, 2006</xref>). The analysis uses PROC GLIMMIX in SAS version 9.1, incorporating random effects for respondents, alter organizations, and coalitions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1098214011424201">Flom, McMahon, &amp; Pouget, 2006</xref>) as well as a measure of reciprocity for the dependent variable that accounts for the fact that two organizations may report similar levels of activity with each other.</p>
<p>An alternative approach would be to model only reciprocated relationships—those collaborative activities and interorganizational relationships in which both organizations reported the same values for each other. Such an approach results in a symmetrical network and shows what are perhaps the network’s strongest relationships, since both organizations are in agreement as to whether a relationship exists. Our intent with this study, however, was to model the perspective of the respondent organization—essentially, how alter organization characteristics and the respondent’s perceived interorganization relationships affected the respondent’s view of their collaborative activities with the alter organization. As a test of the robustness of our results, we limited the data to only reciprocated collaborative activities and interorganizational relationships, and then ran logistic regression models using those reciprocated variables (and omitting the reciprocity measure for the dependent measure on right-hand side of the equation because the data reflected this dimension). First, as was to be expected, all reciprocated dependent and independent measures were less frequent than the original relationships. Second, the regression results obtained with the reciprocated data were similar to the findings we obtained with the original data (results available from the authors). The one exception was in the significance of the policy maker contact variable: when we considered only reciprocated data, the number of contacts that an alter organization reported with policy makers was no longer significant.</p>
<p>In addition to logistic regression, we use correlations to measure the association at the coalition level between interorganizational relationship measures and collaborative advocacy activities. Using both of these analytical approaches helps to answer the fourth research question. Because a sample of 12 cases is too small for Pearson product–moment correlation coefficients, we calculated correlations between pairs of variables using Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1098214011424201">
<title>The Specific Models</title>
<p>The first p2 model regresses the dependent variable (the number of collaborative advocacy activities) on organization characteristics. Two additional models add measures of interorganizational relationships. To explore an observed strong relationship between communication and collaborative advocacy activities, we also use a fourth p2 model that includes organization characteristics and interorganizational relationship measures, as well as coalition-level measures for communication and size (the number of organizations in the coalition). This model identifies how the overall structure and processes of the coalition influence the collaborative advocacy activities between two coalition organizations. To do so, we created an aggregate mean communication score for each coalition, assigning a value of 3 to communicating everyday or almost everyday and to every week or almost every week, with lower values assigned to less frequent communication. Zero was assigned to don’t know, missing, and no contact responses. We averaged the communication scores across respondent and alter organization pairs, and then centered the individual respondent–alter organization communication scores around the mean coalition communication score by subtracting the mean score from the organization pair score. This approach was necessary to make the two communications measures (at the coalition and organization pair levels) orthogonal.</p>
<p>For all models, zero collaborative advocacy activities serve as the reference group. All results are statistically significant at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 level unless otherwise noted.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1098214011424201">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Results from the three p2 ordered logistic regression models are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1098214011424201">Table 6</xref>
. Model 1 uses only organization characteristics to predict the number of collaborative advocacy activities with an alter organization. Models 2 and 3 add interorganizational relationship measures. Because communication and sharing values are both highly correlated at the respondent–alter organization level, we do not combine them in the same model. Model 2 uses prior experience working together along with communication; Model 3 combines prior experience and sharing values.</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>P2-Ordered Logistic Regression Estimates Predicting Number of Collaborative Advocacy Activities Using Organization Characteristics and Interorganization Relationships</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table6.tif"/>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table6a.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="3">Model 1</th>
<th colspan="3">Model 2</th>
<th colspan="3">Model 3</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>Estimate</th>
<th>Standard Error</th>
<th>Odds Ratio</th>
<th>Estimate</th>
<th>Standard Error</th>
<th>Odds Ratio</th>
<th>Estimate</th>
<th>Standard Error</th>
<th>Odds Ratio</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Intercept 2</td>
<td>−2.385<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.761</td>
<td>0.092</td>
<td>−4.939<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.765</td>
<td>0.007</td>
<td>−3.759<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.768</td>
<td>0.023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intercept 1</td>
<td>−0.293</td>
<td>0.754</td>
<td>0.746</td>
<td>−2.411<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.743</td>
<td>0.090</td>
<td>−1.483<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1098214011424201">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.753</td>
<td>0.227</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intercept 0</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reciprocity</td>
<td>0.706<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.125</td>
<td>2.026</td>
<td>0.279<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1098214011424201">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.134</td>
<td>1.321</td>
<td>0.506<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.125</td>
<td>1.658</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">Alter organization characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"> Years of experience</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Fewer than 2 years</td>
<td>0.178</td>
<td>0.503</td>
<td>1.195</td>
<td>0.533</td>
<td>0.475</td>
<td>1.704</td>
<td>0.628</td>
<td>0.455</td>
<td>1.874</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2–5 years</td>
<td>−0.040</td>
<td>0.421</td>
<td>0.961</td>
<td>0.202</td>
<td>0.396</td>
<td>1.223</td>
<td>0.403</td>
<td>0.381</td>
<td>1.496</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  6–9 years</td>
<td>−0.224</td>
<td>0.418</td>
<td>0.799</td>
<td>−0.037</td>
<td>0.395</td>
<td>0.964</td>
<td>−0.235</td>
<td>0.377</td>
<td>0.790</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  10 or more years</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"> Size (annual budget)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Missing</td>
<td>0.650</td>
<td>0.583</td>
<td>1.916</td>
<td>0.748</td>
<td>0.541</td>
<td>2.113</td>
<td>1.167<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1098214011424201">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.513</td>
<td>3.211</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Less than $400,000</td>
<td>0.472</td>
<td>0.398</td>
<td>1.602</td>
<td>0.438</td>
<td>0.371</td>
<td>1.550</td>
<td>0.496</td>
<td>0.353</td>
<td>1.642</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  $400,000 to $999,999</td>
<td>0.711<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1098214011424201">†</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>0.370</td>
<td>2.036</td>
<td>0.340</td>
<td>0.343</td>
<td>1.404</td>
<td>0.701<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1098214011424201">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.323</td>
<td>2.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  $1,000,000 to $2,999,999</td>
<td>0.309</td>
<td>0.356</td>
<td>1.363</td>
<td>0.433</td>
<td>0.328</td>
<td>1.542</td>
<td>0.376</td>
<td>0.312</td>
<td>1.457</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  $3,000,000 or more</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"> Health policy focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Missing</td>
<td>−0.868</td>
<td>0.800</td>
<td>0.420</td>
<td>−0.470</td>
<td>0.741</td>
<td>0.625</td>
<td>−0.618</td>
<td>0.713</td>
<td>0.539</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  One of several policy areas</td>
<td>−0.197</td>
<td>0.500</td>
<td>0.822</td>
<td>−0.115</td>
<td>0.461</td>
<td>0.892</td>
<td>−0.090</td>
<td>0.444</td>
<td>0.914</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Most important of many policy areas</td>
<td>−0.812</td>
<td>0.543</td>
<td>0.444</td>
<td>−0.530</td>
<td>0.502</td>
<td>0.589</td>
<td>−0.577</td>
<td>0.483</td>
<td>0.562</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Only policy area</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coalition grantee</td>
<td>1.339<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.495</td>
<td>3.815</td>
<td>0.562</td>
<td>0.475</td>
<td>1.754</td>
<td>1.223<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.446</td>
<td>3.396</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Policy maker contacts</td>
<td>0.129<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.040</td>
<td>1.138</td>
<td>0.093<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1098214011424201">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.037</td>
<td>1.097</td>
<td>0.115<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.035</td>
<td>1.121</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">Interorganization relationships</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Worked together before CVC</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>0.388</td>
<td>0.253</td>
<td>1.474</td>
<td>0.827<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.244</td>
<td>2.287</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"> Communication in previous 6 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Everyday/week</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>4.356<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.450</td>
<td>77.906</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Every month</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>2.935<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.371</td>
<td>18.829</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  A few times</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>1.619<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.352</td>
<td>5.048</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  No contact</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Don’t know/missing</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>0.847</td>
<td>0.532</td>
<td>2.332</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"> Shared values</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  To a great extent</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>1.278<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.264</td>
<td>3.591</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  To some extent</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Can’t assess/missing</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>−0.928<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.357</td>
<td>0.395</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td>866</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>866</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>866</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>−2 log pseudo-likelihood</td>
<td>7458.5</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>8581.27</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>12811.86</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">Covariance parameter estimates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent</td>
<td>4.016</td>
<td>0.843</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>4.031</td>
<td>0.866</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>3.555</td>
<td>0.771</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alter organization</td>
<td>0.596</td>
<td>0.208</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>0.371</td>
<td>0.185</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>0.314</td>
<td>0.159</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coalition</td>
<td>1.145</td>
<td>1.010</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>0.470</td>
<td>0.692</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>1.334</td>
<td>1.060</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alter organization characteristics</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interorganization relationships</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 866 organization pairs. Ordered logistic regression estimates predicting the number of collaborative advocacy activities (0, 1, or 2) identified by a respondent organization with an alter organization.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1098214011424201">
<p><sup>†</sup>
<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-1098214011424201">
<p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-1098214011424201">
<p>**<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn10-1098214011424201">
<p>***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Among the organization characteristics included in Model 1, organizations were more likely to report collaborative advocacy activities with organizations that had more policy maker contacts or were the grantee. The reciprocity measure was significant, suggesting that a respondent had 2.0 times higher odds of reporting collaborative advocacy activities when the alter organization also reported activities with the respondent. Years of experience, organization size, and the degree of health policy focus were not significant. Respondents had more than 3.8 times greater odds of reporting collaborative advocacy activities when the alter organization was the grantee than when it was not. Finally, the respondent was 14% more likely to report collaborative advocacy activities with an alter organization for every policy maker contact reported by the alter organization.</p>
<p>We find similar results for organization characteristics when we include the interorganization relationship measures in Models 2 and 3, with two exceptions. First, when communication frequency was included in Model 2, the positive estimate of the alter organization being the grantee was not statistically significant. However, when working together before the CVC and sharing values on health coverage were included with organization characteristics (Model 3), the grantee estimate was again significant, though the estimate was not as large as for Model 1. Second, in Model 3, there was a tendency for respondents to identify more collaborative advocacy activities with alter organizations that had annual budgets between $400,000 and $999,999 or had missing size data than with organizations that were among the largest in size.</p>
<p>All interorganizational relationship measures were significant predictors of collaborative advocacy activities, though not necessarily in combination with each other (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1098214011424201">Table 6</xref>). Model 2 shows that more frequent communication was significantly and positively associated with the collaborative advocacy activities reported by an organization with an alter organization, though prior experience working together was not related. In Model 3, however, prior experience working together was significantly and positively related to collaborative advocacy activities. In addition, compared with the reference group (sharing values to some extent), sharing values to a great extent was positively associated with collaborative advocacy activities, while not being able to assess values or a missing response was negatively associated with the dependent measure.</p>
<p>To explore the association between the interorganizational relationships and collaborative advocacy activities at the coalition level, we calculated the correlations among coalition-level relationship measures with the average number of collaborative advocacy activities per organization. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1098214011424201">Table 7</xref>
 shows the correlations for the proportion of organization pairs that had worked together before, that communicated at least monthly, and that shared values to a great extent with the coalition-level advocacy activity measure. Large correlations were found between communication and collaborative advocacy activities and between sharing values and collaborative advocacy activities. However, only the former correlation was statistically significant. Having worked together before was not associated with collaborative advocacy activities at the coalition level. The strong, positive relationship between communication and collaborative advocacy activities at the coalition level is confirmed visually in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1098214011424201">Figure 2</xref>
.</p>
<table-wrap id="table7-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Spearman Rank Correlations for Coalition-Level Interorganization Relationships and Collaborative Advocacy Activities</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Worked Together Before</th>
<th>Communication</th>
<th>Shared Values</th>
<th>Collaborative Advocacy Activities</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Worked together before</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>−0.042</td>
<td>0.207</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Communication</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>0.385</td>
<td>0.923<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn15-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Shared values</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>0.525<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-1098214011424201">†</xref></sup>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn11-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 12 coalitions. “Worked together before” indicates the proportion of organization pairs that had worked together before the CVC grant began. “Communication” shows the proportion of organization pairs for which communication in the past 6 months was every month or almost every month or more frequent. “Shared values” shows the proportion of organization pairs for which the respondent believed that the two organizations shared the same health coverage values to a great extent. “Collaborative advocacy activities” is the mean number of collaborative advocacy activities per coalition organization.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn12-1098214011424201">
<p>
<sup>†</sup>
<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn13-1098214011424201">
<p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn14-1098214011424201">
<p>**<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn15-1098214011424201">
<p>***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Communication level and average number of collaborative advocacy activities for each coalition.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig2-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Because of the strong relationship between communication and collaborative advocacy activities at the coalition level, we included communication at the coalition level in an additional p2 ordered logistic regression model. Model 4 includes the coalition-level mean communication score and the centered respondent–alter organization communication score described earlier as well as a measure of the coalition size (in terms of number of organizations; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table8-1098214011424201">Table 8</xref>
). The level of communication of the overall coalition was positively and significantly associated with the number of collaborative advocacy activities reported, but the size of the coalition was not significant. After accounting for the coalition-level communication, the interorganizational relationship measures of having worked together before was positively associated at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .10, while reported communication with an alter organization continued to be strongly associated with the collaborative advocacy activities reported with the alter organization. As with Model 2, only the number of policy maker contacts reported by an alter organization was a significant predictor of the number of collaborative advocacy activities.</p>
<table-wrap id="table8-1098214011424201" position="float">
<label>Table 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>P2-Ordered Logistic Regression Estimates Predicting Number of Collaborative Advocacy Activities Using Organization Characteristics, Interorganization Relationships, and Coalition Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table8-1098214011424201" xlink:href="10.1177_1098214011424201-table8.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">Variable</th>
<th colspan="3">Model 4</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Estimate</th>
<th>Standard Error</th>
<th>Odds Ratio</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Intercept 2</td>
<td>−6.526<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn20-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.562</td>
<td>0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intercept 1</td>
<td>−4.000<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn19-1098214011424201">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.549</td>
<td>0.018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intercept 0</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reciprocity</td>
<td>0.272<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-1098214011424201">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.134</td>
<td>1.313</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Alter organization characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Years of experience</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Fewer than 2 years</td>
<td>0.527</td>
<td>0.477</td>
<td>1.694</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2–5 years</td>
<td>0.139</td>
<td>0.398</td>
<td>1.149</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  6–9 years</td>
<td>0.015</td>
<td>0.400</td>
<td>1.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  10 or more years</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Size (annual budget)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Missing</td>
<td>0.723</td>
<td>0.539</td>
<td>2.060</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Less than $400,000</td>
<td>0.369</td>
<td>0.372</td>
<td>1.447</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  $400,000 to $999,999</td>
<td>0.324</td>
<td>0.344</td>
<td>1.382</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  $1,000,000 to $2,999,999</td>
<td>0.373</td>
<td>0.330</td>
<td>1.453</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  $3,000,000 or more</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Health policy focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Missing</td>
<td>−0.561</td>
<td>0.746</td>
<td>0.571</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  One of several policy areas</td>
<td>−0.210</td>
<td>0.461</td>
<td>0.810</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Most important of many policy areas</td>
<td>−0.652</td>
<td>0.504</td>
<td>0.521</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Only policy area</td>
<td align="center">Reference</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coalition grantee</td>
<td>0.567</td>
<td>0.474</td>
<td>1.763</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Policy maker contacts</td>
<td>0.088*</td>
<td>0.037</td>
<td>1.092</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Interorganization relationships</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Worked together before CVC</td>
<td>0.440<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn17-1098214011424201">†</xref></sup>
</td>
<td>0.253</td>
<td>1.552</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Communication in previous 6 months (centered)</td>
<td>1.308<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn20-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.128</td>
<td>3.699</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coalition characteristics</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Communication (mean)</td>
<td>2.454<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn20-1098214011424201">***</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.566</td>
<td>11.629</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Size</td>
<td>0.008</td>
<td>0.071</td>
<td>1.008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<italic>N</italic>
</td>
<td align="center">866</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>−2 log pseudo-likelihood</td>
<td>8456.88</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Covariance parameter estimates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent</td>
<td>4.105</td>
<td>0.891</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alter organization</td>
<td>0.376</td>
<td>0.185</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coalition</td>
<td>0.125</td>
<td>0.568</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alter organization characteristics</td>
<td align="center">Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interorganization relationships</td>
<td align="center">Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coalition characteristics</td>
<td align="center">Yes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn16-1098214011424201">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 866 organization pairs. Ordered logistic regression estimates predicting the number of collaborative advocacy activities (0, 1, or 2) identified by a respondent organization with an alter organization.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn17-1098214011424201">
<p>
<sup>†</sup>
<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn18-1098214011424201">
<p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn19-1098214011424201">
<p>**<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn20-1098214011424201">
<p>***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1098214011424201">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In the first year of operations, coalitions varied in the extent to which their members were engaged in collaborative advocacy-related activities. On average, organizations reported participating in at least one collaborative advocacy activity with almost two thirds of other organizations within their coalitions. Using ordered logistic regression and correlation methods, we examined whether the characteristics or interorganizational relationships of coalition member organizations were associated with differences in the level of these collaborative advocacy activities in the first year of the CVC grant program. Analyses showed these main findings:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Organizations reported collaborating more often on advocacy activities with member organizations that had more resources, as measured by the number of reported policy maker contacts. Other measures of resources, such as size, experience, or health policy focus, were not related to collaborative advocacy.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>As might be expected, organizations reported collaborating with grantees more often than nongrantee organizations, though when frequency of communication was added to the model, this finding was no longer statistically significant.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Organizations reported more collaborative advocacy activities with alter organizations with which they had more frequent communications outside of regular coalition meetings; with which they shared the same values on health coverage; and, to a lesser extent, with which they had worked before the CVC grant.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>At the coalition level, the frequency of communication explained differences in the average number of collaborative advocacy activities reported between coalitions. In addition, coalitions with higher levels of both communication and sharing values on health coverage among organizations had higher averages in the number of collaborative advocacy activities among members. However, the proportion of organizations that had worked together before the CVC was not significantly associated with shared advocacy at the coalition level.</p>
</list-item>
</list>Frequency of communication outside of meetings might be the most relevant aspect of the connections among organizations within an advocacy coalition. Communication and collaborative advocacy activities are both process measures, and it is not likely that two organizations will engage in advocacy activities without also having communication. However, our measure asks about communication outside of meetings; joint activities could also emerge only through only the formal meetings held by a coalition. Coalitions that can foster communication among their members might be in a better position to have member organizations act in concert toward the coalition’s goals. This finding is important as new coalitions are created: having high levels of communication is related to the coalition promoting the activities for which it was designed. Communication among members also provides opportunities to build strong connections that members can use well after the project and its funding have passed. As such, communication represents an aspect of social capital in that coalition organization members are building connections with each other, developing a common language and vision about advocacy, sharing knowledge with each other, and finding ways to collaborate.</p>
<p>Sharing values was also influential, but it did not vary much across these coalitions—respondents perceived that most other organizations within their coalition shared the same values. As a starting point, organizations submitting applications for the CVC grant probably had to have been somewhat in agreement on health coverage issues and the direction they desired for the coalition. From a practical standpoint, however, when organizations are not in agreement on their values, the coalition may have to spend additional time and effort working to bring its members into alignment before it can begin to address policy issues.</p>
<p>Although having worked together before the grant was a positive predictor of collaborative advocacy activities between organizations, the proportion of a coalition’s organizations that had such prior experience was not related to its overall level of collaborative advocacy activities. This finding is counterintuitive, but may reflect the different views of the coalition at the organization and network levels. The expectation is that coalitions with many members who had worked together before would have already established a high degree of trust and knowledge among those members. Such coalitions, it could be assumed, would therefore be quicker to agree on the direction of the coalition and to engage in activities. Because this expectation was not confirmed, it might be that our measure represents a weaker or indirect measure of interorganization relationships, particularly because the measure does not capture any information about the quality or intensity of the prior experience. Sharing values may also override the importance of prior relationships within advocacy coalitions.</p>
<p>Having more policy maker contacts and being the grantee organization were the only organizational characteristics significantly associated with reports of collaborative advocacy activities. Both measures represent the resources that an organization has access to and can offer other members. Organizations with more policy maker contacts may have more knowledge about the policy environment and so can attract other coalition members to collaborate with them in advocacy activities. Grantee organizations, particularly in the first year, may play a more active role in communicating with members and working on activities to address the coalition’s objectives, both of which would lead to their being more often identified by coalition members on these measures. When communication frequency is included, the grantee measure was no longer a significant predictor of collaborative advocacy activities, a finding that confirms how central grantees are in terms of communication and organizing the coalition. How important the grantee is for the success and continuance of the coalition is a question for further study.</p>
<sec id="section16-1098214011424201">
<title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
<p>A strength of this analysis is that it includes data from 12 coalitions. Much of the existing research on coalitions or partnerships involves only one or a few coalitions. Having a larger number of subjects provides an opportunity to use regression and correlation methods not practicable with smaller samples. The analysis also shows coalitions in an initial stage of development—their first year grant funding. The evaluation of the CVC continued to track these coalitions to observe how they changed and the outcomes they had on their state policy environment.</p>
<p>However, this study has two limitations. First, we cannot be sure of the direction of causality between interorganizational relationships and collaborative advocacy activities. In part, we measured several different kinds of relationships by asking organizations to recall or assess other organizations on these measures at a single point in time. In addition, there is likely some endogeneity regarding the relationship measures. Although we treat these relationships as distinct concepts, they are somewhat related in that they are all types of activities, and they may reflect underlying factors that were not measured—that communication and collaborative advocacy activities, for example, may both be related to a third, unmeasured factor, such as grantee characteristics or a state’s policy environment. Second, we had varying amounts of missing data for each coalition. Missing data can be especially detrimental for network analyses, because the structure might be different depending on the proportion of organizations that are missing. Although our results could differ if we had complete data from all involved organizations, the response rate was sufficiently high to be representative of those involved in the overall project. Despite these limitations, this analysis is exploratory in nature, and its results inform the understanding of how advocacy coalitions operate and how they might best achieve their goals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1098214011424201">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>Funding agencies and foundations have an interest in coalitions because they offer opportunities to bring many members of a state or community together to apply their collective resources to an issue and to build an infrastructure that remains in the community after funding ends. The results of this study suggest that when advocacy coalitions are created, it is not necessary to fund those coalitions whose members already have a history of working together. Coalitions can begin collaborative advocacy relatively quickly even without prior experience working together or sharing the same values, but it is important that initial coalitions create an environment that encourages communication among members.</p>
<p>Further, coalitions can have a range of resources among members, as long as some members have existing relationships with policy makers. Coming from different backgrounds in terms of policy interests and experience need not hinder collaboration if member organizations have existing connections with a number of relevant policy makers. Because these coalitions are designed to affect policy, they cannot achieve their goals without building relationships with policy makers. Including organizations with existing ties to policy makers may offer a quicker path to forging new policy maker relationships with coalition members.</p>
<p>These findings also show that SNA techniques can usefully be applied to advocacy evaluations to understand the capacities and functioning of coalitions. We were able to measure the level of communication among organization members, the extent to which they shared similar values, and the degree to which organizations were engaged in collaborative advocacy activities; moreover, for each measure, we examined the overall level of such relationships at the coalition (aggregate) level. Such measures may relate to the coalition’s eventual effectiveness in achieving long-term outcomes. SNA enabled us, the coalitions, and the funder to see the structure of connections among organizations and how these structures differed across the 12 coalitions. The observed structure can be compared with what the funding agency intended for the project, the impression or theory of change of the program, and the coalition’s own vision of what its structure should be. Discussions with each stakeholder about the data that emerge from the SNA can identify potential successes and opportunities for improving operations.</p>
<p>Using SNA for evaluation is not without its challenges. First, defining the network—those involved in the coalition—may be difficult. For our study, the definition was made easier by including the organization members of the formal leadership team of each coalition. Second, making the findings relevant for those involved is important. Although advocates are sophisticated in terms of data and policy analysis, SNA represents a novel tool within this context; for that reason, we invested in materials to help coalitions understand the data and in time to review the data with each coalition. This review also provided an opportunity to enable members to discuss possible reasons for their results. Finally, as mentioned earlier, there is no ideal network; it is important to place SNA findings in the context of the network studied.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge Brian Quinn of the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation for his ongoing support of the evaluation. The authors also thank Russell Cole, John Deke, and Beth Stevens, all of Mathematica, who offered insightful comments and instructive technical feedback. The authors express their gratitude to the two anonymous reviewers who provided helpful comments on the article.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-1098214011424201">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1098214011424201">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research was funded by a grant from the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<title>Note</title>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1098214011424201">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The number of policy maker contacts reported by an organization could be endogenous to one of our outcome activities, meeting with a policy maker or attending a public meeting or hearing with the organization. To test the sensitivity of the relationship between policy maker contacts and collaborative activities, we conducted the same analyses excluding that outcome measure and modeling just the collaborative activity of making joint decisions. The estimates regarding policy maker contacts and that collaborative activity remained similar to the results presented here.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Agresti</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>An introduction to categorical data analysis</source>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Community Catalyst</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Consumer health advocacy: A view from 16 states</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved March 3, 2009, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.communitycatalyst.org/doc_store/publications/consumer_health_advocacy_a_view_from_16_states_oct06.pdf">http://www.communitycatalyst.org/doc_store/publications/consumer_health_advocacy_a_view_from_16_states_oct06.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dickman</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Newman-Gonchar</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fagan</surname>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Using mixed-method design and network analysis to measure development of interagency collaboration</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Evaluation</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Crowe</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>In search of a happy medium: How the structure of interorganizational networks influence community economic development strategies</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doyle</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brady</surname>
<given-names>A.-M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Byrn</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>An overview of mixed methods research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Nursing</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Flom</surname>
<given-names>P. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McMahon</surname>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pouget</surname>
<given-names>E. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Using PROC NLMIXED and PROC GLIMMIX to analyze dyadic data with a dichotomous dependent variable</article-title>. <source>SAS Global Forum 2007 Proceedings, No. 179-2007</source>. <comment>Retrieved February 13, 2010, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.sas.com/proceedings/forum2007/179-2007.pdf">http://www2.sas.com/proceedings/forum2007/179-2007.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gold</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Doreian</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>E. F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Understanding a collaborative effort to reduce racial and ethnic disparities in health care: Contributions from social network analysis</article-title>. <source>Social Science and Medicine</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>1018</fpage>–<lpage>1027</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>J. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luke</surname>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mueller</surname>
<given-names>N. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Seeing the forest and the trees: Using network analysis to develop an organizational blueprint of state tobacco control systems</article-title>. <source>Social Science and Medicine</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>1669</fpage>–<lpage>1678</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Onwuegbuzie</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Mixed methods research: A research paradigm whose time has come</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krauss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mueller</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Luke</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Interorganizational relationships within state tobacco control networks: A social network analysis</article-title>. <source>Preventing Chronic Disease: Public Health Research, Practice, and Policy</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lemieux-Charles</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>L. W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cockerill</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaglal</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brazil</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>… Schulman</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Evaluating the effectiveness of community-based dementia care networks: The Dementia Care Networks’ Study</article-title>. <source>Gerontologist</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shortell</surname>
<given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The governance and management of effective community health partnerships: A typology for research, policy, and practice</article-title>. <source>Milbank Quarterly</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mizruchi</surname>
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marquis</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Egocentric, sociocentric, or dyadic? Identifying the appropriate level of analysis in the study of organizational networks</article-title>. <source>Social Networks</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Provan</surname>
<given-names>K. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nakama</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Veazie</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Teufel-Shone</surname>
<given-names>N. I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huddleston</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Building community capacity around chronic disease services through a collaborative interorganizational network</article-title>. <source>Health Education and Behavior</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Provan</surname>
<given-names>K. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Veazie</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Staten</surname>
<given-names>L. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Teufel-Shone</surname>
<given-names>N. I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The use of network analysis to strengthen community partnerships</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Robert Wood Johnson Foundation</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Mission and history</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved June 3, 2011, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rwjf.org/about/mission.jsp">http://www.rwjf.org/about/mission.jsp</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Valente</surname>
<given-names>T. W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coronges</surname>
<given-names>K. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cousineau</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Collaboration and competition in a children’s health initiative coalition: A network analysis</article-title>. <source>Evaluation and Program Planning</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van de Ven</surname>
<given-names>A. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferry</surname>
<given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <source>Measuring and assessing organizations</source>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van Duijn</surname>
<given-names>M. A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snijders</surname>
<given-names>T. A. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zijlstra</surname>
<given-names>B. J. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>p2: A random effects model with covariates for directed graphs</article-title>. <source>Statistica Neerlandica</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Faust</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Social network analysis: Methods and applications</source>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zakocs</surname>
<given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>E. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>“What explains community coalition effectiveness? A review of the literature.”</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1098214011424201">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zijlstra</surname>
<given-names>B. J. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Duijn</surname>
<given-names>M. A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snijders</surname>
<given-names>T. A. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The multilevel p2 model: A random effects model for the analysis of multiple social networks</article-title>. <source>Methodology: European Journal of Research Methods for the Behavioral and Social Sciences</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>