<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="en">
  
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DAS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdas</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Discourse &amp; Society</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0957-9265</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-3624</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0957926513482066</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0957926513482066</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Learning to make racism funny in the ‘color-blind’ era: Stand-up comedy
          students, performance strategies, and the (re)production of racist jokes in
          public</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pérez</surname>
            <given-names>Raúl</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1-0957926513482066">University of California, Irvine, USA</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="corresp1-0957926513482066">Raúl Pérez, Department of Sociology, University of
          California, Irvine, 1712 Verano Place, Irvine, CA 92617, USA. Email:
            <email xlink:type="simple">raulp@uci.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>24</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>478</fpage>
      <lpage>503</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>This article contends performance comedy serves as a mechanism for expressing ethnic and
          racial stereotypes in public and presents a challenge to studies of contemporary racial
          discourse which suggest overt racetalk in public is on the decline. In this ethnographic
          study on the training of stand-up comedians, I probe how comedy students learn to use
          rhetorical performance strategies to couch ethnic and racial stereotypes in more palatable
          ways, in order to be ‘funny’ rather than ‘offensive’ in public. Using critical discourse
          analysis (CDA), this study illustrates the role elites play in managing racial discourse.
          It is found that white versus non-white comedy students are taught to engage in racial
          discourse in different ways. Whites are taught distance and denial strategies which allow
          them to engage in overt racial commentary and deny racism or racist intent, while
          non-whites are often encouraged to engage in racial stereotypes uncritically. This study
          shows how strategic use of humor allows the ‘constraints’ on current racial discourse, on
          whites in particular, to be broken, suggesting a new phase of color-blind racism may be
          underway.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Color-blind racism</kwd>
        <kwd>comedy</kwd>
        <kwd>critical discourse analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>ethnography</kwd>
        <kwd>humor</kwd>
        <kwd>jokes</kwd>
        <kwd>performance</kwd>
        <kwd>racetalk</kwd>
        <kwd>racial discourse</kwd>
        <kwd>racism</kwd>
        <kwd>strategies</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>I’m not a misogynistic and racist person . . . [b]ut I do find those jokes funny, so I
          say them.</p>
        <attrib>– Comedian Daniel Tosh (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0957926513482066">Hibberd,
            2011</xref>)</attrib>
      </disp-quote>
    </p>
    <p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>I’ve skewered whites, blacks, Hispanics, Christians, Jews, Muslims, gays, straights,
          rednecks, addicts, the elderly, and my wife. As a standup comic, it is my job to make the
          majority of people laugh, and I believe that comedy is the last true form of free
          speech.</p>
        <attrib>– Comedian Jeff Dunham (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0957926513482066">Miller,
            2008</xref>)</attrib>
      </disp-quote>
    </p>
    <p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>Racism has not managed to harden. It has had to renew itself, to adapt itself, to change
          its appearance. . . to undergo the fate of the cultural whole that informed it.</p>
        <attrib>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0957926513482066">Fanon, 1967</xref>:
          32)</attrib>
      </disp-quote>
    </p>
    <sec id="section1-0957926513482066" sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Scholars have noted the decline in overt racist discourse in public in the post-civil
        rights era and contend that the ideology of overt Jim Crow racism has been replaced by a
          <italic>new racetalk</italic>, one that is subtle, covert, ‘color-blind’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman, 2000</xref>), or
        of a ‘kinder and gentler’ form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957926513482066">Bobo et
          al., 1997</xref>). As a result, scholars argue that public expression of racism<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0957926513482066">1</xref></sup> has changed dramatically where
        strategic forms of public racetalk have emerged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957926513482066">Bobo and Charles, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1992</xref>). Overall, the literature on new
        public expressions of racism suggests that overt expressions are unlikely to occur in public
        as there are strong social norms and repercussions that have produced a strategic,
        politically correct and/or polite racial discourse.</p>
      <p>But consider stand-up comedy. Comedians frequently breach norms of etiquette and polite
        public discourse. With respect to race, stand-up comics often rely on blatant racial and
        ethnic stereotypes of the perceived deficiencies and proclivities of ‘others.’ Joke-tellers
        justify the use of such stereotypes by pointing out that the role of comedy is to confront
        touchy subjects, breach norms of etiquette, name taboos, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0957926513482066">Dundes, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0957926513482066">Gilbert, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0957926513482066">Morreall, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0957926513482066">Oring, 2003</xref>). What matters is ‘being funny.’ The use
        of comedy to rupture the taboo is not unique to racial discourse, as one can imagine sexual
        or political humor surfacing in sexually or politically repressive societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0957926513482066">Davies, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0957926513482066">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0957926513482066">Morreall, 1983</xref>). Yet what is of interest in this
        study is the increasingly unique and understudied role racial-comedic performance currently
        plays in American public racial discourse, where overt racist language in public is
        restricted in an ostensibly color-blind or post-racial society.</p>
      <p>In this article, I argue that comics make racist discourse palatable by learning to employ
        certain strategies of talk which are intended to circumvent the current ‘constraints’ on
        racial discourse in public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte,
          1987</xref>). These strategies, however, are different from those used for public racetalk
        in which racist discourse is coded or hidden rather than expressed directly, as others have
        documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2002</xref>;
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman, 2000</xref>;
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0957926513482066">Jackman and Crane, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1987</xref>). If color-blind
        racism tends to be concealed, racism in comedy is hidden in plain sight. The strategies that
        comics learn suggest another possible answer to the question of how racism is communicated
        in a society that disavows racist speech: racism is expressed in public and overtly, but its
        offensiveness is deflected, in part, by the use of strategies that make the performers seem
        ‘not racist,’ even as they say racist things.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section2-0957926513482066">
      <title>Shifting racial discourse</title>
      <p>Many Americans believe racism to be a thing of the past (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0957926513482066">Coates, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0957926513482066">Hyman and Sheatsley, 1956</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0957926513482066">Lipset, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0957926513482066">Sniderman and Piazza, 1993</xref>). Studies show a shift in
        American racial views and an overwhelming condemnation of racism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0957926513482066">Jackman and Crane, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0957926513482066">Sigelman and Welch, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0957926513482066">Slavin and Madden, 1979</xref>). Yet numerous studies
        continue to illustrate that racial discrimination and stereotyping persist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957926513482066">Bobo et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0957926513482066">Feagin, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0957926513482066">2000</xref>). The current period of race relations, scholars
        argue, consists of subtle and elusive forms of racism and has produced many contradictory
        behaviors, attitudes, and realities in contemporary American society. A ‘racism without
        racists,’ contends <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva
          (2010)</xref>, is the racial ideology of the post-Jim Crow USA, where there tends to be an
        unwillingness to believe that racism continues to exist and negatively impact the ‘life
        chances’ of racial and ethnic minorities.</p>
      <p>Researchers find that racial discourse has changed dramatically in the post-civil rights
        era, altering the landscape of racetalk. Scholars have offered two complementary answers to
        the question of how racism is expressed in a society that claims to reject racism.</p>
      <p>One theory suggests that racist arguments are now coded or covert. In public discourse, for
        example, individuals often rely on a variety of strategies to impugn racial minorities
        without doing so overtly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957926513482066">Augoustinos and
          Every, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957926513482066">Bobo et al.,
          1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva,
          2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman,
          2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0957926513482066">Doane, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0957926513482066">Hill, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0957926513482066">1993a</xref>). Scholars have documented various strategies
        or semantic moves in racial discourse in the post-civil rights era. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman (2000)</xref> in particular contend
        that the current racial ideology, reflected by a ‘new racetalk’ which has emerged in recent
        decades, has been to elude overt racist claims in public while ‘[preserving] the
        contemporary racial order’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman, 2000</xref>: 51). This new racetalk, captured in interviews and
        surveys regarding racial attitudes, is used by whites in contemporary public racial
        discourse where overt racism has become taboo.</p>
      <p>For instance, scholars have shown terms such as ‘urban, welfare, crime’ are often used to
        refer publically to poor inner-city black and brown minorities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0957926513482066">Mendelberg, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0957926513482066">Mendelberg and Oleske, 2000</xref>). Such terms are meant to
        invoke clear cultural deficiencies where biological claims are no longer legitimate. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0957926513482066">Mendelberg (2001)</xref> contends that such
        coded terminology is often used by ‘white political elites to appeal to white voters’ at the
        expense of racial minorities. These strategies suggest that public forms of racetalk have
        changed dramatically from overt forms of Jim Crow racism to covert or subtle expressions of
        public racism in the post-Jim Crow era (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957926513482066">Bobo and Charles, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2010</xref>).</p>
      <p>A second answer to the question of how racism is expressed in a society that claims to
        reject racism is that overt racist discourse continues to be shared in private settings.
        Studies find that racist talk persists in the form of sharing and expressing stereotypes and
        prejudicial statements in private conversations, discussions, and/or jokes, and continues as
        usual in intimate settings of family, friends, the workplace, and other closely knit social
        circles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0957926513482066">Eliasoph, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0957926513482066">Feagin et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0957926513482066">Hill, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0957926513482066">Myers, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0957926513482066">Myers and Williamson, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0957926513482066">Picca and Feagin, 2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>The two answers suggest complementary forms of racetalk: that which is covert in public
        settings and that which is overt in private ones. At the same time, they suggest that overt
        or explicit racetalk in public settings is unlikely to occur in the current post-racial or
        color-blind period as a result of the shift in public racial discourse after the civil
        rights movement. However, race scholars have paid little attention to the development and
        role of stand-up comedy as a space where overt racial discourse occurs in public.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section3-0957926513482066">
      <title>Comedy and the race question</title>
      <sec id="section4-0957926513482066">
        <title>The declining significance of race?</title>
        <p>Just as race scholars claim that overt racist discourse has disappeared from the public
          realm, many humor scholars agree. The most significant theories of humor frame it as a way
          to create in-group cohesion versus out-group boundaries by oppressing or controlling
          others, as a relief or social safety valve, and/or a way to resolve incongruity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0957926513482066">Morreall, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0957926513482066">Raskin, 1985</xref>). While not mutually
          exclusive, these theories offer different perspectives on the role of humor in
          society.</p>
        <p>According to the <italic>superiority theory</italic> of humor, one of its main functions
          is to dominate others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957926513482066">Boskin and
            Dorinson, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957926513482066">Burma,
            1946</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0957926513482066">Morreall, 1983</xref>).
          For over a century, from the pre-civil war period to the pre-civil rights era, ‘blackface
          minstrel shows’ were one of the prominent forms of humor in American society in which
          humor functioned to subordinate black Americans. Until the civil rights period, white
          performers unabashedly painted their faces black using burnt corks while imitating,
          mocking, and caricaturing southern and northern African Americans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957926513482066">Boskin, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0957926513482066">Roediger, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0957926513482066">Saxton, 1998</xref>). Scholars also note how humor was
          used to force immigrants to ‘Americanize’ through ridicule of language and customs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0957926513482066">Lowe, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0957926513482066">Mintz, 1996</xref>).</p>
        <p>The pre-civil rights period was marked by what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957926513482066">Boskin and Dorinson (1985)</xref> call ethnic and racial
          ‘humor of accommodation’ (that is, accommodating to white tastes and expectations). They
          observe that it was during and after the civil rights period that ethnic and racial
          minorities, blacks in particular, openly engaged in anti-racist comedy or ‘reverse
          discourse’ as a form of resistance to oppression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-0957926513482066">Weaver, 2010b</xref>). The <italic>relief theory</italic>
          notes that humor also functions as a way to release social anxieties and tensions, rupture
          social taboos, and subvert ‘polite realities’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957926513482066">Attardo, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957926513482066">Billig, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0957926513482066">Morreall, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0957926513482066">Ritchie, 2005</xref>). It might be argued that the racial
          conflict during the civil rights period was eased in part by comedians of color who
          appealed to white audiences as they sought to challenge racial inequality with their wit
            (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957926513482066">Boskin, 1979</xref>).</p>
        <p>As a result, scholars find that the problematic aspects of race humor in public discourse
          have been largely relegated to the private sphere in the post-civil rights and color-blind
          eras (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0957926513482066">Eliasoph, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0957926513482066">Feagin, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0957926513482066">Myers, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0957926513482066">Picca and Feagin, 2007</xref>) or have taken a coded form.
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957926513482066">Abrahams and Dundes (1969)</xref>,
          for instance, suggest that the rise of ‘elephant joke cycles’ in the 1960s were a covert
          way in which whites expressed their anxieties about racial integration and miscegenation,
          where ‘elephant jokes’ were code for black:</p>
        <speech>
          <speaker>Q:</speaker>
          <p>How do you know when an elephant’s in bed with you?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <speaker>A:</speaker>
          <p>Nine months later you have a problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <p>These jokes exist as a ‘cultural phenomenon,’ they contend, arising out of a
          socio-historical context and in response to the ‘Negro Revolution’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957926513482066">Abrahams and Dundes, 1969</xref>: 238). Others note how
          overt racist humor is harbored in ‘cyberspace’ among white supremacist organizations
            (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957926513482066">Billig, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-0957926513482066">Weaver, 2011</xref>).</p>
        <p>However, stand-up comedy breaks this mold. Much like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957926513482066">Bakhtin’s (1968)</xref> observations of the
            <italic>carnivalesque</italic>, from the Middle Ages through the 20th century, as a
          bracketed social space where dominant social norms are believed to not apply, a comedy
          club is a public space where performers can push and invert the boundaries of polite and
          formal public discourse.</p>
        <p>The seismic shift in public racial discourse in the post-civil rights era seemingly
          impacted the world of stand-up comedy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957926513482066">Berger (1993)</xref>, for instance, suggests that by the early 1990s ‘ethnic and racial
          minorities [had] gained enough political power to make it just about impossible to direct
          hostile humor against ethnic and racial groups … in the media and public forums’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957926513482066">Berger, 1993</xref>: 73). Lawsuits and/or
          public apologies for humor deemed derogatory by targeted groups were quite common during
          this period. A notable example is comedian Ted Danson’s controversial blackface
          performance at the Friars Club in New York City (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0957926513482066">Fisher, 1993</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte (1987)</xref>, ‘ethnic humor’ in American society
          during this time was more ‘constrained’ than at any point in American history, in the
          public sphere in particular. ‘Traditionally oppressed groups’ began to ‘assert themselves
          and … protest their being made the butt of humor initiated by anyone but themselves’
            (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte, 1987</xref>: 27). While Apte
          and Berger stress that overt racial discourse in comedy has greatly diminished, more
          recent observers have begun to take notice of the reemergence of such discourse via comedy
          by whites in particular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0957926513482066">Lockyer and
            Pickering, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0957926513482066">Santa Ana,
            2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0957926513482066">Stanley,
          2007</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section5-0957926513482066">
        <title>Critical humor studies</title>
        <p>While much of the humor literature echoes the race literature with respect to the decline
          in public racial discourse, it offers conceptualizations to help us understand why
          race-based comedy persists in an ostensibly post-racial or color-blind society.</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957926513482066">Billig (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-0957926513482066">Weaver (2010a)</xref> contend that
          conventional humor scholarship often takes a ‘celebratory stance’ on humor, ignoring or
          minimizing the role it plays in reproducing racism. More critical humor scholarship
          suggests that the role of humor in perpetuating detrimental racial ideologies is in need
          of further research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957926513482066">Billig,
            2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0957926513482066">Ford, 1997</xref>;
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0957926513482066">Lockyer and Pickering, 2008</xref>;
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-0957926513482066">Weaver, 2011</xref>). While some
          argue jokes are essentially harmless (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0957926513482066">Davies, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0957926513482066">2004</xref>),
          critical scholars contend race-based humor walks a fine line between challenging racial
          inequality and strengthening hegemonic notions of race (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957926513482066">Boskin, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0957926513482066">Gilbert, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0957926513482066">Husband, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0957926513482066">Park et al., 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-0957926513482066">Weaver (2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-0957926513482066">2010b</xref>), distinguishing between racist and
          anti-racist humor, suggests that ‘[where] humour draws on dichotomous stereotypes of race
          and/or seeks to inferiorise an ethnic or racial minority, not labelling the humour racist’
          as opposed to racial, ‘is a form of ideological denial’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-0957926513482066">Weaver, 2010a</xref>: 537). He further suggests, citing
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0957926513482066">Davidson (1987)</xref>, that there
          is an exaggeration of ‘racial’ humor in the literature. Raskin also observes that ‘most
          ethnic humor is functionally deprecatory, or disparaging’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0957926513482066">1985</xref>: 180).</p>
        <p>Humor is also socially and historically situated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957926513482066">Abrahams and Dundes, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-0957926513482066">Weaver, 2010a</xref>). Jokes may be perceived as funny or
          unfunny in different contexts and periods. Jokes are polysemic, ambiguous, and elusive
            (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0957926513482066">Lockyer and Pickering,
          2008</xref>). A theoretical grasp of the social functions of humor, therefore, can assist
          in understanding how and why overt and racist language is permissible in comedy in the
          current color-blind and politically correct period. While the <italic>superiority
            theory</italic> holds that humor is a way to dominate and the <italic>relief
            theory</italic> has it as a way to ease social tensions, the <italic>incongruity
            theory</italic> suggests humor also functions as a way to resolve incongruous ideas. The
          sudden realization of certain incongruities, theorists suggest, often gives rise to humor
            (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0957926513482066">Morreall, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0957926513482066">Raskin, 1985</xref>). Thus, one can argue
          that racist comedy in the color-blind era is acceptable in part because of the incongruity
          between our ‘common-sense’ notion that ‘racism is bad’ and a ‘thing of the past,’ while
          performers make inappropriate racial comments as a way to rupture taboo racial discourse
          in public, and stand behind ‘just a joke’ and free speech claims as they publically
          disparage racial and ethnic minorities.</p>
        <p>While one can argue that discussing racial topics while trying to challenge traditional
          racist tropes is not racist in the conventional sense, race-based humor often teaches the
          audience <italic>how</italic> to think about race while reifying and relying on racial
          stereotypes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0957926513482066">Gilbert (2004)</xref>,
          citing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte (1987)</xref>, notes that
          the ‘liberatory’ and ‘empowering’ potential of self-disparaging humor risks becoming
          ‘self-flagellation’ if unremitting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0957926513482066">Gilbert, 2004</xref>: 19). This issue is highlighted by comedian Richard Pryor and,
          more recently, comedian Dave Chappelle, both noted African-American comedians who took
          trips to Africa during periods of ideological crisis concerning their roles in
          perpetuating versus undermining racism through their work. Pryor publically stated he
          would drop his use of the word ‘nigger’ upon his return (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0957926513482066">Jackson, 2005</xref>), while Chappelle left his hit cable
          TV program <italic>Chappelle’s Show</italic> and a $50 million contract with cable network
            <italic>Comedy Central</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0957926513482066">Johnson, 2009</xref>). These examples raise important questions with respect to ‘racial
          versus racist’ humor engaged in by comedians in the post-civil rights and color-blind
          period.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section6-0957926513482066">
      <title>Performing racial discourse</title>
      <p>While scholars debate whether race-based humor is intended to dominate others, relieve
        social tensions or resolve incongruities, I argue that comedians must <italic>learn</italic>
        to utilize rhetorical performance strategies in order to navigate public racetalk – not as a
        way to avoid overt racist expressions, as other studies have found, but often to state them
        publically. Joke-tellers often invoke perceived and commonly assumed racial differences,
        which tend to take the form of stereotypes. As a result of the shift in racial discourse,
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte (1987)</xref> warns that it must
        be made clear to the audience that the performer is not a racist when performing ethnic and
        racial stereotypes in public. Such a feat is accomplished, I argue, by employing certain
        performance strategies which help preserve a veil of <italic>authentic
          inauthenticity</italic> for the performer: ‘I am not racist even as I say racist things.’
        This purposefully invoked veil on the part of the performer works to ensure distance between
        literal claims and comedic intent and is maintained through rhetorical performance
        strategies: self-disparaging humor, the ‘equal opportunity offender,’ distance and
        disclaimer mechanisms, and so on. They are not only intended to ‘save face,’ but borrowing
        from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk (1992)</xref> I argue that
        such strategies are also intended to deny racism or racist intent in performances that
        engage in offensive racist discourse in public.</p>
      <p>Using a play frame, Tannen suggests that the ‘metamessage’ of play shapes how actions and
        behaviors are to be interpreted in a humorous context (i.e. they are not to be taken
        literally) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0957926513482066">Tannen, 2005</xref>: 32).
        Using Goffman’s frame analysis, Clift also notes that humor such as irony allows a ‘reduced
        personal responsibility’ by creating distance and detachment between the author and what is
        said (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0957926513482066">Clift, 1999</xref>: 28). This is
        particularly important for performers when using racist and sexist discourse. As comedian
        Daniel Tosh, host of <italic>Tosh.O</italic> (one of the most watched programs on
          <italic>Comedy Central</italic> in the post-<italic>Chappelle’s Show</italic> period),
        suggests: <disp-quote>
          <p>I’m not a misogynistic and racist person … [b]ut I do find those jokes funny, so I say
            them. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0957926513482066">Hibberd, 2011</xref>)</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0957926513482066">Park et al. (2006)</xref> contend that
        performers uncritically enacting racial stereotypes ‘naturalize’ racial differences, as they
        often do little to challenge the racial hierarchy. In a society where ‘racism is deeply
        rooted,’ they argue that race-based jokes ‘reinforce hierarchically structured racial
        differences,’ which are less likely to be critically challenged when veiled through humor.
        Performances dealing with racial stereotypes are often ‘uncomfortably reminiscent of racist
        ideologies that have been used to justify racial discrimination in the past’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0957926513482066">2006</xref>: 159). According to Ford, humor
        often ‘blunts the critical sensitivity’ of the audience towards ‘socially unacceptable
        actions or sentiments’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0957926513482066">Ford,
          1997</xref>: 272). When strategically engaging in taboo racial discourse and masking it
        with performance strategies, a successful performance pleases an audience and often shields
        the performer from accusations of racism. Without a strategic performance, however, comics
        risk being offensive or, worse still, not funny.</p>
      <p>Take the public outcry that followed comedian Michael Richards’ racist tirade in a
        Hollywood comedy club in November 2006. During this incident, Richards proceeded to verbally
        attack a black audience member heckling his routine. The verbal attacks were filmed by
        audience members, and millions later witnessed his vicious comments online. ‘Shut up!’
        Richards yelled, ‘50 years ago we’d have you upside down with a fucking fork up your ass!
        (scattered laughs, cheers, and oohh’s from the audience) … throw his ass out (pointing at
        the audience member) he’s a nigger!’ (audience gasps) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0957926513482066">TMZ Staff, 2006</xref>). ‘I’m a performer. I push the
        envelope,’ Richards stated as he publically apologized for his comments. ‘I’m not a racist;
        that’s what’s so insane about this,’ Richards later told David Letterman, host of
          <italic>The Late Show</italic> on CBS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-0957926513482066">Von Meistersinger, 2006</xref>).</p>
      <p>Part of what makes Richards’ performance unsuccessful, offensive, and racist is that it
        veers from a ‘playing with racism’ frame. By failing to employ the rhetorical performance
        strategies that preserve the veil of <italic>authentic inauthenticity</italic> (until after
        the fact – ‘I push the envelope … I’m not a racist’), which protect and distance the
        performer from both audience and content, his performance comes off as ‘real racism.’ As
        stand-up comedy author and instructor, Judy Carter, observes: <disp-quote>
          <p>Chris Rock can talk about things he doesn’t like about black people and sound hip and
            cutting edge. If you are white and you do it, you sound like an ignorant, ugly bigot.
              (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957926513482066">Carter, 2001</xref>: 149)</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>Richards’ performance fails to engage the proper strategies. The audience perceives no
        incongruity in his performance; anxieties are heightened, not reduced; the veil is removed;
        and his performance becomes a racist rather than comedic/ironic spectacle. A strategic
        presentation of humor in public allows individuals to circumvent the constraints of public
        racial discourse and engage in overt stereotypical depictions of the ‘other’ which are
        disavowed in most public spaces.</p>
      <p>Scarpetta and Spagnolli suggest that while scholars have looked at the way humor is
        structured and made recognizable, less attention has been paid to the ‘interactional
        practices through which humor is made acceptable’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0957926513482066">Scarpetta and Spagnolli, 2009</xref>: 213). In line with
        other studies on the strategic use of racial discourse, I argue that it is ritualized social
        practices, and not context alone, that allow performers to make stereotypical references
        often deemed unacceptable in most public settings, funny and entertaining in this
        context.</p>
      <p>This project, therefore, focuses on how performers learn to use such strategies in a
        stand-up comedy school and how students are taught to engage in racial discourse in a
        society that ostensibly claims to reject explicit racial commentary in public. I borrow from
        and modify <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0957926513482066">Van Dijk’s (1993b</xref>,
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-0957926513482066">1995b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-0957926513482066">2002)</xref> list of discursive structures which were used
        by the instructors in my evaluation of the managing of racial discourse in this context:
          <italic>metaphor</italic>, <italic>positive self-presentation</italic>, <italic>negative
          other-presentation</italic>, <italic>apparent empathy</italic>, <italic>positive
          lexicalization</italic>, and <italic>phonological distancing</italic> are some of the
        discursive structures used by instructors to <italic>deny racism</italic> in student
        performances. These discursive structures were used in combination with three recurring
        performance strategies: <italic>using racial common sense</italic>,
          <italic>self-deprecation</italic>, and <italic>distancing mechanisms</italic> such as
        creating characters or mimicking dialects. Moreover, the legitimation of such strategies
        taught by comedy instructors illustrate the ‘symbolic capital’ and ‘symbolic power’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957926513482066">Bourdieu, 1989</xref>) they have while
        imposing their vision of racial comedy on students.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section7-0957926513482066" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Data and methods</title>
      <p>I gathered data for this project using participant observation by enrolling as a student in
        a stand-up comedy school in Los Angeles in August 2008. Participation and observation
        enabled me to ‘grasp the meanings associated with the actions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0957926513482066">Lofland et al., 2006</xref>: 15) of the students and
        instructors in the school. While context is important and significant in the evaluation of
        any discourse, this study situates comedic racetalk in a cultural and historical context,
        placing public racial humor in the broader shift of contemporary public racial discourse.
        According to Gee, ‘[c]ontext refers to an ever-widening set of factors that accompany
        language in use,’ such as setting, people present (e.g. ethnic, racial, and gendered
        identities), ‘as well as cultural, historical and institutional factors’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0957926513482066">2004</xref>: 28). Participation and
        observation, therefore, allowed me not only to grasp the ‘local meaning’ in the context of
        the comedy school, but also to situate these meanings and actions in a critical analysis of
        comedic racial discourse in a color-blind society. These observations were triangulated
        against studies of racial discourse, theories of humor and pedagogical literature on
        contemporary performance comedy in order to analyze the ‘discourse-historical’ background in
        which these ‘discursive “events” are embedded’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-0957926513482066">Wodak, 2001</xref>: 65).</p>
      <p>Data was analyzed using critical discourse analysis (CDA). As an interdisciplinary approach
        to analyzing power and inequality in society via discourse, CDA views language as a form of
        social practice that reproduces ‘social and political domination’ through text and talk
          (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0957926513482066">Fairclough, 1995</xref>). CDA enables
        scholars to identify ways in which individuals engage in ‘everyday racism’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957926513482066">Augoustinos and Every, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-0957926513482066">Wodak and Matouschek, 1993</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk (1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-0957926513482066">1995a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman (2000)</xref>, in particular,
        illustrate how much racial discourse is often intended to deny racism in the post-Nazi and
        post-Jim Crow eras. In his analysis of the reproduction of racism, Van Dijk also contends
        that elites play a major role in ‘initiating, monitoring and controlling’ the ‘orders of
        discourse’ of public text and talk, by virtue of their ‘preferential access’ and power in
        shaping public discourse in society’s major institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1995a</xref>: 4). Therefore, I found CDA to be
        most appropriate in analyzing my data to illustrate <italic>how</italic> students learned to
        engage in public racial discourse through comedy, in ways that often (re)produced and denied
        racism, by focusing on how the instructors ‘initiated, monitored, and controlled’ such
        discourse in this context.</p>
      <p>Two factors motivated this ethnographic study of a comedy school: (1) I sensed that
        racetalk in stand-up comedy failed to conform to the public covert or private overt pattern
        found in most studies of contemporary racial discourse – rather, race-based stand-up comedy
        seems public and overt, which led me to believe that the setting had to be governed by norms
        different from those identified in the existing literature; and (2) I recognized that
        instruction in the stand-up comedy school might reveal the process by which people were
        taught the norms of appropriate racetalk in stand-up comedy. As Scarpetta and Spagnolli
        suggest, stand-up comedy can be seen as an ‘institutional form of talk-in-interaction’
          (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0957926513482066">Scarpetta and Spagnolli, 2009</xref>:
        214). By focusing on the comedy school as an ‘institutionalized community of practice’
          (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0957926513482066">Gee, 2004</xref>: 38), I was able to
        understand the ‘everyday theories’ about race and comedy that allowed performers to engage
        in discourse disavowed in most other public settings.</p>
      <p>I investigated these issues through observation and participation, informal interviews,
        conversations, and group discussions in a Los Angeles area comedy school and comedy club
        between August 2008 and March 2009. I accumulated well over 200 hours of participation and
        observation.</p>
      <p>I found this school on multiple search engines using ‘stand-up comedy schools and Los
        Angeles’ and therefore assumed it to reach a wide and diverse prospective student body. The
        majority of students I encountered found the school online as well. Students were in the
        main white and overwhelmingly male.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0957926513482066">2</xref></sup> My student count consists of classes I attended and not the total number
        enrolled at the time: 20 white males, five Latino males, three black males, one Asian male,
        one white/Asian male, four white females, one Latina female, two black females, and one
        Asian female. The age range was very broad, with the youngest student a recent high-school
        graduate and the oldest students approaching retirement. There were three instructors:
            Ted<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0957926513482066">3</xref></sup> (white male), the
        owner and lead instructor of the comedy school, Shana (black female), a former student and
        working comic, and Joe (white male), also a former student and working comic.</p>
      <p>I did not encounter any self-disclosed LGBT students, although the frequency with which
        male students and male instructors jokingly referred to each other as ‘gay, fag, cocksucker,
        and homo’ may have contributed to this fact. The environment was heavily hetero-male
        dominant in both numbers and content. The ease and frequency with which derisive sex and gay
        jokes were shared was in sharp contrast with the cautious and strategic way race jokes were
        made, demonstrating that race-based jokes were more difficult to perform in public. These
        and other observations contributed to my focus on racial discourse in this setting.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section8-0957926513482066">
      <title>Learning to make racism funny</title>
      <p>In contrast to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte (1987)</xref> and
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957926513482066">Berger’s (1993)</xref> assertion that
        performers can no longer engage in racial and ethnic humor in public about ‘groups other
        than themselves,’ the following observations illustrate how whites and non-whites are taught
        to engage in racial discourse in comedy in the current color-blind era.</p>
      <p>The discursive structures and strategies I observed were typically taught and employed to
        perform race as a way to entertain a live audience rather than offend them. These strategies
        were different from those described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva (2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">2010</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and
          Forman (2000)</xref>, and others who have studied strategic public racetalk. They are
        different in that individuals are not on the <italic>defensive</italic>; that is, managing
        impressions by using coded language while being interviewed about racial attitudes to save
        face. On the contrary, these students are on the <italic>offensive</italic>; that is,
        learning to use strategies to make overt racial statements publically entertaining and
        acceptable, rather than objectionable and offensive. More importantly, however, is how white
        and non-white students were taught to engage in racial discourse in different ways. While
        whites were reminded to tread through racetalk carefully, non-whites were often encouraged
        to embrace racial stereotypes uncritically.</p>
      <p>Performing racial stereotypes required successful execution of performance strategies which
        typically reflected the position in the ‘racial hierarchy’ of the performer. The general
        pattern was the lower on the racial hierarchy, the less elaborate the strategies, while the
        higher on the hierarchy, the more intricate. That is, racetalk was easier for non-whites,
        and more difficult for whites. The result is that whites and non-whites learn to perform
        racial stereotypes in public in an ostensibly post-racial and color-blind society.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section9-0957926513482066">
      <title>Managing white racial discourse</title>
      <sec id="section10-0957926513482066">
        <title>The ‘hurtline’ metaphor</title>
        <p>One of the ways in which instructors emphasized their authority in the school was by
          managing racial discourse, of whites in particular, through the ‘hurtline’
            <italic>metaphor</italic>. The hurtline is crossed when a performer oversteps the
          boundaries of acceptable public racial discourse (from funny to offensive), is understood
          as hurtful to the targets, and there is a disruption of normative racetalk. More
          importantly, in this context, crossing the ‘hurtline’ is costly in terms of laughs.</p>
        <p>Given the difficulty for whites in engaging in racial discourse more generally, it was
          understood, although not openly discussed, that white students had more constraints in
          comedy, as opposed to non-whites. As lead instructor Ted mentioned to me one evening
          following a student’s poor performance in front of a live audience at the comedy club: <disp-quote>
            <p>(1) The hardest people for me to make funny … white boys. They have less to work
              with.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Ted’s job, as he puts it, is to ‘make people funny.’ When failing to do so, he risks not
          only his promise that ‘anyone can learn to be funny,’ but also the wrath of tuition-paying
          students who do not get a return (laughs) on their investment. By suggesting that ‘white
          boys’ have it more difficult because they have ‘less to work with’ (such as the inability
          to freely engage in racial discourse), Ted is <italic>generalizing disadvantage</italic>
          and implying that white comedy students are more difficult to make funny due to their
          ‘constraints’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte, 1987</xref>) on
          certain kinds of discourse. Rather than suggesting that the student’s poor performance may
          in part be due to any number of factors (bad jokes, poor delivery, tough audience, etc.),
          the overestimation that white students are not funny because they have less material to
          work with is a common trope used by whites beyond the comedy school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva and Forman, 2000</xref>).</p>
        <p>The ‘hurtline’ metaphor was often conveyed to students following unsuccessful
          performances in which inappropriate or offensive discourse was performed. Ted reinforced
          this idea following an incident in which he crossed the ‘hurtline.’ At the comedy club one
          evening Ted was on stage introducing Shana, the black female instructor, as the emcee for
          the night. As Shana approached the stage, she extended her arm forward with a closed fist
          to greet Ted. Failing to reciprocate the greeting, Ted gave her a blank stare and then one
          to the audience and said dryly: <disp-quote>
            <p>(2) Sorry … I’m not a negro!</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>The audience responded with a few scattered chuckles. The intended joke was the
          incongruity between Ted, an old white male, being unfamiliar or uncomfortable with
          ‘bumping fists’ because that was a ‘black thing.’ James (white male, late 20s), one of the
          performers that night, told Ted in class the following week that his friends in the
          audience (mostly white) did not know how to react to that joke and it made some of them
          uncomfortable. Ted used this as a teachable moment to reemphasize the ‘hurtline’ metaphor: <disp-quote>
            <p>(3) Yea … I crossed the <bold>hurtline</bold> … that’s what happens.</p>
            <p>(4) You are likely to get in trouble when you talk about a <bold>group you don’t
                represent</bold>.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>This incident reinforced how students, whites in particular, find it difficult to engage
          in racial discourse freely, even in this context. Thereafter, Ted reiterated the
            <italic>racial common sense</italic> strategy – that is, acknowledging the pitfalls of
          engaging in discourse ‘about a group you don’t represent.’ Members higher in the racial
          hierarchy freely mocking those lower goes against current racial common sense by crossing
          the norms of polite racial discourse. While crossing the ‘hurtline’ was suggested at
          face-value as overstepping any form of disrespectful discourse, it was generally
          understood as a euphemism or metaphor for racism.</p>
        <p>This observation is more apparent when compared to other incidents regarding hurtful
          discourse. Jessie (white female, mid-20s), for instance, was developing a joke about
          dating a gay magician: <disp-quote>
            <p>(5) I thought he was straight … but it was a trick … he sure fooled me.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Ted suggested she make him: <disp-quote>
            <p>(6) [A]s gay as possible … make him dance around more … have him flaming.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>White students engaging in racial discourse were never encouraged to amplify racial
          stereotypes in my observations. Yet sex, gender, and sexuality were not only discussed
          more freely and openly when compared to racial discourse, but often in highly
          stereotypical ways. The ‘hurtline’ metaphor, therefore, was mostly reserved for managing
          the racial discourse of white students in particular.</p>
        <p>However, while the ‘hurtline’ metaphor implied that racism would not be tolerated in this
          context, it was often suggested that the best performances invoked potentially offensive
          discourse. According to Ted: <disp-quote>
            <p>(7) Being ‘edgy’ … you want to be able to get just close enough to that hurtline …
              without crossing it.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>This contradiction between being told not to cross the ‘hurtline’ while suggesting that
          the most innovative performers summon offensive discourse was resolved by emphasizing the
          benefits of attending this school. The instructors routinely noted that students could
          develop and improve their skills by attending the school (and paying tuition) at a faster
          rate than ‘hitting the open mics’ (amateur shows open to the public often held in bars or
          comedy clubs), often alluding to the comedy school as a ‘trade school’ where students
          could perfect their craft. As illustrated in the following text, one of the skills
          students were taught was <italic>how</italic> to approach racial discourse in this
          context. Such notions reinforced the authority of the school and instructors as comedy
          experts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section11-0957926513482066">
        <title>Avoiding overt ridicule</title>
        <p>One of the main functions of the ‘hurtline’ metaphor was to ensure students did not
          engage in overt ridicule of non-whites in particular, especially in cases where other
          strategies were absent (e.g. self-deprecation, distancing). Such carefree racial discourse
          on the part of white students would be too reminiscent of earlier periods of racial
          inequality. This kind of engagement would also undermine the ‘hurtline’ metaphor and the
          credibility and reputation of the instructors and school. Therefore, during these
          incidents Ted would stress that such performances are problematic.</p>
        <p>On one occasion, Bob (white male, mid-60s) was developing a joke in class about the
          increasing use of technology in his workplace: <disp-quote>
            <p>(8) Man, these <bold>Chinese</bold> IT guys I tell yah … (mocks the Chinese language)
                <bold>‘ching ching chong’</bold> … they think they can do everything with computers
              (scattered laughs). I want to see you use your computers to walk through the sewer
              mains (scattered laughs).</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Ted (shaking his head) concluded this was inappropriate racial discourse: <disp-quote>
            <p>(9) <bold>Don’t</bold> make it an Asian … <bold>it can be racist</bold>.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Using pragmatic (asserting racism) and interactive (shaking head, withholding laughter)
          discursive strategies, Ted concludes that this joke ‘can be racist’ and reminded students
          to be aware of the ‘hurtline.’ Ted suggested Bob should disengage from racial discourse.
          Bob agreed and dropped the joke from his set. This incident illustrates how Ted’s role as
          instructor can shape how white students in particular are prevented from engaging in overt
          ridicule of non-whites. From a post-racial perspective, this might seem like a good thing.
          While this incident implies that jokes that ‘can be racist’ would not be tolerated, this
          in fact is not the case as illustrated later. Managing white racial discourse, therefore,
          was not intended to prevent white students from engaging in racial commentary, but to
          teach them how to do so strategically in more palatable terms.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section12-0957926513482066">
        <title>Negative self-presentation?</title>
        <p>While <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk (1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-0957926513482066">1995b)</xref> suggests that dominance is
          generally maintained through positive self-presentation (omitting negative characteristics
          of one’s group) and negative other-presentation (highlighting the perceived negatives of
          the ‘other’), in this context students were often required to engage in <italic>negative
            self-presentation</italic>, or self-deprecation, before engaging in negative
          other-presentation. By mocking self or group, culture, background, etc., this rhetorical
          performance strategy allowed the performer to save face while ‘taking one to the chin.’ As
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957926513482066">Carter (1989)</xref> suggests: <disp-quote>
            <p>(10) An audience needs to feel a sense of fair play … a little self-deprecating humor
              makes you seem fallible to the audience and makes them feel more comfortable. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957926513482066">Carter, 1989</xref>: 91)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>This recent sense of ‘fair play’ with regards to racist jokes in public can be attributed
          to changes in race relations and racial discourse in public since the civil rights era.
          White engagement in negative self-presentation, therefore, reflects the notion that overt
          white supremacy and superiority has been apparently delegitimized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">2010</xref>). For instance, following Bob’s Chinese IT guy
          joke above, Ted explained: <disp-quote>
            <p>(11) Opening the show with racial stuff makes audiences uneasy … especially when it’s
              not a group you represent … find one of your buddies to be an IT guy instead of an
              Asian.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Bob, in mocking a group he did not represent, risked being perceived as racist and
          offending an audience. By suggesting he make the target one of his ‘buddies,’ Ted implies
          ‘white males’ should be the target here, not ‘Asians.’ Note, however, that the instructor
          cautioned against ‘<bold>opening</bold> the show’ with racial material. As we will see
          further ahead, to do so later by incorporating strategies, such as negative
          self-presentation, was acceptable.</p>
        <p>The next example illustrates this point more explicitly. Drew (biracial Asian/white male,
          late 20s) was rehearsing his jokes, which dealt primarily with racial stereotypes of
          groups he did not belong to. He began with a series of black jokes. After his set, the
          instructor insisted: <disp-quote>
            <p>(12) I need you to <bold>take some shots at yourself</bold> before you go into your
              race material.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>The fact that his ‘race material’ incorporated banal racial stereotypes (blacks having
          lots of babies, being lazy, complaining too much) was not the issue according to Ted.
          Rather, the problem was that Drew had not ‘taken some shots at himself’ first. Ted
          reinforced the self-deprecation strategy by suggesting he begin by talking about being
          bi-racial. The following week he began with this joke: <disp-quote>
            <p>(13) So I’m half Jewish and half Japanese … or Jewpanese as I call it (class
              laughs).</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Negative self-presentation or self-deprecation, therefore, is a strategic variation of
          the positive self-presentation strategy and alleviates some of the tension of crossing the
          ‘hurtline’ and staving off accusations of racism. While a veil of fairness is produced,
          this strategy conveys to the audience that the performer can also ‘take a joke,’ thus
          allowing the performer to then negatively (re)present ‘others.’</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section13-0957926513482066">
        <title>Negative other-presentation</title>
        <p>Approaching the taboo is the realm of comedy. However, the balancing act between engaging
          in entertaining racial discourse in public and deflecting accusations of racism is not an
          easy one. Yet one consistent variable seems to be the use of self-deprecation as a way to
          engage in <italic>negative other-presentation</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957926513482066">Carter (2001)</xref> observes that this strategy often
          allows the performer to mock others: <disp-quote>
            <p>(14) Comics make fun of themselves so it gives them permission to make fun of the
              audience … If you’re Irish, you do Irish jokes. If you’re Jewish, you do Jewish jokes.
                (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957926513482066">Carter, 2001</xref>: 140)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>However, it is the use of negative other-presentation in discourse that reifies the
          boundaries of dominance and inequality between ‘Us’ and ‘Them’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1995a</xref>). Take the following performance by
          Mike at a showcase event at the comedy club one evening. Mike (white male, mid-20s) was a
          working comic and former student of Ted’s. Ted would often invite former students to
          participate in these events as examples of experienced performers who took his classes.
          During this performance, it was obvious Mike was a quick and skilled performer who
          employed different strategies to engage in racial discourse with ease. Through his
          sustained use of the negative self-presentation strategy, he was able to use multiple
          racial/ethnic stereotypes repeatedly in his set.</p>
        <p>The previous performer, Jessica (black female, late 30s), mocked her former lover and the
          inadequate size of his penis. Following Jessica, Mike incorporated her joke into his
          opening act: <disp-quote>
            <p>(15) Thanks, Jessica, for letting everyone know I have a small penis (audience
              laughs).</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Mike continued this negative self-presentation, mocking the size of his penis and his
          sexual insecurities, throughout his performance, while engaging in negative
          other-presentation repeatedly: <disp-quote>
            <p>(16) Anyone watching the Super Bowl … so I’m doing the fantasy football thing this
              year … not because I’m into the player stats … I just wanted to know what it felt like
              to <bold>own a group of black guys</bold> (mixture of laughs, cheers, oohh’s and
              applause).</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>By engaging in negative self-presentation, Mike was able to push the ‘hurtline’ further
          away and brush up against it with ease. His jokes were well received by the audience and
          his performance was one of the most successful of the night – meaning he received many
          laughs during his set compared to other performers. Mike comforted the audience by
          acknowledging the racial hierarchy: <disp-quote>
            <p>(17) I know … white people have done a lot of fucked up things.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Through the <italic>apparent empathy</italic> semantic move, by speaking briefly of the
          horrors of slavery and the genocide of Native Americans by whites, Mike recognized the
          significance of racism. He continued to deprecate white people while relying on apparent
          empathy to side with the victims of racism, thus giving the impression that he was only
          ‘playing with racism’ and therefore not a racist. Mike was able to joke about other groups
          he did not belong to, while avoiding audience discomfort and diffusing accusations of
          racism by producing a veil of fairness through his <italic>authentic
            inauthenticity.</italic> He then quickly turned to more racial stereotypes, which the
          audience readily enjoyed: <disp-quote>
            <p>(18) Can you imagine if <bold>Jews</bold> had a football team … what would their
              mascot be … a guy holding a <bold>bag full of money</bold>? (audience laughs).</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Mike employed the negative self-presentation strategy, taught in the school, as a way to
          exploit his racist jokes in a way that generated laughter and approval rather than
          offense. Indeed, the audience response to his racist jokes may be a form of Freudian
          tension release, as others have suggested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957926513482066">Abrahams and Dundes, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0957926513482066">Morreall, 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0957926513482066">2009</xref>). More importantly, however, I argue that
          strategic use of such material in public discourse is more likely to produce ‘laughs’
          rather than the material itself, signaling a shift in racial comedic discourse where overt
          and sustained racist ridicule is no longer allowed. The end result is the maintenance and
          (re)production of a racist discourse which relies on conventional ethnic and racial
          stereotypes, while veiled through humor and performance strategies, which is disavowed in
          most other public contexts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section14-0957926513482066">
        <title>Creating distance and denying racism</title>
        <p>Successful performances which relied on ethnic and racial stereotypes often involved
          successfully employing distancing and denial techniques. These not only save face, but
          distance and shield the performer from the content as well, much like the ‘burnt cork’
          used by performers in blackface. Students were also encouraged to use other strategies,
          such as ‘character development’ or ‘disclaimers,’ in their performance to distance and
          deflect audience tension. Again, Carter suggests to: <disp-quote>
            <p>(19) [perform] characters … as if doing a scene in a play. An imaginary wall comes
              between [you] and the audience. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957926513482066">Carter, 1989</xref>: 95)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Students learned that it was safer to engage in racial discourse in character than in
          person. Dave (white male, late 20s), for instance, was encouraged to use
            <italic>phonological distancing</italic> to avoid the issue Bob faced when mocking
          Chinese incoherently. As Ted put it while telling Bob his Chinese joke was problematic: <disp-quote>
            <p>(20) If you could do a great impression then you could <bold>get away with it</bold>
              because you are being a ‘<bold>dialectician</bold>.’</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>By Ted suggesting Dave is a skilled ‘dialectician’ in comparison to Bob, Ted uses
            <italic>positive lexicalization</italic> to ease Dave’s anxiety about racial discourse
          and as a way to legitimize his symbolic power over the students. Because Dave was skilled
          at mimicking ethnic and racial dialects, Ted suggested he could perform racial material
          successfully: <disp-quote>
            <p>(21) Dave doing <bold>Japanese characters</bold> is ok because he can do the
                <bold>accent</bold> and <bold>mimic</bold> the <bold>dialect</bold> well.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Dave, however, previously noted his discomfort with racetalk in his performances for
          ‘ethical reasons.’ Nonetheless, Ted encouraged him by suggesting: <disp-quote>
            <p>(22) Look … <bold>you are not being racist</bold> … you are explaining your
                <bold>cultural ignorance</bold>.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Ted attempted to address Dave’s concern about ‘coming off as racist,’ as Bob did with his
          Chinese jokes, by <italic>denying racism</italic> in Dave’s performance. Ted absolved Dave
          from engaging in racist discourse by removing the constraints and suggesting he is merely
          explaining his ‘cultural ignorance,’ which eased some of Dave’s anxieties and increased
          his comfort with performing racial material in both class and the comedy club. Dave, who
          worked as a teacher, was developing a joke where he discussed dealing with his
          international students and their homework excuses: <disp-quote>
            <p>(23) (In a stereotypical Asian accent) Teachah … ahhh … I soo soly bout homewok …
              ahhh my dog ate my homewok … and ahhh … I ate my dog (audience laughs).</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Dave’s abilities as a ‘dialectician,’ according to Ted, would allow him to perform Asian
          stereotypes (Asians are dog eaters, with poor language abilities) successfully by creating
          distance between Dave and the audience, whereas Bob mocking Chinese incoherently would
          appear racist. Positive lexicalization and the denial of racism were used by Ted to
          persuade Dave to engage in racial discourse. While Dave’s ability to mimic racial dialects
          helped him distance the content of the joke (Asian stereotypes) from Dave the ‘white guy,’
          Dave was cajoled by Ted despite his reluctance to engage in racial discourse early on,
          illustrating the role of the instructor in managing white racial discourse.</p>
        <p>The result: Dave’s impression was perceived as clever and funny, while Bob’s incoherent
          gibberish was perceived as crude and offensive. This reinforced the <italic>authentic
            inauthenticity</italic> of Dave’s performance as ‘playing with racism’ while Bob is
          ‘being racist,’ thus denying racism in Dave’s performance. At the comedy club, the joke
          was so successful Dave believed it was the biggest laugh in his set that evening: <disp-quote>
            <p>(24) Ahhh! . . . I knew this joke was gonna work … and I knew I just had to get to
              it.</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Dave went from ‘not doing racial stuff for ethical reasons’ to performing Asian
          stereotypes in public in a matter of weeks. This example illustrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0957926513482066">Van Dijk’s (1993a)</xref> point about the role elites play
          in the reproduction of racism in public despite a veiled language of tolerance, much like
          the ‘hurtline’ discourse in this context.</p>
        <p>These kinds of distance and denial rituals in comedy conform to racial discourse
          strategies more generally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957926513482066">Augoustinos
            and Every, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0957926513482066">Coates,
            2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk, 1992</xref>).
          As suggested by Van Dijk and others, they are intended to save face, for whites in
          particular, against accusations of racism – not by refraining from racial discourse, as
          others suggest, but by learning to perform overt racial discourse strategically. These
          examples demonstrate the challenges white students face with respect to racial discourse
          and how Ted managed such discourse in this space. While negative self-presentation also
          allows non-whites to talk about race, as illustrated next, distance and denial mechanisms
          were most often encouraged and used by white students as a way of redirecting audience
          tension and discomfort with public racial discourse by asserting an <italic>authentic
            inauthenticity</italic> frame in their performances.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section15-0957926513482066">
      <title>Managing non-white racial discourse</title>
      <p>While white students grappled with the ‘hurtline,’ non-white students often received the
        opposite lesson from the instructors. Not only were non-white students allowed to engage in
        racial discourse more freely, as opposed to white students, they were often encouraged to do
        so in ways that reproduced racial stereotypes. In contrast to the potential
        inappropriateness or offensiveness when whites performed racial material, non-white student
        engagement in racial discourse was not typically viewed as crossing the ‘hurtline.’ At most,
        that line was much further away.</p>
      <p>For example, Drew (biracial Asian/white male, late 20s) was advised by Joe (white male,
        assistant instructor) on how to improve his Asian jokes: <disp-quote>
          <p>(25) I want you to sound <bold>more Asian</bold>.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>Comparing this incident to the previous ones where Bob mocks Chinese incoherently or Dave
        is encouraged to use his ‘dialectician’ skills to mimic his Asian students, the overarching
        message conveyed to students is a double standard when it comes to engaging in racial
        discourse. Because Drew ‘looked’ more Asian than white, he was encouraged to stereotypically
        mock Asians by sounding ‘more Asian.’ Drew was granted <italic>phonological freedom</italic>
        because his ‘Asian-ness’ was more salient than his ‘whiteness,’ from the point of view of
        the instructor, and was directed toward Asian stereotypes. This incident was starkly
        different from Bob’s Chinese jokes, where Bob was advised to abandon them, and Drew did not
        need special phonological skills such as the ability to mimic racial dialects to distance
        his stereotypical Asian accent.</p>
      <p>While non-white students were granted more freedom to engage in racial discourse, they were
        also reminded to engage in negative self-presentation, which again was often directed at
        reproducing racial stereotypes. Joseph (Latino male, mid-20s), for instance, was encouraged
        in class to use stereotypes about Mexicans and Latinos by the instructor. As Ted suggested: <disp-quote>
          <p>(26) <bold>You can</bold> make fun of them [Mexicans] … <bold>but I can’t</bold> make
            fun of them because it makes me seem racist.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>Ted denies racism by implying that non-whites who engage in self-deprecation cannot be
        racist despite engaging in hegemonic race humor. While Dave’s engagement in racetalk was
        seen as expressing ‘cultural ignorance,’ Joseph was encouraged to ‘make fun of them.’ More
        important is how the instructors used their authority in this context to encourage non-white
        students to engage in stereotypical racial discourse about groups ‘they <italic>do</italic>
        belong to.’</p>
      <p>Thereafter, non-white students were reminded to engage in negative-other presentation, but
        to a greater degree. Ted entices Joseph: <disp-quote>
          <p>(27) Now … if you’re going to get <bold>racist</bold> let’s go <bold>all the
            way</bold>.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>This suggestion of ‘going all the way’ with racist jokes was never suggested to white
        students, even when stressing the use of other strategies. Again, this reflects how the
        strategies are taught differently to individuals in different positions in the racial
        hierarchy. Joseph talked about growing up as a Mexican-American but was often confused for
        being Filipino: <disp-quote>
          <p>(28) So I get confused for being <bold>Filipino</bold> sometimes … some Filipino guy
            comes up to me and starts talking (audience laughs) … I have no idea what he’s saying …
            it sounds so <bold>chicken cluckish</bold> to me (audience laughs) … all I hear is
              ‘<bold>cluck cluck cluck</bold>’ (audience laughs).</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>Joseph’s Filipino joke was similar to Bob’s Chinese joke. Both disparaged the language of a
        group ‘they did not belong to.’ Joseph made no effort and was not told to engage
        phonological distancing. Joseph was not advised to drop this joke, but rather to ‘go all the
        way’ with his racist jokes. Since Joseph’s joke was not seen as problematic, again Ted
        denies racism in this performance despite how closely it resembles Bob’s joke, which was
        interpreted as racist. By Ted allowing non-whites to freely engage in overt racial
        discourse, it reinforces his notion earlier that ‘white boys have less to work with.’ These
        kinds of interactions between non-white students and the instructors illustrate the kind of
        symbolic power the instructors, Ted in particular, had over students in legitimizing racial
        discourse in their performances. They also demonstrate how racial discourse was managed
        differently between white and non-white students.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section16-0957926513482066">
      <title>Resistance</title>
      <p>The general message for students seemed to be that reproducing stereotypical racist imagery
        was tolerable when (1) performed strategically by creating distance and denying racism; (2)
        performed by a ‘perceived’ member of that group, even when deliberately misrepresenting
        reality; and (3) it was funny. Although the instructors exerted much influence and power
        over student engagement in racial discourse, and most students followed this script
        accordingly, performers also illustrated moments of resistance to the reproduction of
        stereotypical racial discourse in this context. More passive forms of resistance took the
        form of withholding laughter, students wriggling in their seats, making eye contact with
        friends, avoiding eye contact with the performer, and occasional vocalizations from students
        and audience members. Few occasions offered more open forms of resistance.</p>
      <p>In one instance, Jessica experienced tension when Ted suggested that in a joke about her
        mother she give her a black southern ‘mammy’ dialect. Jessica refused to portray the
        character of her mother in this way, despite various attempts by Ted to have her do
        otherwise: <disp-quote>
          <p>(29) I just think it would be <bold>funnier</bold> to do it this way.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>By suggesting that it would be ‘funnier to do it this way,’ Ted used his symbolic power as
        a comedy instructor to attempt to persuade Jessica to engage in a stereotypical portrayal of
        her character. Jessica looked bothered by Ted’s advice during class. I spoke with her later
        that evening, and she expressed her discontent: <disp-quote>
          <p>(30) Stereotypes just <bold>don’t reflect reality</bold> for me … like when Ted wanted
            me to give my mom a ‘black southern accent’ … you know the stereotype of a ‘big southern
            black woman’ … I don’t feel like I need to do that … <bold>that’s just not who she
              is</bold> … and I don’t want to go there.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>Jessica sees the limitations and problems of reproducing racial stereotypes and stresses
        that they are a misrepresentation of her lived experience. Despite various attempts by the
        instructor to have her do otherwise, Jessica stood her ground, omitted racial stereotypes in
        her jokes and proved to be a successful performer without them.</p>
      <p>While non-white performers could certainly be funny without engaging in racial stereotypes,
        Shana acknowledged the challenge non-white performers face: <disp-quote>
          <p>(31) I don’t want to be seen as a black comic … but as a comic who happens to be black
            … <bold>I want to get away</bold> from stereotypical black humor … I want to be a Bill
            Cosby black.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>By suggesting that she is often perceived as a ‘black comic,’ rather than one who ‘happens
        to be black,’ she implies that there is an expectation that she needs to engage in
        ‘stereotypical black humor.’ While acknowledging her desire to ‘get away’ from black
        stereotypes, the reality is that much of her act consisted of black stereotypes. As she puts
        it: <disp-quote>
          <p>(32) I try not to pull the race card <bold>but it works</bold> … I do it and it
            works.</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>This tension, therefore, between performing to the audience’s ‘expectations’ from a
        performer of color and the desire to ‘get away’ from racial stereotypes is not one white
        performers have to face. This tension also challenges the notion that whites are
        ‘disadvantaged’ because they are unable to engage in racial discourse freely in comedy, when
        the freedom non-white performers have is to trade in racial stereotypes, whether or not the
        intention is to subvert or reinforce such notions.</p>
      <p>In comedy, stereotypes of all sorts reign supreme, not just racial ones. The instructors
        are reflecting, in the examples shown, on what they believe to be successful material and
        routines among non-whites in comedy more generally, namely the use of racial stereotypes.
        However, they also exercise symbolic power over the students. While these examples confirm
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0957926513482066">Van Dijk’s (1992)</xref> analysis of
        elite discourse in the reproduction of racism, they also demonstrate the tensions and
        resistance they produce as in the example of Jessica, though such examples were rare in my
        observations as students often followed the suggestions of the instructors.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section17-0957926513482066" sec-type="discussion|conclusions">
      <title>Discussion and conclusion</title>
      <p>This study challenges prominent scholarly views of how racism is communicated in the
        post-civil rights era: covert in the frontstage, overt in the backstage. It suggests that
        racism in stand-up comedy can be public and overt, but made palatable because the comic is
        typically not regarded as racist. This subterfuge is partly a result of the context and of
        engaging in ‘playful’ or ‘unserious’ discourse, but more important is the use of rhetorical
        performance strategies depicted here and <italic>how</italic> they safeguard and allow the
        performer to (re)produce a veil of <italic>authentic inauthenticity</italic> by using racial
        stereotypes in public under the guise of humor to deny literal claims.</p>
      <p>As biological and functionalist views of race have been increasingly delegitimized, those
        grounded in cultural affirmations continue to gain momentum and reaffirm the racial
        hierarchy in the post-racial and color-blind USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0957926513482066">Coates, 2008</xref>). These cultural differences and
        deficiencies are often fodder for comedy, which, I argue, currently plays an increasingly
        unique role in racial discourse. This study illustrates how individuals are taught to
        (re)present ‘others’ in public in a humorous and entertaining way, how race is performed in
        order to navigate the treacherous landscape of public racial discourse, and how the
        strategies depicted here are legitimated by authorities with symbolic power. Attention is
        focused on the way the instructors manage white and non-white racial discourse in the comedy
        school, as students learn to engage in public racial discourse in a color-blind society.
        Such racial discourse, which is ostensibly disavowed in public, often relies on
        stereotypical racial depictions and serves to reinforce racial ideologies and distinctions,
        despite intentions otherwise from both whites and non-whites.</p>
      <p>The liberating element of humor is generally taken to be a weapon used by traditionally
        oppressed groups (e.g. racial, ethnic, and gender minorities). ‘Ethnic humor,’ suggests
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957926513482066">Boskin (1979)</xref>, is often
        acknowledged for its ‘liberatory’ and ‘rebellious’ potential, where scholars note the humor
        of ‘Negros’ and ‘Jews’ as subversive acts against oppression. The prominent narrative of
        oppression in the post-civil rights period, however, is one where the dominant group feels
        oppressed. Legalized racial integration, the culture of political correctness which limits
        racial discourse by whites in particular, affirmative action policies that whites believe
        disadvantage more qualified whites in favor of less qualified ‘token’ minorities, all create
        a sense of unfairness and oppression for the ‘former oppressor.’ If indeed humor serves to
        liberate censured behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957926513482066">Bakhtin,
          1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0957926513482066">Eliasoph, 1998</xref>),
        we should expect more, not less, overt racial discourse through humor in the post-racial and
        color-blind eras.</p>
      <p>It is important, therefore, to pay close attention to the shifting racial discourse in the
        world of comedy as a critical site where a <italic>new racial discourse</italic> is tested
        and normalized. It may further be argued that such discourse is a preview of what is to come
        in a post-racial USA, where comedians are ‘ahead of their time.’ As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957926513482066">Bakhtin (1984)</xref> noted, ‘a carnival sense of the world’
        begins to permeate life outside the carnival. The rise of racial/racist humor in the
        color-blind era suggests a turn from prior decades where others have documented the
        constraints that limit whites in particular from engaging in racial humor freely in public
          (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957926513482066">Berger, 1993</xref>).</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0957926513482066">Stanley (2007)</xref> also observes the
        shift in comedic race discourse from one where ‘only non-white comics could get away with
        provocative material about blacks,’ to a discourse where ‘white comedians are increasingly
        testing the limits of taste and mock intolerance.’ Comedians Andrew Dice Clay and Ted
        Danson, for instance, faced public criticism for breaching norms of appropriate racial (and
        gender) discourse during the late 1980s and early 1990s. And while Michael Richards
        illustrates the persisting limits of white engagement in racial discourse in comedy, the
        color-blind era and the persistent attack against a culture of political correctness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0957926513482066">Eliasoph, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0957926513482066">Fairclough, 2003</xref>) appear to have ushered in a new
        racial discourse where (white) comedians, under the banner of free speech, are at the
        forefront of a more openly racial/racist public discourse. Comedians Daniel Tosh and Jeff
        Dunham, for example, are noted for ‘bravely’ venturing into a racist discourse that others
        avoid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0957926513482066">Hibberd, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0957926513482066">Mooallem, 2009</xref>). While more research
        is needed to support this hypothesis, one need only pay attention to the increasing trend in
        the use of humor and the <italic>carnivalesque</italic> to rupture the constraints of public
        racial discourse in the color-blind era (e.g. on college campuses, in the workplace, in
        politics, in various forms of media) to suggest this possibility.</p>
      <p>While <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0957926513482066">Stanley (2007)</xref>
        acknowledges the potential pitfalls of ‘defying political correctness’ as emboldening
        ‘genuine racists to join in the fun,’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957926513482066">Billig’s (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957926513482066">2005</xref>)
        study of racist humor among white supremacist organizations is such an example. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-0957926513482066">Weaver (2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-0957926513482066">2011</xref>) also contends that racist humor, as a
        rhetorical device, can support racist discourse, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0957926513482066">Santa Ana (2009)</xref> notes that racist jokes can impact
        on public perceptions of racial minorities, particularly when broadcast to millions of
        viewers regarding their perceived ‘threats.’</p>
      <p>In this sense, stand-up comedy is a ‘race-making institution.’ At the micro-level, Omi and
        Winant suggest that ‘racial projects’ are maintained in part through everyday common-sense
        assumptions about racialized others. In the everyday, stereotypes allow us to consciously
        and unconsciously ‘notice’ race (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0957926513482066">Omi and
          Winant, 1994</xref>: 59). The implication that people are laughing at stereotypes, which
        are the currency of comedy, may suggest that it is appropriate racial discourse, whether or
        not performers believe themselves to be engaging in stereotypical or subversive discourse.
        At the macro-level, scholars note that the ‘humor industry’ is a very profitable and
        increasingly influential venture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957926513482066">Apte,
          1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957926513482066">Boskin, 1979</xref>;
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0957926513482066">Gilbert, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0957926513482066">Santa Ana, 2009</xref>). Race-based comedy,
        therefore, preserves what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0957926513482066">Feagin
          (2010)</xref> calls the ‘white racial frame.’ That is, racism is not solely a question of
        individual prejudice, but of actors legitimizing racial hierarchies, reinforcing racial
        power structures, and reproducing racial ideologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0957926513482066">Feagin, 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0957926513482066">Van Dijk (1993a)</xref> reminds us that some actors have
        more power and influence than others.</p>
      <p>The point, however, is not only that peripheral ‘genuine racists’ might be emboldened
        through the mainstreaming of racist comedy, but that the unique and frequently unchallenged
        (re)production of racism <italic>through</italic> humor more generally fits within the
        larger logic of a shifting racial discourse in public. The implication of a more critical
        assessment of race-based humor, therefore, is not the enforcement of a politically correct
        discourse, but rather that it should ‘make the familiar strange’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0957926513482066">Mills, 1959</xref>) by pulling the veil and challenging
        commonly-held notions about the nature of such humor in society as ‘just a joke.’</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>I would like to thank the anonymous reviewers of this article and my advisors on the
        project, Francesca Polletta and David J Frank. I would also like to thank Ann Hironaka,
        Belinda Robnett-Olsen, David A Snow, Frank B Wilderson III, and Otto Santa Ana for their
        helpful comments on earlier drafts.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <label>Funding</label>
        <p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public,
          commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0957926513482066">
          <label>1.</label>
          <p>I borrow from Bonilla-Silva’s definition of racism as part of ‘the ideological
            structure of a social system that crystallizes racial notions and stereotypes’ which
            become ‘common sense’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957926513482066">Bonilla-Silva, 1997</xref>: 474).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0957926513482066">
          <label>2.</label>
          <p>The underrepresentation of women is reflected in the profession at large where stand-up
            comedy continues to be a male-dominated space. Humor scholar Mikita Brottman believes
            stand-up comedy to be a ‘world of male heterosexual machismo’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0957926513482066">Brottman, 2004</xref>: 114).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0957926513482066">
          <label>3.</label>
          <p>Participant names have been altered.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
    <bio xlink:type="simple">
      <title>Author biography</title>
      <p><bold>Raúl Pérez</bold> is a PhD candidate in Sociology at the University of California,
        Irvine and a research fellow at the University of California Center for New Racial Studies
        (UCCNRS). His dissertation research investigates the intersections of racial discourse and
        stand-up comedy in the USA from the civil rights era to the present.</p>
    </bio>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bibr1-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahams</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Dundes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>On elephantasy and
            elephanticide</article-title>. <source>The Psychoanalytic Review</source>
          <volume>56</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr2-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Apte</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Ethnic humor versus sense of humor: An
            American sociocultural dilemma</article-title>. <source>American Behavioral
            Scientist</source>
          <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr3-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Attardo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Irony as relevant
            inappropriateness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pragmatics</source>
          <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>826</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr4-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Augoustinos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Every</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Accusations and denials of racism:
            Managing moral accountability in public discourse</article-title>. <source>Discourse
            &amp; Society</source>
          <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr5-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhtin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <source>Rabelais and his World</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT
          Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr6-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhtin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Problems of Dostoevsky’s Poetics</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr7-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>An Anatomy of Humor</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction
            Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr8-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Billig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Humor and hatred: The racist jokes of
            the Ku Klux Klan</article-title>. <source>Discourse &amp; Society</source>
          <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr9-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Billig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comic racism and
            violence</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Locker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (eds) <source>Beyond a Joke: The Limits of Humour</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Basingstoke</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave
            Macmillan</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr10-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bobo</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Race in the American mind: From the
            Moynihan report to the Obama candidacy</article-title>. <source>ANNALS of the American
            Academy of Political and Social Science</source>
          <volume>621</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr11-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bobo</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Kluegel</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Laissez faire racism: The
            crystallization of a kinder, gentler antiblack ideology</article-title>. In:
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuch</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (eds) <source>Racial Attitudes in the 1990s: Continuity and
            Change</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>, pp.
          <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr12-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Rethinking racism: Toward a structural
            interpretation</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>
          <volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr13-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>White Supremacy and Racism in the Post-Civil
            Rights Era</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne
            Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr14-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The linguistics of a color blind
            society: How to talk nasty about Blacks without sounding ‘racist’</article-title>.
            <source>Critical Sociology</source>
          <volume>28</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr15-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Racism without Racists: Color-blind Racism and
            the Persistence of Racial Inequality in the United States</source>, <edition>3rd
            edn.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp;
            Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr16-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>‘I am not a racist but …’: Mapping
            White college students’ racial ideology in the USA</article-title>. <source>Discourse
            &amp; Society</source>
          <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr17-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Boskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>Humor and Social Change in Twentieth-century
            America</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Trustees of
            the Public Library of the City of Boston</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr18-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Boskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Sambo: The Rise and Demise of an American
            Jester</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford
            University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr19-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Boskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Ethnic humor: Subversion and
            survival</article-title>. <source>American Quarterly</source>
          <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr20-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Bourdieu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Social space and symbolic
            power</article-title>. <source>Sociological Theory</source>
          <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr21-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Brottman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Funny Peculiar: Gershon Legman and the
            Psychopathology of Humor</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>The Analytic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr22-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Burma</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1946</year>) <article-title>Humor as technique in race
            conflict</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>
          <volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>710</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr23-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Stand-up Comedy: The Book</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dell
          Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr24-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Comedy Bible: From Stand-up to Sitcom –
            The Comedy Writer’s Ultimate ‘How to’ Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>New
            York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fireside Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr25-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Clift</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Irony in conversation</article-title>.
            <source>Language in Society</source>
          <volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr26-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Covert racism in the US and
            globally</article-title>. <source>Sociology Compass</source>
          <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr27-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Ethnic jokes: An introduction to race
            and nationality</article-title>. <source>Teaching Sociology</source>
          <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr28-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Jokes and their Relation to Society</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mouton de
            Gruyter</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr29-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>The right to joke</source>. Research Report
          37. <publisher-name>The Social Affairs Unit</publisher-name>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://socialaffairsunit.org.uk/digipub/content/view/11/" xlink:type="simple">http://socialaffairsunit.org.uk/digipub/content/view/11/</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr30-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Jokes and Targets</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr31-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Doane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>What is racism? Racial discourse and
            racial politics</article-title>. <source>Critical Sociology</source>
          <volume>32</volume>(<issue>2–3</issue>): <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr32-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Dundes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>A study of ethnic slurs: The Jew and
            the Polack in the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal of American
            Folklore</source>
          <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr33-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Eliasoph</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Avoiding Politics: How Americans Produce
            Apathy in Everyday Life</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr34-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Fairclough</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Critical Discourse Analysis</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Addison-Wesley</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr35-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Fairclough</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>‘Political correctness’: The politics
            of culture and language</article-title>. <source>Discourse &amp; Society</source>
          <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr36-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Fanon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Racism and culture. In:</article-title>
          <source>Toward the African Revolution (Political Essays)</source> (trans. <person-group person-group-type="transed">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
          </person-group>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Grove
            Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr37-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Feagin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The continuing significance of race:
            Antiblack discrimination in public places</article-title>. <source>American Sociological
            Review</source>
          <volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr38-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Feagin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Racist America: Roots, Current Realities, and
            Future Reparations</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr39-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Feagin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The White Racial Frame: Centuries of Framing
            and Counter-framing</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr40-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Feagin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Batur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>White Racism: The Basics</source>,
            <edition>2nd edn.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr41-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Racial jokes spur apology from
            Friars</article-title>. <source>New York Times</source>, <day>10</day>
          <month>October</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/10/10/nyregion/racial-jokes-spur-apology-from-friars.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/1993/10/10/nyregion/racial-jokes-spur-apology-from-friars.html</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr42-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Effects of stereotypical television
            portrayals of African-Americans on person perception</article-title>. <source>Social
            Psychology Quarterly</source>
          <volume>60</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr43-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Discourse analysis: What makes it
            critical?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (ed.) <source>An Introduction to Critical Discourse Analysis in
            Education</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ and London</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>, pp.
            <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr44-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Performing Marginality: Humor, Gender, and
            Cultural Critique</source>. <publisher-loc>Detroit, MI</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Wayne State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr45-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Daniel Tosh at TCA: ‘I’m not sexist or
            racist, I just like the jokes.’</article-title>
          <source>Inside TV</source>, <day>5</day>
          <month>January</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://insidetv.ew.com/2011/01/05/daniel-tosh-defends-jokes/" xlink:type="simple">http://insidetv.ew.com/2011/01/05/daniel-tosh-defends-jokes/</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr46-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Everyday Language of White
          Racism</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr47-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Husband</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Racist humour and racist ideology in
            British television, or ‘I laughed till you cried’</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>GEC</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (eds) <source>Humour in Society: Resistance and Control</source>.
            <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>, pp.
            <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr48-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheatsley</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1956</year>) <article-title>Attitudes toward
            desegregation</article-title>. <source>Scientific American</source>
          <volume>195</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr49-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>‘Some of my best friends are black’:
            Interracial friendship and Whites’ racial attitudes</article-title>. <source>Public
            Opinion Quarterly</source>
          <volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr50-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The N-word and Richard
            Pryor</article-title>. <source>New York Times</source>, <day>15</day>
          <month>December</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/15/opinion/15iht-edjackson.html?_r=0" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/15/opinion/15iht-edjackson.html?_r=0</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr51-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dave Chappelle: ‘I wasn’t
            crazy.’</article-title>
          <source>The Associated Press</source>, <day>11</day>
          <month>February</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbsnews.com/2100-207_162-1281321.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cbsnews.com/2100-207_162-1281321.html</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr52-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipset</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>American Exceptionalism: A Double-edged
            Sword</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.W.
            Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr53-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Lockyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>You must be joking: The sociological
            critique of humour and comic media</article-title>. <source>Sociology Compass</source>
          <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr54-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Lofland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/>
          </person-group>. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Analyzing Social Settings: A Guide to
            Qualitative Observation and Analysis</source>, <edition>4th edn.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Toronto, ON</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Wadsworth/Thomas</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr55-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Theories of ethnic humor: How to enter
            laughing</article-title>. <source>American Quarterly</source>
          <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr56-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendelberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Executing Hortons: Racial crime in the
            1988 presidential campaign</article-title>. <source>Public Opinion Quarterly</source>
          <volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr57-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendelberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Race Card: Campaign Strategy, Implicit
            Messages and the Norm of Equality</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton,
          NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University
          Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr58-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendelberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Oleske</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Race and public
            deliberation</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source>
          <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr59-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comedian defends ‘Achmed the Dead
            Terrorist’ puppet routine against South African ban</article-title>. <source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Foxnews.com" xlink:type="simple">Foxnews.com</ext-link></source>,
            <day>2</day>
          <month>October</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,431866,00.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,431866,00.html</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr60-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1959</year>) <source>The Sociological Imagination</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr61-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Humor and ethnic stereotypes in
            vaudeville and burlesque</article-title>. <source>Melus</source>
          <volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr62-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Mooallem</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Comedy for dummies</article-title>.
            <source>New York Times</source>, <day>29</day>
          <month>October</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/01/magazine/01ventriloquist-t.html?pagewanted=all" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/01/magazine/01ventriloquist-t.html?pagewanted=all</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr63-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Morreall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Taking Laughter Seriously</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SUNY
          Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr64-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Morreall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Comic Relief: A Comprehensive Philosophy of
            Humor</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr65-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Racetalk: Racism Hiding in Plain
            Sight</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp;
            Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr66-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Race talk: The perpetuation of racism
            through private discourse</article-title>. <source>Race and Society</source>
          <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr67-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Omi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Winant</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Racial Formation in the United States: From
            the 1960s to the 1990s</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr68-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Oring</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Engaging Humor</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Champaign, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr69-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabbadon</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Chernin</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Naturalizing racial differences through
            Comedy: Asian, Black, and White views on racial stereotypes in Rush Hour
            2</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communications</source>
          <volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr70-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Picca</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Feagin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Two-faced Racism: Whites in the Backstage and
            Frontstage</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr71-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Raskin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>Semantic Mechanisms of Humor</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>D.
          Reidel</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr72-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Frame shifting in humor and
            irony</article-title>. <source>Metaphor and Symbol</source>
          <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr73-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Roediger</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Wages of Whiteness: Race and the Making of the
            American Working Class</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr74-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Santa Ana</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Did you call in Mexican? The racial
            politics of Jay Leno immigrant jokes</article-title>. <source>Language in
            Society</source>
          <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr75-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Saxton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Blackface minstrelsy, vernacular
            comics, and the politics of slavery in the north</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Roediger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Blatt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (eds) <source>The Meaning of Slavery in the North</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Garland
            Publishing</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr76-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Scarpetta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnolli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The interactional context of humor in
            stand-up comedy</article-title>. <source>Research on Language &amp; Social
            Interaction</source>
          <volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr77-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Sigelman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The contact hypothesis revisited:
            Black–White interaction and positive racial attitudes</article-title>. <source>Social
            Forces</source>
          <volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr78-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Slavin</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>School practices that improve race
            relations</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>
          <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr79-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Sniderman</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The Scar of Race</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr80-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Pushing their luck, sitcoms are playing
            with race cards</article-title>. <source>New York Times</source>, <day>14</day>
          <month>November</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/14/arts/television/14watc.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/14/arts/television/14watc.html</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr81-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Tannen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Conversational Style: Analyzing Talk among
            Friends</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford
            University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr82-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">TMZ Staff</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>‘Kramer’s’ racist tirade
            caught on tape</article-title>. <source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://TMZ.com" xlink:type="simple">TMZ.com</ext-link></source>, <day>20</day>
          <month>November</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tmz.com/2006/11/20/kramers-racist-tirade-caught-on-tape/#.T2PU_sUgfkU" xlink:type="simple">http://www.tmz.com/2006/11/20/kramers-racist-tirade-caught-on-tape/#.T2PU_sUgfkU</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr83-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Communicating Racism: Ethnic Prejudice in
            Thought and Talk</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr84-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Discourse and the denial of
            racism</article-title>. <source>Discourse &amp; Society</source>
          <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr85-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993a</year>) <source>Elite Discourse and Racism</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>:
          <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr86-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993b</year>) <article-title>Principles of critical discourse
            analysis</article-title>. <source>Discourse &amp; Society</source>
          <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr87-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1995a</year>) <article-title>Elite discourse and the reproduction
            of racism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Slayden</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Slayden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
          </person-group>(eds) <source>Hate Speech</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park,
            CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, pp.
            <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr88-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1995b</year>) <article-title>Ideological discourse
            analysis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ventola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Solin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (eds) <source>New Courant: Special Issue Interdisciplinary Approaches to
            Discourse Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Helsinki</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>English Department, University of Helsinki</publisher-name>, pp.
            <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr89-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Discourse and racism</article-title>.
            <source>A Companion to Racial and Ethnic Studies</source>, pp.
            <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr90-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Von Meistersinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Michael Richards speaks to David
            Letterman</article-title>. <source>Gothamist</source>, <day>21</day>
          <month>November</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gothamist.com/2006/11/21/michael_richard.php" xlink:type="simple">http://gothamist.com/2006/11/21/michael_richard.php</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr91-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2010a</year>) <article-title>Developing a rhetorical analysis of
            racist humor: Examining Black jokes on the Internet</article-title>. <source>Social
            Semiotics</source>
          <volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr92-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2010b</year>) <article-title>The ‘other’ laughs back: Humour and
            resistance in anti-racist comedy</article-title>. <source>Sociology</source>
          <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr93-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Jokes, rhetoric and embodied racism: A
            rhetorical discourse analysis of the logics of racist jokes on the
            Internet</article-title>. <source>Ethnicities</source>
          <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr94-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Wodak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The discourse-historical
            approach</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Wodak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (eds) <source>Methods of Critical Discourse Analysis</source>.
            <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, pp.
            <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr95-0957926513482066">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Wodak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Matouschek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>‘We are dealing with people whose
            origins one can clearly tell by just looking’: Critical discourse analysis and the study
            of neo-racism in contemporary Austria</article-title>. <source>Discourse &amp;
            Society</source>
          <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>