<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EXT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spext</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Expository Times</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0014-5246</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1745-5308</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0014524611426060a</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0014524611426060a</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Sermons for the Christian Year</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>12<sup>th</sup> February: Sixth Sunday after Epiphany: Mark 1: 40-45</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelavala</surname><given-names>Surekha</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0014524611426060">Pastor, Global Peace Lutheran Church, Frederick MD</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>123</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>180</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Making a Choice</p>
<p>“Oh! There he is. I have heard that Jesus healed many people, I also have heard that he is a man of compassion and a man of power. I believe, I know deep within me that he can. Shall I go and beg? No! Demand! After all I did not deserve this! Or, maybe I will say something completely different….” And so, he approaches Jesus and says, “Lord whatever you choose for my life, so be it”, trusting in Jesus that he will choose the best for him.</p>
<p>This thought came from the leper in our gospel story this morning. It is one of the most interesting passages of scripture because of what it has to offer for us today. The text says, “A leper came to him begging him, and kneeling, he said to him, “If you choose, you can make me clean.” Notice what he said. He said to the Lord, “Lord! If only you choose, you can do this for me.” He did not demand, and although his other communication says that he is pleading because he is on his knees while saying these words, he makes a statement that is alarming. He says, “If you choose, you can make me clean.” Normally, it is possible to ignore someone who is begging, or someone who is demanding, or someone who is annoying, but it’s just not possible to ignore someone who says, “If you choose, you can make the difference in my life.” That surely would make us stop and think. It is fact that Jesus has the ability to make the leper clean, now it is all about making a choice.</p>
<p>The leper is taking a chance with Jesus. Jesus could walk away as the scribes and Pharisees did, or cast stones at him, or taunt him like many people were accustomed to doing, but he knows that Jesus is different.</p>
<p>I met my friend last week and she shared with me her dilemma about whether or not to help her friend who came to her seeking for help. She has a childhood friend who is suffering from a strange disease that the doctors are unable to diagnose. It seems she is losing all her teeth at the age of 35, and has several other abnormal symptoms. This lady has called my friend to seek for help asking her to lend some money or give some support for her treatment. My friend told me that she is in a dilemma, not because she cannot help, not because she has no heart to help, not because the situation is not genuine but because she is not ready to take a risk. Second thoughts in her are warning about risk. She is worrying and thinking, if I gave her a big sum of money what if she cannot repay! A lot of times choices may be risky for us but helpful to others, they may be threatening to us but generous to others, they may be upsetting for us but fulfilling for others. A famous quotation goes, “Our philosophy is not best expressed in our words but in our choices.”</p>
<p>Let us see what Jesus chooses to do for the leper in the text. The text says that Jesus was moved with pity, stretched out his hand, and touched him, and said to him, “I do choose. Be made clean.” What a powerful statement! What a relief to the leper! The leper finally met a person who chooses the best for his life. It says in the text that immediately leprosy left him and he was made clean. Jesus didn’t forsake the man, when he was able, Jesus didn’t turn his back when he was needed, and Jesus didn’t ignore him when he was approached but was moved with pity and reached out to touch this man.</p>
<p>When we hear some sad story, or see someone suffering, no doubt, we too move with pity, feel sympathetic like Jesus did. But do we go as far as Jesus went to make that risky choice, which will put us in an altogether different status? Jesus was not afraid of what would people think if he touched a leper, he was not worried if he would be made unclean because of Jewish customs, nor was he horrified by being around the diseased, but he was moved with pity, stretched out his hand and touched a leper.</p>
<p>How many times are we so status conscious that we avoid giving a hug to someone in despair? How many times are we too conscious of our cleanliness that we refuse to touch someone in need? How many of us are so power conscious that we avert embracing our subordinates even when their hard work paid off and benefited us? Here is Jesus, a Rabbi; a clean Jew who has no second thoughts about touching someone who is unclean, a leper. Jesus could have simply said to the leper “be made clean” and it would have been so according to the other miracle stories in the Bible. But he touched the leper as a sign of acceptance, a sign of approval, a sign of comfort. May be it made a great difference in the life of the leper to be touched by Jesus. All along a leper only experienced people giving him disgusting looks, or people ignoring him because they did not want to have anything to do with this unclean, cursed being. Here is Jesus, putting balm on all that hurt he carried with his gentle touch, that made him clean, not just from leprosy but from the sadness and emptiness that he carried for years within him. How many of us are ready to stretch out our hand and do what is needed. A lot of times we extend our help to the people not really understanding their actual need. We do it because we need satisfaction. It takes much sensitivity to understand the need of a person beyond just the physical need.</p>
<p>Jesus’ touch affirms his sensitivity to the leper to think beyond his physical need. Let us think, how much are we caught up in our professions, in our routines that we can’t think in simple terms, understand the simple needs of people around us, and respond with simple logic. An on-call doctor’s wife, after being alone with her children days and nights, shared with her husband how difficult it is for her, and how depressed she gets these days and how she has no time for anything but parenting. Immediately, the husband’s response is to prescribe what drug would help if she gets depressed. As you can see, he has totally missed the point. He is a doctor, an intellectual, but someone who has no sensitivity to understand what actually is her need, and what he may do to help meet her need. We tend to give to others what we are accustomed to rather than what they really need. Jesus in this story chooses according to the immediate need of the leper. He does not waste time on what else could be the best solution. He is not afraid of risking his reputation by touching the leper if that is what would make the difference in his life. Are we ready to make such a choice?</p>
<p>Sometimes when people come for help we try to give them advice. We do not understand that a person in need must have looked into all possibilities, and came to us trusting that their need will be met here. If only we are in a position to meet the need of a person, is it possible to reach out and stretch out our hands as Jesus did? In a world where there are so many challenges and financial crises, are we abstaining from stretching our hands and instead closing our fists? Jesus challenges us to make a choice that is helpful. He gives us a model of stretching out with the gifts that we have rather than closing our fists. God bless these words! Amen.</p>
</body>
</article>