<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spijm</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Music Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0255-7614</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1744-795X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0255761411434824</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0255761411434824</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Orchestrating life skills: The effect of increased school-based music classes on children’s social competence and self-esteem</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rickard</surname><given-names>Nikki S.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0255761411434824">School of Psychology, Psychiatry &amp; Psychological Medicine, Monash University, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Appelman</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0255761411434824">School of Psychology and Psychiatry, Monash University, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-0255761411434824">School of Psychology and Psychiatry, Monash University, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>Fintan</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff4-0255761411434824">School of Music, Monash University, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>Anneliese</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff5-0255761411434824">School of Psychology and Psychiatry, Monash University, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bambrick</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff6-0255761411434824">School of Psychology and Psychiatry, Monash University, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0255761411434824">Nikki S. Rickard, Monash University, School of Psychology and Psychiatry, Melbourne, 3800, Australia. Email: <email>nikki.rickard@monash.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>292</fpage>
<lpage>309</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Society for Music Education: ISME</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Music training has been found to produce a range of cognitive benefits for young children, although well-controlled evaluation of the effects on psychosocial functioning has been limited. In this study participants were recruited from two grade levels (prep/grade 1, <italic>N</italic> = 210; grade 3, <italic>N</italic> = 149), and were allocated to a music education condition, or a control condition which continued to receive their usual curriculum. In the treatment condition, Kodaly music classes were introduced into the younger cohort’s curriculum, while the older cohort received additional instrumental classes which were predominantly strings-based. Results indicated that school-based music classes prevented a decline in global self-esteem measures experienced by the control group in both the younger and older cohorts, and in general and academic self-esteem for the older cohort. Preliminary data also suggest that a similarly engaging, arts-based activity (juggling) may confer similar benefits for older children’s self-esteem. While difficulties inherent in performing experimental research within schools prevent strong conclusions, the data imply that increasing the frequency and quality of arts-based activities can be beneficial for the self-esteem of primary school-aged children.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>group-based</kwd>
<kwd>Kodaly</kwd>
<kwd>music education</kwd>
<kwd>psychosocial functioning</kwd>
<kwd>school-based</kwd>
<kwd>string pedagogy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Learning to play a musical instrument requires the development of a range of skills such as disciplined practice, visual-motor ability, sustained attention and concentration, memory, motivation, coordination, emotional sensitivity and team work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0255761411434824">Hietolahti-Ansten &amp; Kalliopuska, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0255761411434824">Hurwitz, Wolff, Bortnick, &amp; Kokas, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0255761411434824">Orsmond &amp; Miller, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0255761411434824">Rauscher &amp; Zupan, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0255761411434824">Schellenberg, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0255761411434824">Shore &amp; Strasser, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0255761411434824">Warner, 1999</xref>). Music training may also ‘enrich’ the brain, as evidenced by studies which show that children who have actively engaged in music training display enhanced cortical volume in a range of auditory, somatosensory, motor and visual spatial brain regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0255761411434824">Gaser &amp; Schlaug, 2003</xref>) as well as a thicker corpus callosum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0255761411434824">Schlaug, Jäncke, Huang, Staiger, &amp; Steinmetz, 1995</xref>). Musically trained participants also demonstrate more efficient processing by auditory neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0255761411434824">Pantev et al., 1998</xref>) and enhanced cortical representation of somatosensory areas relating to their instrument, each of which is more pronounced in musicians who began their training at an early age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0255761411434824">Elbert, Pantev, Wienbruch, Rockstroh, &amp; Taub, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0255761411434824">Schlaug et al., 1995</xref>). Given the significant range of abilities and experiences associated with music training, it is not surprising that the benefits of music training might extend to non-musical domains such as intelligence, memory, learning, and self-esteem.</p>
<p>The majority of research investigating the collateral benefits of music training has focused on gains in intelligence and academic performance. Music training can enhance mathematical performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0255761411434824">Cheek &amp; Smith, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0255761411434824">Gardiner, Fox, Knowles, &amp; Jeffrey, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0255761411434824">Graziano, Peterson, &amp; Shaw, 1999</xref>), literacy skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0255761411434824">Butzlaff, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0255761411434824">Hurwitz et al., 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0255761411434824">Standley &amp; Hughes, 1997</xref>), spatial-temporal performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0255761411434824">Graziano et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0255761411434824">Rauscher &amp; Zupan, 2000</xref>), general intelligence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0255761411434824">Schellenberg, 2004</xref>) and verbal memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0255761411434824">Chan, Ho, &amp; Cheung, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0255761411434824">Ho, Cheung, &amp; Chan, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0255761411434824">Rickard, Vasquez, Murphy, Toukhasati, &amp; Gill, 2010</xref>). However, the impact of music training on the psychosocial aspects of human function, such as self-esteem and social skills, has received less empirical attention despite a long history of research interest in the potential benefits of music on self-esteem (see reviews in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi, 2004</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0255761411434824">Gill &amp; Rickard, 2012</xref>). Nonetheless, the inherent characteristics of music are ideally suited to the facilitation of these abilities. For instance, music: is generally perceived as non-threatening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0255761411434824">Trusty &amp; Oliva, 1994</xref>); promotes psychological development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0255761411434824">Duffy &amp; Fuller, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0255761411434824">Luftig, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0255761411434824">Salaman, Stefabo, &amp; Kim, 2002</xref>); has a natural appeal to children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0255761411434824">Shore &amp; Strasser, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0255761411434824">Trusty &amp; Oliva, 1994</xref>); and provides opportunities for children to feel good about themselves and build a sense of community in the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0255761411434824">Shore &amp; Strasser, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0255761411434824">Warner, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>There is a wealth of anecdotal evidence from music educators and therapists attesting to the value of music in enhancing pro-social behaviour and self-esteem. As an expressive form of art, music invites discovery and play. Music education also demands participation and group collaboration and, as such, is seen to be an effective medium for promoting social cohesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0255761411434824">Peretz, 2005</xref>) and for facilitating the development of social skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0255761411434824">Blandford &amp; Duarte, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>). Music classes are thought to promote trust (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0255761411434824">Camilleri, 2002</xref>) and to help children develop empathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0255761411434824">Levine, 1997</xref>) and respect and understanding of others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0255761411434824">Kim, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0255761411434824">Palmer, 2001</xref>). Playing music together can help children learn to cooperate effectively with each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0255761411434824">Palmer, 2001</xref>), inspiring them to develop ways to solve problems and to generate ideas collaboratively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0255761411434824">Sawyer, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Skills that assist with the development of social competence have also been reported to benefit from music instruction. Both listening skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0255761411434824">Kim, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0255761411434824">Sawyer, 1999</xref>) and the ability to concentrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0255761411434824">Camilleri, 2002</xref>) are thought to improve with music training. Music education may also help children in the development of self-control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0255761411434824">Kim, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0255761411434824">McClung, 2000</xref>) which is necessary for curbing impulsive and potentially disruptive behaviour in the classroom. Finally, playing music with others aids in the development of self-awareness and self-confidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0255761411434824">Cleave &amp; Dust, 1989</xref>), which may be important factors in initiating relationships with peers and developing self-esteem.</p>
<p>While observations such as these provide a valuable indication of the potential for music training to foster social competence and self-esteem, there is a lack of empirical-based research supporting the benefits outlined, especially for social skills. In fact only one study appears to have experimentally examined the relationship between music instruction and social functioning. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0255761411434824">Schellenberg (2004)</xref> measured adaptive and maladaptive behaviour using the parent rating scale of the Behavioural Assessment System for Children (BASC) and observed no improvements in either measure of behaviour for the groups receiving voice or keyboard lessons. In contrast, improvements in adaptive behaviour were reported for those students receiving drama lessons. While apparently inconsistent with previous non-experimental research, caution is advised in interpreting these findings for several reasons. First, the duration of the programme was relatively short term (36 weeks of lessons), and therefore may not reflect benefits that can arise following more persistent training and practice. Second, participation was restricted to children who possessed a full-sized keyboard with at least four octaves, and therefore the sample was likely to be narrower than the general student population, and potentially more socioeconomically advantaged.</p>
<p>Research on the effects of music training on self-esteem is also quite sparse. Studies focusing on the longer term effects (for instance, greater than one year) of music training have generally found a significant impact on global self-esteem. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0255761411434824">Luftig (1994)</xref> evaluated a four-year arts programme (which included music, drama and arts) whilst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi (1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0255761411434824">2004)</xref> measured the effects of formal piano lessons over a three-year period. Both researchers measured primary school children’s self-esteem at baseline and 12-month intervals for the duration of their respective programmes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi (2004)</xref> reported a significant increase in global self-esteem, in particular between years one and two, when compared with control groups. Luftig also found that students in his study experienced a significant increase in social self-esteem. These findings are consistent with correlational studies, for instance with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0255761411434824">Hietolahti-Ansten and Kalliopuska’s (1990)</xref> finding that young adolescents (mean age of 12) with an average of six years music training demonstrated higher global self-esteem than students who were not active in music.</p>
<p>Several studies have shown that shorter duration periods of music training are typically less effective, although there is some limited evidence that children with specialised needs may benefit from very brief training programmes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0255761411434824">Duffy &amp; Fuller, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>). In contrast, the short-term effects of music training on self-esteem in the normal student population have been found to be negligible. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0255761411434824">Zimmerman (2002)</xref> compared two groups of primary school children (4th and 5th graders) who participated in the school band over a period of nine months and reported no significant changes in self-concept from baseline to post-test. Similarly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0255761411434824">Legette (1994)</xref> found no significant differences in self-esteem between groups of grade 1, 2 and 4 students who participated in a specialised electronic keyboard programme over a period of four to eight months and those who did not. This suggests that, whilst there is some modest support for an effect of music training on self-esteem, potential benefits may require at least 12 months of music instruction to be realised. Furthermore, drawing strong conclusions from any of these studies is complicated by the fact that they are limited by methodological problems such as neglecting to use appropriate control groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0255761411434824">Zimmerman, 2002</xref>), failing to implement an additional control condition of an equally engaging non-musical activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi, 2004</xref>), drawing participants from pre-existing populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0255761411434824">Hietolahti-Ansten &amp; Kalliopuska, 1990</xref>) and using restricted age or socioeconomic groups which limits generalizability.</p>
<p>The urgent need for experimental research on the range of benefits of music education for children is highlighted in the recent National Review of School Music Education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0255761411434824">Pascoe et al., 2005</xref>). Music training, however, is not easily accessed, particularly by families in geographically or socially disadvantaged areas. The National Review of School Music Education recognised this limit and recommends access to music education be encouraged by increasing the frequency and quality of music education within Australian schools. Nevertheless, research on the benefits of music training which is <italic>embedded within</italic> the school curriculum and class groups is lacking. Given that the majority of previous research into the benefits of music has focused on private (one-to-one) rather than school- or classroom-based (group) music lessons, the aim of the current study was to experimentally investigate whether more accessible classroom music education could also generate such benefits for children’s self-esteem and social skills.</p>
<sec id="section1-0255761411434824" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section2-0255761411434824">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Participants were drawn from 10 primary schools in a regional shire in Victoria, Australia, clustered within 20km of the regional centre. All schools expressed an interest in participating in the full music programme although allocation to the new music training programme required an agreement from the school that they possessed or could contribute towards the purchase of necessary resources (such as instruments) for the programme. Allocation to the treatment groups was therefore not random, although the music programme and control group schools were similar at baseline on all demographics examined, including socioeconomic status and previous music lessons (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0255761411434824">Table 1</xref>). The gender breakdown differed for each analysis as a result of missing data, but in each instance, chi-square tests confirmed males and females were equally distributed across the treatment groups.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0255761411434824" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographic profile of music programme and control group samples.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0255761411434824" xlink:href="10.1177_0255761411434824-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Music programme</th>
<th align="left">Control</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Number of schools</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean students per school testing group</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Previous informal use of instruments<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0255761411434824">1</xref></sup></td>
<td>61%</td>
<td>54%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Previous formal music lessons<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0255761411434824">1</xref></sup></td>
<td>15%</td>
<td>16%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Socioeconomic status units (school)</td>
<td>0.46 (SD 0.06)</td>
<td>0.48 (SD 0.09)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Distance from regional centre</td>
<td>39.4km</td>
<td>42.9km</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Distance from local centre</td>
<td>8.4km</td>
<td>7.9km</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0255761411434824">
<label>1</label>
<p>Older cohort only (negligible in younger cohort).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Two cohorts of participants were recruited from each school: a younger cohort (prep/grade 1 at baseline) and an older cohort (grade 3 at baseline). Parental permission was originally obtained for 210 younger children (117 females, 93 males) and 149 older children (75 females, 74 males) to participate. Children were allocated to treatment or control groups based on the school they were attending. Movement of students from schools, absences during testing days and non-compliance on behalf of either students or teachers completing assessments resulted in considerable attrition across the duration of the study (three years). Nevertheless, missing data were fairly evenly distributed across the treatment and control conditions. The main analyses were performed on only those data sets which were complete across the three years, and the final sample sizes, as well as baseline (pre-test) data, for self-esteem and social skills measures are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref> (see also the Results section).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0255761411434824" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of music programme and control groups on age and dependent measures at baseline (pre-test).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0255761411434824" xlink:href="10.1177_0255761411434824-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Cohort and measure</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Music programme</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Control</th>
<th align="left">Significance of Difference</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">YOUNGER COHORT</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Self-esteem analyses</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline age</td>
<td>5.92</td>
<td>0.53</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>6.06</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>30</td>
<td><italic>t(94) = 1.11, p = .67</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline SE score</td>
<td>97.52</td>
<td>13.03</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>110.52</td>
<td>8.08</td>
<td>21</td>
<td><italic>t(58) = 4.86, p &lt; .001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0255761411434824">**</xref></italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social skills analyses</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline age</td>
<td>5.97</td>
<td/>
<td>100</td>
<td>6.13</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>58</td>
<td><italic>t(156) = 1.73, p = .09</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline SS scores</td>
<td/>
<td>0.54</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  SS</td>
<td>99.34</td>
<td>13.83</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>104.00</td>
<td>12.16</td>
<td>35</td>
<td><italic>t(92) = 1.61, p = .11</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  AC</td>
<td>94.13</td>
<td>11.93</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>101.63</td>
<td>13.96</td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>t(90) = 2.7, p = .008<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0255761411434824">**</xref></italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  PB</td>
<td>98.74</td>
<td>12.02</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>97.66</td>
<td>10.59</td>
<td>35</td>
<td><italic>t(92) = 0.56, p = .58</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">OLDER COHORT</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-esteem analyses</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline age</td>
<td>8.65</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>8.69</td>
<td>0.71</td>
<td>43</td>
<td><italic>t(97) = 0.30, p = .77</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline SE scores</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  GSe</td>
<td>99.08</td>
<td>14.96</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>100.41</td>
<td>15.15</td>
<td>34</td>
<td><italic>t(98) = 0.12, p = .91</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  ASe</td>
<td>10.06</td>
<td>2.37</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>11.24</td>
<td>2.17</td>
<td>37</td>
<td><italic>t(98) = 2.39, p = .019<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0255761411434824">**</xref></italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  GenSE</td>
<td>9.51</td>
<td>3.40</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>9.88</td>
<td>3.32</td>
<td>34</td>
<td><italic>t(98) = 0.04, p = .97</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  PSe</td>
<td>10.08</td>
<td>2.79</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>10.16</td>
<td>3.10</td>
<td>37</td>
<td><italic>t(98) = 0.53, p = .60</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  SSe</td>
<td>9.52</td>
<td>2.90</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>9.78</td>
<td>2.54</td>
<td>36</td>
<td><italic>t(98) = 0.48, p = .64</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social skills analyses</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline age</td>
<td>8.53</td>
<td>0.68</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>8.73</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>39</td>
<td><italic>t(65) = 1.38, p = .17</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Baseline SS scores</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  SS</td>
<td>104.83</td>
<td>15.68</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>109.41</td>
<td>16.81</td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>t(65) = 1.15, p = .25</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  AC</td>
<td>91.31</td>
<td>11.17</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>99.44</td>
<td>11.09</td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>t(65) = 2.98, p = .004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0255761411434824">**</xref></italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  PB</td>
<td>99.94</td>
<td>13.47</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>99.66</td>
<td>17.01</td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>t(65) = 0.77, p = .94</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0255761411434824">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: GSe = global self-esteem; ASe = academic self-esteem; GenSe = general self-esteem; PSe = parental self-esteem; SSe = social self-esteem; SS = social skills; AC = academic competence; PB = problem behaviour; * p &lt; .05; **p &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0255761411434824">
<title>Materials</title>
<p>A personal details form recording age, gender and participation in informal and formal music training was completed for each student. Self-esteem was assessed by two age-appropriate versions of the Culture-Free Self Esteem Inventory, third edition (CSFEI-3; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0255761411434824">Battle, 2002</xref>) whilst social skills were measured with the social skills rating system (SSRS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>). The CSFEI-3 is a self-report inventory used to determine the self-esteem levels of children and adolescents between 6–18 years, 11 months in a culturally fair manner. It can be individually or group administered requiring simple yes/no verbal or written responses. The primary response form (6–8yrs) assesses global self-esteem and consists of 29 statements such as: ‘Boys and girls like to play with me’ and ‘My family thinks I am important’. The intermediate response form (9–12 yrs) consists of 64 statements which assess self-esteem in four areas: academic, general, parental/home and social. Statements such as: ‘I usually take a long time to do my schoolwork’ measure individuals’ perceptions of their ability to perform academic tasks; ‘Most boys and girls are better at doing things than I am’, measure individuals’ overall perception of self worth; ‘I often feel left out of things at home’ measure individuals’ perceptions of how they fit in at home; and ‘Other kids think I have pretty good ideas’ measure individuals’ perceptions of anxiety and self-worth. In addition to the sub-scale measures, the CSFEI-3 intermediate form also yields a global self-esteem quotient (total score) ranging from <italic>very low self-esteem</italic> to <italic>very high self-esteem</italic>. Both forms also yield a defensiveness score (lie scale; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0255761411434824">Battle, 2002</xref>). The CFSEI-3 has been shown to be highly reliable with average internal consistency coefficients ranging from 0.81–0.93 and time sampling coefficients ranging from 0.72–0.98. It also correlates strongly with other measures of self-esteem and self-concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0255761411434824">Battle, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The SSRS assesses student social behaviours with three different behaviour rating forms (teacher, parent and student versions) that may be used separately or in combination to obtain a measure of social skills, problem behaviours and academic competence; the teacher form was used in the current study for its greater reliability. The teacher form elementary level (SSRS-teacher) was designed to assess primary school children ranging from grades K to 6 and consists of 57 items across the three scales; 30 items for social skills (e.g., ‘Controls temper in conflict situations with peers’), 18 items for problem behaviours (e.g., ‘Fights with others’), and nine items for academic competence (e.g., ‘In reading, how does this child compare with other students?’). Each of these scales measures various sub-domains of the associated behaviour. The social skills scale encompasses an assessment of cooperation, assertion and self-control. Externalizing problems, hyperactivity and internalizing problems comprise the problem behaviours scale whilst academic competence samples relevant behaviour such as student motivation, parental encouragement and performance in mathematics and reading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>).</p>
<p>Items on the social skills and problem behaviours scales are rated according to perceived frequency within the classroom with each item measured on a four-point scale ranging from 0 (<italic>never</italic>) to 3 (<italic>very often</italic>). Social skills items are also rated according to perceived importance for success within the classroom with each item measured on a four-point scale ranging from 0 (<italic>not important</italic>) to 3 (<italic>critical</italic>). Academic competence items are rated according to how the student compares with others in the same class with each item measured on a five-point scale ranging from 1 (<italic>lowest 10%</italic>) to 5 (<italic>highest 10%</italic>); (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>). The SSRS has been shown to have good internal consistency and test–retest reliability. Overall teacher forms are the most reliable with strong internal consistency coefficients (social skills 0.94; problem behaviours, 0.88; academic competence, 0.95) and test–retest correlations ranging from 0.84–0.93 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>). The SSRS has also been shown to have good construct validity (especially with the teacher and parent forms) with other measures of social skills and problem behaviours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0255761411434824">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Class teachers were invited to complete the SSRS for all participating students and the CFSEI-3 for the younger cohort. All consenting teachers received instruction on how to administer the questionnaires from the researchers prior to each testing session. Due to the potentially sensitive nature of some of the statements, the final decision to administer the CFSEI-3 primary form was left to the discretion of the class teacher. Both questionnaires were completed for the younger and older cohort at baseline (prior to intervention, or ‘pre-test’), and at approximately one year and two years post music intervention. In addition, a sub-group of the older cohort was again administered the CFSEI-3 at 2.5 yrs to determine the effects of an engaging and novel non-music intervention, juggling, introduced into one control school in the second year of the programme. All procedures for this study were approved by Monash University’s Human Research Ethics Committee.</p>
<p>Students completed the remaining questionnaires within one of their classes during morning break and lunch-time (avoiding the risk of fatigue in afternoon sessions). As this research formed part of a larger study (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0255761411434824">Rickard et al., 2010</xref>), the CFSEI-3 intermediate form was administered as part of a test battery (approximately 90 minutes duration) conducted in the following order: demographics, children’s memory scale (CMS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0255761411434824">Cohen, 1997</xref>) verbal learning and immediate recall, short break, Benton’s visual retention test (BVRT; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0255761411434824">Sivan, 1992</xref>) form C and D, CFSEI-3, short break, CMS delayed recall and delayed recognition, CMS digit span forward. At baseline (due to the young age of the participants) each statement was read aloud by the test administrator with sufficient time and instruction provided for the participants to respond appropriately. For all subsequent testing sessions the participants read each statement independently and completed all items in a non-speeded manner. Research assistants were present in the classroom to assist children to complete the questionnaires.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0255761411434824">
<title>Music programme intervention</title>
<p>Five schools received the music intervention which consisted of age-specific music programmes for the two age cohorts examined. Whilst these programmes were administered as part of the normal school curriculum (and required whole class participation) they did not replace the pre-existing, general school music programme and classes. Rather, they resulted in a net increase in the frequency of children’s exposure to music training. Children in the younger group received three 30-minute Kodaly music classes per week. The Kodaly method provides children with a sequential music curriculum based on established principles of early childhood development. Designed for children from kindergarten level to primary school, it places particular emphasis on singing, with children encouraged to learn the nursery rhymes and traditional folk songs of their homeland. Musical proficiency is developed through the use of the ‘moveable-do solfège’ system, the sounding of rhythm syllables and the use of Curwen hand signs (for a thorough explanation of these concepts, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0255761411434824">Choksy, 1974</xref>).</p>
<p>The older children participated in weekly (one-hour) group string instrumental classes taken by two qualified teachers, one leader and one assistant. The instruments were provided by the schools and each student was allocated to either violin, viola or cello. The mixed string groups ranged in size from 10–24 students with a typical class incorporating tuning, singing, rhythm training, basic music literacy skills, teacher demonstration and some small group and solo performances. The repertoire consisted of simple beginner level folk tunes with up to four parts. After an initial instrument familiarization period, students were permitted to take their instruments home to practice (although parental and teacher observations indicated that home practice was rare).</p>
<p>The four control schools did not receive these specialised music programmes but continued with their regular school music programme. However, additional group music (e.g., percussion ensemble) and vocal classes were offered to both control and experimental schools to ensure that all schools had the opportunity to benefit in some manner from this educational initiative.</p>
<p>In the second year, a structured juggling programme was introduced in one of the control schools to provide a preliminary assessment of whether the benefits from the music intervention were specific to the music programme or whether they could be due to the introduction of a novel arts based activity. These one-hour weekly classes were taken by experienced circus skill instructors and were also programmed into the school curriculum. A typical class included spinning, catching, throwing and passing plates, cascade scarves, 2–3 ball juggling, club and diabolo activities and poi patterns.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0255761411434824" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section7-0255761411434824">
<title>Self-esteem – younger cohort</title>
<p>In addition to missing data, two cases were omitted due to high defensiveness scores on the CFSEI-3, and one case was omitted due to being an outlier on age. In the remaining data set, the music group (mean age = 5.82 years, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.54) was found to be significantly younger at the baseline test time than the control group (mean age = 6.25, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.68, <italic>t</italic>(57.8) = 3.35, <italic>p</italic> = .001. The dataset was cleaned to yield two groups that were better matched on age by pseudo-randomly omitting 17 participants from the music group and five participants from the control group. The resulting groups were of equivalent mean age at baseline (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref>). While samples were of unequal size, the assumptions of homogeneity of variances (Levene’s test) and normally distributed self-esteem scores were met.</p>
<p>The groups differed at baseline with regard to self-esteem scores, with the control group showing higher mean self-esteem (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref>). Participants in the music group showed a substantial increase in global self-esteem scores from baseline to the first retest, while control participants showed a substantial decrease (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0255761411434824">Figure 1A</xref>). The groups, however, yielded very similar self-esteem scores at the second retest. A mixed-model analysis of variance (ANOVA) with schools nested within treatments was not significant, <italic>F</italic>(2,120) = 2.49, <italic>p</italic> = .087, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .040. Nevertheless, analyses performed on the baseline to first retest data only (which enhanced sample size as cases missing second retest data were not excluded) revealed the time × group interaction from baseline to first year test was significant, <italic>F</italic>(1,65) = 4.90, <italic>p</italic> = .030, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .070. Repeated measures post-hoc tests revealed that this was a result of a significant decrease in self-esteem from baseline to first year test in the control group (<italic>t</italic>[20] = 4.97, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) that was not observed in the music group (<italic>t</italic>[46] = 1.39, <italic>p</italic> = .173). No such interaction was observed from first to second retest.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0255761411434824" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Self-esteem score changes across two years for music programme and control groups (a) global self-esteem scores for younger and older cohorts and (b) self-esteem sub-scale scores for older cohort.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0255761411434824-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0255761411434824">
<title>Self-esteem – older cohort</title>
<p>In addition to missing data, one further case was omitted due to a high defensiveness score. The mean age of the music and control groups was not significantly different (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref>). The assumptions of homogeneity of variances (Levene’s test) and normally distributed self-esteem scores were met at baseline and year one for the majority of measures. Levene’s test revealed that the variances for all measures of self-esteem at year two were heterogenous, so caution was taken interpreting changes in the final year in these data. The groups were equivalent at baseline on each self-esteem sub-scale score except academic self-esteem, for which the control group showed a higher mean scores (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref>). As with the younger cohort, the control participants experienced a decline in several sub-scale measures of self-esteem across the first year that was not present for the music group participants. Separate mixed model ANOVAs with treatment nested within schools across three time points revealed significant time × group interactions for global self-esteem, <italic>F</italic>(2, 146) = 6.34, <italic>p</italic> = .002, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .083, as well as the general, <italic>F</italic>(2, 148) = 3.16, <italic>p</italic> = .045, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .041, and social CFSEI-3 sub-scales, <italic>F</italic>(2, 154) = 3.77, <italic>p</italic> = .025, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .047, and the parental CFSEI-3 sub-scale interaction approaching significance, <italic>F</italic>(2, 156) = 2.87, <italic>p</italic> = .060, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .036. Post-hoc analyses revealed that the global self-esteem interaction was due to both a significant interaction from baseline to first year test, <italic>F</italic>(1,91) = 6.38, <italic>p</italic> = .013, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .066 and a significant interaction from first year to second year test, <italic>F</italic>(1,73) = 11.90, <italic>p</italic> = .001, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .014. The general self-esteem interaction was also attributable to interactions from baseline to first year test, <italic>F</italic>(1,91) = 5.63, <italic>p</italic> = .020, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .058, and from first year to second year test, <italic>F</italic>(1,74) = 5.12, <italic>p</italic> = .027, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .065. The primary interaction in both global and general self-esteem scores was therefore attributable to a decline in self-esteem from baseline to year one in the control group that did not occur in the music group. In contrast, the increase from first to second year test was steeper for the control group than the music group. The parental self-esteem interaction was also attributable to changes at both time periods: baseline to first retest, <italic>F</italic>(1,91) = 4.21, <italic>p</italic> = .043, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .044, and from first to second year test, <italic>F</italic>(1,78) = 5.39, <italic>p</italic> = .023, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .065. While the music group’s scores increased more during the first year, the control group’s self-esteem scores increased more in the second year. In contrast, the social self-esteem interaction was attributable to changes from first to second year test only, <italic>F</italic>(1,77) = 5.24, <italic>p</italic> = .025, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .064; again this was due to a sharper increase in self-esteem scores for the control than music group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0255761411434824">
<title>Juggling</title>
<p>One school also participated in a preliminary evaluation of a juggling programme in the third year. This sample (<italic>n</italic> = 19) consisted of eight females and 11 males, and at this time point age ranged from 8 to 10.08 years (mean = 8.69, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.58).</p>
<p>Unfortunately the considerably smaller sample sizes, different age at onset of the programme and shorter duration of the juggling programme prevent inclusion of these data into the main analyses. However, the descriptive data (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0255761411434824">Figure 1</xref>) reveal that the juggling programme appeared to yield similar trends for the older children’s self-esteem as did the music programme. This pattern was evident for global self-esteem and all sub-scales.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0255761411434824">
<title>Social skills – younger and older cohorts</title>
<p>Cases with missing data were omitted prior to analyses from both the younger and older cohort datasets. There was no significant difference in mean age score across the music and control groups (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref>). The assumptions of homogeneity of variances (Levene’s test) and normally distributed social scores were met for each cohort. Social skills and problem behaviour scores for the groups were equivalent at baseline, although the control group exhibited a higher mean academic competence score in each cohort (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0255761411434824">Table 2</xref>). Social skills, problem behaviours and academic competence in the younger cohort were fairly constant across the duration of the study, and were similar across groups (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0255761411434824">Figure 2A</xref>). Mixed model ANOVAs with treatment nested within schools revealed no significant time × group effects across the three time points, or across any two time points. Similarly there appeared to be little effect of the music programme on social skills in the older cohort (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0255761411434824">Figure 2B</xref>). A mixed model ANOVA with treatment nested within schools across the three time points revealed some change in problem behaviours and academic competent-relevant social skills across time, but no time × group interaction. When analyses were performed for two years only, the time × group interaction approached significance for academic competence from baseline to first retest only, <italic>F</italic>(1,84) = 2.91, <italic>p</italic> = .092, ŋ<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup> = .034.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0255761411434824" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Social skill sub-scale scores changes across two years for music programme and control groups in (a) younger cohort and (b) older cohort.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0255761411434824-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0255761411434824" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The aim of the current study was to provide an experimental evaluation of the psychosocial benefits of increasing class-based music education in primary school children. Age-appropriate music programmes were introduced into a younger and older cohort of students in a cluster of primary schools in a rural region. Self-esteem and social skills were measured longitudinally in these students, as well as in control students who continued to receive their usual curriculum. The primary finding in this study was that the music programme yielded a number of benefits for both younger and older children’s self-esteem, although the effect sizes were generally modest and dissipated in the second year. A preliminary examination of an alternative arts-based programme (juggling) revealed similar benefits for self-esteem, although conclusions on this point are limited due to differences between comparison groups. In contrast, no benefits of the music programme were observed on children’s social skills.</p>
<p>The effects of the music programme on self-esteem were observed for global self-esteem, as well as for general and social self-esteem sub-scales in the older cohort. The significant benefit appeared to reflect a protection against a decline in self-esteem which occurred in the absence of the programme during the first year. An age-related decline in self-esteem among control students is consistent with previous findings of declining self-concept in the early years of primary school (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0255761411434824">Burnett, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0255761411434824">Eshel &amp; Klein, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0255761411434824">Marsh, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0255761411434824">Marsh, Barnes, Cairns, &amp; Tidman, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0255761411434824">Soares &amp; Soares, 1997</xref>). It is notable that the control students exhibited considerably higher global self-esteem scores at baseline, which may mean that the interaction is an artifact of these above average scores. However, the fact that the beneficial effect of music occurred across the two different cohorts would suggest it was not an artifact, as does perusal of the individual school data, which typically showed a decline across this interval in most schools across all measures.</p>
<p>The current finding of increased global self-esteem among students in the music programme is consistent with previous research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0255761411434824">Hietolahti-Ansten &amp; Kalliopuska, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0255761411434824">Luftig, 1994</xref>). Costa-Giomi demonstrated that private formal piano lessons over a three-year period benefited global self-esteem, while Hietolahti-Ansten and Kalliopuska’s correlational study found higher global self-esteem among students with extensive musical training than those who were not musically trained. However, no previous research has experimentally investigated the effects of <italic>school</italic>-based music education on self-esteem. The current findings provide the first evidence to our knowledge that the benefits of music training on self-esteem reported previously extend to school-based music classes. This finding is valuable given that the expenses associated with private lessons and purchase of instruments make private tuition inaccessible to many, particularly low socioeconomic status groups. Thus school-based music lessons may be a more accessible alternative to private tuition that provides similar benefits to self-esteem.</p>
<p>Numerous elements inherent in the school-based music classes may have contributed to improved self-esteem. Students were required to engage socially and function as a cohesive group, each of which is thought to foster a sense of belonging and self-confidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0255761411434824">Cleave &amp; Dust, 1989</xref>) and may have contributed to the observed increases in social self-esteem. Music tasks were structured so that students were equally competent before a more complex piece was introduced, which potentially facilitated self-perceptions of competence and ability to achieve goals. All children in the younger cohort were given the opportunity by the Kodaly teacher to direct the activities of the group. This opportunity was likely to have validated the significance of the individual in the group, boosting self-worth, and also increased feelings of competence in being entrusted this responsibility. In addition, the programmes enabled students to receive positive feedback on their performance from their peers, teachers and family.</p>
<p>At least some of these characteristics inherent in the music intervention may be generalised to other arts-based programmes, which accounts for the similar benefits to self-esteem found in the juggling group. However, it is still likely that there are other benefits that are specific to music training. Previous research indicates that benefits specific to music education may be more apparent in the cognitive domain than the psychosocial domain. For instance, children allocated to the music programme in the current study’s older cohort also demonstrated improvements in verbal memory that were not apparent in the juggling group (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0255761411434824">Rickard et al., 2010</xref>). In addition, a study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0255761411434824">Schellenberg (2001)</xref> that randomly allocated 144 6-year-old children to 36 weeks of Kodaly voice lessons, keyboard lessons, drama lessons or no lessons revealed widespread intellectual benefits for both the music groups that were absent in the drama group.</p>
<p>In contrast to self-esteem, no benefits to social skills were apparent amongst the intervention students. This finding was unexpected. As music requires participation and group collaboration, it is generally thought that music promotes social cohesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0255761411434824">Humpal, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0255761411434824">Peretz, 2005</xref>) and enhances the development of social skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0255761411434824">Blandford &amp; Duarte, 2004</xref>). One possible explanation for the lack of improvement in the current study is that the social skills of participants were above average at baseline, whereas benefits of music training may be apparent only in children with poorer social skills. Nevertheless, the present finding is consistent with that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0255761411434824">Schellenberg (2004)</xref>, who assessed the impact of weekly lessons in Kodaly voice or keyboard training in 6-year-old children over a nine month period. Both programmes failed to increase socially adaptive behaviour or reduce maladaptive behaviour. More empirical research is needed to determine whether music training can benefit social skills.</p>
<p>Several limitations in the current study should be acknowledged. Students were non-randomly allocated to the control or intervention group, although groups were similar at baseline on all demographics. In addition, although variations across schools were controlled through the use of nested analyses, a fully experimental design could not be used. Despite these limitations, the finding that age-appropriate music training benefited global self-esteem in both age cohorts is very promising and supplements the broader argument for arts-based education across the curriculum. It is important to note, however, that the observed benefits occurred only in the first year of the two-year programme. This suggests that variations to the programme may need to be introduced in order to maintain benefits to students’ self-esteem over the course of primary school. Nevertheless, this finding is consistent with those of previous research which also demonstrated stronger improvements in self-esteem after the first year of piano lessons than subsequent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0255761411434824">Costa-Giomi, 2004</xref>). In conclusion, the current findings provide the first known evidence that long-term age-appropriate school-based music education improves self-esteem in primary school children. Specifically, it appears that music training protected against a decline in self-esteem experienced by those students that were not involved in additional music classes. The observed benefits to self-esteem may generalise to other arts-based programmes, as preliminary data indicated that juggling lessons yielded similar benefits.</p>
<p>Clearly efforts shown to support development of children’s social skills and self-esteem are highly sought in the education context. Low self-esteem is associated with a range of mental health problems for children and adolescents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0255761411434824">Elmer, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0255761411434824">Mann, Hosman, Schaalma, &amp; de Vries, 2004</xref>), including mental illness (suicidal tendencies, depression, eating disorders, and anxiety) and social problems (antisocial behaviour, difficulty in sustaining and forming close relationships, violence and substance abuse) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0255761411434824">Dubois &amp; Tevendale, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0255761411434824">Elmer, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0255761411434824">Mann et al., 2004</xref>). Given the poor expected outcomes for children with demonstrated deficiencies in self-worth, it is vital that children are provided with environments conducive to developing better self-esteem. Recognizing this, educators are increasingly seeking to provide children with the means to realise their psychosocial competence as well as their academic potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0255761411434824">Department of Education and Training, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0255761411434824">McClung, 2000</xref>). In addition to its intrinsic musical benefits, music training might offer the necessary environmental conditions for schools to foster this development. The current study is among the first to provide empirical support for the value of increasing structured arts-based activities within the school curriculum.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We gratefully acknowledge the Australian Research Council who supported this research via an ARC Linkage grant (#LP0669864), and the Victorian Department of Education and Early Childhood Development for permission to perform this research in state schools. We would also like to thank the staff and students involved in the music education programme, in particular Ms Marilyn Keogh and Ms Linda Browne.</p>
</ack>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Nikki Rickard</bold>, BBSc(Hons), PhD, is an Associate Professor, specializing in research evaluations of positive interventions on cognitive and emotional well-being, particularly in school settings. She has authored over 50 peer-reviewed publications in international journals and recently completed a large Australian Research Council funded project investigating the psychosocial benefits of intensive music education for schoolchildren. She is currently Co-Director of the Emotion and Well-Being Unit at Monash University, Secretary of the Australian Music &amp; Psychology Society (AMPS) and Co-Editor-in-Chief of the new Springer Open Access journal <italic>Psychology of Well-Being: Theory, Research &amp; Practice</italic> launched in 2011.</p>
<p><bold>Peter Appleman</bold>, Dip Holistic Therapy, GradDip (Science), PGrad (Psych), has experience working in counselling and stress management, and is currently working in the field of environment and sustainability.</p>
<p><bold>Richard James</bold>, BBSc, PGrad (Psych) is currently working in a community-based organization in Melbourne Australia that provides both assessment and therapeutic intervention for children and adolescents who have engaged in problematic or abusive behaviour. He has co-authored one publication: <italic>Life Skills: Facilitation Guides for Educators Working with People with an Intellectual Disability</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Fintan Murphy</bold> is a Senior Lecturer in the School of Music, Monash University, Australia. His main research areas are body use and coordination in string playing and the use of multimedia in instrumental teaching. Recent publications include the DVDROM’s Violin Bow Technique (Twofold/Alfred, 2008) and the <italic>Violin Alive</italic> series (Twofold/Young Musicians, 2001–2009), the CD recording <italic>The Soul of the Viola</italic> (Move, 2004) and the Series 7 violin books (consultant editor) for the Australian Music Examinations Board (Allans, 2001).</p>
<p><bold>Anneliese Gill</bold>, MMus, Post-Grad. Dip. Psyc, a musician and Fulbright Scholar, spent a number of years as part of the music-psychology research team in the School of Psychology and Psychiatry at Monash University. She is involved in researching the benefits of school-based music education and is a guest lecturer on Music Performance Anxiety.</p>
<p><bold>Caroline Bambrick</bold>, BSci (Hons) (Psych), has conducted a wide range of research studies over a number of years in the School of Psychology and Psychiatry at Monash University, ranging from the effects of sleep deprivation, interventions for clinical depression and well-being of carers in dementia, in addition to her role investigating the benefits of school-based music education.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Battle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Culture-free self-esteem inventories: Examiners’ manual</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pro. Ed</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blandford</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Inclusion in the community: A study of community music centres in England and Portugal, focusing on the development of musical and social skills within each centre</article-title>. <source>Westminster Studies in Education</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Gender and grade differences in elementary school children’s descriptive and evaluative self-statements and self-esteem</article-title>. <source>School Psychology International</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Butzlaff</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Can music be used to teach reading?</article-title> <source>Journal of Aesthetic Education</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Camilleri</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Community building through drumming</article-title>. <source>The Arts in Psychotherapy</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Music training improves verbal memory</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>396</volume>, <fpage>128</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheek</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Music training and mathematics</article-title>. <source>Adolescence</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>761</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choksy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <source>The Kodály method</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cleave</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dust</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>A sound start: The schools’ instrumental music service</source>. <publisher-loc>Windsor, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NFER-Nelson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Children’s memory scale</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa-Giomi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The effects of three years of piano instruction on children’s cognitive development</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Music Education</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa-Giomi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Effects of three years of piano instruction on children’s academic achievement, school performance and self-esteem</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Music</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Department of Education and Training</collab>. (<year>2002</year>). <source>Social competencies: An integrated approach to linking student learning and wellbeing</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tevendale</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Self-esteem in childhood and adolescence: Vaccine or epiphenomenon?</article-title> <source>Applied and Preventive Psychology</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Role of music therapy in social skills development in children with moderate intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elbert</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pantev</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wienbruch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rockstroh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taub</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Increased cortical representation of fingers of the left hand in string players</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elmer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Self-esteem: The costs and consequences of self-worth</source>. <publisher-loc>York, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>York</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eshel</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Development of academic self-concept of lower-class and middle-class primary school children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeffrey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Learning improved by arts training</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>381</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Brain structures differ between musicians and non-musicians</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>9240</fpage>–<lpage>9245</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rickard</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Non-music benefits of school-based music training</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Rickard</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McFerran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Lifelong engagement with music: Benefits for mental health and well-being</source> (pp. <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nova Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Enhanced learning of proportional math through music training and spatial-temporal training</article-title>. <source>Neurological Research</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gresham</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>The social skills rating system manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Circle Pines, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Guidance Service</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hietolahti-Ansten</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalliopuska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Self-esteem and empathy among children actively involved in music</article-title>. <source>Perceptual and Motor Skills</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>1367</fpage>–<lpage>1374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y. -C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>M. -C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Music training improves verbal but not visual memory: Cross-sectional and longitudinal explorations in children</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychology</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Humpal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The effects of an integrated early childhood music program on social interaction among children with handicaps and their typical peers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Music Therapy</source>, <volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bortnick</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kokas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Nonmusical effects of the Kodály music curriculum in primary grade children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Learning Disabilities</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Nurturing students through group piano lessons</article-title>. <source>American Music Teacher</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Legette</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The effect of a selected use of music instruction on the self-concept and academic achievement of elementary public school students</article-title>. <source>Dissertation Abstracts International Section A: Humanities &amp; Social Sciences</source>, <volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Someday that might be me</article-title>. <source>Educational Leadership</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luftig</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>The schooled mind: Do arts make a difference? Year 2, An empirical evaluation of the Hamilton Fairfield SPECTRA+ program, 1993–1994, executive summary</source>. Unpublished manuscript, <publisher-name>Center for Human Development, Learning, and Teaching, Miami University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hosman</surname><given-names>C. M. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaalma</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Self-esteem in a broad-spectrum approach for mental health promotion</article-title>. <source>Health Education Research</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Age and sex effects in multiple dimensions of self-concept: Preadolescence to early adulthood</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tidman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Self-description questionnaire: Age and sex effects in the structure and level of self-concept for preadolescent children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>940</fpage>–<lpage>956</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Extramusical skills in the music classroom</article-title>. <source>Music Educators Journal</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orsmond</surname><given-names>G. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Cognitive, musical and environmental correlates of early instruction</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Music</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The music, movement and learning connection</article-title>. <source>Young Children</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pantev</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oostenveld</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engelien</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Increased auditory cortical representation in musicians</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>392</volume>, <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>814</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacCallum</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackinlay</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Winterton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>National review of school music education</source>. <publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Education, Science and Training, Australian Government</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The nature of music</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Music Education</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rauscher</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zupan</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Classroom keyboard instruction improves kindergarten children’s spatial-temporal performance: A field experiment</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rickard</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toukhsati</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Benefits of a classroom based instrumental music program on verbal memory of primary school children</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Music Education</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salaman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stefabo</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Music as an aid in the development of the social self</article-title>. <source>Medical Science Monitor</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Improvised conversations: Music, collaboration, and development</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Music</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellenberg</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Music and nonmusical abilities</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Science</source>, <volume>930</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellenberg</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Music lessons enhance IQ</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jäncke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Increased corpus callosum size in musicians</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1055</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Music for their minds</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1055</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Benton visual retention test</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <source>The self-concept: Mini, maxi, multi?</source> <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>New York, USA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of an early intervention music curriculum for enhancing prereading/writing skills</article-title>. <source>Music Therapy Perspectives</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trusty</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The effect of arts and music education on students’ self-concept</article-title>. <source>Update: Applications of Research in Music Education</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A byproduct of quality classroom music</article-title>. <source>Childhood Education</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0255761411434824">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Playing in the school band: Its effect on the self-esteem of elementary students in at risk environments</article-title>. <source>Dissertation Abstracts International Section A: Humanities &amp; Social Sciences</source>, <volume>62</volume>(<issue>7-A</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="section12-0255761411434824">
<title>Abstracts</title>
<sec id="section13-0255761411434824">
<title>Orchestrer les compétences de vie: l’effet de l’augmentation des cours de musique dans le milieu scolaire sur les compétences sociales des enfants et l’estime de soi</title>
<p>Cette étude a examiné l’effet d’augmenter la fréquence et la qualité des activités musicales en classe sur les compétences de l’estime de soi et sociales des enfants en âge d’écoles primaires pendant plusieurs années. Les enfants ont été recrutés à partir de deux niveaux scolaires (Prep / Grade 1, <italic>N</italic> = 210; Grade 3, <italic>N</italic> = 149) à partir d’un ensemble de 10 écoles dans une région rurale de Victoria, en Australie. Les écoles ont été soumises soit à la condition expérimentale, ou à la condition de contrôle, qui a continué à recevoir leur cursus habituel. Dans la condition expérimentale, des cours de musique basés sur la méthode Kodaly ont été introduits dans les programmes des plus jeunes, tandis que les plus âgés ont reçu des classes supplémentaires principalement d’instrument à cordes. L’effet de l’introduction de ces classes de musique sur les compétences d’estime de soi et sociales des enfants a été évaluée à travers les 2 ans de recherche, en utilisant la troisième édition <italic>du Culture Free Self-Esteem Inventories</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0255761411434824">Bataille, 2002</xref>) et le <italic>Social Skills Rating System</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>), respectivement. Les résultats ont indiqué que les cours de musique en milieu scolaire ont empêché une baisse de l’estime de soi globale, qui a été observée chez le groupe de contrôle, à la fois dans les plus jeunes et les plus âgés, et en estime de soi générale et académique pour les plus âgés. Aucuns avantages du programme de musique ont été observés sur les compétences sociales des enfants. Il est à remarquer, toutefois, que les données préliminaires suggèrent qu’une semblable engagement observées dans les activité artistique (jonglerie) peut conférer des avantages similaires pour l’estime de soi des enfants plus âgés. Alors que les difficultés inhérentes à effectuer des recherches expérimentales dans les écoles empêchent des conclusions solides, les données impliquent que l’augmentation de la qualité dans les activités artistique est bénéfique pour l’estime de soi des enfants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0255761411434824">
<title>Orquestando habilidades vitales: el efecto del incremento de clases de música basadas en la escuela en la competencia social y autoestima de los niños</title>
<p>Este estudio investigó el efecto de aumentar la frecuencia y calidad de actividades musicales de aula en la autoestima y las habilidades sociales de niños de Primaria durante varios años. Se seleccionaron niños de dos niveles distintos (1er curso escuela preparatoria, <italic>N</italic> = 210; 3°, <italic>N</italic> = 149) en un grupo de diez escuelas de una región rural de Victoria, Australia. Se asignaron las escuelas o bien al grupo experimental o bien al grupo control, el cual continuaba recibiendo su currículo habitual. En el grupo experimental, se introdujeron clases musicales de Kodaly en el currículo del grupo más joven, mientras que el grupo de mayor edad recibía clases instrumentales adicionales basadas principalmente en la cuerda. El efecto de introducir estas sesiones escolares en la autoestima y habilidades sociales de los niños fue evaluada a lo largo de los dos años de aplicación utilizando el Inventario de Autoestima Libre de Cultura, tercera edición (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0255761411434824">Battle, 2002</xref>) y el Sistema de Clasificación de Habilidades Sociales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0255761411434824">Gresham &amp; Elliot, 1990</xref>), respectivamente. Los resultados indicaron que las clases de música escolares evitaron una reducción en las mediciones de la autoestima del grupo control, tanto en los grupos de los más jóvenes como en los de más edad, así como en la autoestima académica y general en el de más edad. No se observaron beneficios respecto al programa de música en relación con las habilidades sociales de los niños. En gran medida, no obstante, datos previos sugieren que una actividad igualmente atractiva, basada en el arte (malabares), puede aportar beneficios similares para la autoestima de los niños de mayor edad. Mientras que las dificultades inherentes en la realización de la fase experimental evitan evitan conclusiones fuertes, nuestros datos implican que un incremento de las actividades de calidad basadas en arte es beneficioso para la autoestima de los niños.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</back>
</article>