<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CHP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spchp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Evidence-Based Complementary &amp; Alternative Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2156-5872</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2156-5899</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0883073813495142</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0883073813495142</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Memorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Memorial</article-title>
<subtitle>Roger Alan Brumback, MD (1948-2013)</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Buehler</surname>
<given-names>Bruce A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<aff id="aff1-0883073813495142">Interim Editor, <italic>JEBCAM</italic></aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>169</fpage>
<lpage>169</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>So much one man can do,</p>
<p>That does both act and know</p>
<attrib>—Andrew Marvel (upon Oliver Cromwell’s return to Ireland)</attrib>
</disp-quote>
On May 15, 2013, Dr Roger Brumback and his wife were in their home, when they suddenly became the victims of an awful crime, leaving both dead. They were to have retired to West Virginia in July 2013. Roger and his wife Mary were a team; their departure leaves a very large crater in the academic and clinical medical community.</p>
<p>It is impossible to ignore Roger’s accomplishment beyond the journals he edited—<italic>Journal of Evidence-Based Complementary &amp; Alternative Medicine</italic> (<italic>JEBCAM</italic>) and <italic>Journal of Child Neurology</italic>. He was board certified in pathology, neurology, and pediatrics. He had 147 scholarly publications, with 19 edited or coedited books. His curriculum vitae was 54 pages long, in small font. From 2001 to 2010 he was Chairperson of the Department of Pathology, Creighton University School of Medicine.</p>
<p>Roger’s humor, although he couldn’t ever finish a joke, was sharp; his laughter genuine; and his friendship invaluable. He was a very moral, ethical man. A true teacher, he valued every student and resident. He was quiet because he always listened before speaking, but then he spoke with conviction.</p>
<p>Roger took over what became <italic>JEBCAM</italic> in 2011, at the request of Sage Publishing Company. His prowess as an editor had been demonstrated by his development of the <italic>Journal of Child Neurology</italic> into a premier journal. As with everything, he took on the task with vision, hard work, and contacts around the world.</p>
<p>Due to Roger’s passing, I have accepted the task of acting as Interim Editor of <italic>JEBCAM</italic>. A formal search for editors will take place in coming months.</p>
<p>As a <italic>JEBCAM</italic> Associate Editor stationed a mile away at the University of Nebraska Medical Center, we spent many working lunches together, with Roger’s indulging in his favorite item, filet mignon. In our last discussion, he felt we were ahead of schedule, and he had plans to involve the outstanding editorial board in more activities for the journal. He was also working to ready <italic>JEBCAM</italic> for a review to be considered for inclusion in Medline.</p>
<p>As his memorial, I trust the editorial board will continue his task of making <italic>JEBCAM</italic> a leader in the science of complementary and alternative medicine.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Bruce A. Buehler, MD</sig>
<sig>Interim Editor, <italic>JEBCAM</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>