<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsw</journal-id>
<journal-title>Research on Social Work Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-7315</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7581</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049731512465473</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049731512465473</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Building Research Culture and Infrastructure</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>Katherine J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512465473"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1049731512465473"><italic>University of Georgia, Athens, GA, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>110</fpage>
<lpage>112</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McRoy</surname>
<given-names>Ruth G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flanzer</surname>
<given-names>Jerry P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zlotnik</surname>
<given-names>Joan Levy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <source>Building Research Culture and Infrastructure</source> <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>. <page-count count="210"/> pp. <price>$33.97</price> (paperback). <isbn>ISBN: 978-0-19539964-6</isbn>
</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<italic>Building Research Culture and Infrastructure</italic> is an overview and instructional text on how to build a social research culture and infrastructure. The text examines the numerous and multifaceted issues contextualizing research in social work. The target audience appears to be current and future social work faculty, deans, students, and other researchers. Since the 1991 National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)-supported Task Force on Social Work Research, research in social work and evidence-based practice have come to the forefront as major priorities of social work education. The authors make it apparent that the purpose of this text is to review the history of social work research, as well as discuss the state of research in social work, and table future implications for research. The text is divided into eight chapters, each containing several subheadings as well as a summary or implications subsection at the end of the chapter, with a synopsis of the previous material covered.</p>
<p>Chapter 1 presents the reader with an overview of the goals and main objectives of the text. It defines social work research and how it can be used in the profession, as well as specific terminology about how it will be used in the later chapters. This chapter sets the stage for the rest of the book and discusses that its purpose is to examine the current research infrastructure, status, and climate in social work educational programs. This is a nice lead-in overviewish foundational chapter that highlights major issues that the book purports to address. There are also three scenarios introduced here regarding issues found in research for: a new dean, an unsuccessful research application, and a junior faculty. The authors emphasize the importance of keeping these scenarios and dilemmas in mind while reading the ensuing text, as they are to be addressed in subsequent chapters.</p>
<p>Chapter 2 focuses on a historical overview of the national U.S. social work research-building efforts. This chapter has subheadings for the different research-related organizations and tracks each organization’s history in regard to research. Included in this chapter are also discussions regarding social work research and the National Institutes of Health (NIH), along with the NIH’s strategies to help build and support social work research infrastructures, as well as a description of the NIH Plan for Social Work research which delineates recommendations for the future (pp. 28–29). There is also a lengthy and well-developed discussion of instances where research has begun to bridge with practice, specifically in the areas of intervention, translational, comparative effectiveness, culturally competent, community-based participatory, and policy analysis research. This chapter comprehensively develops the concepts of the structure of social work research, its history, and emphasizes its major priorities for the future.</p>
<p>Chapter 3 focuses on social work programs in regard to their capacities for research and also the readiness for change in such programs. The authors begin by discussing the various models of change and how these can be applied to aspects inducing change in social work programs. In one example in particular, the authors use an excerpt from a recent article by Simpson (2009) from <italic>Research on Social Work Practice</italic>, where social service organizations and their readiness to embrace innovation implementation are addressed. These authors show how the same concepts of innovation implementation can be applied to social work research by inserting words regarding building research capacity in schools of social work into this excerpt (p. 41).</p>
<p>Chapter 4 presents suggested guidelines that social work faculty should follow to support their research. The information presented here appears to me to be some of the most valuable in the book, with the inclusion of practical tools and tips for faculty members to utilize, to enhance, and to engage in research. I also found the end of this chapter very useful, as it presented steps for conceptualizing a study, putting together a proposal, and of how to handle issues that may arise in this process (pp. 78–82).</p>
<p>Chapter 5 focuses on research administration and offers well-heeded discussion regarding the importance and purpose of research administrators, as well as a breakdown of the common roles of administrators as cited by Landen and McCallister (2006). It reviews issues related to pre-award administration, university-level responsibilities, budget, institutional review board (IRB), post-award administration, effort, and expenditure reports. Although the chapter has a great deal of useful and pertinent information, at times I felt it touched on seemingly complicated topics, without going into great detail on any.</p>
<p>Chapter 6 focuses on how “connections” can be a great source of research, and it does a good job discussing the different forms of collaboration within and outside of the university. There is much detailed discussion regarding how agency and university collaboration can be utilized. The authors touch upon difficulties that new faculty may come across and provide examples of how these difficulties can be overcome. The authors also suggest reasons for reluctance of faculty to engage in community-based research, and how this type of research can be better promoted. The last portion of this chapter discusses how to enhance interdisciplinary, cross-university, and cross-community collaborations. I found this chapter helpful and the use of numerous examples made the information more applicable and relevant.</p>
<p>Chapter 7 focused on funding social work research through federal and foundation opportunities. The authors discussed the various types of research that may be available from several U.S. federal departments. There are subsections for the Department of Health and Human Services and other federal agencies that can support social work research. In addition, there is a subsection dealing solely with Foundation funding, as well as examples of such funding. The latter portion of this chapter focused on how to use legislative strategies to build a research infrastructure. Various states and initiatives are offered as well illustrated examples, as well as various Congressional reports that use social work related language.</p>
<p>Finally, Chapter 8 illuminates the purpose of the book, and braids together the previous chapters. This was another useful chapter in providing the reader ideas for future research development. The inclusion of various illustrative figures namely, an Assessment of Current Research Initiatives (Figure 8, p. 166), a Funding Assessment (Figure 8.2, p. 167), an Assessment of Internal and External Collaborations (Figure 8.3, p. 168), Faculty Experiences and Perceptions of Research Support (Figure 8.4, p. 169), and an Overall Assessment of the Integration of the School or Program’s Research Initiatives with the Academic Mission of the School and University (Figure 8.5, p. 169), serve as added bonuses to the plethora of information laid out previously. This chapter ended with both a summary and implications subsection, which highlighted the overarching goals of the text, and the authors’ desires for future efforts.</p>
<p>Overall, I feel generally that this book did deliver on the stated purpose and succeeded in laying out some of the vital components necessary for engaging in social work research. One of its strengths was the use of numerous examples throughout the text such as, examples of funding opportunities and various forms of research collaboration. There was also an effective breakdown of specific and well-illustrated information throughout, which allows readers to easily follow the purpose and major themes of the text. The inclusion of the summary chapter at the beginning of the text also presented a format noting how information is formatted in the remaining chapters; enabling easy access to the desired information. In Chapter 5 and the remaining chapters, the authors moved away from just summarizing materials, and included an implications subsection. This amendment proved useful in showing how one can move forward and apply the chapter content to practical future applications.</p>
<p>However, there were a few minor issues which I felt distracted from its overall readability. The placement of the scenarios in the first chapter made them hard to follow or even to remember, once they were revisited later on in Chapters 4–6. It may have been more beneficial to introduce these scenarios in the actual chapters themselves in which the resolutions were addressed, so the information would be fresh in a reader’s mind. I also appreciated the numerous website links embedded within the book; however, at times these also distracted from the content flow of the book and perhaps could have been added to the text in a less obtrusive manner. It also would have been helpful to have these websites formatted in a summary table, to make them more user-friendly to the reader. I also thought that the organizational placement of some of the chapters in this text did not seem appropriate. For example, Chapter 6 about collaboration and partnership may have made more sense if it followed Chapter 4, which focused on social work faculties’ roles in research rather than Chapter 5, which dealt with research administration. I also felt that Chapter 5 covered an extensive amount of information regarding complicated research administration topics. However, it did not seem as if there was enough information to make these concepts accessible to the reader. This chapter was a bit overwhelming compared to the rest of the text content-wise.</p>
<p>As a social work PhD student and hopefully future faculty member, I found the majority of the text relatively easy to follow, and the information accessible. Overall, I felt the manner in which the information was presented allowed for the understanding of the complex and sometimes daunting task of engaging in research. I also believe that with the inclusion of various scenarios, examples, and settings that this book would be beneficial to anyone engaging in, or facilitating research in social work. The authors were cognizant of the various individuals and settings in which social work research may be undertaken, and were able to show how it could be enhanced by deans and directors, and how partnerships between various faculty members, students, as well as outside agencies can be formulated in an effort to promote research. I would recommend this text be used in a supplemental capacity, as a way of orienting both beginning and seasoned researchers, to the culture of social work research in efforts to more fully develop individual and organizational research capacities.</p>
</body>
</article>