<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CQX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcqx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Cornell Hospitality Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1938-9655</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-9663</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1938965512438545</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1938965512438545</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Law</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cities versus Online Travel Companies</article-title>
<subtitle>Liability for Room Occupancy Taxes</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Arthur</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1938965512438545">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>S. Brooks</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1938965512438545">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>Hugh A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1938965512438545">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1938965512438545"><label>1</label>James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1938965512438545"><label>2</label>University of the District of Columbia, DC, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1938965512438545">Hamilton, Arthur John, James Madison University - Department of Finance and Business Law, MSC 0202, 800 S. Main St., Harrisonburg, VA, 22802 Email: <email>hamiltaj@jmu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>53</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>357</fpage>
<lpage>364</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Cornell University</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article examines suits by municipalities against online travel companies (OTCs) for not remitting the appropriate room occupancy tax. At issue is whether OTCs should collect tax on the amount they pay hotels for rooms or on the higher amount charged consumers. This article describes the business structure of OTCs as related to tax collection and discusses legal issues and recent court decisions as well as state and federal legislative proposals to address occupancy tax issues. At this time, it is not possible to cite a single rule that applies in all situations due to the numerous state and local laws and court holdings in relation to this matter. A key question involves whether OTCs are agents for hotels, as argued by many municipalities, or if instead the OTC acts as a personal shopper for would-be guests. In the <italic>agency model</italic>, the OTCs are in effect selling rooms subject to occupancy tax; while in the <italic>merchant model</italic>, the OTC would be providing a service, rather than rooms themselves, and the service would not be subject to occupancy taxes. A key element in the tax liability determination is the physical presence of a business. Although the U.S. Supreme Court has issued holdings on physical presence and other issues relating to occupancy taxes, the Court has not spoken on what constitutes physical presence. Lower courts have been divided on matters relating to occupancy taxes. Given conflicting holdings, the matter’s resolution may rest with the Supreme Court, if it chooses to hear this matter.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>commerce clause</kwd>
<kwd>diversity cases</kwd>
<kwd>enabling legislation</kwd>
<kwd>occupancy tax</kwd>
<kwd>online travel company</kwd>
<kwd>out-of-state entity</kwd>
<kwd>services tax</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Local governments are increasingly suing online travel companies (OTCs) like Priceline, Expedia, and Orbitz on the grounds that the OTCs are not remitting the occupancy tax that is due. The fundamental issue is whether the OTCs should pay tax on the amount they pay hotels for the room or on the higher amount they collect from the consumer. Existing statutes and case law have not provided clarity on this matter. This article examines those laws and court cases, in an effort to explain the situation as it stands. We describe the structure of OTCs, recent court decisions, and legislative proposals. We conclude with a projection of the actions needed to bring some predictability into taxing online booking.</p>
<sec id="section1-1938965512438545">
<title>Travel Company Business Models</title>
<p>The issue in most of the disputes involves the three-party nature of online booking. In a simple two-party transaction, the consumer books a room and pays one price including any occupancy tax. In an OTC transaction, there are two rates: the wholesale rate negotiated by the OTC and the retail rate paid by the consumer. Typically the OTC does not disclose which portion of what it collects is for the room, taxes, or its facilitation fee. Nor does the OTC disclose to hotels the amount paid by consumers. There are several ways to view the transaction when an OTC books a room. We examine the two models most frequently argued by OTCs and municipalities.</p>
<p>In the <italic>agency model</italic>, preferred by municipalities, OTCs function as a hotel’s agent, booking consumers into rooms, charging service fees to hotels, and sometimes charging service fees to consumers. Hotels set the price of the room and are the <italic>merchant of record</italic> for the transaction. The consumer pays the hotel directly.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1938965512438545">1</xref></sup> However, most OTCs prefer to be seen as a mere facilitator between the hotel and the customer; this is the <italic>merchant model</italic>. Under the merchant model, OTCs purchase rooms from hotels at wholesale rates, then resell those rooms to consumers at a higher retail rate. The OTC sets the retail price and is the merchant of record.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1938965512438545">2</xref></sup> A variant of the merchant model is the “<italic>personal shopper model</italic>.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1938965512438545">3</xref></sup> In this model, consumers are seen as paying the OTC a fee for finding and providing a hotel room. In essence the OTC is acting as a personal shopper for the consumer. The price paid to the OTC by the consumer includes the OTC’s cost of the room, the tax, and its commission and fees. The OTC in turn pays the hotel the wholesale rate and the corresponding tax on the negotiated rate.</p>
<p>OTCs hold that they do not maintain an inventory of rooms, do not operate hotels, and do not furnish or supply hotel rooms. OTCs maintain that they are not agents of the hotels simply because they have contracts with them. Indeed they have contracts with numerous competing hotel companies. In short, OTCs argue that occupancy taxes are a tax on hotels not on the service they provide.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1938965512438545">
<title>Recent Litigation</title>
<p>The language of the statutes in each state and municipality is unique and often unclear as to who or what is being taxed. Judicial interpretations of laws enacted decades before OTCs existed are deciding multi-million-dollar lawsuits. The difficulty in trying to reach any wide-ranging conclusions about the current state of the law is illustrated by the decision of a federal appeals court that agreed with the reasoning of another court but said that “the lack of equivalent language in the ordinances before us leads to the opposite result.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1938965512438545">4</xref></sup> Although most courts do not find it necessary to determine whether OTCs are “innkeepers,” they do question whether OTCs “furnish” or “supply” rooms under hotel occupancy ordinances. What has been determinative in some cases is not who owns and maintains the room but, rather, who is accepting money in exchange for the room. A federal district court has held that “if consumers access a website, use it to book a hotel room, pay the website directly, and never pay the hotel, or interact with the hotel at all until they arrive, the court cannot accept Defendants’ assertion that they do not furnish accommodations to consumers.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1938965512438545">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>There are essentially two claims being made by the municipalities. The first is that the tax due should be based on the retail rate paid by consumers. The second, less frequent claim is that the OTC has engaged in <italic>conversion</italic>, a civil claim that OTCs are collecting tax on the retail price, remitting tax on the wholesale rate, and pocketing the difference. Most of the cases are still in the preliminary stages in which questions of procedure are being argued. During this stage, OTCs often make a <italic>motion to dismiss for failure to state a claim</italic>, also known as a <italic>demurrer</italic>. This motion claims that the plaintiff does not have a leg to stand on, that the language of the tax statute clearly does not apply to the OTC, and the case should be dismissed. There is a strong presumption against granting motions to dismiss. A court must accept as true all well-pleaded facts and draw all permissible inferences in the plaintiff’s favor. A claim will be dismissed only when it does not contain enough facts to make the claim “plausible on its face.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1938965512438545">6</xref></sup> Most federal district courts have denied, at least in part, OTCs’ motions to dismiss and allowed the case to proceed to trial. When a suit is <italic>dismissed without prejudice</italic>, the plaintiff can amend its complaint and bring the suit back before the court.</p>
<p>In 2009, a group of 170 Texas cities was awarded $20 million in a class-action suit.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1938965512438545">7</xref></sup> The municipalities argued that the OTCs were buying rooms at wholesale and selling them at retail and that the tax was due on the retail rate. The jury agreed. The municipalities also claimed that the OTC practice of bundling charges to customers for “tax recovery charges” and “service fees” was in effect the collection of tax on the retail rate and payment of tax on the lower wholesale rate, which constituted the tort of conversion. The jury, however, rejected this “tax and pocket” argument.</p>
<p>In June 2009, the Georgia Supreme Court handed the OTCs their first major defeat. In <italic>Expedia, Inc. v. City of Columbus</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1938965512438545">8</xref></sup> the court held that under a plain reading of the occupancy tax ordinance, the applicable tax rate must be applied to the amount OTCs charge a customer rather than the discounted amount for which the OTC contracts with hotels to pay for a room. The court’s decision “marks the first time any state’s highest court has ruled on the substantive issues at the center of dozens of legal and administrative battles between the OTCs and municipalities around the country.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1938965512438545">9</xref></sup> The court enjoined Expedia from future bookings if it did not pay the city occupancy tax based on the room rate paid by online customers. The city may have won the suit, but Expedia stopped listing hotels in Columbus and is directing consumers to hotels nearby.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1938965512438545">
<title>Judicial Review</title>
<p>Questions about a state’s tax laws are clearly within the jurisdiction of that state’s courts, so any of the disputes between municipalities and OTCs may be heard in state courts. However <italic>federal diversity of citizenship</italic> law provides that when the parties are from different states and the amount in controversy is more than $75,000, the plaintiff may elect to bring the case before a federal district court. Furthermore, federal law provides that when the plaintiff has elected to sue in state court, the defendant can have the suit <italic>removed</italic> to a federal district court. In short, when parties are from different states, either of them may direct a case, which would otherwise be heard in state court, to come before a federal court. Once either party puts the case in federal court, it stays there. The rationale for diversity jurisdiction is that it helps protect out-of-state defendants from potentially biased state courts. When hearing <italic>diversity cases</italic>, the federal court is obliged to decide the case as it believes the supreme court of the state would do. Thus, the federal court must consider state court precedent in the interpretation of that state’s tax statutes</p>
<p>A fundamental maxim governing judicial review of state statutes and municipal ordinances is that any ambiguity or doubt as to the meaning of the statute must be resolved in favor of the taxpayer. Courts in all states have long held that to hold a citizen liable to pay a tax, the law must be plain and precise. Because a tax imposes a burden upon the people, that burden must be explicitly and distinctly revealed in the language of the statute. Many state laws enacted before the advent of the Internet did not contemplate the online method of doing business. These statutes do not directly address the liability of intermediaries or other Internet sellers and, thus, are ambiguous with respect to the liability of OTCs.</p>
<p>Some of the variation in the decisions is due to the considerable difference in tax ordinances, enabling statutes, and unfair trade practices laws. However, the variation is also due to the fact that the legal principles are very much unsettled and there is a lack of established precedent in the matter of taxing online bookings. Even if ordinances and statutes were identical, two different federal district courts could still arrive at opposing interpretations.</p>
<p>We believe that eventually an OTC will appeal an adverse decision to the U.S. Supreme Court. There are two paths for such a case to reach the Supreme Court. The first is an appeal from one of the federal circuit courts of appeal. The second is an appeal from one of the state supreme courts. There is no guarantee that the high court would accept such a case for consideration, but the chances are far greater if lower courts are in direct conflict as to the meaning of the law.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1938965512438545">
<title>Enabling Legislation</title>
<p>Since all municipal governments are subdivisions of their state, they must derive their ability to levy local taxes from state <italic>enabling legislation</italic>. A typical enabling statute authorizes municipalities to impose taxes related to hotel visits and to use the collected taxes to encourage tourism. When cases are before the courts, they typically involve not only the interpretation of a municipal ordinance but also the state law that authorizes the municipality to levy the tax. Because both the ordinance and the statute must clearly spell out liability for the tax, there is a greater likelihood that the OTCs can prove some ambiguity or omission and that the law does not cover them.</p>
<p>In what is perhaps the most significant victory to date for the OTCs, a U.S. Court of Appeals rejected a North Carolina county’s claim that North Carolina’s enabling statute was intended to cover the OTC markup.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1938965512438545">10</xref></sup> This decision is the first federal appellate decision on the occupancy tax issue. The court reasoned that online companies have no role in the day-to-day operation or management of hotels and that “they cannot be said to operate the hotels.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1938965512438545">11</xref></sup> The court also rejected the argument that online travel companies were “similar type businesses” to hotels and thus could be considered “retailers.” The court declined to substitute its judgment for that of the legislature, leaving to the legislature the function of addressing any oversights, omissions, or loopholes. The court acknowledged that the legislature may have failed to consider a situation where hotel rooms are rented first at wholesale and later re-let at retail rates to consumers, but also noted that the statute’s language may have been a deliberate choice to limit the application of the tax to actual hotel operators. The court emphasized the often-stated maxim in resolving ambiguity in tax statutes: where the meaning of a tax statute is doubtful, it should be construed against the state and in favor of the taxpayer unless a contrary legislative intent appears.</p>
<p>In response to the federal court’s ruling, the North Carolina legislature amended its occupancy tax law effective January 1, 2011 to provide that occupancy tax is due on the price of the rental of an accommodation marketed by a “facilitator” (OTC), and the tax applies to charges designated as “facilitation fees” as well as any other charges necessary to complete the rental (the OTC markup).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1938965512438545">12</xref></sup> On February 4, 2011, several OTCs filed suit alleging that the North Carolina law violates provisions of both the U.S. Constitution and the North Carolina Constitution.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1938965512438545">13</xref></sup> Among other allegations, the OTCs claim that the law violates the nexus requirement of the Commerce Clause<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1938965512438545">14</xref></sup> in that OTCs do not have sufficient contacts with North Carolina to subject their services the tax. We will discuss the <italic>nexus</italic> issue in a moment.</p>
<p>In neighboring South Carolina, the federal district court took a different view of legislative intent.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1938965512438545">15</xref></sup> The OTCs’ challenged their liability under South Carolina’s enabling legislation because the statute expressly prohibited the levying of taxes on corporations beyond the municipalities’ borders. The court was willing to go beyond a literal reading of the statute to find that as long as the OTCs had an impact within the municipalities, they were subject to the tax. The difference between these two federal decisions appears to demonstrate contradictory results from two courts. However, it is better interpreted as reflecting the differences in the specific language of the enabling statutes. The South Carolina law, unlike most, included a statement that reversed the traditional maxim favoring the taxpayer: “the power of a municipality to impose the tax shall be liberally construed in favor of the <italic>municipality</italic>.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1938965512438545">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>Enabling legislation was also critical in a 2010 New York decision.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1938965512438545">17</xref></sup> The OTCs challenged 2009 amendments to the occupancy tax law enacted by New York City,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1938965512438545">18</xref></sup> which imposed occupancy tax on the entire amount paid by a consumer. The law created a new class of entities, “room remarketers,” specifically including OTCs. The law also redefined “rent” and included the new terms “net rent,” and “additional rent, to include OTC markups.” In addition to imposing the tax on the retail rate, the act also requires OTCs to inform consumers of the breakdown between rent, taxes, and fees.</p>
<p>Several OTCs, led by Expedia,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1938965512438545">19</xref></sup> challenged the law, arguing that New York City exceeded its authority under New York’s enabling legislation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1938965512438545">20</xref></sup> The OTCs argued the statute did not authorize a new tax on travel booking services and the tax could not be imposed on the OTC service fees. The court rejected their arguments holding that the enabling statute did not distinguish between “operators” and “room remarketers” and the tax was being properly levied on the amount being paid by the consumer even though only a fraction of that amount was received by the OTCs.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1938965512438545">21</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1938965512438545">
<title>Rejecting Absurd Loopholes</title>
<p>The federal district court in the South Carolina case was willing to do what most other courts will not: it broadened its review to consider the broader policy implications of a ruling negating the tax.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1938965512438545">22</xref></sup> The court refused to accept a reading of the statute that would create a number of “absurd loopholes.” The court hypothesized that there would be nothing to prevent a hotel from establishing a wholly owned subsidiary in a different municipality to handle all of its reservations and bookings. The hotel could then provide rooms to the subsidiary at an extremely cheap price, and the subsidiary could sell them to consumers at a much higher rate. In this way, said the court, the company would be able to provide accommodations to customers without having to charge the tax on the amount the customers actually pay for the room.</p>
<p>The opposite approach was reached in the decision of a federal appeals court in Kentucky.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1938965512438545">23</xref></sup> That court rejected the argument that a narrow interpretation of the Kentucky law would lead to an absurd result. The municipalities had made essentially the same claim as in the South Carolina case: if the OTCs were not covered by the law, they would be positioned to open up a “potentially gaping loophole” whereby a hotel operator could simply incorporate a shell entity; rent the hotel rooms to that entity for a nominal amount; and then rerent the rooms to consumers, who would be taxed only on the nominal sum paid by the side entity to the operator. The court rejected the municipalities’ argument, stating that it is the function of the legislature, not the courts, to close potential loopholes. The court remarked that the Kentucky enabling acts “have simply failed to keep up with the times.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-1938965512438545">24</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1938965512438545">
<title>Jumping the Gun: Exhaustion of Administrative Remedies</title>
<p>Municipalities frequently sue the OTCs before the tax collector has filed a petition, held a hearing, or used the tax department’s internal appeal process. The OTCs often respond by claiming the municipalities are “jumping the gun.” Specifically, the OTCs file a motion to dismiss the suit as premature; the city has failed to follow its own administrative procedures. The doctrine of <italic>exhaustion of administrative remedies</italic> requires that when a statute provides for complaints and hearings before an administrative body, such as a municipal tax authority, a party seeking relief must avail itself of all such procedures before a court will have jurisdiction to act. The doctrine exists to prevent premature interference with administrative agency processes and to afford the parties and the courts the benefit of the agency’s experience and expertise. As a general rule, only when the agency’s procedures are finished, or exhausted, can a litigant file a complaint in a court.</p>
<p>In many states, once companies have completed or exhausted the administrative process of the assessment office, they must pay those assessments before being allowed to contest them in a court of law. Some states require that cash be put up, while others allow a bond to be posted. This requirement is commonly referred to as “pay to play.” Some courts have ruled that municipalities are not obligated to exhaust administrative remedies by conducting an audit, because exhaustion would be futile. These courts reason that because OTCs were vigorously litigating their liability under similar tax ordinances around the country, the OTCs would not have acquiesced to the audits, and administrative process would have been rendered a “charade.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-1938965512438545">25</xref></sup> These decisions reason that an administrative remedy would be inadequate because the fundamental issue underlying the municipality’s claim was not merely its allegation that the OTCs have an outstanding tax obligation but, rather, the legal question of whether the defendants are subject to the tax ordinance in the first place.</p>
<p>Other courts have taken an opposing view. In a 2006 case involving the City of Philadelphia, a court noted that it was “troubled” that the city filed a lawsuit without first performing an audit, providing notice, or otherwise attempting to collect the tax, powers that were expressly delegated to the city’s taxing authority.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-1938965512438545">26</xref></sup> The court stated that, just as a taxpayer is obligated to exhaust administrative remedies, so too was the city. The court reasoned that municipalities could not sidestep the exhaustion requirement on the basis of speculation that the OTCs might later refuse to participate in the administrative process. Not until the OTCs actually refused to participate in the process could the cities argue that the court should consider the administrative process exhausted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1938965512438545">
<title>Unlawful Retention of Tax Revenues</title>
<p>Some suits against the OTCs allege a second more serious claim: c<italic>onversion</italic>. They claim the OTCs have <italic>exercised unauthorized control over the property of another</italic>, that is, tax revenues collected from consumers and rightfully belonging to the municipality. These suits claim that OTCs have collected tax on the higher rate paid by the consumer but have remitted tax based only on the lower rate and have pocketed the difference. These suits are not as straightforward as they might seem because it is not clear from the OTCs’ financial statements what part of the OTC markup is a fee and what is tax. In the Texas case discussed above, the jury found that there was no conversion, but the allegation of conversion is still pending in other suits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1938965512438545">
<title>Deceptive Trade Practices</title>
<p>Some suits assert the tax must be separately specified on the consumer’s invoice. These suits claim that when the invoice lumps together the tax with the OTC service fee, the practice constitutes <italic>consumer fraud</italic>—or <italic>deceptive trade practice</italic>. State consumer fraud statutes vary significantly in their approach, language and the degree of protections they provide. Most statutes use words such as “deceptive,” “unfair,” “unconscionable,” or “fraudulent” to describe the prohibited trade practice. Some of the more consumer-friendly statutes do not require that the person charged with committing an act of deception have the intent to deceive, that actual deception has occurred, or that a person has knowledge that a statement is false to be liable for violation of the statute.</p>
<p>In May 2009, a trial court in Washington State ruled against Expedia in a consumer class-action suit.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-1938965512438545">27</xref></sup> The decision, based on the contract between Expedia and its customers, held that Expedia’s method of fee disclosures breached its contracts with consumers and constituted a deceptive trade practice under Washington’s consumer protection act. Expedia claimed its fees simply covered room taxes and the company’s costs. The court found that the bundled billing method employed by the company contained hidden profits and ordered Expedia to pay $184.5 million in damages for misleading customers about these fees. Although the court found that Expedia was in breach of contract with its customers, it did not go so far as to hold that tax had been collected and withheld from the government.</p>
<p>In the South Carolina case discussed above, one of the claims made by the municipalities was that the OTCs violated the South Carolina Unfair Trade Practices Act. The municipalities alleged that the OTCs were collecting the accommodations taxes from consumers based on the marked-up rates but only remitting the taxes based on the lower rate. The OTCs defended by arguing the unfair trade practices law only applies to misrepresentations made to consumers and that the law does not apply to tax disputes between persons and governments. The court disagreed, finding that “if a consumer is charged a ‘tax’ in addition to the retail price of an accommodation, he or she would reasonably assume that the amount of the tax is set by the state or local government in question, and the money will be paid to the… government.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-1938965512438545">28</xref></sup> The court did not address the question of whether the OTCs did in fact keep part of the money collected as tax but did rule there was sufficient evidence to allow the claim to go to trial.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1938965512438545">
<title>Nexus: A Commerce Clause Requirement</title>
<p>Most of the cases decided thus far involve questions about local taxes on local rooms and local transactions. Appellate courts may find that OTCs are not in the business of supplying rooms but are instead providing a service. If the states respond by enacting new laws levying taxes directly on OTC markups for <italic>services</italic> rendered, it will represent a major change in the nature of the tax. Taxing an out-of-state service provider presents an entirely new set of legal concerns. For example, there are the questions of where the service was provided, where the rental transaction occurred, and where the OTC is located. The OTCs would no doubt assert a claim that heretofore has not been an issue: they are engaging in interstate commerce. A business is deemed to be from out-of-state in all states but the state of incorporation and its principal place of business.</p>
<p>One of the main reasons for the adoption of the U.S. Constitution was that the existing national government had no power to prevent states from levying taxes that were discriminatorily burdensome on those doing business across state lines. The seminal 1824 Supreme Court decision interpreting the new Constitution’s commerce clause, <italic>Gibbons v. Ogden</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-1938965512438545">29</xref></sup> invalidated a state’s law as unfairly burdensome on interstate travel.</p>
<p>In the wake of <italic>Gibbons</italic>, the commerce clause has been repeatedly found to limit the ability of states to impose taxes on out-of-state entities and to expand the power of the U.S. Congress to regulate commerce among the states. The commerce clause is the first line of defense in protecting companies that do business in several states from suffering overlapping, inconsistent, and sometimes onerous tax burdens imposed by multiple states. On the other hand, the U.S. Constitution recognizes that the states have the right to impose taxes on visitors for goods purchased and services provided while in the state.</p>
<p>Although the Supreme Court has addressed the subject many times over the years, the decisions hardly present clear rules for determining the constitutionality of state taxes on out-of-state businesses. The decisions set forth the all-important requirement that before a state can levy a tax, the business must have some <italic>nexus</italic> to the taxing state. The nexus requirement means that the business must have some “minimum contacts” within the state. In the context of states’ sales tax laws, the Supreme Court has held that at least some kind of “physical presence” is required before the state can lawfully levy its tax. The Court has been concerned that imposing sales tax collection duties on every interstate seller, thus requiring them to sift through the “many variations in rates of tax, in allowable exemptions, and in administrative and record-keeping requirements,” was far too burdensome.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-1938965512438545">30</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has handed down three landmark decisions that have direct bearing on the question of whether states may impose a service tax on Internet booking services. In <italic>National Bellas Hess, Inc.</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-1938965512438545">31</xref></sup> the Court ruled that it is a violation of the commerce clause to impose a tax on a company whose only connection with customers in the state is by common carrier or by mail. In <italic>Brady</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-1938965512438545">32</xref></sup> the Court permitted states to impose a direct tax on interstate commerce as long as the tax is fairly apportioned, does not discriminate against interstate commerce, and is fairly related to services provided by the state. The Court most recently revisited nexus in its 1992 decision, <italic>Quill Corp</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-1938965512438545">33</xref></sup> Quill, a Delaware corporation, maintained no retail outlets or sales representatives in North Dakota. North Dakota imposed the duty to collect sales tax from state residents on Quill Corporation, whose only contact in the state consisted of catalogs and flyers mailed to customers, advertisements in national periodicals, and telephone calls. North Dakota argued that as commerce and technology had evolved, the requirement on out-of-state companies to collect local sales was no longer as burdensome as when <italic>Hess</italic> was decided. The Court disagreed and reaffirmed its “substantial nexus requirement,” holding that there must be a physical presence by a company in a state for that state to require the collection of taxes from consumers.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding these three decisions, the Supreme Court has left unresolved what exactly constitutes physical presence. Does the law require an actual physical presence, such as a “brick-and-mortar” store? Or can some other minimal connection such as in-state advertisements or traveling salespeople satisfy the physical presence requirement? Also, thus far, no court has specifically addressed <italic>nexus</italic> in relation to Internet sales of goods, much less the interstate sale of services. <italic>Quill</italic> remains the guiding law. The decisions do not prevent vendors from voluntarily collecting sales tax, which in fact some Internet vendors do collect, but they do prohibit states from requiring vendors to collect the tax if they do not have nexus. Until either Congress acts or the Supreme Court revisits the rule articulated in <italic>Quill</italic>, the ability of states to tax Internet sales of goods or services will remain doubtful.</p>
<p>The issue of nexus was critical in a recent decision of the South Carolina Supreme Court.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-1938965512438545">34</xref></sup> The OTC, Travelscape, appealed an administrative agency finding that it owed occupancy tax on the gross proceeds received from furnishing hotel accommodations in South Carolina. In ruling against Travelscape, the court held the OTC was in the business of furnishing accommodations in South Carolina even though it lacked physical presence there. Because the OTC entered into contracts with South Carolina hotels and sent its employees to South Carolina to conduct inspections and negotiate contracts, Travelscape had established and maintained a market within the state sufficient to satisfy the nexus requirement.</p>
<p>In reaching its decision, the South Carolina court relied heavily on a less celebrated 1987 U.S. Supreme Court decision, <italic>Tyler Pipe</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-1938965512438545">35</xref></sup> decided five years prior to <italic>Quill</italic>, in which the State of Washington imposed a sales tax on a corporation that manufactured products outside of Washington for in-state sale. The Supreme Court found the corporation had a physical presence in Washington even though it maintained no offices, owned no property, and had no employees in Washington. The corporation did have nonemployee in-state sales representatives who were essential to the corporation’s ability to make sales in Washington, including calling on customers and soliciting orders.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-1938965512438545">36</xref></sup> The decision of the South Carolina Supreme Court may have set the stage for an appeal by the OTC to the U.S. Supreme Court on the question of nexus.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1938965512438545">
<title>Legislative Solutions—Similarities to State Sales Tax Issues</title>
<p>The problem of occupancy taxes and OTCs is essentially the same problem that presents itself in a slightly different way in each of the fifty states. Each of the states may craft its own tax policy and may do so in a variety of ways, as long as it stays within the confines of the U.S. Constitution. Individual state legislatures can amend or enact legislation to clarify their position. The reason more states have not revised their laws is a function of both a lack of political will within the legislatures and genuine uncertainty of how to properly and effectively change the law without setting the stage for new round of court challenges based on the issue of nexus.</p>
<p>Even as states such as North Carolina amend their statutes to include the OTC markup, there remain critical questions that will be raised by the OTCs. Namely, is the purported occupancy tax actually a tax on services? Is the service being provided occurring in interstate commerce? If so, is there sufficient nexus to the taxing state to allow the imposition of a local tax?</p>
<p>If states tax the OTC markup as a service under existing laws or new legislation, the challenge facing the states will be similar in many respects to the problem they face in the collection of sales tax on Internet sales of goods. The debate over uncollected sales tax by companies like <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Amazon.com">Amazon.com</ext-link> has been going on since the birth of Internet sales, and the issues debated have much to teach us about the service tax liability on OTCs. States have long recognized that Internet sales are costing them significant tax revenues. As they begin to act to capture tax on goods sold on the Internet, they may address the issue of services at the same time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1938965512438545">
<title>A Model Statute for Taxing OTCs</title>
<p>In an effort to specifically address the problems faced by OTCs and municipal tax authorities, the Multistate Tax Commission, an advisory panel of tax experts representing the interests of the states, drafted the “Model Statute Clarifying the Tax Collection Responsibilities of Accommodations Intermediaries.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-1938965512438545">37</xref></sup> The model statute would require OTCs to collect and remit tax based on the price paid by the consumer. It would also allow each state to impose taxes differently. As the result of being poorly drafted and containing overly broad language, the proposal has for now been withdrawn.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-1938965512438545">38</xref></sup></p>
<p>The OTC industry’s position has been articulated in a letter to the National Conference of State Legislatures.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-1938965512438545">39</xref></sup> It proposes that OTCs collect and remit tax based on the wholesale price. It recommends that if OTC fees are taxed, they should be taxed by the state where the consumer is located (where the service, in its view, is received) and not the location of the hotel. It provides that the OTC not be required to disclose to consumers its fees or the amount of taxes on its fees. State legislatures are encouraged to decide the tax rate on OTCs’ fees separately from setting the occupancy tax. The rate could be the same, but whatever it is, it should be distinctly settled upon by legislatures rather than ambiguously included in a broad occupancy tax statute.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1938965512438545">
<title>Proposed Federal OTC Law</title>
<p>For the past two years, the Internet travel industry lobby, as represented by the Internet Travel Services Association (ITSA) and the Coalition for Internet Travel Tax Fairness, has been seeking enactment of federal law that would require the states to preempt municipal taxes on travel agency or booking services.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-1938965512438545">40</xref></sup> The bill embraces the merchant model: occupancy taxes would be based on the amounts hotels receive, collected by the OTC, and remitted to the municipality. The bill also provides that the states may tax online travel booking services, as long as the tax does not discriminate by only taxing online services. Finally, the proposed law addresses the “loophole” of possible wholesale evasion of occupancy taxes discussed in some of the decisions. The proposal prohibits hotels from creating joint ventures designed to shelter amounts paid by consumers from occupancy tax.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1938965512438545">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Lawsuits against OTCs for unpaid taxes are in various stages of litigation and continue to grow in number. In addition, many municipalities are conducting audits to determine whether taxes are due. Some have issued huge assessments against OTCs. The OTCs claim that they do not supply rooms but rather are in the business of providing a service and that occupancy taxes do not apply to the services they provide. Some courts have held that the OTCs are in fact “supplying” or “furnishing” rooms to consumers, and the OTCs must collect and remit occupancy taxes at the retail rate paid by consumers.</p>
<p>The states can and do impose taxes on <italic>services</italic>. However, when those services are being provided by an out-of-state entity, any local tax on these remote sellers is subject to judicial scrutiny to ascertain whether the company is sufficiently present in the locality to comport with the requirements of the commerce clause of the U.S. Constitution. The current patchwork of inconsistent, and sometimes contradictory, state and federal judicial decisions governing taxation of OTCs activities demands clarification.</p>
<p>There are two possible paths to clarification. First, the states can enact new laws that uniformly impose occupancy tax liability and state how the tax is to be collected and remitted. This would require a coalition of state lawmakers to draft a uniform law, which could then be adopted by the individual states. Such a law would establish a more uniform and simplified system to meet the requirements of the commerce clause. It would also ensure that out-of-state companies do not bear an unfair portion of tax burden. Congress would assist the states by establishing a legislative framework for the states to impose this tax. Given that this solution will require both congressional and state action, this scenario is not likely.</p>
<p>The second more likely path is through the U.S. Supreme Court. At this time, there are two U.S. Court of Appeals and two state supreme court decisions with conflicting results. The Court would need to resolve the question of who is furnishing rooms to consumers and whether the OTCs have sufficient presence in the states to satisfy the requirement of nexus. We believe that when state statutes are properly amended to include the activity of OTCs and when OTC representatives are physically present in a state, their activity satisfies the U.S. Constitution’s requirements for the taxation of out-of-state entities.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1938965512438545">
<label>1.</label>
<p><italic>City of Goodlettsville v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Priceline.com">Priceline.com</ext-link></italic>, 605 F. Supp. 2d 982 (M.D. Tenn. 2009).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1938965512438545">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Ibid., 985.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1938965512438545">
<label>3.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1938965512438545">Henchman (2010)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1938965512438545">
<label>4.</label>
<p><italic>Louisville/Jefferson County Metro Gov’t v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, L.P.</italic>, 590 F.3d 381, 389 (6th Cir. Ky., 2009).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1938965512438545">
<label>5.</label>
<p><italic>City of Charleston and Town of Mt. Pleasant, S.C. v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, L.P.</italic>, 520 F. Supp. 2d 757, 768 (D.S.C. 2007).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1938965512438545">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Ibid., 570.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1938965512438545">
<label>7.</label>
<p><italic>City of San Antonio v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link></italic>, U.S. District Court for the Western District of Texas, San Antonio Division, 2011 U.S. Dist. Lexis 72665 (July 1, 2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1938965512438545">
<label>8.</label>
<p>285 Ga. 684, 681 S.E.2d 122 (2009).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1938965512438545">
<label>9.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1938965512438545">Gilroy (2009)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1938965512438545">
<label>10.</label>
<p><italic>Pitt County v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, L.P.</italic>, 553 F.3d 308 (4th Cir. 2009).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1938965512438545">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Ibid., 313.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1938965512438545">
<label>12.</label>
<p><italic>CCH Sales &amp; Use Tax Alert</italic> (2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1938965512438545">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1938965512438545">
<label>14.</label>
<p>U.S. Const. Art. I, § 8, cl. 3.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1938965512438545">
<label>15.</label>
<p><italic>City of Charleston and Town of Mt. Pleasant, S.C. v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, LP, 520 F. Supp. 2d 757 (D.S.C 2007).</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1938965512438545">
<label>16.</label>
<p>Ibid., 766 n6.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1938965512438545">
<label>17.</label>
<p><italic>Expedia, Inc. v. The City of New York Department of Finance</italic>, 1st Judicial District, No.650761/09 (October 21, 2010).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1938965512438545">
<label>18.</label>
<p>New York City, Local Law 43, Laws 2009.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1938965512438545">
<label>19.</label>
<p><italic>Expedia, Inc. v. The City of New York Department of Finance, 1st Judicial District, No.650761/09, October 21, 2010.</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-1938965512438545">
<label>20.</label>
<p>New York Unconsolidated Law, Ch.288-C, §1.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-1938965512438545">
<label>21.</label>
<p><italic>Expedia, Inc. v. The City of New York Department of Finance, 1st Judicial District, No.650761/09, October 21, 2010.</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-1938965512438545">
<label>22.</label>
<p><italic>City of Charleston and Town of Mt. Pleasant, S.C. v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, LP, 520F.3d 381 (6th Cir. Ky., 2009).</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-1938965512438545">
<label>23.</label>
<p><italic>Louisville/Jefferson County Metro Gov’t v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, L.P., 590 F.3d 381 (6th Cir, Ky., 2009).</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-1938965512438545">
<label>24.</label>
<p>Ibid., 384.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-1938965512438545">
<label>25.</label>
<p><italic>City of Charleston and Town of Mt. Pleasant, S.C. v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, LP, 520 F. Supp. 2d 757, 770 (D.S.C. 2007).</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-1938965512438545">
<label>26.</label>
<p><italic>City of Philadelphia v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link></italic>, No. 860, 2006 Phila. Ct. Com. Pl. LEXIS 218 (Pa. C.P. Phila. May 25, 2006).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-1938965512438545">
<label>27.</label>
<p>Information taken from the Form 10-K of the United States Securities and Exchange Commission, Annual Report Pursuant to Section 13 or 15(d) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, for the fiscal year ended December 31, 2010. Commission File No.: 0-25581, Expedia, Inc. footnote 33.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-1938965512438545">
<label>28.</label>
<p><italic>City of Charleston and Town of Mt. Pleasant, S.C. v. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Hotels.com">Hotels.com</ext-link>, LP, 520 F. Supp. 2d 757, 776 (D.S.C. 2007).</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-1938965512438545">
<label>29.</label>
<p>22 U.S. 1 (1824).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-1938965512438545">
<label>30.</label>
<p><italic>National Bellas Hess, Inc. v. Dept. of Revenue of Illinois</italic>, 386 U.S. 753,759 (1967).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-1938965512438545">
<label>31.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-1938965512438545">
<label>32.</label>
<p><italic>Complete Auto Transit, Inc. v. Brady</italic>, 429 U.S. 813 (1976).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-1938965512438545">
<label>33.</label>
<p><italic>Quill Corp. v. North Dakota</italic>, 504 U.S. 298 (1992).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-1938965512438545">
<label>34.</label>
<p><italic>Travelscape, LLC. v. South Carolina Department of Revenue</italic>, 391 S.C. 89; 705 S.E.2d 28 (2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-1938965512438545">
<label>35.</label>
<p><italic>Tyler Pipe Industries, Inc. v. Washington State Department of Revenue</italic>, 483 U.S. 232 (1987).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-1938965512438545">
<label>36.</label>
<p>Ibid., 250.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-1938965512438545">
<label>37.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1938965512438545">Henchman (2010)</xref>, 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-1938965512438545">
<label>38.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-1938965512438545">
<label>39.</label>
<p>Walter Hellerstein to National Conference of State Legislatures, 16 July 2009, “Views of Walter Hellerstein Regarding Proposals for Taxing Services of Travel Intermediaries,” as quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1938965512438545">Hamilton (2009)</xref>, 661, 664.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-1938965512438545">
<label>40.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1938965512438545">Hamilton (2009)</xref>, 661, 664.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Arthur Hamilton</bold> received his J.D. from the University of South Carolina in 1974. He has been admitted to the Bar in Maine, South Carolina and Virginia. He has been a Professor of Business Law at James Madison University since 1975. His primary focus is contract, commercial law and taxation.</p>
<p><bold>Hugh Hobson</bold> received a Ph.D. in finance from the University of Georgia in 1976 and a J.D. from Loyola University of New Orleans in 1983. In 2011 he was awarded Professor Emeritus at James Madison University. He is currently Visiting Professor of Finance at the University of the District of Columbia. Primary interests are corporate finance and real estate.</p>
<p><bold>S. Brooks Marshall</bold> received his Doctorate in finance from the University of Virginia and received his Chartered Financial Analyst designation in 1986. Since that time he has been employed at James Madison University in the Department of Finance and Business Law.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1938965512438545">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>CCH Sales &amp; Use Tax Alert</collab>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>Online travel companies challenge N.C. tax on accommodations</article-title>. <volume>31</volume>, no. 4 (<month>March</month> <day>1</day>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1938965512438545">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Georgia Supreme Court: Online travel firm facilitation fee subject to hotel tax</article-title>. <source>Elec. Com. &amp; L. Rep. (BNA)</source> <volume>14</volume> (<month>June</month> <day>18</day>): <fpage>848</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1938965512438545">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Billy</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Shirt tales and online travel companies</article-title>. <source>State Tax Law Notes</source>, <month>November</month> <day>30</day>, p. <fpage>54</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1938965512438545">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henchman</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Cities pursue discriminatory taxation of online travel services, special report</article-title>. <publisher-name>Tax Foundation</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington D.C.</publisher-loc>, Local Law 43, Laws 2009. <month>February</month> <day>3</day>. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.taxfoundation.org/files/sr175.pdf">http://www.taxfoundation.org/files/sr175.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>