<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NVS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnvs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0899-7640</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7395</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0899764012462457</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0899764012462457</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Symposium: Faith-Based Organizations in Context, Edited by Jo Anne Schneider</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Unintended Consequence of the Faith-Based Initiative</article-title>
<subtitle>Organizational Practices and Religious Identity Within Faith-Based Human Service Organizations</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>Jill Witmer</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0899764012462457">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0899764012462457"><label>1</label>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, Camden, NJ, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0899764012462457">Jill Witmer Sinha, MDiv, PhD, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, School of Social Work, 217 N. 6th Street, Camden, NJ 08102, USA. Email: <email>jilsinha@ssw.rutgers.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>563</fpage>
<lpage>583</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association For Research On Nonprofit Organizations And Voluntary Action</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The faith-based initiative announced in 2001 was accompanied by media coverage, new funding mechanisms, and state-level policies requiring the inclusion of faith-based organizations (FBOs) in Requests for Proposals. This study examined 33 organizations’ expression of religious identity through (a) proportion of board and (b) staff who were coreligionist; (c) change in proportion of revenues from public sources; (d) strategies for seeking resources; and (e) religious elements in service provision, staff training, and board meeting procedures. Interview transcripts from the Faith and Organizations Project, annual reports, and financial information were examined. Analysis suggested four patterns (no change, increased government funding related to the faith-based initiative, strategies for seeking resources, and active preservation of religious identity). Four African American organizations received funding connected to the faith-based initiative and 14 utilized or preserved religious identity. Faith-based policies are discussed as inadvertently affirming organizational distinctiveness and religious identity among some faith-based organizations.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>faith-based initiative</kwd>
<kwd>human service organizations</kwd>
<kwd>organizational change</kwd>
<kwd>religious identity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Social services in the United States have long been provided through religiously affiliated organizations. However, the faith-based initiative signaled a new era of inclusion and increased partnership between the federal government and human service organizations, which were strongly religiously affiliated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0899764012462457">Hein, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0899764012462457">Rogers &amp; Dionne, 2008</xref>). More than a decade after the creation of the White House Office of Faith-based and Community Initiatives (referred to in this article as White House Office), is there evidence that faith-based organizations (FBOs) were affected internally by the widely publicized initiative? This study searched within organizations for change in (a) the proportion of coreligionists who serve on the board, (b) the proportion of coreligionists who make up the staff, (c) change in proportion of revenues from public sources, (d) strategies for seeking resources from the wider community, and (e) change in organization’s use of religious elements related to service provision, staff training, and board meeting procedures. In-depth qualitative data from 33 organizations in the Faith and Organizations (F&amp;O) project offered rich case studies with which to assess this question.</p>
<sec id="section1-0899764012462457">
<title>Background: Charitable Choice and the Faith-Based Initiative, 1996-2010</title>
<p>The faith-based initiative refers to policy and administrative changes set in motion 15 years ago, which aimed to “level the playing field” for a wider pool of partners for the delivery of government-funded social services. In 1996, the Welfare Reform Law enacted under President Bill Clinton included the Charitable Choice provision, which identified FBOs, including congregations, as eligible to apply for public funds. The legislation promised equal footing with secular agencies for the purpose of providing social services and clarified restrictions on the use of funds for religious activities or materials. In 2001, President George W. Bush issued an executive order that established the White House Office and expanded outreach to faith-based nonprofits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0899764012462457">Office of Housing and Urban Development, 2001</xref>). A Compassion Capital Fund was created that supported grants through intermediary organizations for youth development, prisoner reintegration, and welfare-to-work programs. Subsequently, state-level offices to liaise with the faith-based community were created. By 2006 more than half the states had a faith-based office and about a fifth of direct <italic>federal</italic> contracts (17%) went to faith-based or religious organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0899764012462457">Montiel &amp; Wright, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0899764012462457">Ragan &amp; Wright, 2005</xref>). However, very little new funding was appropriated through state offices: 29 out of 35 state-level faith-based liaisons reported almost no funding outside of their salary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012462457">Sager, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>A quick review of two federal funding streams indicates that FBOs remain a minority of federal grant recipients: The Department of Education’s Profile and Performance Information Collection System indicates that out of 4,418 21st-Century Community Learning Centers’ grantees between 2002 and 2010, less than 1%, or 130, were faith based; Weed and Seed data, available from the Office of Justice Programs’ Community Capacity Development Office, shows 7% of grantees were faith based.</p>
<p>Despite the allure of cost-effective “armies of compassion” mobilized through congregations and FBOs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0899764012462457">Owens &amp; Smith, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0899764012462457">Sinha, Jones, Cnaan, &amp; Dichter, 2003</xref>), lack of funding, lack of coordination and regulation of policies at state and local levels, and lack of capacity among smaller faith-based providers resulted in little substantial change in service capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0899764012462457">Kennedy &amp; Bielefeld, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0899764012462457">Monsma, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0899764012462457">Wineburg, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012462457">2007</xref>). Smaller faith-based providers remain underresourced in terms of funding, workers, and experience in professional service provision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012462457">Sager, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Outside of these criticisms, changes in state-level legislation enforced the inclusion of FBOs in government-contracted service provision in several ways. First, language on grants and executive orders must be inclusive of faith-based providers. Second, states must monitor intermediary agencies’ inclusion of faith-based providers in Requests for Proposals. Inclusion of FBOs has been carried out through state-sponsored conferences to assist FBOs with grant-writing and awareness of funding, distribution of funding when available, and including representatives from the faith community on advisory boards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012462457">Sager, 2010</xref>). Third, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0899764012462457">Chaves (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0899764012462457">Ragan and Wright (2005)</xref> noted other state-level incentives targeted at smaller faith-based providers, including scaled-down contract sizes, grants for capacity building and start-up, technical assistance, and encouraging contractors to subcontract with FBOs.</p>
<p>The current administration has done little to dismantle or alter policies implemented under the faith-based initiative. In 2008, the former office was retitled the “White House Office of Faith-Based and Neighborhood Partnerships” and the priorities focused on connecting faith- and community-based organizations to initiatives on economic recovery, healthy fatherhood, reduced teen pregnancy and abortion, maternal and child health, interreligious dialogue and building the capacity of community-based human service organizations. One mechanism to support these initiatives was the Strengthening Communities Fund (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0899764012462457">DuBois, 2009</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0899764012462457">1</xref></sup>; The administration pledged support for community-based efforts and faith-based providers, but as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0899764012462457">Campbell’s (2011)</xref> longitudinal study of 40 organizations suggested, faith-based policies have failed to support the long-term integration of faith-based service providers into an existing continuum of service delivery, nor has their capacity increased (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012462457">Sager, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012462457">Wineburg, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>If the faith-based initiative did not increase the amount of services being provided through FBOs, have other impacts been observed <italic>within</italic> organizations? Some scholars questioned whether faith-based providers who contracted with the government would also become more secularized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0899764012462457">Chambre, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0899764012462457">Chaves, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0899764012462457">Jeavons, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0899764012462457">Smith &amp; Sosin, 2001</xref>). Others observed that FBOs who used government funding maintained a strong religious identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0899764012462457">Monsma, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0899764012462457">Vanderwoerd, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>This study adds to the discussion by examining evidence for organizational change in FBOs since 2001, which may have been influenced by the faith-based initiative. Change in organizational religious identity was examined through (a) the proportion of board members who are coreligionist, (b) proportion of staff members who are coreligionist, (c) change in proportion of revenues from public sources, (d) strategies for seeking resources from the wider community, and (e) change in organization’s use of religious elements related to service provision, staff training, and board meeting procedures, in relation to subsequent media coverage, funding mechanisms, and state-level policy changes connected to the faith-based initiative.</p>
<p>Several organizational factors were examined in relation to change. These factors include denomination, size, and years in existence, as well as the system type of an organization. System type refers to three different ways that FBOs are related to a sponsoring faith community. The institutional system centralizes this relationship, while congregational systems retain the most autonomy at the level of the congregation, and networked systems form and operate independently from a congregation or regional religious body. Accordingly, institutional, larger, and more established organizations were expected to be less responsive to federal funding, media, and policy changes, whereas smaller and newer congregational and networked organizations were expected to be more responsive and to be more likely to indicate change in one or more of the five areas.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0899764012462457">
<title>Description of System Type</title>
<p>Organizations vary—in governance style, size, complexity, funding mix, and other characteristics. As noted, unlike secular organizations FBOs also vary in how they are connected to the congregations or faith communities who initiated them and the level of control exerted by regional affiliates or denominational networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0899764012462457">Demerath, Hall, Schmitt, &amp; Williams, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0899764012462457">Pipes &amp; Ebaugh, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0899764012462457">Polson, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0899764012462457">Sosin &amp; Smith, 2006</xref>). The variable organizational system type emerged during prior analysis of the F&amp;O data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0899764012462457">Schneider &amp; Morrison, 2009</xref>; see also Schneider, this issue). System type was found to differentiate organizations’ relationship to their founding community and its impact on organizational culture and administrative structure. Therefore, system type was used along with denomination to simplify the variation in administrative structures by dividing the 33 organizations into 3 system types: institutionalized, congregational, and networked. This division enabled an examination of whether system type appeared to differentiate organizations’ expression of religious identity.</p>
<p><italic>Institutionalized</italic> systems are found within Jewish and Catholic traditions, where governance, collection and distribution of resources, and service provision are highly centralized through adjudicatory and federated bodies connecting the local and national levels. The entire community subscribes to the founding principle that the collective body is responsible for those in need. The highly centralized, institutional systems primarily use denomination-based networks to solicit volunteers and donations. <italic>Congregational</italic> systems are characteristic in Mainline Protestant, Quaker, some African American, and Evangelical traditions. These denominations have regional bodies with some oversight of collection and distribution of resources, but typically governance and service initiatives are carried out at local, congregational levels. Some congregational organizations mature and spin off into independent organizations with limited or informal ties to their sponsoring congregation(s). <italic>Networked</italic> systems typically transcend congregations and grow from a founder’s personal and institutional networks. Networked types are member based; their membership comprises individuals and organizations who share a similar vision. Fundraising often occurs through a network of private or member supporters rather than established institutional networks. Networked systems are prominent in the Evangelical tradition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0899764012462457" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods: Data Source and Analysis</title>
<p>This study utilized F&amp;O “Maintaining Connections” (2008-2009, Phase 1) data from religiously affiliated or faith-based nonprofits within African American, Catholic, Evangelical, Jewish, Mainline Protestant, and Quaker traditions. The F&amp;O project examined connectedness between nonprofits and their sponsoring faith community and not data on actual service provision or program outcomes. During the original data collection, key informant interviews with executive directors, staff, volunteers, pastors, and board members were conducted with 40 nonprofit organizations and their sponsoring faith community. The organizations were located in Baltimore, Philadelphia, and Washington, D.C. In addition to interview transcripts, field notes from participant observation of daily operations, board meetings, and other community and organization events were used. F&amp;O researchers coded documents from each organization using the coding scheme developed for the project.</p>
<p>For this analysis, seven pairs of organizations were excluded. One organization dissolved before data collection was completed, two sponsoring bodies merged, and four organizations had insufficient data to determine change.</p>
<p>NVivo 8 was used to search interview transcripts, field notes, annual reports, and published documents from the remaining 33 organizations and their founding religious partner(s) using terms that were developed to correspond with the original F&amp;O coding scheme. The selection of additional search terms was guided by two typologies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0899764012462457">Jeavons (1998)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0899764012462457">Unruh and Sider (2004)</xref> developed categories that describe the expression of religious values in organizations. The following categories guided the search within transcripts, field notes, annual reports, and other published documents:</p>
<list id="list1-0899764012462457" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p><italic>Board composition</italic>: Interviewers asked respondents what proportion of the board were from the sponsoring community of faith, what proportion were coreligionists, and whether the bylaws required this. Descriptions of how board members and executive directors were recruited and selected were examined, including whether the process was intentional and/or informal.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Staff composition</italic>: Interviewers asked respondents what proportion of the staff were from the sponsoring community, what proportion were coreligionists, and whether any statement of faith, lifestyle, or beliefs was a condition for employment. If hiring decisions were influenced by an applicant’s religious beliefs or membership in a religious tradition, this was noted, along with whether this was formally required or implied.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Change in proportion of revenues from public sources</italic>: Transcripts, field notes, annual reports, and published documents were searched for description of revenue sources, including fee-for-service (tuition), private contributions and fundraising, versus public grants or contracts from federal and state government. Based on reported total revenues, it was estimated whether government funding awarded after 2001 represented a significant increase to the total budget.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Strategies for seeking resources from the wider community</italic>: How and from where organizations sought additional or in-kind and monetary resources from the wider faith community was examined.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Use of religious elements in service provision, staff training, or board meeting procedures</italic>: Transcripts, field notes, annual reports, and published documents were searched for discussions of training for staff or board members, day-to-day descriptions of service provision to clients, and descriptions of board meeting procedures. References to prayer, scripture, religious beliefs, or explanations of why certain religious practices are carried out were examined.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Additional key word searches using terms from the original F&amp;O coding scheme were used to find sections of text that referenced ways that organizations’ religious mission, values, scripture, or history were reflected in daily operations, such as service provision or practices of board meetings. Text that related to the five areas were recoded and analyzed for change that occurred after 2001. Information reported in transcripts and field notes, such as board and staff composition and size, sources of revenues, and age of the organization, was confirmed using published annual reports, GuideStar USA, and organization websites.</p>
<sec id="section4-0899764012462457">
<title>Description of the Sample</title>
<p>The 33 organizations were fairly evenly divided among the 6 faith traditions, including African American (5, 15%), Catholic (8, 24%), Evangelical (6, 18%), Jewish (4, 12%), Mainline Protestant (5, 15%), and Quaker (5, 15%). As displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0899764012462457">Table 1</xref>, by system type, half of the organizations in the study were congregational (17, 51%); about one quarter were institutional (9, 27%) and the remaining were networked (7, 21%). All of the Jewish and five of the eight Catholic organizations were institutional. All but one African American and all the Quaker organizations were congregational. Mainline Protestant and Evangelical organizations were split between congregational and networked system types. Types of social services provided included: schools (9, 27%); relief (6, 18%), senior services (4, 12%), Community Development Corporations (CDC; 4, 12%), social service such as mental health or counseling (4, 12%), housing (3, 9%), individual development such as adult education or training (2, 6%), and one hospital.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0899764012462457" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Denomination, Service Type, Board and Staff Composition, and Change Category by System Type.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0899764012462457" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012462457-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Denominational affiliation</th>
<th align="center">Service types provided</th>
<th align="center">Board and staff (size,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0899764012462457">a</xref></sup> percent coreligionist<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012462457">b</xref></sup>)</th>
<th align="center">Years in existence</th>
<th align="center">Change category</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="5">Institutional (<italic>n</italic> = 9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Jewish</td>
<td>Senior/Other</td>
<td>Board (11, 99%), and staff (60, 60%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>Hospital</td>
<td>Board (19, 25%), and staff (6,500; &lt;25%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>Individual development</td>
<td>Board (25, 75%), and staff (25, 50%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Jewish</td>
<td>Individual development</td>
<td>Board (45, 100%), and staff (100, 95%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>Social service/relief/individual development</td>
<td>Board (24, 100%), and staff (800, 15%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Jewish</td>
<td>School</td>
<td>Board (18, 98%), and staff (82, 90%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Jewish</td>
<td>Senior/housing</td>
<td>Board (30, 100%), and staff (18, 75%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>School</td>
<td>Board (20, 80%), and staff (100, 80%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>School</td>
<td>Board (25, 90%), and staff (80, 80%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="5">Congregational (<italic>n</italic> = 17)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical</td>
<td>Relief/shelter/individual development</td>
<td>Board (9, 100%), and staff (45, 10%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline</td>
<td>Housing</td>
<td>Board (25, 50%), and staff (45, not available)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline</td>
<td>Housing/relief</td>
<td>Board (35, 50%), and staff (25, 20%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline</td>
<td>Relief</td>
<td>Board (13, 50%), and staff (2, 100%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>School/individual development</td>
<td>Board (9, 90%), and staff (12, 80%)</td>
<td>&lt;10</td>
<td>FUNDING</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>CDC/individual development</td>
<td>Board (9, 100%), and staff (20, 75%)</td>
<td>&lt;10</td>
<td>FUNDING</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>School/individual development</td>
<td>Board (13, 75%), and staff (35, 80%)</td>
<td>&lt;10</td>
<td>FUNDING</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline</td>
<td>Social service—immigrants</td>
<td>Board (15, 100%), and staff (100, 10%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quaker</td>
<td>School</td>
<td>Board (26, 40%), and staff (35, 5%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quaker</td>
<td>Senior/housing</td>
<td>Board (19, 95%), and staff (100, 5%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>RELIG IDENTITY</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>School/CDC</td>
<td>Board (24, 75%), and staff (75, 50%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical</td>
<td>Relief/individual development</td>
<td>Board (20, 100%), and staff (25, 100%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical</td>
<td>Relief</td>
<td>Board (0, not available), and staff (0, not available)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quaker</td>
<td>Senior/housing</td>
<td>Board (18, 100%), and staff (60, 5%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>N0 CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quaker</td>
<td>School</td>
<td>Board (13, 50%), and staff (25, 40%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Quaker</td>
<td>Social service/individual development</td>
<td>Board (20, 95%), and staff (7, 20%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline</td>
<td>CDC/individual development</td>
<td>Board (9, 90%), and staff (20, 25%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="5">Networked (<italic>n</italic> = 7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>Relief</td>
<td>Board (12, 50%), and staff (6, 75%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>Housing/development</td>
<td>Board (13, 50%), and staff (40, 40%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>STRATEGIES</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> African American</td>
<td>CDC /individual development</td>
<td>Board (12, 95%), and staff (8, 75%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>FUNDING</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical</td>
<td>Relief/individual development</td>
<td>Board (5, 90%), and staff (8, 100%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical</td>
<td>CDC/individual development</td>
<td>Board (7, not available), and staff (1, not available)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical</td>
<td>School</td>
<td>Board (11, 80%), and staff (140, 100%)</td>
<td>&gt;30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>Social service/ individual development</td>
<td>Board (25, 50%), and staff (5, 50%)</td>
<td>10-30</td>
<td>NO CHANGE</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0899764012462457">
<p>Note: CDC = Community Development Corporation.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0899764012462457">
<label>a</label>
<p>The “staff” number includes paid, full-time staff and does not reflect volunteers.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0899764012462457">
<label>b</label>
<p>This percent was the proportion of members who were reported from the same religious background as the Denominational Affiliation/faith community of the organization.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The organizations ranged in age from less than 10 to more than 100 years in existence. Institutional organizations were oldest with a mean of 71 (median of 60) years in existence. Congregational organizations averaged 45 (median of 30) years in existence. Networked organizations were newest, with an average of 25 (median of 20) years of existence. The three youngest organizations (less than 10 years old) were African American, congregational organizations. Governing boards ranged in size from 9 to 45 members and paid staff ranged from 0 to 6,500. The largest organizations were institutional with an average size of 862 staff (median of 82 staff). Congregational organizations had an average size of 37 (median of 25) staff, and networked organizations were the smallest with an average size of 30 (median of 8) staff.</p>
<p>This study is limited by its sample size and purposive sampling. The F&amp;O project purposefully recruited organizations within six denominations, which had varying degrees of connection to the original sponsoring community of faith, thus portraying the three system types. Findings are not representative of all faith-based nonprofits.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0899764012462457">
<title>Findings: Categories of Change Regarding Use of Religious Identity</title>
<p>From the reiterative search process, four patterns emerged: Some organizations did not report change in the five areas (no change), some organizations changed primarily in new government funding (funding), some organizations changed primarily in strategies for seeking resources from the wider community to meet increased or evolving service needs (strategies), and some organizations reviewed and/or revised ways in which religious identity was expressed through service provision, staff training, and within board meetings (religious identity).</p>
<sec id="section6-0899764012462457">
<title>No Change</title>
<p>About two fifths of organizations (<italic>n</italic> = 14) indicated no change in proportion of board or staff members who were coreligionist, primary sources of revenue; resourcing strategies, or religious elements related to service provision, hiring requirements, staff training, or board meeting procedures. Change was particularly absent among five out of six Evangelical organizations in the sample, of which four provided relief (food, shelter, counseling, or referrals), one CDC that provided counseling services, and one school that provided K-12 education. About half of the organizations reporting no change tended to be small: They had relatively smaller budgets, fewer than 20 staff, and their volunteers and boards were comprised primarily of members of the founding congregation or a similar faith tradition. Two of these organizations, the school and a pregnancy counseling center, required staff and board members to sign a statement of faith and adhere to certain practices, but these practices were in place prior to 2001.</p>
<p>Five larger organizations did not report overall change. These included two Catholic (institutional) schools, one Quaker school, a federally funded Head Start program provided by an African American CDC (congregational) since the late 1960s, and one Jewish organization that provided senior housing (institutional). The schools in this category were relatively large, were established more than 10 years ago, and reported tuition as their primary funding source (75% to 85%). In these cases, the organizations did not use a significant amount of public (state or federal) funding.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0899764012462457">
<title>Change in Proportion of Public Funding Related to the Faith-Based Initiative</title>
<p>A distinct subset of this sample—four out of the five African American organizations—received new funding through mechanisms that were introduced or amended in connection with faith-based policies. The federal funding sources were the Healthy Marriage Initiative, 21st-Century Community Learning Centers, the Compassion Capital Fund, and the Weed and Seed initiative.</p>
<p>The new funding, such as US$2 million for a community-based parenting and marriage counseling program and US$400,000 to expand preschool and early education programming, reflected significant growth in the proportion of their revenues from a public source. The multiyear structure and size of the grants represented significant increases to total revenues and substantially changed the reported revenue mix: After receiving the grants, the organizations reported 75% to 95% of their revenues as public.</p>
<p>These organizations reported development in relation to the increased funding. Two organizations applied for 501-c-3 status and developed a separate governing board for the expanded program. Several hired additional staff, bought or utilized additional space, and used the federal funding to leverage additional funding. Key administrative staff, board members, and some volunteers were members of the founding congregations, and this is characteristic of African American congregational programs, which remain strongly affiliated with the founding congregation(s) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0899764012462457">Sinha, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0899764012462457">Unruh, Sinha, &amp; Belcher, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The development that occurred through these four funding mechanisms is the type of capacity building that was intended by Charitable Choice–related announcements of 2001 and 2004 and is the only area of change that was directly attributable to faith-based policy initiatives. If federal funds had not been awarded, it is unlikely these relatively newer and smaller African American organizations would have experienced comparable development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0899764012462457">
<title>Strategies for Seeking Resources From the Wider Community</title>
<p>The following organizations reported change that was termed “strategies for seeking resources from the wider community” to describe organizations’ response to increased or evolving service demand. Overall, 10 organizations reported an increase in service demand, and two strategies for raising resources were observed. The first strategy was distinctive because organizations specifically targeted outreach to the sponsoring faith community and the larger faith community. For example, several organizations hired ministers to spearhead outreach to congregations. One Mainline Protestant congregational housing organization created a new staff position and hired an ordained minister to conduct outreach. The minister reported, “We have exponentially increased the number of faith partners that we have . . . without losing all our corporate partners, our school partners.” This organization also initiated a new fundraising project, which appealed specifically to the faith community. The organization published a book using Muslim, Jewish, and Christian teachings about providing shelter. These strategies emphasized the organization’s religious mandate and appeal within the faith community, even though their service provision was not explicitly religious. There were no formal religious requirements for hiring or for training staff and no formal directives for volunteers.</p>
<p>A very similar strategy was observed in a large Catholic, institutional social services organization that implemented a “parish program” in 2008 to better connect local parishes with social services and to advertise volunteer opportunities. The newly hired parish program director, also a minister, reported, “We’re going from parish to parish, talking to the pastors, talking to the social concerns [director of ministries/outreach] person. . . . How can we leverage those relationships to get our program and our agency in front of everyone in the pew?” These examples reflect outreach to an established community of faith to seek resources and volunteers or to market services.</p>
<p>A second strategy in response to increased demand for services was observed. Several organizations formalized internal policies or expectations for board members, executive directors, employees, and member organizations, or formalized accounting practices in order to garner additional resources, such as donations, volunteers, in-kind services, or to comply with external funder’s expectations. Several Mainline Protestant congregational and smaller organizations—all less than 30 years old, hired new executive directors, recruited board members with certain skills or connections, or clarified the role of member organizations in order to better utilize member and volunteer resources.</p>
<p>Similarly, one large Evangelical congregational 100-year-old agency that provided multiple relief services (food, clothing, and temporary shelter) responded to increased service demand by hiring a new executive director who planned to make accounting practices more transparent in order to apply for external funding. The organization remained strongly connected to its founding denomination—its large board was composed of men from 80-plus congregations and its governing board was composed of 9 men from the founding denomination.</p>
<p>A Catholic networked organization that provided up to 500 meals per day with 125 volunteers (6 staff) also recently hired a new executive director who observed the following: The number of board members had decreased, members with specific skills and networks were being recruited, and board members were expected to take more of a strategic role in guiding the organization. The religious identity of the organization appeared to remain stable: The board remained about half Catholic, and the founder of the organization was present on a regular basis despite her increasing age. Her presence, it was observed, set the culture and religious tone of the organization. Prayer was offered with volunteers and staff before the meal was served.</p>
<p>In this second pattern of resource raising, religious identity appeared to be stable, with two exceptions. Two organizations in this category reported strategies that appeared to de-emphasize religious identity in order to accommodate increased need or change in constituents or clientele. One organization removed the word “Jewish” from its center name, and a large hospital voted to reduce the number of Sisters from the Founding Order required on its executive board because of difficulty finding replacements from within the Order. Both of these organizations were institutional, were larger (60 to 6,500 staff), and were more than 30 years old.</p>
<p>In general in the “strategies” patterns, organizational changes did not appear to be in response to faith-based policies and change was not reported in funding sources, or in religious elements related to service provision, hiring requirements, staff training, or board meeting procedures. The “strategies” category suggest that religious identity can be emphasized or de-emphasized, for example, to appeal to certain constituents and raise resources in response to changing service demands.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0899764012462457">
<title>Active Preservation of Religious Identity</title>
<p>The category “active preservation of religious identity” was characterized by concern about the expression of an organization’s religious identity and was reflected through intentional processes to examine religious identity or values. Such processes included discussion of religious elements in service provision, hiring requirements, staff training, or board meeting procedures. Several organizations in this category reviewed or added religious elements in training for staff or board members, particularly for those who were not coreligionists.</p>
<p>Within five organizations, formal reviews of mission were conducted. An established, large, Mainline Protestant congregational social service organization hired a new president in 2002 who implemented a visioning process among executive staff. Prior to 2000, staff described the organization, which had partnered with the government for 30 years to provide refugee assistance, as a “government agency” with less than 10% of staff who were coreligionists. The organization reported 94% of its revenues from the federal government. After the visioning process, a department was created both to reach out and respond to congregations’ concerns: The organization invested substantial funds to redesign its website and created video and print materials to be used for training and advocacy around refugee services and resettlement. This initiative was not reported as a response to increased service demand or for additional funding but as an attempt to engage congregations in service and as an expression of its founding religious mission of “serving the stranger.” The organization’s board remained essentially the same: Fifteen members, five of whom were required to be coreligionists and all of whom typically are.</p>
<p>A Catholic networked organization just over 10 years old also participated in a formal Order-sponsored “Sponsorship Review” process to “develop and ensure the sustainability of . . . that special quality that distinguishes [Order-sponsored] ministries. . . .” The executive director of the organization reported, “We have discovered that [the Founding Order]-ness is the very DNA of our program, without our necessarily having designed it that way!” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0899764012462457">School Sisters of Notre Dame, Atlantic Midwest Province, 2008</xref>). About half of the staff was Catholic, of which eight were Sisters. The governing board (28 members) included four Sisters from the Founding Order, and four additional Catholic members. At the regional level, one fifth of board members were Catholic and two trustees and the President of the Board were required to be Sisters of the Order.</p>
<p>In addition to the formal reviews, other examples of mission review were present. One Quaker senior residential program created a new “mission oversight board” to review how mission was expressed through service provision, and two Quaker schools’ boards discussed mission in relation to hiring decisions. As noted, none of these cases reported financial difficulty, nor was evaluating religious identity described primarily as an appeal to donors or as outreach for volunteers. These review processes reflect one way organizations preserved and expressed their founding mission.</p>
<p>An additional activity related to preservation of religious identity was observed through the revision or addition of religious elements present within training for staffs who were not coreligionists. Three schools and a community center introduced or revised training materials to include or expand religious elements, such as religious history or information about religious beliefs and practices. These changes were reported as a way to maintain a certain approach and culture within the organization rather than to attract new clients or donors. For example, a 30-year-old Jewish school remained strongly affiliated with its founding congregation: Almost all members of the predominantly Jewish board were also members of the congregation; the board had only recently changed its bylaws to include nonsynagogue members, and about a third of the 82 staff (90% Jewish) were also members of the congregation. In the year prior to the interview, the school initiated informal training for its non-Jewish staff on the meaning and practice of Jewish traditions, such as morning Minyan. These actions appeared to be put in place in order to preserve the strong religious identity of the school.</p>
<p>At a much larger Jewish community center, changing demographics in the service community also prompted choices which, in the end, served to preserve religious identity. By the late 1990s, the center had a larger proportion of younger Jewish and non-Jewish members, had expanded its daycare services and youth programming, and changed its name from a “location” to a major Jewish donor’s name. In 2001, after extensive deliberations, the board voted to open the facility on the Sabbath (Saturday), but this decision was reversed by the regional religious body that owned the building. The center recently began to celebrate additional cultural and religious elements, including Shabbat dinners, selling Challah, and “strongly encourage[ing]” staff to attend onsite bimonthly worship. The center continues to include religious elements in training for its few non-Jewish staff. The current executive director described these actions as “putting the J back in ‘JCC’.”</p>
<p>These examples of formal reviews and inclusion or revision of religious elements that emphasized religious identity cannot be interpreted as a direct response to faith-based policies or funding. They do appear to indicate concern and commitment to preserving and expressing religious identity within organizational culture.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0899764012462457" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This analysis used secondary data to examine internal organizational practices among FBOs during the decade since the faith-based initiative was announced. Five areas through which FBOs may express religious identity were examined: proportion of board and staff members who were coreligionists, change in revenues from public sources, strategies for seeking resources, and use of religious elements in service provision, staff training, or board meeting procedures. Furthermore, organizational system type, denomination, size, age, and type of service provided were used to compare highly varied types of organizations. Four categories emerged, which described whether a change was observed in the ways these FBOs expressed religious identity, from “no change” to “active preservation of religious identity.”</p>
<p>Fourteen (42%) or less than half of the organizations overall were categorized as having no change in the five areas. Among these organizations, some characteristics were similar. About half of the congregational and networked organizations that reported <italic>no change</italic> were smaller (average staff size of 28) and younger (30 or less years) organizations, with the exception of a large Evangelical school (140 staff) that had existed more than 30 years. This pattern corroborates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0899764012462457">Clerkin and Grønbjerg’s (2007)</xref> recent survey, which found that a majority of small and midsized FBOs remain either unaware or uninterested in seeking potential federal funding. In addition, all but one Evangelical organization reported no change. Among Evangelical organizations there may be a perception of service provision as a direct expression of obedience to a higher authority that, for some organizations, presents a conflict to accepting government grants or contracts. Schools (five out of the seven in the sample) also tended not to report change.</p>
<p>As expected, institutional, larger, and more established organizations were not responsive to federal funding connected to the faith-based initiative and the four organizations that were awarded federal funding were smaller and newer (three congregational and one networked). However, among institutional type organizations, almost half (four out of nine) reported activities that actively preserved aspects of religious identity, compared to less than one-fifth congregational types and no networked types, and this was not as expected. The four institutional organizations that preserved religious identity were Jewish and Catholic, had staff ranging in size from 25 to 800, were 30 or more years old, and provided individual development, social services, and primary education. The congregational organizations that preserved religious identity were similar in age and size; these three Mainline and Quaker organizations had staff ranging in size from 35 to 100, were 30 or more years old, and provided a school, a senior housing residence, and social services for immigrants.</p>
<p>The discussion proceeds by considering whether the changes that were observed in proportion of public funding, in strategies for seeking resources, and in preservation of religious identity could be related to funding and policies that were implemented in connection with the faith-based initiative. In this sample, four of five African American organizations that were strongly “under the care of” a community of faith applied for and received new funding through federal initiatives that explicitly required the inclusion of FBOs in their application process. Early faith-based initiative efforts to “court” the Black Church were sharply criticized by opponents such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0899764012462457">Barry Lynn (2003)</xref>, Americans United for Separation of Church and State, who stated, “The administration has been setting up how-to seminars to lure people, particularly African-American pastors, into hearing about this faith money, as one of their spokesmen calls it, and actually trying to convince them they might get some of it” (2005). Related concerns were expressed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0899764012462457">Mrs. Christensen (2001)</xref> “. . . I am insulted and deeply resent the way the administration has specifically courted the Black Church with this initiative. . . .”</p>
<p>Although limited to 33 organizations, this analysis supports the observation that a very particular subset of organizations responded to funding requests, and that FBOs were not <italic>equally impacted</italic> by legislation that encouraged inclusion and collaboration with the faith-based community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012462457">Sager, 2010</xref>). Some organizations were more likely to respond to the funding announcements: The four organizations that were awarded new funding in this sample were congregational and networked, less than 30 years old, African American, and smaller (8 to 35 staff) on average than other organizations. They provided primary education and community-based, individual development (CDCs), and remained strongly connected to their founding religious community through board appointments and staffing. This finding confirms two previous observations. First, African American organizations have been receptive to government funding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0899764012462457">Chaves &amp; Wineburg, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0899764012462457">Cnaan, Boddie, Handy, Yancey, &amp; Schneider, 2002</xref>). Second, African American organizations and congregations have traditionally engaged in providing the types of services that were prioritized through faith-based initiatives, namely, employment and economic development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0899764012462457">Boddie, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0899764012462457">Chaves, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0899764012462457">Littlefield, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0899764012462457">Owens &amp; Smith, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, however well these four African American organizations exemplify the intentions of the Clinton, Bush, and Obama administrations to include or expand the capacity of FBOs as service providers, this data also confirm that responsiveness to new funding sources and expansion of service delivery capacity among faith-based human service organizations is an isolated rather than widespread occurrence. These four cases thus substantiate the reality that very little <italic>new</italic> federal funding was distributed through the Compassion Capital fund and other appropriations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0899764012462457">Kennedy &amp; Bielefeld, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0899764012462457">Kramer, De Vita, Finegold &amp; Wherry, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0899764012462457">Kuo, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>In this sample, additional government collaboration or new funding was not observed among larger established social services organizations. Catholic Charities, Lutheran, and Jewish social services agencies were more likely to have preexisting service contracts with government through Medicaid, Community Block Grants, or through direct federal programs such as Head Start. Additional funding was sought through institutional organizations’ pooled resources and their existing member base, or through fee for service, not through additional government contracts.</p>
<p>However, neither does this analysis support an overall pattern of declining religious authority or trend toward secularization within these organizations. For the most part, FBOs in the sample, particularly those that were strongly faith based, preserved their fundamental religiously informed purpose while remaining accountable to dual administrative and religious authorities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0899764012462457">Weber, 1978</xref>). One explanation is that strategies that preserve or express religious identity make good business sense; they appeal to a particular portion of the donor base. A second explanation is that the strategies observed here, which preserved or which utilized religious identity, may reflect a broader willingness to talk about the religiously informed values that influence organization culture and service provision. I propose that changes associated with the faith-based initiative supported an atmosphere in which talking about an organization’s religious identity became an asset for some FBOs. These changes included the creation of the White House Office of Faith-Based and Community Initiatives, media coverage, policies that required (a) inclusive language on legislation and grant proposal requests, and (b) required faith-based providers and members of faith communities to be included on state-level advisory boards.</p>
<p>The data analyzed here cannot prove or disprove this interpretation. Further policy analysis might examine whether the inclusion of faith-based providers as “religious partners” who were not expected to alter their core mission, inadvertently affirmed organizations’ expression of religious identity through such characteristics as board and staff composition, resourcing strategies, and use of religious elements in training, service provision, board meeting procedures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0899764012462457">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>The failure of the faith-based initiative to increase partnerships with or expand social service provision by FBOs should not be equated with a lack of impact on FBOs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012462457">Sager (2010)</xref> concluded that faith-based practices implemented at state levels reshaped public understanding of the role that religion might play in government, and the role religious groups play in church–state collaboration. Likewise, faith-based policies that included FBOs as potential providers of federal and state grant-supported programming—without requiring that they fundamentally change their religious identity, signaled an acceptance of certain aspects of organizational culture that are informed by religious identity.</p>
<p>An organization’s religious heritage influences its decisions, from who is hired to who serves on the board, where resources are sought, which marketing strategies are used, how staff is trained, and how services are provided. Religious heritage and identity are an inherent part of what makes some organizations distinct, and, among nonprofits, having a distinctive mission has been theorized to contribute to organizational stability and longevity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0899764012462457">Salipante &amp; Golden-Biddle, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0899764012462457">Vanderwoerd, 2004</xref>). When an organization’s core identity and mission remain stable, it provides a constant which guides decision making. Organizations in this sample expressed and preserved their distinctive religious identity in multiple ways: High proportions of boards and 50% or more of staff were coreligionists; there was evidence of continuing use of religious elements in staff training, service provision, and board meeting procedures; and strategies for seeking resources targeted the religious membership base.</p>
<p>Stability and longevity among faith-based nonprofits are desirable, given the particular ways that faith-based providers appear to complement service delivery by other providers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0899764012462457">Campbell, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0899764012462457">Daly, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0899764012462457">Wineburg, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012462457">2007</xref>). In particular, FBOs have been found to provide a wider range of services or serve the neediest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0899764012462457">Chaves, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0899764012462457">Cnaan, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0899764012462457">Kearns, Park, &amp; Yankoski, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0899764012462457">Monsma, 2004</xref>). Unlike their secular counterparts, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0899764012462457">Reingold, Pirog, and Brady’s (2007)</xref> comparison of faith-based and secular service recipients found that recipients at FBOs were more likely to have experienced <italic>multiple and more extreme</italic> conditions of poverty and need, including unemployment, substance use, and lack of food, shelter, or utilities, than recipients of secular service providers. Campbell’s observation is equally striking: In California, FBOs that received funding through the state’s initiative served twice as many hard-to-employ recipients than other workforce development organizations. Participants at faith- and community-based organizations reported more individualized attention and referrals to at least one other community service agency. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0899764012462457">Kennedy and Bielefeld (2006)</xref> also found that strongly faith-based organizations were more likely to provide additional services to clients for which they were not reimbursed.</p>
<p>These studies suggest that policies that allow FBOs to retain their distinctive mission and way of doing business may support the organization’s stability and longevity as well as support a particular kind of service provision. In other words, although not necessarily expanding FBOs’ capacity for service provision, policies that allow FBOs the freedom to hire coreligionists and otherwise express their religious identity through the ways examined here may also support an important niche of providers for extremely needy and/or persons with multiple service needs.</p>
<p>Future systematic surveys and qualitative studies can examine whether there is a link between religious identity, distinctive practices, type of service recipient, and organizational sustainability. Continued discourse on the nature, relative quality, capacity, and constitutionality of implementing human services with public funds through faith-based and religious organizations remains necessary: The United States is becoming increasingly religiously pluralistic and faces continued impact of the recession on public resources and social welfare needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0899764012462457">Cnaan &amp; Boddie, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0899764012462457">Kramer et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0899764012462457">Smith, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0899764012462457">Smith, Bartkowski &amp; Grettenberger, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0899764012462457">Sosin &amp; Smith, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012462457">Wineburg, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>On the basis of this small but diverse sample, I have proposed here that faith-based policies inadvertently affirmed organizational distinctiveness and religious identity among some FBOs. Although less than half (42%) of organizations in the sample reported <italic>no change</italic>, including five out of the six Evangelical organizations, several schools and a Head Start program, the remaining organizations reported the following patterns of change. Four out of the five African American (three congregational and one networked) organizations reported <italic>Change in proportion of public funding related to the faith-based initiative</italic>, including a substantial shift in the proportion of funding from government and a resulting capacity development in organization staff and program size. One quarter or eight organizations reported <italic>Strategies for seeking resources from the wider community</italic>, including half whose strategies targeted the religious membership base and the other half formalized internal procedures to seek external resources. Six organizations reported <italic>Active preservation of religious identity</italic>, including formal reviews of mission or the addition of religious elements to staff training, service provision, or board meeting procedures. Of these six, four institutional-type organizations typified strongly faith-based organizations. Thus, a slight majority of organizations in this sample expressed and preserved their distinctive religious identity in multiple ways, including boards and staff comprised of high proportions of coreligionists.</p>
<p>I applied this finding to suggest that when organizations’ core identity and mission are stable, they provide a source of values that guide decision making. Furthermore, I proposed that stability and longevity among faith-based nonprofits are desirable, in part because these organizations often serve clients who are particularly or multiply “needy.” Based on these assumptions, the continuation of federal and state policies that include and support the provision of services by faith-based nonprofits is advised.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0899764012462457">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The Strengthening Communities Fund (SCF) is authorized under Section 1110 of the Social Security Act governing Social Services Research and Demonstration activities; Title VIII of the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009, Public Law (P.L.) 111-5</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Jill Witmer Sinha</bold>, assistant professor with the School of Social Work, Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey, collected primary data on the F&amp;O Project. She studies the provision of social services by nonprofit organizations, including faith-based and religious organizations, within disenfranchised communities.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boddie</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Social services of African American congregations in the Welfare Reform Era</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cnaan</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dichter</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Draine</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>A century of social work and social welfare at Penn</source> (pp. <fpage>322</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Reconsidering the implementation strategy in faith-based policy initiatives</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chambre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The changing nature of “faith” in faith-based organizations: Secularization and ecumenicism in four AIDS organizations in New York City</article-title>. <source>Social Services Review</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Secularization as declining religious authority</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>749</fpage>-<lpage>774</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Congregations in America</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wineburg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Did the faith-based initiative change congregations?</article-title> <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (speaker). (<conf-date>2001, July 19</conf-date>). <conf-name>Proceedings and debates of the 197th Congress</conf-name> (First Session, the United States of American Congressional Record, <volume>Vol. 147</volume>, No. 10, p. <fpage>13797</fpage>). <conf-loc>Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clerkin</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grønbjerg</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The capacities and challenges of faith-based human service organizations</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cnaan</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>The newer deal: Social Work and religion in partnership</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cnaan</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boddie</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Charitable choice and faith-based welfare: A call for social work</article-title>. <source>Social Work</source>, <volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cnaan</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boddie</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Handy</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yancey</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>The invisible caring hand: American congregations and the provision of welfare</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>God’s economy: Faith-based initiatives and the caring state</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Demerath</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Sacred companies: Organizational aspects of religion and religious aspects of organizations</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Speaker). (<year>2009</year>, <month>June</month> <day>11</day>). <source>Government partnerships with faith-based organizations: Looking back, moving forward</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Pew Research Center’s Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The quiet revolution: The President’s faith-based community initiative: A seven-year progress report</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/government/fbci/pdf">http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/government/fbci/pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeavons</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>When the bottom line in faithfulness: Management of Christian service organizations</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeavons</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Identifying characteristics of “religious” organizations: An exploratory proposal</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Demerath</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Sacred companies: Organizational aspects of religion and religious aspects of organizations</source> (pp. <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yankoski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Comparing faith-based and secular community service corporations in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Pennsylvania</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bielefeld</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Charitable choice at work: Evaluating faith-based job programs in the states</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finegold</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vita</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wherry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>, <month>July</month>). <source>Federal policy on the ground: Faith-based organizations delivering local services</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Urban Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Tempting faith</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Littlefield</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Social service, faith-based organizations, and the poor</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1014</fpage>-<lpage>1026</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Speaker). (<year>2003</year>, <month>March</month> <day>5</day>). <source>The faith-based initiative two years later: Examining its potential, progress and problems</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monsma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>When sacred and secular mix: Religious nonprofit organizations and public money</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowan &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monsma</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Putting faith in partnerships: Welfare-to-work in four cities</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Montiel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Getting apiece of the pie: Federal grants to faith-based social service organizations</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany: NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State University of New York, Roundtable on Religion and Social Welfare, Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Office of Housing and Urban Development</collab>. (<year>2001</year>, <month>January</month>). <source>Rallying the armies of compassion</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://archives.hud.gov/reports/rally.pdf">http://archives.hud.gov/reports/rally.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Congregations in low-income neighborhoods and the implications for social welfare policy research</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>316</fpage>-<lpage>339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pipes</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebaugh</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Faith-based coalitions, social services, and government funding</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Religion</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Polson</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The inter-organizational ties that bind: Exploring the contributions of agency-congregation relationships</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Religion</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>, <month>December</month>). <source>Scanning the policy environment for faith-based social services in the United States: What has changed since 2002? Results of a 50-state study</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Roundtable on Religion and Social Welfare Policy Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pirog</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Empirical evidence on faith-based organizations in an era of welfare reform</article-title>. <source>Social Service Review</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dionne</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>, <month>December</month>). <source>Serving people in need, safeguarding religious freedom: Recommendations on partnerships with faith-based organizations</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Brookings Institution in cooperation with Wake Forest University Divinity School’s Center for Religion and Public Affairs</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sager</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Faith, politics, and power: The politics of faith-based initiatives</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salipante</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Golden-Biddle</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Managing traditionality and strategic change in nonprofit organizations</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit Management and Leadership</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2009</year>). <source>Comparing strategies to maintain connections between faith communities and organizations across religions</source>. <publisher-loc>College Park, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Maryland College Park, Faith and Organizations Project</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>School Sisters of Notre Dame, Atlantic-Midwest Province</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <source>Sponsorship review process initiated. United in mission</source>. <publisher-loc>Norridge, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sider</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Typology of religious characteristics of social service and educational organizations and programs</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The black church and organizations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Comparing strategies to maintain connections between faith communities and organizations across religions. Vol. 2: Maintaining vital connections between faith communities and their nonprofits</source> (pp. <fpage>40</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>). <publisher-loc>College Park, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Maryland College Park, Faith and Organizations Project</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cnaan</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dichter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Analysis of a collaborative faith-based demonstration project: The unique capacity of congregation- and community-based collaboration</article-title>. In the <source>Independent sector: The role of faith-based organizations in the social welfare system spring research forum working papers</source> (pp. <fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Independent Sector Roundtable on Religion and Social Welfare Policy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The challenge of strengthening nonprofits and civil society</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bartkowski</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grettenberger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Comparative views on the role and effect of faith in social services</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Roundtable on Religion and Social Welfare Policy Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The varieties of faith-related agencies</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>651</fpage>-<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>New responsibilities of faith-related agencies</article-title>. <source>The Policy Studies Journal</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>533</fpage>-<lpage>562</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Mainline Protestants and their organizations</article-title>. in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Comparing strategies to maintain connections between faith communities and organizations across religions. Vol. 2: Maintaining vital connections between faith communities and their nonprofits</source> (pp. <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>). <publisher-loc>College Park, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Maryland College Park, Faith and Organizations Project</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vanderwoerd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>How faith-based social service organizations manage secular pressures associated with government funding</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit Management and Leadership</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>Economy and society</source> (<volume>Vols. 1-2</volume>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wittich</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Ed.). <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wineburg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>A limited partnership: The politics of religion, welfare and social service</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0899764012462457">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wineburg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Faith-based inefficiencies: The follies of Bush’s initiatives</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>