<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546512456974</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546512456974</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>13</subject>
<subject>27</subject>
<subject>40</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Evaluation of Arthroscopic Remplissage by High-Resolution Magnetic Resonance Imaging</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Min Jung</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MMSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512456974">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>Grant</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546512456974">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>Amit</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546512456974">‡</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546512456974">‡</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tjoumakaris</surname><given-names>Fotios P.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0363546512456974">§</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>John D.</given-names><suffix>IV</suffix></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512456974">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546512456974">‖</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546512456974"><label>*</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546512456974"><label>†</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Hospital for Special Surgery, New York, New York</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0363546512456974"><label>‡</label>Department of Radiology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0363546512456974"><label>§</label>Rothman Institute, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0363546512456974">Investigation performed at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546512456974"><label>‖</label>John D. Kelly IV, MD, University of Pennsylvania, Department of Orthopedic Surgery, 3400 Spruce Street, 2 Silverstein, Philadelphia, PA 19104 (e-mail: <email>john.kelly@uphs.upenn.edu</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>2331</fpage>
<lpage>2336</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0363546512456974">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Arthroscopic remplissage is a novel procedure recently advocated for the treatment of large Hill-Sachs lesions with recurrent anterior glenohumeral instability. We have shown previously that infraspinatus tenodesis and Bankart repair reduce the risk of recurrent instability in high-risk patients. The ability to perform this procedure arthroscopically and without the need for bone grafting or an open approach makes this an appealing alternative to more traditional techniques.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546512456974">
<title>Purpose:</title>
<p>To evaluate and characterize the postoperative appearance of the remplissage procedure on high-resolution magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and to correlate these findings to clinical outcome (Western Ontario Shoulder Instability [WOSI] score, range of motion).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546512456974">
<title>Study Design:</title>
<p>Case series; Level of evidence, 4.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546512456974">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>In patients who had undergone arthroscopic remplissage for recurrent glenohumeral instability with large Hill-Sachs defects, images were acquired with a 3-T protocol (and reviewed by 2 musculoskeletal radiologists) with the shoulder in the abduction-external rotation (ABER) and neutral positions at the time of the latest clinical examination. Measured parameters included signal intensity of tissue within the prior defect, signal intensity of the residual infraspinatus, degree of fatty infiltrate and muscle atrophy as a percentage of fat signal versus muscle signal (Goutallier grade), presence of marrow edema, and number of anchors in the defect. Functional scores were obtained with the WOSI questionnaire, and comprehensive range of motion data were recorded with a goniometer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546512456974">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>In 11 patients with an average clinical follow-up of 18.0 months (range, 8.8-27.2 months), the average size of the Hill-Sachs deformity was 334.3 mm<sup>3</sup> (range, 93.6-825.1 mm<sup>3</sup>). The percentage of the deformity filled in with tendon was 75% to 100%, and the degree of atrophy was 0% to 25% for all patients studied. No defects were left unfilled. Two patients had granulation tissue filling the lesion, and 3 patients had fibrous tissue, while the rest of the patients had the MRI appearance of both granulation and fibrous tissue. Four of 9 patients had tendinopathy or partial tears of the residual infraspinatus tendon insertion, and 1 patient demonstrated residual bone marrow edema. The average number of anchors used was 1.4 (range, 1-3). The average WOSI score was 74.3% (range, 41.6%-99.2%), with an average external rotation loss of 5.8° (range, 0°-22°). One patient had recurrence of instability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546512456974">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>Our data suggest that there is evidence of tendon incorporation and fill into the Hill-Sachs defect following arthroscopic remplissage at 8 months and beyond. Although MRI findings did not correlate with the clinical findings, patients were satisfied with the procedure and demonstrated minimal loss of external rotation (average, 5.8°) at early follow-up.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>arthroscopic</kwd>
<kwd>remplissage</kwd>
<kwd>shoulder</kwd>
<kwd>instability</kwd>
<kwd>Hill-Sachs</kwd>
<kwd>Bankart</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Burkhart and De Beer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512456974">3</xref></sup> described the pathological Hill-Sachs lesion as an osteoarticular deficit on the humeral head that “drops into” the glenoid rim during abduction and external rotation. At this point of engagement, the humeral head pivots on the anterior glenoid rim, and the patient experiences a painful dislocation. Its incidence has been estimated to range from 47% to 80% in anterior shoulder dislocation cases and up to 100% in cases of recurrent instability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512456974">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512456974">9</xref></sup> In the setting of bone defects and recurrent instability, nonoperative treatment is typically ineffective at restoring full function and stability to the injured shoulder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512456974">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512456974">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512456974">12</xref></sup> As for surgical treatment, techniques centered on correcting the “engaging” Hill-Sachs lesion have been described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546512456974">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512456974">14</xref></sup> By correcting or eliminating the defect, this increases the articular surface area of the humerus and prolongs its contact with the surface of the glenoid, thereby creating a more stable shoulder joint. Alternatively, an improvement in the arc length can also be achieved by augmenting bone stock to the glenoid side as well. There are currently many different techniques for eliminating engagement such as coracoid transfer (Latarjet, Bristow), iliac crest bone grafting of the anterior glenoid, proximal humerus rotational osteotomy, osteochondral allograft transplant, and arthroscopic remplissage. The majority of these techniques are typically achieved via an open approach (although arthroscopic Latarjet has recently been advocated) and may not anatomically address the bone deficiency in cases of isolated humeral head bone loss,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512456974">6</xref></sup> especially when glenoid augmenting procedures are used to address humeral head defects by increasing articular arc. In contrast, arthroscopic remplissage is a minimally invasive approach to address large, engaging humeral head defects that contribute to anterior instability. The procedure is named after the French word “to fill” and consists of arthroscopic infraspinatus tenodesis that fills the humeral head defect and prevents early engagement.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512456974">7</xref></sup> We have previously shown good results with this technique with minimal complications and restoration of stability to the majority of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512456974">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>One of the concerns with remplissage is the possibility of motion loss after surgery and degeneration of the infraspinatus tendon and muscle as a result of the tenodesis. Deutsch and Kroll<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546512456974">5</xref></sup> reported on a case of significant motion loss after the procedure, which has been of concern to sports surgeons. A more recent report demonstrated very little loss of motion relative to Bankart repair alone; however, patients in this series were more likely to complain of posterosuperior shoulder pain relative to isolated repairs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512456974">10</xref></sup> Other studies have also shown that arthroscopic remplissage leads to clinically insignificant external rotation deficits that patients rarely notice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512456974">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512456974">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512456974">15</xref></sup> Zhu and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512456974">15</xref></sup> also included magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) as part of their study; however, their study was not optimally designed for a critical analysis of defect “fill” or interpretation of tendon and muscle quality based on the field strength of the images that were obtained. Therefore, the purpose of this present study was to further investigate the major concerns of the remplissage procedure, namely, the quality and amount of fill of the humeral head defect, the quality of the infraspinatus after tenodesis into a Hill-Sachs lesion, and the amount of motion loss that this repair may ultimately cause for the patient at various time points after arthroscopic remplissage. We hypothesized that high-resolution 3-T MRI measurements of granulation tissue and fatty infiltration of the infraspinatus muscle (Goutallier classification) would show that over time there is significant tendon-bone integration and good maintenance of infraspinatus muscle integrity. Additionally, we will describe the progression by which tissue maturation occurs from granulation precursor tissue to incorporated fibrous tissue.</p>
<sec id="section7-0363546512456974" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>This study was designed as a prospective study. Funding for the imaging studies was provided by an internal grant from our institution. Institutional Review Board approval was obtained before patient recruitment and data collection, and all data collection was performed during a 2-year period from 2010 to 2011. Patients were enrolled for the study if they met strict inclusion criteria and were candidates for arthroscopic remplissage: age greater than 18 years, traumatic and recurrent anterior glenohumeral instability (&gt;2 dislocations), and preoperative imaging that identified a large Hill-Sachs defect on MRI (&gt;25% of the humeral head surface with glenoid deficiency &lt;20%, using the best-fit circle method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512456974">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512456974">13</xref></sup>). None of the patients was a participant of a previous study. Preoperative evaluation of humeral head defect size was performed with the same protocol as the postoperative evaluation on MRI scans (largest dimensions on sagittal, coronal, and axial image measurements as major, minor, and vertical axis multiplied by the volume of an ellipsoid-shape conversion factor, Pi/6). This preoperative measurement was done to guide our treatment but not used in the data analysis, as we could not control for variations of coil, magnet strength, and scanner used. At the time of arthroscopy, the lesions were further classified and confirmed to be large if they were at least 2 cm long and 0.3 cm deep, further defining the inclusion criteria.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512456974">12</xref></sup> Patients with prior surgery on the affected shoulder and those with less than an 8-month follow-up were excluded from the study. All clinical follow-ups were performed by fellowship-trained sports medicine physicians and consisted of goniometer range of motion measurements with the patient supine and all angles measured relative to the scapular plane. The Western Ontario Shoulder Instability (WOSI) questionnaire was evaluated at the conclusion of the final MRI scan, and the clinical examination and the MRI scan were performed on average 18.0 months (range, 8.8-27.2 months) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546512456974">Table 1</xref>) postoperatively. All surgeries were performed by a single surgeon.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546512456974" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption><p>Study Results<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512456974"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546512456974" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512456974-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Patient</th>
<th align="center">Age, y</th>
<th align="center">Follow-up, mo</th>
<th align="center">Humeral Defect, mm<sup>3</sup></th>
<th align="center">Type of Tissue Fill</th>
<th align="center">No. of Anchors</th>
<th align="center">WOSI, %</th>
<th align="center">External Rotation Loss, deg</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>20.3</td>
<td>27.2</td>
<td>428.9</td>
<td>Fibrous</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>99.2</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>18.6</td>
<td>26.3</td>
<td>447.2</td>
<td>Fibrous</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>79.8</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>18.5</td>
<td>25.2</td>
<td>93.6</td>
<td>Fibrous</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>93.6</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>23.9</td>
<td>24.0</td>
<td>183.2</td>
<td>Granulation/fibrous</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>75.7</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0363546512456974"><italic>b</italic></xref></sup></td>
<td>31.2</td>
<td>23.3</td>
<td>825.1</td>
<td>Granulation/fibrous</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>54.0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>19.1</td>
<td>15.5</td>
<td>258.0</td>
<td>Granulation/fibrous</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>91.7</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>28.7</td>
<td>14.8</td>
<td>226.3</td>
<td>Granulation/fibrous</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>60.7</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>39.3</td>
<td>11.8</td>
<td>132.6</td>
<td>Granulation/fibrous</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>89.3</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>21.8</td>
<td>11.4</td>
<td>582.9</td>
<td>Granulation/fibrous</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>41.6</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>35.0</td>
<td>9.5</td>
<td>309.9</td>
<td>Granulation</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>70.2</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>21.9</td>
<td>8.8</td>
<td>189.6</td>
<td>Granulation</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>61.9</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average</td>
<td>25.3</td>
<td>18.0</td>
<td>334.3</td>
<td/>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>74.3</td>
<td>5.8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546512456974">
<label>a</label>
<p>WOSI, Western Ontario Shoulder Instability.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0363546512456974">
<label>b</label>
<p>Patient 5 had a dislocation at 21 months postoperatively.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Postoperative MRI evaluation was performed utilizing a closed high-field 3-T scanner (MAGNETOM Triotrim, Siemens Healthcare, Malvern, Pennsylvania) with a shoulder coil for the neutral position images and a flexible coil for the abduction-external rotation (ABER) position images. The following MRI protocol was used in all patients (repetition time/echo time): coronal oblique T1-weighted spin echo (890/9.5 milliseconds), coronal oblique T2-weighted fat suppressed (3500/37 milliseconds), sagittal oblique T1-weighted spin echo (660/10 milliseconds), sagittal oblique T2-weighted fat suppressed (4000/37 milliseconds), and axial T2-weighted fat suppressed (3700/37 milliseconds). Imaging parameters included a slice thickness of 3.0 mm and slice spacing of 3.3 mm.</p>
<p>The same MRI technician prepared the patients for both the regular position scan and the ABER view scan. The MRI scans were evaluated independently by 2 fellowship-trained musculoskeletal radiologists, and the average of the 2 values was used for the purpose of the data analysis. All values were measured directly from the digital imaging software. The MRI scans were evaluated for infraspinatus muscle integrity based on fatty infiltration (Goutallier classification) and tendon granulation (granulation baseline signal as skeletal muscle). The number of anchors used based on operative report was verified with the imaging. The humeral head defect was measured as an ellipsoid mathematical formula using the largest measurements at coronal, sagittal, and axial images as vertical, major, and minor axis values. The percentage of the “fill” by the tendon was also measured. The percentage fill was measured based on previously outlined ellipsoid volume calculations and categorized as a percentage of the defect size: 0%-25%, 25%-50%, 50%-75%, and 75%-100%. Infraspinatus fatty infiltration and muscle atrophy were measured using 4 categories—0%-25%, 25%-50%, 50%-75%, and 75%-100%—based on the Goutallier grade using muscle signal to fat signal as an indicator of volume and atrophy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546512456974">Figures 1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546512456974"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0363546512456974"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0363546512456974"/>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0363546512456974">5</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0363546512456974" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Abduction-external rotation position on T2-weighted fat-saturated image demonstrates a moderate-sized Hill-Sachs deformity on the right, filled (75%-100%) with fibrous tissue. Note that the signal intensity of the tissue filling the defect is isointense to hypointense relative to skeletal muscle. Arrowhead, outline of humeral head bony defect; arrow, outline of soft tissue filling the defect.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512456974-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0363546512456974" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Coronal oblique T1-weighted image best demonstrates the Hill-Sachs deformity (hypointense relative to marrow), which contrasts with the high signal intensity fat within the medullary cavity of the humerus. Signal intensity of the tissue filling the Hill-Sachs deformity is not well assessed on the T1-weighted image. Arrowhead, outline of humeral head bony defect; arrow, outline of soft tissue filling the defect.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512456974-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0363546512456974" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Coronal oblique T2-weighted fat-saturated image demonstrates mixed signal intensity tissue within the large-sized Hill-Sachs deformity, suggesting this represents a combination of granulation tissue, fibrous tissue, and fluid. This was the only patient in our study group to have a dislocation after the procedure, which is supported by the marrow edema–like signal surrounding the Hill-Sachs deformity. The patient was imaged approximately 23 months after the surgery, 2 weeks after dislocation and self-reduction. Arrowhead, outline of humeral head bony defect; arrow, outline of soft tissue filling the defect.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512456974-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0363546512456974" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sagittal T2-weighted fat-saturated image with the patient in a conventional position demonstrates a moderate-sized Hill-Sachs deformity, filled (75%-100%) mostly with fibrous tissue. Approximately 90% of the tissue is isointense relative to skeletal muscle. There is a small resorptive cyst (arrow) adjacent to the infraspinatus anchor, manifested as fluid-like signal on the T2-weighted image. Just posterior and lateral to the anchor, the native infraspinatus tendon insertion site demonstrates intermediate to high signal intensity, with small linear areas of fluid signal (arrowhead), in keeping with mild tendinopathy and small intrasubstance tears.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512456974-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0363546512456974" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><p>Coronal oblique T2-weighted fat-saturated image with the patient in a conventional position demonstrates a large Hill-Sachs deformity, filled (75%-100%) with 50% fibrous tissue and 50% granulation tissue (arrow). Approximately 50% of the tissue is hyperintense relative to skeletal muscle.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512456974-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0363546512456974" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Twelve patients were identified based on the inclusion criteria described. One of the patients was excluded from the study because of the age restriction (under the age of 18 years). Eleven patients were ultimately recruited for this study, and the average follow-up of the patients was 18.0 months (range, 8.8-27.2 months). For the remplissage portion of the procedure, 2 patients were treated with 2 anchors, 1 patient with 3 anchors, and the rest of the patients with 1 anchor. The patient with the largest Hill-Sachs defect in our study reported a postoperative dislocation 2 weeks before the MRI evaluation. He was playing softball and felt the shoulder dislocate after the follow-through phase of his throwing motion. He was able to get his shoulder reduced without much difficulty and has not had any further episodes. The patient’s MRI scan showed cystic changes around the 2 anchors used for the remplissage procedure, and more fibrous fill than granulation, but 75% to 100% of the defect was filled with soft tissue. The average WOSI score was 74.3% (range, 41.6%-99.2%), with an average external rotation loss of 5.8° (range, 0°-22°). None of the patients in this series reported the loss of motion as significant or adversely affecting their activities of daily living. All patients were able to tolerate the standard MRI protocol, and these images were used for the purpose of data analysis. All but 1 patient (claustrophobia) were able to tolerate the ABER position and underwent MRI in this position. The average size of the Hill-Sachs deformity was 334.3 mm<sup>3</sup> (range, 93.6-825.1 mm<sup>3</sup>) as measured on axial, coronal, and sagittal cuts representing the largest value on each axis, using ellipsoid volume calculation. The percentage of the deformity filled in with tendon was 75% to 100%, and the degree of fatty infiltration based on fat versus muscle signal was 0% to 25% for all patients studied at a minimum of 8-month follow-up. No defects were left unfilled. Two patients with the shortest follow-up had granulation tissue filling the deformity, and 3 patients with the longest follow-up had fibrous tissue, while the rest of the patients had a mixture of granulation tissue and fibrous tissue, with a transition from granulation to fibrous tissue between 8.8 and 9.5 months after surgery. Four of 9 patients had tendinopathy or partial tears of the residual tendon at the original insertion site, superior and lateral to the tenodesis. In 1 case, the patient had a large resorptive cyst at the distal aspect of the anchor but was clinically asymptomatic. One patient had mild humeral marrow edema but did not have any specific complaints.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0363546512456974" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The purpose of our study was to evaluate the postoperative MRI and clinical findings of the arthroscopic remplissage procedure. With the MRI evaluation, we aimed to show adequate filling of the humeral head defect and physiological response to the tenodesis. As mentioned previously, Zhu and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512456974">15</xref></sup> described postoperative imaging in 15 of 49 patients in their series. Although the reasons for performing postoperative MRI in the patients were not clearly identified, the authors reported satisfactory filling of the defect with the tenodesis. However, the field strength and protocol utilized during this study may not have offered enough information with regard to the quality of the tissue filling the defect, muscle quality, and integrity. With the current study, we were able to prospectively enroll consecutive patients undergoing arthroscopic remplissage with previously defined, well-established operative criteria. High-resolution 3-T MRI provided us with excellent image quality, with scans that were evaluated by fellowship-trained musculoskeletal radiologists who determined that contrast is not necessary to evaluate the tenodesis and granulation in this setting. With consistent methodology and measurements, we were able to objectively demonstrate a positive physiological response (ie, no fatty infiltration, loss of muscle bulk) after tenodesis of the infraspinatus tendon into the Hill-Sachs defect and subsequent tendon-bone integration.</p>
<p>Our average clinical outcome score (WOSI) of 74.3 is very closely approximated to our previous report (74.5)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512456974">11</xref></sup> and other studies in the medical literature. Zhu et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512456974">15</xref></sup> reported an average postoperative Constant Score of 97.8 at 2-year follow-up, and Haviv et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512456974">6</xref></sup> demonstrated improvement of the Simple Shoulder Score from 6.6 preoperatively to 11 and the Rowe Score from 10.6 to 85. Interestingly, from our results, the degree of fill or granulation tissue versus fibrous tissue in the defect or even infraspinatus atrophy did not seem to correlate with the functional shoulder score. In addition, our patients had excellent shoulder range of motion as shown by the fact that all of the patients were physically able to tolerate the ABER position (1 patient refused to complete the MRI protocol in the ABER view because of claustrophobia), and external rotation loss of 5.8° was deemed clinically insignificant to all the patients in this cohort. The patient with the largest external rotation deficit compared with the contralateral side (22°) did not notice the deficit, and he was able to return to his recreational sporting activities, including softball.</p>
<p>In our study, the recurrence rate was 9.1% (1/11 patients). Compared with our previous results (15%),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512456974">11</xref></sup> and more recent outcome data with 8.2%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512456974">15</xref></sup> and 0%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512456974">6</xref></sup> recurrence rates, we believe that the arthroscopic remplissage technique can be safely used to treat these patients who meet the strict preoperative indications (recurrent dislocations, distinct traumatic cause, large Hill-Sachs lesions with good glenoid bone stock). Historically, the patients with large Hill-Sachs lesions have done poorly with Bankart repair alone,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546512456974">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512456974">3</xref></sup> and one should be reminded of the patient selection criteria when determining the optimum treatment strategy. Although larger humeral head defects may need more than 1 anchor, 1 anchor is often enough to fill the humeral head defect to prevent the “engaging” of the humeral head to the glenoid rim. It is not necessary to cover the entire defect to achieve a clinically acceptable “fill.” If the defect size is reduced enough so that the Hill-Sachs lesion no longer engages with the anterior glenoid, one can prevent future dislocation. As shown in our study, 1 anchor is often enough to reduce the size of the humeral head defect to achieve a good clinical result, as all but 3 patients had only 1 anchor for the remplissage portion of the procedure. The decision to use more than 1 anchor should be made intraoperatively, after a careful intraoperative examination of the degree of engagement and tissue fill and shoulder stability after the first anchor is placed.</p>
<p>
There are several limitations to our study. First, we do not have preoperative 3-T MRI imaging data to compare with the imaging studies we obtained during this study. Although all patients underwent preoperative MRI evaluations, not all studies were done at our institution, and comparing different quality MRI scans with the high-resolution 3-T postoperative images would not have provided fair comparison between the patients. Also, because of the relatively rare nature of the patients needing the procedure and cost involved in the study, we were only able to include 11 patients in our study. With more patients included for longer follow-up, it is possible that we could capture more potential complications that were not seen in our study. However, from our clinical examination, we have no reason to believe that these patients would have significant procedure-related morbidity moving forward.</p>
<p>Our data suggest that there is evidence of tendon incorporation and fill into the Hill-Sachs defect after remplissage at 8 months and beyond with no damage incurred to the infraspinatus muscle. Patients did not have clinically significant external rotation deficits and demonstrated good clinical outcome scores, as has previously been reported.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>Presented at the interim meeting of the AOSSM, San Francisco, California, February 2012.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared that they have no conflicts of interest in the authorship and publication of this contribution.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546512456974">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boileau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Villalba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hery</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neyton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for recurrence of shoulder instability after arthroscopic Bankart repair</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1755</fpage>-<lpage>1763</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546512456974">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danaceau</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Articular arc length mismatch as a cause of failed bankart repair</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>740</fpage>-<lpage>744</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546512456974">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Beer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Traumatic glenohumeral bone defects and their relationship to failure of arthroscopic Bankart repairs: significance of the inverted-pear glenoid and the humeral engaging Hill-Sachs lesion</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>-<lpage>694</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546512456974">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bushnell</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Creighton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bony instability of the shoulder</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1061</fpage>-<lpage>1073</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546512456974">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decreased range of motion following arthroscopic remplissage</article-title>. <source>Orthopedics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>492</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546512456974">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haviv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biggs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of arthroscopic "remplissage": capsulotenodesis of the engaging large Hill-Sachs lesion</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Surg Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546512456974">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huysmans</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dhert</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The shape of the inferior part of the glenoid: a cadaveric study</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>759</fpage>-<lpage>763</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546512456974">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ochoa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic double-pulley remplissage technique for engaging Hill-Sachs lesions in anterior shoulder instability repairs</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1343</fpage>-<lpage>1348</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546512456974">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dewing</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warme</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsen</surname><given-names>FA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of osseous defects associated with anterior shoulder instability</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546512456974">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nourissat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kilinc</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Werther</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doursounian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A prospective, comparative, radiological, and clinical study of the influence of the "remplissage" procedure on shoulder range of motion after stabilization by arthroscopic Bankart repair</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2147</fpage>-<lpage>2152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546512456974">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tjoumakaris</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JD</given-names><suffix>4th</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic remplissage with Bankart repair for the treatment of glenohumeral instability with Hill-Sachs defects</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1187</fpage>-<lpage>1194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546512456974">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zarins</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ciullo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent anterior dislocation of the shoulder after surgical repair: apparent causes of failure and treatment</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546512456974">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sugaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moriishi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dohi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Glenoid rim morphology in recurrent anterior glenohumeral instability</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>878</fpage>-<lpage>884</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546512456974">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melean</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moraga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Remplissage: infraspinatus tenodesis and posterior capsulodesis for the treatment of Hill Sachs lesions. An all intraarticular technique</article-title>. <source>Techn Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546512456974">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic Bankart repair combined with remplissage technique for the treatment of anterior shoulder instability with engaging Hill-Sachs lesion: a report of 49 cases with a minimum 2-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1640</fpage>-<lpage>1647</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>