<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DVD</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdvd</journal-id>
<journal-title>British Journal of Diabetes &amp; Vascular Disease</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1474-6514</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1474651413486680</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1474651413486680</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Letter to the Editor</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fasting glucose in the post-natal period</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>Richard IG</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1474651413486680">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>Matthew AG</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1474651413486680">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1474651413486680"><label>1</label>Human Development and Health Academic Unit, Faculty of Medicine, University of Southampton, Southampton, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1474651413486680"><label>2</label>Southampton NHS Foundation Trust, Southampton, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1474651413486680">Professor Richard IG Holt, IDS Building (MP887), Southampton General Hospital, Tremona Road, Southampton SO16 6YD, UK Email: <email>righ@soton.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>106</fpage>
<lpage>107</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>March/April 2013</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Dear Editor,</p>
<p>We read the paper by Joseph and colleagues with interest.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1474651413486680">1</xref></sup> In their study, the results of 147 postnatal glucose tolerance tests in women with a recent history of gestational diabetes were reported. 52 women had persistent abnormalities, of whom eight were diagnosed with diabetes. The authors concluded that the measurement of fasting plasma glucose is an inadequate postnatal screening test as many women with impaired glucose tolerance were not identified.</p>
<p>The main purpose of postnatal glucose testing is to identify women with pre-existing undiagnosed diabetes and this depends on the underlying prevalence of type 2 diabetes in the general population and the availability of adequate health care provision and screening facilities. In our original paper, we proposed the use of a fasting plasma glucose of 6.0 mmol/L to identify women who should have formal testing for diabetes by an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1474651413486680">2</xref></sup> This proposal was subsequently adopted by NICE.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1474651413486680">3</xref></sup> It is interesting to note that the current study performed in a similar UK population actually provides support for our approach as all 8 women with postnatal diabetes were identified while it would have spared 126 (86%) women from undergoing an OGTT.</p>
<p>Consistent with other studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1474651413486680">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474651413486680">5</xref></sup> a significant proportion (30%) did not have the recommended postnatal OGTT and thereby missed the opportunity for screening at this stage. By measuring fasting plasma glucose in the immediate postnatal period, we have ensured that all women with gestational diabetes attending our service receive postnatal screening for diabetes.</p>
<p>In our paper, we accepted that our approach missed cases of impaired glucose tolerance, albeit to a lesser extent than was found by Joseph and colleagues (2.4% vs. 14.3%). The importance of diagnosing impaired glucose tolerance is to identify women at high risk of subsequent diabetes and cardiovascular disease. However, as the diagnosis of gestational diabetes has already done this, we argue that a finding of postnatal impaired glucose tolerance does not affect management as all women with gestational diabetes should be encouraged to adopt appropriate lifestyle changes to reduce their risk of future diabetes.</p>
<p>In some populations where the demographics differ from those in Southampton, a fasting plasma glucose may miss a diagnosis of diabetes in the short term;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1474651413486680">6</xref></sup> however, it is also important to recognise postnatal testing for diabetes is not an isolated test and subsequent annual testing for diabetes and cardiovascular disease is recommended for women with a history of gestational diabetes. This later testing will be by fasting glucose or glycated haemoglobin according to NICE guidance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1474651413486680">7</xref></sup> As lifestyle intervention forms the cornerstone of management for both diabetes prevention and early diabetes, a delay in the diagnosis should not adversely affect the woman.</p>
<p>It seems anomalous to insist on an OGTT in the postnatal period at a time which is probably the most inconvenient for the woman. While glycated haemoglobin cannot be used in postnatal period because of the pregnancy effects on red cell turnover, a fasting glucose remains a pragmatic, acceptable and economical option.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This letter received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of conflicting interests</label>
<p>RH was a member of the NICE Diabetes in Pregnancy Guideline Development Group. MC declares no conflicts of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1474651413486680">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Photiou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goenka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clement-Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying women with persistent abnormal glucose metabolism following gestational diabetes mellitus: changing times, changing populations and changing needs</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Diabetes and Vascular Disease</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1474651413486680">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A postnatal fasting plasma glucose is useful in determining which women with gestational diabetes should undergo a postnatal oral glucose tolerance test</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>594</fpage>-<lpage>598</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1474651413486680">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Collaborating Centre for Women’s and Children’s Health</collab>. <article-title>Diabetes in Pregnancy: management of diabetes and its complications from preconception to the postnatal period</article-title>. <year>2008</year>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>RCOG Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1474651413486680">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipscombe</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feig</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Missed opportunities for type 2 diabetes testing following gestational diabetes: a population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>1484</fpage>-<lpage>1490</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1474651413486680">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malcolm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karovitch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>et al</source>. <article-title>The effectiveness of implementing a reminder system into routine clinical practice: does it increase postpartum screening in women with gestational diabetes?</article-title> <source>Chronic Dis Can</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1474651413486680">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kakad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fasting plasma glucose is not sufficient to detect ongoing glucose intolerance after pregnancy complicated by gestational diabetes</article-title>. <source>Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>-<lpage>236</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1474651413486680">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</collab>. <article-title>Preventing type 2 diabetes: risk identification and interventions for individuals at high risk</article-title>. PHG38. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://guidance.nice.org.uk/PH38">http://guidance.nice.org.uk/PH38</ext-link>. <year>2012</year>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>