<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GOM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgom</journal-id>
<journal-title>Group &amp; Organization Management</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1059-6011</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3993</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059601113500871</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1059601113500871</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Call for Proposals</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Conceptual Issue</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>538</fpage>
<lpage>539</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>Group &amp; Organization Management</italic> is pleased to announce that Professors Lucy Gilson (University of Connecticut) and Caren Goldberg (American University) will serve as Editors for the next <italic>GOM</italic> Conceptual Issue.</p>
<p>Accordingly, the Special Issue Editors would like to invite authors to submit proposals for the fourth <italic>Group &amp; Organization Management</italic> Conceptual Issue. Articles for the Conceptual Issue are intended to be high-impact scholarly pieces based on extant developments in research literatures. This Conceptual Issue will consist of papers that offer more than just a summary of existing knowledge in a certain area. Beyond summarizing recent research, manuscripts should provide an integration of management literatures, offer an integrated framework, provide value added, and highlight directions for future inquiry. Papers are not expected to offer empirical data. Inter-disciplinary and/or multi-level insights on management and organizational processes are encouraged.</p>
<p>To be considered for the Special Conceptual Issue, <bold><italic>authors must first submit a proposal</italic></bold>. Proposals should contain 1500-1800 words (a figure and/or table can be added) and should provide sample references. References, figures, and tables do not count against the word count. All proposals will be subject to editorial review prior to requesting that they be developed into full papers. Full papers will NOT be considered at the proposal stage. Submissions will be evaluated on the following criteria:</p>
<list id="list1-1059601113500871" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>(a) Relevance. The proposed manuscript should thoroughly review a significant and important research area within the group and organizational management field.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(b) Viability. The proposal demonstrates how the paper will be completed within the time frame below.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(c) Scope of Interest. A proposal of broad interest to scholars in diverse research areas is preferred.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(d) Organization and Coherence. The proposal follows a logical structure, reads clearly, and thoroughly represents the field of knowledge.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(e) Conceptual Value Added. The proposal offers insights that go beyond a thorough summary of current literature.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(f) Agenda for Future Research. The proposal conveys relevant implications for future research.</p></list-item></list>
<p>Authors must adhere to a stringent timeline. Relevant dates are as follows:</p>
<list id="list2-1059601113500871" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>September 13, 2013: Proposal submission due date.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>November 15, 2013: Final decision on proposal and initial feedback provided to authors.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>May 9, 2014: First draft of paper due.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>August 8, 2014: Feedback to authors on first draft.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>November 7, 2014: Final paper submitted.</p></list-item></list>
<p>Proposals should be submitted as a <italic>single</italic> file to Lucy Gilson at <email>lgilson@business.uconn.edu</email>
</p>
</body>
</article>