<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EJC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spejc</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Communication</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0267-3231</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-3705</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0267323112441294</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0267323112441294</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Bastard Culture! How User Participation Transforms Cultural Production</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Carpentier</surname><given-names>Nico</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0267323112441294">University of Loughborough, UK; Vrije Universiteit Brussel, Belgium; Charles University, Czech Republic</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>211</fpage>
<lpage>212</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>Mirko Tobias</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Bastard Culture! How User Participation Transforms Cultural Production</source>, <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>; <page-count count="249"/> pp.: <price>€32.50</price></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>While the first wave of new media theorizations used the concept of interactivity to capture changing audience–media relationships, present-day reflections have returned to the concept of participation as a framework to provide meaning to new media usages. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0267323112441294">Henry Jenkins’s (2006)</xref> emphasis on participatory (convergence) culture, together with Axel Bruns’s labelling of (some) new media users as produsers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0267323112441294">2008</xref>), are key moments in this theoretical reconfiguration. This reconfiguration relocates the participatory moment within the realm of cultural production and no longer exclusively within the realm of politics, and more specifically direct democracy, as was often the case before. Mirko Tobias Schäfer’s book is aligned with this theoretical-conceptual shift and the centrality awarded to the concept of participation, although Schäfer prefers to label this shift as the redefinition of participation as access and connectivity into participation as collaboration and social interaction.</p>
<p><italic>Bastard Culture!</italic> is firmly embedded within this tradition of participation and new media studies, but it is also very explicit in its desire to avoid a too celebratory approach. To use Schäfer’s (p. 168) words (in his defence of the use of the concept of the ‘extended cultural industry’): ‘It refuses hasty enthusiasm about user participation, and thus questions the power structures unfolding in an interdependence of business and politics.’ It comes as no surprise that in his fifth chapter, Schäfer makes a considerable effort to show the response of this ‘extended cultural industry’ towards participatory practices and claims. To analyse the role of the cultural industry, Schäfer uses the three-tier structure of confrontation (fighting participation), implementation (controlling participation) and integration (embracing participation), combined with a wide range of case studies, on for instance modchips, open-source software, P2P, Lucasfilm, Google maps, Last-fm and (slightly surprisingly in this context) Wikipedia.</p>
<p>A similar tension is addressed in Chapter 3; this time in relation to technology, where Schäfer explicitly aims to avoid the celebratory fallacy. In this chapter, we can find a rather detailed and inspired discussion of three technologies: the computer, software and the internet. Entitled ‘Enabling/repressing participation’, this chapter uses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0267323112441294">Norman’s (2002)</xref> concept of affordances to qualify the role that technologies play in participatory practices. Schäfer produces a discussion of these three technologies, with a keen eye for detail, where the politics and contingencies of these technologies receive the attention they deserve (but in many cases don’t receive).</p>
<p>Another distinction Schäfer introduces is between explicit and implicit participation. This is very much the core of the second and fourth chapters of the book. Explicit participation is seen as ‘intrinsically motivated actions exercised in social formations which share a high degree of interaction, common objectives, and interests’ (p. 44). In contrast, implicit participation is played out on ‘a rather subliminal level’, ‘where users are participating – often without acknowledgement from the companies offering such services – in shaping and expanding the information infrastructure’ (p. 44). In Chapter 4, itself entitled ‘Bastard culture’, a series of case studies illustrates the logics of explicit and implicit participation. In the former case, we find a detailed discussion of the Xbox (the hacking of the Xbox Development Kit and the Xbox-Linux-Project) and the hacking of the AIBO. Implicit participation is illustrated by less focused cases, discussing websites/projects like Flickr, Delicious, Internet Archive, Napster and the Pirate Bay (among others).</p>
<p>The first two chapters contain the more theoretical reflections that frame the already mentioned debates – this immediately shows for me that the book would have benefited from a more elaborate discussion on the concept of participation itself. In many analyses of participatory culture, the notion of participation remains somewhat black boxed, which impedes upon theoretical elegance and in-depth empirical analysis. Schäfer does contribute to the theoretical debate on participation with his distinction between explicit and implicit participation, but the introduction of this distinction opens up new problems and questions, which require much more attention and debate. If we accept that participation can be unconscious, what then are the limits of participation? When does participation stop being participation? Is there a point where (following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0267323112441294">Arnstein, 1969</xref>) we have to label these practices non-participatory, and forms of manipulation? And how can we distinguish between the different participatory intensities in the cases of explicit and implicit participation?</p>
<p>If we have a closer look at <italic>Bastard Culture!</italic> we can mainly see a very detailed and well-documented analysis of contemporary new media cultures, which sometimes shifts from in-depth analyses of the participatory dimensions of these new media cultures. Of course, also the very explicit (one could say: understandably reductionist) focus on new media does not facilitate the contextualization of these participatory practices within a broader societal framework. Although there are references to the political and civic realms, they remain rare and there are many societal realms which should perhaps also be analysed before we can speak about a participatory culture. Maybe for now, it would be more appropriate to talk about a participatory media culture instead. Schäfer does provide many good arguments to support the existence of a participatory media (sub)culture, but maybe we need to study more actual new media usages in a diversity of everyday lives, and more non-participatory new media environments before we can use the label of participatory media culture. Despite Schäfer’s warning signs against the over-celebration of new media, many of his actual case studies still show the participatory nature of the new media environments, and at this stage there is also a need to look more at the existence and significance of authoritarian new media cultures. Nevertheless, Schäfer’s contribution offers its readers a detailed, well-written and convincing set of arguments in favour of the existence of such a participatory media (sub)culture.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0267323112441294">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arnstein</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>A ladder of citizen participation</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Institute of Planners</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0267323112441294">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Blogs, Wikipedia, Second Life, and Beyond – From Production to Produsage</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0267323112441294">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Convergence Culture: Where Old and New Media Collide</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0267323112441294">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Design of Everyday Things</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>