<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmsj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mult Scler</journal-id>
<journal-title>Multiple Sclerosis Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1352-4585</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0970</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458511423778</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1352458511423778</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sunlight exposure and sun sensitivity associated with disability progression in multiple sclerosis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>D’hooghe</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458511423778">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Haentjens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1352458511423778">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nagels</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458511423778">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1352458511423778">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Garmyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1352458511423778">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>De Keyser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1352458511423778">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-1352458511423778">6</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1352458511423778"><label>1</label>National Center For Multiple Sclerosis, Melsbroek, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1352458511423778"><label>2</label>Center for Outcomes Research and Laboratory for Experimental Surgery, Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel, Vrije Universiteit Brussel, Brussels, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1352458511423778"><label>3</label>Service d’orthopédagogie Clinique, Faculty of Psychology and Education Sciences, University of Mons, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1352458511423778"><label>4</label>Department of Dermatology, Universitaire Ziekenhuizen, Leuven, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff5-1352458511423778"><label>5</label>Department of Neurology UZ Brussel, Vrije Universiteit Brussel (VUB), Brussels, Belgium</aff>
<aff id="aff6-1352458511423778"><label>6</label>Department of Neurology University Medical Center Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1352458511423778">Marie B D’hooghe, MD, National Center for Multiple Sclerosis, Vanheylenstraat 16, 1820 Melsbroek, Belgium. Email: <email>marie.dhooghe@ms-centrum.be</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>451</fpage>
<lpage>459</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>26</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>17</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>23</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background:</bold> Sunlight and vitamin D have been inversely associated with the risk of multiple sclerosis (MS).</p>
<p><bold>Objective:</bold> We investigated sunlight exposure and sun sensitivity in relation to disability progression in MS.</p>
<p><bold>Methods:</bold> We conducted a survey among persons with MS, registered by the Flemish MS society, Belgium, and stratified data according to relapsing-onset and progressive-onset MS. We used Kaplan–Meier survival and Cox proportional hazard regression analyses with time to Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) 6 as outcome measure. Hazard ratios for the time from onset and from birth were calculated for the potentially predictive variables, adjusting for age at onset, gender and immunomodulatory treatment.</p>
<p><bold>Results:</bold> 704 (51.3%) of the 1372 respondents had reached EDSS 6. In relapsing-onset MS, respondents reporting equal or higher levels of sun exposure than persons of the same age in the last 10 years had a decreased risk of reaching EDSS 6. In progressive-onset MS, increased sun sensitivity was associated with an increased hazard of reaching EDSS 6.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> The association of higher sun exposure with a better outcome in relapsing-onset MS may be explained by either a protective effect or reverse causality. Mechanisms underlying sun sensitivity might influence progression in progressive-onset MS.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>disability progression</kwd>
<kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
<kwd>multiple sclerosis</kwd>
<kwd>sun sensitivity</kwd>
<kwd>sunlight exposure</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1352458511423778" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>A complex interaction between individual genetic susceptibility and environmental factors is thought to explain the development of multiple sclerosis (MS). Higher sun exposure during childhood and early adolescence has been associated with a reduced MS risk,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1352458511423778">1</xref></sup> independent of genetic susceptibility.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1352458511423778">2</xref></sup> The beneficial effect of ultraviolet radiation (UVR) has been largely attributed to vitamin D synthesis by the skin. The recent finding of a highly conserved vitamin D receptor response element in the promoter region of the HLA-DRB1*1501 gene strengthens the candidacy of vitamin D as a key player in MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458511423778">3</xref></sup> However immunosuppressive effects due to other mechanisms involving UVA and UVB irradiation and the release of neuropeptides such as α-Melanocyte-Stimulating Hormone (α-MSH) or melatonin have also been shown.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1352458511423778">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Epidemiological studies suggest that certain environmental factors which are associated with MS risk might also be related to the clinical phenotype. The month of birth effect was found in relapsing-onset MS, but not in progressive-onset MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458511423778">5</xref></sup> Relapse rates and disability in MS have been inversely associated with prior sun exposure and serum 25(OH) vitamin D levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458511423778">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1352458511423778">8</xref></sup> Two death certificate-based studies found occupational sunlight exposure to be inversely related with MS mortality.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1352458511423778">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1352458511423778">10</xref></sup> However, reverse causality cannot be excluded.</p>
<p>The effects of UVR on human skin, including vitamin D synthesis, are substantially determined by skin colour and ability to tan. Despite a better ability to synthesize vitamin D under limited UV exposure, an increased MS risk has been found in fair skin phenotypes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1352458511423778">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1352458511423778">11</xref></sup> Having a fair skin has also been related to both a better and a worse outcome in MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1352458511423778">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1352458511423778">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>The objective of our study was to investigate whether sun exposure and phenotypic skin type characteristics might be associated with the progression of disability in relapsing-onset and progressive-onset MS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1352458511423778" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1352458511423778">
<title>Study design</title>
<p>We designed a questionnaire with questions on demographics, MS characteristics, level of sunlight exposure and skin type characteristics.</p>
<p>Respondents were asked to indicate whether they had a definite, probable or possible diagnosis of MS. Characteristics included the year of first MS symptoms, relapsing onset or progressive onset, and use of immunomodulatory drugs. We used the self-assessment scale of disability developed for the European study on costs and quality of life in MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1352458511423778">13</xref></sup> It is based on the original validated description in the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1352458511423778">14</xref></sup> and on the Patient Determined Disease Steps instrument.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1352458511423778">15</xref></sup> Subjects were asked to select from a series of statements describing limitations and walking disability. The self-assessment scale of disability allowed participants to be categorized into 11 steps of disability, from 0–10, corresponding to an EDSS score of 0, 1–1.5, 2–2.5, 3–3.5, 4–4.5, 5–5.5, 6, 6.5, 7–7.5, 8–8.5, 9–9.5. When the current disability level was estimated to be 6 or more, the year of reaching step 6 needed to be recorded.</p>
<p>Questions to assess skin type and sun exposure were based upon the validated questionnaire used in the Australian multicentre study of environmental factors and immune function (Ausimmune study), kindly provided by Ponsonby.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1352458511423778">16</xref></sup> Skin colour and sun reactivity in the middle of the day, for the first time in summer without sunscreen were assessed, as well as the tendency to burn, the number of lifetime burns and the ability to tan. An estimation of the time spent in the sun during weekends and holidays in summer and in winter during the last 10 years allowed categorization into three levels: less than 1 h, 1–2 h and 2 h or more daily. Whether activities were taking respondents outside in summer and in winter during the last 10 years included the possibilities less than, equal to or more than peers. Peers were defined as persons of the same age. Information about sunscreen use and outdoor job time was requested.</p>
<p>Instructions were given at the beginning of the questionnaire and in a separate information letter. The study was approved by the ethics committee at the Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussels, and the local ethics committee at the National MS Center in Melsbroek, Belgium</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1352458511423778">
<title>Data collection and management</title>
<p>The questionnaire was distributed in September 2009 via a mailing office to all persons with MS, registered by the Flemish MS society. In each of the five Flemish provinces, the MS society provides psychosocial support to persons with MS and their families, irrespective of neurological disability and medical care. Taking into account MS prevalence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1352458511423778">17</xref></sup> and general population data, we estimate that about half of the total Flemish MS population is registered. According to the annual report 2009, this MS registry has a small proportion of youngsters (12.2% younger than 40 years of age) and a high proportion of elderly people with MS (34.8% 60 years of age or older).</p>
<p>Respondents were invited to sign a consent statement. Completed questionnaires were returned to the investigators using a pre-addressed and prepaid envelope.</p>
<p>To increase the response rate, a reminder announcement was made in the journal and on the website of the Flemish MS society. Upon receipt, the questionnaires were checked to ensure the data were complete. When incomplete, participants were contacted whenever possible.</p>
<p>Only data from participants who reported a definite MS diagnosis were used for the analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1352458511423778">
<title>Outcome variables</title>
<p>The outcome measure was the time from onset to reach EDSS 6 in the self-assessment scale of disability. Because this step signifies the use of a cane or support to walk for a distance of 100 m, it is considered a reliable milestone during the course of MS. Both time from disease onset and time from birth to EDSS 6 were calculated using the year of MS onset, the year of birth and the year of reaching the irreversible disability step of EDSS 6.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1352458511423778">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>All analyses were stratified according to relapsing onset or progressive onset. Predictive variables included skin type characteristics and self-reported levels of sun exposure in the last 10 years.</p>
<p>When participants had reached EDSS 6 without indicating the year of reaching that milestone, these data as well as other missing data were handled as missing values. Because the levels of sun exposure were assessed during the 10-year period before the survey, data from participants who reached EDSS 6 before this period and data from participants with a disease duration of less than 10 years were excluded from the analysis of these variables.</p>
<p>MS variables included gender, age at onset and current immunomodulatory treatment. Time-to-event plots using time from disease onset and time from birth to reach EDSS 6 were constructed by the Kaplan–Meier method, with differences in survival analysis assessed by the log rank test. From these Kaplan–Meier curves, the median time-to-event and 95% confidence interval (CI) were calculated.</p>
<p>Cox proportional hazards regression modelling adjusting for gender, age at onset, and immunomodulation was used to estimate hazard ratios for time from onset to EDSS 6 and for time from birth to EDSS 6, for each predictive life style variable. The first category was the reference group.</p>
<p>In addition, we fitted Cox models further adjusted for phenotypic skin characteristics and explored interactions of sun exposure by sex and immunomodulatory treatment in the selected group of participants.</p>
<p>Data were analysed using PASW version 17.0 for windows (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL).</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section7-1352458511423778" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section8-1352458511423778">
<title>Participant characteristics</title>
<p>We received 1431 questionnaires (response rate of 43.1%). The inclusion of all usable surveys with definite MS diagnosis resulted in 1372 questionnaires to be analysed. The characteristics of our study population are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1352458511423778">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1352458511423778" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline characteristics of the relapsing and progressive onset groups</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1352458511423778" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511423778-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristic</th>
<th align="left">Relapsing onset</th>
<th align="left">Progressive onset</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic> = 893 (33.3%)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic> = 479 (34.9%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Female, number (%)</td>
<td>675 (75.6%)</td>
<td>298 (62.2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Age at survey, yr</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean</td>
<td>50.3</td>
<td>58.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median (range)</td>
<td>50 (17–85)</td>
<td>59 (23–89)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Age at onset, yr</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean</td>
<td>31.5</td>
<td>37.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median (range)</td>
<td>30 (4–65)</td>
<td>37 (9–69)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Disease duration, yr</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean</td>
<td>18.8</td>
<td>21.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median (range)</td>
<td>17 (0–63)</td>
<td>20 (0–62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EDSS ≥ 6 at survey, number (%)</td>
<td>321 (35.9%)</td>
<td>383 (80%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Treatment at survey, number (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Interferon beta</td>
<td>358 (40.1%)</td>
<td>101 (21%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Glatiramer acetate</td>
<td>95 (10.6%)</td>
<td>19 (4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Natalizumab or mitoxantrone</td>
<td>70 (7.8%)</td>
<td>19 (4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No immunomodulatory treatment</td>
<td>370 (41.4%)</td>
<td>349 (71%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p>Compared with the age-group distribution of the members of the Flemish MS society, our study sample showed a small shift towards younger age groups: 30.3% of respondents were 60 years or older compared with 34.8% of the persons with MS registered by the Flemish MS society (data not shown). Some 14% of respondents were aged 40 years or younger.</p>
<p>After a mean disease duration of 19.7 years, 704/1372 (51.3%) had reached EDSS 6. Time to EDSS 6 was specified in 547/704 (78%) subjects. Some of them, 173/547 (31.6%), had reached EDSS 6 before the start of the 10-year period of assessing sun exposure. In 299/1372 (21.8%) participants disease duration was less than 10 years. Data from all these participants were excluded when investigating the association of sun exposure and sun protection in the last 10 years with progression of disability, leaving 895 subjects for the final analysis.</p>
<p>Skin colour, skin characteristics and working place were related to the time to reach EDSS 6 in the total patient population (<italic>n</italic> = 1372).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1352458511423778">
<title>Kaplan–Meier estimates</title>
<p>The main results are shown <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1352458511423778">Table 2A</xref> (relapsing-onset group) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458511423778">Table 2B</xref> (progressive-onset group).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1352458511423778" position="float">
<label>Table 2A.</label>
<caption>
<p>Kaplan–Meier estimates: factors affecting time to sustained EDSS 6 in relapsing-onset MS</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1352458511423778" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511423778-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">number</th>
<th align="left">Time from onset</th>
<th/>
<th align="left">Time from birth</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">Median years to EDSS 6 (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th>
<th align="left">Median years to EDSS 6 (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Skin colour when out of sun</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> white</td>
<td>760</td>
<td>27 (24.6–29.4)</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>59 (56.5–61.5)</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> brown</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>28 (20.4–35.6)</td>
<td/>
<td>58 (51.3–64.7)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Skin reaction following intense sun exposure</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never burning</td>
<td>152</td>
<td>25 (22.2–27.8)</td>
<td>0.55</td>
<td>59 (55.0–63.0)</td>
<td>0.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 2 h</td>
<td>355</td>
<td>28 (21.6–34.4)</td>
<td/>
<td>62 (57.6–66.4)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 30 min–1 h</td>
<td>271</td>
<td>27 (23.2–30.8)</td>
<td/>
<td>58 (54.9–61.1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning in less than 30 min</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>28 (22.3–33.7)</td>
<td/>
<td>57 (51.8–62.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in summer*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>190</td>
<td>31 (27.3–34.7)</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>60 (53.6–66.4)</td>
<td>0.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>187</td>
<td>30 (24.0–36.0)</td>
<td/>
<td>60 (56.6–63.4)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>234</td>
<td>33 (30.9–35.10)</td>
<td/>
<td>65 (56.8–73.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in winter<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>387</td>
<td>29 (25.5–32.5)</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>59 (54.9–63.1)</td>
<td>0.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
<td>133</td>
<td>35 (27.1–42.9)</td>
<td/>
<td>79 (.-.)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h more daily</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>33 (26.8–39.2)</td>
<td/>
<td>65 (56.8–73.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in summer compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>335</td>
<td>29 (26.2–31.8)</td>
<td><bold>0.001</bold></td>
<td>58 (55.6–60.4)</td>
<td><bold>0.021</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
<td>206</td>
<td>35 (.-.)</td>
<td/>
<td>68 (58.8–77.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
<td>70</td>
<td>53 (.-.)</td>
<td/>
<td>65 (56.3–73.7)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in winter compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>378</td>
<td>29 (25.9–32.1)</td>
<td><bold>0.005</bold></td>
<td>59 (56.0–62.0)</td>
<td><bold>0.041</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
<td>192</td>
<td>. (.-.)</td>
<td/>
<td>79 (.-.)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
<td>41</td>
<td>53 (.-.)</td>
<td/>
<td>72 (.-.)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun screen/protection<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>30 (26.5–33.5)</td>
<td><bold>0.048</bold></td>
<td>67 (58.3–75.7)</td>
<td><bold>0.018</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> sometimes</td>
<td>377</td>
<td>32 (29.0–35.0)</td>
<td/>
<td>65 (58.9–71.1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> always</td>
<td>121</td>
<td>26 (24.1–27.9)</td>
<td/>
<td>56 (52.7–59.3)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Working place</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly inside work</td>
<td>727</td>
<td>28 (25.8–30.2)</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>59 (56.7–61.3)</td>
<td>0.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> both inside and outdoor</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>28 (21.0–35.0)</td>
<td/>
<td>61 (52.5–69.5)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly outdoor</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>27 (19.0–34.0)</td>
<td/>
<td>54 (51.3–56.7)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1352458511423778">
<label>*</label>
<p>analysis of subjects who reached EDSS 6 within the last 10 years and had disease duration of at least 10 years</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1352458511423778">
<label>**</label>
<p>If the cumulative survival distribution does not go below 50% for the range of times in the data, the median can not be estimated and does not appear in the output. If the standard error of a median equals zero, the 95% confidence of that median does not appear in the output.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-1352458511423778" position="float">
<label>Table 2B.</label>
<caption>
<p>Kaplan–Meier estimates: factors affecting time to sustained EDSS 6 in progressive-onset MS</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1352458511423778" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511423778-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">number</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Time from onset</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Time from birth</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">Median years to EDSS 6 (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th>
<th align="left">Median years to EDSS 6 (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Skin colour when out of sun</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> white</td>
<td>385</td>
<td>13 (11.3–14.7)</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>52 (50.3–53.7)</td>
<td>0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> brown</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>14 (8.9–19.1)</td>
<td/>
<td>55 (52.4–57.6)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Skin reaction following intense sun exposure</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never burning</td>
<td>123</td>
<td>14 (10.7–17.3)</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>54 (52.3–55.7)</td>
<td><bold>0.03</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 2 h</td>
<td>165</td>
<td>13 (10.6–15.4)</td>
<td/>
<td>53 (50.2–55.8)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 30 min–1 h</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>14 (11.6–16.4)</td>
<td/>
<td>54 (51.5–56.5)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning in less than 30 min</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>11 (8.2–13.8)</td>
<td/>
<td>44 (40.8–47.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in summer<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>19 (16.4–21.6)</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>59 (56.0–62.0)</td>
<td>0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>15 (7.9–22.1)</td>
<td/>
<td>54 (51.7–56.3)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>16 (12.5–19.5)</td>
<td/>
<td>56 (51.8–60.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in winter<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>199</td>
<td>18 (15.4–20.6)</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>58 (55.9–60.1)</td>
<td>0.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>17 (11.3–22.7)</td>
<td/>
<td>53 (50.4–55.6)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>16 (7.4–24.5)</td>
<td/>
<td>56 (39.6–72.4)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in summer compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>186</td>
<td>18 (15.6–20.4)</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>57 (54.4–59.6)</td>
<td>0.93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>20 (12.3–27.7)</td>
<td/>
<td>56 (51.1–60.9)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>13 (4.2–21.8)</td>
<td/>
<td>54 (45.5–62.5)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun exposure in winter compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>208</td>
<td>17 (14.6–19.4)</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>57 (54.3–59.7)</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>20 (15.4–24.6)</td>
<td/>
<td>60 (51.3–68.7)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>11 (3.3–18.7)</td>
<td/>
<td>44 (39.2–48.8)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Sun screen/protection<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>17 (13.4–20.6)</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>59 (54.0–64.0)</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> sometimes</td>
<td>159</td>
<td>17 (13.6–20.4)</td>
<td/>
<td>56 (53.4–58.6)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> always</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>18 (5.4–30.6)</td>
<td/>
<td>60 (51.9–68.1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Working place</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly inside work</td>
<td>367</td>
<td>13 (11.5–14.5)</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>52 (50.2–53.8)</td>
<td>0.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> both inside and outdoor</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>13 (11.5–14.5)</td>
<td/>
<td>53 (45.5–60.5)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly outdoor</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>11 (6.9–15.1)</td>
<td/>
<td>(52 48.8–55.2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1352458511423778">
<label>*</label>
<p>analysis of subjects who reached EDSS 6 in the last 10 years and had disease duration of at least 10 years</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In the relapsing-onset group, time from onset and from birth differed significantly for sun exposure in summer and winter in the last 10 years compared with peers, with increased intervals when participants reported equal or higher levels of sun exposure compared with peers. A shorter time to reach EDSS 6 was found in subjects reporting always to use sun protection. Skin type characteristics did not reveal any significant differences.</p>
<p>In the progressive-onset group, time from birth to EDSS 6 differed significantly for the skin reactivity to sunlight, with decreased time intervals for those who reported to burn quickly (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458511423778">Table 2B</xref>). Levels of sun exposure did not significantly affect the time to EDSS 6 in the progressive-onset group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1352458511423778">
<title>Cox proportional hazards analysis</title>
<p>The hazard ratios adjusted for age at onset, gender and immunomodulatory treatment are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1352458511423778">Tables 3A</xref> (relapsing-onset group) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1352458511423778">3B</xref> (progressive-onset group).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1352458511423778" position="float">
<label>Table 3A.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relapsing onset: adjusted hazard ratios (HR) for time to sustained EDSS 6</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1352458511423778" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511423778-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">number</th>
<th align="left">Time from onset</th>
<th align="left">Time from birth</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">adjusted HR (95% CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1352458511423778">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">adjusted HR (95% CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1352458511423778">*</xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Skin colour when out of sun</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(95% CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1352458511423778">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> white</td>
<td>760</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> brown</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>1.14 (0.80–1.61)</td>
<td>1.13 (0.80–1.60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Skin reaction following intense sun exposure</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never burning</td>
<td>152</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 2 h</td>
<td>355</td>
<td>0.92 (0.65–1.31)</td>
<td>0.97 (0.68–1.37)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 30 min–1 h</td>
<td>271</td>
<td>0.93 (0.64–1.34)</td>
<td>0.90 (0.62–1.21)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning in less than 30 min</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>1.11 (0.69–1.62)</td>
<td>1.16 (0.76–1.77)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in summer<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>190</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>187</td>
<td>1.13 (0.78–1.65)</td>
<td>1.15 (0.79–1.68)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>234</td>
<td>0.94 (0.64–1.37)</td>
<td>0.95 (0.66–1.38)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in winter<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>387</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>0.72 (0.47–1.11)</td>
<td>0.69 (0.45–1.07)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>0.74 (0.47–1.18)</td>
<td>0.73 (0.46–1.14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in summer compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>335</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to</td>
<td>206</td>
<td><bold>0.67 (0.48–0.95)</bold></td>
<td><bold>0.68 (0.48–0.96)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than</td>
<td>70</td>
<td><bold>0.44 (0.24–0.81)</bold></td>
<td><bold>0.45 (0.25–0.81)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in winter compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>378</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to</td>
<td>192</td>
<td><bold>0.63 (0.44–0.91)</bold></td>
<td><bold>0.66 (0.45–0.96)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>0.49 (0.23–1.06)</td>
<td><bold>0.48 (0.23–0.99)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun screen/protection<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> sometimes</td>
<td>377</td>
<td>1.04 (0.68–1.58)</td>
<td>0111 (0.73–1.68)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> always</td>
<td>121</td>
<td><bold>1.78 (1.10–2.86)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.79 (1.11–2.88)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Working place</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly inside work</td>
<td>727</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> both inside and outdoor</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>0.76 (0.47–1.22)</td>
<td>0.76 (0.47–1.22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly outdoor</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>1.15 (0.75–1.77)</td>
<td>1.15 (0.75–1.77)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1352458511423778">
<label>*</label>
<p>after adjusting for gender, age at onset, immunomodulating therapy (yes/no)</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1352458511423778">
<label>**</label>
<p>analysis of subjects who reached EDSS 6 in the last 10 years and had disease duration of at least 10 years</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table5-1352458511423778" position="float">
<label>Table 3B.</label>
<caption>
<p>Progressive onset: adjusted hazard ratios (HR) for time to sustained EDSS 6</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1352458511423778" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511423778-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">number</th>
<th align="left">Time from onset</th>
<th align="left">Time from birth</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">adjusted HR (95% CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1352458511423778">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">adjusted HR (95% CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1352458511423778">*</xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Skin colour when out of sun</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> white</td>
<td>385</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> brown</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>0.78 (0.57–1.07)</td>
<td>0.75 (0.55–1.03)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Skin reaction following intense sun exposure</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never burning</td>
<td>123</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 2 h</td>
<td>165</td>
<td>1.08 (0.79–1.48)</td>
<td>1.08 (0.78–1.48)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning after 30 min–1 h</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>1.16 (0.83–1.63)</td>
<td>1.15 (0.82–1.61)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> burning in less than 30 min</td>
<td>66</td>
<td><bold>1.54 (1.05–2.25)</bold></td>
<td><bold>1.78 (1.21–2.61)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in summer<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>1.25 (0.80–1.95)</td>
<td>1.18 (0.75–1.86)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>1.12 (0.75–1.68)</td>
<td>1.13 (0.76–1.69)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in winter<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than 1 h daily</td>
<td>199</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1–2 h daily</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>1.26 (0.80–1.99)</td>
<td>1.27 (0.81–2.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2 h or more daily</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>1.09 (0.64–1.87)</td>
<td>0.93 (0.54–1.62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in summer compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>186</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>0.87 (0.57–1.33)</td>
<td>0.87 (0.57–1.32)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>0.98 (0.55–1.75)</td>
<td>0.88 (0.50–1.57)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun exposure in winter compared with peers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> less than</td>
<td>208</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> equal to</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>0.92 (0.60–1.43)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.52–1.27)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> more than</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>2.02 (0.97–4.20)</td>
<td><bold>2.25 (1.08–4.67</bold>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Sun screen/protection<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511423778">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> never</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> sometimes</td>
<td>159</td>
<td>1.08 (0.72–1.61)</td>
<td>1.10 (0.74–1.65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> always</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>0.96 (0.54–1.70)</td>
<td>0.99 (0.55–1.76)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Working place</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly inside work</td>
<td>367</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
<td>1.0 (Reference)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> both inside and outdoor</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>0.88 (0.57–1.36)</td>
<td>0.93 (0.60–1.44)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> mostly outdoor</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>1.00 (0.69–1.46)</td>
<td>0.97 (0.67–1.42)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1352458511423778">
<label>*</label>
<p>after adjusting for gender, age at onset, immunomodulating therapy (yes/no)</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1352458511423778">
<label>**</label>
<p>analysis of subjects who reached EDSS 6 in the last 10 years and had disease duration of at least 10 years</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In the relapsing-onset group, reporting of equal levels of sun exposure compared with peers in summer and winter was associated with a significantly reduced risk to reach EDSS 6. Hazards decreased when the levels of sun exposure were reported to be higher than in persons of the same age, but did not reach significance during winter in the time-from-onset analysis. Always using sun protection was associated with an increased risk to reach EDSS 6, both from onset and from birth. The Cox model, further adjusted for phenotypic skin characteristics, indicated that skin phenotype was not a confounder. The magnitude of hazard ratios and 95% CIs in this analysis did not markedly differ from the hazard ratios and 95% CI in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1352458511423778">Tables 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1352458511423778">3B</xref>. The multivariate models incorporating the interactions of sun exposure by sex and immunomodulatory treatment showed no significant interactions.</p>
<p>In the progressive-onset group, reporting of intense skin reactions during sun exposure with burning in less than 30 min was associated with an increased risk of reaching EDSS 6. The increasing hazards according to the speed of burning suggest a dose–effect relationship. The increased risk to reach EDSS 6 in association with higher levels of sun exposure compared with peers reached statistical significance in the time-from-birth analysis.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section11-1352458511423778" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In our study of persons with MS registered by the Flemish MS society, self-reported measures of sunlight exposure and sun sensitivity were associated with progression of disability. A different pattern of associations was found in relapsing versus progressive-onset MS.</p>
<p>In the relapsing-onset group, reporting of equal or higher levels of sun exposure than persons of the same age in the last 10 years was associated with a decreased likelihood to reach EDSS 6. The association between sun exposure and the time to milestone EDSS 6 was not confounded by phenotypic skin characteristics. No interaction of sun exposure by sex or immunomodulatory treatment was evident. In the progressive-onset group, the skin tendency to burn within 30 min of intense sun exposure was related to an increased progression rate.</p>
<p>Our questionnaire-based study has a number of limitations. First, despite our efforts to increase the number of replies, the response rate in our total study sample was below 50% and included a slight bias towards younger persons with MS. We speculate that older persons with MS may have been too disabled to participate. Nevertheless, the proportion of elderly persons with MS, age 60 or more, both in the registry of the Flemish MS Society (34.8%) and in our study sample (30.3%), was higher than reported in prevalence studies (21–26%),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1352458511423778">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1352458511423778">18</xref></sup> indicating that this registry is not representative of the entire MS population. Likewise, the high proportion of progressive-onset MS in our study sample might reflect the selection of more severe MS cases, registered by the Flemish MS society. Data collection in this specific population, albeit not representative of the total MS population, offers opportunities to study associations of predictive variables with long-term outcome and generate hypotheses about the mechanisms involved in disease progression. Second, we relied on self-reported data with regard to predictive variables, disease onset and disability. This always brings a risk of recall bias. Nevertheless, a population-based case-control study provided evidence that adults were able to recall past sun exposure with demonstrated validity and reliability, and a good test–retest agreement was obtained for skin questions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1352458511423778">19</xref></sup> Furthermore a very good correlation with self-administered EDSS using ambulation has been reported, with an intraclass coefficient of 0.89 (95% CI not reported),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1352458511423778">20</xref></sup> and the validity of patient-derived data including retrospective data on year of disease onset, diagnosis and time-to-disability milestones, including EDSS 6, seems to be robust with intraclass coefficients of respectively 0.93 (0.86–0.96), 0.98 (0.97–0.99) and 0.95 (0.90–0.97).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1352458511423778">21</xref></sup> Third, there were 22% missing values with regard to the time of reaching sustained EDSS 6 in participants who otherwise indicated that they had an EDSS equal or above 6. Fourth, we assessed self-reported sun exposure during the last 10 years and had to exclude data from 472 subjects in whom sun exposure was assessed after reaching EDSS 6 or prior to disease onset. Even then, the associations in relapsing-onset MS persist. Fifth, no objective measures of skin phenotype were included.</p>
<p>In relapsing-onset MS, reporting of equal or higher levels of sun exposure than persons of the same age in the last 10 years was associated with a reduced risk to reach EDSS 6. The decreasing hazards from low to high levels of sun exposure suggest a dose–effect relationship. Taken together with the increased risk of reaching EDSS 6 in subjects always using sun protection, a protective effect of sun exposure, possibly mediated by vitamin D, cannot be excluded. Our findings are in line with the observations in a population-based sample of predominantly relapsing-onset MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458511423778">6</xref></sup> A strong correlation between reduced sun exposure during the last 3 years, lower vitamin D levels and higher disability, as measured by the EDSS, was reported. Decreased mobility and reduced outdoor behaviour were thought to explain the results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458511423778">6</xref></sup> In two cross-sectional studies, including a rather low number of cases, parameters of self-reported sun exposure were not associated with the MS Severity Score (MSSS), an approach to correct EDSS by comparing a patient’s disability with the distribution of scores in cases with equivalent disease duration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1352458511423778">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1352458511423778">22</xref></sup> However, in one study information regarding sun exposure during childhood, not during adult life, was requested.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1352458511423778">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>Irrespective of causality or reverse causality, it remains difficult to explain why these associations were restricted to the relapse-onset group. In view of the inverse association between monthly sunlight exposure and relapse rates in MS,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458511423778">7</xref></sup> it cannot be ruled out that sun exposure might protect against relapse-related disability.</p>
<p>In progressive-onset MS, an increased progression was associated with the tendency to burn within 30 min, characteristic for fair skin types.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1352458511423778">23</xref></sup> The association of reporting higher levels of sun exposure in winter than persons with the same age with an increased risk to reach EDSS 6 should be interpreted with caution, because of the small number of subjects.</p>
<p>Skin reactivity to sun exposure is known to be determined by genetic factors. The present association suggests that mechanisms linked with sun reactivity might be involved in the time to reach EDSS 6 in progressive-onset MS.</p>
<p>An important gene in humans, known to account for the substantial variation in skin and hair colour, is the melanocortin 1 receptor (MC1R) gene, encoding the receptor for α-MSH. People with fair skin, red hair and increased sun sensitivity often carry germ-line polymorphisms in the MC1R gene that reduce the activity of the receptor. A better ability to synthesize vitamin D under conditions of limited UVR exposure has been proposed to explain an association of a fair skin with a reduced risk of having EDSS 6 in a subgroup analysis of 169 females with MS of at least 10 years of duration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1352458511423778">12</xref></sup> On the other hand, polymorphisms in the pigmentation-related gene, MC1R, related to sun-sensitive skin phenotypes, have been associated with a worse outcome of MS, which was defined as having reached EDSS 6 or not.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1352458511423778">11</xref></sup> Certain MC1R alleles have been associated with the MSSS, only in those with a positive history of sunburn, suggesting a complex interaction between skin phenotype, genotype and severity of MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1352458511423778">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>MC1R are expressed on various cell types involved in immune response. The major ligand for this receptor is α-MSH, a neuropeptide with potent immunomodulatory effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1352458511423778">24</xref></sup> It downregulates proinflammatory cytokines and induces IL 10 and regulatory T cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1352458511423778">4</xref></sup> In subjects carrying defective MC1R variants, termed the Red Hair Colour variants, a reduced response to the action of α-MSH might explain why they appear to be less protected against the risk of MS, even in the context of sun exposure during summer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1352458511423778">25</xref></sup> The wide distribution of several MCR subtypes, including the MC1R, in neural, glial and endothelial cells and the protective effects of α-MSH and melanocortins in animal models of brain ischemia and spinal cord injury,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1352458511423778">26</xref></sup> suggest that lack of full receptor functioning with reduced α-MSH secretion in response to UV might also affect neuroprotective mechanisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1352458511423778">26</xref></sup> We hypothesize that reduced effects of α-MSH in subjects with defective MC1R variants might adversely affect axonal degeneration in progressive-onset MS.</p>
<p>The main conclusion from our exploratory study is that measures of sun exposure and sun reactivity were associated with progression of disability in MS. The association in relapsing-onset MS might be explained by either a beneficial effect of sun exposure or reverse causality. The association of an increased sun sensitivity of the skin with a worse outcome in progressive-onset MS suggests an underlying mechanism, which could be related to defective MC1R activity. The difference in associations between relapsing and progressive-onset MS supports the hypothesis that separate mechanisms are involved in relapse-mediated disability and progressive axonal degeneration. While recognizing the limitations of a survey in a specific MS population, these findings may contribute to our understanding of the disease processes in MS.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>We thank all respondents from the Flemish MS society. We are grateful to the nurses, Ann Van Remoortel and Gert Ooms, for their unremitting support.</p></ack>
<sec id="section12-1352458511423778">
<title>Conflicts of interest statement</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1352458511423778">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This study was a collaboration between the Flemish MS society, the neurological and statistical department from the University of Brussels and the National MS Center in Melsbroek, with financial support from the “MS fonds” from the University of Leuven-Melsbroek.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1352458511423778">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van der Mei</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsonby</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Past exposure to sun, skin phenotype, and risk of multiple sclerosis: case-control study</article-title>. <source>Br Med J</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1352458511423778">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gauderman</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cozen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Childhood sun exposure influences risk of multiple sclerosis in monozygotic twins</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1352458511423778">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramagopalan</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maugeri</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Handunnetthi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Expression of the multiple sclerosis-associated MHC class II Allele HLA-DRB1*1501 is regulated by vitamin D</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000369</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1352458511423778">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ponsonby</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Mei</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>UVR, vitamin D and three autoimmune diseases – multiple sclerosis, type 1 diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Photochem Photobiol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1267</fpage>–<lpage>1275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1352458511423778">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sadovnick</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duquette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebers</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A timing-of-birth effect on multiple sclerosis clinical phenotype</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1352458511423778">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van</surname><given-names>der</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsonby</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Vitamin D levels in people with multiple sclerosis and community controls in Tasmania, Australia</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>254</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1352458511423778">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tremlett</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van</surname><given-names>der</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pittas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Monthly ambient sunlight, infections and relapse rates in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neuroepidemiology</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1352458511423778">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>S</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blizzard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Higher 25-hydroxyvitamin D is associated with lower relapse risk in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1352458511423778">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feychting</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nise</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Occupational exposure to UV light and mortality from multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Am J Ind Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1352458511423778">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dosemeci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alavanja</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mortality from multiple sclerosis and exposure to residential and occupational solar radiation: a case-control study based on death certificates</article-title>. <source>Occup Environ Med</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1352458511423778">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weatherby</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woolmore</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Susceptibility and outcome in MS: associations with polymorphisms in pigmentation-related genes</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>2323</fpage>–<lpage>2325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1352458511423778">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woolmore</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pye</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Studies of associations between disability in multiple sclerosis, skin type, gender and ultraviolet radiation</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1352458511423778">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kobelt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Costs and quality of life for patients with multiple sclerosis in Belgium</article-title>. <source>Eur J Health Econ</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>): <fpage>S24</fpage>–<lpage>S33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1352458511423778">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurtzke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rating neurologic impairment in multiple sclerosis: an Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS)</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1444</fpage>–<lpage>1452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1352458511423778">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hohol</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Disease steps in multiple sclerosis: a longitudinal study comparing disease steps and EDSS to evaluate disease progression</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1352458511423778">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsonby</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMichael</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Observational analytic studies in multiple sclerosis: controlling bias through study design and conduct. The Australian Multicentre Study of Environment and Immune Function</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>827</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1352458511423778">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Ooteghem</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D’Hooghe</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vlietinck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carton</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of multiple sclerosis in Flanders, Belgium</article-title>. <source>Neuroepidemiology</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1352458511423778">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentzen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flachs</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stenager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bronnum-Hansen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch-Henriksen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of multiple sclerosis in Denmark 1950–2005</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1352458511423778">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van der Mei</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blizzard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsonby</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of adult recall of past sun exposure in a case-control study of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1538</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1352458511423778">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gianas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self-administered Expanded Disability Status Scale with functional system scores correlates well with a physician-administered test</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1352458511423778">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ben-Shlomo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Validity of patient-derived disability and clinical data in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>479</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1352458511423778">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strange</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeegers</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Multiple Sclerosis Severity Score: associations with MC1R single nucleotide polymorphisms and host response to ultraviolet radiation</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1116</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1352458511423778">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The validity and practicality of sun-reactive skin types I through VI</article-title>. <source>Arch Dermatol</source> <year>1988</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>871</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1352458511423778">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Do hyporesponsive genetic variants of the melanocortin 1 receptor contribute to the etiology of multiple sclerosis?</article-title> <source>Med Hypotheses</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1352458511423778">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Mei</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsonby</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Melanocortin 1 receptor genotype, past environmental sun exposure, and risk of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1352458511423778">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Catania</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Neuroprotective actions of melanocortins: a therapeutic opportunity</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>