<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppim</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part M: Journal of Engineering for the Maritime Environment</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1475-0902</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-3084</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1475090212441444</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1475090212441444</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The future of natural gas as a fuel in marine gas turbine for LNG carriers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>El-Gohary</surname><given-names>M Morsy</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1475090212441444">Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering Department, Alexandria University, Egypt</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1475090212441444">M Morsy El-Gohary, Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering Department, Faculty of Engineering, Alexandria University, Egypt. Email: <email>prof.morsy@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>371</fpage>
<lpage>377</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>3</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This paper discusses the suitability of using natural gas as a fuel for marine gas turbine electric propulsion (DFGE), utilizing natural boil-off gas and forced boil-off gas, as well as investigating its economical and environmental beneﬁts over other propulsion options. The benchmark ship chosen for this study has a capacity of 150,000 m<sup>3</sup> and is powered by conventional steam propulsion. For this purpose a spreadsheet model was developed to determine the liquefied natural gas carrier operating costs for different propulsion options. This is in addition to a sensitivity analysis to study the effect of varying range, heavy fuel oil (HFO) and natural gas prices on ship operating cost. Recently, about 40% of the new orders shifted to slow speed diesel engines with re-liquefaction plant and dual fuel diesel electric propulsion. To date, marine gas turbines are not used in liquefied natural gas carriers.</p>
<p>It was found that using natural gas as a fuel with the proposed marine gas turbine cycle at current HFO and natural gas prices provides the highest cost saving for a distance less than 4000 nautical miles (NM). With the expected changes in fuel prices, the proposed cycle achieves cost saving of 3% per round trip, and this saving is directly proportional to increasing fuel prices, compared to other options.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Natural gas</kwd>
<kwd>marine gas turbine</kwd>
<kwd>liquefied natural gas carriers</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1475090212441444" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>During the last decade economical factors have played a major role in the choice of diesel fuel type and engine combination for ship propulsion. Because more than 50% of a ship’s operating cost is, generally, the cost of fuel oil, most of the world’s ship-owners use degraded residue heavy fuel oil in marine power plants, for economy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1475090212441444">1</xref></sup> These degraded heavy oils, however, contain high levels of asphalt, carbon residues, sulfur and metallic compounds, which are the main source of air pollution.</p>
<p>Since the beginning of the twenty-first century, there has been a significant increase in emission regulations, not only by the International Maritime Organization (IMO), but also regional regulation in some countries. The use of heavy fuel oil has, consequently, been limited, especially in areas where the emissions from ships has shown noticeable increase, for example, in European countries,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1475090212441444">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1475090212441444">3</xref></sup> as shown <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1475090212441444">in Figure 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1475090212441444">Figure 1</xref> presents the comparison between expected increase of SO<sub>2</sub> emissions resulting from land-based sources and from international shipping in European sea areas during the period of 2000–2030.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>SO2 emission European countries increment. Source: adapted with permission.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1475090212441444">3</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section2-1475090212441444">
<title>Conventional liquid fuels international specification</title>
<p>The International Standard Organization (ISO), in cooperation with marine and petroleum industries, prepared specifications to meet the requirements for marine fuels supplied worldwide for use onboard ships. There are 19 categories of residual fuels available internationally. Out of these 19, four categories or grades are most frequently supplied and used by ships. The industry names for the four grades are IFO180, IFO380, MDO and MGO, as shown <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1475090212441444">Table 1</xref>. Industrial nomenclature is based on the fuel viscosity at 50 °C. IFO180 and IFO380 indicate that the viscosity of the fuel is 180 and 380 cSt, respectively, at 50 °C. IFO180 has about 6 to 7% gas oil and IFO380 has about 3% gas oil.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Diesel fuel types for marine use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1475090212441444">4</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1475090212441444" xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Fuel type</th>
<th align="left">Fuel grades</th>
<th align="left">Common industry name</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Distillate</td>
<td>DMX, DMA, DMB, DMC</td>
<td>Gas oil or marine gas oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intermediate</td>
<td>IFO 180-IFO 380</td>
<td>Marine diesel fuel or Intermediate fuel oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Residual</td>
<td>RMA-RML</td>
<td>Fuel oil or residual fuel oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1475090212441444">
<p>Table adapted from data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1475090212441444">4</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Because of the higher gas oil content in IFO180, the price of the IFO180 is higher than the heavier IFO380 grade. MDO stands for marine diesel oil, which is a blend of gas oil and heavy oil. Marine gas oil (MGO) is a clear type of oil, i.e. not blended with heavy oil.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1475090212441444">
<title>Conventional liquid fuels and environmental issue</title>
<p>Although diesel fuels showed a notable spread as the main fuel for the majority of marine power plants, recent years have shown some problems due to the emissions issue, which presents one of the main dis-advantages to using diesel oil onboard ships. Uncontrolled emissions from diesel fuel oils have a significant impact upon our environment. There are some adverse impacts caused by the various emission components, including NO<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>, SO<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>, CO and HC. A more comprehensive review was recently carried out by various organizations concerned with air pollution, discussing health and welfare impacts from burning the fuel oils and quantifying the financial benefits that result from reducing these emissions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1475090212441444">5</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1475090212441444">
<title>Marine liquid fuel prices</title>
<p>Fuel prices in general have shown a change through the last years. The price has increased by the beginning of 2007, reaching its maximum value in July 2008; consequently marine fuel types also followed this change. However, with the beginning of the economic crisis the fuel prices showed a rapid drop and reached its minimum level within a few months. But it is expected that the prices will show a slight increase throughout the next months as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1475090212441444">Figure 2</xref>. Surely the unstable fuel price plays a role in the economy of the marine industry; therefore, it will be a good idea to look forward to a marine fuel that has a stable price or is less affected by the world political and economical issues.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Expected fuel prices through coming months. Source: used with permission.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1475090212441444">6</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1475090212441444">
<title>Propulsion options</title>
<p>The propulsion options for LNG carrier should be able to utilize boil-off gas (BOG) very safely and easily.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1475090212441444">7</xref></sup> Also, they should be able to improve the operational efficiency and reduce the engine room size to increase cargo carrying capacity which is considered the main market requirements.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1475090212441444">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1475090212441444">9</xref></sup> The various proposed machinery arrangement being considered by the American Bureau of Shipping (ABS) and LNG industry (owners and shipyards) are as follows.</p>
<sec id="section6-1475090212441444">
<title>Steam turbine (ST)</title>
<p>Steam turbine installation has dominated in LNG shipping so far. This is because it can easily handle the evaporated boil-off gas (BOG), in addition to its high reliability and maintainability. The machinery layout with components efficiency as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1475090212441444">Figure 3</xref>. A high-speed gearbox drives a single fixed pitch propeller. The auxiliary power is obtained by steam turbine driven generator, and one or two diesel engine driven by a stand by generator. The boiler most commonly fires HFO and natural boil-off gas (N-BOG). Although, this installation has successfully met market requirements, the total plant efficiency is very low (calculated and found to be 30%), which led to high running costs. Another disadvantage of this installation is the shortage of qualified crew and low system redundancy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1475090212441444">10</xref></sup> These disadvantages opened a new window of opportunities for alternative methods of producing power for LNG carriers.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Typical steam plant for LNG Carrier of 150,000 m<sup>3</sup>.</p>
<p>Source: adapted from data with permission.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>LP: Low pressure turbine; HP: high pressure turbine.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1475090212441444">
<title>Slow speed diesel engine with reliquefaction plant (DERL)</title>
<p>Slow speed diesel engine has dominated the propulsion and electric power generation in all segments of merchant shipping, except LNG carriers. Experience gained from thousands of diesel engine installations in service has resulted in the development of high efficiency (about 50%), reliable and safe operation. It commonly burns liquid fuel as HFO. BOG has to be re-liquefied onboard by re-liquefaction plant and fed back to the cargo tank. These re-liquefaction plants require a substantial amount of electric power (3600 kW) to operate, representing a considerable added cost (6 MUS$) and weight.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref></sup> However, it delivers more cargo due to saving the BOG. A gas combustion unit (GCU) is also installed in case of reliquefaction plant failure. A typical plant arrangement for MC-90K SSDE made by B&amp;W is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1475090212441444">Figure 4</xref>. This configuration was carried out for Qatar gas for their new order ships.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig4-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Slow speed diesel engine with a re-liquefaction plant for LNGC carrier of 150,000 m<sup>3</sup>.</p>
<p>Source: adapted from data with permission.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Although, the total efficiency was calculated and found to be 49% as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1475090212441444">Figure 4</xref>, it could be increased by installing a combined power take off/take in (PTO/PTI) or using two diesel engines arrangement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1475090212441444">
<title>Dual fuel diesel engine (DFDE)</title>
<p>Dual fuel power plants may be mechanical or electrical drive. Using electric drive arrangement, the engines can be installed on a higher deck and hence, a great reduction in engine room could be provided. This layout offers a multiple system redundancy, apart from the shafting and the gearbox, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1475090212441444">Figure 5</xref>. This arrangement is ratified by ABS and ordered by Gaz de France energy for their new seven LNG carriers, which are in service now.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1475090212441444">12</xref></sup> The dual fuel engines is manufactured by Wartsila namely 50 DF engine. It utilizes natural boil-off gas (NBOG) in addition to the MDO for their pilot injection. In case of no NG available the engine will burn HFO. The main disadvantage of this system is the slightly higher cost for alternators and transformers, the low thermal efficiency of the plant (calculated efficiency is reduced to 42%), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1475090212441444">Figure 5</xref>, and the incompatibility of lube oil when shifting between gas and liquid mode.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Dual fuel diesel engine plant for LNG Carrier of 150,000 m<sup>3</sup>.</p>
<p>Source: adapted from data with permission.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1475090212441444">12</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Suggested advanced cycle marine gas turbine for LNG Carrier of 150,000 m<sup>3</sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1475090212441444">
<title>Suggested advanced cycle marine gas turbine (ACGT)</title>
<p>Daewoo Shipbuilding &amp; Marine Engineering (DSME) and Gaztransport &amp; Technigaz (GTT) have carried out extensive technical and economic studies on the gas turbine propulsion systems. From the study, it can be concluded that gas turbines propulsion can be one of the feasible alternative propulsion option for LNG carriers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1475090212441444">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1475090212441444"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1475090212441444"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1475090212441444">15</xref></sup> But it has not been adopted as a new propulsion system in LNG carriers so far.</p>
<p>The advanced marine gas turbine cycle is employed in two gas turbine/electric generators in father and son arrangement. The larger generator is based on the converted simple cycle and provides all power needed for sea going service. The small unit provides power of 5000 kW, for cargo pumping and port duty. Additionally, the small unit provides get-home service in case of non-availability of the large unit. The primary fuel used for gas turbines is natural boil-off gas (N-BOG) and forced boil-off gas (F-BOG). Marine diesel oil (MDO) is carried only to provide an emergency secondary fuel source to/from dry dock when gas is not available. The suggested plant efficiency was calculated to be 40%.</p>
<sec id="section10-1475090212441444">
<title>Economical evaluation</title>
<p>LNG cargo is bought at the export terminal at a certain price, namely free onboard price (FOB) and sold at the import terminal at a higher price namely, carriage and insurance freight (CIF). For a given class of LNG carrier design (cargo capacity, boil off gas rate), the propulsion and the corresponding fuel type used can generate a significant reduction in ship operating cost. Operating cost is divided to fixed and variable costs, which are the same for all propulsion options. The only relevant differences are the fuel, depreciation and maintenance cost which incurred by the choice of propulsion option and fuel type. Therefore, the economical benefit of using NG as a bunker fuel with the suggested advanced marine gas turbine cycle compared to other propulsion options was determined through an economical model. For this purpose a spreadsheet model was developed by the author to determine the difference in LNG carrier operating cost compared to the benchmark ship. The model incorporates the primary parameters as machinery efficiency, machinery specific weight, primary investment cost, maintenance cost, voyage distance, boil off gas rate (BOR) at laden and ballast, ship speed, ship capacity and finally HFO, MDO and NG price.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1475090212441444">
<title>Model description</title>
<p>The base engine examined during this study is GE-LM2500, one of the most diffused aero-derivative marine gas turbines in naval and commercial ships.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1475090212441444">16</xref></sup> It is a simple cycle-twin shaft gas turbine directly derived from GE-CF6 family of commercial aircraft engines and GE-TF39 military engines. It consists of a gas generator and power turbine. The gas generator includes a 16-stage axial flow compressor of pressure ratio = 18.7 to compress the atmospheric air from state point 1 to state point 2. Then fuel is added in a fully annular combustion chamber to increase the temperature at constant pressure to state 3. The hot gas is then expanded to state 4 by a two stage high-pressure turbine, which drives the compressor and accessory gearbox. After the aerodynamic coupling, the hot gases are expanded by a six-stage power turbine as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1475090212441444">Figure 7</xref>. The station numbering is in accordance with Aerospace Recommended Practice (ARP) 755A.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1475090212441444">17</xref></sup> Engine specifications at sea level, using marine diesel oil (MDO), with no inlet and exhaust losses, 60% relative humidity and ISO conditions are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1475090212441444">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig7-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Simple cycle marine gas turbine (LM2500).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>GE-LM2500 main specifications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1475090212441444">18</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1475090212441444" xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Nominal continuous power</td>
<td>25.060  kW</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pressure ratio</td>
<td>18.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Air flow</td>
<td>70 kg/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Turbine inlet temperature</td>
<td>1493 k</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Specific fuel consumption</td>
<td>225 g/kWh</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Heat rate</td>
<td>9703 kJ/kWh</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Thermal efficiency</td>
<td>37.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Exhaust gas temperature</td>
<td>839 k</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dimension</td>
<td>6.52 × 2.08 × 2.04 m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Weight</td>
<td>4.67 t</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1475090212441444">
<p>Table adapted from data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1475090212441444">18</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1475090212441444">
<title>Model assumptions</title>
<list id="list1-1475090212441444" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The state-of-the-art engine is selected for each option with their rated power, maintenance cost and specific weight, shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1475090212441444">Table 3</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Values of power plants efficiencies were calculated to be 30%, 49%, 42%, and 40% for steam turbine, DERL, DFDE and ACGT respectively.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Initial investment cost is considered, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1475090212441444">Table 4</xref>. For Re-liquefaction plant, an addition of 6 MUS$ extra investment for 3600 kW power.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For DFDE and ACGT options an addition of 7.5 MUS$ for E-motors, transformers and converters.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Amortizing over 20 years and 7.5% interest rate.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Boil off gas rate is 0.12% per day and 0.06% per day for laden and ballast conditions respectively.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Voyage distance is 7000 nautical miles (NM) and speed of 20 knots.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Based on previous data from 2000 to 2005, an average price of N-BOG (FOB), F-BOG (CIF), HFO and MDO were taken to be 104 US$/t, 156 US$/t, 135 US$/t and 210 US$/t respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1475090212441444">19</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Calorific value for NG, HFO, and MDO were 50 MJ/kg, 40 MJ/kg and 42 MJ/kg respectively.</p></list-item>
</list>
<table-wrap id="table3-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Propulsion options specifications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1475090212441444">19</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1475090212441444" xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Propulsion option</th>
<th align="left">Rated power (kW)</th>
<th align="left">Specific weight(kg/kW)</th>
<th align="left">Maintenance cost US$/kWh</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Steam turbine</td>
<td>33,000</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Slow speed diesel engine MAN B&amp;W 7K98MC</td>
<td>34,320</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>0.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dual fuel diesel engines (4 × Wartsila 9L50DF)</td>
<td>34,200</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>0.005</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1475090212441444">
<p>Table adapted from data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1475090212441444">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1475090212441444">19</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Initial investment cost of relevant propulsion systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1475090212441444">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1475090212441444">19</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1475090212441444" xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">System</th>
<th align="left">Initial cost</th>
<th align="left">US$M</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Steam turbine</td>
<td>Boiler,</td>
<td>13.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Condenser, turbine</td>
<td>3.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Gear box</td>
<td>0.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1 turbine gensets</td>
<td>0.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1 diesel gensets</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Propeller and shafting</td>
<td>0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Rudder and steering gear</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Total initial cost</td>
<td>19.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Slow speed diesel engine MAN B&amp;W 7K98MC</td>
<td>Main engines</td>
<td>7.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Re-liquefaction plant</td>
<td>6.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 diesel gensets</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Propeller and shafting</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Rudder and steering gear</td>
<td>0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Auxiliary boiler</td>
<td>0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Total initial cost</td>
<td>16.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Four dual fuel diesel engines (Wartsila 9L50DF)</td>
<td>4 × DFDE and alternators</td>
<td>11.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 Electrical motor-transformer</td>
<td>5.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Converter</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Gear box</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Propeller and shafting</td>
<td>0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Rudder and steering gear</td>
<td>0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>EMER. gas damping unit</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Total initial cost</td>
<td>20.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Suggested advanced cycle gas turbine</td>
<td>Main and auxiliary engines with alternators</td>
<td>13.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 electrical motor.</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>transformer, converter</td>
<td>5.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Gear box</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Propeller and shafting</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Rudder and steering gear</td>
<td>0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>EMER. gas damping unit</td>
<td>0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Total initial cost</td>
<td>22.4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1475090212441444">
<p>Table adapted from data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1475090212441444">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1475090212441444">19</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1475090212441444">
<title>Fuel cost</title>
<p>It was calculated for all options owing to its importance in the economic evaluation. The fuel cost saving compared to the benchmark ship was determined based on the calculated plant efficiencies, relevant fuel prices, lower fuel calorific values and BOG rate for both laden and ballast voyages. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1475090212441444">Figure 8</xref> shows the relevant fuel costs in percent compared to the steam propulsion option “benchmark ship”, which represents 100%. It is evident from the figure, that slow speed diesel engine with a re-liquefaction plant (DERL) burning HFO provides the least fuel cost saving by about 15%, followed by dual fuel diesel engine (DFDE) which, burning a fixed amount of N-BOG and an extra amount of HFO, in addition to MDO for pilot injection. DFDE provides a reduction in fuel cost by 30% compared to benchmark ship.</p>
<fig id="fig8-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relevant fuel cost saving compared to the benchmark ship.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Finally, the suggested advanced marine gas turbine cycle (ACGT) has the greatest cost saving by 45%. It utilizes natural boil-off gas (N-BOG) and forced boil-off gas (F-BOG) only. The higher heating value and lower NG price overcompensate the lower plant efficiency compared to other propulsion options.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1475090212441444">
<title>Sensitivity analysis</title>
<p>Length of the LNG carrier trading routes varies quite widely today, from below 1000 NM (round trip from Algeria to the other side of the Mediterranean) up to 7000 NM (round trip from Arabian Gulf to USA) and may be even more in the future. There is also an expected future increase in fuel prices. Therefore, the effect of varying range and HFO and NG price on the ship operating expenses was determined through a sensitivity analysis as follows:</p>
<sec id="section15-1475090212441444">
<title>Sensitivity to range</title>
<p>The percent saving of operating cost per round trip was compared to the benchmark ship for different trade routes of 1500, 3000, 5000 and 7000 NM. A speed of 20 knots together with the previously assumed fuel prices was used in the calculation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1475090212441444">Figure 9</xref> demonstrates that the suggested advanced marine gas turbine cycle (ACGT) is a viable option for distance below 4000 NM, which could achieve the highest saving in operating cost by 2% per round trip among other propulsion options; this is mainly due to the low specific weight of the gas turbine, which delivers more cargo capacity. For longer trade routes above 4000 NM, the slow speed diesel engine with reliquefaction (DERL) and dual fuel diesel engine (DFDE) options are more beneficial; the cost saving per round trip is increased by 2%–2.5% respectively compared to benchmark ship.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Influence of changing navigational range on operating cost saving compared to the benchmark ship.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1475090212441444">
<title>Sensitivity to HFO price</title>
<p>To consider the future increase in fuel prices, the status and outlook of the global liquid fuel and natural gas market during last years is reviewed from 2000 to 2005. It could be concluded that the average price of HFO and MDO are increasing in linear fashion with LNG price by about 20% per year. Also the LNGFOB is increasing by 50% of LNGCIF price.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1475090212441444">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1475090212441444">20</xref></sup> The relevant saving of operating cost in percentage due to expected increase in fuel prices compared to the benchmark ship is demonstrated as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1475090212441444">Figure 10</xref>. At the current HFO and LNG prices (HFO/LNG = 1.2) it could be seen the importance of the re-liquefaction plant represented by DERL option. For (HFO/LNG=1.3-1.7) the maximum saving is achieved by DFDE. This of course shows why the order book is shifting from conventional steam propulsion, to be powered by DFDE as for the new seven LNG carriers ordered by Gaz de France. For HFO/LNG price above 1.7, which is expected in near the future, using NG as a bunker fuel with the suggested advanced marine gas turbine cycle (ACGT), provides the maximum cost saving, reaching 2.8% per round trip compared to the benchmark ship and this percentage is directly proportional with HFO/LNG ratio. From the previous analysis, it could be concluded that the application of using NG as a bunker fuel together with the suggested advanced gas turbine cycle could be one of the feasible solution as propulsion option for LNG carriers.</p>
<fig id="fig10-1475090212441444" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Influence of changing HFO price on operating cost saving compared to the benchmark ship.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1475090212441444-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1475090212441444" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This paper discuses the applicability and the economical benefits of using natural gas as a fuel with marine gas turbine electric propulsion as a propulsion option for LNG carriers. A specially designed spreadsheet model revealed a significant reduction in operating cost by 2% for a trading distance below 4000 NM, compared to conventional steam propulsion, which dominated in LNG carriers for decades. While, above 4000 NM the slow speed diesel with reliquefaction plant and dual fuel diesel engine become more beneficial. With the expected increase in fuel prices, and at HFO/LNGcif =1.7, the suggested gas turbine cycle also achieves the highest cost saving reaching 2.8% per round trip. This saving is directly proportional with the increasing of the fuel prices compared to other options.</p>
<p>Also, the study showed that there are some obstacles facing the spread of natural gas use onboard ships such as the cost of converting existing engines and the ports infrastructure for refueling with natural gas. This means further development is required to make gas fuelled ship commercially feasible. This needs help from the involved parties such as governments, manufacture and owners to push the shifting process forward.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not for profit sectors</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1475090212441444">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cherng–Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Compliance with international emissions regulations: Reducing the air pollution from merchant vessels</article-title>. <source>J Marine Policy</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1475090212441444">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<article-title>Per Mange Einang M. MARINTEK, Norway, gas fuelled ships</article-title>. In: <conf-name>25th CIMAC conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Vienna</conf-loc>, <year>2007</year>, pp.<fpage>261</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1475090212441444">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>The European Environmental Bureau, Air pollution from ships</article-title>, Technical report, Sweden, <year>2004</year>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.flad.pt/documentos/tos/1227109470H7mFL7ge1Kr88CN8.pdf">http://www.flad.pt/documentos/tos/1227109470H7mFL7ge1Kr88CN8.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1475090212441444">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<collab>IFC consulting group</collab>, <article-title>In–Use Marine Diesel Fuels, Technical report prepared for Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), USA</article-title>, <year>1999</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1475090212441444">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Stationary Source Division</collab>. <article-title>Risk reduction plan to reduce particulate emissions from diesel-fueled engines and vehicles, Technical report, prepared for California Air Resources Board, CA, USA</article-title>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1475090212441444">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Bunkerworld</collab>. <article-title>Futures prices, today’s futures prices</article-title>, <year>2009</year>, available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bunkerworld.com/prices/">http://www.bunkerworld.com/prices/</ext-link> [note that current prices differ] (<access-date>accessed 5 May 2009</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1475090212441444">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Transportation of clean energy at Sea-Mitsubishi LNG carrier, at present and in future</article-title>. <source>Mitsubishi Heavy Industries Ltd, Technical Review</source>, <year>2003</year>, <volume>40</volume>(<month>February</month>): pp.<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1475090212441444">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Javanmardi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility of transporting LNG from South-Pars gas field to potential markets</article-title>. <source>Applied Thermal Engineering</source>, <year>2006</year>; <fpage>1812</fpage>–<lpage>1819</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1475090212441444">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kazuaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katsuya</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Junshiro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Key technologies of Mitsubishi LNG carriers – Present and future</article-title>. <source>Mitsubishi Heavy Industries Ltd, Technical review</source>, <year>2001</year>; pp.<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1475090212441444">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Küver</surname></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of propulsion options for LNG carriers</article-title>. In: <source>GASTECH</source>, <publisher-loc>Germany</publisher-loc>, <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1475090212441444">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kivela</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nurmi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Machinary selection from an operator’s point of view: alternatives to steam turbine on an LNG carrier</article-title>. In: <source>Ship propulsion systems</source>, <publisher-loc>Hamburg, Germany</publisher-loc>, <year>2001</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1475090212441444">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Future development options for LNG marine transportation</article-title>. In: <conf-name>American Institute of Chemical Engineering spring national meeting</conf-name>, <conf-loc>New Orleans, LA, USA</conf-loc>, <conf-date>January</conf-date> <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1475090212441444">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaughan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Economics, environment driving new generation of LNG carriers</article-title>. <source>LNG Observer</source>, <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1475090212441444">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Masaru</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazuyoshi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development of next generation LNGC propulsion plant and HYPRID system</article-title>. <source>Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Technical Review</source>, <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1475090212441444">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaughan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prime mover rivals are ready</article-title>. In: <source>LNG World shipping</source>, <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1475090212441444">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woodyard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Pounder’s marine diesel engines and gas turbines</source>, <edition>8th edn.</edition> <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher-loc>, <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1475090212441444">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mattingly</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Elements of gas turbine propulsion</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.). <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>, <year>1996</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1475090212441444">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diesel and gas turbine worldwide catalog</article-title>. <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookfield</publisher-name>, <year>1992</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1475090212441444">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy</collab>. <article-title>The global liquefied natural gas market: status &amp; outlook</article-title>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>, <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1475090212441444">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Banawan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>El Gohary</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sadek</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Environmental and economical benefits of changing from marine diesel oil to natural-gas fuel for short-voyage high-power passenger ships</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part M: J Engineering for the Maritime Environment</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>224</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>