<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjrp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Reinforced Plastics and Composites</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0731-6844</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-7964</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0731684413485826</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0731684413485826</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mechanical properties and water absorption of snake grass longitudinal fiber reinforced isophthalic polyester composites</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Sathishkumar</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684413485826">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0731684413485826"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Navaneethakrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684413485826">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0731684413485826">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rajasekar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0731684413485826">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0731684413485826"><label>1</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, Kongu Engineering College, Erode, Tamil Nadu, India</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0731684413485826"><label>2</label>Department of Mechatronics Engineering, Kongu Engineering College, Erode, Tamil Nadu, India</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0731684413485826">TP Sathishkumar, Department of Mechanical Engineering, Kongu Engineering College, Kongu College Rd, Kumaran Nagar, Erode 638052, Tamil Nadu, India. Email: <email>tpsathish@kongu.ac.in</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>16</issue>
<fpage>1211</fpage>
<lpage>1223</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Natural fiber reinforced composites have replaced the existing conventional materials due to its light weight and enhanced load-bearing capabilities. In the present work, the newly identified snake grass (<italic>Sansevieria ehrenbergii</italic>) fiber-reinforced isophthalic polyester composites are prepared by simple hand lay-up method with different fiber weight fractions. The mechanical properties like tensile strength, flexural strength and modulus are analyzed for the longitudinal and transverse direction according to the prescribed standards. The obtained tensile strength and modulus are compared with the theoretically predicted values. The impact strength and energy absorption of the composites are analyzed and compared with control. The water uptake of pure and fiber incorporated resin under varying time period and climatic conditions are examined. The experimental results proves that the composites containing high fiber weight content contribute to remarkable increase in mechanical properties and water absorption capabilities compared to control.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Mechanical characterization</kwd>
<kwd>natural fibers</kwd>
<kwd>composites</kwd>
<kwd>water absorption</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0731684413485826" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Environmental awareness around the world focuses on the effective usage of the natural fiber reinforced polyester composites for commercial applications. In last two decades, the usage of natural cellulous fibers such as hemp, jute, ramie, sisal, flax, kenaf, cotton, coir, abaca, pineapple, banana, flax, etc., are increased for several applications. Many unknown natural fibers possess good mechanical properties compared to existing fibers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0731684413485826">1</xref></sup> The mechanical properties and fiber pullout of randomly oriented snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684413485826">2</xref></sup> and combination of snake grass, coir and banana fibers reinforced hybrid polyester composites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0731684413485826">3</xref></sup> were increased with different volume fractions. The chemically treated longitudinal fiber reinforced polyester composites have higher tensile strength than the raw fiber composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0731684413485826">4</xref></sup> The mechanical properties of the prepared sisal, jute and coir fiber reinforced polyester/epoxy composites were studied and recommended for usage in household appliances.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0731684413485826">5</xref></sup> Polyester composites had been developed using green husk coir fiber with different length and content. The results showed that fiber content had major role on the mechanical properties than fiber length.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0731684413485826">6</xref></sup> The tensile strength of the random and longitudinal oriented sisal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0731684413485826">7</xref></sup> and jute fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684413485826">8</xref></sup> based polyester composites were compared with various volume fractions. The maximum tensile strength was achieved for longitudinally oriented fiber composite. Hemp fiber polyester composites were prepared using resin transfer molding technique. The composites showed remarkable improvement in flexural and impact properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0731684413485826">9</xref></sup> Treated fique fiber was found to have strong interfacial bonding with polyester resin, which indeed resulted in high static and dynamic mechanical properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0731684413485826">10</xref></sup> The interlaminar shear strength of jute fiber was improved by chemical treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0731684413485826">11</xref></sup> The physical and mechanical properties of sisal fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0731684413485826">12</xref></sup> and banana fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0731684413485826">13</xref></sup> reinforced thermoset and plastic composites were compared with the theoretical models.</p>
<p>The water and chemical solvent was used as absorption medium to examine the mechanical properties of coir fiber polyester composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0731684413485826">14</xref></sup> The water absorption of polyester–sisal fiber composites prepared using different surface modifiers was analyzed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref></sup> Kinetics of water absorption in hemp fiber,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0731684413485826">16</xref></sup> woven banana fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref></sup> polyester composites and lantana camara fiber epoxy composites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> were studied. The mechanical properties of roselle/sisal polyester hybrid composites were decreased after water absorption.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0731684413485826">19</xref></sup> The thermal and mechanical properties of random and quasi-unidirectional oriented phormium tenax fiber epoxy composites were studied. The maximum mechanical properties was found in unidirectional than random orientation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0731684413485826">20</xref></sup> The effect of fiber length and fiber content on the mechanical properties of banana fiber epoxy composites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0731684413485826">21</xref></sup> and <italic>Sansevieria cylindrica</italic> fiber polyester composites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0731684413485826">22</xref></sup> were examined. With regard to application aspects, different interior and exterior components of the automobiles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0731684413485826">23</xref></sup> can be replaced with the help of natural fiber reinforced composites.</p>
<p>Many research works had been carried out on natural fiber based polymer composites, but the studies on the development of snake grass fiber based composite constitutes in lesser dimension. The main objective of this article is to prepare the longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites (LSGC). Mechanical properties and water absorption of the prepared composites at different climatic conditions has been analyzed. In addition, the obtained experimental tensile strength and modulus are compared with theoretically predicted values.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0731684413485826" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<sec id="sec3-0731684413485826"><title>Snake grass fiber (<italic>S. ehrenbergii</italic> fiber) and resin</title>
<p>Snake grass fibers, which are abundantly available in Tamilnadu, southern part of the India, are extracted by the simple water retting process. Commercially available isophthalic unsaturated polyester resin, accelerator – methyl ethyl ketone peroxide (MEKP) and catalyst – cobalt naphthalene are used for the composite preparation. The distinctive properties of the isophthalic polyester resin and fiber are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0731684413485826">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0731684413485826">2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table1-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The distinctive properties of the isophthalic polyester resin.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>S. No</th>
<th>Properties</th>
<th>Unit</th>
<th>Range</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1.</td>
<td>Specific gravity</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>1.1–1.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.</td>
<td>Density</td>
<td>kg/m<sup>3</sup></td>
<td>1125</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3.</td>
<td>Tensile strength as per  ASTM standard</td>
<td>MPa</td>
<td>16–18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4.</td>
<td>Tensile modulus as per  ASTM standard</td>
<td>GPa</td>
<td>0.25–0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5.</td>
<td>Compressive strength</td>
<td>MPa</td>
<td>90–250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6.</td>
<td>Flexural strength as per  ASTM standard</td>
<td>MPa</td>
<td>30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7.</td>
<td>Flexural modulus as per  ASTM standard</td>
<td>GPa</td>
<td>1.1–1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8.</td>
<td>Shrinkage</td>
<td>%</td>
<td>0.004–0.008</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The physical and tensile properties of snake grass fiber.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Properties</th>
<th>Snake grass fiber</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Density (kg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td>
<td>887</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diameter (µm)</td>
<td>45–250</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tensile strength (MPa)</td>
<td>240–450</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tensile modulus (GPa)</td>
<td>6.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>%Elongation</td>
<td>2.87</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0731684413485826"><title>Composite preparation</title>
<p>The simple hand lay-up technique is adapted to prepare the composite specimen with various weight contents likes 10%, 20%, 30% and 40%, respectively. About 1% of catalyst and accelerators are used to cure the isophthalic polyester resin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684413485826">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0731684413485826">3</xref></sup> Steel dies are designed to prepare the composite specimens. Fiber orientation and uniformity in the composites is maintained by longitudinal fiber orientation attachment to achieve the unidirectional material property. The resin is poured over the fiber in female die and two rollers are used to entrap all the air bubbles. Then the closed mould is kept on the hydraulic press and the compressive pressure is applied for 4 h at atmospheric temperature. Finally the fibers are reinforced with the polyester resin within the mould cavity of dimensions 300 × 300 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>. The composite plate is then post-cured for 1 h in oven and the final shape of the composite plate is obtained. The longitudinal oriented snake grass fiber reinforced composites as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0731684413485826">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="fig1-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Longitudinal oriented snake grass fiber reinforced composites plate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0731684413485826" sec-type="methods"><title>Experimental procedure</title>
<sec id="sec6-0731684413485826"><title>Mechanical properties</title>
<p>Mechanical properties such as tensile, flexural and impact properties are measured based on the ASTM standards. The tensile properties are measured based on the ASTM D 638 standards<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0731684413485826">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> and the sample size is 165 × 12.7 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> The electronic tensometer setup is used to perform the tensile testing with a cross-head speed of 1 mm/min using the load cell of 5 kN. Three-point bending testing is used to measure the flexural properties as per ASTM D 790 standards. The sample size is 48 × 12.7 × 3 mm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0731684413485826">3</xref></sup> with the depth to width ratio of 16:1. In bending test, the load cell of 2 kN is used with the cross head speed of 2.5 mm/min. The impact properties are measured based on ASTM D-256.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0731684413485826">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684413485826">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref></sup> The sample size is 64 × 12.7 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>. Five specimens are used for testing and the average values of the properties are reported in this article.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0731684413485826"><title>Water absorption of composites</title>
<p>Water absorption tests are carried out with different time periods and different climatic conditions such as cold at 10℃, room temperature (25℃) and hot at 60℃.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref></sup> The specimens are prepared based on ASTM D570 standard. The sample size is 64 × 12.7 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0731684413485826">20</xref></sup> The specimens are taken periodically and a tissue paper is used to remove the surface water of the composites. The percentage of weight absorption is calculated at different time intervals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0731684413485826">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>The percentage weight gain of water absorption in the composites is calculated at different time interval by using the following equation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0731684413485826"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>W<sub>o</sub></italic> and <italic>W<sub>t</sub></italic> denotes the initial dry weight of the sample and weight of the sample after specific time (<italic>t</italic>) in water.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0731684413485826"><title>Scanning electron microscope</title>
<p>The fracture morphology of pure resin, untreated and treated SGFs composites are examined using scanning electron microscope (SEM, model: JEOL JSM-6390). The facture zones of the specimens are cut into dimension of 1 × 1 cm<sup>2</sup>. The fracture ends of the tensile and impact specimens of the composites are mounted on aluminium stubs in SEM machine for taking image.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0731684413485826" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec10-0731684413485826"><title>Effect of longitudinal tensile strength and modulus of the longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced composites</title>
<p>The tensile properties of the LSGC are measured for the various fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> and the resulting plots and SEM images are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684413485826">Figures 2</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684413485826">6</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0731684413485826">Figure 2</xref> shows the variation of longitudinal tensile strength versus tensile strain of LSGC. The stress increases linearly with respect to strain for all <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> cases. The increase in fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> shows increase in tensile strength and strain. In tensile strength, the percentage increase between the pure resin to 10%, 20%, 30%, 40% and 50%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> are 56.8%, 72.8%, 79.9%, 83.2% and 78.60%, respectively. However, very marginal increase in tensile strength has been observed for the fiber loading above 30%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The obtained tensile strength is found much higher as compared to the earlier reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0731684413485826">4</xref></sup> Similarly in tensile strain, the percentage increases between the pure resin to the corresponding <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> are 14.9%, 33.4%, 44%, 51.3% and 44%, respectively. The increase in <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> leads to more fiber accumulation in the composites. The breakage of composites in the beginning takes little more strain to failure due to less interaction between fiber and matrix at higher tensile load.
<fig id="fig2-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Longitudinal tensile stress versus strain of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Transverse tensile properties of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The maximum tensile strength and strain has been observed for the 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> fiber loaded composite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0731684413485826">Figure 3</xref>). Gradual increase in loading of fiber in the resin leads to gradual increase in tensile modulus. The percentage improvements in tensile modulus between the pure resin to the corresponding <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of composites are 49.3%, 59.2%, 64.7% and 65.6% respectively. The improvement in modulus is higher compared to earlier report.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0731684413485826">4</xref></sup> The tensile strength, modulus and elongation at break of the composites shows 6, 2.9 and 2 times higher compared to pure resin. Hence, it proves that addition of fiber in the resin significantly increases the tensile strength of the composite. But more fiber (50%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>) in the composites decreases the tensile properties. The SEM image of the tensile fracture specimen and pure resin are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0731684413485826">Figure 4</xref>. The fibers and fibers pull out is more in composites. The obtained results for the longitudinally oriented fiber reinforced polyester composites are compared with the polyester composites containing randomly oriented short fibers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684413485826">2</xref></sup> with same <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The percentage improvement between them is 118.4 and 97.1 for tensile strength and modulus. Hence the tensile properties of longitudinally oriented fiber reinforced polyester composites in longitudinal direction are higher than the randomly oriented short fiber composites.
<fig id="fig3-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Longitudinal tensile properties of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>The SEM image of tensile fractured specimen: (a) pure resin and (b) 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber.</p>
<p>SEM: scanning electron microscopy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Specific tensile strength and modulus of pure and fiber-filled resin are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0731684413485826">Figure 5</xref>. Specific tensile strength of LSGC increases linearly with increase in <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber. Highest tensile strength is found for the composites containing 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber. The percentage improvements in specific tensile strength between the pure resin and corresponding <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> are 57.4%, 75%, 82.4% and 85.9%, respectively. The specific tensile modulus also increases linearly with respect to <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of snake grass fiber for all composites. The percentage improvement between the resin and corresponding <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> are 54.6%, 64.9%, 70.9% and 72.7%, respectively.
<fig id="fig5-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Longitudinal specific tensile modulus and strength versus volume fraction of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0731684413485826"><title>Effect of transverse tensile strength and modulus of the LSGC</title>
<p>The transverse tensile strength of LSGC is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0731684413485826">Figure 6</xref>. Increasing the fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> decreases the tensile strength of the composite. Resin containing 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> fiber shows 10.2% decrease in tensile strength compared to pure resin and 6.3 times lesser than the value obtained for longitudinal direction. Also increasing the fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> (50%) in composites leads to decrease the strength and modulus. The percentage improvement of transverse tensile modulus between the pure resin to 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> is 24.1% and it is 2.2 times less than the longitudinal tensile strength of composites. Increase in fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> shows gradual increase in tensile modulus. The obtained transverse tensile strength of unidirectional fiber composite is 7 to 8 times lesser than the tensile strength of longitudinal direction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0731684413485826">8</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0731684413485826"><title>Comparison of experimental and theoretically predicted tensile strength</title>
<p>The experimental and theoretical value of longitudinal and transverse tensile strength of LSGC is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684413485826">Figures 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684413485826">8</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0731684413485826">Figure 7</xref> shows the composite strength versus volume fraction (<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic>) of the longitudinal fiber composites. The theoretically predicted tensile strength is higher than the experimental values of unidirectional oriented fiber composite. The percentage difference between the theoretical and experimental tensile strength of longitudinally oriented fiber composites are 20.5% for 13.5%<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic>, 27.3% for 27%<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic>, 25.9% at 40%<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic> and 27.9% at 51%<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic>, respectively. The obtained result shows high deviation between the experimental and theoretical values. High fiber loading in resin leads to less adhesion between the fiber and matrix. Hence, fiber pullout is more for composites containing high fiber content. The obtained transverse tensile strength of LSGC also reveals similar results. The theoretical transverse tensile strength is less than the experimental values for all fiber <italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic>. The theoretical values are obtained by using the rule of mixture of longitudinal fiber composite.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0731684413485826">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0731684413485826">24</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig7-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Composite strength versus volume fraction (<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic>) of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig8-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Composite modulus versus volume fraction of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Longitudinal mixture
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0731684413485826"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>LC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0731684413485826"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>LC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Transverse mixture
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0731684413485826"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math4-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>TC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0731684413485826"><label>(5)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math5-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>TC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>σ<sub>LC</sub></italic>, <italic>σ<sub>TC</sub></italic>, <italic>σ<sub>f</sub></italic> and <italic>σ<sub>m</sub></italic> are strength of composite, fiber and matrix expressed in MPa, <italic>E<sub>LC</sub></italic>, <italic>E<sub>TC</sub></italic><sub>,</sub> <italic>E<sub>f</sub></italic> and <italic>E<sub>m</sub></italic> are Young’s modulus of composite, fiber and matrix expressed in GPa, <italic>V<sub>C</sub></italic>, <italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic> and <italic>V<sub>m</sub></italic> are volume fraction of the composite, fiber and matrix, respectively. <italic>T</italic> and C are transverse and longitudinal fiber composite, respectively.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0731684413485826">Figure 8</xref> shows the experimental and theoretical Young’s modulus values for the unidirectional fiber reinforced composites. The experimental Young’s modulus tested in longitudinal direction is less compared to theoretical modulus and higher than transverse modulus of the composite. The result shows that the experimental Young’s modulus lie in between the theoretical Young’s modulus of matrix and fiber. Theoretically calculated longitudinal Young’s modulus at 40% <italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic> is 48.6% higher and transverse Young’s modulus at 40%<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic> is 13.7% higher than the experimental values. The fiber accumulation increases the fiber matrix delamination very quickly in the composite testing. The experimental value is studied up to 51%<italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic> because if the <italic>V<sub>f</sub></italic> increases more than a critical value the thickness of the composite also increases and the matrix dispersion is not uniform during composite preparation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0731684413485826"><title>Effect of impact strength of the LSGC</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0731684413485826">Figure 9</xref> shows the impact strength of LSGC. The impact resistance increases linearly with increasing fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The percentage improvement between the resin to the <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber-filled composites are 47.2%, 60.8%, 68.7%, 72.9% and 66.5%, respectively. The maximum improvement is achieved for the 40% <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> fiber loaded composites, which is 3.7 times greater than the pure resin. The percentage improvements between the <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber loaded composites are 29.7%, 21.4%, 13.2% and −23.26%, respectively. It is found that the percentage improvement decreases with increase in <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber.
<fig id="fig9-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Impact resistance and energy versus fiber weight fraction of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The impact energy increases linearly with increasing <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber. The percentage improvement between the pure resin to <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> are 44.4%, 60.9%, 68.9%, 73% and 57.3%, respectively. The impact energy of composite in 40% <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of snake grass fiber content is 3.7 times higher than pure resin. So the maximum improvement between the pure resin to 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> is 73%. The impact resistance and energy is increased with fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The impact load is evenly distributed in unidirectional fiber composites. The higher fiber content leads to more crack path and absorb more energy. Hence the composites can sustain maximum dynamic load due to the maximum fiber content present (40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>) in the composites. If the fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> is more than 40%, it decreases the impact properties. The SEM image of impact fractured specimen of the pure resin and fiber containing composites are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0731684413485826">Figure 10</xref>. The fiber and fiber pull out is more in the fracture zone of the specimen.
<fig id="fig10-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>The SEM image of impact fractured specimen: (a) pure resin and (b) 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber.</p>
<p>SEM: scanning electron microscopy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig10.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0731684413485826"><title>Effect of flexural strength of LSGC</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0731684413485826">Figures 11</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0731684413485826">12</xref> show the longitudinal flexural strength and modulus of LSGC. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0731684413485826">Figure 11</xref> shows the flexural strength versus strain for the LSGC and it is almost increases with increase in strain. It is absorbed that the flexural strength gradually increases with increase in fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of the composites. The percentage improvement between the resin and <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber containing composites are 22.2%, 61.8%, 80.5%, 82.5% and 77.56%, respectively. The flexural load increases with increase in <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> and the maximum load of 200 N is obtained at 40% <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>, which is 5.7 times greater than the pure resin. The flexural strain increases with increment in weight fraction of fiber. Maximum strain rate of 5.6% is obtained at 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The improvement in strain rate between the pure resin to 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> is 37.7%. The flexural strength does not show much improvement for fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> beyond 30%. This may be due to less quantity of matrix isolated in the composite. The maximum flexural strength and strain is obtained at 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> fiber containing composite and it is 5.7 times greater than the pure resin.
<fig id="fig11-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Flexural strength versus strain of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig11.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig12-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Longitudinal flexural properties of LSGC.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig12.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0731684413485826">Figure 12</xref>, the flexural modulus increases linearly with increasing fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The percentage improvement of modulus between the resin and <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber containing composites are 25.8%, 57.1%, 70%, 82.5% and 65.6%, respectively. The maximum flexural modulus is obtained for 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>, which is 3.6 times greater than the pure resin. It is clear that the less adhesion between the fibers and polyester is the reason for more strain to failure and maximum fiber pullout. Also the flexural properties of the longitudinally oriented fiber reinforced polyester composites in longitudinal direction are higher than the randomly oriented short fiber composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0731684413485826">2</xref></sup> The percentage improvement between them is 15.75 and 32.43 for flexural strength and modulus, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0731684413485826"><title>Effect of water absorption of the LSGC</title>
<p>The trends of moisture absorption for 10%, 20%, 30% and 40% <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of LSGC under different environmental conditions are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0731684413485826">Figure 13</xref>. The average values of three specimens are considered to plot the curve for all the composites. The maximum water absorption takes place at higher fiber loading composites. For all the three environmental conditions, the maximum water absorption is obtained at 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. However, the initial rate of water absorption is found higher at hot condition (60℃) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0731684413485826">Figure 13(c)</xref>). The acceleration of water uptake of LSGC is based on four factors such as hydrophilicity of fiber cellulous, lumen, microcracks in fiber and adhesion between fiber and matrix. The <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber in the composites is responsible for increase in the number of free OH groups. It comes into contact with the moisture and forms hydrogen bonding which results in more swelling. It can be clearly seen that the water absorption normally increases with immersion time. The weight of the composite is not found to increase more than a certain value beyond the saturation point. The acceleration of diffusion of water molecules into the composite is purely time and temperature dependent. Elevated temperature increases the activation of diffusion due to formation of microcracks or voids in the composites, which in turn weakens the adhesion between the fiber and matrix. In these three conditions, the time taken for reaching the saturation point of water absorption is not equal. The saturation time is approximately 80 h, 60 h, 40 h under cold, normal and hot water absorptions. The maximum water absorption for 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> is 14.2%, 20.9%, 34.2% under cold, normal and hot water, respectively. The percentage of water observed for all composites is listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684413485826">Table 3</xref>. The percentage absorption of water for the fiber-filled composites enhances with increasing <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. Composites containing fibers of 20%, 30%, 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> shows 119.8%, 256%, 412% (cold water) 128.6%, 261.8%, 429.4% (normal water) and 180.7%, 401.3%, 632.7% (hot water) increase in water uptake compared to 10%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber-filled composites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0731684413485826">Figure 13</xref>). From the experimental results, it proves that rate of water absorption increases with temperature and time.
<fig id="fig13-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>Water absorption versus square root of time period of LSGC at different conditions.</p>
<p>LSGC: longitudinal snake grass fiber reinforced polyester composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-fig13.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table3-0731684413485826" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>The water absorption properties of LSGC in different environmental conditions.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Environment</th>
<th rowspan="2">Fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> (%)</th>
<th rowspan="2"><italic>M</italic> (%)</th>
<th colspan="2">Kinetics of water absorption</th>
<th colspan="3">Transports coefficients</th>
</tr>
<tr><th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th><italic>k</italic></th>
<th>Diffusion coefficient  × 10<sup>−10</sup> (<italic>D</italic>) (m<sup>2</sup>/min)</th>
<th>Sorption coefficient (<italic>S</italic>) (g/g)</th>
<th>Permeability coefficient <italic>P</italic>) (m<sup>2</sup>/min)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Cold water at 10℃</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>0.50310</td>
<td>0.15338</td>
<td>1.9778</td>
<td>0.027778</td>
<td>5.4939 × 10<sup>−12</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>6.11</td>
<td>0.43030</td>
<td>0.20189</td>
<td>3.5087</td>
<td>0.061111</td>
<td>2.1442 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30</td>
<td>9.92</td>
<td>0.42705</td>
<td>0.18300</td>
<td>5.0359</td>
<td>0.099237</td>
<td>4.9975 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40</td>
<td>14.24</td>
<td>0.34125</td>
<td>0.25910</td>
<td>5.9202</td>
<td>0.142433</td>
<td>8.4323 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Normal water at atmospheric</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>3.95</td>
<td>0.66851</td>
<td>0.11190</td>
<td>2.5365</td>
<td>0.041121</td>
<td>1.0430 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>9.03</td>
<td>0.45222</td>
<td>0.16588</td>
<td>3.3654</td>
<td>0.099236</td>
<td>3.3397 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30</td>
<td>14.29</td>
<td>0.38153</td>
<td>0.22458</td>
<td>5.4453</td>
<td>0.166666</td>
<td>9.0754 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40</td>
<td>20.91</td>
<td>0.45780</td>
<td>0.18279</td>
<td>7.8753</td>
<td>0.264406</td>
<td>2.0822 × 10<sup>−10</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Hot water at 60℃</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>4.67</td>
<td>0.68561</td>
<td>0.11206</td>
<td>2.6050</td>
<td>0.046729</td>
<td>1.2173 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>13.11</td>
<td>0.56884</td>
<td>0.14434</td>
<td>5.0543</td>
<td>0.130769</td>
<td>6.6094 × 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30</td>
<td>23.41</td>
<td>0.54562</td>
<td>0.16255</td>
<td>8.3768</td>
<td>0.233766</td>
<td>1.9582 × 10<sup>−10</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40</td>
<td>34.22</td>
<td>0.29920</td>
<td>0.32315</td>
<td>0.1248</td>
<td>0.341935</td>
<td>4.2690 × 10<sup>−10</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<sec id="sec16-0731684413485826"><title>Kinetics of water absorption</title>
<p>The kinetics and diffusion mechanism of water absorptions are obtained based on curve fitting using the experimental values and Fickans theory.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref></sup> The values of <italic>n</italic> and <italic>k</italic> are essential factors which are analyzed from the following equation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0731684413485826"><label>(6)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math6-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0731684413485826">equation (6)</xref>, <italic>k</italic> and <italic>n</italic> are constant and explains the mechanism of diffusion which takes place inside the natural fiber reinforced polyester composite. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684413485826">Table 3</xref>, the value of <italic>k</italic> and <italic>n</italic> constants explains the mechanism of diffusion that takes place inside the natural fiber reinforced polyester composites. The <italic>k</italic> denotes the interaction between the polymer and water, <italic>n</italic> denotes the mode of diffusion take place in the composites. The value of <italic>n</italic> should lie in between 0 and 1. If the value of <italic>n</italic> = 0.5, the diffusion is Fickian, from 0.5 ∼ 1, the diffusion is non-Fickian and <italic>n</italic> &gt; 1, the diffusion is said to be anomalous.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> The values of <italic>n</italic> and <italic>k</italic> for water sorption for the LSGC are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684413485826">Table 3</xref>. The low and high value of <italic>n</italic> clearly shows that the mechanism of transport deviates from the Fickian. The fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> increases with decrease in <italic>n</italic> values. It is also clear that the <italic>n</italic> value deviates from the Fickian, which results in more diffusion of water absorption further improving molecular motion in the composites. The percentage of water absorption is increased at higher temperatures and it can be attributed to the relaxation mechanism in the polymer for distorting the polymer network.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> Also <italic>k</italic> values increases the water–polymer interaction in the composites.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-0731684413485826"><title>Transport coefficients in water absorption</title>
<p>The transport coefficients are determined for all environmental conditions. The diffusion coefficient (<italic>D</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> is the most important parameter of Fickian model, which explains the penetration of water molecules inside the composite. ‘<italic>D</italic>’ can be obtained by values measured from the curve of moisture absorption in percentage (<italic>M</italic>) with square root of time taken. In this the initial linear portion of the curve fit is consistent with Boltzman’s solution.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref></sup> The following equation is used to determine the <italic>D</italic> value.
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0731684413485826"><label>(7)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math7-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>tD</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>M<sub>m</sub></italic> is the equilibrium absorption of moisture content in the sample, <italic>M<sub>t</sub></italic> is the moisture content at a specified time <italic>t</italic>, <italic>D<sub>x</sub></italic> is the moisture diffusion coefficient and <italic>h</italic> is the sample thickness. The ability of water molecules to imprecate among the polymer segments is determined by the diffusion coefficient. Finally, the diffusion coefficient can be calculated from the following equation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0731684413485826">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0731684413485826">20</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0731684413485826"><label>(8)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math8-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub> are selected square root of time taken for water absorption of points in the initial linear portion, <italic>M</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>M</italic><sub>1</sub> is the respective percentage of moisture content at time <italic>t</italic><sub>1,2</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref></sup> The fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> increases the diffusion coefficient (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684413485826">Table 3</xref>). The diffusion coefficient for the hot water absorption is found to be higher compared to cold and normal water absorption. The higher fiber loading of LSGC can have higher cellulous content which leads to greater diffusivity. The hot water can quickly diffuse inside the composites, where it entraps inside fiber cellulose and polymer chains. Hence, it results in more diffusivity values. The permeability of small water molecules into the polymer is dependent on diffusion and sorption or solubility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0731684413485826">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0731684413485826">18</xref></sup> of the liquid in the polymer.</p>
<p>The sorption coefficients can be calculated by the following equation.
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0731684413485826"><label>(9)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math9-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula9-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>S</italic> is the sorption coefficient, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> is the mass of the water molecules taken up at equilibrium swelling and <italic>M<sub>p</sub></italic> is the initial mass of the polymer sample.</p>
<p>The value of sorption coefficient (<italic>S</italic>) of the LSGC is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684413485826">Table 3</xref>. The increase in fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> increases the value of <italic>S</italic> i.e. the water molecules absorbed in the composites are more. The permeability (<italic>P</italic>) is the product of sorption and diffusion coefficient.</p>
<p>The permeability of the polymer composite to water absorption can be expressed by the following equation.
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0731684413485826"><label>(10)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math10-0731684413485826"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula10-0731684413485826" xlink:href="10.1177_0731684413485826-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0731684413485826">Table 3</xref> gives the values of permeability coefficient of fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of the composites. The increase in permeability leads to less fiber–matrix interaction and also the presence of more fiber content in the composites.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-0731684413485826" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The LSGC is prepared with various fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The mechanical properties and water uptake under different environmental conditions are analyzed. The following conclusions are obtained from the experimental and theoretical observations.
<list id="list1-0731684413485826" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The tensile strength and modulus of the LSGC improves with gradual increase in fiber weight fractions of the composites. The maximum values are achieved for composites containing 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber. The composites are subjected to longitudinal and transverse modes of testing. The results show that the longitudinal tensile strength and modulus are comparatively higher than the transverse values of LSGC. Theoretically predicted tensile strength and modulus of LSGC are higher than the obtained experimental values. Also the mechanical properties of the longitudinally oriented fiber reinforced polyester composites are higher than the randomly oriented short fiber composites.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The flexural strength and modulus of LSGC increases with increase in <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> of fiber. Composites containing 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> fiber shows maximum flexural strength and modulus. The strain rate has been found higher for more fiber containing composites.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The impact load is applied on the composite specimens perpendicular to the fiber direction, which absorbs more impact energy. The impact resistance and energy gradually increases with increase in fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>. The maximum properties are obtained at 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In water absorption, the percentage of moisture absorption, mode of diffusion, sorption and permeability coefficients increases with gradual increase in fiber <italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> the composites and immersion time. From the extensive analysis results, it shows that hot water absorption is predominantly higher than the other two. Hence, the optimum weight fraction of LSGC is achieved for 40%<italic>W<sub>f</sub></italic> fiber containing composites.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec19-0731684413485826"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec20-0731684413485826"><title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0731684413485826"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satyanarayana</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukumaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Natural fiber –polymer composite</article-title>. <source>Cem Compos</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0731684413485826"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sathishkumar</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Navaneethakrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tensile and flexural properties of snake grass natural fiber reinforced isophthallic polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1183</fpage>–<lpage>1190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0731684413485826"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Sathishkumar TP, Navaneethakrishnan P, Shankar S, et al. Mechanical properties of randomly oriented snake grass fiber with banana and coir fiber reinforced hybrid composites. <italic>J Compos Mater</italic> 2012. DOI: 10.1177/0021998312454903</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0731684413485826"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murali Mohan Rao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratna Prasad</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranga Babu</surname><given-names>MNV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tensile properties of elephant grass fiber reinforced polyester composite</article-title>. <source>J Mater Sci</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>2666</fpage>–<lpage>2672</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0731684413485826"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Composite materials from local resources</article-title>. <source>Constr Build Mater</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>470</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0731684413485826"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jayabal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of fiber parameters on tensile, flexural, and impact properties of nonwoven coir–polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Adv Manuf Technol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>2969</fpage>–<lpage>2977</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0731684413485826"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuruvilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Romildo</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Beena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A review on sisal fiber reinforced polymer composites</article-title>. <source>Revista Brasileira de Engenharia Agricola e Ambiental</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0731684413485826"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laranjeira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>JRM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>LHDE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of fiber orientation on the mechanical properties of polyester/jute composites</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1269</fpage>–<lpage>1278</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0731684413485826"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Callum</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>RTM hemp fibre-reinforced polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Appl Compos Mater</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0731684413485826"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondragon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fique fibre-reinforced polyester composites: effects of fibre surface treatments on mechanical behavior</article-title>. <source>J Mater Sci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>3121</fpage>–<lpage>3128</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0731684413485826"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutlay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehmet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoldas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The mechanical properties of c-methacryloxypropyltrimethoxy silane-treated jute/polyester composites</article-title>. <source>J Compos Mater</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1912</fpage>–<lpage>1924</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0731684413485826"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yiu</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sisal fibre and its composites: a review of recent developments</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>2037</fpage>–<lpage>2055</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0731684413485826"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkateshwaran</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Elayaperumal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Banana fiber reinforced polymer composites - a review</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>2387</fpage>–<lpage>2396</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0731684413485826"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sindhu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuruvilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Degradation studies of coir fiber/polyester and glass fiber/polyester composites under different conditions</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1571</fpage>–<lpage>1585</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0731684413485826"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sreekumar</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvin</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jean Marc</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of fiber surface modification on the mechanical and water absorption characteristics of sisal/polyester composites fabricated by resin transfer molding</article-title>. <source>Composites: Part A</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1777</fpage>–<lpage>1784</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0731684413485826"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhakal</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>MOW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of water absorption on the mechanical properties of hemp fibre reinforced unsaturated polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>1674</fpage>–<lpage>1683</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0731684413485826"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jannah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariatti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu Bakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of chemical surface modifications on the properties of woven banana-reinforced unsaturated polyester composites</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1519</fpage>–<lpage>1532</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0731684413485826"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chittaranjan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of moisture absorption on mechanical properties of chopped natural fiber reinforced epoxy composite</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>2513</fpage>–<lpage>2521</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0731684413485826"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Athijayaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruchitrambalam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of moisture absorption on the mechanical properties of randomly oriented natural fibers/polyester hybrid composite</article-title>. <source>Mater Sci Eng</source> <year>200</year>; <volume>517</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0731684413485826"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igor</surname><given-names>MDR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabrizio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanical and thermal characterization of epoxy composites reinforced with random and quasi-unidirectional untreated Phormium tenax leaf fibers</article-title>. <source>Mater Des</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>2397</fpage>–<lpage>2405</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0731684413485826"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkateshwaran</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Elayaperumal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagatheeshwaran</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of fiber length and fiber content on mechanical properties of banana fiber/epoxy composite</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1621</fpage>–<lpage>1627</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0731684413485826"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sreenivasan</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanical properties of randomly oriented short sansevieria cylindrica fibre/polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Mater Des</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>2444</fpage>–<lpage>2455</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0731684413485826"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sergio</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Felipe</surname><given-names>PDL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ailton</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Natural-fiber polymer-matrix composites: cheaper, tougher, and environmentally friendly</article-title>. <source>J Compos Mater</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0731684413485826"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Greszczuk LB. Theoretical and experimental studies on properties and behavior of filamentary composites. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 21th annual meeting of SPI, Section 8-A</italic>, vol. 2, 10 February 1966. Douglas Missile &amp; Space Systems Division, Douglas Aircraft Co., Inc</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>