<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppih</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part H: Journal of Engineering in Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4119</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-6518</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954411912444213</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954411912444213</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging-compatible tactile sensing device based on a piezoelectric array</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>Abbi</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954411912444213">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Masamune</surname><given-names>Ken</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0954411912444213">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>Zion Tsz Ho</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0954411912444213">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lamperth</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954411912444213">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dohi</surname><given-names>Takeyoshi</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0954411912444213">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954411912444213"><label>1</label>Mechatronics in Medicine Laboratory, Imperial College London, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0954411912444213"><label>2</label>Department of Mechano-Informatics, Graduate School of Information Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0954411912444213"><label>3</label>Faculty of Engineering, The University of Georgia, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954411912444213">Abbi Hamed, Department of Advanced Robotics, Chiba Institute of Technology, 2-17-1 Tsudanuma, Narashino, Chiba, 275-0016, Japan. Email: <email>a.hamed@imperial.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>565</fpage>
<lpage>575</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>28</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>12</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Minimally invasive surgery is a widely used medical technique, one of the drawbacks of which is the loss of direct sense of touch during the operation. Palpation is the use of fingertips to explore and make fast assessments of tissue morphology. Although technologies are developed to equip minimally invasive surgery tools with haptic feedback capabilities, the majority focus on tissue stiffness profiling and tool–tissue interaction force measurement. For greatly increased diagnostic capability, a magnetic resonance imaging-compatible tactile sensor design is proposed, which allows minimally invasive surgery to be performed under image guidance, combining the strong capability of magnetic resonance imaging soft tissue and intuitive palpation. The sensing unit is based on a piezoelectric sensor methodology, which conforms to the stringent mechanical and electrical design requirements imposed by the magnetic resonance environment. The sensor mechanical design and the device integration to a 0.2 Tesla open magnetic resonance imaging scanner are described, together with the device’s magnetic resonance compatibility testing. Its design limitations and potential future improvements are also discussed. A tactile sensing unit based on a piezoelectric sensor principle is proposed, which is designed for magnetic resonance imaging guided interventions.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Tactile sensing</kwd>
<kwd>piezoelectric</kwd>
<kwd>magnetic resonance compatibility</kwd>
<kwd>minimally invasive surgery</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0954411912444213">
<title>Tactile sensing in minimally invasive surgery</title>
<p>Minimally invasive surgery (MIS) has obtained increasing popularity, primarily because of the clear advantages to patient well-being, and the scope of MIS principles has grown to include a wide range of diagnostic and surgical procedures, which can be combined with medical imaging techniques, such as computed tomography (CT), ultrasound (US) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954411912444213">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954411912444213">2</xref></sup> The unique drawbacks associated with MIS are diminished visual feedback and loss of depth perception, complicated manual manipulation of instruments and almost complete loss of haptic information.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954411912444213">3</xref></sup> Palpation is a direct and intuitive modality used by clinicians in the assessment of tool–tissue interaction forces, the localisation of subsurface anatomical features and the rapid assessment of approximate tissue morphology and condition through perception of compliance, texture, pressure distribution and shape. It has been shown that the loss of haptic feedback can negatively affect a clinician’s ability to perform tool manipulations, such as grasping and suturing, targeting of hidden subsurface structures and estimation of tissue compliance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954411912444213">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Haptic perception is comprised both of the kinaesthetic and tactile senses, which are derived from receptors in the muscles and joints, and the skin, respectively. The distributed nature allows determination of characteristics, such as hardness, mass distribution, texture, temperature and shape of objects in contact. Many receptive fields in the skin overlap and no two points in the skin contain the same pattern of nerve fibres. Although touch perception is subjective, it can provide an immediate binary assessment of tissue stiffness changes;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954411912444213">5</xref></sup> the loss of this ability is a major drawback in MIS.</p>
<p>As a consequence, the research and development of medical tools providing haptic feedback has been ongoing for around 20 years. Two general mechanical design principles have been found reported in literature. The first type takes the form of sensorised stiff-bodied laparascopic grasping tools or forceps. Some of these tools are simply equipped with force sensors mounted either at the jaw surface itself,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954411912444213">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0954411912444213">8</xref></sup> or otherwise remotely wherein the forces are transferred mechanically through the body of the tool.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954411912444213">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954411912444213">10</xref></sup> Other tools more closely approximate the form of tactile sensors by taking the form of distributed arrays capable of measuring pressure distribution.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954411912444213">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954411912444213">13</xref></sup> The second type takes the form of stiff-bodied laparascopic tools or catheter devices, intended for direct indentation, for measurement of tissue compliance or tool interaction force. These tools usually only contain one sensor, mounted at the tip or remotely, and can measure only a single point;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954411912444213">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954411912444213">15</xref></sup> many are based on a vibrotactile sensing methodology.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954411912444213">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0954411912444213">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>Most of these forms of tool design are intended for manual operation, wherein the clinician operates the device by squeezing a handle or trigger (grasping tools/forceps) or manipulates the end of the tool directly on to the tissue. For most, operation is intended to be similar to the use of standard MIS tools, therefore, they are useful when the desired general area of application is known and can be localised by endoscopic imaging. Some work has been conducted on robotically actuated palpation devices that have the advantage of controlled, and thus safer, indentation forces.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954411912444213">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954411912444213">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954411912444213">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0954411912444213">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Tools designed solely for measuring tissue compliance and/or tissue pressure distribution are less commonly reported. These types of tools, in contrast to the interaction force measuring type, are useful solely for diagnostic procedures and are intended to replace the information derived from investigative palpation. Ideally these are tactile sensors mounted on tools that approximate the form and mechanical characteristics of the finger, with position and indentation feedback; they must, in principle, also encapsulate properties of shape, texture and temperature measurement and must, therefore, consist of an array of sensors placed in direct contact with the tissue under examination, measuring multiple points concurrently.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0954411912444213">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0954411912444213">21</xref></sup> For actual quantitative data of tissue stiffness, the local tissue morphology must be known and non-linear viscoelastic properties accounted for.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0954411912444213">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0954411912444213">24</xref></sup> There are so far no reported designs that purport all of these properties simultaneously. Tactile sensor arrays are useful to produce pressure distribution maps for more accurate positioning of sub-surface anatomical features, more convenient than the use of medical image guidance. Tools that have been developed with array sensors almost all follow the basic format of a grasper, with the sensors mounted on closing jaws; however, the requirement of a protective covering limits their force and spatial resolutions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954411912444213">25</xref></sup></p>
<p>Where the area of application of a sensing device is a region that cannot easily be differentiated by visual feedback alone, medical imaging techniques become necessary for localisation and tool guidance. MRI and US are common forms of medical imaging for image guided therapy as they do not employ ionising radiation. Although US has major advantages of being relatively cheap and convenient in terms of the size of equipment involved, it suffers from relatively poor resolution and imaging range limitations compared with other imaging technologies. MRI has significant advantages in its ability to resolve soft tissue boundaries, capability of multiplanar imaging and use of optimisable image sequences. However, owing to the operating principle based on magnetic state and gradient fields, and radio-frequency pulsing, challenges exist in the design of devices compatible to the magnetic resonance (MR) environment that do not produce mutual interferences, especially when electronic or magnetically susceptible components are used in the design.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954411912444213">26</xref></sup> Force sensors have been developed for certain applications in MRI-compatible devices, in particular for systems used for neuroscientific studies of brain activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954411912444213">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954411912444213"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0954411912444213">30</xref></sup> Zbyszewski et al. reported a design of an MRI compatible force sensor based on an optical sensing to detect the deflection of a rolling ball mounted at the tip of the stiff laparascopic device when indented against a target tissue, with return force provided by air pressure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0954411912444213">31</xref></sup> The sensor measures force only at a single point, although it may be rolled across a surface. Similar force sensing techniques applicable in the MR environment based on optical reflection and refraction principles have also been reported in literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0954411912444213">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0954411912444213">34</xref></sup> Sutherland et al. have developed the NeuroArm system MRI-guided tele-surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0954411912444213">35</xref></sup> The system includes two 7-degree-of-freedom slave manipulators mounted on a base platform that incorporates end effectors with 3-axis force sensors for haptic feedback to the master controllers at the workstation. However, none of these systems are medical tools intended for tactile sensing to be applied internally or within the scanner isocentre. Syntouch Inc has developed BioTac<sup>®</sup>, a tactile sensor with an embedded sensing electrode array, thermistors and pressure sensors, mimicking the sensory modalities of force, vibration and temperature in the human fingertip, although this sensor is not designed for use inside a MRI environment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0954411912444213">36</xref></sup> There is an almost complete absence of MRI-compatible tactile sensing tools, mainly owing to the technological challenges involved, as well as the limited employment of MRI-guided surgery to date. In comparison to tactile sensing technology, there has been a greater quantity of development of MRI-compatible actuators and techniques, including the use of manual actuation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0954411912444213">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0954411912444213">37</xref></sup> pneumatic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0954411912444213">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0954411912444213">39</xref></sup> and hydraulic principles,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0954411912444213">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0954411912444213">41</xref></sup> ultrasonic motors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0954411912444213">42</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0954411912444213"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0954411912444213">44</xref></sup> and electro-rheological fluids.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954411912444213">28</xref></sup> Detailed comparative studies of different actuation principles have also been reported in literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0954411912444213">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0954411912444213">46</xref></sup></p>
<p>This article describes the design concept and compatibility testing of an MRI-compatible tactile sensor array to investigate pressure distribution and localise sub-surface anatomical features. The design is based on piezoelectric sensing principle and allows real-time tele-palpation of tissue features during MRI, providing one-to-one direct haptic feedback from a target position.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0954411912444213">
<title>MR compatibility</title>
<p>The MR environment imposes significant restrictions on the device design, as any device applied within it must be MR compatible. MR-compatible equipment are required to cause negligible adverse effects on the image quality and scanner operation during their normal operating conditions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0954411912444213">47</xref></sup> Furthermore, an MR-compatible device should cause no additional risk to the patient by way of induced forces, torques, induced currents or heating.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954411912444213">26</xref></sup> Unfortunately, devices incorporating electronic components experience mutual electromagnetic interferences (EMIs) by interaction with the scanner magnetic fields and detector coils. MR-compatible devices are designed with alternative solutions for the required structural materials, actuation, sensing, signal and motion transmission and control components, to ensure normal functionality and minimal interference with the scanner.</p>
<p>Standard procedures for the testing of MR compatibility of passive devices are defined by the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0954411912444213">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0954411912444213">49</xref></sup> Chinzei et al. proposed a zone classification in MR scanner rooms that provided design guidelines, for both active and passive devices, of levels of MR compatibility required according to the device separation from the imaging volume and its working principle methods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0954411912444213">50</xref></sup> For accepted levels, the signal to noise ratio (SNR) reduction caused by a device should not exceed 10% in any circumstance,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0954411912444213">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0954411912444213">50</xref></sup> this guarantees that very minimal noise interference occurs within MR images in pathological, diagnostical or anatomical MRI with most of the imaging sequences.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0954411912444213">
<title>Piezoelectric sensor array</title>
<p>Existing technology developed for tactile sensing was investigated for the selection of the sensor type. In MIS applications, tactile sensing techniques have been developed and the predominant choices are piezoelectric, resistive or capacitive arrays, with strain gauges preferred for force measurement.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0954411912444213">51</xref></sup> Two commercial tactile pressure distribution sensors have been found: ‘TactArray’, a capacitive array by Pressure Profiling Systems Incorporated, and another primarily for measuring foot pressures and gait analysis, developed by Tekscan Incorporated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0954411912444213">52</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although a large range of sensors may potentially be applicable to this system, the requirement of MRI compatibility regrettably entails that most of these cannot be considered owing to their use of large currents or non-compatible materials. Gassert et al. provide a detailed review of a vast majority of MR-compatible sensing solutions, including principles of measuring optical transmittance after modulation, and hydrostatic water pressure transducer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0954411912444213">53</xref></sup> all of these are applied to devices not intended for application within the body. Only one reference has been found relating to a sensor for an internally applied MIS medical tool.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0954411912444213">31</xref></sup> However, owing to their relatively large spatial requirements, none of the methods in literature are suitable for a tactile sensing array design.</p>
<p>Piezoelectric sensors are unique among other electrically based transduction types in that they are self-generating, needing no external energy supply, and have extremely high electrical impedance, meaning that they produce negligible current in operation and, therefore, minimal EMI with the MRI scanner. Furthermore, they are highly scalable and thus can achieve high spatial resolution and are also relatively cheap; the main drawback of piezoelectric sensors is that they cannot be used to measure static forces. Piezoceramic sensors made of lead zirconium titanate (PZT) with low magnetic susceptibility and good MRI compatibility were used in previous work.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0954411912444213">54</xref></sup></p>
<p>For force measurement, a changing force must be applied to the piezoelectric sensors. Electrically, their operation can be compared with a high pass filter; therefore, input signals below a certain frequency are attenuated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954411912444213">Figure 1</xref>). As the charge generated by the sensor is directly proportional to the input force, the input force signal in turn is subjected to this direct high pass filtering transformation at the sensor output. To improve the SNR and to simultaneously increase the operating bandwidth, a signal conditioning circuit, known as a charge amplifier, was designed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0954411912444213">54</xref></sup> Charge amplifiers are based on op-amp circuits, with high terminal input impedance and capacitive feedback. The use of a capacitor ensures that charge on the sensor is immediately drawn off and replaced with a corresponding charge and associated voltage developed on the capacitor.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Frequency dependant output characteristics of a piezoelectric sensor, showing output voltage to input force ratio (V<sub>o</sub>/F<sub>i</sub>) against input force frequency (f). (1) Low cut-off frequency owing to finite internal and load impedances. (2) Point of greater than 10% output increase occurring at 20% of the sensors natural frequency (f<sub>n</sub>). (3) Natural frequency f<sub>n</sub>. (4) Operating frequency range.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In previous work, a vector of piezoelectric sensors mounted within an endoscopic probe was used to measure tissue stiffness variation by translation across the surface of a tested tissue object. The stiffness variation caused an output waveform per sensor within which a peak occurred at the stiffest location. The waveforms were combined to form a three-dimensional (3D) pressure distribution contour map. The drawbacks of this method were that the outputs were relative, not absolute, proportional indications of force measured and, additionally, the sensors suffered from extra noise caused by the shear forces of friction caused by sliding across the material surface.</p>
<p>An alternative method for the measurement of pressure distribution is to use a more conventional array design and then actuate this in the normal direction to the surface over the material (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954411912444213">Figure 2</xref>). To measure data from a sufficient area, a large array of sensors is required, where the separation of the elements is small enough to be comparable to the spatial resolution of the finger tip. Extensive work has been carried out in studies of human touch sensing and many performance characteristics have been identified.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0954411912444213">55</xref></sup> One characteristic that has been of particular value to tactile sensor design is the two-point discrimination capability or two-point limen. This is the minimum distance at which two simultaneous, static, contacts can be uniquely resolved. At the finger tip this is approximately 1.8 mm<sup>6</sup> and is treated as a benchmark for the minimum spatial resolution of devices intended to represent realistic feeling forces to a user. Sensitivity varies with the frequency of the applied stimulus and it has been shown that, in active exploration with the fingertip (as in palpation), features as small as 2 μm can be discriminated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0954411912444213">56</xref></sup> As the design of the sensor in this work requires static placement with respect to lateral relative position with the tissue, the two-point limen has greater significance. The advantages of this method is greatly simplified signal conditioning and absolute values of measured force, but at the expense of slower speed of acquisition between areas of interest, a larger number of required electrical connections and a more complicated actuation scheme.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Normal vibration sensing method. (1) An array of sensors vibrated at constant frequency and amplitude over tissue surface. (2) A sinusoidal force at a single frequency is generated. (3) Sensor array may sample tissue surface in steps; a 3D pressure distribution plot may be generated at each position.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0954411912444213">
<title>Mechanical design</title>
<p>Vibration of piezoelectric sensors has been proposed in earlier work by Dario and Bergamasco.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0954411912444213">57</xref></sup> In work carried out by Dargahi et al. it was proposed that sensor outputs are measured from the step input response.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0954411912444213">58</xref></sup> This sensing methodology requires an array of piezoelectric sensors capable of being applied to a surface area of tissue. As an indentor, the shape and compliance affects the measured pressure distribution.</p>
<p>A piezoelectric sensor array of this type was developed and mounted within a probe of endoscopic form as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954411912444213">Figure 3</xref>. The probe has a diameter of 12 mm, which is about the maximum for an endoscopic device, and therefore, it is comparable with the size of an adult human index finger. The device contains mechanical components for a cam mechanism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954411912444213">Figure 3(c)</xref>) to generate linear reciprocal motion and electrical connections for the sensor array. A 4 × 4 array with a resolution of 2 mm is positioned on the outer-facing surface of a mobile sensor mount and electrical connections are routed through the centre of the device; a single electrical cable is required per sensor. The sensor device is designed to be positioned at the image volume and so its MRI-compatibility requirements are stringent. The mount is actuated by a single cam on a brass rod within the body of the probe, this in turn is connected to an shape memory alloy (SMA) transmission cable by a brass connector to convert the rotational motion of the SMA wire to a sinusoidal linear motion; this results in a sinusoidal actuation imparted on the entire sensor array. A pair of elastic rubber connectors is mounted on the inside of the housing to provide the return force. The piezoelectric sensors are made from a commercially available piezodisk bimorph (Murata 7BB-35-6L0).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0954411912444213">54</xref></sup> The sensor mount and probe housing are fabricated from DURUS resin using a selective laser sintering (SLS) rapid prototyping technique.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>(a) Exploded view of an endoscopic probe for normal vibration; external diameter is 12 mm. Shape memory alloy (SMA) actuation cables and position of a 4 × 4 sensor array are shown. (b) Photograph of the manufactured probe. (c) Cam mechanism for sensor array reciprocal motion using SMA transmission of rotational actuation. (d) A 4 × 4 micro sensor array connected with 16 mini coaxial cables. (e) System components with relative locations within the MRI suite and the intrinsic signal transmission and shielding scheme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>A variety of actuation schemes have been developed for MRI-compatible devices reported in literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954411912444213">26</xref></sup>. The most commonly used actuation methods for MRI-compatible devices include those based on piezoelectric and pneumatic principles;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0954411912444213">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0954411912444213">59</xref></sup> both methods present good MR-compatibility owing to their actuation principles being non-electromagnetic and actuators based on these methods can be custom designed and are also available on the market.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0954411912444213">46</xref></sup> The inherent drawback of using pneumatic actuation is air compressibility, which results in a low bandwidth, long response time and a large positional error in control. Although those issues could be partially resolved by increasing the operational air pressure, this solution could lead to potential danger to patients and clinicians if leakage occurs in a medical device with actuation based on this principle.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0954411912444213">60</xref></sup> A piezoelectric motor possesses good controllability owing to the fast response of the piezoelectric material and the micro/nano step positioning that it can achieve; however, these types of motor, together with their specially designed drivers for motor step control, are costly. A Fukoku-Shinsei USR Series travelling wave ultrasonic motor, as a commonly used MR-compatible actuator,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0954411912444213">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0954411912444213">50</xref></sup> can cost around $300–500 for a set. A compromise between the cost and positional accuracy could be the use of conventional non-MR-compatible actuation principles with proper modifications. In previous work, shielding of electronic hardware has been achieved through the use of aluminium Faraday cages that largely reduce electrical and magnetic field transmissions. It was hypothesised that a low-powered servo d.c. motor, placed into a well-shielded Faraday cage located away from the MRI magnet five-guass line, could provide high positioning accuracy of less than 0.2 mm with no compromise in MR image quality or motor functionality. Cables originating from the Faraday cage, if any, would be radio frequency (RF)-filtered and properly shielded, to minimise RF interference. Use of d.c. motors has been reported in previous work by Burdet et al. and is made possible through the use of electromagnetic shielding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0954411912444213">61</xref></sup></p>
<p>A stiff transmission link is required to ensure that the motor can be placed within the Faraday cage at an adequate separation, around 2 m from the scanner isocentre, to further minimise possible interactions. Nickel titanium shape memory alloy (SMA) wire has a high torsional stiffness but is highly elastic, and therefore, can support rotational actuation over a large distance with the added capability of being positioned around a non-linear route.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0954411912444213">36</xref></sup> In use, the wire is contained within a low friction flexible Nylon guidewire, which is lubricated to further reduce friction, and fixed to a desired position.</p>
<p>Frequency and amplitude requirements in operation are limited to a maximum of 15 Hz and 4 mm, respectively. Maximum indentation force is in the range of 1 N, thus a maximum output torque of 4 N mm is sufficient, which is well within the range of any geared d.c. motor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0954411912444213">
<title>System integration</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954411912444213">Figure 3(e)</xref> is a block diagram of the components of the system. A bundle of 16 mini coaxial cables (coax) are used to connect a 4 × 4 micro sensor array to the acquisition unit; one coax is required per sensor element and there are 16 sensor elements in the array. Greatly increased EMI immunity is achieved by connection of the exterior terminal of the coax to the grounded Faraday cage. Both the coax and SMA transmission wire run out of the scanner isocentre to a remotely placed control box. Both are long and flexible and so in subsequent designs could be contained within a flexible outer tube, similar to an endoscopic device.</p>
<p>The Faraday cage was located within the scanner room containing the d.c. motor and its control drive, the signal conditioning and data acquisition electronics of the sensor and a 12 V lead–acid battery. The lengths of the coax and the SMA wire are kept as short as possible, because a long cable, in the case of coax, lowers the SNR of the output, and in the case of the SMA wire, increases the frictional losses. The separation distance, and hence cable lengths, between the Faraday cage and the sensor device positioned within the scanner isocentre was 2 m. The Faraday cage is a box constructed from 4 mm thick aluminium plates, fastened together with brass screws to eliminate mutual electromagnetic interference and was grounded to the ground of the MRI scanner. The d.c. motor (Hitec Standard Deluxe Karbonite Gear Servomotor) was driven by an LM3886 power amplifier (National Semiconductor, CA, USA) with a standard current-control circuit, providing the maximum indentation force, linear motion range and indentation frequency of 4 N, 5 mm and 18 Hz at the front end of the sensor array, with a maximal positional error of less than 0.14 mm. The motor driver was controlled by a 16-bit resolution control signal (±10 V) from an analogue output card (National Instruments, NI-9263) operated with an NI CompactDAQ 4-slot USB chassis. The motor drive is a standard current-control circuit to convert control signal voltage to current source for motor control. Two analogue input cards (National Instruments, NI 9221) were also installed in the chassis, which acquired 12-bit force signals from the 4 × 4 piezoelectric sensor array after a 16-channel charge amplifier circuit for signal pre-amplification and conditioning. RF low-pass filters with a cut-off frequency of 2.5 MHz (BLP-1.9+, Minicircuit, NU, USA) were implemented in each of the coaxial cables before leaving the Faraday cage. Control of the system, and interpretation and display of the data was performed by a laptop PC placed in the control room. This acquired force signals from tissue indentation and displayed them via a graphical user interface developed in National Instruments LabView 9.0. The information from the DAQ was transmitted to the PC using an optical fibre USB extender cable (Opticis M2-110-30).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0954411912444213">
<title>MR compatibility testing</title>
<p>MRI compatibility tests were performed on the device. The tests were comprised of three main parts.</p>
<list id="list1-0954411912444213" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Magnetically induced force. Testing of magnetically induced force requires the component to be hung by a string at the entrance of the scanner. The induced force is deduced by measurement of the angle of deflection from the vertical and the weight of the tested object.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0954411912444213">48</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Generated image artifacts. Testing of an image artifact requires the test component to be placed within a phantom bottle filled with CuSO<sub>4</sub>, and a measurement made of the image artifact surrounding the component. The image artifact is defined to be the area of the image that includes pixels where signal intensity is altered by 30% or more, in comparison with the same area in a control image (phantom only). This test is repeated for all principal axes of the test components aligned with the main field, for spin echo (SE) and gradient echo (GE) image sequences, and for both phase encoding and frequency directions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0954411912444213">49</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>SNR reduction. Testing of SNR reduction compares the SNR value of an MR image of the control image, with the SNR value of an MR image while the test component is present and operating. There are three circumstances considered relating to the test component activation in terms of SNR: unpowered, powered but not actuated, powered and actuated. Tests are repeated for both sequences and component(s) under different circumstances. For a full appreciation of SNR reduction contribution, components were assessed individually, in combinations and with the full system.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>
<?h-4?>The sensor device is intended to be used within the MRI scanner, such that MR compatibility is maintained. The set-up follows the spatial separation specifications shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954411912444213">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Positional requirements for system components relative to the MRI scanner.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954411912444213" xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">System component</th>
<th align="left"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0954411912444213">*</xref>Distance (m)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Phantom and phantom stand</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Piezoelectric sensor, mount, housing and cam with connector</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SMA cable</td>
<td>From 0 to 1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bundle of 16 coaxial cables</td>
<td>From 0 to 1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Faraday box (with d.c. motor and drive circuit, charge amplifier and DAQ device)</td>
<td>From 1.8 to 2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fibre optic cable</td>
<td>From 2.2 to 15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Laptop PC</td>
<td>Outside of scanner room</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0954411912444213">
<label>*</label>
<p>Distances are measured from the scanner isocentre.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0954411912444213">
<p>SMA: shape memory alloy; DAQ: data acquisition.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>At a subsequent stage of development, when the device is physically incorporated into a practical tool design, it is envisaged that the overall tool will be implementable in a method closely following that of standard endoscopic tools. As such, it will be manually controlled, and therefore, entail that the clinician operating it will require adequate access to the patient. Consequently, MR-compatible medical tools intended for use on a patient are mostly used with open-bore rather than closed-bore scanner types.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0954411912444213" sec-type="results|discussion">
<title>Results and discussions</title>
<p>The sensor device was set-up as described above and all experimentation undertaken using a 0.2T Hitachi AIRIS Mate Open-Bore MRI scanner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954411912444213">Figure 4</xref>). Imaging sequence configurations are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0954411912444213">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Testing within 0.2 T open scanner. The Faraday cage is on the right of the image. At the scanner isocentre is the sensor device prototype on a test mount with an MRI receiver coil.</p>
<p>SMA: shape memory alloy.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>MRI scanner sequence configurations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0954411912444213" xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Sequence</th>
<th align="left">Repetitiontime (ms)</th>
<th align="left">Echotime (ms)</th>
<th align="left">Flip angle(deg)</th>
<th align="left">Numberof slices</th>
<th align="left">Thickness ofslice (mm)</th>
<th align="left">Resolution</th>
<th align="left">Field ofview (mm)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Turbo spin echo</td>
<td>300</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>256 × 256</td>
<td>260 × 260</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gradient echo</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>256 × 256</td>
<td>260 × 260</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<list id="list2-0954411912444213" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Magnetically induced force. Testing was carried out on all components of the system. No deflections could be determined from any of the components apart from the SMA cable and coax, which both showed slight deflections from the vertical when hung by their entire length (2 m) of less than 5°, and the magnetically induced forces are 0.08 N and 0.21 N in the SMA cable and coax, respectively.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Generated image artifacts. Testing was not carried out on the Faraday cage or its contents, nor the optical fibre cable, both of which were deemed to be too far separated from the isocentre to cause image artifact interference. Maximum artifact size for the sensor and housing, SMA cable and coax are 4 mm, 3 mm and 8 mm, respectively. The largest artefact generated from the coax is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954411912444213">Figure 5(a)</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>SNR reduction. Testing was carried out on a variety of component configurations to test SNR reduction contributions and the effect of the Faraday shield. Results are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954411912444213">Figure 5(b)</xref>. It was found that in all cases the SNR reduction remained lower than the 10% benchmark put forward in the specifications.</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig5-0954411912444213" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>(a) MR image of the coax bundle with the largest artefact size of 8 mm. (b) Variation of SNR% reduction with component combination and sequence types.</p>
<p>DAQ: ?; SMA: shape memory alloy.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954411912444213-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Results of Test 1 indicate that the components selected experience negligible magnetically induced force. There are minimal attraction forces apparent on both the SMA and the coax bundle, which are much lower than their weight (less than 10% in either case), and as they are firmly mounted during use, they are hence considered MRI safe in the design. Test 2 for image artifacts indicated a maximum artifact of 8 mm owing to the coax. The sensor and sensor housing produced artifacts of 4 mm, indicating the minimum separation from the anatomical features being imaged. Test 3 examined the effect on the image SNR by the sensor device as a whole. Actuation of the motor is shown to consistently produce a greater SNR reduction; similarly the system being powered is consistently more disturbing to the image than when it is unpowered. The introduction of either the coax or, to a lesser extent, the SMA cable, or both, causes a small increase in SNR reduction, which combines with the effect of the actuated motor. Indeed where both cables are combined (using the entire system) and the motor is actuated, the greatest SNR reduction of 8.5% is seen.</p>
<p>The detrimental effect of the cables could be explained by the fact that long cables could act as antennas, picking up RF disturbance and transmitting it into the scanner. A section of the SMA cable could be replaced with an electrically insulating material to minimise RF propagations. In both cases more advanced RF reduction measures, such as use of RF traps, baluns and billabongs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0954411912444213">62</xref></sup> could be implemented in the cables to further suppress RF transmission.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0954411912444213" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>An approach to an MR-compatible tactile sensor design, based on piezoelectric sensors, that can be adapted to a MIS tool, was proposed. The compatibility of the sensing methodology was determined using a basic design, constructed of MRI-compatible materials and with the associated auxiliary hardware and electromagnetic shielding. Test results suggest that the materials selected for the device show MR compatibility in terms of required safety, SNR reduction and artifact generation. In terms of SNR reduction caused to the imaging, the system is also seen to be within the specification criteria of &lt;10% for compatibility, although in a future design, performance could be improved further by placing RF traps, or other RF reduction measures, in the signal transmission cables between the control unit at the Faraday cage and the scanner. A significant result is that the SNR of the MR images was not greatly affected even with the actuation of the d.c. motor, indicating that this is a viable and inexpensive method for actuation compared with ultrasonic motor or pneumatic actuation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0954411912444213">
<title>Future work</title>
<p>Future work will involve additional design of the device for form and function applicable to specified anatomical regions and procedures. One application is for the localisation and analysis of suspected tumours in the prostate or in the lining of the bowel. A haptic MIS tool brings not only the advantage of remote palpation, but additionally, the benefit of quantitative and repeatable measurements, that in combination with statistical data can allow much greater diagnostic capability and accuracy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0954411912444213">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0954411912444213">64</xref></sup> Thus far, thanks to the scalable nature of the sensing methodology, it is predicted that the size of the device could potentially be reduced by half before manufacturing and material availability become limiting. This allows a wide range of MIS regions to be encompassed by different sized sensor arrays. It will also be necessary to test further the MR compatibility of the device by applying the sensor to sensing tasks in phantom trials and tests with different scanner sequences and field strengths to optimise the scanner parameters for this procedure. Finally, for manually controlled image-guided operation within the scanner room, and for visual representation of the developed haptic information, it is intended that the device will be adapted for operation with an MR-compatible display system. MR-compatible image overlay devices have been described in work carried out by Fischer et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0954411912444213">65</xref></sup> and Masamune et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0954411912444213">66</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0954411912444213">
<title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="section10-0954411912444213">
<title>Notation</title>
<p>F<sub>i</sub> input force; force applied on sensor (measurand)</p>
<p>f frequency of force applied on sensor</p>
<p>f<sub>n</sub> mechanical natural frequency of sensor</p>
<p>V<sub>o</sub> output voltage of the sensor</p>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported in part by the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science and the UK Department of Health under NEAT Grant G019.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954411912444213">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chinzei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Towards MRI guided surgical manipulator</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Monit</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954411912444213">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A robotic system for transrectal needle insertion into the prostate with integrated ultrasound</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE international conference on robotics and automation</conf-name>, <year>2004</year>, pp.<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954411912444213">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Minimally invasive and robotic surgery</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Ass</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954411912444213">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DiMaio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salcudean</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Needle insertion modeling and simulation</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Robotics and Automation</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>864</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954411912444213">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Anatomy: palpation and surface markings</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Butterworth–Heinemann</publisher-name>, vol. <volume>2</volume>, <year>1997</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954411912444213">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dargahi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Najarian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Najarian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development and three-dimensional modelling of a biological-tissue grasper tool equipped with a tactile sensor</article-title>. <source>Can J Elec Computer Engng</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954411912444213">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tholey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A compact and modular laparoscopic grasper with tridirectional force measurement capability</article-title>. <source>J Med Devices</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>031001</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954411912444213">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sedaghati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dargahi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Design and modeling of an endoscopic piezoelectric tactile sensor</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Structures</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>5872</fpage>–<lpage>5886</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954411912444213">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bicchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canepa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Rossi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A sensor-based minimally invasive surgery tool for detecting tissue elastic properties</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of IEEE international conference on robotics and automation</conf-name>, <year>1996</year>, pp.<fpage>884</fpage>–<lpage>888</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954411912444213">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tavakoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moallem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Haptic interaction in robot-assisted endoscopic surgery: a sensorized end-effector</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Robotics Computer Assisted Surg</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954411912444213">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trejos</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jayender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perri</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Robot-assisted tactile sensing for minimally invasive tumor localization</article-title>. <source>Int J Robotics Res</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1133</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954411912444213">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ottermo</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stavdahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Palpation instrument for augmented minimally invasive surgery</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE/RSJ international conference on intelligent robots and systems</conf-name>, <year>2004</year>, pp.<fpage>3960</fpage>–<lpage>3964</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954411912444213">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peine</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A palpation system for artery localization in laparoscopic surgery</article-title>. In: <conf-name>1st international symposium on medical robotics and computer assisted surgery</conf-name>, <year>1994</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954411912444213">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A robust uniaxial force sensor for minimally invasive surgery</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Biomed Engng</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1008</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954411912444213">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A tactile enhancement instrument for minimally invasive surgery</article-title>. <source>Computer Aided Surg</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954411912444213">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Omata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Constantinou</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Real time robotic tactile sensor system for the determination of physical properties of biomaterials</article-title>. <source>Sens Actuators</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0954411912444213">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stroop</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uribe</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melisa</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tactile tissue characterisation by piezoelectric systems</article-title>. <source>J Electroceramics</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0954411912444213">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shikida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Active tactile sensor for detecting contact force and hardness of an object</article-title>. <source>Sensors and Actuators A</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0954411912444213">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shimachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirunyanitiwatna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adapter for contact force sensing of the da Vinci® robot</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Robotics Computer Assisted Surg</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0954411912444213">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eltaib</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hewit</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tactile sensing technology for minimal access surgery—a review</article-title>. <source>Mechatronics</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0954411912444213">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tactile sensing for mechatronics—a state of the art survey</article-title>. <source>Mechatronics</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0954411912444213">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manduca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliphant</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dresner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance elastography: non-invasive mapping of tissue elasticity</article-title>. <source>Med Image Analysis</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0954411912444213">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noonan</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zweiri</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The development of nonlinear viscoelastic model for the application of soft tissue identification</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE/RSJ international conference on intelligent robots and systems</conf-name>, <conf-loc>San Diego, CA</conf-loc>, <year>2007</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0954411912444213">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Samani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luginbuhl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plewes</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance elastography technique for breast tissue in-vitro elasticity measurement</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE international biomedical imaging symposium</conf-name>, <year>2002</year>, pp.<fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>934</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0954411912444213">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shostek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalanovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Artificial tactile sensing in minimally invasive surgery – a new technical approach</article-title>. <source>Minimally Invasive Therapy and Allied Technologies</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0954411912444213">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elhawary</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ZTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The case for MR-compatible robotics: a review of the state of the art</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Robotics Computer Assisted Surg</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0954411912444213">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elster</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Simultaneous measurement of human joint force, surface electromyograms, and functional MRI-measured brain activation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Meth</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0954411912444213">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khanicheh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Triantafyllou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>fMRI-compatible rehabilitation hand device</article-title>. <source>J NeuroEngng Rehabilitation</source> <year>2006</year>; <fpage>3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0954411912444213">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fluekiger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bullo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapuis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>fMRI compatible haptic interface actuated with traveling wave ultrasonic motor</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE industry applications conference: 40th IAS annual meeting</conf-name>, <year>2005</year>, pp.<fpage>2075</fpage>–<lpage>2082</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0954411912444213">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hidler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mbwana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeffiro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>MRI compatible force sensing system for real-time monitoring of wrist moments during fMRI testing</article-title>. In: <conf-name>9th international conference on rehabilitation robotics, ICORR</conf-name>, <year>2005</year>, pp.<fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0954411912444213">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zbyszewski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polygerinos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seneviratne</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A novel MRI compatible air-cushion tactile sensor for minimally invasive surgery</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE/RSJ international conference on intelligent robots and systems</conf-name>, <year>2009</year>, pp.<fpage>2647</fpage>–<lpage>2652</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0954411912444213">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tokuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-precision MRI-compatible force sensor with parallel plate structure</article-title>. In: <conf-name>2nd IEEE RAS &amp; EMBS international conference on biomedical robotics and biomechatronics, BioRob</conf-name>, <year>2008</year>, pp.<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0954411912444213">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hao Sand Fischer</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A 3-axis optical force/torque sensor for prostate needle placement in Magnetic resonance imaging environments</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE international conference on technologies for practical robot applications, TePRA</conf-name>, <year>2009</year>, pp.<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0954411912444213">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>UX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gullapalli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Design and development of a 3-axis MRI-compatible force sensor</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE international conference on robotics and automation, ICRA</conf-name>, <year>2010</year>, pp.<fpage>2586</fpage>–<lpage>2591</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0954411912444213">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McBeth</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Louw</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <article-title>NeuroArm: an mr compatible robot for microsurgery</article-title>. <source>Computer Assisted Radiology Surg</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>1256</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0954411912444213">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Susil</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Menard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Design of a novel MRI compatible manipulator for image guided prostate interventions</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Biomed Engng</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0954411912444213">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fichtinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Susil</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Transrectal prostate biopsy inside closed mri scanner with remote actuation, under real-time image guidance</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the 5th medical image computing and computer-assisted intervention</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Tokyo, Japan</conf-loc>, <year>2002</year>, pp.<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0954411912444213">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stoianovici</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A new type of motor: pneumatic step motor</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatronics</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0954411912444213">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ZTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elhawary</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zivanovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A 3 degree of freedom MR compatible device for magic angle related in vivo experiments</article-title>. <source>ASME/IEEE Trans Mechatronics</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0954411912444213">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gassert</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burdet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bleuler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>MRI/fMRI-compatible robotic system with force feedback for interaction with human motion</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatronics</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0954411912444213">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gassert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burdet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dynamics and control of an MRI compatible master-slave system with hydrostatic transmission</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE international conference on robotics and automation</conf-name>, <conf-loc>New Orleans, LA, USA</conf-loc>, <year>2004</year>, pp.<fpage>1288</fpage>–<lpage>1294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0954411912444213">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chinzei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jolesz</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Surgical assist robot for the active navigation in the intraoperative MRI: hardware design issues</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of IEEE/RSJ international conference of intelligent robots and systems</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Maui, HI, USA</conf-loc>, <year>2000</year>, pp.<fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0954411912444213">
<label>43.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Masamune</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masutani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development of an MRI-compatible needle insertion manipulator for stereotactic neurosurgery</article-title>. <source>J Image Guided Surg</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0954411912444213">
<label>44.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flueckiger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bullo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapuis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>fMRI compatible haptic interface actuated with traveling wave ultrasonic motor</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the 40th industry applications annual conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Provo, UT, USA</conf-loc>, <year>2005</year>, pp.<fpage>2075</fpage>–<lpage>2082</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0954411912444213">
<label>45.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iordachita</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <source>MRI compatibility of robot actuation techniques – a comparative study medical image computing and computer-assisted intervention – MICCAI</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Metaxas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. eds. <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>, pp.<fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0954411912444213">
<label>46.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gassert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapuis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Actuation methods for applications in MR environments</article-title>. <source>Concepts in Magnetic Resonance Part B: Magnetic Resonance Engng</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0954411912444213">
<label>47.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shellock</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Metallic surgical instruments for interventional MRI procedures: evaluation of MR safety</article-title>. <source>J MRI</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0954411912444213">
<label>48.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<comment>ASTM, Standard test method for measurement of magnetically induced displacement force on medical devices in the magnetic resonance environment. ASTM F2052-02</comment>, <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0954411912444213">
<label>49.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<comment>ASTM-F2119, Standard Test method for evaluation of MR image artifacts from passive implants. ASTM F2119</comment>, <year>2007</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0954411912444213">
<label>50.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chinzei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kikinis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jolesz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>MR compatibility of mechatronic devices: design criteria</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of 2nd international conference on medical image computing and computer-assisted interventions</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Cambridge, UK</conf-loc>, <year>1999</year>, pp.<fpage>1020</fpage>–<lpage>1031</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0954411912444213">
<label>51.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puangmali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Althoefer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seneviratne</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>State-of-the-art in force and tactile sensing for minimally invasive surgery</article-title>. <source>IEEE Sensors J</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0954411912444213">
<label>52.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Papakostas</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A large area force sensor for smart skin applications</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the 1st IEEE international conference on sensors</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Florida, USA</conf-loc>, <year>2002</year>, pp.<fpage>1620</fpage>–<lpage>1624</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0954411912444213">
<label>53.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gassert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapuis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bleuler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sensors for applications in magnetic resonance environments</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatronics</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0954411912444213">
<label>54.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ZTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Applying tactile sensing with piezoelectric materials for minimally invasive surgery and magnetic-resonance-guided interventions</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE, Part H: J Engineering in Medicine</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>223</volume>; <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0954411912444213">
<label>55.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burdea</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Haptic feedback for virtual reality</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Virtual reality and prototyping workshop</conf-name>, <year>1999</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0954411912444213">
<label>56.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beauregard</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The impact of visual information on the haptic perception of stiffness in virtual environments</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the ASME dynamics systems and control division</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Georgia, USA</conf-loc>, <year>1996</year>, pp.<fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0954411912444213">
<label>57.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dario</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergamasco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An advanced robot system for automated diagnostic tasks through palpation</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Biomed Engng</source> <year>1988</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0954411912444213">
<label>58.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dargahi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parameswaran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Payandeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A micromachined piezoelectric tactile sensor for an endoscopic grasper-theory, fabrication and experiments</article-title>. <source>J Microelectromech Sys</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0954411912444213">
<label>59.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ZTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance elastography hardware design: a survey</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE, Part H: J Engineering in Medicine</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>223</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0954411912444213">
<label>60.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elhawary</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zivanovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A review of magnetic resonance imaging compatible manipulators in surgery</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE, Part H: J Engineering in Medicine</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0954411912444213">
<label>61.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burdet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gassert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gowrishankar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>fMRI compatible hapticinterfaces to investigate human motor control</article-title>. In: <conf-name>9th international symposium on experimental robotics</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Berlin</conf-loc>, <year>2006</year>, pp.<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0954411912444213">
<label>62.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bottomley</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Designing passive MRI-safe implantable conducting leads with electrodes</article-title>. <source>Med Physics</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>3828</fpage>–<lpage>3843</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0954411912444213">
<label>63.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tholey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Force feedback plays a significant role in minimally invasive surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>241</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0954411912444213">
<label>64.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ottermo</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ovstedal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lango</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The role of tactile feedback in laparoscopic surgery</article-title>. <source>Surg Laparosc Endosc Percutan Tech</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0954411912444213">
<label>65.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deguet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Csoma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>MRI image overlay: application to arthrography needle insertion</article-title>. <source>J Computer Assisted Surg</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0954411912444213">
<label>66.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Masamune</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Non-metal slice image overlay display system used inside the open type MRI</article-title>. <source>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>5128</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>