<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOU</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjou</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1464-8849</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3001</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1464884911431538</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1464884911431538</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Different roles, different content? A four-country comparison of the role conceptions and reporting style of political journalists</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>van Dalen</surname><given-names>Arjen</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1464884911431538">University of Southern Denmark, Denmark</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>de Vreese</surname><given-names>Claes H</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1464884911431538">University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Albæk</surname><given-names>Erik</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-1464884911431538">University of Southern Denmark, Denmark</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1464884911431538">Arjen van Dalen, Centre for Journalism, University of Southern Denmark, Campusvej 55, 5230 Odense M, Denmark. Email: <email>avd@sam.sdu.dk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>903</fpage>
<lpage>922</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The relation between journalistic role conceptions and news content is central for the understanding of differences in journalistic cultures. Previous research has shown that the professional roles of individual journalists can influence their behaviour and that occupational socialization leads to similar role conceptions within countries. This article therefore studies the relation between cross-national differences in role conceptions and news content. A survey among political journalists in Denmark, Germany, the United Kingdom, and Spain (<italic>N</italic> = 425), combined with a content analysis of political coverage in these countries (<italic>N</italic> = 1,035 newspaper articles) shows that role conceptions vary more across countries than within countries. Spanish political journalists see their role as more sacerdotal and partisan than their colleagues in northern Europe, while British journalists are most entertainment oriented. These differences in role conceptions are reflected in the reporting style of political news.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Comparative research</kwd>
<kwd>content analysis</kwd>
<kwd>journalistic cultures</kwd>
<kwd>political journalism</kwd>
<kwd>reporting style</kwd>
<kwd>role conceptions</kwd>
<kwd>survey</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1464884911431538" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>A growing body of literature is concerned with the question of how journalistic cultures differ across countries. Such studies generally take two approaches. On the one hand, survey-based research addresses the different ways journalists see their roles (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1464884911431538">Hanitzsch et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1464884911431538">Weaver and Willnat, forthcoming</xref>). On the other hand, we can distinguish a line of research which looks at the actual news content that is produced (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1464884911431538">Benson and Hallin, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1464884911431538">Esser, 2008</xref>). Both types of studies generally assume a relation between the way journalists in a country see their roles and news content in this country. Studies of cross-national role conception variation presumes that variation in role conceptions causes variation in content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1464884911431538">Patterson, 1998</xref>: 30), while cross-national studies of content speculate that content variation is caused by variation in role conceptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1464884911431538">De Vreese et al., 2001</xref>). The relation between role conceptions and news content is crucial for the understanding of the origins and consequences of differences in journalistic cultures. In the words of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1464884911431538">Donsbach (2008)</xref>, role conceptions ‘can have a strong influence on journalists’ professional behaviour and thus can explain differences between news cultures’.</p>
<p>However, the study of role conceptions by means of journalism surveys and the study of news content by means of content analysis are generally not combined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1464884911431538">Weaver and Löffelholz, 2008</xref>: 6). Pioneering studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1464884911431538">Köcher (1986)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1464884911431538">Patterson and Donsbach (1996)</xref> have included news scenarios in journalism surveys and shown a relation between role conceptions and news decisions, both at the individual level and the aggregated country level. But such studies are still exceptions and, especially, studies combining journalism surveys with content analysis are lacking (for exceptions see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1464884911431538">Scholl and Weischenberg, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1464884911431538">Weaver and Wilhoit, 1996</xref>). Studies of journalistic cultures generally study <italic>either</italic> role conceptions <italic>or</italic> news content.</p>
<p>Following recommendations by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1464884911431538">Esser (2008)</xref> this article therefore studies cross-national differences in journalistic roles <italic>in combination</italic> with news content. In other words: what is the relation between the way journalists in a particular country describe their role and the way they do their work? This question is addressed by combining a survey among political journalists in four European countries (<italic>N</italic> = 425) with a content analysis of political coverage in these countries (<italic>N</italic> = 1035 news items). The role conceptions of Danish, German, British and Spanish political journalists are compared with the content they produce along three dimensions (pragmatic–sacerdotal, impartial–partisan and information–entertainment), each addressed later.</p>
<p>The merits of international comparative journalism research are widely acknowledged (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1464884911431538">Blumler and Gurevitch, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1464884911431538">Donsbach, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1464884911431538">Esser and Pfetsch, 2004</xref>). Only by comparing journalistic cultures in different countries can we see what makes each of these cultures special and thereby ‘render the invisible visible’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1464884911431538">Blumler and Gurevitch, 1995</xref>: 76). Our comparative design will show whether cross-national differences in content reflect cross-national differences in roles. However, cross-national comparisons do not provide a rigid test for causal relations in the same way as experiments or large N-studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1464884911431538">Donsbach, 2010</xref>: 168). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1464884911431538">Smelser (1976</xref>: 157–158) therefore speaks of ‘systematic comparative illustration’ rather than of comparative analysis. This does not mean that comparative analysis should not aim to seek for explanations and search for meaningful relations. In this comparative study of roles and content, we search for regularities and ‘on the basis of prior research or theory (…) place causal interpretations on those observations’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1464884911431538">Jackman, 1985</xref>: 172). Studies showing a relation at the individual level are ultimately a prerequisite to explain similar relations found at the macro-level studies. This study therefore builds on journalism studies of the professional attitude–behaviour relation at the individual level and extends these to explain the role–content relation on the macro level.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1464884911431538">
<title>Linking journalistic roles and content</title>
<p>The study of journalistic role conceptions goes back to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1464884911431538">Cohen’s (1963)</xref> study of the conceptions of the roles of foreign correspondents. Later, studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1464884911431538">Johnstone et al. (1976)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1464884911431538">Weaver and Wilhoit (1986)</xref> led to numerous survey projects which describe how journalists around the world see their professional tasks (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1464884911431538">Hanitzsch et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1464884911431538">Weaver and Willnat, forthcoming</xref>). Several studies go beyond descriptive accounts of the way journalists within a country see their role by studying role conceptions as a dependent variable. This has provided insight into the effect of personal, organization and societal factors on role conceptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1464884911431538">Zhu et al., 1997</xref>). Such studies have given valuable insight into newsroom socialization and the professionalization of journalism. For most scholars, however, the rationale for studying role conceptions is based on the assumption that journalists’ role conceptions influence their work. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1464884911431538">Shoemaker and Reese (1996</xref>: 103) argue that professional roles have direct influence on news content, since these ‘determine what the communicator thinks is worth transmitting to his or her audience and how the story should be developed’.</p>
<p>The relation between attitudes and behaviour is not only presumed theoretically, but also supported empirically. This is not only the case for journalism studies, but also for communication research more broadly. A meta-study of communication research looking into the attitude–behaviour relation by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1464884911431538">Kim and Hunter (1993)</xref> convincingly showed a strong relation when controlling for methodological differences. The relation was particularly strong for attitudes which are of great relevance for the individuals. Professional role conceptions have great attitudinal relevance for journalists, since they define the identity of the journalistic profession. We can therefore expect that these professional attitudes have some impact on journalists’ behaviour. Several journalism studies have indeed shown a relation between professional role conceptions and news content. An experiment by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1464884911431538">Starck and Soloski (1977)</xref> showed that articles by journalism students who have participant role conception include more analyses and interpretations than articles by students who see their role as neutral reporters. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1464884911431538">Culbertson (1983)</xref> showed a relation between the role conception of newspaper journalists and the emphasis they place on particular journalistic practices. He found that journalists who preferred the role of providing interpretation also preferred investigative reporting over local news. Based on a survey among Danish journalists, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1464884911431538">Skovsgaard et al. (2011)</xref> showed that role conceptions influence the way journalists operationalize the objectivity norm. When comparing role conceptions of journalists and what they see as their best journalistic work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1464884911431538">Weaver et al. (2007</xref>: 233) conclude that ‘journalist’s support for a particular professional role occasionally seemed to have a modest association with the kind of story he or she chose’. In a similar study in Germany, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1464884911431538">Scholl and Weischenberg (1998)</xref> found a significant correlation between the roles of individual journalists and their content. By aggregating their findings, Scholl and Weischenberg were even able to show a relation between roles and content at the national level.</p>
<p>Studying the relation between roles and content at the national level can be justified, since single country studies of journalists generally describe a homogeneous journalistic profession, with limited variation between the role conceptions and ethical standards among journalists working for different news organizations (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1464884911431538">Deuze, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1464884911431538">Skovsgaard et al., forthcoming</xref>). Role conceptions are shaped through professional experience and learned on the job (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1464884911431538">Breed, 1955</xref>). Socialization takes place not only within but also across news organizations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1464884911431538">Donsbach (2010</xref>: 157) sees role conceptions as a characteristic of journalists as an occupational group and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1464884911431538">Weaver and Wilhoit (1996</xref>: 138) argue that the role conceptions of individual journalists are influenced by ‘journalism’s majority culture’ of the country they work in.</p>
<p>We can expect that role conceptions will be particularly homogeneous for political journalists who are central in this study. Occupational socialization is especially influential among journalists covering the same subject, like the political beat. Journalists working in a beat tend to express similar points of view and report from the same perspective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1464884911431538">Schudson, 2003</xref>: 139), a phenomenon described earlier as pack journalism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1464884911431538">Frank, 2003</xref>). Through the interaction with their competitor-colleagues on the job and outside work, these beat journalists develop ‘commonly shared perspectives’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1464884911431538">Donsbach, 2004</xref>: 142), which influence the news decisions. Despite growing globalization, journalistic professions are still nationally organized. Political journalists work in beats around the institutions of national government and parliament. Newspapers and television channels compete for audiences within national borders. Based on these considerations we expect to find strong similarities in role conceptions within countries and differences across countries, which will be reflected in news content.</p>
<p>An empirical study comparing the role conceptions of journalists in China, Taiwan and the United States supports the expectation that role conceptions vary more across countries than within. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1464884911431538">Zhu et al. (1997</xref>: 84) came to the conclusion that ‘societal factors had the strongest impact on journalists’ views about media roles, the organizational factors had a significant, but weak impact and the individual factor has virtually no impact’. Although one can expect that the role conceptions of the Danish, German, Spanish and British political journalists included in this study vary less than the roles of journalists in the United States, Taiwan and China, the first hypothesis expects that cross-national differences remain important, even among European countries:
<disp-quote>
<p>H1 The country in which political journalists work has more influence on their role conceptions than organizational and individual factors.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1464884911431538">
<title>Roles and content: Three dimensions</title>
<p>As with role conceptions, political news content also shows strong similarities between news outlets within countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1464884911431538">Cook, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1464884911431538">Esser, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1464884911431538">Sparrow, 1999</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1464884911431538">Cook (2005</xref>: 64) summarizes the similarities in work practice by stating that the ‘transorganizational agreement of news processes and content suggest that we should think of the news media not as a set of diverse organizations, or even a batch of individual institutions, but collectively as a single social institution’. These similarities in content are strongest for news outlets which aim at similar audiences and which rely on similar types of funding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1464884911431538">Strömbäck and Van Aelst, 2010</xref>). Since previous research suggests that both journalistic roles and content vary more across countries than within countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1464884911431538">Donsbach, 2010</xref>: 167) and since previous studies have proven that roles and content are related at the level of the individual journalist, the main expectation of this study is that there is a relation between roles and news content at the national level. This expectation is supported by the findings of two pioneering comparative journalism research projects. Using news scenarios, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1464884911431538">Köcher (1986)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1464884911431538">Patterson and Donsbach (1996)</xref> went beyond studying the relation between attitudes and news decisions at the individual level and convincingly showed that the same relations were present when news cultures were compared. We want to add to the external validity of these findings by comparing role conceptions with news decisions as they are expressed in news content.</p>
<p>To test the link between journalistic attitudes and behaviour at the macro level, we compare the role conceptions of political journalists in Denmark, Germany, the UK and Spain with the reporting style of political news along three dimensions: first, the status of political news (pragmatic versus sacerdotal); second, the degree of partisan commitment (impartial versus partisan); and, third, the approach to the audience (information versus entertainment). Similar dimensions has been used in previous journalism surveys, observational studies or content analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1464884911431538">De Vreese, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1464884911431538">Semetko et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1464884911431538">Weaver and Willnat, forthcoming</xref>). These dimensions are relevant, furthermore, because of their potential effects on audiences. The more pragmatic the approach to politics the greater the likelihood of applying news frames such as conflict and game, which in turn may impact on political cynicism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1464884911431538">Cappella and Jamieson, 1997</xref>). Partisan commitment may influence the attention and tone towards different politicians, which in turn affect vote preference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1464884911431538">Hopmann et al., 2010</xref>). Entertainment features in news may entice and excite audiences but may also decrease electoral participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1464884911431538">Adam and Maier, 2010</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section4-1464884911431538">
<title>Pragmatic–sacerdotal</title>
<p>The first dimension is the pragmatic–sacerdotal approach to politics. Journalists with a sacerdotal role conception believe national politics and politicians should be treated with respect ‘as if imbued with a degree of sacredness’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1464884911431538">Blumler and Gurevitch, 1995</xref>: 50). Since national parliament and government are fundamental for the functioning of a democratic society, sacerdotal journalists consider these institutions newsworthy by definition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1464884911431538">Semetko et al., 1991</xref>). Journalists with a pragmatic journalistic role conception do not automatically attribute such a special status to national politics. When deciding whether and how national politics should be covered, they apply the same selection criteria and news values as they would apply to any other topic.</p>
<p>Whether journalists have a pragmatic or sacerdotal role conception is expected to be related to two aspects of the reporting style of national politics. First, the dominant role conception will influence the overall visibility of national politics in the news. Because national politics has a special status in countries where journalists predominantly have a sacerdotal role conception, political news will be covered extensively and will often be visible on the front page. Second, in countries where a pragmatic role conception is dominant, journalists will base their news coverage more on news values. Pragmatic journalists do not treat news about politics as inherently relevant, but will try to make political news attractive to the audience by framing politics in terms of conflict or by presenting politics as a game (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1464884911431538">Patterson, 1993</xref>). We expect differences in focus on conflicts and game framing to be a consequence of either a dominant pragmatic or a dominant sacerdotal role conception in countries. The two hypotheses about the influence of a pragmatic versus sacerdotal role conception on news content are therefore:
<disp-quote>
<p>H2a The more sacerdotal the role conceptions of political journalists in a country, the more visible national politics will be in the news.</p>
<p>H2b The more sacerdotal the role conceptions of political journalists in a country, the less news about national politics will be covered with a conflict or game frame.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1464884911431538">
<title>Impartial–partisan</title>
<p>Second, a relation between journalistic roles and content is studied on the impartial-partisan dimension. Journalists can have a partisan role conception and believe that the political line of the medium should guide their work, or see their role as impartial and aim to give a balanced account of events. Journalists who have a partisan role conception believe it is acceptable for journalists to take sides in political disputes, while impartial journalists aim to present balanced coverage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1464884911431538">Blumler and Gurevitch, 1995</xref>). A partisan role conception can lead to coverage bias or statement bias (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1464884911431538">D’Alessio and Allen, 2000</xref>: 135–136). Coverage bias refers to imbalance in the <italic>visibility</italic> of politicians in the news. If politicians belonging to a certain political party systematically receive more coverage than politicians from other parties, coverage is biased towards this political party. Statement bias refers to the <italic>tone</italic> of coverage in favour or against political parties or blocks. News is considered to be balanced when positive and negative evaluations are represented equally. Partisan bias should be distinguished from structural biases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1464884911431538">Hoffstetter, 1976</xref>: 34). If all media outlets are consistently negative of one party or political block, this is likely to be due to general news routines. In the four countries under study, broadsheet newspapers generally have a distinct political profile, which is expressed in the editorials, opinion pieces and columns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1464884911431538">Tresch, 2009</xref>). These political profiles are also recognizable in the political preferences of readers of these newspapers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1464884911431538">Seymoure-Ure, 1974</xref>). Whether the political leaning of the newspaper is also visible in news coverage is expected to depend on the dominant role conceptions of journalists. Thus, the following hypotheses will be tested:
<disp-quote>
<p>H3a The more partisan the role conceptions of political journalists in a country, the more news about national politics will have a partisan coverage bias.</p>
<p>H3b The more partisan the role conceptions of political journalists in a country, the more news about national politics will have a partisan bias in tone towards politicians.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1464884911431538">
<title>Information-entertainment</title>
<p>The third dimension along which roles and content will be compared is the information-entertainment dimension. Journalists can, on the one hand, see their role mainly as information providers, who give the audience the type of information they need to make informed democratic decisions. On the other hand, journalists can see it as their role to provide the audience with the entertainment and relaxation they desire. Differences between these two ways of seeing the journalistic role are expected to be reflected in different topics in focus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1464884911431538">Esser, 1999</xref>). Where journalists see it as their role to provide information, political news will focus more on hard news, while political journalists who want to entertain will focus more on ‘sex, scandals and infotainment’ (Kublin, 1997, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1464884911431538">Esser, 1999</xref>: 292). In this study we look, in particular, at two entertainment topics: scandals and politicians’ private lives.</p>
<p>First, an entertainment orientation is expected to be reflected in more scandal coverage. In the literature, a desire to capture a large audience with ‘lively, entertaining news’ is mentioned as one of the reasons for scandal coverage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1464884911431538">Thompson, 2000</xref>: 78–79; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1464884911431538">Tumber, 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1464884911431538">Esser (1999)</xref> sees scandals as an indicator of the level of tabloidization of broadsheet newspapers. Scandals sell, especially those involving moral outrage over the behaviour of politicians in powerful positions. A second indicator of information versus entertainment journalistic style is the focus on the private life of politicians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1464884911431538">Brants and Neijens, 1998</xref>: 153). Purely information-oriented journalists will not cover the private life of politicians, but only portray them in their official function. On the other hand, in journalistic cultures where entertainment is more important, the private life of politicians gets more attention in the news (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1464884911431538">McNair, 2009</xref>). This leads to the following two hypotheses about the influence of cross-national differences in role conceptions on content:
<disp-quote>
<p>H4a The more entertainment oriented the role conceptions of political journalists in a country, the more news about national politics will focus on scandals.</p>
<p>H4b The more entertainment oriented the role conceptions of political journalists in a country, the more news about national politics will focus on the private life of politicians.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1464884911431538">
<title>Design</title>
<p>To test our expectations, a survey among political journalists is combined with a content analysis of political news in two broadsheet dailies from each of Denmark, Germany, the UK and Spain. The historical developments of the media in these four countries varied widely, resulting in different structural characteristics of these media systems today and different journalistic cultures. Spain belongs to the polarized pluralist media system, the UK to the liberal media system, and Germany and Denmark are respectively a large and a small country belonging to the democratic corporatist media system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1464884911431538">Hallin and Mancini, 2004</xref>). Studies of role conceptions among news journalists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1464884911431538">Köcher, 1986</xref>) have shown that journalistic roles vary between countries belonging to different media systems. One can therefore expect that role conceptions will also vary across the four countries in this study, which makes them suitable cases to study the relation between role conceptions and content cross-nationally.</p>
<sec id="section8-1464884911431538">
<title>Survey</title>
<p>To see how role conceptions vary across countries a survey was conducted among 425 political reporters in Denmark, Germany, the UK and Spain. Political journalists are defined as ‘journalists who report, analyze or give commentary on national politics’ and operationalized as the members of parliamentary press galleries or unions of parliamentary journalists. Newsrooms were contacted to update lists with members of these unions. Focusing on parliamentary journalists rather than general reporters gives the advantage of functional equivalence, since these journalists all report about similar sources: government and members of parliament. Between November 2007 and February 2009 the surveys were distributed in each of the four countries. Response rates of the targeted population were 31 per cent in the UK, 32 per cent in Germany, 57 per cent in Spain, and 74 per cent in Denmark.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1464884911431538">1</xref></sup> Checks of representativeness showed that the characteristics of the group of respondents match the characteristics of the research population well.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1464884911431538">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>Respondents answered five questions asking the level to which they agreed or disagreed with statements indicating different role conceptions, on a 5-point scale. Questions were translated into Danish, German, English and Spanish by native speakers and discussed with political and communication scientists from each of the four countries. Two questions measure a <italic>pragmatic versus sacerdotal</italic> role conception: (1) national politics is newsworthy by definition; and (2) mass media should report about national politics in full detail. Both Cronbach’s alpha (0.43) and bivariate correlations (r = 0.28) for these two questions were below acceptable levels.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1464884911431538">3</xref></sup> These two questions will be treated as separate dimensions of a pragmatic versus sacerdotal role conception and will not be combined into a summative index. The <italic>impartial–partisan</italic> index summed the score for the agreement with the statement that: (1) The medium I work for has a specific political colour which guides me in how to do my work; and (2) In the news section, my medium keeps a neutral position in partisan or policy disputes (reversely coded).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1464884911431538">4</xref></sup> The bivariate correlation of the two items is 0.42 across the four countries.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1464884911431538">5</xref></sup> The <italic>information–entertainment</italic> role was measured with one standard question used in journalism studies around the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1464884911431538">Weaver and Willnat, forthcoming</xref>). Factor analysis showed that the answers to these questions are indeed structured along these three factors, explaining respectively 20, 27 and 18 per cent of total variance.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1464884911431538">6</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1464884911431538">
<title>Content analysis</title>
<p>Newspaper content was analyzed for two constructed news weeks in the period 8 December 2007 until 8 February 2008.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1464884911431538">7</xref></sup> This period started a month after the national elections in Denmark, and finished one month before national elections in Spain. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1464884911431538">Riffe et al. (2005)</xref>, constructed weeks are more representative than consecutive days or randomly selected samples. Newspaper journalists had different role conceptions from television journalists, especially on the partisan dimension (see below, for similar findings see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson, 2004</xref>). Therefore, we compare the news content of two broadsheet newspapers per country with the role conceptions of print journalists. For each country two elite newspapers were included which are traditionally associated with a left and right political leaning:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1464884911431538">8</xref></sup> respectively <italic>Politiken</italic> (59 articles) and <italic>Jyllands-Posten</italic> (82) for Denmark, <italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic> (141) and <italic>Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</italic> (173) for Germany, <italic>The Guardian</italic> (80) and <italic>The Daily Telegraph</italic> (75) for the UK, <italic>El País</italic> (144) and <italic>ABC</italic> (147) for Spain. Elite newspapers are a common object of cross-national comparative research since they have comparable positions in the media markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1464884911431538">Benson and Hallin, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1464884911431538">Strömbäck and Shehata, 2007</xref>). Tabloid newspapers were not included since there is no Spanish tabloid. No regional or local newspapers were included, since secondary analysis of our survey data showed that the role conceptions of journalists working for these outlets were similar to journalists working for national newspapers.</p>
<p>We included all news items about national politics in the analysis.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1464884911431538">9</xref></sup> Editorials, opinion pieces and columns are not included since these are article types which are most likely to reflect the political leaning of the newspaper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1464884911431538">Tresch, 2009</xref>). Since the study addresses the relation between the role conceptions of political reporters and the content they produce, only news items appearing in the news section are included in the analysis.</p>
<p>Visibility of political news was operationalized as the proportion of stories on the front page which cover national politics (compared to the total number of stories on the front page). Coders coded whether the story was framed in terms of conflict (focusing on disagreement between politicians) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1464884911431538">De Vreese et al., 2001</xref>) or presented politics as a game (focusing on a politician winning or losing) to allow testing of Hypothesis 2b. For each article, coders coded the political affiliation and number of quotes for up to five national political actors (members of governments, members of parliament and other politicians) and the overall tone towards these actors. The presence of coverage bias was measured by comparing the visibility of political actors belonging to the largest left leaning and right leaning political party (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1464884911431538">Brandenburg, 2006</xref>). The presence of statement bias was measured by comparing the mean tone towards politicians of these two parties. The tone can range from positive (when the emphasis in the story is on the actor’s merits, successful solutions, solved problems or abilities) to negative (when the emphasis is on the actor’s failures, unresolved problems or inabilities). As in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1464884911431538">Brandenburg (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1464884911431538">Schuck and De Vreese (2008)</xref>, a scale was built measuring the mean tone, based on the news items in which politicians were evaluated either positively or negatively. The scale can range from −1 (when all evaluative statements about a political party were negative) to +1 (only positive evaluations). To test Hypothesis 4a, coders coded whether the main topic of the story was a scandal and the story involved allegations of wrongdoing, disgrace or moral outrage. Finally, the coders coded whether the news item focused on the private life of politicians rather than presenting them as political spokespersons.</p>
<p>Coders who were native speakers or had a high proficiency in one of the four languages coded the material. Before the start of the coding, coder-trainer tests were done on the level of the news item in the English working language to assess whether coders with different language background had sufficient understanding of the English codebook (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1464884911431538">Peter and Lauf, 2002</xref>). After the coding was finished, intercoder reliability tests were done for coder pairs in each of the four countries, with a sample of at least 10 per cent of the material. Intercoder reliability scores ranged from 0.70 for conflict and game framing in Spain to 0.97 for coverage of private life in Germany and the UK (Holsti’s method).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1464884911431538" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>To test Hypothesis 1, we ran regression models (not shown) to compare how much variance in role conceptions is explained by (1) the backgrounds of the journalist, (2) the type of news organization they work for, and (3) the country they work in. Regression models which only included individual characteristics of the journalists (gender, journalism education and professional experience) showed that the influence of these individual factors was negligible with a maximum explained variance (adjusted R<sup>2</sup>) of 2 per cent. When type of news organization was added to the regression model, the explained variance increased.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1464884911431538">10</xref></sup> For the information–entertainment role and the second pragmatic– sacerdotal role, including medium type led to a modest increase in explanatory power (3 to 5% of variance explained). For the impartial–partisan dimension, this increase was considerably higher, as explanatory power increased to 17 per cent in comparison to the model with background variables only.</p>
<p>When the country was added to the regression analysis including the background variables and medium type, the percentage of explained variance increased further to 14 per cent for the pragmatic–sacerdotal role, to 9 per cent for the information–entertainment role and to 33 per cent for the impartial–partisan role. In sum, including the country in the regression model led to the highest increase in explained variance, which is support for Hypothesis 1. In line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1464884911431538">Zhu et al. (1997)</xref>, we find that the country level has more influence on role conceptions than organizational or individual factors.</p>
<p>To classify the dominant role conceptions in each of the four countries under study, the mean scores of political journalists in these countries on the three scales are compared (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1464884911431538">Table 1</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1464884911431538">11</xref></sup> The regression analysis reported above showed that medium type did have an influence on role conceptions, especially on the impartial–partisan dimensions. Therefore cross-national differences in the roles of <italic>print</italic> journalists will be compared to newspaper content. For each of the three main dimensions, role conceptions differ cross-nationally. Danish and Spanish journalists have more sacerdotal conceptions of their role than British and German journalists. Spanish print journalists have a significantly more partisan role conception than their colleagues in northern Europe. British journalists attach most attention to providing entertainment. These cross-national differences in role conceptions will be compared to the dominant reporting style in political coverage in the four countries to test Hypotheses 2, 3 and 4.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1464884911431538" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Role conceptions of political journalists working for newspapers in Denmark, Germany, the UK and Spain.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1464884911431538" xlink:href="10.1177_1464884911431538-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Denmark</th>
<th align="left">Germany</th>
<th align="left">UK</th>
<th align="left">Spain</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Pragmatic (1) – sacerdotal (5)</td>
<td>3.35<sub>a</sub> (0.85)</td>
<td>2.71<sub>b</sub> (1.00)</td>
<td>2.66<sub>b</sub> (0.97)</td>
<td>3.73<sub>a</sub> (0.94)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Impartial (1) – partisan (5)</td>
<td>1.90<sub>a</sub> (0.83)</td>
<td>2.78<sub>b</sub> (0.80)</td>
<td>2.82<sub>b</sub> (1.00)</td>
<td>3.36<sub>c</sub> (1.04)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Information (1) – entertainment (5)</td>
<td>2.60<sub>a</sub> (1.04)</td>
<td>2. 94<sub>a</sub> (0.95)</td>
<td>3.34<sub>b</sub> (1.00)</td>
<td>2.14<sub>c</sub> (1.13)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic> (minimum)</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1464884911431538">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: Mean score on scales from 1 to 5 with standard deviations between brackets. Means in the same row that do not share subscripts differ at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 in the Tukey honestly significant differences comparison.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section11-1464884911431538">
<title>Pragmatic–sacerdotal</title>
<p>While the survey showed that both Spanish and Danish journalists have a more sacerdotal role conception than their colleagues in Germany and the UK, in the content only Spain stands out in comparison to the other three countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1464884911431538">Table 2</xref>). National politics is more visible in Spanish dailies than in broadsheets in northern Europe, especially for <italic>ABC</italic>, where more than 63 per cent of the stories on the front page deal with national politics. For the other indicators of a pragmatic versus sacerdotal reporting style, Spain also stands out. Spanish broadsheets have the smallest percentage of news stories using the conflict and the game frame, while the use of this frame hardly varies between Germany, Denmark and the UK. The differences in use of conflict frames and game frames between Spain and the other three countries are statistically significant (conflict: χ<sup>2</sup> = 75.269, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, df = 1; game χ<sup>2</sup> = 41.535, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, df = 1).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1464884911431538">12</xref></sup> In sum, partial support was found for Hypotheses 2a and 2b. On the basis of the three measures for a pragmatic versus sacerdotal reporting style, we can conclude that the sacerdotal role conception is reflected in the content in Spain, but not in Denmark.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1464884911431538" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Indicators of a pragmatic versus sacerdotal reporting style in coverage of national politics in Danish, German, British and Spanish broadsheet newspapers.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1464884911431538" xlink:href="10.1177_1464884911431538-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Visibility of national politics<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Style<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">% of stories<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1464884911431538">1</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>N</italic> (news items)</th>
<th align="left">Conflict frame<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1464884911431538">2</xref></sup> (%)</th>
<th align="left">Game frame<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1464884911431538">2</xref></sup> (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Denmark</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Politiken</italic></td>
<td>16</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Jyllands Posten</italic></td>
<td>32</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Germany</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>22</td>
<td>141</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Frankfurter Allgemeine zeitung</italic></td>
<td>27</td>
<td>173</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>UK</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Guardian</italic></td>
<td>29</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Daily Telegraph</italic></td>
<td>27</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Spain</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>El País</italic></td>
<td>34</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>ABC</italic></td>
<td>63</td>
<td>147</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1464884911431538">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: <sup>1</sup>Percentage of stories on front page (for 14 newspaper issues). <sup>2</sup>Percentage of news items which use conflict or game framing.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1464884911431538">
<title>Impartial–partisan</title>
<p>The survey showed that Spanish journalists have a more partisan role conception than their colleagues in northern Europe. To test whether this is reflected in the news content, the ways newspapers with different political profiles cover the largest left-wing and right-wing political party are compared. Looking at the visibility of different parties, we see no proof of a partisan bias in any of the four countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1464884911431538">Table 3</xref>). Within countries, left-wing newspapers and right-wing newspapers do not vary in their treatment of the largest party on the left and right side of the political spectrum. On the basis of Hypothesis 3a, one would expect Spanish newspapers to have a partisan coverage bias. This hypothesis is not supported.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1464884911431538" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Visibility of largest left-wing and right-wing party in Danish, German, British and Spanish broadsheet newspapers.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1464884911431538" xlink:href="10.1177_1464884911431538-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left"><italic>N</italic> (political actors)</th>
<th align="left">Attention for left-wing party<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1464884911431538">1</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">Attention for right-wing party<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1464884911431538">2</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Denmark</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Politiken</italic></td>
<td>135</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Jyllands Posten</italic></td>
<td>216</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Germany</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>272</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>356</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>UK</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Guardian</italic></td>
<td>196</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Daily Telegraph</italic></td>
<td>150</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Spain</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>El País</italic></td>
<td>320</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>ABC</italic></td>
<td>368</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>43</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1464884911431538">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: Attention for left-wing and right-wing party is the percentage of all political actors who belong to either the largest left-wing or right-wing party. <sup>1</sup>Left-wing parties: Denmark: Socialdemokraterne; Germany: SPD; UK: Labour; Spain: PSOE. <sup>2</sup>Right-wing parties: Denmark: Venstre; Germany: CDU/CSU; UK: Conservative; Spain: PP.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>A second way in which partisan role conception can be reflected in newspaper content is in the tone towards different political parties. Coders assessed for all political actors whether they were presented in a positive, neutral or negative context. In all countries and outlets, the presentation of most political actors was neutral, and if politicians were evaluated, this was mostly negatively. For each newspaper the tone towards the largest left-wing and right-wing party are compared (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1464884911431538">Table 4</xref>). The treatment of the largest left-wing and right-wing party varied significantly for Spanish newspapers <italic>El País</italic> and <italic>ABC</italic>. In Spain, partisanship manifested itself in a negative bias towards opposing parties, but not in a positive evaluation of the party with which these newspapers are aligned. Politicians belonging to (left-wing) PSOE receive almost neutral treatment in left-wing newspaper <italic>El País</italic>, while they are predominantly presented negatively in right-wing newspaper <italic>ABC</italic>. For politicians belonging to (right-wing) PP we see the opposite pattern. In newspapers in northern Europe there was no significant difference in tone towards left and right-wing politicians (independent sample t-tests). This was either due to a negative tone towards all politicians (in the British newspapers), an on average almost neutral treatment of both parties (for German newspaper <italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic>), or a low number of items in which politicians were evaluated (for Danish newspaper <italic>Politiken</italic>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1464884911431538" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Tone towards largest left-wing and right-wing party in Danish, German, British and Spanish broadsheet newspapers.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1464884911431538" xlink:href="10.1177_1464884911431538-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Left-wing party<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1464884911431538">1</xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Right-wing party<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1464884911431538">2</xref></sup><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">tone</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">tone</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Denmark</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Politiken</italic></td>
<td>0.0<sub>a</sub> (1.14)</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>−0.65<sub>a</sub> (0.79)</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Jyllands Posten</italic></td>
<td>−0.43<sub>a</sub> (0.94)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>−0.81<sub>a</sub> (0.60)</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Germany</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>−0.04<sub>a</sub> (1.02)</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>−0.32<sub>a</sub> (0.96)</td>
<td>41</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>−0.45<sub>a</sub> (0.93)</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>−0.78<sub>a</sub> (0.65)</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>UK</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Guardian</italic></td>
<td>−0.41<sub>a</sub> (0.92)</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>−0.75<sub>a</sub> (0.68)</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Daily Telegraph</italic></td>
<td>−0.56<sub>a</sub> (0.84)</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>−0.25<sub>a</sub> (1.04)</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Spain</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>El País</italic></td>
<td>+0.06<sub>a</sub> (1.01)</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>−0.78<sub>b</sub> (0.64)</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>ABC</italic></td>
<td>−0.71<sub>a</sub> (0.71)</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>+0.14<sub>b</sub> (1.00)</td>
<td>37</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1464884911431538">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: The mean tone towards a party is based only on news items in which politicians were evaluated either positively or negatively and can range from −1 (all evaluations negative) to +1 (all evaluations positive). Mean scores in the same row which do not share subscripts are significantly different at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (independent sample t-tests). <sup>1</sup>Left-wing parties: Denmark: Socialdemokraterne; Germany: SPD; UK: Labour; Spain: PSOE. <sup>2</sup>Right-wing parties: Denmark: Venstre; Germany: CDU/CSU; UK: Conservative; Spain: PP.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1464884911431538">
<title>Information–entertainment</title>
<p>The survey showed that British journalists stand out as the most entertainment oriented. The content analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1464884911431538">Table 5</xref>) shows that British journalists give more attention to scandals than journalists in Germany and Spain (χ<sup>2</sup> = 4.724, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), but not compared to Danes (χ<sup>2</sup> = 0.215, ns). For the second indicator (coverage of private life), ‘sleazy Britain’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1464884911431538">Canel and Saunders, 2006</xref>: 27) stands out in comparison to the three other countries. In all the Spanish coverage there was only one newspaper article featuring the private life of a politician. In Denmark and Germany there is only limited focus on politicians’ private lives. Differences between the UK and continental Europe are significant (χ<sup>2</sup> = 38.410, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). This supports Hypothesis 4b. Combining the coverage of scandals and politicians’ private lives, we can conclude that the UK stands out as most entertainment focused, which is in line with their role conceptions.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1464884911431538" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Coverage of scandals and the private life of politicians in Danish, German, British and Spanish broadsheet newspapers.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1464884911431538" xlink:href="10.1177_1464884911431538-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="left">Scandals<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1464884911431538">1</xref></sup> (%)</th>
<th align="left">Private life<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1464884911431538">1</xref></sup> (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Denmark</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Politiken</italic></td>
<td>82</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Jyllands Posten</italic></td>
<td>59</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Germany</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>141</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</italic></td>
<td>173</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>UK</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Guardian</italic></td>
<td>75</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>The Daily Telegraph</italic></td>
<td>80</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Spain</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>El País</italic></td>
<td>144</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>ABC</italic></td>
<td>147</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1464884911431538">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: <sup>1</sup>Percentage of news items which cover scandals or the private life of politicians.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1464884911431538" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This article studied the relation between cross-national differences in role conceptions and news content. The survey of political journalists showed that the role conceptions of political journalists vary more across countries than within countries. Spanish political journalists were most dissimilar from their colleagues in Denmark, Germany and the UK. They saw their role as sacerdotal rather than pragmatic and partisan rather than impartial. These distinct Spanish role conceptions were reflected in the reporting style of Spanish newspapers, where news about politics was more visible, less often framed in terms of conflict or as a game, and had a partisan tone towards politicians. British journalists stand out as most entertainment oriented, both in their role conceptions and the content they produce.</p>
<p>The distinct role conceptions of Spanish and British journalists resonate with the characteristics of the media systems they work in. The sacerdotal Spanish journalistic culture goes back to the democratic transition period where Spanish journalists felt it was their task to support the new democratic regime and to help the Spanish population ‘internalize fundamental norms of democratic behavior’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1464884911431538">Gunther et al., 2000</xref>: 51). The partisan role conceptions can be explained by the partisan cleavage in Spanish society, which is deeper than in other countries. This is reflected in audience segmentation along partisan lines and the need for journalists to compete over partisan audiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1464884911431538">Hallin and Mancini, 2004</xref>). A second reason is the less autonomous position of the Spanish journalists and, in particular, pressure from owners who want to use the media to have an impact on the political process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1464884911431538">De Miguel and Pozas, 2009</xref>). The commercial and competitive nature of the liberal media system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1464884911431538">McNair, 2009</xref>) is reflected in the entertainment orientation of British journalists. This is further support that role conceptions form a vital link between media systems and news content.</p>
<p>Differences between the three Northern European countries were not always reflected in the content. For example, the sacerdotal role conceptions of Danish journalists did not lead to more attention for political news and less conflict framing. These findings should be interpreted in acknowledgement of some limitations which may have influenced these results. First, while Spanish journalists are clearly outsiders, the cross-national differences in role conceptions and content between Denmark, Germany and the UK are not that strong. Future studies should compare the relation between roles and content by comparing countries with more distinct media systems and journalistic cultures. A second reason why relation between roles and content was less clear might be the intervening influence of other factors in the political system or political culture. Such alternative explanations are inherent in cross-national comparisons and can only be addressed by repeating this study and conducting similar studies in more countries. Thirdly, due to privacy concerns, it was not possible to assure that the journalists filling out the survey were exactly the same journalists as the ones who wrote the news items which were included in the content analysis. This is an increasingly common problem for journalism surveys as a result of stricter privacy rules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1464884911431538">Weaver and Löffelholz, 2008</xref>: 6). Other studies with a different design which combined roles and news decisions of the very same journalists have demonstrated stronger effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1464884911431538">Köcher, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1464884911431538">Patterson and Donsbach, 1996</xref>). A possible fourth limitation, inherent in any cross-national comparative content analysis, is the use of standardized measures in order to make findings in different countries comparable. As a trade off, this gives the disadvantage that indirect measures had to be used to classify the reporting style along the pragmatic–sacerdotal and the information–entertainment dimensions. Single country studies could observe the news values of certain stories more directly and study the characteristics of scandals which are covered more in depth. Not being able to do this complicated the comparative analysis. Future studies might compare the reporting style applied in covering concrete issues or scandals. Alternatively, we recommend that a more qualitative approach be taken, based on observations in news organizations, to see how news values are applied and how journalists decide which issues to cover (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1464884911431538">De Vreese, 2001</xref>). Such newsroom observations can provide more insight into the mechanisms through which role conceptions influence content.</p>
<p>While acknowledging these limitations, we believe that our comparative study has led to further insight into the differences in journalistic culture and to the importance of role conceptions as explanation for these differences. The finding that the role conceptions of Spanish journalists stand out in comparison to the roles of journalists in northern Europe, and that this is reflected in content, goes against criticism of the study of journalistic role conceptions by means of survey. Critics claim that when journalists are asked about their role, they give idealized answers which often reflect the Anglo-American journalistic model of critical, objective journalists, but bear little relation to actual work practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1464884911431538">Josephi, 2005</xref>). To some extent it may be true that when asked about their role conceptions, journalists do not describe their actual work practice, but rather pay ‘lip service’ to the researchers and give desirable answers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1464884911431538">Weischenberg et al., 2006</xref>: 98). However, this comparative survey has shown that what journalists expect researchers want to hear varies across journalistic cultures and represents different normative ideals. When asked about their role conception in this study, some Spanish journalists indeed saw their role to be impartial pragmatists. For these journalists, who do not follow the dominant role conceptions within their journalistic culture, there will be a wide gap between theory and practice. However, this article has shown that when the roles and content of Spanish journalists are seen <italic>in comparison</italic> to the roles and content of journalists in northern Europe, Spanish journalists adhere least to the Anglo-American watchdog model both in ideals (roles) as in practice (content). This shows that cross-national differences in journalistic culture remain relevant, despite homogenization of media systems and journalistic convergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1464884911431538">Hallin and Mancini, 2004</xref>). In this respect the findings presented in the article are in line with the conclusion of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson (2004</xref>: 267) that ‘Western news systems are more alike than different, although their differences are important and consequential.’</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We wish to thank Klaus Schönbach, Peter Bro, Jesper Strömbäck and two anonymous reviewers for helping us to improve the article.</p>
</ack>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1464884911431538">
<label>1</label>
<p>These response rates are comparable to other surveys among journalists (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1464884911431538">Shoemaker et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1464884911431538">Weaver and Willnat, forthcoming</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1464884911431538">
<label>2</label>
<p>For all countries representativeness was checked by comparing distribution of gender and medium type of the respondents with the target population of the survey. For Denmark, Germany and the UK the respondents were representative for the population in terms of gender distribution and type of medium they work for. Spain showed an under-representation of print journalists. This was taken into account in the analysis as medium type was included as one of the independent variables in the explanatory analysis. In the description of the role conceptions per country (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1464884911431538">Table 1</xref>), the role conceptions of print journalists only are compared.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1464884911431538">
<label>3</label>
<p>Cronbach’s alpha per country: Denmark 0.53, Germany 0.43, UK 0.40, Spain 0.62. Bivariate correlations per country: Denmark 0.36, Germany 0.28, UK 0.25, Spain 0.45.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1464884911431538">
<label>4</label>
<p>This dimension is closely related to the neutral-advocate dimension used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1464884911431538">Donsbach and Patterson (2004</xref>: 265), with the difference that in our study we are only interested in whether the journalists support a political party, while Donsbach and Patterson’s dimension also includes advocating a group or ideology.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1464884911431538">
<label>5</label>
<p>Bivariate correlations per country: Denmark 0.42, Germany, 0.29, UK 0.48, Spain 0.52. The scores for different media types were compared as an external validity check, showing that journalists working for press agencies scored lowest on this scale, while print journalists scored highest.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1464884911431538">
<label>6</label>
<p>The factor analysis used was a principal components analysis, with varimax rotation, using Kaiser Criterion to determine the number of factors. Factor analysis in each of the countries separately revealed the same three factors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1464884911431538">
<label>7</label>
<p>Since the <italic>Süddeutsche Zeitung</italic> did not have a Sunday edition, for the German newspapers the constructed news weeks consist of 12 issues. For the other newspapers the samples consisted of 14 issues. <italic>The Observer</italic> was included as Sunday edition of <italic>The Guardian</italic> and <italic>The Sunday Telegraph</italic> was included as Sunday edition of <italic>The Daily Telegraph</italic>. The weeks before and after Christmas were excluded from the sample as political activity was minimal during this period.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1464884911431538">
<label>8</label>
<p>Political leaning is meant here as the political profile which is expressed in the editorials, opinion pieces and columns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1464884911431538">Tresch, 2009</xref>) and visible in the political preferences of readers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1464884911431538">Seymoure-Ure, 1974</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1464884911431538">
<label>9</label>
<p>Because of privacy concerns it was not possible to match the response of journalists with news items on the individual level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1464884911431538">Weaver and Löffelholz, 2008</xref>: 6). News items about national politics were operationalized as items in which at least one of the following terms is mentioned within a national context: ‘parliament, government, minister, ministry and/or the name of a politician (member of parliament or member of government) and/or the name of a national political party or national party leader or member’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1464884911431538">
<label>10</label>
<p>To measure whether the medium in which journalists work influences their role conception, dummy variables for print, press agencies and commercial broadcasting were included in the analysis, with public service broadcasting as baseline.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1464884911431538">
<label>11</label>
<p>The pragmatic–sacerdotal dimension in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1464884911431538">Table 1</xref> is based on the question ‘Mass media should report about national politics in full detail’. Answers to the other question measuring a pragmatic–sacerdotal role conception did not differ cross-nationally. This question is therefore not reported.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1464884911431538">
<label>12</label>
<p>Country differences between use of conflict and game framing were not due to differences in story length. The German and Danish newspapers included relatively many short news items of fewer than 200 words. When short articles were excluded from the analysis the difference between Spain and the other countries remains significant.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Biographical notes</title>
<p><bold>Arjen van Dalen</bold> is Assistant Professor at the Centre for Journalism at the University of Southern Denmark. He wrote his PhD dissertation on Political Journalism in Comparative Perspective. His research interests are in comparative communication research, particularly journalistic cultures and the relations between journalists and politicians. He has published about these topics in <italic>The Global Journalists in the 21st Century</italic> (edited by David Weaver and Lars Willnat, forthcoming 2012) and journals such as the <italic>European Journal of Communication, Political Communication, The International Journal of Press/politics</italic> and <italic>Journalism Studies</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Claes H de Vreese</bold> is Professor and Chair of Political Communication and Scientific Director of the Amsterdam School of Communications Research in the Department of Communication Science at the University of Amsterdam. He is also Adjunct Professor of Political Science and Journalism at the University of Southern Denmark. He has published more than 75 articles in international peer-reviewed journals, including <italic>Communication Research, Journalism Studies, Political Communication, Journal of Communication, International Journal of Public Opinion Research, Public Opinion Quarterly, Scandinavian Political Studies, European Journal of Communication, West European Politics, EU Politics, Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly, Mass Communication &amp; Society</italic> and <italic>European Journal of Political Research</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Erik Albæk</bold> is Professor at the Centre for Journalism of the University of Southern Denmark. Professor Albæk has been visiting professor at MIT, Harvard University, Vilnius University (Lithuania), Potsdam University (Germany) and the University of Amsterdam. He has been chairman of the Danish Social Science Research Council and the Nordic Political Science Association. He has published articles in journals including: <italic>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly, Journalism, Political Communication, Journal of Communication</italic> and <italic>Party Politics</italic>.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Personalization of politics – towards a future research agenda. A critical review of the empirical and normative state of the art</article-title>. <source>Communication Yearbook</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>How states, markets and globalization shape the news: The French and US national press, 1965–97</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Communication</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blumler</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gurevitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>The Crisis of Public Communication</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brandenburg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Party strategy and media bias. A quantitative analysis of the 2005 UK election campaign</article-title>. <source>Journal of Elections, Public Opinion, and Parties</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brants</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neijens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The infotainment of politics</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breed</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>Social control in the newsroom: A functional analysis</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Canel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Morality Tales: Political Scandals and Journalism in Britain and Spain in the 1990s</source>. <publisher-loc>Cresskill, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hampton Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cappella</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Spiral of Cynicism: The Press and the Public Good</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>) <source>The Press and Foreign Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Governing with the News. The News Media as a Political Institution</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Culbertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Three perspectives on American journalism</article-title>. <source>Journalism Monographs</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>D’Alessio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Media bias in presidential elections: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Miguel</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pozas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Polarización ideological o económica? Relaciones entre los medios y el poder politico y corporativo</article-title>. [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Ideological or economical polarization? Relations between the media and political and corporate power</trans-title>]. <source>Viento Sur</source> <volume>130</volume>(Mayo): <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Vreese</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Election coverage – new directions for public broadcasting: The Netherlands and beyond</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Communication</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Vreese</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Semetko</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Framing politics at the launch of the Euro: A cross-national comparative study of frames in the news</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deuze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Journalists in the Netherlands: An Analysis of the People, the Issues and the (Inter-)National Environment</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aksant</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donsbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Psychology of news decisions: Factors behind journalists’ professional behavior</article-title>. <source>Journalism</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donsbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Journalists’ role perception</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Donsbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>The International Encyclopedia of Communication</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donsbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The global journalist. Are professional structures being flattened?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dobek-Ostrowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Głowacki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jakubowicz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sükösd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Comparative Media Systems. European and Global Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Budapest</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donsbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Political news journalists: Partisanship, professionalism, and political roles in five countries</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfetsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Comparing Political Communication: Theories, Cases, and Challenges</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Tabloidization of news: A comparative analysis of Anglo-American and German press journalism</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Communication</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dimensions of political news culture: Sound bite and image bite news in France, Germany, Great Britain, and the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Press/Politics</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfetsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2004</year>) <source>Comparative Political Communication. Theories, Cases, and Challenges</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>‘These crowded circumstances’: When pack journalists bash pack journalism</article-title>. <source>Journalism</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gunther</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wert</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The media and politics in Spain: From dictatorship to democracy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gunther</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mughan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Democracy and the Media: A Comparative Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Comparing Media Systems. Three Models of Media and Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanitzsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanusch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mellado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mapping journalism cultures across nations: A comparative study of 18 countries</article-title>. <source>Journalism Studies</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffstetter</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Bias in the News: A Study of Network Coverage of the 1972 Presidential Campaign</source>. <publisher-loc>Columbus</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ohio State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopmann</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vliegenthart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vreese</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albæk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Effects of election news coverage: How visibility and tone influence party choice</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Cross-national statistical research and the study of comparative politics</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>JWC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slawski</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>The News People: A Sociological Portrait of American Journalists and their Work</source>. <publisher-loc>Urbana</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Josephi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Journalism in the global age: Between normative and empirical</article-title>. <source>Gazette, the International Journal for Communication Studies</source> <volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Attitude-behavior relations: A meta-analysis of attitudinal relevance and topics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Köcher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Bloodhound or missionaries: Role definition of German and British journalists</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Communication</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McNair</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Journalism and democracy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wahl-Jorgensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanitzsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Handbook of Journalism Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Out of Order</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>A Knopf</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Political roles of the journalist</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Graber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McQuail</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Politics of News: the News of Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CQ Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donsbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>News decisions: Journalists as partisan actors</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lauf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Reliability in cross-national content analysis</article-title>. <source>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</source> <volume>79</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>815</fpage>–<lpage>832</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riffe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lacy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fico</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Analyzing Media Messages: Using Quantitative Content Analysis in Research</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weischenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Journalismus in der Gesellschaft. Theorie, Methodologie und Empirie</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Journalism in society: Theory, methodology, and empirical results</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Opladen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Westdeutscher Verlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schuck</surname><given-names>ART</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vreese</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Dutch no to the EU constitution: Assessing the role of EU skepticism and the campaign</article-title>. <source>Journal of Elections, Public Opinion &amp; Parties</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schudson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Sociology of News</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WW Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Semetko</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blumler</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gurevitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>The Formation of Campaign Agendas: A Comparative Analysis of Party and Media Role in Recent American and British Elections</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seymoure-Ure</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <source>The Political Impact of Mass Media</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Constable/SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Mediating the Message</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eichholz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Individual and routine forces in gatekeeping</article-title>. <source>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</source> <volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skovsgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albæk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vreese</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A reality check: How individual, professional, and organisational influences shape journalists’ conceptualisation of the objectivity norm</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the International Communication Association Conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Boston</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skovsgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albæk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vreese</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>forthcoming</year>) <article-title>Danish journalist</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willnat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Global Journalist in the 21st Century</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smelser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Comparative Methods in the Social Sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Uncertain Guardians: The News Media as a Political Institution</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The John Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Starck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soloski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Effect of reporter predisposition in covering controversial stories</article-title>. <source>Journalism Quarterly</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strömbäck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shehata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Structural biases in British and Swedish election news coverage</article-title>. <source>Journalism Studies</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>798</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strömbäck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Aelst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Exploring some antecedents of the media’s framing of election news: A comparison of Swedish and Belgium election news</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Press/Politics</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Political Scandal. Power and Visibility in the Media Age</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tresch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Politicians in the media: Determinants of legislators’ presence and prominence in Swiss newspapers</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Press/Politics</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tumber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Scandal and media in the United Kingdom: From Major to Blair</article-title>. <source>American Behavioral Scientist</source> <volume>47</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1122</fpage>–<lpage>1137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Löffelholz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Questioning national, cultural and disciplinary boundaries. A call for global journalism research</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Löffelholz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Global Journalism Research: Theories, Methods, Findings, Future</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilhoit</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>The American Journalist: A Portrait of US News People and their Work</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilhoit</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>The American Journalist in the 1990s: US News People at the End of an Era</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willnat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>forthcoming</year>) <source>The Global Journalist in the 21st Century</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beam</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brownlee</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voakes</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilhoit</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The American Journalist in the 21st Century: US News People at the Dawn of a New Millennium</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weischenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Die Souffleure der Mediengesellschaft: Report über die Journalisten in Deutschland</source>. [<trans-source xml:lang="en">The prompters of the media society. Report about journalists in Germany</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Konstanz</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UVK</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1464884911431538">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>V-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Individual, organizational, and societal influences on media role perceptions: A comparative study of journalists in China, Taiwan, and the United States</article-title>. <source>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</source> <volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>