<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BUL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spbul</journal-id>
<journal-title>NASSP Bulletin</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0192-6365</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1930-1405</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0192636512444715</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0192636512444715</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comparing the Contexts of Middle-Grade Schools, Their Instructional Practices, and Their Outcomes</article-title>
<subtitle>A Regression Discontinuity Approach</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Elias</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0192636512444715">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>Ronald H.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0192636512444715">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0192636512444715"><label>1</label>Hawaii Department of Education, Honolulu, HI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0192636512444715"><label>2</label>University of Hawaii at Manoa, Honolulu, HI, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0192636512444715">Ronald Heck, Department of Educational Administration, University of Hawaii at Manoa, 1776 University Avenue, Honolulu, HI 96822, USA Email: <email>rheck@hawaii.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>96</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">National Association of Secondary School Principals</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The purpose of this study is to describe an alternative means of estimating school effectiveness, referred to as an “absolute year” of schooling and demonstrate its usefulness as a measure of school effectiveness in the middle grades. More specifically, the study investigated (a) whether the absolute schooling effect in math and reading outcomes varied across a statewide sample of 53 secondary schools (e.g., middle, intermediate) and (b) whether differences in school variables explained the variability in the absolute-schooling effect.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>school effectiveness</kwd>
<kwd>middle schools</kwd>
<kwd>regression discontinuity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>External mandates such as No Child Left Behind (NCLB) and Race to the Top (RTTT) have increased the requirements for school accountability, heightened the expectations and standards for academic performance, and raised the stakes for the evaluation of teachers and principals. Shifting the responsibility for student outcomes from the state and district hierarchy to individual schools and their personnel implies that schools can be compared in valid, accurate, and equitable ways in terms of their contribution to student outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0192636512444715">Linn, Baker, &amp; Betebenner, 2002</xref>). Despite these federal mandates, the development of technically accurate and equitable large-scale assessments for evaluating and comparing schools has been challenging, especially given the wide diversity of school contexts and resources in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0192636512444715">Linn et al., 2002</xref>). NCLB holds schools with dissimilar student intake variables (e.g., socioeconomic status [SES], language background) to the same standards of accountability—even though it is well known that inequities in schools’ structures and practices (e.g., tracking, ability grouping, unequal access to college preparatory courses, and qualified teachers) reinforce and perpetuate societal inequities by negatively affecting the quality of educational experiences for some students and their resulting academic outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0192636512444715">Gamoran &amp; Ayalon, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0192636512444715">Hammond, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0192636512444715">Lee &amp; Burkam, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0192636512444715">Oakes, 1985/2005</xref>). With increased school-level accountability for outcomes, it is important therefore to continue to identify new ways of accurately and fairly measuring the effects of a particular school’s educational environment, practices, and personnel on student learning.</p>
<p>The purpose of this study is to present results comparing the effectiveness of schools serving middle-grade students (e.g., middle schools, intermediate schools) by using a relatively new approach for describing schools’ contribution to student learning outcomes. We focus on testing this alternative approach in schools serving students in the middle grades (Grades 6-8) since educational effectiveness in these types of schools has been less studied than in elementary schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0192636512444715">Heller, Calderon, &amp; Medrich, 2003</xref>). Although policy makers are quick to dismiss discussions of research methods as deflecting the central issue of educational accountability (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0192636512444715">Birnbaum, 2000</xref>), it is critical to provide valid comparisons of schooling effects since various student and school community inputs can be quite different (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0192636512444715">Hill &amp; Rowe, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0192636512444715">Linn &amp; Haug, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0192636512444715">Scheerens &amp; Bosker, 1997</xref>). The research design used in this study to estimate schools’ academic outcomes is referred to as <italic>regression discontinuity</italic> (RD) because of its focus on identifying the average difference, or discontinuity, in an outcome associated with individuals who are similar in every way except for whether or not they receive a particular treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0192636512444715">Shadish, Cook, &amp; Campbell, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0192636512444715">Trochim, 1984</xref>). RD is one way to assess the impact of a treatment in the absence of an experimental design by establishing a precise criterion for assigning participants to the treatment and control groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0192636512444715">Cahan &amp; Davis, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0192636512444715">Cook, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0192636512444715">Luyten, Peschar, &amp; Coe, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0192636512444715">Thistlethwaite &amp; Campbell, 1960</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0192636512444715">Trochim, 1984</xref>).</p>
<p>In applying this design to assess student learning progress, the treatment is defined as receiving an <italic>absolute</italic>, or added, year of schooling, which refers to the discontinuity (or change) in achievement that occurs as a result of being in a higher versus lower grade level (e.g., eighth vs. seventh grade). The assumption underlying this measure of effectiveness is that schools will likely differ in terms of the average amount of learning that takes place between successive grade levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0192636512444715">Cahan &amp; Cohen, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0192636512444715">Cahan &amp; Davis, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>). Our presentation of absolute-schooling effects as a means of comparing schools is based on preliminary research suggesting this may be a promising academic outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0192636512444715">Kyriakides &amp; Luyten, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0192636512444715">Luyten et al., 2008</xref>). One of the primary advantages of the approach is that it does not require accounting for differences in student background within schools before making comparisons between them. This makes it easy to apply in diverse school settings.</p>
<sec id="section1-0192636512444715">
<title>Background of the Study</title>
<p>School effectiveness research has attempted to link theory and empirical evidence to identify educational practices that can improve schools. At present, however, there are still a number of identified shortcomings that limit the usefulness of this research in producing practical knowledge that educators can directly implement in a strategic manner to improve academic outcomes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0192636512444715">Creemers &amp; Kyriakides, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0192636512444715">Opdenakker &amp; Van Damme, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0192636512444715">Scheerens &amp; Bosker, 1997</xref>). As Creemers and Kyriakides conclude, previous reviews of school effectiveness research have been diverse in their goals, varied in selectivity of their criteria for including studies, weak in their assessment of research designs, and inconsistent in the range of school factors examined for which little empirical support or theoretical relevance was provided.</p>
<p>First, it has been challenging to attribute causal effects to particular types of school structures and educational practices since it is difficult to undertake randomized experiments that might raise ethical concerns by excluding a group of students from attending particular types of schools or receiving specific instructional practices, especially with the availability of other simpler and more flexible methods to obtain the same information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0192636512444715">Cook, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0192636512444715">Shadish et al., 2002</xref>). Second, given this design issue, school effectiveness studies typically measure the <italic>added value</italic> of schools, often at one point in time. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0192636512444715">Hill and Rowe (1996)</xref> assert, however, adjusting student outcomes for differences in student inputs can lead to underestimating the school’s actual contribution to student outcomes. This is because part of the school’s effect may be diminished by statistically removing differences because of student background variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0192636512444715">Hill &amp; Rowe, 1996</xref>). As some have noted, the term <italic>school effect</italic> can actually be misleading since it represents the <italic>relative</italic> difference between schools. This means that the estimate of the outcome being examined depends on its variability across the other schools in the sample (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0192636512444715">Coe &amp; Fitz-Gibbon, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0192636512444715">Goldstein, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>). For example, if a district’s schools were all high producing, their relative effectiveness would appear diminished since all schools were performing well. Third, although comparisons based on individual students’ learning growth over time are often preferred over comparisons at one point in time because the former approach provides more valid information about learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0192636512444715">Hill &amp; Rowe, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0192636512444715">Sammons &amp; Luyten, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0192636512444715">Teddlie &amp; Reynolds, 2000</xref>), this type of extended data collection of a student cohort over time is more expensive than comparing successive sets of students and can also be problematic in estimating changes for schools where student mobility is high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0192636512444715">Christie, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>As a result of these identified limitations, recent research has focused primarily on building theory regarding various types of school factors that influence student achievement outcomes through using stronger research designs and identifying a more integrated set of school educational processes that lead to increased student outcomes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0192636512444715">Creemers &amp; Kyriakides, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0192636512444715">Opdenakker &amp; Van Damme, 2007</xref>). Opdenakker and Van Damme, for example, specified three types of school factors that influence student outcomes. These include the school’s <italic>context</italic> (e.g., its structure, size, facilities), its <italic>composition</italic> (i.e., including students’ backgrounds as well as the teaching and administrative staff), and its <italic>instructional practice</italic>. This latter set of factors includes the school’s educational framework (e.g., mission, goals), academic and social organization, work environment and climate (e.g., teacher collaboration regarding curriculum, teaching, and students), and school-community partnerships. In a recent meta-analysis of previous studies on school factors and academic outcomes, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0192636512444715">Creemers and Kyriakides (2008)</xref> found support for two overarching sets of process variables that influence student outcomes: those aimed at the <italic>instructional environment</italic> (e.g., providing support for special needs students, increasing teacher collaboration and professional development opportunities, establishing partnerships, developing values that support learning) and those that aimed directly at <italic>teachers’ classroom practices</italic> (e.g., improving the quality of teaching, enhancing opportunities to learn, managing the quantity of time spent without disruptions). It is expected that school-level strategic activity, facilitated by leadership, can “coordinate,” or filter, the range of individual activity at a lower level—especially since most of the variability in teacher effects appears to be within schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0192636512444715">Heck, 2009</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section2-0192636512444715">
<title>Describing the Use of Regression Discontinuity to Evaluate Schools’ Contribution to Learning</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0192636512444715">Scheerens (2012)</xref> recently argued that longitudinal designs (i.e., designs that include temporal conditions) are clearly the way ahead to further improve educational effectiveness studies. Our study represents an initial attempt to illustrate the concept of an absolute year of schooling, rather than the more familiar relative effect, in describing results for a sample of middle-grade schools using successive student cohorts rather than longitudinal cohorts. The design provides a strong, reliable alternative to the randomized experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0192636512444715">Pedhazur &amp; Schmelkin, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0192636512444715">Shadish et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0192636512444715">U.S. Department of Education, 2005</xref>). The RD design makes it possible to assess the impact of a treatment accurately by establishing the precise criteria for assigning students to the treatment and the control groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0192636512444715">Thistlethwaite &amp; Campbell, 1960</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0192636512444715">Trochim, 1984</xref>). Bias in the estimation of treatment effects can be avoided in the RD design, not because of the random assignment of subjects, but because the selection process is known beforehand and modeled as part of the results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0192636512444715">Pedhazur &amp; Schmelkin, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0192636512444715">Shadish et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Students are assigned to treatment and control groups strictly on the basis of a determined cut point on the particular covariate used for the assignment process. In initial school-effects studies, students have been assigned on the basis of their educational system’s age requirement to enroll in kindergarten (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>). Subjects above the cut point are assigned to the treatment group (i.e., the higher grade level), and those below are assigned to the control group. If it is shown that the age-outcome regression line is linear, and if the treatment has no effect on the outcome, a single regression line would be expected, with older students in each cohort likely performing higher in reading or math than younger students. Instead, if the treatment is effective (i.e., students assigned to the higher grade perform better), a discontinuity in the regression line would reflect the effect of the treatment, controlling for the assignment criterion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0192636512444715">Shadish et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>We specify the RD model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0192636512444715">Figure 1</xref>. The figure suggests the absolute-schooling effect describes the gap in achievement between seventh and eighth graders, controlling for students’ age months in relation to the date of the test (i.e., April). One of the primary advantages of the RD approach for comparing schools is that the estimated size of the absolute effect does not depend on the relative distribution of absolute effects in other schools; nor does it depend on schools’ demographic characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>). This makes it more equitable in comparing schools, since differences in student background variables typically make little difference in the size of the estimated absolute-schooling effect, in contrast to their often sizable effects in models assessing relative effectiveness. Another advantage is that the approach is more cost effective since it does not depend on longitudinal data collection but can yield unbiased treatment effects.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0192636512444715" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relationship between age and achievement</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0192636512444715">
<title>Research Focus on Middle Grades</title>
<p>Despite its adaptability for many research situations where true experiments are unfeasible, RD has only begun to be used as an alternative approach for comparing schools in terms of their effectiveness, with almost all existing studies taking place in Europe (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0192636512444715">Kyriakides, &amp; Luyten, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0192636512444715">Luyten et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0192636512444715">Luyten, Tymms, &amp; Jones, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0192636512444715">Sammons &amp; Luyten, 2009</xref>). The models and design used in this study represent an attempt to expand the scope of past studies on effectiveness in at least two ways. First, the study compares the effectiveness of middle-grade schools, which is important because these settings have been understudied in previous school effectiveness research. Second, it explores the RD design as an alternative approach for examining differences between schools in terms of their effectiveness in producing student outcomes.</p>
<p>Over the past several decades there has been considerable discussion about the adequacy of various school configurations for educating students between their elementary and high school years. For example, the middle school approach has been viewed as more directly addressing the social and academic needs of adolescents as they transition between the elementary setting, typically with one teacher per grade level, to the more complex, departmentalized instruction typical of the high school setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0192636512444715">Coladarci &amp; Hancock, 2003</xref>). Previous studies have noted that student achievement tends to dip after students transfer from elementary to middle, intermediate, or junior high school settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0192636512444715">Alspaugh, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0192636512444715">Gronna, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0192636512444715">Offenberg, 2001</xref>). In an attempt to solve various achievement and student engagement issues associated with middle-grade education, during the past decade many public school districts have again changed middle-level configurations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0192636512444715">Coladarci &amp; Hancock, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0192636512444715">Howley, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0192636512444715">Weiss &amp; Kipnes, 2006</xref>). Various configurations are used, although the sixth through eighth combination is generally favored, representing about 65% in one state estimate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0192636512444715">California Department of Education, 2008</xref>). Recent concern with academic outcomes for adolescents, however, has also brought some renewed interest in K-8 school settings (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0192636512444715">Arcia, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0192636512444715">Byrnes &amp; Ruby, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Research has also indicated that various school configurations for students in their middle years may not be differentiated by achievement levels, once a number of other educational process variables are considered in addition to more obvious differences in grade structure. In one recent study, for example, nonsignificant parameter estimates were observed between K-8 and middle schools, controlling for other types of process indicators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0192636512444715">Gomez, Marcoulides, &amp; Heck, 2012</xref>). This research suggests that major factors in determining student achievement included organizational values focused on achievement, a motivated staff, and strong school leadership, and not simply the structural configuration of the school or a change in its educational program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0192636512444715">Balfanz, Legters, West, &amp; Weber, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0192636512444715">Erb, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0192636512444715">Viadero, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0192636512444715">Weiss, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0192636512444715">Williams et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0192636512444715">Whitley, Lupart, &amp; Beran., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0192636512444715">Yecke, 2006</xref>). Critics have also noted that previous research on middle-grade education has not always used rigorous advanced statistical techniques to study such complex multivariate phenomena (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0192636512444715">Viadero, 2008</xref>); for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0192636512444715">Klump (2006)</xref> argued that there have been few previous large-scale studies explaining the relationships between the middle-school grade configuration and student achievement. Research, therefore, has not provided any definitive results that can provide clear direction for schools and districts to follow when establishing their grade configurations for students’ middle educational years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0192636512444715">Connolly, Yakimowski-Srebnick, &amp; Russo, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The study addresses two specific research questions:</p>
<list id="list1-0192636512444715" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>What is the average size of the effect of an absolute year of schooling on students’ reading and mathematics outcomes variables and does it vary across schools?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Do school-level instructional practices and structural characteristics (i.e., school type) explain variability in the size of the absolute-schooling effects among schools, net of contextual and other school characteristics?</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0192636512444715" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method and Analyses</title>
<sec id="section5-0192636512444715">
<title>Data</title>
<p>In the RD approach for estimating school outcomes, age is used as the criterion to assign individual students to the control (lower grade) and treatment (higher grade) groups. To be included in the study, an individual student had to be in the same grade as her or his peers as determined by age at kindergarten entry. The cutoff date for children entering kindergarten in this state was December 31. Students who were 5 years old by the December 31 school entry date of their cohort were assigned to the treatment group (Grade 8). Student who were 5 years old by the December 31 entry date of their cohort a year later were assigned to the control group (Grade 7). After students were assigned to their respective treatment and control groups, students’ age in months was centered on the month the state tests were administered (i.e., April). The premise for the RD approach is that the treatment effect should be most noticeable for students whose birthdays fall right around (i.e., on either side of) the school entry date (December 31) cut point.</p>
<p>The final data set consisted of 21,861 seventh and eighth graders (10,343 seventh graders and 11,518 eighth graders) who were in 53 public middle-grade schools (i.e., elementary or other; e.g., Grades K-8), intermediate (Grades 7-8), and middle (Grades 6-8). Fifty percent were female, 12% received English Language Learning (ELL) services, and 38.4% participated in the federal free/reduced lunch program (which served as a proxy for student SES). Students whose birth dates were missing or were identified as retained or accelerated were not included in the study (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0192636512444715">Luyten, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>We conducted follow-up analyses to determine whether there were any differences between the final sample and the initial sample.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0192636512444715">1</xref></sup> Missing data on other variables (less than 5%) were addressed using multiple imputation of missing values. This approach is effective in reducing parameter bias that is due to missing data. The approach proceeds by generating random plausible values based on information from similar individuals based on patterns of missing data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0192636512444715">Peugh &amp; Enders, 2004</xref>). A total of five separate databases including plausible values were generated and the results were found to be consistent across all data sets.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0192636512444715">
<title>Variables in the Models</title>
<sec id="section7-0192636512444715">
<title>Student Variables</title>
<sec id="section8-0192636512444715">
<title>Math and reading outcomes</title>
<p>Students’ scaled scores on the Stanford Achievement (SAT) in math and reading were used as measures of student outcomes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0192636512444715">
<title>Grade level</title>
<p>This variable is simply an indicator of the added-year effect, with students who were in seventh grade (control) coded 0, and students in the eighth grade (treatment) coded 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0192636512444715">
<title>Age</title>
<p>Age represents the transformed measure of the student’s age in relation to birth month and the April SAT administration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0192636512444715">
<title>Student SES</title>
<p>Students eligible for free or reduced lunch (low SES) were coded 1, and those who did not participate in the free/reduced lunch program were coded 0.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0192636512444715">
<title>Female</title>
<p>Gender was coded as 1 = female and 0 = male.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0192636512444715">
<title>English Language Learner</title>
<p>Students who received English language services were coded 1, and those who did not receive services were coded 0.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0192636512444715">
<title>School Variables</title>
<p>The school variables included in our models were operationalized from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0192636512444715">Opdenakker and Van Damme’s (2007)</xref> framework of school factors that affect academic outcomes. These factors include composition (e.g., student and staffing variables), context (e.g., grade configuration, size), and instructional practice. The subscales comprising the instructional practice factor were consistent with their description of instructional practice as consisting of the school’s educational framework (e.g., mission, goals), academic and social organization, work environment and climate, and school-community relationships.</p>
<sec id="section15-0192636512444715">
<title>Instructional practice</title>
<p>We operationalized school instructional practice from five subscales (each of which had 10 items) describing the extent to which each school has educational programs that are aligned to state curriculum standards, seeks ways to implement programs that promote student achievement over time, has a well-developed range of academic and social support services for students, and has a professional teaching staff well qualified for assignments and responsibilities and committed to the school’s purpose.</p>
<p>State survey data were used to develop a weighted factor score (<italic>M</italic> = 0, <italic>SD</italic> = 1) composed of the domains describing the perceived quality of schools’ instructional practices. Higher factor scores suggest more favorable stakeholder perceptions about the quality of the school’s instructional practices. The survey is regularly administered at 2-year intervals to all certificated staff, all Grade 5 students, and a random sample of parents (i.e., approximately 20% across grade levels) in each school. The 50 items used to describe the five subscales were measured on 5-point Likert-type scales and expressed as the percentage of positive agreement with each statement.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0192636512444715">2</xref></sup> The specific subscales included (a) teacher practices in monitoring student progress, (b) school academic expectations for student achievement, (c) classroom emphasis on academic instruction, (d) school climate, and (e) relationships between the school and home. The factor loadings on the instructional practice factor were all substantial (ranging from 0.88 to 0.96), and the factor accounted for 86% of the variance among the observed subscales. This indicated strong correspondence between the underlying dimension and its observed indicators. These process indicators have been found in previous research to be reliable (as estimated by Cronbach’s alpha) and valid in terms of differentiating elementary schools according to their student achievement levels and growth for the type of student cohorts examined in this study (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0192636512444715">Heck, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>For <italic>teacher practices in monitoring student progress</italic> (10 items, α = .83), example items included the extent to which teachers evaluate student academic problems, provide feedback to students and parents, set homework expectations, are prompt in evaluating homework, maintain adequate grading practices, use varied means of evaluating progress, and maintain appropriate standards for class behavior. For <italic>school expectations regarding student achievement</italic> (10 items, α = .84), example items included expectations for student learning, the relative curricular emphasis on developing a wide range of academic skills, the extent to which challenging academic work is valued, and communication regarding expected student learning goals. For <italic>classroom emphasis on academic instruction</italic> (10 items, α = .86), example items included how teachers use class time (e.g., primarily for instruction, maximize students’ instructional time on task); the extent to which teachers use varied instructional strategies (e.g., cooperative learning, peer tutoring, computers), provide help for students who are having difficulties, and engage students actively in participating in class activities; and the extent to which teachers continually assess their instruction to refine teaching, collaborate with peers to develop and refine the academic curriculum, and regularly participate in professional development regarding instruction. For <italic>school climate</italic> (10 items, α = .89), example items included maintaining a safe environment, having clean and comfortable buildings, having personnel that demonstrate caring attitudes, having students with positive attitudes about the school, and feelings of togetherness at the school. Finally, for relationships between the <italic>school and parents</italic>, (10 items, α = .90), example items included having open communication processes, having regular communication with the home, making parents feel welcome at school, seeking parent involvement in decision making, and having parents involved in school activities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0192636512444715">
<title>Student composition</title>
<p>Student composition was a factor score (<italic>M</italic> = 0, <italic>SD</italic> = 1) consisting of a weighted combination of the percentage of students in the school receiving free/reduced lunch, ELL services, and special education (SPED) services. Larger positive scores indicate schools with higher percentages of students receiving these types of academic support services.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0192636512444715">
<title>Student stability</title>
<p>Student stability was a standardized measure (<italic>M</italic> = 0, <italic>SD</italic> = 1) describing the proportion of students who remained at the school for the entire year.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0192636512444715">
<title>Large school</title>
<p>Schools with student enrollments of 850 or greater were coded as large schools (1) and schools with enrollments of 849 or fewer students were coded 0.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0192636512444715">
<title>Middle</title>
<p>Middle schools (<italic>N</italic> = 19) consisted of schools with a sixth-, seventh-, and eighth-grade configuration (coded 1). Other school types (<italic>N</italic> = 34) were coded 0 (e.g., intermediate, Grades 7-8). This latter school type also included a few K-8 or K-12 schools that were primarily in rural areas of the state.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0192636512444715">3</xref></sup> We noted in preliminary analyses that middle schools had stronger perceived levels of instructional practice than other types of middle-grade school settings. We tested an interaction term for middle school and the quality of instructional practice but found that it was not significant in explaining achievement effects.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0192636512444715">
<title>Staff stability and staff experience</title>
<p>We also examined staff stability (i.e., the percentage of teachers who have been at a particular school for at least 5 years) and staff experience (average years of teaching experience) but found that both were not significant in explaining outcomes, so they were not included in the final models in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0192636512444715" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Standardized Model Estimates</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0192636512444715" xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="center">Read M1</th>
<th align="center">Read M2</th>
<th align="center">Math M1</th>
<th align="center">Math M2</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Intercept model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intercept</td>
<td>−0.126<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.031<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.186<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.089<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Instructional practices</td>
<td/>
<td>0.042<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>0.049<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Middle school</td>
<td/>
<td>0.160<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>0.170<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Student composition</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.292<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−0.302<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Student stability</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.030</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.036</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Large school</td>
<td/>
<td>0.003<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td/>
<td>0.211<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−.107<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> English Language Learning services</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.251<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low socioeconomic status</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.455<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−0.412<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Grade model</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Grade</td>
<td>0.229<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.222<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.286<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.259<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Grade × Student composition</td>
<td/>
<td>0.058<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Grade × Middle school</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.075<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Grade × Large school</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.003<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Grade × Student stability</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.055<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Level 2 variance (Intercept)</td>
<td>0.081<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.017<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.095<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.029<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Level 1 variance (Intercept)</td>
<td>0.892<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.829<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.864<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.826<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Level 2 variance (Grade)</td>
<td>0.006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.014<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
<td>0.012<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0192636512444715">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> −2 Log likelihood</td>
<td>58303.19</td>
<td>56681.17</td>
<td>57651.50</td>
<td>56628.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Parameters estimated</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intercept <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Level 2</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Level 1</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.08</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0192636512444715">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0192636512444715">
<title>Steps in the Regression Discontinuity Analyses</title>
<p>The RD design can produce an unbiased causal inference, provided certain assumptions are met (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0192636512444715">Trochim, 1984</xref>). First, it is assumed that students are assigned to groups correctly according to the agreed-on cut score (i.e., the age at school entry date). Second, it is assumed that the pattern of the assignment criterion has been specified correctly by the statistical model used; that is, the treatment effect must be modeled correctly with respect to the assignment criterion (i.e., age) and the dependent variable (i.e., achievement). Finally, it is assumed that there is no coincidental factor at the chosen cut score that would result in the observed schooling effect.</p>
<p>The preliminary step in an RD analysis is to determine the functional relationship between the assignment criterion (age) for the treatment variable and the outcome. A linear relationship is assumed. If the relationship turns out to be nonlinear (i.e., requiring quadratic or cubic terms), the analysis may result in biased treatment effects. Preliminary analyses, however, indicated there were no significant higher order age effects or treatment-age interactions. The first model for each outcome addresses the transformed age variable (centered on the month the test is given) and treatment (grade) effect. At the student level (Level 1), the model is as follows:</p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0192636512444715">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0192636512444715">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>age</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>grade</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0192636512444715" xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
<p>The size of the slope coefficient β<sub>2<italic>j</italic></sub> determines whether there is a statistically significant effect of an absolute year of schooling. At the school level (Level 2) there are two random parameters, the intercept and the absolute-schooling (or grade) slope:</p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0192636512444715">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0192636512444715">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>00</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0192636512444715" xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0192636512444715">
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-0192636512444715">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>20</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0192636512444715" xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
<p>At Level 2, the intercept model (Equation 2) determines whether there is significant variability in the achievement levels of the control group (i.e., seventh-grade scores) across schools. This information is contained in the random parameter (<italic>u</italic><sub>0<italic>j</italic></sub>). In the slope model (Equation 3), the random effect <italic>u</italic><sub>2<italic>j</italic></sub> addresses whether there is significant variability in the size of the absolute-schooling effect across schools. We note in passing that we determined the age effect did not vary across schools, so we fixed it at the school level (i.e., β<sub>1<italic>j</italic></sub> = γ<sub>10</sub>) by removing the random parameter (<italic>u</italic><sub>1<italic>j</italic></sub>).</p>
<p>The final models presented for math and reading in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> provide adjusted estimates of intercepts, absolute-schooling effects, and variances after controlling for student-level and school-level variables. Possible effects of school-level variables on reading or math intercepts (Equation 2) represent differences in school outcomes for seventh-grade students in the model. Possible differences in the absolute-schooling outcomes (Equation 3) are represented as cross-level interactions between the predictor and the absolute-schooling effect. This latter analysis would describe whether particular school variables were responsible for variation in the size of absolute effects for eighth graders. For the final models, we retained only the significant interactions between school-level predictors and absolute-schooling effects. In testing the school-level effects on the intercept and absolute-schooling outcomes, we provide significance tests at both the <italic>p</italic> = .10 and <italic>p</italic> = .05 levels because there were only 53 schools in our statewide sample.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0192636512444715" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section23-0192636512444715">
<title>Model 1: Age and Treatment Effects on Outcomes</title>
<p>We present our model results with the coefficients standardized, which facilitates comparing the relative strength (or effect sizes) of the variables on student outcomes since they are transformed to have the same scale of measurement. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref>, Model 1 provides the treatment (grade) and age effects on achievement. The intercept can be interpreted as the standardized score for an individual when the predictors are equal to zero. In this case, the intercept represents the standardized mean scaled scores of seventh-grade (grade = 0) students who were born in April (i.e., the month the tests were administered = 0). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> suggests that student age affected both reading (γ = 0.016) and math (γ = 0.016) scores significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05), suggesting that students born earlier in the year do better on average than students born later in the year. More specifically, for every month increase in age, achievement scores increased by about 0.02 of a standard deviation (<italic>SD</italic>). The grade coefficient of 0.229 for reading and 0.286 for math describes the achievement growth in <italic>SD</italic> units between seventh and eighth grades. This suggests the effect size of an additional year of schooling was about 0.23 <italic>SD</italic> in reading and about 0.29 <italic>SD</italic> in math. These effects are consistent with typical student growth observed between Grades 7 and 8 on six nationally normed tests in reading and math in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0192636512444715">Bloom, Hill, Black, &amp; Lipsey, 2008</xref>). More specifically, Bloom et al. found that student growth between Grades 7 and 8 on commonly used achievement tests (including the SAT) averaged about 0.26 <italic>SD</italic> in reading and 0.32 <italic>SD</italic> in math.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> also presents the tests of randomly varying grade and achievement effects across schools in the sample. Both intercepts and added-year slopes were found to vary significantly across schools (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). Since significant variation in intercepts and grade slopes exists between schools for both the math and reading models, developing school-level models to explain this variability was warranted. Finally, as we might expect, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> suggests that the age and added-year effects only accounted for modest variation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) in math and reading outcomes at the student and school levels.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0192636512444715">
<title>Model 2: Adding Predictors to Explain Achievement and Treatment Effects</title>
<p>Our final models presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> add the student demographic controls as well as the set of school-level variables (e.g., student composition, staffing, school type, enrollment, instructional practices). Keep in mind that we included a more limited set of school indicators in our models since our school sample size was relatively small. We also tested for possible cross-level interactions between the school indicators and absolute-schooling slopes, but we only retained those interactions that were statistically significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .10 or lower in our final models.</p>
<p>After adding the covariates, Model 2 indicates the absolute-schooling effects were only slightly reduced in size (i.e., 0.22 <italic>SD</italic> in reading and 0.26 <italic>SD</italic> in math, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). We also noted that the correlation between the adjusted absolute-schooling effect and the intercept was substantial for math (<italic>r</italic> = .56, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, not tabled). In contrast, however, the correlation between the absolute-schooling effect and the intercept was considerably weaker in reading (<italic>r</italic> = 0.25, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, not tabled). This suggests greater school-level consistency for math outcomes across grade levels than for reading outcomes.</p>
<p>Regarding the intercept model (which describes seventh-grade scores), as we might suspect, schools with more challenging student composition (as indicated by students requiring special academic services) had lower standardized achievement outcomes in reading and math (−0.292 and −0.302, respectively, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). School variables affecting seventh-grade achievement levels in reading and math included instructional practice (0.042 and 0.049, respectively, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) and middle school (0.160 and 0.170, respectively, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). For the quality of schools’ instructional processes, an increase in perceived quality of 1 <italic>SD</italic> would result in an achievement increase of about 0.05 <italic>SD</italic> in reading or math. This can be considered a small effect. However, we should keep in mind that since students only grow on average somewhere between 0.2 and 0.3 <italic>SD</italic> in reading and math between Grades 7 and 8, school-level effects can actually be more substantial than they seem.</p>
<p>Because the standardized effects on seventh-grade achievement levels due to attending a middle school were substantively meaningful, we followed up with RD analyses that also included our sample’s sixth-grade achievement results (not tabled). First, we observed no differences in levels of sixth-grade achievement in math and reading between students in the study who attended middle schools versus other types of schools. This result suggested students in our sample were relatively similar in math and reading achievement at Grade 6. Second, we noted a significant absolute-schooling effect for students attending middle schools versus others schools between Grades 6 and 7. More specifically, this result indicated that students who entered middle schools at Grade 6 experienced larger absolute-schooling effects between sixth and seventh grade than students in other school configurations. This result accounted for the fact that students in middle schools started seventh grade with higher achievement levels in reading and math compared with their peers in schools with other grade configurations, as summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> (see Model 2). To illustrate, we summarize these achievement relationships over three grade levels for math in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0192636512444715">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0192636512444715" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Differences in math achievement between middle schools and schools with alternative grade configurations over time</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Turning to the absolute-schooling (or added year) effects in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref>, we retained two significant cross-level interactions (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10) in each model. We can think of such interaction effects as tests of parallel regression lines; that is, a significant interaction suggests that the size of the treatment effect is systematically different for students in specific types of school settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0192636512444715">Moss &amp; Yeaton, 2006</xref>) while a nonsignificant result suggests the treatment effect is the same (or parallel) in each type of school setting. More specifically, with respect to added-year reading effects, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0192636512444715">Table 1</xref> suggests that the size of the average reading effect (0.222) was enhanced by almost 0.06 for students attending schools 1 <italic>SD</italic> above the mean in student composition (i.e., students requiring special academic services) compared with their peers in schools at the grand mean. In contrast, the added-year effect was smaller for students in middle schools compared with students in other school configurations (−0.08). This suggests that in middle schools, the overall positive achievement advantage for eighth-grade students because of attending this type of school was about half the size of what it was for seventh graders (0.16 + [−0.08] = 0.08)]. For treatment effects in math, we retained significant interactions for school size and student stability. In the case of student stability, the results indicated that eighth-grade students in schools with a more stable student population had enhanced achievement results in math (0.26 + 0.06 = 0.32) compared with their peers in schools at the grand mean for stability. We also noted positive absolute-schooling effects in math and reading related to enhanced middle school instructional practices (0.03, not tabled) compared with other school types, but these results were not statistically significant.</p>
<p>Middle schools also had larger growth in math between Grades 7 and 8 than other types of middle-grade schools (not tabled), but the results were not statistically significant. When we combine seventh-grade achievement and absolute-schooling effects by grade configuration, we obtain somewhat different results. We illustrate the correspondence between seventh-grade math outcomes and absolute-schooling effects for middle schools versus other schools in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0192636512444715">Figure 3</xref>. As the figure suggests, the strength of the relationship between seventh-grade math outcomes and absolute-schooling effects was statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) and considerably stronger in middle schools compared with other middle-grade schools (i.e., <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .30 vs. .03, respectively). This implies greater continuity in math outcomes, as well as greater observed effectiveness, among middle schools compared with other grade configurations (e.g., intermediate, K-8). To illustrate, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0192636512444715">Figure 3</xref>, lower absolute-schooling effects appear to describe other school configurations more frequently than middle schools.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0192636512444715" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relationship between seventh-grade math achievement levels and absolute-schooling effects between middle schools and other middle-grade configurations</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0192636512444715-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0192636512444715" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion and Implications</title>
<p>In the article, we proposed an alternative approach for comparing schools’ contributions to student learning. We had two primary goals in undertaking this research. First, we wanted to determine whether an absolute-schooling effect might be a useful way of differentiating the performance of schools in terms of their effectiveness. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0192636512444715">Sammons and Luyten (2009)</xref> argue, it is often useful to distinguish between <italic>school</italic> effects, which typically focus on the relative differences in achievement between schools in a sample, and <italic>schooling</italic> effects, which represent the effect of an absolute (or additional year) effect of schooling. More specifically, in the case of school effects, if all the schools in a sample are similar, their relative effects on outcomes may be underestimated.</p>
<p>Our results provide support of the premise that the RD design represents a viable alternative for making comparisons between schools in terms of the <italic>absolute</italic> size of the effect of an additional year of schooling on student-learning outcomes. Second, we wanted to apply this alternative approach to study schools that serve early adolescents (age 12-14 years) and determine whether differences in the size of their absolute-schooling effects could be explained by other types of school context, composition, and because the achievement of U.S. eighth-grade students on international tests of math and science (i.e., Trends in International Mathematics and Science Study [TIMSS], Program for International Student Assessment [PISA]) is average at best (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0192636512444715">National Center for Educational Statistics, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>At least three conclusions can be drawn from this study. First, the study reveals the potential for the RD approach to identify an absolute-schooling effect. We found that the reading and math absolute-schooling effects produced varied significantly across schools in the study. The average size of the absolute effects in this study (0.2-0.3 SD) were consistent with Hill et al.’s (2008) estimates of average student progress between Grades 7 and 8 on several commonly used standardized tests. This helped us validate the size of expected effects for students in middle grades (i.e., student gains between grade levels are typically largest in primary grades [0.8-0.9] and diminish gradually during upper elementary years [0.4-0.5]). Examining absolute-schooling effects appeared more equitable since adjustments for student background (i.e., social class, gender, students requiring special academic services) only marginally affected the size of the estimated effects. This provides considerable support for the fairness of this type of measure in examining individual student progress. This first result holds promise for school effectiveness research because differences between schools in their absolute effects can be more fairly and accurately estimated based on the quality of their <italic>educational efforts</italic> and not primarily on their social composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0192636512444715">Creemers &amp; Kyriakides, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Second, not only do our results reveal that schools differed in terms of the size of their absolute effects, but they also suggest the importance of identifying school factors that explain variation in levels of academic outcomes as well as absolute-schooling effects. More specifically, previous research has consistently determined that student background (e.g., SES, language, ethnicity, prior achievement) affects levels of student achievement (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0192636512444715">Bosker &amp; Scheerens, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0192636512444715">Sammons, Nuttall, &amp; Cuttance, 1993</xref>). Similarly, in our intercept models, we noted that school context and composition indicators were related to seventh-grade levels of math and reading achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0192636512444715">Bosker &amp; Scheerens, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0192636512444715">Davison, Seo, Davenport, Butterbaugh, &amp; Davison, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0192636512444715">Lee &amp; Bryk, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0192636512444715">Sammons et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0192636512444715">Willms &amp; Raudenbush, 1989</xref>). We also identified several school factors that were related to absolute-schooling effects. These included differences related to student stability, student composition, school type, and school size. Regarding student stability, since the cross-level interaction between student stability and the absolute-schooling effect was significant and positive, it suggests that in schools with higher student stability, student change between seventh and eighth grades was enhanced compared with student change in schools that were more average in student stability. This should not be surprising since math is a subject primarily learned in school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0192636512444715">Cohen, Raudenbush, &amp; Ball, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0192636512444715">Konstantopoulos, 2006</xref>). Student mobility, therefore, negatively affects student academic achievement in math.</p>
<p>We also noted differences in the levels of seventh-grade outcomes because of school type (i.e., middle school vs. other configurations). More specifically, in our intercept model, middle schools produced significantly stronger reading and math outcomes among seventh graders than other school configurations. The absolute-schooling results were more complex to interpret. As we noted, in the absolute-schooling effect model, interactions between school factors and the added-year (grade level) effects can be considered as tests of parallel slopes. For example, the significant, negative interaction (Middle school × Grade) suggests some of this initial middle-school advantage in reading outcomes at Grade 7 diminished among eighth graders. In contrast, the lack of interaction in math suggests eighth graders in middle schools maintained the advantage observed among seventh graders (as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0192636512444715">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0192636512444715">3</xref>). Because the students in the two types of schools had similar outcomes at Grade 6, the timing of student transitions (i.e., after Grade 5 for middle-school students and after Grade 6 for intermediate school students) may also affect the observed results in various ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0192636512444715">Gronna, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>Our analyses also indicated that schools with stronger instructional practices had higher levels of seventh-grade outcomes in reading and math. Even though this advantage did not increase between seventh and eighth grade (i.e., as indicated by the lack of a statistically significant cross-level interaction), it remained parallel since eighth-grade reading and math scores were also higher in schools with stronger perceived instructional practices compared with schools at the grand mean for instructional practices. This result suggests the importance of monitoring schools’ instructional processes (e.g., academic environment, commitment and implementation of curricular and instructional focus, student support system) over time since they appear to be related to differences in achievement outcomes. We noted in preliminary analyses that middle schools had stronger perceived instructional practices than schools with other types of grade configurations. Even though we could not find a statistically significant interaction between school type and instructional practice and its impact on outcomes, the absolute-schooling effects in middle schools with stronger instructional practices were in the hypothesized direction, and we surmise that we did not have enough statistical power to detect this effect in our relatively small sample of middle-grade schools.</p>
<p>Third, the present study also helps us describe potential theoretical linkages between school context and student composition, mediating school processes such as the quality of schools’ instructional practices, and improved student outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0192636512444715">Opdenakker &amp; Van Damme, 2007</xref>). These findings are potentially important since issues, such as common core curriculum, teacher effectiveness tied to salary and tenure, and the impact of strategic leadership actions in order to improve instructional practices are at the center of school improvement (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0192636512444715">Creemers &amp; Kyriakides, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0192636512444715">Heck &amp; Hallinger, 2009</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section26-0192636512444715">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>Our findings are also important for practitioners and policy makers since the results provide evidence that school context and social composition do not really matter as much when the focus is on absolute-schooling effects. The results provide some evidence that middle schools yield higher outcomes in math and reading outcomes than other middle-grade settings after considering students’ sixth-grade academic years. In this state where the study was conducted, adolescents in other types of schools may be better served academically if they were to be in middle schools (given local contextual factors). This is probably the most important implication for policy that comes from this study. Although we noted that middle schools had higher perceived instructional practices than other types of middle-grade schools, as reported by parents, teachers, and students, it remains unknown from these data what characteristics and day-to-day practices of middle schools may contribute to higher observed achievement outcomes.</p>
<p>Further study about school characteristics and practices that make achievement results in middle schools higher than those in non–middle schools would therefore be recommended. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0192636512444715">Hill (2007)</xref> noted that middle-school math teachers with stronger preparation in math coursework had higher mathematical knowledge for teaching. However, teacher knowledge was inequitably distributed across groups of students. Certain school systems in the United States have closed middle schools and reverted to other grade-level configurations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0192636512444715">Beane &amp; Lipka, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0192636512444715">Weiss &amp; Kipnes, 2006</xref>). Therefore, it is critical to have more empirically based studies to add to the few studies on middle school academic effectiveness. Further investigation into their particular internal organizations and instructional environments (e.g., parent support, student engagement, school climates) may provide additional evidence about why middle schools appear to achieve greater effects on student outcomes and provide future directions for studies of middle school effectiveness.</p>
<p>Importantly, the results of this study point toward greater validity and equity in comparing schools for accountability purposes when absolute-schooling effects are included as indicators of school effects, rather than solely relying on raw student achievement levels or percentages of students who meet proficiency targets. More specifically, the focus on raw achievement levels does not acknowledge the diversity present among schools and mandates that all students and all schools be held to the same expectations. Absolute-schooling effects and growth models appear to reduce bias in estimating school outcomes because of differences in student background. Despite the relative complexity of this approach, estimating the absolute effect of schooling on student outcomes provides researchers, policymakers, parents, and students with a very understandable measure of a school’s effectiveness. Since the absolute-schooling estimate does not depend on other schools in the sample, it means that any difference above the age effect is due to the treatment effect or solely the effect of that school. This is why the size of the absolute effect was found to vary between schools. Therefore, this approach provides policymakers a viable and understandable measure in making fair comparisons between schools regarding their effectiveness in producing student outcomes. Hence, using the RD approach would allow school personnel to be held more accountable for student outcomes and also for having structures and instructional practices in place in order to foster positive student outcomes.</p>
<p>Several limitations should be noted in considering the results presented in this study. First, external validity may be limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0192636512444715">Imbens &amp; Lemieux, 2008</xref>). RD predicts an effect at a specific point on the age continuum, so explanations of the effect should relate to that point (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0192636512444715">Luyten et al., 2008</xref>). In addition, the design is specific to the cohorts examined (i.e., in this study, seventh- and eighth-grade students), and results should not be generalized over other variations in treatments, settings, or outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0192636512444715">Shadish et al., 2002</xref>). The RD approach also requires the assumption that samples of students are similar between adjacent years (i.e., such that selection bias can be minimized). The size of our samples and their consistency in composition render this less of a concern in this study.</p>
<p>Second, there are many school practice indicators that may contribute to students’ learning outcomes. We acknowledge that only a few selected variables from four primary sets of school factors (i.e., context, composition, staffing variables, instructional practice) were examined in our multilevel model to illustrate their effects on added-year outcomes. Although all have been found to influence various types of student outcomes in past research, it would be a mistake to think of any chosen set of school indicators as theoretically complete. For example, although absolute-schooling effects varied significantly across schools, few consistent predictors were found that explained variability in the size of the effects. Our results therefore suggest there is still considerable room to add school variables that explain variability in absolute-schooling effects among schools serving students in the middle grades. This could include further process indicators (e.g., curricular organization, grouping strategies, peer relationships, teacher quality, and effectiveness) and wider contextual influences.</p>
<p>Third, the instructional practice factor provided a broad measure of schools’ educational processes. Although role group data from the statewide school survey provide a general measure of what schools are doing academically within a given year, they cannot be expected to reveal a detailed description of daily (or monthly) classroom and teacher activity. In fact, the classroom level was not part of this study. If it is assumed that the classroom effect is largely the teacher effect, this could explain why school-level process and teacher staffing variables did not manifest themselves fully in the results of this study. Moreover, in identifying differences across schools in absolute-schooling effects specifically, it would be very likely that curricular and instructional practices of each teacher (as well as the particular grade level) would be related to the size of the effects produced. Observation and interviews provide closer descriptions.</p>
<p>Although there is likely some bias in these types of broad measures of schools’ instructional practice, our results suggest they are useful in explaining schools’ productivity. Unlike elementary schools with students largely in self-contained classrooms, at the secondary level a student has multiple teachers, which makes the connection between school and classroom effects to student outcomes more complicated to model and to estimate individual teacher effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0192636512444715">Murdock &amp; Miller, 2003</xref>). Aggregate measures of school instructional practices (e.g., teacher classroom practices, coordination of curriculum, participation in professional development to improve instruction), therefore, may not fully explain absolute-schooling outcomes in secondary school settings without the classroom level included. We note one thing learned from previous studies of the implementation of intended changes in teacher instructional practices within secondary schools is that it is much harder to examine the impact of such changes on secondary students because they have a considerably greater number of teachers in any given year than elementary students. Therefore, the potential effects of individual teacher participation in professional development activities can be greatly dispersed among individual students because of the perceived relevance of the particular activity to each of the teachers (and level of participation) that a particular student encounters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0192636512444715">Thomas &amp; Heck, 2009</xref>). This problem is a feature of the greater organizational complexity of middle and high schools. We believe this is an important point to keep in mind for school leaders in designing, implementing, and assessing the effects of intended efforts focused on improving instruction at the secondary level.</p>
<p>Hence, in future studies, the inclusion of the classroom level may provide more refined estimates of school process and teacher variables in explaining differences in absolute-schooling effects across middle-level schools. It is clear that students’ academic experiences in their middle years, after transition from elementary school, are important in understanding their academic success during high school. An obvious difference is that students in the middle years typically first encounter multiple teachers in different content disciplines, which can reduce the salience of the critical relationship between student and teacher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0192636512444715">Murdock &amp; Miller, 2003</xref>) as well as the relative focus on academics and discipline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0192636512444715">Eccles, Lord, &amp; Midgley, 1991</xref>). Students also encounter a number of peer and self-identity issues that can affect their motivation, engagement in learning, and achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0192636512444715">Roeser &amp; Eccles, 1998</xref>). Moreover, there is some evidence that student achievement drops for students who transition to an intermediate school or middle school versus students who stay in the same K-8 school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0192636512444715">Alspaugh, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0192636512444715">Gronna, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0192636512444715">Zanobini &amp; Usai, 2002</xref>). These issues may interact in various ways with the estimation of school effects described in this study.</p>
<p>Despite these potential limitations, our results imply the RD design is a promising approach in differentiating school effectiveness and the leadership and educational processes that influence added-year outcomes. It produced results consistent with previous research suggesting that background factors matter less when explaining student “absolute gains” in learning. In contrast, school type, student attendance, and instructional processes matter relatively more. Further research using RD should include more detailed measures of school efforts to change teachers’ classroom activity (e.g., classroom observations) in order to determine how more focused teacher behaviors (e.g., quality of instruction, curriculum coverage, instructional grouping strategies) may affect absolute-schooling outcomes. For example, math teachers (and perhaps science teachers) likely have the largest impact on student math outcomes, with reading (or language) outcomes perhaps more dispersed across multiple subject areas.</p>
<p>With respect to school leadership, our research focuses attention on a set of key instructional practices that may be linked to successful school improvement. In preliminary analyses, we noted collaborative leadership appeared to contribute to the development of school academic capacity and indirectly to student learning outcomes. Thus, the findings provide support for calls for the development of broader and deeper capacity to lead in schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0192636512444715">Barth, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0192636512444715">Opdenakker &amp; Van Damme, 2007</xref>). Combining detailed information about what teachers do in classrooms to facilitate learning and what school leaders can do to build the school’s instructional capacity should contribute to a more thorough understanding about how RD can be applied to estimate absolute-schooling effects under a variety of classroom and school conditions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0192636512444715">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Several analyses were undertaken to see whether being “selected” into the study (i.e., the student being in his or her proper school entry birth year) or not interacted with student background variables in explaining achievement in reading and math. For eighth-grade students, no significant interactions were noted between background, being selected or not, and student achievement in math or reading (<italic>p</italic> &gt; .01). For seventh-grade students, there was one significant interaction for reading (native language English, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). In this case, the direction was in favor of students not selected; that is, students whose native language was English and were not selected in the study had higher reading scores than students whose native language was English and were selected in the study. These results suggest the data can be considered missing at random (MAR)—that is, MAR implies that the missing data may depend on other variables in the model, but the missing case is assumed to be independent of the value on the unobserved (missing) value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0192636512444715">Hox, 2010</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0192636512444715">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The items used to define the dimensions were preliminarily developed using multilevel (i.e., teachers nested within schools) confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and a sample of 4,056 teachers within 60 elementary and secondary schools. At the teacher level, the item loadings were all statistically significant and ranged from 0.35 to 0.99. At the school level, the item loadings were all greater than 0.93.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0192636512444715">
<label>3.</label>
<p>In the preliminary analyses, the relative effects of middle schools, intermediate schools, and other configurations on reading and math outcomes were examined. The analyses suggested that middle schools produced higher outcomes than either intermediate schools or other school configurations. There were no consistent differences between intermediate schools and other configurations. Based on these results, the intermediate and other school configurations were combined into one reference category (other types of schools) coded 0, and middle schools were coded 1.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Elias Ali</bold> is a high school principal in the Hawaii Department of Education. His research interests include school effects on student learning.</p>
<p><bold>Ronald H. Heck</bold> is a professor of educational administration at the University of Hawaii at Manoa. His research interests include school leadership and school improvement.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alspaugh</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Achievement loss associated with the transition to middle school and high school</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arcia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A comparison of elementary/k-8 and middle schools’ suspension rates</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>-<lpage>469</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Balfanz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Legters</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Are NCLB’s measures, incentives and improvement strategies the right ones for the nation’s low-performing high schools?</article-title> <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>559</fpage>-<lpage>593</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Improving schools from within</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beane</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Guess again: Will changing the grades save middle-level education?</article-title> <source>Educational Leadership</source>, <volume>63</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Policy scholars are from Venus: Policy makers are from Mars</article-title>. <source>Review of Higher Education</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipsey</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Performance trajectories and performance gaps as achievement effect-size benchmarks for educational evaluations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research on Educational Effectiveness</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bosker</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheerens</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Conceptual and methodological advances in educational effectiveness research</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byrnes</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Comparing achievement between K-8 and middle schools: A large scale empirical study</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Education</source>, <volume>114</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cahan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Age versus schooling effects on intelligence development</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1239</fpage>-<lpage>1249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cahan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>A between-grades-level approach to the investigation of the absolute effects of schooling on achievement</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>California Department of Education</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <source>California’s middle grades at a glance</source> (<year>2007-08</year>). <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/gs/mg/documents/ataglance.doc">http://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/gs/mg/documents/ataglance.doc</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Providing the facts</article-title>. <source>Phi Delta Kappan</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitz-Gibbon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>School effectiveness research: criticisms and recommendations</article-title>. <source>Oxford Review of Education</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>438</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raudenbush</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Resources, instruction, and research</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coladarci</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The (Limited) evidence regarding effects of grade-span configurations on academic achievement: What rural educators should know</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-2/rural.html">http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-2/rural.html</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yakimowski-Srebnick</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>An examination of K-5, 6-8 versus K-8 grade configurations</article-title>. <source>ERS Spectrum</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Randomized experiments in education: A critical examination of the reason the educational evaluation community has offered for not doing them</article-title> <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Waiting for life to arrive: A history of the regression-discontinuity design in psychology, statistics and economics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Econometrics</source>, <volume>142</volume>, <fpage>636</fpage>-<lpage>654</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Creemers</surname><given-names>B. P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kyriakides</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The dynamics of educational effectiveness: A contribution to policy, practice and theory in contemporary schools</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Butterbaugh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>When do children fall behind? What can be done?</article-title> <source>Phi Delta Kappan</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>752</fpage>-<lpage>761</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>What are we doing to early adolescents? The impact of educational contexts on early adolescents</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Education</source>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>521</fpage>-<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>T. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Middle school models are working in many grade configurations to boost student performance</article-title>. <source>American Secondary Education</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gamoran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayalon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Stratification in academic secondary programs and educational inequality in Israel and the United States</article-title>. <source>Comparative Education Review</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Methods is school effectiveness research</article-title>. <source>School Effectiveness and School Improvement</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcoulides</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Examining culture and performance at different middle school level structures</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Educational Management</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gronna</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Effects of grade of school transition and school characteristics of eight-grade achievement: A multilevel analysis</source> <comment>(Doctoral dissertation). Available from ProQuest Dissertations and Theses database. (ProQuest ID No. 733030101)</comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Securing the right to learn: Policy and practice for powerful teaching and learning</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Assessing school achievement progress: Comparing alternative approaches</article-title>. <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>667</fpage>-<lpage>699</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Teacher effectiveness and student achievement: Investigating a multilevel cross-classified model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Administration</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallinger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Assessing the contribution of distributed leadership to school improvement and growth in math achievement</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>659</fpage>-<lpage>689</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calderon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Medrich</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Academic achievement in the middle grades: What does research tell us? A review of the literature</source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Southern Regional Education Board</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eric.ed.gov/PDFS/ED478009.pdf">http://www.eric.ed.gov/PDFS/ED478009.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mathematical knowledge of middle school teachers: Implications for the No Child Left Behind policy initiative</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Multilevel modeling in school effectiveness research</article-title>. <source>School Effectiveness and School Improvement</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howley</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Grade-span configurations: Where 6th and 7th grades are assigned may influence student achievement, research suggests</article-title>. <source>The School Administrator, March</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hox</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Multilevel analysis: Techniques and applications</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Imbens</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Regression discontinuity designs: A guide to practice</article-title>. <source>Journal of Econometrics</source>, <volume>142</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>-<lpage>635</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klump</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>What the research says (or doesn’t say) about K-8 versus middle school grade configurations</article-title>. <source>Changing Face of the Classroom</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Konstantopoulos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Trends of school effects on student achievement: evidence from NLS:72, HSB:82 and NELS:92</article-title>. <source>Teachers College Record</source>, <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>2550</fpage>-<lpage>2581</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kyriakides</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The contribution of schooling to the cognitive development of secondary education students in Cyprus</article-title>. <source>School Effectiveness and School Improvement</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>186</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>V. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryk</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>A multilevel model of the social distribution of high school achievement</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>V. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burkam</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Dropping out of high school: The role of school organization and structure</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betebenner</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). Accountability systems: Implications of requirements of the No Child Left Behind Act of <year>2001</year>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Stability of school-building accountability scores and gains</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An empirical assessment of the absolute effect of schooling: Regression discontinuity applied to TIMSS-95</article-title>. <source>Oxford Review of Education</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>397</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peschar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Effects of schooling on reading performance, reading engagement, and reading activities of 15-year olds in England</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tymms</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Assessing school effects without controlling for prior achievement?</article-title> <source>School Effectiveness and School Improvement</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeaton</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Shaping policies related to developmental education: An evaluation using the regression-discontinuity design</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Teachers as sources of middle school students’ motivational identity. Variable-centered and person-centered analytic approaches</article-title>. <source>Elementary School Journal</source>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>-<lpage>399</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>National Center for Educational Statistics</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Fast facts</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nces.ed.gov/fastfacts/display.asp?id=1">http://nces.ed.gov/fastfacts/display.asp?id=1</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Keeping track: How schools structure inequality</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>. (<comment>Original work published 1985</comment>)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Offenberg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>, <month>March</month>). <article-title>The efficacy of Philadelphia’s K-to-8 schools compared to middle grades schools</article-title>. <source>Middle School Journal</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Opdenakker</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Do school context, student composition, ands school leadership affect school practice and outcomes in secondary education?</article-title> <source>British Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pedhazur</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmelkin</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Measurement, design, and analysis: An integrated approach</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peugh</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Missing data in educational research: A review of reporting practices and suggestions for improvement</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>556</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roeser</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Adolescents’ perceptions of middle school: Relation to longitudinal changes in academic and psychological adjustment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research on Adolescence</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sammons</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Editorial article for special issue on alternative methods for assessing school effects and schooling effects</article-title>. <source>School Effectiveness and School Improvement</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sammons</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nuttall</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cuttance</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Differential school effectiveness: Results from a re-analysis of the Inner London Education Authority’s junior school project data</article-title>. <source>British Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>-<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scheerens</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Anatomy of some representative school leaders’ effectiveness studies</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sheerens</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>School leadership effects revisited: Review and meta-analysis of empirical studies</source> (pp. <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scheerens</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bosker</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>The foundations of educational effectiveness</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pergamon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shadish</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Experimental and quasi-experimental design for generalized causal inference</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teddlie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>The international handbook of school effectiveness research</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Falmer Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thistlethwaite</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1960</year>). <article-title>Regression-discontinuity analysis: An alternative to ex post facto experiment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>317</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>December</month> <day>31</day>). <source>Hawaiian Cultural Influences in Education (HCIE) multilevel statistical analyses</source>. <comment>Report prepared for Kamehameha Schools/Bishop Estate, Honolulu</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trochim</surname><given-names>W. M. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Research design for program evaluation: The regression-discontinuity approach</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>U.S. Department of Education</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Scientifically based evaluation methods (Notice RIN 1890-ZA00)</article-title>. <source>Federal Register</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>3586</fpage>-<lpage>3589</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Viadero</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Evidence for moving to K-8 not airtight</article-title>. <source>Education Week</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>19</issue>), <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Re-examining middle school effects: What the research says</article-title>. <source>Principal</source>, <volume>87</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kipnes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Reexamining middle school effects: A comparison of middle grades students in middle schools and K-8 schools</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Education</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lupart</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beran</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Differences in achievement between adolescents who remain in a K-8 school and those who transition to junior high school</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Education</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>649</fpage>-<lpage>669</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirst</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haertel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Padia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balfanz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Woodward</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Gaining ground in the middle grades: Why some schools do better</source>. <publisher-loc>Mountain View, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EdSource</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.edsource.org/middle-grades-summary.html">http://www.edsource.org/middle-grades-summary.html</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Willms</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raudenbush</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>A longitudinal hierarchical linear model for estimating school effects and their stability</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yecke</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Mayhem in the middle: Why we should shift to K-8</article-title>. <source>Educational Leadership</source>, <volume>63</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0192636512444715">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zanobini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Usai</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Domain-specific self-concept and achievement motivation in the transition from primary to low middle school</article-title>. <source>Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>-<lpage>217</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>