<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AIP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaip</journal-id>
<journal-title>AADE in Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2325-1603</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2325-5161</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2325160312473431</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2325160312473431</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>From the Editor</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Working Together Toward a New Beginning</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS, RN, CDE, FAADE</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>1</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 by the American Association of Diabetes Educators</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Association of Diabetes Educators</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic id="img1-2325160312473431" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_2325160312473431-img1.tif"/>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Here we are. This is the inaugural issue of <italic>AADE in Practice</italic>, which combines the heart, the art, and the science of diabetes education. We hope to inspire, inform and empower you, the diabetes educator. We aspire to become a preferred and trusted resource for practical tools and strategies that can help you in your day-to-day work.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>It seems so long ago that I sat in a coffee shop at the 2012 ADA Scientific Sessions in Philadelphia talking with Sandi Burke, then president of AADE. We talked about her vision of a practice journal and the future of the <italic>AADE in Practice</italic> newsletter, of which I was editor at the time. Transitioning to a journal seemed like a natural step.</p>
<p>What you are holding in your hand is the result of a lot of hard work by many people. Talk about teamwork! I cannot even begin to name everyone involved. I had no idea what it took to put a publication like this together. From original manuscripts that started out as crude Word documents, we ended up with this. WOW!</p>
<p>Our publishing company, SAGE Publications, provided expert guidance as we planned and completed this issue. Their editors honed the copy, and their marketing and sales staff ensured the delivery of a successful first issue. From AADE, Diana Pihos and Joyce Lee supported and worked with us every step of the way, along with AADE leadership and the Board of Directors.</p>
<p>I am grateful for an awesome Editorial Board: Cindy Halstenson, RD, LD, CDE; Jerry Meece, RPh, CDE, FACA; and Joe Nelson, MA, LP, CST. They were amazing to work with on the newsletter and thankfully agreed to continue with this new format. In addition, Karol Carstensen joins us as associate editor bringing a strong publishing background, primarily in the fields of health care and diabetes.</p>
<p>Finally, I cannot forget our authors—diabetes educators like you. Without your contributions and your willingness to share your experiences, <italic>AADE in Practice</italic> could not exist.</p>
<p>We have come a long way. From a foldout newsletter that started about six years ago to this. You told us you liked the newsletter and that you wanted more. And we are happy to provide it for you.</p>
<p>Now let me tell you a little about what you can expect from <italic>AADE in Practice</italic>.</p>
<p>Each issue will have three regular departments:</p>
<list id="list1-2325160312473431" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Capsules</italic> provides insights on new and current therapies and tools for the clinical management of diabetes and prediabetes, their implementation in providing best-practice care, and their use in improving adherence. In this issue, J Meece looks at needle length and the science behind skin thickness and injection depth. Old practices can be hard to break, but strong evidence helps us change with confidence.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Food for Thought</italic> gives updates on nutrition and lifestyle issues related to diabetes and prediabetes, including meal planning, weight management, and physical activity. In this issue, C Halstenson writes of lifestyle changes that have been proven to reduce the risk of developing diabetes. Through a personal story about counseling someone with prediabetes, Halstenson reminds us of the impact we have as diabetes educators even when it seems like a small thing to us.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Mind Sights</italic> explores the psychosocial aspects of diabetes education including counseling, mind-body connections, and strategies for facilitating behavior change. In this issue, J Nelson uses his own experience snorkeling in the Florida Keys in the company of a shark to help us understand how the brain works and the value of mindfulness. I wish my psychology professors had used stories like this!</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I love to hear a choir. I love the humanity…to see the faces of real people devoting themselves to a piece of music. I like the teamwork. It makes me feel optimistic about the human race when I see them cooperating like that.</p>
<attrib>—SIR PAUL MCCARTNEY</attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Each issue will also offer feature articles focused on practical strategies for applying best practices, providing examples and results where possible. Topics may include innovative diabetes programs, continuous quality improvement projects, business aspects of diabetes education, new roles for diabetes educators, translating research into practice, application of the AADE7 Self-Care Behaviors™, and tools for improving practice. We have several good examples of what you can expect to see in this issue.</p>
<p><disp-quote><p>Great things are not done by impulse, but by a series of small things brought together.</p>
<attrib>—VINCENT VAN GOGH</attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>To disseminate the curriculum used in the Diabetes Prevention Program, which proved we could reduce the risk of diabetes by 58% using a lifestyle intervention, the National Diabetes Prevention Program (National DPP) from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) is well underway. Many of you have wondered about where diabetes educators fit with the National DPP. Emory University’s Diabetes Technical and Training Center (DTTAC) has contracted with CDC to provide the training for lifestyle coaches on the National DPP curriculum and S Piper, from DTTAC gives us an overview of their role and how you can become involved. At last, we have an answer for the 79 million people with prediabetes.</p>
<p>One thing about diabetes educators is your tremendous ability to be innovative in spite of difficult and challenging circumstances. Google Camden, NJ and you will find it is a nine square mile area that has been labeled the most dangerous city in America and has been dubbed the “silenced poverty” in a post by Jeff Putthoff, SJ, because much of what happens in Camden goes unnoticed. But in health care, there is a group of people who have decided to make a difference. F Grabowski writes of the Camden Diabetes Coalition, part of a large health care initiative that started in 2002. This program is giving the people of Camden the help they need to be healthier. We all struggle to help those patients who fall through the cracks and Camden is finding the answers.</p>
<p>But in our struggle to best meet the needs of our patients, we also work hard to stay on top of the latest research and recommendations. In that search, have you ever wondered what all those various “practice documents” are about? R Lipman explains what those documents are, how various organizations might use them, and how they might apply to your day-to-day practice.</p>
<p><italic>Reflections</italic> is an exciting offering that provides a creative outlet for self-expression related to any aspect of diabetes. This is a celebration of our wholeness—a recognition that we are not defined by our jobs and that we each have a full life. Bringing our whole selves to the table makes us better at our profession and can help prevent burnout. Our first Reflections comes from T Benge who shares a poignant and very personal story about growing up around diabetes and the impact that experience has on her practice. I am sure her story will touch you and may even inspire you to share your own story.</p>
<p><italic>Practice Pearls</italic> are short, timely tips, advice, ideas, or motivational messages for diabetes educators. This might include a quick introduction to an educational tool, a brief how-to related to communicating a concept or demonstrating a skill, or anything else that is quickly applicable in practice. To start us off, C Ponte provides tips on doing a quick assessment of health literacy, a common problem for many of our patients. Ponte describes a few methods that don’t take a lot of time but can make a big difference for your patients.</p>
<p><italic>Patient Stories</italic> is a vehicle for honoring our patients. We all have interesting patients we like to talk about. But sometimes our patients have a story to tell, too. We welcome stories from patients about their experience with diabetes, how diabetes has affected their lives and relationships, how they have achieved their dreams, what impact their diabetes educator has had on them, etc. Stories can be inspiring, provocative, controversial, informative, motivational, or anything that may have a useful message for readers.</p>
<p>In <italic>Educators in Practice</italic>, we focus on the great work people in our profession do. In this issue, we highlight S Perry, a diabetes educator delivering the National DPP. She has some good pointers for those of you interested in implementing this program yourself. If you know of someone doing innovative things, let us know. We would love to highlight them and their work.</p>
<p>So that is our first issue. It packs in a lot of good information from many talented contributors. I hope you like it. I hope it helps you in your day-to-day practice. I hope you find it inviting to read.</p>
<p>Tell us what you think and what you would like to see more of. In addition, we invite you to submit feature articles, Practice Pearls, Reflections, and Patient Stories for publication. This is your practice journal and we are delighted to be a part of it. ■</p>
</body>
</article>