<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Textile Research Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5175</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1746-7748</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040517511420763</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040517511420763</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Development and analysis of novel electroluminescent yarns and fabrics for localized automotive interior illumination</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>Tilak</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0040517511420763">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0040517511420763"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Monaragala</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0040517511420763">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040517511420763"><label>1</label>School of Art and Design, Nottingham Trent University, Nottingham, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0040517511420763"><label>2</label>Centre for Research and Development (Ministry of Defence), Sri Lanka</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0040517511420763">Tilak Dias, Nottingham Trent University, Burton Street, Nottingham NG1 4BU, UK Email: <email>tilak.dias@ntu.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>82</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>1164</fpage>
<lpage>1176</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Textiles used in automotive interiors can be used to provide localized illumination if made to illuminate. In this study a novel electroluminescent (EL) yarn has been developed that can be integrated with knitted and woven fabrics. An EL yarn construction and an appropriate EL coating have been studied; moreover, a novel automated single yarn coating system has also been developed. An analytical model of the luminance of this yarn was also created based on alternating current thin-film EL technology. An automated EL yarn driver system, which electrically drives the yarn to provide illumination, and an illuminance measurement system to detect its illumination have been explained. The luminescence of the EL yarn has been analyzed based on the luminance derived by the analytical model and the illuminance detected by the measurement system. Finally, knitted fabrics integrated with this yarn are described with possible applications in automotive or aerospace interiors.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>aerospace industry</kwd>
<kwd>automotive industry</kwd>
<kwd>automotive interior illumination</kwd>
<kwd>coating</kwd>
<kwd>electroluminescence</kwd>
<kwd>light</kwd>
<kwd>yarns</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The automobile industry is the largest user of technical textiles, with about 20 kg in each of the 45 million or so cars made every year worldwide. Car interiors have become more important within recent years, as people are spending more time in their cars, commuting longer distances to work on a daily or weekly basis. Thus textiles are widely used in the automotive industry to provide both comfort to the passengers and an aesthetic appearance to the automotive interior. Consumer researchers in the USA believe that the car interior will become a focal point of brand recognition. Textile design and color will inevitably be an essential tool in creating these distinctive interiors,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0040517511420763">1</xref></sup> and sophisticated textiles may well be used to address a common requirement in an automobile interior: namely, the provision of localized interior illumination.</p>
<p>From its inception the automotive interior has been illuminated by the use of conventional direct current (DC) incandescent bulbs. One such device fitted on to a suitable location of the headliner generally illuminates a modern compact automobile. In more expensive models there may be such devices fitted to door panels, the parcel shelf, and boot. However, the system requires intricate wiring, which must be integrated in special grooves fabricated in the particular area of the automotive interior, such as the headliner. The illumination of the dome light may be adequate for a general region surrounding the device; however, its high location can blind occupants with its glare while driving and the seats can cast shadows that hinder searches for items. Therefore, original equipment manufacturers (OEMs) and their suppliers are developing technology for optimized interior illumination and greater brand differentiation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517511420763">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>However, if localized regions of the automotive interior fabric can be made to illuminate, it is possible to provide localized illumination. Moreover, the wiring can be less intricate, as the wiring pattern can be fabricated in the fabric design by means of conductive yarn.</p>
<p>Work has been done to integrate optical fibers into fabrics to make them illuminate;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517511420763">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0040517511420763">4</xref></sup> however, as the illumination depends on notches on the cladding it may make the zone of illumination uneven. Moreover, the fibers have to be illuminated at one end by an incandescent source. The completed fabric may also be rigid dueto the stiffness of the polymeric optical fibers. Luminescent fabrics have been created based on photoluminescent glow yarn technology,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0040517511420763">5</xref></sup> but there is no control over the luminescence of the yarn and it cannot be switched on and off. Moreover, for its operation the fabric has to be exposed to a light source for a lengthy duration (sunlight for three minutes, or for 20 minutes to luminescent light) and even then the effect takes place in the dark, which may not be entirely desirable.</p>
<p>Thus, this paper investigates the development of a novel electroluminescent (EL) yarn based on thin-film alternating current (AC) EL technology, which can be easily integrated into fabrics.</p>
<sec id="sec1-0040517511420763"><title>Electroluminescent yarn construction</title>
<p>The general construction of the EL yarn is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0040517511420763">Figure 1</xref>, where the base electrode comprises the electro-conductive yarn over which a layer of insulation paste and a layer of EL phosphor ink are applied. To protect the coated layers from moisture and abrasion, a transparent non-conductive flexible encapsulation layer is also applied.
<fig id="fig1-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Electroluminescent (EL) yarn construction: (1) electro-conductive base yarn; (2) dielectric insulation layer; (3) EL layer; (4) dielectric transparent layer; (5) conductive yarn; (6) alternating current voltage source.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The second electrode comprises a similar electro-conductive yarn to the core yarn or a fine copper wire. This yarn is wound as a helix about the coated inner yarn. Asilver coated 235 dtex, 34 multifilament nylon yarn (Trade name SHIELDEX®)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0040517511420763">6</xref></sup> was chosen as the electro-conductive base yarn for the study. Three folds of this yarn with a slight twist were used for the application. An optical microscope image of the yarn at 0.05 N tension is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0040517511420763">Figure 2</xref>.
<fig id="fig2-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Microscopic image of silver-coated polyester yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The DuPont 8153 EL dielectric screen printing paste was chosen as the material for the dielectric insulation layer of the EL coating. It has a dielectric constant/relative permittivity of 40 at 1000 Hz and a viscosity between 10 and 20 Pa.s.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0040517511420763">7</xref></sup> The dielectric paste consists of barium titanate and the breakdown electric field of the material is greater than 20 MV/m.</p>
<p>The EL phosphor ink produced by DuPont Ltd, which consists of microencapsulated phosphor powder suspended in a hydrophobic vehicle/binder, was used as the phosphor coating. The encapsulation of the phosphor grains prevents the degradation of their luminescent properties due to prolonged exposure to moisture in ambient air.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0040517511420763">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0040517511420763">10</xref></sup> Depending upon the chromaticity of the phosphor grains used, the phosphor ink is available in three colors as follows:
<list id="list1-0040517511420763" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>8150L White Electroluminescent Phosphor;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0040517511420763">8</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>8152L Blue Green Electroluminescent Phosphor;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0040517511420763">9</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>8154L Yellow Green Electroluminescent Phosphor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0040517511420763">10</xref></sup></p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Dymax 9001-E-V3.5 encapsulant was chosen for the flexible transparent encapsulation. The fluid can be cured within 30 seconds upon exposure to 150 mW/cm<sup>2</sup> UV irradiation. Moreover, the breakpoint of the cured solid occurs at 150% elongation (tensile test performed as per ASTM D 638 standard). The stiffness of the material in the cured state is 2500 psi (17.24 MPa). The water absorption is 1%. The dielectric breakdown of the cured material is stated as 500 V/mm (0.5 V/m) and its dielectric constant at 1 MHz is 3.27.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0040517511420763">11</xref></sup> In the uncured form the material is a colorless liquid of 400 cPa (4 Pa), and the cured material provides reasonable flexibility.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-0040517511420763"><title>Automated yarn coating system</title>
<p>The system can be best described by segregating it into sections, each performing a particular task, and finally looking at the entire system as a whole.</p>
<sec id="sec3-0040517511420763"><title>Driver section</title>
<p>The electro-conductive yarn is delivered from a package, which is held by the yarn package holder. The yarn unwinds from the top end of the package into a yarn feeding unit. This unit consists of a yarn guide and a roller of 50 mm diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517511420763">Figure 3</xref>), which is driven by a stepper motor.
<fig id="fig3-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Yarn feed unit.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The yarn dispensed from the cone package is guided through the built-on yarn guide to the roller. For proper feeder operation, the yarn is wound once around the roller.</p>
<p>The yarn is then sent through the dispensing and curing sections and guided by a stepper-motor-driven yarn take-up unit, which has a similar construction to the yarn feeder unit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517511420763">Figure 3</xref>). The yarn is then wound as a cheese package by a stepper-motor-driven yarn winder unit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517511420763">Figure 4</xref>).
<fig id="fig4-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Yarn winder unit.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig4.tif"/></fig></p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-0040517511420763"><title>Coating system</title>
<p>The yarn delivered from the yarn feeder unit is sent through three dispensing and curing sections of the coating system. The first section applies a single layer of the dielectric paste, the second section applies a layer of phosphor ink, and the third section applies a single layer of the transparent encapsulant. The operation of the dispensing sub unit and the curing sub unit is described in the following sections.</p>
<sec id="sec5-0040517511420763"><title>Dispensing sub unit</title>
<p>Each dispensing sub unit consists of a JBE1113 pneumatic fluid dispenser unit<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517511420763">12</xref></sup> and a fluid bath holder. The dispenser units operate between 5 and 7 bar of pneumatic pressure. The fluid is deposited inside a syringe. The volume of liquid dispensed is determined by the inner diameter of the blunt tip needle of the syringe and the dispense timer of the unit. The dispensing action is triggered through an electronic transistor–transistor logic (TTL) pulse from the control section of the system. The fluid is dispensed from the blunt tip needle to a special bath holder (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517511420763">Figure 5</xref>).
<fig id="fig5-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Fluid bath holder.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The yarn is immersed in the fluid bath on its way through the cavity of the device. Thus, in the process, a coating of the fluid is applied to the yarn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517511420763">Figure 6</xref>). Owing to the surface tension between the yarn and the fluid, the fluid sticks on the yarn surface. However, due to gravity, any excess fluid on the yarn surface may drip down from the yarn as it proceeds to the respective curing section.
<fig id="fig6-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Cross-sectional view of the fluid bath holder.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig6.tif"/></fig></p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-0040517511420763"><title>Curing sub unit</title>
<p>The coated yarn (wet) is cured using ultraviolet (UV) light. For this purpose a Dymax BlueWave 50 UV spot lamp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517511420763">12</xref></sup> is employed. The equipment emits UV light at 2.70 W/cm<sup>2</sup> at the end of the flexible liquid light guide, which is connected to the light output of the equipment. The UV light is shone on to the coated yarn with a light guide held 2 mm above the yarn. The emitted light can be switched on by a shutter of the equipment controlled by TTL pulses from the controller unit. The emitted light is reflected back on to the opposite side of the yarn with the aid of a parabolic mirror. The focal point of the mirror is adjusted to the underside of the yarn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517511420763">Figures 7(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517511420763">b</xref>)). The mirror has UV-enhancing aluminum coating, which reflects the UV wavelengths.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517511420763">13</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig7-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>(a) Cross-sectional view of ultraviolet (UV) curing process of the coated yarn. (b) Pictorial view of UV curing process of the coated yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The yarn is illuminated for a length of 15 mm by this process, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517511420763">Figure 7(b)</xref>. The system is configured to move the yarn by 1.37 mm length in 2 seconds intervals. This determines the speed of the system, which is 2.466 m of coated yarn per hour. It was observed that this dosage of UV irradiation yields an optimum curing rate without accumulated heat burning the yarn.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec7-0040517511420763"><title>Control system</title>
<p>A Labview-based software was created to control the yarn coating system. The program generates signals to control the dispense and curing units, which is converted to TTL pulses by a NI PCI 7334 stepper motor controller unit and sent to the respective equipment. Moreover, the stepper motors of the system are also activated by the same software program with an NI MID 7664 stepper motor controller.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec8-0040517511420763"><title>System operation</title>
<p>The system is set up on a metric base plate of 1500 mm × 300 mm. The syringes of the dispenser units, the UV liquid light guides of the curing units, and the associated parabolic mirrors, are mounted on this base plate using posts, bar type lens filter holders, cross clamps, and optical mounts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517511420763">13</xref></sup> Moreover, the yarn feeder unit, the yarn take-up unit, and the yarn winder are also assembled on this base. The assembled system is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0040517511420763">Figure 8</xref>. As can be seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0040517511420763">Figure 8</xref>, the yarn is taken from the yarn package through a ceramic yarn guide on to the yarn feeder unit. Next the yarn goes through the dielectric paste dispenser section and the UV curing sections. Afterwards the coated and dry yarn goes to the phosphor ink-dispensing section via a yarn guide. The phosphor-coated (wet) yarn is then cured by the UV section. This phosphor-coated and dry yarn then enters the transparent fluid dispensing section via a ceramic yarn guide. The UV section cures this (wet) yarn, which is then taken up, via the yarn take-up unit and a ceramic yarn guide, by the yarn winder, which winds the yarn evenly on to a cheese package.
<fig id="fig8-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>The yarn coating system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>For a proper coating operation and locomotion of the system, it has been observed that the yarn requires tension devoid of slack. This can be achieved with all three stepper motors operating in unison. Moreover, to obtain tension devoid of slack in the flow of yarn through the system, the yarn winder can be operated while the yarn feeder and yarn take-up units are switched off prior to the coating operation. Furthermore, to avoid bulging due to gravity of the uncured fluid due to its weight under the yarn at the phosphor coating stages, the yarn is set at an inclination. This causes the uncured fluid to trickle away from the curing section and drop to the metal base plate, resulting in yarn to free from gnarls after the curing stage.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec9-0040517511420763"><title>Structure, material content, and the thickness of coating of the electroluminescent yarn</title>
<sec id="sec10-0040517511420763"><title>Structure of the EL yarn</title>
<p>The multifilament electro-conductive yarn, after passing through the bath holder of the dielectric paste coating stage, conforms to a monofilament yarn due to the paste adhering to the yarn surface by means of its surface tension and viscosity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517511420763">Figure 9</xref>). Moreover, the interstices between filaments may be filled with the paste due to wicking.
<fig id="fig9-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Cross-sectional view of the multifilament conductive yarn after bath holder of the dielectric paste.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig9.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Thus, after the curing stage there is a reduction in the flexibility of the yarn. An image of the cured yarn of coated with 8153L dielectric paste, taken from an optical microscope, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0040517511420763">Figure 10</xref> where the compacted individual filaments are evident.
<fig id="fig10-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Optical microscope image of the dielectric layer coated yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The dielectric paste holds the compacted filaments together even when there is zero tension on the yarn. As such the application of the phosphor ink layer is in effect coating a monofilament. The phosphor coating adheres on to the outer surface of the dielectric paste coated yarn due to surface tension (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0040517511420763">Figure 11</xref>).
<fig id="fig11-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Cross-sectional view of the yarn with two phosphor layers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig11.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>An optical microscope image of the yarn coated with two layers of 8152L blue green phosphor ink is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0040517511420763">Figure 12</xref>, where it can be seen that the phosphor coating on the yarn is virtually devoid of any gnarled surfaces and the yarn is now effectively a monofilament yarn.
<fig id="fig12-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Optical microscope image of the phosphor-coated yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig12.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Similarly, the coating of the DYMAX E-9001 V3.5 transparent flexible layer in effect is coating a monofilament yarn. Therefore, in this case, the fluid also adheres to the outermost surface of the phosphor coating of the yarn due to surface tension.</p>
<p>Finally, a 0.174 mm diameter copper strand was wound around the yarn in a helical manner using an AGTEKS Direct Twistcone cone-to-yarn twisting machine. An optical microscope image of the completed yarn is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0040517511420763">Figure 13</xref>. Images of the EL yarn in the undriven and driven states are given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0040517511420763">Figure 14</xref>.
<fig id="fig13-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>Optical microscope image of the completed electroluminescent yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig14-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p>Images of electroluminescent (EL) yarn in undriven and driven states. (a) EL yarn in the unexcited state. (b) EL yarn when excited by an alternating current power source.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig14.tif"/></fig></p></sec>
<sec id="sec11-0040517511420763"><title>Material content of the respective layers</title>
<p>In order to determine the material content of the respective layers, the weight of the uncoated yarn was measured, being the average weight of 10 samples of the uncoated yarn each 30 cm in length (<italic>w<sub>yarn</sub></italic>). Secondly, the weights of 10 samples each of 30 cm length of this yarn coated with a single layer of the dielectric paste were measured and their average taken (<italic>w<sub>dielectric</sub></italic>). Similarly 10 samples of 30 cm length of single layers of dielectric paste and phosphor ink coated yarn were measured, their average being (<italic>w<sub>phosdie</sub></italic>).</p>
<p>Finally the weights were measured of 10 samples 30 cm of length of the complete inner EL yarn, their average being <italic>w<sub>EL</sub></italic>.</p>
<p>The material content of the dielectric paste (<italic>m<sub>die</sub></italic>), the phosphor ink (<italic>m<sub>p</sub></italic>), and the transparent encapsulant (<italic>m<sub>e</sub></italic>) for a unit length of the yarn at the cured state are obtained from the following equations:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0040517511420763"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0040517511420763"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0040517511420763"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>l</italic> is the length of the yarn measured, which in this case was 10 cm.</p>
<p>The volume of material of a particular layer in the uncured state can be obtained by multiplying its material content in the cured state with the solid content of that particular material. The solid contents of the dielectric paste, the phosphor ink, and the transparent flexible encapsulant are 67%, 61%, and 100%, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0040517511420763">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0040517511420763">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0040517511420763">11</xref></sup> The measured data and the calculated values of the material content in the cured and uncured state of a particular single layer for a unit length of the yarn are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0040517511420763">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0040517511420763">Table 2</xref>, respectively.
<table-wrap id="table1-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Measured data of a single layer of electroluminescent (EL) yarn in the cured state</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0040517511420763" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Material type</th>
<th>Weight (g/m)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="center">
<tr>
<td>Uncoated yarn (<italic>w<sub>yarn</sub></italic>)</td>
<td>0.083</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Dielectric paste coated yarn (<italic>w<sub>die</sub></italic>)</td>
<td>0.14</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Phosphor ink and dielectric paste coated yarn(<italic>w<sub>phosdie</sub></italic>)</td>
<td>0.27</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Complete EL yarn (<italic>w<sub>EL</sub></italic>)</td>
<td>0.48</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The material content of single layers of the respective coating both in the cured and uncured state of the electroluminescent yarn</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0040517511420763" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>State</th>
<th>Material content of dielectric paste (g/m)</th>
<th>Material content of phosphor ink (g/m)</th>
<th>Material content of transparent encapsulant (g/m)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Cured</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.21</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Uncured</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.21</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The volume of the material content is effectively measured in terms of weight, as these are commercially available in weight rather than volume. It can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0040517511420763">Table 2</xref> that in the cured state the material content of the transparent encapsulant is nearly the same as the combined weight of the dielectric and phosphor layers.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec12-0040517511420763"><title>Coating thickness of individual layers of the EL yarn</title>
<p>To measure the thickness of each individual layer, the diameter of the uncoated yarn was first measured (<italic>d<sub>y</sub></italic>), followed by the diameters of the dielectric paste coated yarn (<italic>d<sub>dy</sub></italic>), the phosphor and dielectric paste coated yarn (<italic>d<sub>dpy</sub></italic>), and the complete EL yarn (<italic>d<sub>EL</sub></italic>). A Projectina optical microscope with associated Projectina 4000 image acquisition software was used for this purpose, measurements being taken at 50 different locations on the yarn samples described in the previous section.</p>
<p>Considering the coated layers and the yarn as concentric cylinders, the thicknesses of the dielectric layer (<italic>t<sub>die</sub></italic>), phosphor layer (<italic>t<sub>p</sub></italic>), and the encapsulation layer (<italic>t<sub>enc</sub></italic>) can be determined as follows:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0040517511420763"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0040517511420763"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0040517511420763"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The measured and calculated data is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0040517511420763">Table 3</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table3-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Thickness of individual layers of the electroluminescent yarn</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0040517511420763" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th><italic>d<sub>y</sub></italic> (mm)</th>
<th><italic>d<sub>dy</sub></italic> (mm)</th>
<th><italic>d<sub>dpy</sub></italic> (mm)</th>
<th><italic>d<sub>EL</sub></italic> (mm)</th>
<th><italic>t<sub>die</sub></italic> (mm)</th>
<th><italic>t<sub>p</sub></italic> (mm)</th>
<th><italic>t<sub>enc</sub></italic> (mm)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>0.296</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.1</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>From <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0040517511420763">Table 3</xref> the thickness of the transparent encapsulant is seen to be higher than the thickness of the other layers, as there is more material content of this layer on the yarn in comparison to the material content of the other layers. Moreover, it is the same as the combined thickness of both the dielectric and the phosphor coating layers.</p>
<p>Therefore, as the thickness and the material content of the transparent encapsulant is more or less the same as the coating composed of both the dielectric and the phosphor coating layers, the flexible properties of this layer may offset the brittle nature of the combined phosphor and dielectric layers. Thus the yarn has the appearance of a flexible plastic strip.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec13-0040517511420763"><title>Electroluminescence of the electroluminescent yarn</title>
<p>The electroluminescence of the EL yarn can be analyzed by the parameters of luminance and illuminance. The luminance can be derived based on the structural properties, the electrical properties of the EL yarn, and from the properties of the applied power. The measurement systems to detect the luminescence of the EL yarn measure the parameter illuminance, which is proportional to luminance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517511420763">14</xref></sup> Therefore, these two parameters can be used to study the luminescence of EL yarns.</p>
<sec id="sec14-0040517511420763"><title>Analytical prediction of luminance of EL yarn</title>
<p>Both the dielectric and transparent insulation layers of the EL coating of the yarn act as capacitors, with capacitances per unit area of <italic>C<sub>d</sub></italic> and <italic>C<sub>t</sub></italic>, respectively. When the applied AC voltage (which is a square wave form) is increased from 0 volts the phosphor coating acts as a leaky capacitor beyond a certain threshold voltage (<italic>V<sub>th</sub></italic>), which can be best described as a capacitor in parallel with a non-linear resistor of resistance <italic>R<sub>EL</sub></italic>. This phenomenon can be depicted as the electrical circuit shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0040517511420763">Figure 15</xref>, based on the corresponding electrical circuit derived by Ono<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0040517511420763">15</xref></sup> for thin-film AC EL devices.
<fig id="fig15-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 15.</label><caption><p>Ideal electrical model of electroluminescent yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig15.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The luminance (<italic>L</italic>) of the yarn can be described from the derivation given by Ono<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0040517511420763">15</xref></sup> for thin-film AC EL devices as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0040517511420763"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>L</italic> is the luminance in cd/m<sup>2</sup>; <italic>η</italic> is the luminance efficiency, assumed as 2.5 lm/w; <italic>V<sub>a</sub></italic> is the amplitude of the applied AC voltage in volts; <italic>V<sub>th</sub></italic> is the threshold voltage (in volts) across the transparent, phosphor, and dielectric layers (at a cross section of the yarn) at which the phosphor layer starts to act as a leaky capacitor and emit light; <italic>V<sub>ELth</sub></italic> is the threshold voltage (in volts) across the phosphor layer (at a cross section of the yarn) at which the EL phosphor particles get excited and emit light; <italic>C<sub>it</sub></italic> is the series capacitance of the capacitances of the transparent layer (<italic>C<sub>t</sub></italic>) and the dielectric layer (<italic>C<sub>d</sub></italic>) in F/m<sup>2</sup>; <italic>f</italic> is the frequency of the AC voltage in Hz.</p>
<p>The inner conductive yarn of the EL yarn is assumed to be a cylinder and the coating layers around it are considered as concentric cylinders. Moreover, the fine copper wire wrapped as a helix about the EL yarn can be assumed as composed of circular loops separated by the pitch (<italic>p</italic>) of the helix, considering the methodology used in analyzing the radiation field of helical antennas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0040517511420763">16</xref></sup> The cross section of the copper wire is assumed to be a rectangle with its side in contact with the EL coating equal to its actual diameter (<italic>d<sub>c</sub></italic>). Thus, EL yarn can be depicted as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-0040517511420763">Figure 16</xref> based on these assumptions.
<fig id="fig16-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 16.</label><caption><p>Cross section lengthwise of the electroluminescent yarn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig16.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The nomenclature for the inner yarn and the coating layers in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517511420763">Figure 9</xref> is as described in the <italic>Coating thickness of individual layers of the EL yarn</italic> section. The capacitances of the dielectric layer (<italic>C<sub>d</sub></italic>) can be given as follows, upon considering the concentric cylinder of the dielectric layer and the inner conductive yarn:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0040517511420763">17</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0040517511420763"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>n</italic> is the number of turns of the copper loops per meter, <italic>ε</italic><sub>0</sub> is the permittivity of free space, which is 8.85419 · 10<sup>- 12</sup> F/m,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0040517511420763">17</xref></sup> and <italic>ε<sub>d</sub></italic> is the relative permittivity of the dielectric paste.</p>
<p>This can be expressed in terms of the coating thickness of the dielectric (<italic>t<sub>die</sub></italic>) layer:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0040517511420763"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Similarly, by considering the concentric cylinders of the complete EL yarn, the capacitance of the transparent layer can be expressed in terms of the thickness of the transparent encapsulation (<italic>t<sub>enc</sub></italic>), the phosphor (<italic>t<sub>p</sub></italic>), and the dielectric (<italic>t<sub>die</sub></italic>) layers:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0040517511420763"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The series capacitance (<italic>C<sub>it</sub></italic>) of the dielectric and transparent encapsulation layers can be given as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-0040517511420763"><label>(11)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>According to Ono,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0040517511420763">15</xref></sup> the threshold voltage of the EL phosphor is governed by the applied electric field through the phosphor layer and its thickness, as shown below:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0040517511420763"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>E<sub>ELt</sub></italic><sub>h</sub> is the threshold electric field to activate the EL phosphor in Mvolts per cm and <italic>d<sub>p</sub></italic> is the phosphor layer thickness in µm.</p>
<p>In order to calculate the luminance <italic>L</italic>, Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0040517511420763">9</xref>) and, (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-0040517511420763">10</xref>) are substituted into Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11-0040517511420763">11</xref>), and the resultant is in turn substituted into Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-0040517511420763">7</xref>). Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula12-0040517511420763">12</xref>) is substituted into Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-0040517511420763">7</xref>). The simplification of the equations as explained above was carried out by using Mathematica, and the result is given below:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0040517511420763"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0040517511420763">13</xref>) gives the luminance of the EL yarn in terms of the thickness of the dielectric, the phosphor and the encapsulation layers of the EL coating, the applied voltage, and the frequency.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec15-0040517511420763"><title>EL yarn driver and illuminance measurement system</title>
<sec id="sec16-0040517511420763"><title>The EL yarn driver</title>
<p>The EL yarn is driven from a personal computer (PC)-controlled inverter. The schematic diagram of the system is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-0040517511420763">Figure 17</xref>.
<fig id="fig17-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 17.</label><caption><p>Personal computer (PC)-controlled inverter. DAQ: data acquisition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig17.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In the system shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-0040517511420763">Figure 17</xref>, the Labview software residing in the PC generates a square waveform. The duty cycle, frequency, and amplitude can be changed to any value as required in the software. This signal is output via an analog output port of the M6259 multifunction data acquisition (DAQ) board to a 50 W audio amplifier. The amplifier amplifies the signal to 11 Vrms. This amplified signal is then fed to the secondary winding of a 230 V/12 V step down transformer, which amplifies it to 300 Vrms. This voltage can be varied by changing the amplitude of the analog output, as generated by the software. The two output leads from the primary winding of the transformer are connected to the EL yarn, with one lead connected to the inner conductive yarn of the coated yarn and the other to the copper strand wound around it. With this system it is possible to drive the EL yarn with the desired AC voltage frequency and duty cycle.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec17-0040517511420763"><title>The illuminance measurement system</title>
<p>The illuminance measurement system was configured as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0040517511420763">Figure 18</xref>.
<fig id="fig18-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 18.</label><caption><p>Illuminance detector system for electroluminescent (EL) yarn. DAQ: data acquisition, PC: personal computer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig18.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0040517511420763">Figure 18</xref>, the luminance flux from the light source is concentrated by a planar convex lens of 30 mm diameter. An ultra-sensitive silicon photo diode with a built-in preamplifier integrated with feedback resistance and capacitance (S8745-01) from Hamamatsu Photonics UK Ltd<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517511420763">18</xref></sup> is placed at the focal point of the lens to collect the maximum luminance flux emanating from the light source. The device generates a voltage signal proportional to the incident luminance flux. This signal is taken via a NI M6259 DA device to a Labview DA application program in the PC. The acquired signal is then low-pass filtered with a cut-off frequency of 1 Hz by the application software to remove any undue interference in the signal and to obtain the DC component. The filtered signal is then measured with an oscilloscope configured in the software.</p>
<p>The system was calibrated using a 625 nm wavelength light-emitting diode (LED) and a lux meter. When obtaining illuminance measurements, the S8745-01 detector, planar convex lens, and the luminescent source were placed inside an enclosure to prevent interference from ambient light. The system was kept in a room devoid of any natural sources of illumination and when obtaining measurements all sources of illumination, except the source under test, were switched off.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec18-0040517511420763"><title>Effect of twists per meter of the outer conductive yarn on the luminescence of the EL yarn</title>
<p>To analyze this effect, three samples of EL yarn of 1 meter length were prepared with the electro-conductive yarn described in the <italic>Electroluminescent yarn construction</italic> section, wound with a 0.174 mm, diameter 40 SWG copper wire. The samples were wound with 400, 200, and 100 turns per meter (TPM); they were denoted as EL400, EL200 and EL100, respectively.</p>
<p>The EL yarns were driven with a square waveform from the driver system explained in the section titled <italic>The EL yarn driver</italic>. The applied rms voltage (<italic>V<sub>rms</sub>)</italic> was measured as 370 V and its frequency was varied from 100 to 2000 Hz. The luminescence was detected using the illuminance detector explained in the section titled <italic>The illuminance measurement system</italic>. The measurements were taken on five random locations of a particular sample. Three sets of readings were taken on a particular location. All the readings were then averaged to obtain the illuminance with respect to the driven frequency of theparticular sample. The measured illuminances of the yarns are given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19-0040517511420763">Figure 19</xref>.
<fig id="fig19-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 19.</label><caption><p>Illuminances of the electroluminescent yarn with different turns per meter (TPM) of the outer conductor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig19.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The luminance of the yarns was simulated using Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0040517511420763">13</xref>). The applied peak voltage (<italic>V<sub>a</sub></italic>) required for Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0040517511420763">13</xref>) was obtained as 523.18 V from the following relationship:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0040517511420763"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The rms threshold voltage of the EL yarn at which illumination can be detected was measured as 60 V using an Agilent 34401A Digital Multimeter. Thus, the peak threshold voltage (<italic>V<sub>th</sub></italic>) of the EL yarn was obtained as 90 V from Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula14-0040517511420763">14</xref>). The permittivity of the transparent encapsulant (<italic>ε<sub>t</sub></italic>) and the dielectric paste (<italic>ε<sub>d</sub></italic>) were obtained from their manufacturers as 3.27 and 40, respectively. The electric permittivity of free space was taken as 8.85419 · 10<sup>- 12</sup> F/m.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0040517511420763">17</xref></sup> The threshold electric field is taken as 1.5 Mvolts/cm [19]. The thickness of the transparent encapsulant (<italic>t<sub>enc</sub></italic>), the phosphor layer (<italic>t<sub>p</sub></italic>), and the dielectric paste (<italic>t<sub>die</sub></italic>) of the yarn were obtained from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0040517511420763">Table 3</xref>. The simulated luminances of the yarn samples are given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20-0040517511420763">Figure 20</xref>.
<fig id="fig20-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 20.</label><caption><p>Luminance of electroluminescent (EL) yarn with different twist per meter of the outer conductor. TPM: turns per meter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig20.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>It can be seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19-0040517511420763">Figures 19</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20-0040517511420763">20</xref> that the luminescence of the EL yarn increases more or less linearly with the frequency of the applied voltage. Moreover, the figures indicate a general trend in the increase of luminescence with the increase of the TPM of the EL yarn.</p>
<p>The illuminance of a single strand of the EL yarn is poor, as it is less than 1 lux; however, the illuminance canbe improved by integrating more EL yarns into a fabric.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec19-0040517511420763"><title>Electroluminescent fabrics and their applications</title>
<p>Fabrics were created from EL yarn by inlaying them in to the knitted structure. An example of a fabric knitted with EL yarn is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig21-0040517511420763">Figure 21</xref>.
<fig id="fig21-0040517511420763" position="float"><label>Figure 21.</label><caption><p>Electroluminescent yarn inlayed in to a fabric knitted from 167 dtex polyester multifilament yarn. (a) Non-excited state. (b)Excited state.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517511420763-fig21.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Unlike fabrics where optical fibers have been integrated, the fabric knitted with EL yarn is flexible. The brightness of its luminescence can be controlled by changing the frequency of the applied voltage. The current consumption by the fabric was measured to be between 10 and 20 mA.</p>
<p>The fabric can be used in the door panel, the headliner, and the boot of the automobile. Conductive pathways can be knitted to the luminescence zone. Further, the luminance zone can be made active using contact switches (K-Switch) technology.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0040517511420763">19</xref></sup> Thus, the K-Switch and the luminescence zone can both be incorporated in a single fabric. The power for the inverter can be obtained from the automotive battery, which has a high capacity.</p>
<p>Furthermore, this fabric can be used in the aisle of an aircraft. The high frequency (400 Hz) of the aircraft AC supply could be used to provide power directly to these fabrics without the use of an inverter.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec20-0040517511420763" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Increasing the twist (TPM) of the outer electro-conductive yarn or fine gauge copper wire, and an increase in frequency of the applied voltage, can improve the luminescence of the EL yarn. The increase of TPM may affect the flexibility of the final fabric if copper wire is used as the outer conductor. However, if a monofilament or multifilament electro-conductive yarn is used instead of the copper wire, this discrepancy could be avoided. Future work will be directed to this aspect.</p>
<p>Operation of the EL fabric at a higher frequency (say more than 1000 Hz) may reduce the lifetime of the EL yarn as the EL coating may deteriorate, as envisaged by the EL ink manufacturers. Thus, the operating frequency and acceptable brightness and expected lifetime of the fabric have to be optimized and tested further.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec21-0040517511420763"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec22-0040517511420763"><title>Conflict of interest statement</title>
<p>None declared.</p></sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0040517511420763"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardcastle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Textiles in automotive engineering</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing Limited</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0040517511420763"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enlightened interiors</article-title>. <source>Aut Eng Int</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0040517511420763"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Makinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuorivirta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of polymeric optical fiber fabrics as illumination elements and textile displays</article-title>. <source>AUTEX Res J</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0040517511420763"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koncar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Optical fiber fabric displays</article-title>. <source>Optica Photonics News</source> <year>2005</year>; <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>April</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0040517511420763"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>SWICOFIL AG Textile Services. ‘Luminous Glowing Yarns’, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.swicofil.com/glowyarn.html">http://www.swicofil.com/glowyarn.html</ext-link> (2006). Date Accessed: May 2007</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0040517511420763"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>SWICOFIL AG Textile Services. ‘Silver Coated Nylon Yarns, Flock and Fibres’, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.swicofil.com/statexshieldex.html">http://www.swicofil.com/statexshieldex.html</ext-link> (2006)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0040517511420763"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DuPont Microcircuit Materials. <italic>Luxprint 8153 Electroluminescent Dielectric Insulator</italic>. North Carolina: E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Company, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0040517511420763"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DuPont Microcircuit Materials. <italic>Luxprint 8150L Long Life White Electroluminescent Phosphor</italic>. North Carolina: E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Company, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0040517511420763"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DuPont Microcircuit Materials. <italic>Luxprint 8152L Long Life Blue Green Electroluminescent Phosphor</italic>. North Carolina: E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Company, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0040517511420763"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DuPont Microcircuit Materials. <italic>Luxprint 8154L Long Life Yellow Green Electroluminescent Phosphor</italic>. North Carolina: E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Company, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0040517511420763"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DYMAX Corporation. <italic>Resilient Clear Encapsulants 9001-E-series</italic>. Torrington, Connecticut, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0040517511420763"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>I &amp; J Fisnar Inc. <italic>Dispensing for all applications</italic>. I &amp; J Fisnar Inc., Wayne, New Jersey; 2004</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0040517511420763"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Edmund Optics Ltd. <italic>Optical and optical instruments catalog</italic>. York: Edmund Optics Ltd, 2006</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0040517511420763"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AEF</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Illumination fundamentals</source>. <publisher-loc>Pasadena, California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Optical Research Associates</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0040517511420763"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name></person-group>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Electroluminescent displays</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>Vol. 1</volume>. <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Scientific Publishing Company Limited</publisher-name>, <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0040517511420763"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balanis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Antenna theory: Analysis and design</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0040517511420763"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duffin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Electricity and magnetism</source>. <publisher-loc>East Yorkshire</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.J Duffin Publishing</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0040517511420763"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hamamatsu Corporation. ‘Si Photodiode with PreampS8745-01,S8746-01’, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hamamatsu.co.uk">http://www.hamamatsu.co.uk</ext-link> (Hamamatsu City, Japan: 2004)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0040517511420763"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKittrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Luminescent inorganic materials, <italic>http://www.4physics.com/phy_demo/glow/luminescent.html, Date accessed May 2007</italic></source> <year>2002</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0040517511420763"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijesiriwardana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Capacitive fiber-meshed transducers for touch and proximity-sensing applications</article-title>. <source>IEEE Sensors J</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>989</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>