<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NMS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnms</journal-id>
<journal-title>New Media &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1461-4448</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7315</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1461444811434402</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1461444811434402</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>David Domingo and Chris Paterson (eds), <italic>Making online news — Volume 2: Newsroom ethnographies in the second decade of internet journalism</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>Thomas F.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1461444811434402">Pennsylvania State University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>539</fpage>
<lpage>541</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds), <source>Making online news – Volume 2: Newsroom ethnographies in the second decade of internet journalism</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <volume>xx</volume> + <page-count count="181"/> pp. ISBN <isbn>9781433110641</isbn>, <price>$36.95</price> (pbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Amid contradictory claims of journalism’s collapse and potential, newsmakers are taking up digital technologies – telling stories to (and with) publics in both familiar and novel ways. Nuanced looks at <italic>how</italic> online news is produced and <italic>why</italic> journalists employ those processes are crucial to understanding contemporary newsmaking.</p>
<p>David Domingo and Chris Paterson’s edited collection, <italic>Making Online News – Volume 2</italic>, provides answers to these nitty-gritty ‘how’ and ‘why’ questions. Twelve ethnographic essays take readers inside online newsrooms and unpack local journalistic processes. The selections are evidence, as Domingo says in the volume’s introduction, of a worldwide ‘boom of newsroom ethnography’ using ‘very diverse theoretical approaches and specific objects of study’ (p. xvi). The selections are also evidence of this scholarship’s quality and insight. The collection includes accounts (mostly from 2007 to 2010) of newsrooms in Denmark, Malaysia, Norway, the USA, UK, and Zimbabwe. Several chapters compare more than one newsroom. Represented outlets include commercial and public media, net-natives, news agencies, blogs, and newsrooms integrated with the major traditional news media.</p>
<p>Each essay includes an editor’s note, descriptions of the newsroom(s) and methods, discussions of key findings/themes, and a conclusion. Domingo’s introduction and Pablo J. Boczowski’s suggestions for future research bookend the ethnographies. Paterson and Domingo’s preface highlights the <italic>Making Online News</italic> series’ utility for teaching online journalism. The editors suggest thematic reading clusters from the two volumes (e.g., professional identity; participatory journalism). Online journalism teachers and researchers alike will find these reading clusters helpful.</p>
<p>The ethnographies are presented in three sections. Section one (five chapters) augments <italic>Volume 1</italic>’s main insights: the digital era’s key structural convergences – multi-media production and audience interactivity – are reshaping journalism’s occupational norms and culture. This process is less direct and more complex than such an assertion may imply. Steve Paulussen, Davy Geens, and Kristel Vandenbrande usefully catalog factors shaping innovation adoption at two Belgian news organizations, and they stress the importance of ‘practical and structural factors’ (p. 13). Anja Bechmann assesses cross-media collaboration among TV, radio, newspaper, and Web editors at a Northern Denmark ‘superdesk’ (p. 15). Bechmann’s analysis of spatial proximities between workers at the superdesk suggests that editors’ interactions are best explained by ‘shared networks of interest such as media similarities, similar work routines, and shared raw materials and news products’ (p. 23). Time is of the essence in Nikki Usher’s study of the US public radio program, <italic>Marketplace</italic>. Podcasts and blogging bolstered humor, listener-engagement, and transparency; however, the program’s ‘broadcast clock’ (p. 49) and routines constrained a more extensive incorporation of online journalism.</p>
<p>Section two (three chapters) looks at how changes in journalistic processes are reshaping news values and formats. Jannie Møller Hartley’s chapter in this section is an assessment of how Gaye <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1461444811434402">Tuchman’s (1978)</xref> seminal news ‘typifications’ (i.e., soft, spot, developing, and continuing news) can be applied to online journalism. This contribution is particularly valuable. Danish online journalists employ classic news typifications; however, routines and news values privilege ‘breaking news’ – ‘the “exclusives” of online news production’ (p. 83). Brooke Van Dam’s account captures this heightened pace in 2008 US presidential election coverage at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Salon.com">Salon.com</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://LATimes.com">LATimes.com</ext-link>. Van Dam points to the production and formats at each outlet as challenges to top-down, control theories of newsmaking.</p>
<p>Section three (four chapters) moves ‘beyond the newsroom’ (p. 113) to understand changes in the broader online news ecosystem. Paterson pairs two decades of news agency research with more recent (although limited) observations. News wholesalers have long been leaders in newsroom convergence, but Patterson points to an ongoing struggle between efforts to detect news and a focus on managing its flow.</p>
<p>C.W. Anderson’s ecosystemic approach to ethnography makes his entry the collection’s strongest, most provocative chapter. He turns to Social Network Analysis and Actor-Network Theory to make sense of the <italic>whole</italic> Philadelphia news ecosystem – ‘journalists, editors, activists, bloggers, and media executives’ (p. 153). Anderson argues that we cannot take the newsroom’s ‘primacy for granted,’ as he points out that ‘digital technologies flatten and disperse the (post)modern workspace’ (pp. 152–153).</p>
<p>Anderson’s and Bechmann’s chapters are among Volume 2’s most methodologically innovative selections. Andy Williams, Karin Wahl Jorgensen, and Claire Wardle deployed a team of researchers with consistent briefing packs into BBC newsrooms at regional, national, and network levels. This allowed the researchers to ‘track where and how audience material circulated both within and among newsrooms’ (p. 119). Steen Steensen combines ethno-methods with textual analysis to understand how the feature journalism genre is being (re)constructed, discursively, at a Norwegian online newspaper. Since each <italic>Making Online News</italic> chapter includes methodological descriptions and reflections, the series represents an indispensable collection for subsequent newsroom ethnographers.</p>
<p><italic>Making Online News – Volume 2</italic>’s selections (like those that came before in <italic>Volume 1</italic>) use technological change as an entry point while avoiding determinism; ethnographic approaches allow researchers to account for a range of contributing processes, including broader commercial and political landscapes. At a US newspaper in the ‘crisis’ (p. 36) of shifting to online-only publication, Sue Robinson shows how multi-skilled reporting and audience interactivity complicated journalists’ understandings of news and their professional identity. Amira Firdaus looks at how (the Malaysian national news agency) BERNAMA’s efforts to market news outside the country produced tensions with its traditionally pro-government ‘journalistic logic’ (p. 144). And amid state censorship, Hayes Mawindi Mabweazara shows how Zimbabwean print journalists use the internet and e-mail to gain new access to news and sources; at the same time, fears of surveillance circumscribe such uses.</p>
<p>While these examples demonstrate the text’s attention to diverse influences, the bearing of race, class, and gender on journalistic processes flies largely beneath the radar. Critiquing what’s missing in a text is poor book review form; however, ethnographic methods are uniquely suited to understanding how social identities shape and are shaped by social practices. Centering processes like gender construction alongside technological innovation, for instance, may offer novel inroads for understanding online journalism’s developing norms and culture.</p>
<p>Another critique would be <italic>Volume 2</italic>’s length. In keeping selections so short (approximately 10–15 pages per chapter), the editors sacrifice some of the richness that makes ethnography great reading. Despite these problems, <italic>Making Online News – Volume 2</italic> is a valuable collection. It furthers understandings of journalism practice in the digital era while moving online news research ‘forward’ (toward texts) and ‘outward’ (into the news ecosystem). Scholars of journalism and new media will find <italic>Volume 2</italic> to be an empirically rich example to inspire their research and teaching.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1461444811434402">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tuchman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Making News: A Study in the Construction of Reality</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>