<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JTC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjtc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Thermoplastic Composite Materials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0892-7057</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-7980</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0892705711401845</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0892705711401845</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Synthesis and Characterization of Polyimide–Silver Nanocomposite Containing Chalcone Moieties in the Main Chain by UV radiation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Faghihi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0892705711401845">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shabanian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0892705711401845">Organic Polymer Research Laboratory, Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Arak University, Arak 38156, Iran</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0892705711401845"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>k-faghihi@araku.ac.ir</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>89</fpage>
<lpage>99</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The soluble polyimide (PI)–silver nanocomposite (PISN) <bold>6a</bold> containing chalcone moieties as a photosensitive group was synthesized successfully by a convenient ultraviolet irradiation technique. A precursor such as AgNO<sub>3</sub> was used as the source of the silver particles. PI <bold>6</bold> was synthesized by the one-step synthesis of PI from polycondensation reaction of 4,4′-diamino chalcone <bold>4</bold> with pyromellitic anhydride <bold>5</bold> in the presence of iso-quinoline solution. The resulting composite film was characterized by Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy, X-ray diffraction, scanning electron microscopy, thermogravimetry analysis, and differential scanning calorimetry.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>polyimide–silver nanocomposite</kwd>
<kwd>chalcone moieties</kwd>
<kwd>thermal properties</kwd>
<kwd>ultraviolet irradiation</kwd></kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0892705711401845"><title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>Polyimides (PIs) are a class of high-performance polymers that have excellent thermal, electrical, and mechanical properties and are widely used in microelectronic devices, such as buffer coatings, interlayer insulation, and wafer-scale packages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0892705711401845">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0892705711401845">2</xref>].</p>
<p>Recently, photosensitive PIs have attracted a great interest, because they simplify processing steps by avoiding the use of photoresists to obtain the desired patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0892705711401845">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0892705711401845">5</xref>].</p>
<p>There is intense interest in the synthesis and properties of metal clusters and nanoparticles prepared in both aqueous and organic solutions and prepared in condensed state, for instance, polymers, zeolites, and glasses. Clusters, nanoparticles, and their containing materials are potentially useful in a wide range of applications, including highly active catalysts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0892705711401845">6</xref>], magnetic materials, quantum dots, and miniaturization of electronic devices and nonlinear optical materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0892705711401845">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0892705711401845">11</xref>].</p>
<p>Various methods can be used to produce metal nanoparticles within a polymeric matrix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0892705711401845">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0892705711401845">13</xref>]. Most of them are based on <italic>in situ</italic> reactions, that is, the particles are generated from the respective metal precursors in the presence of the matrix polymer. Different procedures for the synthesis range from chemical reduction, photoreduction, thermal decomposition to vapor deposition methods and sputtering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0892705711401845">14</xref>]. Several basic routes can be employed, in the case of dispersions, the solution of the metal precursor and the polymer are combined, and the reduction is subsequently performed in solution. Another method is by deposition, where the metal precursor and the polymer are first sprayed onto a substrate, and the reduction to the metal colloids is then performed. The last method is the immersion, where the solid polymeric material is placed into a solution containing the metal precursor. The selection of the polymeric matrix is crucial for the optimization of the systems. Frequently, the polymers are employed not only as protective coatings but also as the dispersing and stabilizing media for the metal nanoparticles. In many cases, the polymers that surround the metal nanoparticles can also exert direct influence on the particles and material properties. Up to now, several types of stabilizing and protective agents for metal nanoparticles have been thoroughly investigated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0892705711401845">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0892705711401845">17</xref>].</p>
<p>In this study, we investigated the preparation of new PI–silver nanocomposite (PISN) by convenient ultraviolet irradiation technique at room temperature. The silver nanoparticles were homogeneously dispersed in the PI matrix and the PISNs exhibited an ultraviolet–visible (UV–vis) absorption peak, corresponding to the characteristic surface Plasmon resonance (SPR) of silver particles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0892705711401845"><title>EXPERIMENTAL</title>
<sec id="sec3-0892705711401845"><title>Materials</title>
<p>All chemicals were purchased from Fluka Chemical Co. (Switzerland), Aldrich Chemical Co. (Milwaukee), Merck Chemical Co. (Germany), and Acros Organics N.V/S.A (Belgium).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0892705711401845"><title>Techniques</title>
<p>Fourier transform infrared (FT-IR) spectra were recorded on Galaxy Series FTIR 5000 spectrophotometer (England). Thermogravimetry analysis (TGA) and differential thermal analysis (DTG) data were taken on a Mettler TA4000 System under N<sub>2</sub> atmosphere at a rate of 10°C/min. The morphologies of PISN <bold>6a</bold> were investigated on Cambridge S260 scanning electron microscope (SEM). The film was cryogenically fractured in liquid nitrogen and then coated with Pt/Pd. Differential scanning calorimetric (DSC) analysis was performed on differential scanning calorimeter (Du Pont 910) at a heating rate of 10°C/min. X-ray diffraction (XRD) was performed on Philips X-Pert (Cu-Kα radiation, <italic>λ</italic> = 0.15405 nm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0892705711401845"><title>Monomer Synthesis</title>
<sec id="sec6-0892705711401845"><title>SYNTHESIS OF 4,4′-DINITROCHALCONE 3</title>
<p>To a solution of 4-nitroacetophenone <bold>1</bold> (1.65 g, 10 mmol) and 4-nitrobenzaldehyde <bold>2</bold> (1.51 g, 10 mmol) in mixture of H<sub>2</sub>O/EtOH (3:1, 100 mL), Na<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>·12H<sub>2</sub>O (0.038 g, 0.1 mmol) was added. The mixture was stirred under reflux conditions for 2 h and then the mixture was cooled to room temperature. The precipitate was filtered off, washed thoroughly with water, and dried to afford 2.72 g <bold>3</bold> (yield 91%). mp: 215–216°C; FT-IR (KBr): 3113 (m), 3086 (w), 3049 (w), 1670 (s), 1599 (s), 1518 (s), 1415 (w, sh), 1338 (s, br), 1288 (s), 1209 (s), 1107 (m), 1028 (s), 987 (m, sh), 839 (s, sh), 787 (m), 742 (m), 682 (m), and 499 (w) cm<sup>−1</sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0892705711401845"><title>SYNTHESIS OF 4,4′-DIAMINOCHALCONE 4</title>
<p>To a solution of Na<sub>2</sub>S (1.56 g, 20 mmol) and NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (1.26 g, 15 mmol) in water (10 mL), methanol (10 mL) was added. The mixture was stirred for 30 min at room temperature. The precipitate was filtered, the filtrate was added to a mixture of 4,4′-dinitrochalcone <bold>3</bold> (1.19 g, 4 mmol) and methanol (100 mL), and stirred for 3 h under reflux conditions. Then, the mixture was concentrated using rotary evaporator, and the residue poured into water, an orange crude product was formed and collected by filtration, washed thoroughly with water, and dried to afford 0.69 g (7) (yield 72%). mp: 177–179°C; FT-IR (KBr): 3485 (w), 3367 (m), 3329 (s), 3213 (w), 1630 (s), 1595 (s, sh), 1512 (s), 1439 (m), 1346 (m), 1300 (m), 1226 (s), 1170 (s), 1024 (m), 983 (w), 815 (m), 611 (w), and 513 (w) cm<sup>−1</sup>. <sup>1</sup>H-NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>), <italic>δ</italic>: 5.84 (br, 4H), 6.58–6.63 (m, 4H), 7.50–7.53 (m, 4H), and 7.88 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 8.6 Hz, 2H) ppm.</p>
<p>Anal. Calcd. for C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>14</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O: C, 75.6; H, 5.9; and N, 11.8; Found: C, 75.4; H, 6.0; and N, 11.6.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0892705711401845"><title>Preparation of PI</title>
<p>A quantity of 5 mmol 4,4′-diamino chalcone <bold>4</bold>, 5 mmol pyromellitic anhydride <bold>5</bold>, and two drops of <italic>iso</italic>-quinoline were dissolved in 25 mL <italic>m</italic>-cresol, consecutively. The mixture was stirred at room temperature for 2 h and then at 180°C for 3 h. The obtained PI solution was precipitated in 100 mL ethanol. The precipitate was immersed in distilled water and ethanol for 2 h, and then washed with distilled water and ethanol several times to remove the residual <italic>m</italic>-cresol. The inherent viscosity of this soluble PI is 0.74 dL/g.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0892705711401845"><title>Preparation of PISN 6a</title>
<p>A 250-W high-pressure mercury lamp was used as the ultraviolet irradiation source. The AgNO<sub>3</sub> was introduced as the source of Ag nanoparticles. First, a solution such as 1.0 g soluble PI in 7.0 mL N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone (NMP) and also a solution of 1.0 mmol AgNO<sub>3</sub>, and 1.2 mmol trifluoroacetic acid in 5.0 mL NMP were prepared. Then, the two solutions were mixed and irradiated for 12 h to ensure the complete reduction of AgNO<sub>3</sub> under ultraviolet irradiation at room temperature. The product was precipitated quickly to distilled water and washed with distilled water several times. Then, the sample was dried in vacuum, redissolved in chloroform by sonication, cast on a glass substrate, and dried at 50°C in vacuum for 2 days.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0892705711401845"><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
<p>Then, 4,4′-dinitrochalcone <bold>3</bold> was reduced using Na<sub>2</sub>S/NaHCO<sub>3</sub> to produce 4,4′-diaminochalcone <bold>4</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0892705711401845">Scheme 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0892705711401845">18</xref>]. The chemical structure and purity of compound <bold>7</bold> were determined by elemental analysis, FT-IR and <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectroscopic techniques. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of compound <bold>7</bold> showed a broad peak at <italic>δ</italic> = 5.75–5.97 ppm, which was assigned to the H<sub>g</sub> and H<sub>h</sub> protons of the NH<sub>2</sub> groups. Peaks at <italic>δ</italic> = 6.58–6.63, <italic>δ</italic> = 7.50–7.53, and <italic>δ</italic> = 7.87–7.90 ppm were assigned to the H<sub>f</sub>, H<sub>e</sub>, H<sub>b</sub>, H<sub>c</sub>, H<sub>d</sub>, and H<sub>a</sub> protons of the phenyl rings and vinyl group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0892705711401845">Figure 1</xref>).
<fig id="fig6-0892705711401845"><label>Scheme 1.</label><caption><p>Synthetic route of diamine <bold><italic>4</italic></bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-sch1.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig1-0892705711401845"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of diamine 4.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<sec id="sec11-0892705711401845"><title>Polymer Synthesis</title>
<p>PI <bold>6</bold> as a source of polymer was synthesized by the one-step synthesis of PI from polycondensation reaction of 4,4′-diamino chalcone <bold>4</bold> with pyromellitic anhydride <bold>5</bold> in <italic>m</italic>-cresol solution and in the presence of <italic>iso</italic>-quinoline as a base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0892705711401845">Scheme 2</xref>).
<fig id="fig7-0892705711401845"><label>Scheme 2.</label><caption><p>Synthetic route of PI 6.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-sch2.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0892705711401845"><title>Preparation of PISN</title>
<p>The soluble PISN was prepared using ultraviolet irradiation is presented in this section. A precursor of the silver (AgNO<sub>3</sub>) particles was used.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0892705711401845"><title>Characterization of PISN</title>
<p>The FT-IR spectrum of PI <bold>6</bold> exhibits characteristic absorption peaks for C=O unsymmetrical stretching of imide groups (at 1776 cm<sup>−1</sup>), C=O symmetrical stretching of imide groups (at 1710 cm<sup>−1</sup>), and C–N stretching of imide groups (at 1380 cm<sup>−1</sup>). These bands show that PI <bold>6</bold> has been successfully synthesized. In addition, no obvious difference between the infrared spectra of the pure PI <bold>6</bold> and the PISN <bold>6a</bold> was observed.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0892705711401845">Figure 2</xref> shows the XRD pattern of the soluble PISN <bold>6a</bold>. The five diffraction peaks in the XRD patterns of samples <bold>6a</bold> widen greatly, indicating the formation of the nanometer scale of silver particles in the PISN. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0892705711401845">Figure 2</xref> containing diffraction signals at 2 h values of 38.2°, 45.3°, 66.1°, 75.5°, and 83.7° attributed to the diffraction planes (1 1 1), (2 0 0), (2 2 0), (3 1 1), and (2 2 2) of fcc silver nanoparticles confirming the presence of silver nanoparticles in the nanocomposites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0892705711401845">19</xref>].
<fig id="fig2-0892705711401845"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>XRD of PISN 6a.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The SEM micrograph of the PISN <bold>6a</bold> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0892705711401845">Figure 3</xref> shows that the silver nanoparticles were homogeneously dispersed in PI matrix.
<fig id="fig3-0892705711401845"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>SEM image of PISN 6a.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0892705711401845"><title>UV–Vis Absorption Characteristics</title>
<p>The photosensitive property of the new polymers <bold>6</bold> and <bold>6a</bold> in the DMF solution was studied by a UV spectrophotometer. The polymer <bold>6</bold> solution exhibits two positions of absorption maximum in UV–vis spectrum around 380 and 270 nm.</p>
<p>The absorption maximum at around 270 nm corresponds to π → π* transition of the olefinic double bond present in the chalcone moiety and carbon double bonds in aromatic rings in the polymer backbone. Also, the absorption maximum at around 380 nm corresponds to <italic>n</italic> → π* transition of the nonbonding electrons present in nitrogen and oxygen atoms in the polymer backbone. The PI shows no obvious absorption at wavelength above 400 nm. The PISN <bold>6a</bold>, however, shows a broadened peak at 418 nm. Overall, the formation of silver nanoparticles was confirmed using SPR phenomenon. This is in agreement with most AgNPs having kmax value in the visible range 400–500 nm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0892705711401845">20</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0892705711401845"><title>Thermal Properties</title>
<p>The thermal properties of pure PI <bold>6</bold> and PISN <bold>6a</bold> were investigated by TGA (in a nitrogen atmosphere at a heating rate of 10°C/min) and DSC experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0892705711401845">Table 1</xref>). The initial decomposition temperatures of 5% and 10% weight losses (<italic>T</italic><sub>5</sub> and <italic>T</italic><sub>10</sub>) and the char yield at 800°C for these samples are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0892705711401845">Table 1</xref>. The temperatures of 5% and 10% weight losses and also the char yield at 800°C of PISN <bold>6a</bold> were higher than the pure PI <bold>6</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0892705711401845">Figure 4</xref>). The higher thermal stability of nanocomposite <bold>6a</bold> can be attributed to the presence of inorganic silver nanoparticles in the PI matrix.
<fig id="fig4-0892705711401845"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>TGA curves of PI 6 and PISN 6a.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0892705711401845" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Thermal behaviors of PI 6 and PISN 6a.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0892705711401845" xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th>Polymer</th>
<th><italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> <sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0892705711401845">a</xref></sup></th>
<th><italic>T</italic><sub>5</sub> (°C)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0892705711401845">b</xref></sup></th>
<th><italic>T</italic><sub>10</sub> (°C)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0892705711401845">b</xref></sup></th>
<th>Char yield<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0892705711401845">c</xref></sup></th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>6</bold></td>
<td>149</td>
<td>370</td>
<td>410</td>
<td>53.89</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>6a</bold></td>
<td>176</td>
<td>410</td>
<td>420</td>
<td>56.19</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0892705711401845"><label>a</label><p>Glass transition temperature was recorded at a heating rate of 10°C/min in a nitrogen atmosphere.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0892705711401845"><label>b</label><p>Temperature at which 5% or 10% weight losses were recorded by TGA at a heating rate of 10°C/min under N<sub>2</sub>.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0892705711401845"><label>c</label><p>Weight percentage of material left after TGA analysis at a maximum temperature of 800°C under N<sub>2</sub>.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Also, the <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> of nanocomposite <bold>6a</bold> was higher than pure PI <bold>6</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0892705711401845">Figure 5</xref>). The increase in the <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> can be attributed to the strong interaction between the silver nanoparticles and polar imide chain.
<fig id="fig5-0892705711401845"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>DSC thermograms of PI 6 and PISN 6a.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711401845-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0892705711401845"><title>CONCLUSION</title>
<p>In this study, a PISN containing chalcone moieties was successfully prepared by a convenient reduction of silver by ultraviolet irradiation technique. PI <bold>6</bold> as a source of polymer was synthesized by the one-step synthesis of PI from polycondensation reaction of 4,4′-diamino chalcone <bold>4</bold> with pyromellitic anhydride <bold>5</bold> in the presence of <italic>iso</italic>-quinoline solution. From the scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and XRD investigations, the silver nanoparticles homogeneously dispersed in the PI matrix. In the UV–vis absorption spectra of the PISN, the absorption peak due to the SPR of silver particles was observed at 418 nm. Due to the presence chalcone moieties in polymer backbone and good thermal properties, these silver/PI nanocomposites can be photosensitive and have the potential for the use in microfabrication of conductive components in microelectronic industry.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0892705711401845"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Polyimides: Fundamentals and Applications</source>, <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0892705711401845"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faghihi</surname><given-names>Kh.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabanian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajibeygi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Optically Active and Organosoluble Poly(amide-imide)s Derived from N,N′-(Pyromellitoyl)bis-L-histidine and Various Diamines: Synthesis and Characterization</article-title>, <source>Macromolecular Research</source>, <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>912</fpage>–<lpage>918</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0892705711401845"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>HSU</surname><given-names>S.L.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Preparation and Properties of Conductive Silver/Photosensitive Polyimide Nanocomposites</article-title>, <source>Journal of Polymer Science Part A: Polymer Chemistry</source>, <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1575</fpage>–<lpage>1583</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0892705711401845"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faghihi</surname><given-names>Kh.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajibeygi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabanian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Photosensitive and Optically Active Poly(amide-imide)s Based on N,N-(pyromellitoyl)-bis-L-amino acid and Dibenzalacetone Moiety in the Main Chain: Synthesis and Characterization</article-title>, <source>Journal of Macromolecular Science Part A: Pure and Applied Chemistry</source>, <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0892705711401845"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faghihi</surname><given-names>Kh.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajibeygi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabanian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and Properties of New Photosensitive and Chiral Poly(amide-imide)s Based on Bicyclo[2,2,2]oct-7-ene-2,3,5,6-tetracarboxylic Diimide and Dibenzalacetonemoieties in the Main Chain</article-title>, <source>Polymer International</source>, <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0892705711401845"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Chemical Catalysis by Colloids and Clusters</article-title>, <source>Chemical Review</source>, <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>2693</fpage>–<lpage>2730</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0892705711401845"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Preparation of Soluble Polyimide–Silver Nanocomposites by a Convenient Ultraviolet Irradiation Technique</article-title>, <source>Materials Chemistry and Physics</source>, <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0892705711401845"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Metal-Polyimide Nanocomposite Films: Single-Stage Synthesis of Silvered Polyimide Films Prepared from Silver(I) Complexes and BPDA/4,4¢-ODA</article-title>, <source>Chemistry Materials</source>, <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>–<lpage>1284</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0892705711401845"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henglein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Small-Particle Research: Physicochemical Properties of Extremely Small Colloidal Metal and Semiconductor Particles</article-title>, <source>Chemical Review</source>, <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1861</fpage>–<lpage>1873</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0892705711401845"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Depth Profile Analysis of the Structure and Composition of a Metal-Implanted Polyimide Surface</article-title>, <source>Surface and Coatings Technology</source>, <volume>196</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0892705711401845"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stucky</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDougall</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Quantum Confinement and Host/Guest Chemistry: Probing a New Dimension</article-title>, <source>Science</source>, <volume>247</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0892705711401845"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbierre</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laaziri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lennox</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Gold Nanoparticle/Polymer Nanocomposites: Dispersion of Nanoparticles as a Function of Capping Agent Molecular Weight and Grafting Density</article-title>, <source>Langmuir</source>, <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>6063</fpage>–<lpage>6072</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0892705711401845"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelsayed</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>Y.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deevi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Polymerization of Butadiene on Nanoparticles’ Surfaces and Formation of Metal/Polymer Nanocomposites</article-title>, <source>Applied Surface Science</source>, <volume>252</volume>: <fpage>3774</fpage>–<lpage>3782</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0892705711401845"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klabunde</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efner</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>T.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ropple</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Solvated Nickel Atoms and Their Free Cluster Formation in Organic Media</article-title>, <source>Journal of American Chemical Society</source>, <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1021</fpage>–<lpage>1023</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0892705711401845"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henglein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Nanometer-Sized Bi Particles in Aqueous Solution: Absorption Spectrum and Some Chemical Properties</article-title>, <source>Journal Physical Chemistry</source>, <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>7656</fpage>–<lpage>7661</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0892705711401845"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faghihi</surname><given-names>Kh.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajibeygi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabanian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Polyimide–Silver Nanocomposite Containing Phosphine Oxide Moieties in the Main Chain: Synthesis and Properties</article-title>, <source>Chinese Chemical Letters</source>, <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1390</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0892705711401845"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burget</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Synthesis of Metal/Polymer Nanocomposite by UV-radiation Curing</article-title>, <source>European Polymer Journal</source>, <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>3180</fpage>–<lpage>3189</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0892705711401845"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faghihi</surname><given-names>Kh.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mozafari</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and Properties of Novel Photosensitive Poly(amide-imide)s Containing Chalcone Moiety and Aromatic Diamines in the Main Chain</article-title>, <source>Turkish Journal of Chemistry</source>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0892705711401845"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>P.S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murali Mohan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varaprasad</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sreedhar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohana Raju</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>First Successful Design of Semi-IPN Hydrogel-Silver Nanocomposites: A Facile Approach for Antibacterial Application</article-title>, <source>Journal of Colloid and Interface Science</source>, <volume>318</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0892705711401845"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasricha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Silver Nanoparticles of Variable Morphology Synthesized in Aqueous Foams as Novel Templates</article-title>, <source>Bulletin Materials Science</source>, <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>