<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spijs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Surg Pathol</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Surgical Pathology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1066-8969</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1940-2465</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1066896912454918</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1066896912454918</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Unicystic Mucoepidermoid Carcinoma Presenting as a Salivary Duct Cyst</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Qannam</surname><given-names>Ahmed</given-names></name>
<degrees>BDS, MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1066896912454918">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>Ibrahim O.</given-names></name>
<degrees>BDS, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1066896912454918">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Al-Kindi</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name>
<degrees>BDS, MSc, FRCD(C)</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1066896912454918">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Al-Hindi</surname><given-names>Maryam</given-names></name>
<degrees>BDS, MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1066896912454918">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1066896912454918"><label>1</label>King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1066896912454918">Ahmed Qannam, Department of Oral Medicine and Diagnostic Oral Sciences, College of Dentistry, King Saud University, PO Box 60169, Riyadh 11545, Saudi Arabia Email: <email>ahmedqannam@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>181</fpage>
<lpage>185</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A cystic swelling in the parotid gland should lead to a differential diagnosis that includes benign cystic lesion of the gland, benign tumors that are frequently associated with cystic degeneration or entirely cystic de novo, or even a malignant neoplasm. The case presented is that of a cystic parotid swelling of 2 years’ duration in a 52-year-old female patient. The clinical differentials in the present case were reviewed and were entirely different from the final histological diagnosis of low-grade mucoepidermoid carcinoma. The uniqueness of this case is the very rare unicystic presentation of the lesion. The authors also discuss why the clinical and radiological investigations were not suggestive of the final diagnosis.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>unicystic</kwd>
<kwd>mucoepidermoid carcinoma</kwd>
<kwd>salivary duct cyst</kwd>
<kwd>parotid gland</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1066896912454918">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 52-year-old woman presented to the Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery Specialist Clinic, College of Dentistry, King Saud University, with a slowly growing right parotid swelling of 2 years’ duration. There was no history of pain or disturbances of facial nerve function. Clinical examination revealed a 4 × 5 cm<sup>2</sup> soft, compressible, nontender right parotid swelling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1066896912454918">Figure 1A</xref>). The swelling was movable and appeared to be fluid-filled on palpation. There were no associated palpable lymph nodes in the neck, and cranial nerve function was grossly normal. Contrast-enhanced CT scan showed an enlarged right parotid gland with a superficially located cystic lesion measuring 3.5 × 3.5 × 2.5 cm<sup>3</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1066896912454918">Figure 1B</xref>). Fine-needle aspiration (FNAC) was done with an inconclusive diagnosis. A clinical impression of idiopathic parotid cystic lesion, pleomorphic adenoma, or Warthin tumor was made.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1066896912454918" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>A. Preoperative photograph of a female patient with a parotid swelling. B. Contrast-enhanced CT scan of the lesion showed it to be located and well outlined on the superficial aspect of the right parotid and clearly cystic. C. The extirpated cystic lesional tissue</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1066896912454918-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Based on our clinical impression and the minimal information from the FNAC, a slightly conservative surgical management was decided on. The goal was to completely extirpate the lesion alongside obtaining a margin of the normal tissue. The patient was scheduled for surgery and underwent a partial superficial parotidectomy under general anesthesia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1066896912454918">Figure 1C</xref>). The tumor was sent for histopathological examination.</p>
<p>An ovoid rubbery mass of yellowish soft tissue measuring 4.5 × 4.0 × 2.0 cm<sup>3</sup> was received for histopathology. The specimen showed glandular tissue at the inferior margin, and the cut surface revealed a large cystic space with yellowish semisolid viscous material. Microscopic examination also revealed a cystic neoplasm lined predominantly by mucous cells and varying proportions of epidermoid, intermediate, and columnar cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1066896912454918">Figure 2</xref>). No cellular anaplasia was seen, and mitotic figures were absent. A few daughter cysts were present in the main cyst wall. Intraluminal extensions of the tumor were seen in a few areas of the main cystic cavity and in some of the daughter cysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1066896912454918">Figures 2A</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1066896912454918">2C</xref>). The tumor cells were positive for mucicarmine (mucous cells), Alcian blue (mucous cells), and p63 (epidermoid cells; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1066896912454918">Figure 3</xref>). Intermediate cells were not positive for p63. The tumor was close to the margins in some areas.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1066896912454918" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>A. Lesion made up of 1 large cystic cavity alongside 4 daughter cysts (hematoxylin and eosin [H &amp; E]; ×12.5). There is no invasion of the connective tissue. B. The tumor tissue is seen as a lining of the cavity with occasional intraluminal papillary projection (H &amp; E; ×50). This is the magnified view of the box in A. C. A magnified view of the area within the box in B stained for mucicarmine (×100)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1066896912454918-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig3-1066896912454918" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>A luminal papillary growth of the tumor from the cyst lining taken from the largest of the daughter cysts, showing abundant mucous cells in addition to epidermoid and intermediate cells (A, hematoxylin and eosin; B, mucicarmine; C, Alcian blue ×100). D. Another part of the lining with mucoepidermoid carcinoma immunostained for p63; the epidermoid cells were well stained, whereas the intermediate cells were not (p63, ×100)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1066896912454918-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>A final diagnosis of low-grade mucoepidermoid carcinoma (MEC) was made. The patient is presently being monitored regularly on a long-term basis for any signs of recurrence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1066896912454918">
<title>Discusssion</title>
<p>MEC is the most common malignant tumor of the parotid gland. It is traditionally divided into low-, intermediate-, and high-grade types based on the criteria laid down by different workers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1066896912454918">1</xref></sup> It is one of the few salivary gland epithelial tumors in which the grade and clinical staging are strongly related to its prognosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1066896912454918">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1066896912454918"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1066896912454918">4</xref></sup> We report the case of a female patient who presented at our center with a moderately large cystic parotid lesion initially thought to be a parotid duct cyst. The clinical and radiographic features of the patient indicated the presence of a superficially located intraparotid cystic lesion more in consonance with parotid duct cyst but which was eventually histologically diagnosed as a low-grade MEC with a unicystic appearance. The objective of the report is to highlight the very rare nature of a unicystic-type low-grade MEC.</p>
<p>Many lesions may present as a cystic mass in the parotid gland. The differential diagnosis of a soft, compressible (appearing cystic), asymptomatic swelling of a relatively long duration should point the clinician toward benign cystic lesions of the gland and some benign neoplasms that are frequently associated with cystic degeneration or that can be entirely cystic de novo. The well-delineated border of the lesion on the superficial aspect of the gland is also supportive of a benign cystic lesion. Our working differential diagnosis, therefore, included a salivary duct cyst, lymphoepithelial cyst, Warthin tumor, cystadenoma, and pleomorphic adenoma, in order of preference in each category, respectively. We initially ruled out a malignancy clinically.</p>
<p>Salivary duct cysts of the parotid gland (parotid duct cyst) are well circumscribed, ovoid, fluctuant, asymptomatic unilocular cystic swelling superficial to or within the gland. Most patients affected have a history of ductal obstruction in the form of calculi, mucous plugs, postoperative or postinflammatory strictures, or even neoplasms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1066896912454918">5</xref></sup> Patients are usually older than 40 years, and the size of the lesion ranges from 0.8 to 10 cm. The cystic contents vary from a serous to a viscid tan fluid. Based on the presentation of our patient, we considered this entity as a very probable diagnosis, although we could not elicit any history of ductal obstruction or any sign of the latter on clinical examination.</p>
<p>Lymphoepithelial cysts of the parotid are almost clinically or grossly indistinguishable from parotid duct cysts in the superficial portion of the gland. The lesion has been reported to occur between the ages of 17 and 79 years, with an average age of 43 years. A recent report suggests a slight female predilection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1066896912454918">6</xref></sup> They range in size between 0.5 and 6 cm in diameter. On palpation and gross examination of the luminal surface, the cyst appears granular or cobblestone-like because of the presence of reactive lymphoid follicles, unlike in parotid duct cysts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1066896912454918">5</xref></sup> The cyst may contain soft yellow-white caseous material, or fluid or jelly-like content. This lesion is also sometimes seen in patients with HIV, usually bilaterally, and is associated with cervical lymhadenopathy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1066896912454918">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Warthin tumor is a benign, cystic, and papillary tumor most commonly seen in the parotid gland. It has been reported in patients aged 12 to 92 years (mean age = 62 years). The sex predilection has gradually equalized over the years owing to increased cigarette smoking in women.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1066896912454918">5</xref></sup> It usually presents as an asymptomatic, well-circumscribed spherical to ovoid swelling in the lower pole of the parotid gland, with size between 2 and 4 cm, although it can grow much larger. It can be partly cystic and solid or almost completely cystic with either a unilocular or multilocular appearance. The cyst fluid may be clear, mucoid, creamy white, or brown.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1066896912454918">5</xref></sup> Up to the point before histological diagnosis, there was no strong evidence to rule out this lesion.</p>
<p>Cystadenoma is a slow-growing, asymptomatic, multicystic, benign epithelial salivary gland tumor commonly seen in the parotid gland. It is more common in women, and the average age of presentation is approximately 57 years (range = 12-89 years).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1066896912454918">8</xref></sup> It may present with a unicystic cavity but more commonly with multicystic cavities surrounded by normal salivary gland tissue or fibrous connective tissue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1066896912454918">9</xref></sup> This diagnosis was not strongly favored because of the unilocular presentation in this patient.</p>
<p>It is almost customary to include pleomorphic adenoma in the diagnosis of any parotid swelling, including those that feel cystic on examination. This is attributable to the protean clinical and morphological presentation of this relatively ubiquitous tumor. Pleomorphic adenoma is usually seen between the ages of 30 and 60 years, is slightly more common in women, and mostly affects the superficial lobe of the gland. It is by far the most common salivary gland tumor. Early stages of the tumor are usually movable but they tend to become nodular and fixed to the underlying structures with time.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1066896912454918">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1066896912454918">10</xref></sup> With a 2-year history in this patient, this diagnosis (pleomorphic adenoma) was more related to fulfilling the obligation of including the chief tumor of the salivary glands (owing to the multiple ways it can present) than it being the most probable cause of the lesion in this patient.</p>
<p>The 3 entities that were strongly considered in our final list of differential diagnoses were parotid duct cyst, lymphoepithelial cyst, and Warthin tumor. However, they were excluded on microscopic examination.</p>
<p>MEC is an epithelial neoplasm characterized by variable presence of mucous, epidermoid, and intermediate cells. The hallmark of low-grade MEC is the presence of prominent cystic structures lined by these cellular components, often with abundant extracellular mucin. The morphology of low-grade MEC is that of a “multicystic” lesion comprising numerous medium- and small-sized “cysts.” These tumors are generally characterized by an attenuated clinical course with very low recurrence, infrequent metastasis, and a very good prognosis.</p>
<p>We compared this relatively unique presentation with all the 21 cases of MECs we have in our archive (1985 to present) and found no lesion with a similar morphological appearance: single, large cavity with closely associated few daughter cysts. An extensive MEDLINE database search for a similar lesion only yielded a single previous report of an MEC with a similar configuration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1066896912454918">11</xref></sup> However, the histology of that case as presented was scanty, unclear, and not similar to the present case.</p>
<p>The gross picture and the histology may partly explain why the FNAC did not yield any result. It is likely that cystic jelly-like fluid devoid of tumor cells was obtained during the aspiration biopsy, particularly if the needle had missed the portion with intraluminal growth and only passed through the area with the thinned out lining of the tumor. The imaging studies were also not very helpful in the diagnosis because of the predominantly unilocular cystic nature of the tumor.</p>
<p>This case can therefore be used to emphasize the need to include MEC in the differential diagnosis of unicystic lesions of the parotid gland. No further surgery was considered after the final histological diagnosis because of the very low-grade presentation of the tumor, with the margins being negative. A monitoring regimen was instituted.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Professor Ilmo Leivo of the Department of Pathology, University of Turku, Finland, for his advice.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1066896912454918">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goode</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>El-Naggar</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mucoepidermoid carcinoma</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eveson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reichart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>World Health Classification of Tumors: Pathology and Genetics of Head and Neck Tumors</source>. <publisher-loc>Lyon, France</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IARC Press</publisher-name>; <volume>2005</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1066896912454918">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brandwein</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mucoepidermoid carcinoma: a clinicopathologic study of 80 patients with special reference to histological grading</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>835</fpage>-<lpage>845</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1066896912454918">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>El-Naggar</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic factors in mucoepidermoid carcinoma of the salivary glands [published online December 16, 2011]</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>2011</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.26697</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1066896912454918">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leivo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makitie</surname><given-names>AA.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Management and outcome of patients with mucoepidermoid carcinoma of major salivary gland origin: a single institution’s 30-year experience</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1066896912454918">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Auclair</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gnepp</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Surgical pathology of the salivary glands</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>LiVolsi</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Major Problems in Pathology</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WB Saunders</publisher-name>; <volume>1991</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1066896912454918">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lymphoepithelial cyst of the parotid gland: its possible histopathogenesis based on clinicopathologic analysis of 64 cases</article-title>. <source>Hum Pathol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>-<lpage>692</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1066896912454918">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Syebele</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butow</surname><given-names>KW.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Comparative study of the effect of antiretroviral therapy on benign lymphoepithelial cyst of parotid glands and ranulas in HIV-positive patients</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1066896912454918">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Skalova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <article-title>Cystadenoma</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eveson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reichart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>World Health Classification of Tumors. Pathology and Genetics of Head and Neck Tumors</source>. <publisher-loc>Lyon, France</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IARC Press</publisher-name>; <volume>2005</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1066896912454918">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Auclair</surname><given-names>PL.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Salivary gland cystadenocarcinomas: a clinicopathologic study of 57 cases</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1440</fpage>-<lpage>1447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1066896912454918">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Damm</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bouquot</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology</source>. <edition>3rd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>St Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders Elsevier</publisher-name>; <volume>2009</volume>:<fpage>478</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1066896912454918">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaik</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soomro</surname><given-names>AG.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Mucoepidermoid carcinoma of parotid presenting as unilocular cyst</article-title>. <source>J Ayub Med Coll Abbottabad</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>