<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Studies in Religion/Sciences Religieuses</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4298</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2042-0587</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/000842981104100103</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_000842981104100103</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews Of Books / Comptes Rendus</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book reviews / Comptes Rendus: Eco-Theology Celia Deane-Drummond Winona, MN: Anselm Academic, 2008. xv + 240 pp.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hrynkow</surname>
<given-names>Christopher</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-000842981104100103">Saint Thomas More College, University of Saskatchewan</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name>
<surname>Rennie</surname>
<given-names>Bryan</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: New Directions for Philosophy of Religion</issue-title>
<fpage>117</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deane-Drummond</surname>
<given-names>Celia</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Winona, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Anselm Academic</publisher-name>, (<year>2008</year>). xv + <page-count count="240"/> pp.
</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) / Le(s) auteur(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This book is offered by Celia Deane-Drummond as both a critical summary of developments in the emerging field of eco-theology and a possible contribution to that sub-discipline. The latter follows from her own “more focused” (viii) stance in relation to diverse ideas in the field that accompanied the writing of <italic>Eco-Theology</italic>. Deane-Drummond suggests that this text will be suitable for students studying the subject matter in depth. She also hopes that it will inspire Religious Studies and Theology departments to take the field seriously and include eco-theology as a focal subject in their course offerings. She draws upon a wide range of thinkers to aid in fulfilling these goals. Her central concern throughout the book is with the implications of ecological thought for Christian tradition and practice.</p>
<p>Deane-Drummond characterizes eco-theology as a contextual form of faith-based reflection that often takes its cues from many of the issues considered to be important by secular environmental movements. These issues include species loss, the connection between human poverty and environmental degradation, patriarchy discerned as an interconnected problem for women and the natural world, pollution, and global climate change. In addressing these issues, the use of the word “ecology” is generally preferred by theologians over the framing of “environment” because the former is more relational in its orientation while the latter implies an anthropocentric framing. Deane-Drummond supports the former framing by an effective argument for the position that ecology is not an option for theology but rather a necessity for theological reflection. This conclusion follows from humanity’s essential location within ecological systems.</p>
<p>In unfolding such themes, Deane-Drummond notes the remarkable phenomenon (which I have also witnessed in my own teaching) whereby students exposed to eco-theological thought speak of the need to change their lifestyles and practices. This phenomenon may be related to a general trend, which is well mapped in this volume, whereby much eco-theological thought is geared towards praxis and/or ethics. During this mapping, the contributions of several Canadian thinkers to the field are mentioned. They include Heather Eaton (Saint Paul University, Ottawa), Stan McKay (the former moderator of the United Church of Canada), Grace Jantzen (born in Saskatchewan; PhD in Philosophy from the University of Calgary) and Anne Marie Dalton (Saint Mary’s University, Halifax).</p>
<p>Several times in this volume, Deane-Drummond seeks to clarify and continue the aforementioned trend towards an eco-ethical praxis. This feature is intensified in the latter chapters of the book. In her own contribution, she attempts to avoid a strong naturalism due to its frequently critiqued tendency to derive “an ought” from “an is.” As such, she bases her recommendations for an eco-ethical updating of theological concepts and faithful Christian living upon the wisdom tradition. An eco-ethical practice of wisdom, she suggests, would permeate all aspects of Christian being in the world, from practical choices in terms of energy use in church buildings, to the genetic modification of organisms and the patenting of life, to eco-liturgics celebrating the beauty and life-giving wonders of creation. Key to this approach is the virtue of prudence, shaded by Deane-Drummond as practical wisdom. Here we come to an intriguing contribution to the field. For prudence in this vein, sustained by a “green” liturgy and praxis-based life of service to people and planet, does have the potential to rework the precautionary principle so important to the environmental movement into a framework that is at once eco-ethical, theo-ethical and integral in the sense of encouraging deep, wisdom-based, contemplation of humanity’s essential location within the natural world.</p>
<p>Crucially, in Deane-Drummond’s framing, this eco-theological praxis is not representative of an context-less utopian formulation in that, for instance, her reflection takes the problems of theodicy seriously. In this regard, delineation of the concept of “shadow sophia” is particularly informative for the eco-theological project. In terms of Deane-Drummond’s analysis, “shadow sophia” is a latent aspect of “creaturely sophia,” both of which are to be understood as separate from the similarly hard to define “divine Wisdom” (Sophia). This formulation will give pause for thought to eco-theologians working within orthodox categories of Christian theology. It allows for the possibility of freedom in the present being expressed in problematic choices supportive of “shadow sophia” that may only become clear in an eschatological future when Sophia itself is made clear to humanity. This concept, by allowing theologians a path to name and come to terms with the presence of anthropogenic evil in the created world, can help eco-theological reflection remain suitably grounded and humble in relation to its task of “greening” Christian thought and practice.</p>
<p>In the introduction to this volume, Deane-Drummond displays a measure of such humility when she confesses that her survey of the material will be somewhat cursory. While she generally presents a good critical summary, at times (for example, during her discussion of Thomas Berry’s work) it seems her presentation is rather shallow in relation to the contributions of certain authors to the eco-theological project. In addition, Deane-Drummond is an incredibly prolific writer. This may have affected the quality of her overall argument in minor ways. As an example, she mentions the importance of “the fifth mark of mission” (180), which rests upon safeguarding the integrity of creation and argues for a prioritizing of “the fifth mark,” in an extensive footnote which lists “the (other) four marks” of mission without noting their source (which is found in documents from the Anglican Communion). Such flaws, however, are outweighed by Deane-Drummond’s thought-provoking contribution in this volume. And in the end, these minor errors may prove to be a fruitful inspiration for discussion if this text is employed in advanced seminars and other appropriate discursive venues.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Christopher Hrynkow<break/><italic>Saint Thomas More College, University of Saskatchewan</italic></sig></sig-block>
</body>
</article>