<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922812456902</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922812456902</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Resident Rounds</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Severe Leg Pain</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>Jake A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812456902">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>Russell W.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812456902">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922812456902"><label>1</label>Ochsner Children’s Health Center and Tulane University School of Medicine, New Orleans, LA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922812456902">Jake A. Kleinman, Ochsner Children’s Health Center and Tulane University School of Medicine, 3504 Laurel St, New Orleans, LA 70115, USA Email: <email>jkleinm1@tulane.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>Unique cases written by pediatric residents with a faculty member.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>1205</fpage>
<lpage>1207</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0009922812456902">
<title>Patient Report</title>
<p>This 5year-old girl with no significant past medical history was admitted with a 5-day history of leg pain and swelling, which progressed to involve her thighs and arms. On admission, she was unable to bear weight on her legs.</p>
<p>She initially presented to her primary care physician 3 weeks prior to admission with fever, sore throat, and an enlarged left submandibular lymph node. She was treated with oral clindamycin and subsequently ampicillin/clavulanate for suspected pyogenic lymphadenitis but without improvement.</p>
<p>On admission to the hospital, additional history revealed that the family had adopted a kitten 1 month prior to the child’s developing the enlarged lymph node. Although neither she nor the family recalled any scratches from the kitten, they did note that the animal had licked the patient’s face and eyes.</p>
<p>Review of systems included fatigue; decreased activity; sore throat 5 weeks prior to admission, which resolved without treatment; and decreased appetite.</p>
<p>On physical exam, her temperature was 96. 0°F, pulse 135 beats/min, respiratory rate 24 breaths/min, and blood pressure 134/85 mm Hg (crying). She was uncomfortable and in pain. There was a 2 × 2 cm<sup>2</sup> nonfluctuant, nonerythematous, mildly tender lymph node in the left submandibular area. She had marked painful swelling of her entire legs bilaterally—nonpitting and nonerythematous—as well as mild swelling of her upper extremities.</p>
<p>Initial laboratory studies yielded a white blood cell count of 20 500/mm<sup>3</sup> (normal 5000-14 500) with 70% polymorphonuclear cell, 2% bands, and 23% lymphocytes; C-reactive protein level of 13.2 (0.1-8.2); erythrocyte sedimentation rate of 42 mm/h (0-20); creatine phosphokinase (CPK) that was highly elevated at 18 986 U/L (20-180); aspartate aminotransferase (AST) of 345 IU/L (10-40); Alanine transaminase (ALT) of 139 IU/L (10-44); and an albumin level of 2.9 mg/dL (3.2-4.7). A viral respiratory panel was Enzyme Immunoassay (EIA) negative for influenza A and B. A bone scan was performed, which revealed no evidence of osteomyelitis.</p>
<p>The patient was started on intravenous rifampin, azithromycin, and gentamicin for suspected cat scratch disease (CSD). Bicarbonate was added to her IV fluids because of proteinuria. After 24 to 48 hours of IV antibiotic therapy, she was noted to have remarkable improvement of her leg pain and swelling. She was discharged on oral rifampin and azithromycin to complete 2 weeks of antimicrobial therapy.</p>
<p><italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> serum antibody concentrations available 5 days after admission revealed an IgM of 1:320 (&lt;1:20) and IgG of &gt;1:1024 (&lt;1:64).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922812456902">
<title>Outpatient Course</title>
<p>After completing her 2-week course of antimicrobial therapy, she was noted to have a persistent fluctuant left-submandibular lymph node. This was drained and subsequently healed without recurrence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922812456902">
<title>Diagnosis</title>
<p>Cat scratch disease with severe myalgia/myositis</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922812456902">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>CSD caused by <italic>B henselae</italic> is the most common cause of chronic lymphadenitis in children, defined as persisting longer than 3 weeks. The disease is most prevalent in Hawaii and the southern part of the United States, where there is high colonization and bacteremia in the cat population.</p>
<p>The most common presentation of CSD is isolated lymphadenopathy, occasionally with fever but rarely with additional associated signs or symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812456902">1</xref></sup> Whereas other presentations exist, such as conjunctivitis, osteomyelitis, and pericarditis, there have been no previously reported cases of myositis with elevated creatine phosphokinase levels. This patient had severe lower-extremity pain from both myositis and edema caused by hypoalbuminemia secondary to proteinuria.</p>
<p>The most well-recognized and reported musculoskeletal manifestation of CSD is osteomyelitis. Few studies have discussed other musculoskeletal findings, including myalgia and myositis. One surveillance study over an 11-year period found that about 5% of CSD patients complained of myalgia and about 10% suffered from all musculoskeletal manifestations combined.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812456902">2</xref></sup> Those most likely to exhibit musculoskeletal involvement were adults, with the median age being 32 years. Children are much less likely to develop myalgia with <italic>B henslae</italic> infection. In this series, osteomyelitis was the rarest musculoskeletal finding associated with CSD. No previous study has examined the incidence of myositis as seen in our patient.</p>
<p>The differential diagnosis of childhood myopathies is challenging. As always, determining the etiology begins with a thorough history focusing on the evolution of the disease manifestations, family history of similar or related diseases, an accurate medication list that includes herbals and supplements, and a detailed social history. A system-based approach is useful to help exclude diseases on the long list of potential etiologies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922812456902">Table 1</xref>). The history can quickly help eliminate some causes of muscle pain or weakness. Seasonal factors are also quite important. During the winter, influenza A and B are certainly the most common causes of both myositis and myalgia in children.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0009922812456902" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>A Partial List of the Important Causes of Childhood Myopathies<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922812456902">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0009922812456902" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812456902-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Category</th>
<th align="center">Causes of Childhood Myositis in the United States</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Idiopathic inflammatory myopathies</td>
<td><bold>Polymyositis</bold>, dermatomyositis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bacterial myositis</td>
<td><bold><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></bold>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812456902">3</xref></sup> Group A <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, pyomyositis, Lyme disease, <italic>Mycoplasma pneumonia, Brucella</italic> spp, <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis, Escherichia coli, Enterobacter</italic> spp, <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp, <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp, <italic>Bacteroides</italic> spp, <italic>Clostridium</italic> spp, <italic>Bartonella</italic> spp</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Viral myositis</td>
<td><bold>Influenza A and B</bold>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812456902">4</xref></sup> HIV, enterovirus, coxsackievirus, echovirus, parvovirus, hepatitis, HTLVI, benign acute myositis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Systemic autoimmune diseases</td>
<td><bold>Juvenile idiopathic arthritis</bold>, systemic lupus erythematosus, systemic sclerosis, mixed connective tissue disease, polyarteritis nodosa, other vasculitides</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Acquired metabolic myopathies</td>
<td>Hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, hypercalcemia, uremia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mitochondrial myopathies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812456902">5</xref></sup></td>
<td>Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, lactic acidosis, stroke (MELAS), myoclonic epilepsy, ragged red fibers, Kearns-Sayre syndrome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Endocrine myopathies</td>
<td><bold>Diabetes mellitus</bold>, hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism, Cushing syndrome/exogenous steroid myopathy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drug-induced myopathy</td>
<td><bold>Glucocorticoids</bold>, hydroxychloroquine, diuretics, caine anesthetics, growth hormone, cimetidine, cyclosporine, colchicine, D-penicillamine</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neurological disorders</td>
<td>Myasthenia gravis, Guillain-Barré syndrome, multiple sclerosis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fungal myositis</td>
<td><bold><italic>Candida</italic> spp</bold>, <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans, Histoplasma capsulatum, Coccidioides</italic> spp</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Parasitic myositis</td>
<td><bold><italic>Trichinella</italic> spp</bold>, toxoplasmosis, filariasis, trypanosome, cysticercosis, <italic>Taenia solium</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other inflammatory conditions</td>
<td>Celiac disease, Chron’s disease, ulcerative colitis</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0009922812456902">
<label>a</label>
<p>The most common causes of myositis in children are given in bold in each category.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In addition to diffuse myositis, <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> is also a rare cause of infectious pyomyositis described primarily in immunocompromised hosts in the United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922812456902">6</xref></sup> Based on this patient’s presentation, it should also be included in the differential diagnosis of children with pyomyositis or myositis. Although admittedly rare in children, it is still an important pathogen with the potential to cause significant morbidity. Pyomyositis is an acute intramuscular bacterial infection that is not from contiguous infection of bone, soft tissue, or penetrating trauma. Myositis may result from any of the above mechanisms. Pyomyositis historically has been well described in tropical regions, most commonly in Africa.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812456902">7</xref></sup> The most common bacterial cause of pyomyositis is <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, normally from hematogenous spread.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812456902">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>The natural host of <italic>B henselae</italic> is most often cats (<italic>Felis catus)</italic>, although dogs can carry and transmit this bacterium. About 10% of pet cats and 33% of feral cats are bacteremic but asymptomatic.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812456902">9</xref></sup> Warmer climates have higher rates of CSD. Infection is spread to humans through either a scratch by an infected host or saliva coming in contact with a mucosal surface. Lymphadenopathy may take weeks to develop, and thus, initial contact with a cat may be difficult to ascertain.</p>
<p>Rifampin is the most effective treatment of <italic>B henselae</italic> infections with an improvement in symptoms in 87% of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922812456902">10</xref></sup> Other effective treatments include gentamicin and azithromycin. Penicillins, cephalosporins, tetracycline, and erythromycin are not clinically effective. Lymphadenopathy can persist for months; however, azithromycin is the only antimicrobial that has been found to decrease lymph node size. Azithromycin is recommended as the initial treatment for children consisting of 10 mg/kg/d on day 1 followed by 5 mg/kg/d for 4 more days. For more serious or systemic infections, such as that present in this case, other antimicrobials and a 2- to 3-week course is recommended.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922812456902">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Florin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaoutis</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaoutis</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Beyond cat scratch disease: widening spectrum of <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>e1413</fpage>-<lpage>1425</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922812456902">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bickels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ephros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Musculoskeletal manifestations of cat scratch disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1535</fpage>-<lpage>1540</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922812456902">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crum-Cianflone</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial, fungal, parasitic, and viral myositis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>473</fpage>-<lpage>494</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922812456902">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical features of influenza A and B in children and association with myositis</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922812456902">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rider</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Juvenile dermatomyositis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Rudolph’s Pediatrics</source>. <edition>22nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Medical</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>:<fpage>821</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922812456902">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crum</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial pyomyositis in the United States</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>420</fpage>-<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922812456902">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Master</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pyomyositis tropicans in Uganda</article-title>. <source>East Afr Med J</source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>-<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922812456902">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sarosi</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pyomyositis in North America: case reports and review</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>668</fpage>-<lpage>677</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922812456902">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piedmont</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bartonellosis. I: <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Biol Clin (Paris)</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>-<lpage>692</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922812456902">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of cat-scratch disease</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Pediatr</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>