<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppig</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part G: Journal of Aerospace Engineering</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4100</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-3025</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954410011426672</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954410011426672</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Performance study of an inlet in supersonic flow</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>Mohammad R</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954410011426672">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954410011426672"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0954410011426672">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954410011426672"><label>1</label>Department of Aerospace Engineering, Sharif University of Technology, Iran</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0954410011426672"><label>2</label>Department of Aerospace Engineering, Sharif University of Technology and Engineering Research Institute, Iran</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954410011426672">Mohammad R Soltani, Department of Aerospace Engineering, Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran. Email: <email>msoltani@sharif.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>159</fpage>
<lpage>174</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The performance characteristics of an axisymmetric inlet at its design and off-design operational conditions are experimentally investigated. The model is tested for wide ranges of free stream Mach numbers, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5–2.5, and mass flow rates. For each test, the pressure recovery, the mass flow passing through the inlet and the pressure distribution over the spike and the cowl are measured. In addition, the shock wave formed in front of the inlet is visualized. The characteristic curve of the inlet is then obtained for each free stream Mach number. As the Mach number is increased, the pressure recovery is reduced, but the maximum value of the mass flow rate grows up. Variations of the mass flow affect the surface pressure over both the front portion of the cowl and the entire surface of the spike. Further, it has changed both pressure and Mach number at the end of the diffuser, which would consequently affect the performance of the propulsion system. In addition, contrary to the internal boundary layer, the external one far from the cowl lip has been found to be almost independent of the inlet mass flow rate for a constant free stream Mach number.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Supersonic inlet</kwd>
<kwd>Mach number effect</kwd>
<kwd>performance at off-design conditions</kwd>
<kwd>boundary layer</kwd>
<kwd>influence of the mass flow rate</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954410011426672" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Inlets are used in all air breathing propulsion systems and have a major role in their operations. Extensive studies have been conducted regarding design and analysis of the inlets. However, up to now, an accurate theoretical method to analyse the flow over and inside the inlet has not been proposed due to the complexity of the problem. Further, numerical methods are not able to completely solve the flow field. Therefore, the newly designed inlets are usually tested in wind tunnels to evaluate their performance. In a supersonic inlet, there are various flow phenomena such as shock waves and their interaction, internal and external shocks and boundary layer separation. The aforementioned variables will make the flow field of the inlet extremely complex and difficult to analyse. As a result, experimental tests are still the main tools for analysis and prediction of the inlet performance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954410011426672">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954410011426672">3</xref></sup> Many studies have been conducted to measure or to calculate the performance parameters of the inlet using experimental and numerical tools. An extensive collection of experimental investigations have been performed on the supersonic inlet in NACA in the 1950s. The main goals of these studies were to find out the physical aspects of the flow around and inside an inlet as well as the effects of free stream conditions on the inlet performance. In addition, the effects of the main geometrical characteristics, such as cone angle and cowl lip radius, were studied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954410011426672">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954410011426672">6</xref></sup> The effect of subsonic diffuser area variations of an axisymmetric inlet was investigated at Mach numbers 1.6, 1.8 and 2.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954410011426672">4</xref></sup> Esenwein and Valerino<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954410011426672">5</xref></sup> measured the pressure along with forces and moments of an external compression inlet. They found that at low angles of attack, the lift and pitching moment remained nearly independent of the mass flow spillage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954410011426672">5</xref></sup> The influence of cone angle on the inlet performance parameters was studied for an axisymmetric inlet by Moeckel et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954410011426672">4</xref></sup> They obtained an optimum semi-cone angle of 25° from their investigation.</p>
<p>Other investigators used various numerical methods to simulate the flow and to predict the performance parameters. Recently, computational fluid dynamics (CFD) approaches are mixed with the optimization techniques to design a high-performance inlet. They changed the major geometrical parameters such as cone angle or cowl leading edge radius and solved the flow over the new inlet using CFD to get the desirable performance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011426672">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954410011426672">9</xref></sup> For instance, Xiong et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954410011426672">9</xref></sup> numerically studied an inlet with different types of cowl leading edges at various Mach numbers, angles of attack and outflow pressures. Hypersonic inlets have also been considered in the past few years.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954410011426672">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954410011426672">12</xref></sup> Nair et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954410011426672">10</xref></sup> used Reynolds-averaged Navier–Stokes to compute the flow through a hypersonic inlet to conduct a detailed aerodynamic analysis. The effects of the position of the sidewall compression and the cowl deflection angle on the inlet performance were investigated to improve the mass flow rate at design point. A few inlet models were designed and tested at Mach numbers 4 and 6. The results showed that the sidewall compression affects the mass flow, whereas the cowl deflection angle manipulates the inlet starting characteristics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954410011426672">11</xref></sup> New methods such as energy addition were used to improve the performance parameters. Chang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954410011426672">12</xref></sup> numerically studied the effects of pulse periodic energy addition to hypersonic inlets and its main factors such as pulsed frequency on the performance parameters. They found that periodic energy addition can improve the inlet performance more than that of the constant energy case.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954410011426672">12</xref></sup> All the numerical studies mentioned above used two-dimensional or axisymmetric solution scheme, except Kim et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954410011426672">13</xref></sup> who solved the three-dimensional flow field. They simulated a supersonic bump inlet flow to find both the growth of the turbulent boundary layer and the characteristics of the shock–boundary layer interaction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954410011426672">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>Extensive experimental tests are still conducted to accurately analyse the flow around and inside an inlet due to the lack of proper numerical or theoretical means.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954410011426672">14</xref></sup> Herrmann et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954410011426672">14</xref></sup> experimentally studied the performance of three chin intakes at a constant free stream Mach number 3 for various angles of attack and sideslip angles, <italic>α</italic> = −30 to 30 and <italic>β</italic> = −30° to 30°. Soltani et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954410011426672">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0954410011426672">19</xref></sup> performed a comprehensive investigation on both the performance and stability of an inlet in a supersonic wind tunnel. They tested an axisymmetric supersonic inlet at various conditions and studied its behaviours at both stable and unstable operations. They also investigated the effect of pressure fluctuations of the propulsion system on the performance of the inlet.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954410011426672">15</xref></sup> Further, the influence of angle of attack on the pressure distribution over the cowl and spike surfaces in a supersonic wind tunnel was studied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954410011426672">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954410011426672">17</xref></sup> They also considered the shock amplitude motion using flow visualization pictures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0954410011426672">18</xref></sup> Detailed characteristics of the flow instability at different free stream conditions were investigated and the results are presented in Soltani et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0954410011426672">18</xref></sup> and Soltani and Farahani.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0954410011426672">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Based on the available data and the results from literature, it is found that many attempts have been made to predict and improve the flow characteristics around and inside the inlets to obtain the performance parameters and improve them, but the predictions are not still reliable. Each inlet has its own special characteristics that could not be accurately predicted yet. In addition, the effects of a few parameters, such as flying at off-designed free stream Mach numbers and angle of attack, on the inlet performance are not still studied in detail. Therefore, to fill the existing gap, in this research, an axisymmetric supersonic external compression inlet designed to operate at a free stream Mach number of 2 was tested for a range of free stream Mach numbers, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5–2.5. The inlet was equipped with accurate pressure sensors that could record both static and total pressure data. External shock structure in front of the inlet was visualized by a shadowgraph system. For each free stream Mach number, tests were conducted at various mass flow rates by means of a plug located at the end of the model. During each test, a complete collection of surface and boundary layer pressure data along with the visualization pictures was obtained. Pressure distribution on the spike surface predicts the locations of the shocks as well as the fluid pressure at the entrance of the propulsion system. Further, the cowl surface pressure contains information about the performance of the cowl lip and the spillage mass flow. In addition, the pressure recovery as a main performance parameter of the inlet is obtained from the total pressure data of a rake installed at the end of the diffuser. Surface static pressures over the spike and the cowl are used to calculate the pressure drag of the inlet. The boundary layer profile over the cowl surface was obtained via a suitably designed rake.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0954410011426672">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0954410011426672">21</xref></sup> It is believed that these information cannot be found so much in detail in the literature. The authors hope that these large amounts of data could help the designers to gain a better understanding of an inlet behaviour at various conditions as well as the CFD experts to improve their codes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954410011426672"><title>Experimental facilities and tests</title>
<sec id="sec3-0954410011426672"><title>Wind tunnel and model</title>
<p>All tests were performed in a continuous trisonic wind tunnel, 0.4 ≤ <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> ≤ 3. This suction-type wind tunnel has a rectangular test section of 60 × 60 cm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954410011426672">2</xref></sup>. The Reynolds number can be varied from 6.5 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954410011426672">6</xref></sup> to 1.3 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011426672">7</xref></sup> per metre<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0954410011426672">22</xref></sup> and the turbulence intensity range is 0.4–1.4%, depending on the free stream Mach number. The glass windows in the sidewalls of the wind tunnel allow observation of the flow pattern and the shock waves over the nose of the inlet via a shadowgraph flow visualization system. The free stream Mach number is controlled by a variable nozzle and by throttling the engine. The flow angle in the test section at free stream Mach number 2 was about 0.5°. A pitot tube is used to measure the free stream Mach number from the Rayleigh pitot tube formula<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0954410011426672">23</xref></sup> with a maximum error of 0.8%. The error of the highest free stream Mach number, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.5, is ±0.02. Note that this uncertainty in the Mach number calculations includes transducer accuracy, data acquisition (DAQ) resolution, etc. The wind tunnel was calibrated for the ranges of Mach number and the flow parameters in the test section, such as flow uniformity, flow angularity and turbulence intensity, which were calculated and within the acceptable range for this type of wind tunnel as mentioned by Pope and Goin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0954410011426672">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>The inlet is an axisymmetric external compression one which is designed and specially manufactured for this investigation. It has a semi-cone angle of 28° and its throat area is selected such as to form a second normal shock in the vicinity of the throat to minimize the losses due to the presence of the shock wave. The model has a fixed geometry with an <italic>L</italic>/<italic>d</italic> of 4.8, <italic>d</italic> = 10 cm, and is designed to operate at a free stream Mach number of 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1</xref>). In this figure, the pressure tab locations and the positions of the inner and outer rakes, <italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub>, are also shown. The mass flow rate passing through the inlet can be varied by means of a plug located at the end of its diffuser, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(a)</xref>. A picture of <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> inner rake which was installed at the end of the diffuser is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(c)</xref>. The model was accurately built and various techniques were used to measure the pressures over and inside the inlet. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(d)</xref> shows the model installed in the wind tunnel.
<fig id="fig1-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Model and its instruments: (a) schematic of the inlet; (b) location of pressure tabs and rakes; (c) picture of <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> rake; and (d) model installed in wind tunnel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954410011426672"><title>Flow visualization system</title>
<p>Shadowgraph flow visualization was used to capture the external shock formation in front of the inlet. The shadowgraph pictures were taken using a high-speed camera, X-PRI, capable of recording 1000 frames/s. The shock wave characteristics are obtained from the pictures recorded by the shadowgraph system at different free stream conditions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954410011426672"><title>Data acquisition system</title>
<p>An accurate and high-resolution A/D card was utilized. The card had 64 channels with 12-bit resolution capable of an acquisition rate of up to 1.25 M samples/s. The conditioner board was designed and manufactured for preparing the input voltage of the sensors and for amplifying their output signals with some proper hardware filters. A special software was set up to acquire and save the data. The board resolution could be varied by setting the maximum input voltage. For example, when the maximum input voltage was ±10 V and the board resolution was ±0.0049 V. However, since the maximum input voltages for all channels were less than 10 V, the board was set to receive a maximum voltage of 10 V, which will result in an output resolution of ±0.0024 V, corresponding to ±24 Pa error for 102 kPa transducer and ±8 Pa error for 34 kPa one. All data were collected at a sample rate of 7000 samples/s for a period of 3–10 s.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954410011426672"><title>Pressure sensors and test procedure</title>
<p>The cowl surface pressure distribution was measured by means of high-sensitive pressure transducers placed at different positions (<italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>2 </sub>… , as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(b)</xref>). The spike surface pressure distribution was measured with pressure probes, S<sub>1</sub>, S<sub>2 </sub>… shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(b)</xref>. At three locations, <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 0.85, 3.4 (both inside the inlet) and <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 4 over the cowl surface, three specially designed rakes were installed to measure the boundary layer profiles and the pressure recoveries at various conditions (<italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(b)</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(c)</xref> shows a picture of the second inner rake (<italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub>) that was built with nine probes for measuring the total pressure distribution. Moreover, the rake <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> was equipped with 10 total pressure probes and a static one and was installed at the end of the cowl surface, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954410011426672">Figure 1(d)</xref>. The diameter of the probe for all rakes was 0.5 mm. The distance between the centres of the two neighbouring probes was 0.7 mm in the vicinity of the wall and was increased on further movement from the surface. Therefore, the maximum error in measuring the boundary layer thickness is about 0.7 mm, the distance between the two neighbouring probes. Thus, using these rakes, the first measured points in the boundary layer was about 0.25 mm above the surface and the second point has a distance of about 0.95 mm from the surface. Further, as mentioned before, the Rayleigh’s pitot formula was used to calculate the approaching Mach number. It was ensured that the internal rakes were installed at points where there was one static pressure hole, exactly at the location of boundary layer measurement. The Mach number was then calculated based on the nine pitot total pressures of the rake and the static pressures underneath the rake. For the external rake, however, there was one static pressure probe whereas the rest of the probes, 10, were all total ones. Thus, Mach number distribution was calculated based on the static and total pressures, all measured by the rake. The differential-type pressure transducers used for this study had an accuracy of ±0.1% based on the full pressure range of each transducer, a natural response frequency of 150 kHz, and infinitesimal resolution in the range 34–102 kPa. In order to increase the accuracy, the low-range pressure transducers, 34 kPa, were used for the important locations such as in the vicinity of the shocks. Since the static pressure range of this investigation is greater than 34 kPa, a known value of pressure on the transducer-referenced port was applied to prevent transducer over ranging.</p>
<p>The model was tested at free stream Mach numbers 1.5, 1.8, 2, 2.2 and 2.5 and at 0° angle of attack. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954410011426672">Table 1</xref> presents the free stream conditions for all tests. For each free stream Mach number, the exit throat area was changed by moving the plug to study the effect of mass flow rate variation on the inlet performance. The mass flow rate was calculated from the data of the inner rake, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub>. From the static and total pressure distributions measured by the <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> rake, the Mach number distribution was obtained. The density distribution was then computed from the Mach number distribution data. Therefore, the mass flow rate was calculated by assuming adiabatic flow, <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> = constant, along with the Mach number and density distributions at the end of the diffuser. The calculated error was about 1.12%. Static and total pressure data as well as the shadowgraph pictures were obtained for all cases.
<table-wrap id="table1-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Free stream conditions of the tests.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954410011426672" xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<tbody align="left">
<tr><th><italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub></th>
<th>1.5</th>
<th>1.8</th>
<th>2.0</th>
<th>2.2</th>
<th>2.5</th>
</tr>
<tr><th><italic>Re</italic> (1/m)</th>
<th>1.27 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011426672">7</xref></sup></th>
<th>1.16 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011426672">7</xref></sup></th>
<th>1.07 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954410011426672">7</xref></sup></th>
<th>9.76 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954410011426672">6</xref></sup></th>
<th>8.42 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954410011426672">6</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> (mbar)</td>
<td>847</td>
<td>846</td>
<td>845</td>
<td>848</td>
<td>847</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> (K)</td>
<td>299</td>
<td>300</td>
<td>301</td>
<td>297</td>
<td>299</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>All experimental data shown in this article were taken several times at different dates to ensure data repeatability. The uncertainties in the mass flow and Reynolds number depend on the measured total and static pressures. As mentioned before, the errors involved in these experiments were due to the pressure transducers, DAQ, calibration and system noise. All of them were analysed based on the method described in Beckwith et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0954410011426672">24</xref></sup> Both the bias uncertainty and the single sample precision in each variable were estimated. The results show that the maximum value of uncertainty of the pressure ratio (<italic>P</italic>/<italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub>) is 1.04%, as shown by an error bar in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954410011426672">Figure 2</xref>. This figure compares the static pressure over the spike surface for two distinct test cases at the same angle of attack, mass flow rate, and especially free stream Mach number but in two different test setups and consequently for different atmospheric conditions such as total pressure and total temperature, Exp<sub>1</sub> and Exp<sub>2</sub>. The differences between the measured data of the two tests are all in the range of 1.04% error and satisfy the repeatability as shown in a zoomed window in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954410011426672">Figure 2</xref>.
<fig id="fig2-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Static pressures on the spike surface for two different test conditions: (a) entire portions of the spike and (b) a zoomed window.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The major measurement inaccuracies of the data and performance parameters are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0954410011426672">Table 2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table2-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Measurement inaccuracies.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0954410011426672" xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Δ<italic>P</italic><sub>0∞</sub> /<italic>P</italic><sub>0∞</sub> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>T</italic><sub>0∞</sub> /<italic>T</italic><sub>0∞</sub> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>ρ</italic><sub>0∞</sub> /<italic>ρ</italic><sub>0∞</sub> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> /<italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>P</italic>/<italic>P</italic> (%)</th>
<th>Δ(<italic>P</italic>/<italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub>) /(<italic>P</italic>/<italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub>) (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>T</italic>/<italic>T</italic> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>ρ</italic>/<italic>ρ</italic> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>u</italic>/<italic>u</italic> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>M</italic>/<italic>M</italic> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>η</italic>/<italic>η</italic> (%)</th>
<th>Δ<italic>Re</italic>/<italic>Re</italic> (%)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>1.12</td>
<td>1.12</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954410011426672"><title>Results and discussions</title>
<p>In this section, the inlet performance at several free stream Mach numbers using the shadowgraph pictures, pressure distribution over both the spike and the cowl, and total pressures obtained from the three rakes is investigated. Furthermore, the characteristic curves of the inlet for all Mach numbers are calculated and examined.</p>
<sec id="sec8-0954410011426672"><title>Flow visualization</title>
<p>The inlet was designed in such a way that a normal shock would form in its diffuser, very close to the inlet throat, which will minimize the losses, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954410011426672">Figure 3</xref>. This figure illustrates the schematic of the shocks at the inlet in a steady operation, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2 and <italic>η</italic> ≈ 0.75, which is near to its design condition, i.e. <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2 and <italic>η</italic> = 0.85. The second normal shock prevents the disturbances in the diffuser from moving upstream, which will affect the inlet performance. Thus, upstream region of the inlet throat is isolated from the propulsion system perturbations which are highly desirable; however, the second normal shock will cause a small total pressure loss. For this inlet, the flow passes through an oblique shock followed by a normal one at the external part of the spike. The subsonic flow then accelerates to a sonic one at the inlet throat and becomes supersonic through the diffuser until the second normal shock appears due to the pressure matching at the end of the diffuser (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954410011426672">Figure 3</xref>). Shadowgraph flow visualization was used to capture the external shock formed in front of the inlet as well as to investigate the shock structure of the inlet at different experimental conditions. From these pictures, geometrical characteristics of the shock wave such as their angles and locations are easily obtained. These pictures were analysed using CAD software, and the angle of attack was measured with a maximum error of ±0.1° and the cone shock angle was measured to be 46.4° which is comparable with its theoretical value of 45.8°. Influence of the Mach number on the inlet shock structure at different mass flow rates is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>. These <italic>η</italic>s, except <italic>η</italic> = 0.217, were chosen to attain a same shock structure for all free stream Mach numbers, which will be used in the following sections. For <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5 and at low mass flow rate, <italic>η</italic> = 0.217, a bow shock with a considerable shock standoff distance forms in front of the spike (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>). At this situation, the mass flow spillage over the cowl surface is high and an oblique shock appears on the cowl near its lip. When the mass flow increases, the bow shock gets closer to the spike nose forming an oblique shock as seen for the case <italic>η</italic> = 0.584 and <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5 shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>. For other free stream Mach numbers, an oblique shock forms in front of the spike and the flow spillage decreases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>). Increasing the free stream Mach number reduces the nose shock angle and pushes the first normal shock towards the cowl lip as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>). For <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> ≥ 1.5, it is clearly seen that both the spike oblique and the normal shocks formed in front of the cowl merge with each other and form a single oblique shock wave (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>). Furthermore, as the free stream Mach number increases, the merged shocks get closer to the cowl lip.
<fig id="fig3-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Schematic of the shocks structure of the inlet, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2 and <italic>η</italic> ≈ 0.75.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Effects of the Mach number variations on the shock system of the inlet.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954410011426672"><title>Effect of Mach number on the spike surface pressure</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5</xref> shows the effects of the mass flow rate on the pressure distributions of the spike at various mass flow rates and for different Mach numbers, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5–2.5. The influence of the mass flow rate is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(a)</xref> for <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2, i.e. the design Mach number. The variations of pressure in front portion of the spike are significant; therefore, the zoomed details of this zone are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(b)</xref>. In addition, the positions of both external and internal normal shocks are determined from the pressure data in this figure. The first jump in the pressure data corresponds to the first normal shock, located at the inlet entrance, while the next one, which occurs only when the mass flow is greater than 0.7 is due to the second normal shock and forms near the end of the diffuser as previously explained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954410011426672">Figure 3</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(b)</xref> clearly shows the aforementioned shock waves. The first normal shock position is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(b)</xref> as an arrow. It is clearly seen that there exists a jump in <italic>P</italic>/<italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub>, for example, around <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.18 for <italic>η</italic> = 0.824. This jump in <italic>P</italic>/<italic>P</italic><sub>∞</sub> is referred to the first normal shock, which is also obvious in the visualization picture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>). The second jump occurs at about <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 1.35 inside the inlet for the same <italic>η</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(b)</xref>). This second jump is referred to the second normal shock. For <italic>η</italic> = 0.902, the jump at <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 1.5 in the pressure data is due to the weak oblique shock formed in front of the strut system of the model, while the jump located at <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 2.6 is the normal shock. The rise in pressure depends on the distance between throat and location of the normal shock. For instance, for a normal shock located at <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.9 (5 mm after the throat), the upstream Mach number is 1.03, resulting in pressure ratio 1.07. These theoretical results are close to those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figire 5(b)</xref> for <italic>η</italic> = 0.818; therefore, the small jump after throat for <italic>η</italic> = 0.818 is related to a weak normal shock. As the normal shock reaches the location of <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 1.35 (by opening the plug), the theoretical pressure rise through a normal shock is 1.61 <italic>p</italic><sub>∞</sub>, which is comparable with experimental results for <italic>η</italic> = 0.824, i.e. 1.5 p<sub>∞</sub> as seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(a)</xref> or (b). The mentioned results confirm the existence of the second normal shock into the diffuser. The location and occurrence of the second normal shock are related to the amount of pressure at the diffuser end which is varied by the plug during the test. The plug simulates the effect of the propulsion system in the inlet performance in a real operation. The second shock is formed at a location that unifies the back pressure with the pressure at the diffuser end, similar to the normal shock formed in the divergent part of a convergent–divergent nozzle. The pressure of diffuser at its end is named as ‘back pressure’ in this article. When the back pressure is decreased (by opening the plug), the second normal shock moves downstream and becomes stronger, as a result, the total pressure loss increases. Consequently, the first normal shock moves downstream and <italic>η</italic> increases. Therefore, the pressure jump due to the second shock moves towards the cowl lip and the pressure over its upstream region reduces as seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(b)</xref>. However, an increment in the back pressure will reduce <italic>η</italic>, the second normal shock is then pushed towards the inlet throat, and it may even disappear for some values of <italic>η</italic>, <italic>η</italic> = 0.556 as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(a)</xref>. At each operational condition, the back pressure is an important inlet performance parameter and indicates the conditions of the flow entering the propulsion system. In the vicinity of the inlet designed condition, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2, <italic>η</italic> ≈ 0.8, the back pressure slightly changes by varying the mass flow with the plug throttling. If the plug is further opened, the back pressure will considerably reduce and the second normal shock will then move far from the throat, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">b</xref>) for <italic>η</italic> = 0.902. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(c)</xref> also shows the position of the second normal shock, <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic>, with the mass flow, <italic>η</italic>, along the diffuser length for a free stream Mach number of 2. The second normal shock slowly moves downstream for the mass flow rates near the designed conditions, which is desirable since the shock strength grows slightly and causes low pressure loss. After that, the shock wave moves abruptly towards the diffuser end, for <italic>η</italic> &gt; 0.8, and becomes stronger at off-design operation of the inlet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(c)</xref>), which is not desirable.
<fig id="fig5-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Pressure distributions over the spike: (a) effect of mass flow rate at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2; (b) details of pressure variations in the front portion of the spike and the locations of the shocks at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2; (c) variations of the location of the second normal shock at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2; and (d) influence of free stream Mach number.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(d)</xref> compares the pressure distribution on the spike for different free stream Mach numbers. The mass flow rates are the same as those of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref> and they were chosen in a way that the shock structure, especially the position of the second normal shock, was the same for all free stream Mach numbers, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5–2.5. Therefore, all cases shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(c)</xref> have approximately unique shock structures. Other parameters such as pressure over the cowl and internal and external boundary layer profiles will be compared at the same mass flow rates, <italic>η</italic> = 0.584–0.809, in the following sections. The shock structure and consequently the pressure distribution for the case <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5 are different from the cases with other Mach numbers as evident from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>. At this free stream Mach number, the first normal shock is not present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>); hence, the corresponding pressure jump cannot be seen from the data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(d)</xref>. As the free stream Mach number increases, the static pressure over the entire surface of the spike, especially at the face of the propulsion system, increases, which is usually desirable for the combustion processes. Furthermore, by increasing the free stream Mach number, the differences between the maximum and the minimum values of the pressure increase, which causes more adverse pressure gradient, particularly near the spike nose, and consequently encourage flow separation. The growth of this separation region can lead to flow instability, which must be avoided.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0954410011426672"><title>Effect of Mach number on the cowl surface pressure</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954410011426672">Figure 6</xref> shows the variations of pressure over the outer surface of the cowl for a free stream Mach number of 1.5 and for different mass flow rates. Further, a zoomed window of the pressure distribution in the vicinity of the cowl lip that has the largest variations is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954410011426672">Figure 6(b)</xref>. As previously seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>, a relatively weak shock is formed near the cowl lip. The flow behind the shock is still supersonic and it expands along the front portion of the cowl surface because of its convex shape. However, when the cowl curvature changes, the flow will be compressed until the slope of the surface becomes constant. The flow will then expand at the end portion of the body since the slope varies. When the mass flow rate is reduced, the shock wave that is created on the cowl surface moves downstream and the static pressure in the front portion of the cowl decreases. At mass flow rates lower than 0.4, <italic>η</italic> = 0.246 or <italic>η</italic> = 0.372, the pressure jump for this shock is clearly seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954410011426672">Figure 6</xref>; however, for <italic>η</italic> &gt; 0.4, the shock is formed before the first pressure tab and cannot be seen in the pressure data of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954410011426672">Figure 6</xref>. The pressure behind the shock decreases because of the flow expansion process previously mentioned. As the cowl curvature changes, a small compression region followed by a constant pressure over the inclined portion of the body surface is seen in the data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954410011426672">Figure 6(a)</xref>. For <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5, the pressure over the inclined section of the cowl varies with the mass flow rate, especially for <italic>η</italic> = 0.658. This behaviour is probably related to a particular shock structure formed for this free stream Mach number. Note that at <italic>η</italic> &lt; 0.5, a bow shock is formed in front of the spike; however, at the highest mass flow rate, <italic>η</italic> = 0.658, an oblique shock is formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>).
<fig id="fig6-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Effect of mass flow rate on the pressure distributions over the outer surface of the cowl at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5: (a) pressure over the whole surface of the cowl and (b) pressure distribution near the cowl lip.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The pressure data for a free stream Mach number of 2 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">Figure 7(a)</xref>. The details of pressure distribution near the cowl lip are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">Figure 7(b)</xref>. From these figures, it is clearly seen that the mass flow rate variations do not have significant effects on the external flow pressure contrary to the internal one previously seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5</xref>). The shock wave formed in front of the cowl surface is located ahead of the first pressure tab; hence, it cannot be seen from the data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">Figure 7(a)</xref> or (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">b</xref>). The static pressure away from the cowl lip is almost independent of the mass flow rate for this free stream Mach number, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2. In addition, comparison of the experimental pressure distributions at a free stream Mach number of 2 with the linearized potential theory<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0954410011426672">24</xref></sup> shows a relatively good agreement for a zone near the cowl lip and for the highest mass flow rate. This prediction was obtained for the mass flow ratio of 1; for the mass flow rates smaller than 1, a small region of separated flow is formed at the cowl lip that affects the downstream flow; thus, the linearized theory is not valid at these conditions and cannot correctly predict the pressure, as seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">Figure 7</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">Figure 7(c)</xref> shows the variation of the base pressure of the inlet with the mass flow rate. Increasing <italic>η</italic>, decreases the base pressure slightly. It seems that an increment in the mass passing through the end of the nozzle causes a vacuum region behind the inlet and decreases the corresponding pressure; hence, the base pressure slightly reduces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954410011426672">Figure 7(c)</xref>).
<fig id="fig7-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Effect of mass flow rate on the external surface pressure of the inlet at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2: (a) experimental and theoretical pressure distributions over the outer surface of the cowl; (b) pressure distribution near the cowl lip; and (c) base pressure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954410011426672">Figure 8(a)</xref> shows the effect of free stream Mach number on the pressure distribution over the cowl outer surface when operating near its designed mass flow rate, <italic>η</italic> = 0.85 at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2. The details of pressure distribution near the cowl lip are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954410011426672">Figure 8(b)</xref>. As the free stream Mach number increases, the static pressure in the vicinity of the cowl lip increases; however, further from the cowl lip, the static pressure reduces with increasing free stream Mach number. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954410011426672">Figure 8</xref>, it is seen that the free stream Mach number does not significantly affect the trend of the pressure variation along the cowl surface; it only varies the value of the pressure at each location. However, for a free stream Mach number of 2.5 near the cowl lip, around <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.3, the variations are different, which is probably due to the existence of a relatively strong normal shock located in front of the inlet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954410011426672">Figure 8(b)</xref>). Moreover, at this Mach number, the cowl surface shock wave is pushed behind the first pressure tab and its corresponding pressure jump can be clearly seen from the data presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954410011426672">Figure 8(b)</xref> for <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.5.
<fig id="fig8-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Influence of free stream Mach number on the pressure distributions over the outer surface of the cowl: (a) pressure distributions over the outer surface of the cowl at different free stream Mach numbers and (b) details of pressure distributions near the cowl lip.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0954410011426672"><title>Effect on the inner total pressure</title>
<p>The effect of free stream Mach number on the total pressure distributions at a location, <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 0.85, of the internal duct is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954410011426672">Figure 9</xref>. These results which were measured by the <italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub> rake, demonstrate losses due to the external shocks and the friction in the front portion of the inlet throat. The values of the mass flow rates are the same as those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figures 5(d)</xref> and 8. As the free stream Mach number increases, the strength of the shock wave and consequently total pressure losses will increase. This figure clearly shows that for cases <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.2 and 2.5, the total pressure losses are greater than those of the other cases, which are in accordance with the shadowgraph photos shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>.
<fig id="fig9-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Effect of Mach number on the total pressure distribution at <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 0.85, <italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub> rake.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The data of the <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> rake for <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2, the designed Mach number of this particular inlet, are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011426672">Figure 10</xref> for different values of mass flow rates. This rake is located at the end of the diffuser; therefore, it can measure the pressure recovery which is a main performance parameter for an inlet. As previously mentioned, by opening the plug located at the end of the inlet, the second normal shock moves downstream and becomes stronger; thus, the inlet loss will increase. For <italic>η</italic> = 0.902, the highest possible mass flow rate case, the second normal shock moves downstream through the diffuser and becomes very strong (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954410011426672">Figure 5(b)</xref>), and causes considerable pressure loss, as seen from the data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011426672">Figure 10</xref>. Further, it is seen that for this case, the thickness of the boundary layer is much more than those for other <italic>η</italic>s, which might be an indication of the shock strength. As <italic>r</italic>/<italic>r</italic><sub>local</sub> increases, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011426672">Figure 10</xref> shows that for <italic>η</italic> = 0.902, <italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>0∞</sub> increases until for <italic>r</italic>/<italic>r</italic><sub>local</sub> ≈ 0.35, where it reaches its maximum value and then <italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>0∞</sub> starts decreasing from <italic>r</italic>/<italic>r</italic><sub>local</sub> ≈ 0.5 and beyond. For all other <italic>η</italic>s, <italic>η</italic> &lt; 0.902, and for all <italic>r</italic>/<italic>r</italic><sub>local</sub> values, <italic>P</italic><sub>0</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>0∞</sub> is almost constant which indicates that the normal shock waves formed at the diffuser are relatively weak.
<fig id="fig10-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Variations of total pressure distribution (pressure recovery) with mass flow rate at the end of the inlet, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> rake, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig10.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954410011426672">Figure 11</xref> shows the pressure distribution at the end of the diffuser, <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 3.4, for all five free stream Mach numbers tested in this study. The variations of total pressure with the mass flow rate was previously investigated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011426672">Figure 10</xref>). The effect of free stream Mach number on the pressure recovery is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954410011426672">Figure 11(a)</xref> for the value of mass flow rate near the designed condition for that specific Mach number. For a free stream Mach number of 1.5, the pressure recovery is about 0.85. Increasing the free stream Mach number decreases the pressure recovery because the shock wave becomes stronger, a phenomenon that is not desirable. For <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.2 and <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.5, which are greater than the designed Mach number, an instability occurs, which causes large amplitude shock movement along with a large pressure fluctuation. This phenomenon is responsible for the high total pressure loss and reduces PR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954410011426672">Figure 11(a)</xref>). Some supersonic inlets have an instability mode known as buzz phenomenon. This supersonic inlet instability is due to the self-sustained shock oscillations and occurs when the entering mass flow is reduced below a particular value. The buzz instability creates significant variations in the inlet pressure and mass flow and can cause undesirable events such as engine surge, thrust loss, or even structural damages to the propulsion system. Please refer to Trapier et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954410011426672">25</xref></sup> for a detailed description of the aforementioned phenomenon. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954410011426672">Figure 11(b)</xref> shows the ratio of the total pressure distribution to the free stream pressure for various free stream Mach numbers. As M<sub>∞</sub> is increased, the pressure at the engine face is increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954410011426672">Figure 11(b)</xref>), which is usually desirable for the engine performance.
<fig id="fig11-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Effect of Mach number on the flow conditions in the end of the inlet, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> rake: (a) pressure recovery and (b) total pressure distribution.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig11.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0954410011426672"><title>Effect on external boundary layer</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(a)</xref> shows the boundary layer profile for different values of the mass flow rates at a constant free stream Mach number of 2. The boundary layer was allowed to naturally transit from laminar to turbulent without any artificial transition mechanisms. Forced transition is usually used for the study of either roughness effect or Reynolds number similarity. Because our model was not a scaled down version of a real vehicle, it was not necessary to apply the Reynolds number similarity. All graphs were plotted for the external portion of the cowl at a location of <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 4, <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> rake data. The data show that the mass flow does not have significant effect on the external boundary layer profile contrary to the internal one, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> rake data, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954410011426672">Figure 10</xref>. The boundary layer profile slightly varies for different <italic>η</italic>s. For a free stream Mach number of 2 and for <italic>η</italic> = 0.36, the boundary layer thickness is about <italic>r</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.21 and it decreases to <italic>r</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.17 for the highest mass flow, <italic>η</italic> = 0.902. It thickens by reducing the value of <italic>η</italic> and its slope at the wall increases by the enhancement of the spillage mass flow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(a)</xref>). Comparison of the experimental data for the cases, <italic>η</italic> = 0.902 and <italic>η</italic> = 0.824, with the theoretical prediction is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(b)</xref>. For the free stream Mach number of 2 and for the range of mass flows considered in this investigation, the velocity profiles in the boundary layer are in good agreement with the 1/7 power law. Usually, the 1/7 power law is applied to a flat plate boundary layer without pressure gradients.
<fig id="fig12-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>External boundary layer profiles at <italic>x</italic>/<italic>d</italic> = 4, <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> rake: (a) influence of mass flow rates at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.0; (b) comparison of experimental and theoretical boundary layer profiles at <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.0; (c) effect of free stream Mach numbers; and (d) details of boundary layer near the wall.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig12.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(c)</xref> shows an in-depth effect of the free stream Mach number on the boundary layer profile over the cowl surface. The shape of the boundary layer is qualitatively the same for all free stream Mach numbers, but a small difference in the slope of the boundary layer at the wall is seen as the Mach number is varied, which is related to the skin friction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(d)</xref>). Further, from this figure, it is clearly seen that the boundary layer thickness increases with increase in the free stream Mach number. As previously mentioned, the maximum error in the boundary layer measurement is about 0.7 mm. The boundary layer thickness was measured up to a position where the velocity reaches 99% of its free stream value, <italic>u</italic> = 0.99 <italic>u</italic><sub>∞</sub>. In addition, the non-dimensional thickness to the subsonic layer, <italic>δ</italic><sub>sub</sub>/<italic>d</italic>, is less than 0.01 for all free stream Mach numbers tested, while the maximum value of the ratio of the boundary layer thickness to body diameter, <italic>δ</italic>/<italic>d</italic>, is about 0.25, i.e. the subsonic layer is about 4% of the total boundary layer thickness (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0954410011426672">Table 3</xref>). For <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5, the boundary layer profile reaches the free stream Mach number at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.11. As seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(c)</xref>, for <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.2, the boundary layer thickness is around <italic>r</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.22 and for a free stream Mach number of 2.5, the boundary layer profile varies more than the other cases, lower <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub>s, and has a thickness of <italic>r</italic>/<italic>d</italic> ≈ 0.25. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(a)</xref> shows that at a constant free stream Mach number, the boundary layer profile on the cowl surface for a location far from the cowl lip is almost independent of the mass flow rates. However, the free stream Mach number slightly changes its profile, as seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954410011426672">Figure 12(c), (d)</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0954410011426672">Table 3</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table3-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Boundary layer thickness at different free stream Mach numbers.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0954410011426672" xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th><italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub></th>
<th><italic>δ</italic>/<italic>d</italic></th>
<th>Position uncertainty (%)</th>
<th>Mach number error</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>6.8</td>
<td>±0.0120</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>5.0</td>
<td>±0.0144</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td>±0.0160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>±0.0176</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>±0.0200</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Further, the amounts of uncertainty in boundary layer thickness and errors of Mach number measurements by the rake, <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub>, are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0954410011426672">Table 3</xref>. Increasing the free stream Mach number reduces the error in the measurement of the boundary layer thickness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0954410011426672"><title>Characteristic curve</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954410011426672">Figure 13</xref> shows the characteristic curves of the inlet at different free stream Mach numbers. This graph shows the effects of the two main important performance parameters of an inlet, i.e. mass flow rate and pressure recovery. As seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954410011426672">Figure 13</xref>, variations of the pressure recovery with <italic>η</italic> for 1.8 ≤ <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> ≤2.2 are almost independent of the free stream Mach number. The case of <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5 has the maximum pressure recovery, while the highest mass flow rate is attained at a free stream Mach number of 2.5, but the pressure recovery decreases due to changes in the shock wave structure that forms in the inlet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954410011426672">Figure 13</xref>). As the free stream Mach number increases, the corresponding shock wave becomes stronger and causes more losses in the PR. In addition, it will decrease the shock angle that forms at the nose of the spike and reduce the mass spillage. At a free stream Mach number of 2, which is the designed Mach number for this inlet, the nose oblique shock crosses close to the cowl lip, and will reach the cowl lip and even it will enter the inlet as the free stream Mach number is further increased. For the free stream Mach number of 2.5, the inlet operates at its supercritical stage; thus, the mass flow rate rarely becomes greater than 1, as seen from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954410011426672">Figure 13</xref>. Note that only for the case <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2.5, the mass flow rate becomes slightly greater than 1. Further, from this figure, it is clearly seen that for <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> ≥ 1.8, by increasing the mass flow, the PR slightly increases until it reaches its maximum value; beyond that, it abruptly reduces. The curve of <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 1.5 shows that PR reduces as <italic>η</italic> increases, contrary to the other Mach number cases, <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> &gt; 1.5. Note that the shock structure for a free stream Mach number of 1.5 is fundamentally different from that of the other cases, as previously mentioned and seen from the flow visualization of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954410011426672">Figure 4</xref>.
<fig id="fig13-0954410011426672" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>Characteristic curve of the inlet at different Mach numbers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954410011426672-fig13.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0954410011426672"><title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>An axisymmetric inlet was tested for a wide range of supersonic speeds and for several values of the mass flow rates. The experiments were carried out to study the inlet performance at various conditions. The inlet was designed to operate at its subcritical mode and at a free stream Mach number of 2. In this research, pressure distributions over the inlet spike and cowl were measured and the flow was visualized using the shadowgraph technique. An external rake was used to measure the boundary layer profile at different conditions. Two internal rakes were used to measure the inlet pressure recovery for each test. In addition, the effects of both free stream Mach number and mass flow rate on the inlet performance were studied. The pressure data as well as the shadowgraph pictures were recorded during each test. The main outcomes of this study were as follows.
<list id="list1-0954410011426672" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>At a free stream Mach number of 1.5, the nose shock was detached for the <italic>η</italic> &lt; 0.5 and the pressures at various locations showed different behaviours.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The mass flow significantly affected the pressure over the entire surface of the spike. This effect was most considerable for the diffuser, where the second normal shock occurred. Increasing the free stream Mach number enhanced the pressure on the whole surface of the spike without any considerable change in the shape of the pressure distribution.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Variations of the mass flow rate noticeably influenced the pressure in the front portion of the cowl. However, the free stream Mach number changed the pressure over the entire surface of the cowl.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Inlet mass flow rate changed both the pressure and the Mach number at the end of the diffuser, and consequently affected the performance of the propulsion system. The pressure loss and the Mach number at the engine face increased with increasing the free stream Mach number.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The boundary layer profile at the end of the cowl outer surface was seen to be nearly independent of the inlet mass flow rate for each free stream Mach number contrary to the internal one. However, increasing the free stream Mach number increases the thickness of the boundary layer and reduces its slope at the wall.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Comparison of the experimental data with the theoretical predictions showed that the cowl surface pressure only at a mass flow rate of 1 can be calculated with reasonable accuracy using the linearized potential theory. The boundary layer velocity profiles are in good agreement with those predicted by the 1/7 power law. In addition, this experimental results show that the boundary layer profile is almost independent of the mass flow rate when operating near the design condition, i.e. <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> = 2, <italic>η</italic> = 0.85.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Variation of the pressure recovery with the inlet mass flow rate was almost independent of the free stream Mach number for 1.8 ≤ <italic>M</italic><sub>∞</sub> ≤ 2.2, i.e. near the design condition. The pressure recovery was reduced when the free stream Mach number was increased, which was caused by the strengthening of the shocks. Furthermore, maximum value of the mass flow rate was increased too.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec18-0954410011426672"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This project was partially supported by the Engineering Research Institute, which is greatly appreciated.</p></sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954410011426672"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Intake aerodynamics</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Science</publisher-name>, <year>1999</year>, pp.<fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954410011426672"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Inlets for supersonic missiles</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AIAA Press</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>, pp.<fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954410011426672"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Practical intake aerodynamic design</source>. <publisher-loc>Collins, London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Scientific Publications</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>, pp.<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954410011426672"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moeckel</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Investigation of shock diffusers at Mach number 1.85 I: projecting single-shock cones</source>. <publisher-loc>Hampton, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NACA, report no. NACA RM E6K27</publisher-name>, <year>1947</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954410011426672"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esenwein</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerino</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Force and pressure characteristics for a series of nose inlets at Mach numbers from 1.59 to 1.99</source>. <publisher-loc>Hampton, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NACA, report no. NACA RM E50J26</publisher-name>, <year>1951</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954410011426672"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Force and pressure-recovery characteristics of a conical-type nose inlet operating at Mach numbers of 1.6 to 2.0 and at angles of attack to 9 degrees</source>. <publisher-loc>Hampton, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NACA, report no. NACA RM E52I30</publisher-name>, <year>1952</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954410011426672"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwabacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High-performance supersonic missile inlet design using automated optimization</article-title>. <source>J Aircr</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>697</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954410011426672"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Xiong C, Sheng ZC, Ya Z, et al. Influence of cowl leading edge on inlet performance of ramjet assisted-range projectiles. In: Proceedings of the <italic>41st AIAA/ASME/SAE/ASEE Joint propulsion conference and exhibit</italic>, Tucson Convention Center, Tucson, Arizona, 10–13 July 2005. Reston, VA: AIAA, paper no. AIAA 2005–3642</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954410011426672"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Xiong C, Sheng ZC, Ya Z, et al. Numerical simulation of ramjet inlet with different cowl leading edge. In: Proceedings of the <italic>35th AIAA Fluid dynamics conference and exhibit</italic>, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 6–9 June 2005. Reston, VA: AIAA, paper no. AIAA 2005-5288</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954410011426672"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Computational analysis of inlet aerodynamics for a hypersonic research vehicle</article-title>. <source>J Propul Power</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954410011426672"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Performance enhancement of three-dimensional hypersonic inlet with sidewall compression</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part G: J Aerospace Engineering</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>222</volume>: <fpage>1211</fpage>–<lpage>1220</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954410011426672"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>FanY</surname></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Performance optimization of hypersonic inlets with pulse periodic energy addition</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part G: J Aerospace Engineering</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>223</volume>: <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954410011426672"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>A numerical analysis on three-dimensional flow field in a supersonic bump inlet</source>. <publisher-loc>Reston, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AIAA, paper no. 2007-689</publisher-name>, <year>January 2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954410011426672"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Triesch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gülhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental study of chin intakes for airbreathing missiles with high agility</article-title>. <source>J Propul Power</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954410011426672"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Soltani MR, Farahani M, Sanaei M, et al. Experimental investigation of combustion chamber pressure effects on performance of an axisymmetric supersonic inlet. In: Proceedings of the <italic>AERO 2009 Conference</italic>, The 8th Iranian Aerospace Society Conference, 17–19 February 2009 Shahinshar, Iran</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954410011426672"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Soltani MR, Farahani M, Kazemi J, et al. Experimental investigation of effects of angle of attack on pressure distribution of an axisymmetric supersonic inlet. In: <italic>17th. Annual (International) conference on mechanical engineering-ISME 2009,</italic> May 2009, University of Tehran, Iran</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0954410011426672"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepahi Younsi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Performance improvement of a supersonic external compression inlet by heat source addition</article-title>. <source>World Acad Sci Eng Technol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>51</issue>): <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0954410011426672"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asgari Kaji</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An experimental study of buzz instability in an axisymmetric supersonic inlet</article-title>. <source>Sci Iranica Trans B</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0954410011426672"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Experimental investigation of flow instability in a supersonic inlet</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ASME, paper no. ESDA2010-24858</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0954410011426672"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Pope A and Goin KL. High-speed wind tunnel testing. New York, NY: John Willey, 1965, pp.211–302</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0954410011426672"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Cebeci T. Three dimensional boundary layer on missiles. In: Hemsch MJ and Nielsen JD (eds). <italic>Tactical missile aerodynamics. Progress Astronautics and Aeronautics</italic>, vol. 104, Washington, DC: AIAA, 1986, pp.723–777</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0954410011426672"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Soltani MR, Taiebi-Rahni M, Farahani M, et al. <italic>Flow measurements around a long axisymmetric body with varying cross section</italic>. Reston, VA: AIAA, paper no. AIAA paper-05-50, 2005</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0954410011426672"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Anderson JD. <italic>Modern compressible flow with historical perspective</italic>. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0954410011426672"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Beckwith TG, Maraugoni RD and Lienhard VJH. <italic>Mechanical measurements</italic>, 5th ed. Cambridge, MA: Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1993, pp.45–115</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0954410011426672"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Trapier S, Duveau P and Deck S. Experimental study of supersonic inlet buzz. <italic>AIAA J</italic> 2006; 44(10): 2354–2365</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list><app-group><app id="app1-0954410011426672"><title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="sec15-0954410011426672"><title>Notation</title>
<p><def-list id="list2-0954410011426672"><def-item><term><italic>d</italic></term><def>
<p>maximum body diameter (mm)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>L</italic></term><def>
<p>body length (mm)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>M</italic></term><def>
<p>Mach number</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm1-0954410011426672"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0954410011426672"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>mass flow rate passing the inlet (kg/s)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm2-0954410011426672"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0954410011426672"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>free stream mass flow rate that passes through the tube with diameter of the cowl lip (kg/s)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>P</italic></term><def>
<p>pressure (Pa)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm3-0954410011426672"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0954410011426672"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>pressure recovery: ratio of total pressures of the rear of the inlet to the free stream</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>r</italic></term><def>
<p>radial distance from the surface</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>r</italic><sub>local</sub></term><def>
<p>local radial distance between the surfaces of the diffuser</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>Re</italic></term><def>
<p>Reynolds number</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>T</italic></term><def>
<p>temperature (K)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>u</italic></term><def>
<p>velocity (m/s)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>x</italic></term><def>
<p>distance from the nose of inlet (mm)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>α</italic></term><def>
<p>angle of attack (°)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>β</italic></term><def>
<p>side slip angle (°)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>δ</italic></term><def>
<p>boundary layer thickness (mm)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>δ</italic><sub>sub</sub>/<italic>d</italic></term><def>
<p>non-dimensional thickness of the subsonic layer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm4-0954410011426672"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0954410011426672"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>ratio of mass flow rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic><sub>ρ</sub></italic></term><def>
    <p>density (kg/m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954410011426672">3</xref></sup>)</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-0954410011426672"><title>Subscripts</title>
<p><def-list id="list3-0954410011426672"><def-item><term>0</term><def>
<p>total conditions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>∞</term><def>
<p>free stream conditions</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>