<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Information Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0165-5515</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-6485</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0165551513479242</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0165551513479242</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reconstructing copyright from ‘copy-centric’ to ‘dissemination-centric’ in the digital age</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Bingbin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0165551513479242">School of Law, Nanjing University, China</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0165551513479242">Bingbin Lu, Law School, Nanjing University, No.22, Hankou Road, Nanjing, 210093, China. Email address: <email>Lbingbin@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>39</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>479</fpage>
<lpage>493</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Chartered Institute of Library and Information Professionals</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Copy or reproduction plays a fundamental and central role in copyright. In the digital world, copying, especially temporary copying and private copying, has challenged the core concept of ‘copy’ in the copyright system. This paper will reflect on whether the basic and central role of reproduction in the copyright system is solid enough, and explore a copyright system focusing on something other than the reproduction right. It proposes a broad and open-ended concept of dissemination right that refers to a group of exclusive rights relating to the information dissemination enjoyed by the copyright holders. This broad and open-ended concept of a dissemination right should replace the reproduction right as the centre of copyright. Under such an approach, the key provision is that mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public, should not be considered as a violation of copyright. Such a proposal can accommodate the challenges brought by the digital technologies, and is also consistent with the main theories underlying the intellectual property system.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>copyright</kwd>
<kwd>copyright exceptions</kwd>
<kwd>dissemination right</kwd>
<kwd>private copying</kwd>
<kwd>temporary copying</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0165551513479242" sec-type="intro">
<title>1. Introduction</title>
<p>The exclusive right to copy is the first and perhaps most basic right of a copyright holder. However, in the digital age, even the most routine access to information by people invariably involves making a copy: computer programs are run by copying them from disk to memory, and web pages are viewed by copying them from a remote computer to the local machine. In addition, digital technologies have made private copying much easier and created the potential for widespread private copying. Private copying has become part of normal use by consumers of copyrighted products. New kinds of copying in the digital age have challenged the copyright system. Against such a background, we should reflect on whether the basic and central role of reproduction in the copyright system is solid enough. Is it necessary to reconstruct the copyright system by centring with something other than the reproduction right? Further, what kind of right or category of rights should play a central role in the copyright law in the digital era? This paper will examine these questions. Such questions go to the very heart of copyright. The first part will discuss the fundamental and central role of copying in copyright. The second part will illustrate the challenges from new types of copying to copyright in the digital era, taking temporary copying and private copying as the most typical examples. Then, the third part will provide this author’s vision of copyright centred on the dissemination right; in this part, a broad and open-ended concept of dissemination right is first constructed, and following the logic ‘from concept to institution’, a copyright system centred on the dissemination right is reconstructed to provide a solution to the copying dilemma in the digital era.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0165551513479242">
<title>2. The fundamental and central role of copying in copyright</title>
<p>The fundamental and central role of copying in copyright can be manifested from the following perspectives: the very terminology of ‘copyright’, evidence from the historical development of copyright and current national copyright laws. As the very name of ‘copyright’ indicates, copyright is a right to copy, and copyright basically is about ‘copying’. The very word ‘copyright’ appears to signify that the fundamental right granted to copyright owners is a right of reproduction.</p>
<p>From the historical view, all other exclusive rights enjoyed by authors have evolved and developed from the initial right of reproduction. Under the current copyright law of most countries, the exclusive right to copy is the first and perhaps most basic right of a copyright holder. Take the largest developed country and the largest developing country as examples here. Under Section 106 of the United States Copyright Act, the first ‘exclusive right’ granted to copyright owners is the right to reproduce the copyrighted work ‘in copies or phonorecords’ or to authorize such reproduction. The Chinese Copyright Law is similar in listing the right of reproduction as the first economic right of an author. According to article 10 of the Copyright Law of the People’s Republic of China, copyright shall include the following economic rights: the right of reproduction; the right of distribution; the right of rental; the right of exhibition; the right of performance; the right of projection (by projector, episcope, etc.); the right of broadcasting; the right of network dissemination of information; the right of making cinematographic work; the right of adaptation; the right of translation; the right of compilation; and other rights which shall be enjoyed by the copyright owners. Under current laws, every copy is presumptively infringing, and copying may only be justified under the limited exceptions or justifications such as fair use. These provisions signify that the right to control copying must be a fundamental part of any system of copyright.</p>
<p>The fundamental role of copying in copyright is self-evident. Nobody will object to it. Different from the concept of ‘fundamental’, the central role of copying in copyright needs further explanation. Current copyright law has been labelled by scholars as ‘copy-centrism’ or ‘copy-centric’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0165551513479242">1</xref>]. Many scholars have realized the central role of copying in the copyright system: ‘the exclusive right to reproduce, or copy, a work lies at the heart of copyright law’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0165551513479242">2</xref>]; ‘as the very name of the law indicates, the right to control the reproduction of works of authorship is central to the law’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0165551513479242">3</xref>]. The current copyright system is truly ‘copy-centric’ or ‘reproduction-centric’. The other economic rights under copyright can be viewed as derivative from and centred in the reproduction right. For example, the distribution right is based on copying. Without copying, there will be no possibility of distribution. However, copying can exist without distribution. In the digital age, temporary copying and private copying have become parts of consumers’ normal uses. Merely copying shall not be a decisive element for copyright infringement. Copying itself can no longer serve as a good indicator of infringement. In this regard, copying should not be a key and decisive element for determining copyright infringement. This puts the central role of reproduction in the copyright system in doubt. A detailed discussion of the copying dilemmas brought about by temporary copying and private copying in the digital era will elaborate such a problem.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0165551513479242">
<title>3. ‘Copy-centrism’ has encountered challenges in the digital age</title>
<p>Although reproduction or copying is the basic and central right in copyright, in the digital world, copy control is difficult, since digital documents are very easily copied. In addition, from the general public’s perspective, copying is necessary even in order to make normal use of works. A tension between the copyright holder’s need to control the reproduction and the public’s need to access the information has emerged. Copyright law is in the age of reform. Copying, especially temporary copying and private copying, has challenged the core concept of ‘copy’ in the copyright system. The next section will examine the problems and controversies around temporary copying and private copying, thus demonstrating the copying dilemma in the digital era.</p>
<sec id="section4-0165551513479242">
<title>3.1. Temporary copying</title>
<p>Digital technology has brought acts of temporary copying to the attention of legislators, courts and scholars. Temporary copying, also termed temporary reproduction, transient copying or ephemeral copying is an act that can only occur in the digital environment. Growing numbers of people rely on the internet as an essential tool for everyday activities (communication, information, knowledge, commercial transactions and leisure). Everyday use of computers and the internet will inevitably involve temporary copying. Copying a program from the hard drive into random access memory, automatically carried out by computers in order to run it, is a typical example of temporary reproduction; copying automatically carried out by computers in the course of online access such as internet browsing, more popularly known as ‘cache copying’, is another typical example of temporary copying. Each web page accessed by a user through the browser is temporarily stored in a cache, in order to be displayed quickly when it is later requested. Typically, cache copies are saved into a hidden folder of the home computer called ‘temporary internet files’.</p>
<p>Legislators and scholars have debated the issue of temporary reproduction for a long time. Some legislators choose to avoid this issue in drafting an international treaty or a domestic law. Scholars have been divided on the issue whether temporary reproductions have economic value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0165551513479242">4</xref>], and whether they constitute copyright infringements. Some scholars consider that acts of temporary or transient reproduction may have economic significance comparable to that of acts of permanent storage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0165551513479242">5</xref>]. Others called for an express privilege for temporary copying: ‘If temporary copies are an unavoidable incident of reading, we should extend a privilege to make temporary copies to all’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0165551513479242">6</xref>].</p>
<p>It is rational to legalize the temporary reproduction. The most basic reason is that, in the digital world, people’s normal use of computers and the internet inevitably requires copying. Reproduction is necessary for ordinary consumption of the work, and people have a right of access to information released on the internet; access also requires copying. Digital works are routinely copied simply in order to access them. In addition, such reproductions are carried out in a technical sense. The technical and legal meanings of reproduction should be distinguished.</p>
<p>After legalizing the temporary reproduction, the immediate issue is how to distinguish ephemeral and permanent copies. In some circumstances, it is not an easy task to determine what is sufficiently ephemeral not to matter. There are some criteria developed by legislators and courts in order to distinguish permanent and temporary reproduction. For example, the scope of the temporary reproduction right is defined by article 5(1) of Directive 2001/29/EC on the harmonization of certain aspects of copyright and related rights in the information society (hereinafter the Information Society Directive) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0165551513479242">7</xref>], which provides for a mandatory limitation to the exclusive right to authorize temporary reproductions. However, as commented by Isabella Alexander, the meaning and scope of the temporary and transient reproduction exception to copyright set out in article 5(1) of the Information Society Directive are far from clear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0165551513479242">2</xref>]. The European Court of Justice (ECJ) has elaborated the criteria for temporary copying. As explained by the ECJ in <italic>Infopaq International A/S v. Danske Dagblades Forening</italic> (Case C-5/08 [2009] E.C.D.R. 16), five cumulative conditions must be fulfilled, in order for an act of reproduction to qualify as temporary reproduction and be exempted from copyright infringement, namely: the act must be temporary; it must be transient or incidental; it must be an integral and essential part of a technological process; the sole purpose of that process must be that of enabling either a transmission in a network between third parties by an intermediary or a lawful use of the work; and the act must have no independent economic significance. Failing to comply with only one of these conditions will cause the act to become a prima facie infringement of the reproduction rights. In this case, the ECJ interpreted the exemption strictly. It found that an act could only be considered ‘transient’ if ‘its duration is limited to what is necessary for the proper completion of the technological process in question’ and that the process must be automated and without human intervention. By this decision the ECJ not only interpreted the reproduction right still more broadly, but also interpreted the mandatory exemption of temporary and transient reproduction strictly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0165551513479242">2</xref>]. Therefore, even after legalizing temporary copying, the criterion to determine its boundary will still be flexible and depend upon to the policy discretion of each jurisdiction.</p>
<p>The debate around temporary copying will not stop in the near future. From a practical perspective, the legal nature and criteria to determine whether it is legitimate still vary from jurisdiction to jurisdiction. In addition, new issues may emerge as technology develops.</p>
<p>The issue of temporary reproduction causes us to rethink the current copyright law. It has been noticed that, in the digital environment, the reproduction right may no longer be the ‘core’ copyright; this is because, when copyright works are available in digital format, any normal use of the works involves an act of reproduction, albeit only incidental and transient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0165551513479242">5</xref>]. Is it proper to replace the core or centre of copyright with something other than the reproduction right? Before answering this question in affirmative, let us review another copying issue that has also caused a legal dilemma.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0165551513479242">
<title>3.2. Private copying</title>
<p>Private copying refers to reproduction of a legitimately obtained copyrighted work by a natural person for private and non-commercial use. The key element and essential feature of private copying is its private nature. It is to be distinguished from disseminating copyrighted materials to the public by any means, even in a non-commercial sense. Professor Litman once contended that policy-makers should start with the widely held idea that copyright should be the exclusive right of commercial exploitation, thus drawing a distinction between commercial and non-commercial uses of content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0165551513479242">8</xref>]. The purpose of her proposal is to guarantee individual users the right to conduct non-commercial reproductions. Strictly speaking, this point of view is not accurate. Disseminating copyrighted material free of charge can be categorized as non-commercial. However, it is not private copying. Private copying cannot include sharing copyrighted content over the internet without copyright owners’ permission. In this regard, file sharing through a peer to peer network or other social networks is definitely not private copying.</p>
<p>Private copying for the purpose of personal private use existed before the emergence of digital technology. However, it is digital technology that creates the potential for widespread private copying, enabling ordinary consumers to easily copy a work for themselves. Although it is not easy to investigate and provide empirical data on private copying, as it occurs in the private sphere, consumer behaviour research supports the assumption that, in the light of technological developments making copying so much easier, private copying has increased rather than declined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0165551513479242">9</xref>]. Another alternative to investigate the scale of private copying is to resort to the private copying levy as discussed below. However, the existing levy collected on private copying cannot actually reflect the scale of private copying. Collection under the levy system is beginning to fall as blank tapes, CDs and DVDs are disappearing from the market, and levies on new devices are increasingly contested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0165551513479242">10</xref>].</p>
<p>The major problem with private copying is the enforceability of copyright. The law and right should be enforceable, otherwise they are meaningless. One of the key elements of private copying is that it is private; it takes place where copyright owners would not be able to monitor and police it. These acts can neither be controlled or licensed nor effectively banned. Lawsuits against each individual private copier would become prohibitively expensive and politically unwise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0165551513479242">11</xref>]. The copyright owner’s exclusive right of reproduction is essentially unenforceable in the private sphere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0165551513479242">12</xref>].</p>
<p>A solution to the private copying problem could be envisaged in the light of a large number of parameters. First, a solution to the private copying problem should take the respect for privacy into consideration. Privacy is a basic right guaranteed by each nation’s Constitution. To enter into a person’s private life in order to control possible copying acts is forbidden as it conflicts with this basic right. The rationale for legalizing private copying is informed, at least in part, by the idea of protecting the end user’s private sphere. Second, a solution to the private copying problem should also take the consumer’s rights into consideration. A consumer should have reasonable expectations for normal use of a product. To forbid private copying could impede the normal use of a product, which is not a wise policy for copyright law to support. In this respect, private copying is not just a copyright law issue, but also a consumer law issue to some extent. Third, a solution to the private copying problem should also take the public’s right of access to information into consideration. To allow access to the knowledge they contain, works should be reproduced freely. On the other hand, the right of access to information should only relate to the messages and the elements of knowledge. Copyright does not concern the ideas but only their forms; the works themselves should not be affected by this reasoning. There is a visible conflict between the copyright enforcement of rights holders and the access right of users.</p>
<p>Since copyright is unenforceable with regard to private copying, and insistence on strict control of private copying is not a good policy to support as it manifestly conflicts with several other rights, currently, certain private copying is usually an exception or limitation to the reproduction right, and exempted from copyright infringement claims. For example, in Europe, article 2 of the Information Society Directive defines the reproduction right broadly as ‘the exclusive right to authorize or prohibit direct or indirect, temporary or permanent reproduction by any means and in any form, in whole or in part’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0165551513479242">7</xref>]. Article 5(2)(b) of the Information Society Directive authorizes that Member States may provide for exceptions or limitations to the reproduction right in respect of reproductions on any medium made by a natural person for private use and for ends that are neither directly nor indirectly commercial, on condition that the rightholders receive fair compensation which takes account of the application or non-application of technological measures to the work or subject-matter concerned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0165551513479242">7</xref>]. In the United States, 17 USC §1008, as legislated by the Audio Home Recording Act of 1992, says that non-commercial copying by consumers of digital and analogue musical recordings is not copyright infringement. This private copying exception is more limited in scope compared with the European one. Other kinds of private copying can be defended under the fair use clause of the US Copyright Act. To allow private copying under the fair use defence is also a common practice. For another example, China also provides for the private copying exception under the fair use clause. Article 22 of the Chinese Copyright Law, the fair use clause, lists several situations where a work may be exploited without permission from, and without payment or remuneration to, the copyright owner, with the condition that the name of the author and the title of the work are mentioned and the other rights enjoyed by the copyright owner are not infringed upon. The first such situation is ‘use of a published work for the purposes of the user’s own private study, research or self-entertainment’.</p>
<p>In addition to taking private copying as an exception to the reproduction right, some courts treat it or tend to treat it as a user right. The different classification as exception or user right is related to the legal nature of private copying. If private copying is a user right, it could signify that end-users are actually in the capacity of invoking this ‘right’ as a legal basis of substantiating claims against potential restrictions of their ability to make private copies and not just an affirmative defence against allegations of copyright infringement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0165551513479242">13</xref>]. At least one national court has recognized it as a user right. In <italic>CHH Canadian Ltd v Law Society of Upper Canada</italic>, the Canadian Supreme Court explicitly stated that copyright exceptions are fully fledged user rights. Within the EU, the legal nature of private copying is also a controversial issue under European copyright law. Whereas private copying is explicitly permitted in the EU by virtue of article 5(2)(b) of the Information Society Directive of 2001, its legal nature is not settled. Does article 5(2)(b) only provide immunity to users against being sued for infringement or is it a positive right to make private copies? In <italic>Padawan SL v Sociedad General de Autores y Editores de Espana</italic> (C-467/08,2011, E.C.D.R. 1, ECJ 3rd Chamber), the ECJ’s line of reasoning affirmed that, if users pay the levy in the final price of media and equipment to compensate for the possible harm they cause to the rights holders owing to copying for private use, they are rightly presumed to use the levied media and equipment to make such copies. By affirming that end-users are rightly presumed to use media and equipment to copy, the ECJ confirmed that private copying is, and should function as, a user right [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0165551513479242">13</xref>]. However, considering that technical measures to limit private copying by copyright holders are also reasonable and legitimate under most jurisdictions’ copyright laws, it is better to take private copying as an exception and limitation to the reproduction right.</p>
<p>One immediate following issue is that legitimating private copying may cause certain loss or harm to copyright holders. This article believes that the harm caused by each copying of a work by an individual for his or her private use is minimal and can be ignored; however, numerous acts of private copying put together can cause economic harm to copyright owners. There may be different views from the first part of this statement. That can be discussed.</p>
<p>It is natural for copyright holders and rights holder organizations to insist on compensation from each individual private copying. This is manifested in the response from rights holder organizations such as the British Copyright Council, the DACS and Equity to the Hargreaves recommendations of introducing a private copying exception in the UK, as discussed in more detail below. The British Copyright Council believes that any private copying exception should provide for fair compensation to rights owners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0165551513479242">14</xref>]. DACS, an organization that collects revenues on behalf of all UK visual artists, argues that private copying does have an economic impact on the rights holder and any argument that a fair and balanced remuneration for this type of copying should equate to zero is unjustified and unsustainable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0165551513479242">15</xref>]. Equity, the UK trade union for professional performers and creative practitioners, also ascertained that a scheme for fair compensation to all private copying would be required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0165551513479242">16</xref>]. Some scholars also argue that private copying has a very serious effect on the reproduction rights of all copyright holders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0165551513479242">17</xref>].</p>
<p>In economics, harm is a lost sale. One copy would presumably cause one lost sale for the rights holders. However, this ‘one copy, one loss’ presumption can be rebutted. First, private copying increases the popularity of a work, which leads to greater consumption of it, and this could counteract the presumptive decrease in sales. Second, copyright law does allow certain loss of sales to occur. The well-established first sale doctrine allows consumers to resell a copyrighted work without the need to obtain the consent of rights holders. Such resale results in loss of sale for rights holders. The law allows this to happen, because copyright law does not aim to maximize the profit of rights holders. Rather, one of its important objectives is to balance the interests of rights holders and the public.</p>
<p>The harm caused by each individual private copying is minimal and can be ignored both in theory and in practice. Widespread private copying in the aggregate, however, could reduce the incentive to create works. Copyright law has to face this private copying dilemma. While recognizing private copying as a copyright exception, fair compensation to copyright holders becomes an accompanying issue. Granting access to copyrighted materials does not mean that the access should be free of charge. It is crucial to ensure that copyright holders receive fair and equitable remuneration. Thus, to authorize private copying through an exception to the exclusive right of reproduction and to couple this exception with the obligation to indemnify copyright owners becomes a balanced approach to the private copying dilemma. Identifying private users and obliging them to compensate copyright owners on a case by case basis is a tremendous amount of work, and practically impossible. A private copying levy emerges as a comparatively feasible solution to the private copying dilemma.</p>
<p>A private copying levy is a special levy (additional to any general sales tax) charged on purchases of certain kinds of copying media and devices. The purpose of this levy is to compensate copyright holders for damages suffered by private copying of protected works. This scheme makes sense, since manufacturers of blank carriers and private copying devices are the main beneficiaries of private copying technologies. Private copying levies accord copyright holders their share of this market [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0165551513479242">12</xref>].</p>
<p>In practice, the private copying levy system has proven popular in Europe. According to the EU law, national exceptions for the copying of copyrighted works for purely private use shall provide fair financial compensation for the economic losses incurred by copyright owners as a result of the exception. Following the Information Society Directive of 2001, currently the laws of 25 EU member states have a private copying exception. The three EU countries that did not opt for it are the UK, Ireland and Cyprus. Out of 25 member states with a private copying exception, 23 states have a system of private copying levies. Only five member states have not implemented a system of private copying levies. The UK, Ireland and Cyprus do not need such a system since they do not have a private copying exception. Malta and Luxembourg have introduced such an exception into their laws, but have done so without implementing a system of levies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0165551513479242">9</xref>]. Some non-European countries such as Canada and Japan have also implemented a similar levy system. Such compensation systems can also be found in Burkina Faso, Paraguay, Russia and the USA, although these systems are more limited, compared with most European countries, and in some countries these system have not yielded much income for rights holders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0165551513479242">9</xref>].</p>
<p>In theory, the levy system can be justified. The most understandable justification of the levy system is the incentive theory. Levies serve as incentives to authors. Indeed, for the purpose of an author’s ‘property’ or economic interest in the work, the exclusive right of control is merely the means to the ultimate end – an economic income. Just remuneration serves as a proper economic incentive to creative works. Where just remuneration is provided by other means, the exclusive right of control becomes an ‘empty shell’ and its abrogation does not detract from that ‘property’ right [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0165551513479242">18</xref>]. Germany, which is the home country of the levy system, has another justification for it. The utilitarian justification for authors’ remuneration right as an incentive to produce more works is not pervasive under the German law. Germany is renowned for its highly principled protection of authors’ connection to and control over their works through moral rights [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0165551513479242">19</xref>]. The Germany Court regards the remuneration right as ‘the fundamental principle of copyright’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0165551513479242">19</xref>]. The right to remuneration can be seen to embody a sense of a deeper, non-monetary wrong that exists when private copying occurs without remuneration – a wrong akin to ingratitude or disrespect towards the author [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0165551513479242">19</xref>]. Either from the economic right perspective or moral right perspective, the levy system can find some theoretical support in both civil law countries and common law countries. Copyright law shall strike a fair balance between the interests of authors and users of copyright protected contents. Authors have their right to obtain compensation for their works. Consumers have rights to access those works. The levy system embodies the art of balancing interests, which is a core issue in law.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the levy system has its inherent problems. First, the most obvious problem with the levy system is that imposing a levy raises fairness concerns, since many copying technologies now are multi-functional, and have uses other than private copying, yet a levy imposes its price uniformly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0165551513479242">11</xref>]. For multi-functional devices, the levy has a much larger effect on persons who do not engage in private copying than on persons who do [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0165551513479242">20</xref>]. Because of this consideration, levies on new media or equipment such as MP3 players, printers and PCs are very controversial. Second, the levy is not a good policy to encourage the development of new emerging technologies. If a levy is imposed on such technology, the levy will increase the price of technology to consumers, creating an artificial price increase and resulting inefficiencies, as it would for existing technologies. A levy may discourage the creation and dissemination of new technologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0165551513479242">11</xref>]. It thus leads to the expected loud objection from a broad array of device manufacturers since the levy affects their interests. Third, under such a system, a consumer or user has no choice. This is also a fairness issue. The users and their associations do not welcome such a levy since it also affects their interests. To impose a cost on consumers in order to avoid costs for copyright holders probably has no solid justification.</p>
<p>With these various problems, the levy system becomes very controversial in practice. For those countries that introduced the private copying levy system, the levy still varies from country to country. For example, the Canadian private copying levy does not apply to iPods. Whether or not copying to iPods and other such devices is legal remains unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0165551513479242">21</xref>]. In addition, not all the countries introducing private copying exceptions are willing to impose a levy system, even within the EU. The UK government has for a long time intended to introduce a limited private copying exception without the levy system. On 9 January 2008, the UK Government considered introducing a private copy exception without compensation, to allow consumers to make copies of CDs they have already bought, as is already the case in many continental European countries such as Germany or France. It was hoped that, if enacted, its narrow scope would ensure that it effectively legitimized the widespread practice of ‘format-shifting’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0165551513479242">22</xref>]. However, the UK government was reluctant to introduce a financial compensation for private copying [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0165551513479242">23</xref>]. The 2008 legislative proposal has not been realized. In August 2011, the UK government once again intended to legalize copying of CDs or DVDs onto digital music players or computers for personal use. The change would mean that a consumer may copy a CD they have bought onto another device such as their iPod or home computer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0165551513479242">24</xref>]. The current UK government initiative on a private copying exception is based on an independent report by Professor Ian Hargreaves, entitled ‘Digital Opportunity, A Review of IP and Growth’, which was produced at the request of the Prime Minister. This Review developed a recommendation to introduce a limited private copying exception without compensation. The report noted:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>We see no economic argument for adding an extra charge to these devices in order to authorise reasonable private acts which are part of the normal use of devices. Indeed, without that copying, normal use of those devices would be largely restricted to playing music or films bought online. We are not aware of strong evidence of harm to rights holders done by this kind of private copying in the normal course of using digital equipment to play works. There is considerable evidence of overall public benefits from consumer use. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0165551513479242">25</xref>]</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>
<?h -4?>Thus, ‘a limited private copying exception which corresponds to the expectations of buyers and sellers of copyright content, and is therefore already priced into the purchase, will by definition not entail a loss for right holders’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0165551513479242">25</xref>]. The UK government agreed with the Review’s central thesis that the widest possible private copying exceptions should be introduced into the UK. However, the government is reluctant to introduce an accompanying levy system. The government’s standpoint is:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>That the amount of harm to rights holders that would result in ‘fair compensation’ under EU law is minimal, and hence the amount of fair compensation provided would be zero. This avoids market distortion and the need for a copyright levy system, which the Government opposes on the basis that it is likely to have adverse impacts on growth and inconsistent with its wider policy on tax. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0165551513479242">26</xref>]</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>In this way, the UK government believes, a certain amount of private copying is already priced into retail purchases, and commercial practice will not be affected as a result of introducing a narrowly conceived private copying exception.</p>
<p>A levy system as a solution to the private copying dilemma will continue to be controversial in practice. It is hoped that technological measures can provide an alternative solution. Article 5(2)(b) of the EU Information Society Directive instructs the Member States that, in calculating the amount of ‘fair compensation’ for acts of digital private copying, the ‘application or non-application of technological measures’ should be taken into account. Ideally, with the exertion of technological measures’ function, levies are to be phased out. Scholars also believe that the emergence of digital right management systems that allow copyright holders to engage in individual end-user licensing has cast doubt on the survival of private copying exemptions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0165551513479242">27</xref>]. Technology has also helped foster new business models that make works available to the public at a variety of price points and enjoyment options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0165551513479242">28</xref>], which could alleviate the high price problem for many copyright protected works. However, technological measures to protection copyright have limited applications in reality. Even applied, a major problem with technological measures is that they can be circumvented or hacked, and the copyrighted work will be reproduced, accessed and even traded without authorization. Legal prohibition on the circumvention of technological protections measures is vital. It is an international obligation under article 11 of the World Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO) Copyright Treaty (WCT) to provide adequate legal protection against the circumvention of effective technological measures. Such provisions can be found in article 6 of the EU Information Society Directive, Section 1201 of the US Copyright Act, article 48 of the Chinese Copyright Law, and other national copyright laws. Such legal prohibitions, however, also face enforcement problems.</p>
<p>Another solution to the digital copyright problem will be access control. Access is a separate and distinct act to the use of copyrighted works. Every act of perception or of materialization of a digital copy requires a prior act of access. By controlling access, copyright holders may also control use of the work. Access control by copyright holders is also achieved through technological protection measures. Technological protection measures usually have been defined as fitting into two categories – technologies controlling the use of the works and technologies controlling access to the works – although the distinction between access and use can lead to difficulties in certain circumstances, because it can occur that these two types of technologies are combined or even that they are merged into one single technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0165551513479242">29</xref>]. Ideally, technologies controlling access to the works could provide an upstream solution to copyright enforcement problems, including the private copying issue. Some scholars employed the term ‘access right’ to describe the status of technological measures controlling access to copyrighted works [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0165551513479242">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0165551513479242"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0165551513479242">32</xref>]. However, the term ‘access right’ is problematic for two reasons. First, it seems to be a somewhat misleading term since here it means the rights holder’s right to control public access to a work, rather than the straightforward and traditional meaning of the public’s right to access information. Second, neither international treaties on copyright law, for example, the WCT and the Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works (<italic>hereinafter</italic> the Berne Convention), nor the domestic laws of major jurisdictions, such as the law of the EU, the USA, China, and Japan, contain such an access right, so this terminology is just a theoretical description by some scholars. Currently, as we can see, absent access controlling technologies, there is no room for access rights to exist. Therefore, it may be better to employ the non-confusing terminology ‘access control’.</p>
<p>A big problem with access control is that it may result in undesirable excessive control by copyright holders. In an access-protected world, an issue with the access control is not only the ability of rights holders to grant initial access but also repeated acts or continuing acts of access, not only for a general purpose but also for specific ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0165551513479242">31</xref>]. Thus, theoretically, a copyright holder has a largely unrestricted power to control. This will affect the public’s right of access to information. The idea/expression dichotomy ensures that the idea embedded within the work is effectively gifted to the world at the time of fixation – once it is revealed, it is impossible to protect again [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0165551513479242">31</xref>]. If all information is locked up by copyright holders, it will lead to a reduction of the public domain. The chief postulate of freedom of information still forms a fundamental counterargument against a prevailing dominant precept of an exclusive right of access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0165551513479242">32</xref>]. Because of these considerations, legislators at both the international level and the national level are very cautious about access control or even the access right. In reality, the risk of overprotection owing to access control has not become a serious one. This is largely because technological protection measures have limited applications. There are countless copyrighted materials in the world. Not each piece of work is suitable for technological protection. In addition, in the market economy, it is also a consumer choice issue. A reasonable consumer will prefer a copyrighted product with fewer controls or limitations. Empirically, the access control technology has already been legally protected in many countries for more than 10 years, but various digital copyright problems, including the private copying issue, remain to be solved.</p>
<p>The debate surrounding private copying will continue. To forbid the private copying is counterintuitive. <italic>Vox poluli</italic> is a factor to reckon with when considering the treatment for private copying. The legalization of private copying can be deemed a process of democratic legislation. The biggest problem with the copyright system today is that the public interest is not adequately represented in the legislative process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0165551513479242">33</xref>]. Too often the interests of the ‘producer’ dominate in the evolution of IP policy, and that of the ultimate consumer is neither heard nor heeded, so policy tends to be determined more by the interests of the commercial users of the system than by an impartial conception of the greater public good [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0165551513479242">34</xref>]. This phenomenon needs to be changed.</p>
<p>The above discussion on temporary copying and private copying has revealed controversial issues surrounding the role of reproduction right in copyright. The fundamental and central role of reproduction right in copyright is in greater doubt. Future technology development may bring further difficulties and copying dilemmas to copyright law. Rather than engage in epicycle-like debates over the legitimacy of temporary copying or private copying, it is time for us to systematically rethink the concepts and principles of current copyright law, and to try to formulate a renewed copyright concept and institution to accommodate the technological challenges.</p>
<p>In order to search for a systematic solution to all these copying dilemmas in the digital age, this article will formulate a dissemination-centric copyright system that focuses on control of dissemination, and let go of certain copying acts as a systematic exception to copyright.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0165551513479242">
<title>4. Reconstructing a ‘dissemination-centric’ copyright in the digital age</title>
<sec id="section7-0165551513479242">
<title>4.1. A broad and open-ended concept of the dissemination right</title>
<p>Before moving to construct a ‘dissemination-centric’ copyright system in the digital age, it is first necessary to define what dissemination in copyright refers to. This article proposes to introduce a broad and open-ended concept of the dissemination right.</p>
<p>Copyright is a concept combining a subset of exclusive rights together. Many such exclusive rights are related to dissemination. The terminology ‘dissemination right’ employed by this article is a broad and open-ended concept, referring to a group of copyright holder’s exclusive rights relating to dissemination. Such a broad and open-ended concept of dissemination should consist in dissemination of a work to the public, by any means whatsoever. Public recitation, public presentation, public performance, distribution of a work to the public, rental or public lending of a specific work to the public, broadcast of a work to the public and communication of a work to the public through the internet are typical examples of dissemination. Therefore, a broad and open-ended dissemination is different from a comparatively narrower concept of ‘the right of communication to the public’ or ‘the right of network communication of information’ found in the WCT and some national legislations. Article 8 of the WCT provides that:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>authors of literary and artistic works shall enjoy the exclusive right of authorizing any communication to the public of their works, by wire or wireless means, including the making available to the public of their works in such a way that members of the public may access these works from a place and at a time individually chosen by them.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>For national laws, one typical and also problematic provision is article 10 of the Chinese Copyright Law, which provides for the right of network communication of information; however, this is limited to ‘the right to provide the public with works by wired or wireless means, so as to make the public able to respectively obtain the works at the individually selected time and place’. Compared with article 8 of the WCT, the Chinese law has narrowed the concept of ‘right of communication to the public’ of the WCT. The right of communication to the public under the WCT is comparatively open-ended. ‘The making available to the public of their works in such a way that members of the public may access these works from a place and at a time individually chosen by them’ is just provided as a typical example of the right of communication to public. However, the Chinese law deleted the word ‘including’, thus implemented this right in a narrow way. Under such a modification, there emerge certain vague areas for legal interpretation. For example, ‘internet TV’ is not covered by ‘the right of network communication of information’ in China, since users cannot access ‘internet TV’ from a place and at a time individually chosen by them. ‘The right of network communication of information’ in China is not broad enough to accommodate technology development. A broad and open-ended concept of the dissemination right could easily and systematically solve such problems.</p>
<p>A broad and open-ended concept of the dissemination right actually relates to the categorization of copyright. Copyright is composed of a subset of exclusive rights. These rights can be conflated into broadly defined categories. One such typical categorization effort can be found in an earlier Australian report on copyright legislation. In February 1999, the Australian Government released the second part of a two-part report on simplification of the copyright legislation, produced by its Copyright Law Review Committee. The report recommended that the Australian Copyright Act should be substantially amended. One of its key recommendations is to provide for two categories of exclusive economic rights. These two exclusive economic rights are the right of reproduction and the right of dissemination to the public [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0165551513479242">35</xref>]. Each of these two rights was constructed as open-ended, by virtue of being defined by reference to an inclusive list of entitlements forming a subset of the right [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0165551513479242">35</xref>]. Under the approach envisaged by the majority of the Committee, the ‘right of dissemination to the public’ includes activities within the performance right, the publication right, the broadly based right of communication to the public, and the right of distribution under the WCT and WPPT to the extent recommended by the majority of the Committee [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0165551513479242">35</xref>]. The Committee considered that the Australian Copyright Act should be recast, in a manner that could simplify it and enable it better to deal with the challenges, both foreseen and as yet unforeseen, raised by the digital environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0165551513479242">35</xref>]. The report’s impact went far beyond the territorial limits of Australia. For example, Professor Christie argued that a simplification of the UK copyright legislation along similar lines as proposed by the Australian Copyright Law Review Committee is both possible and desirable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0165551513479242">36</xref>]. Although such an approach was not applauded by all people – for example Professor Ricketson criticized this type of simplification, and labelled it ‘quiet radicalism’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0165551513479242">37</xref>] – we cannot negate the advantages of such a flexible, simplified and technology-neutral approach to copyright law reform.</p>
<p>Actually, a broad and open-ended concept of dissemination right is not just a legislative proposal; it does exit in the real copyright law world. Some countries have already provided for a general and broad right of dissemination. As pointed out by the Australian Copyright Law Review Committee, the basic economic rights protected in each country fall into the two main categories of reproduction of copyright material and public dissemination of copyright material, and in civil law countries the economic rights are commonly prescribed through an ‘open ended’ system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0165551513479242">35</xref>]. In such countries, besides the authors’ moral rights, rights holders enjoy broadly defined and interpreted economic rights. The French and Dutch laws are two typical examples. Under article L122 of the French Intellectual Property Code of 1992, the authors enjoy two general rights of exploitation: the right of performance (<italic>le droit de représentation</italic>) and the right of reproduction (<italic>le droit de reproduction</italic>). The ‘performance’ under the French law ‘shall consist in the communication of the work to the public by any process whatsoever’. Public recitation, lyrical performance, dramatic performance, public presentation, public projection and transmission in a public place of a telediffused work and telediffusion are listed as the typical examples of ‘performance’. The meaning of the right of performance under the French law is similar to the terminology of dissemination right employed by this author. The Netherlands Copyright Act of 1912 also provides for two general economic rights: the right to communicate the work to the public (<italic>openbaarmakingsrecht</italic>) and the right to reproduce the work (<italic>verveelvoudigingsrecht</italic>). Article 1 of the Netherlands Copyright Act provides that ‘Copyright is the exclusive right of the author of a literary, scientific or artistic work or his successors in title to communicate that work to the public and to reproduce it, subject to the limitations laid down by law’. Article 12 of the Netherlands Copyright Act further provides that the communication to the public of a literary, scientific or artistic work includes: (1) the communication to the public of a reproduction of the whole or part of a work; (2) the distribution of the whole or part of a work or of a reproduction thereof, as long as the work has not appeared in print; (3) the rental or lending of the whole or part of a work, with the exception of works of architecture and works of applied art, or of a reproduction thereof which has been brought into circulation by or with the consent of the rights-holder; (4) the recitation, performance or presentation in public of the whole or part of a work or a reproduction thereof; and (5) the broadcasting of a work incorporated in a radio or television programme by satellite or other transmitter or by a closed-circuit system. This list includes public recitation, performance or presentation, and (since 1995) rental and public lending, and is not an exhaustive enumeration. For instance, before the 1993 revision, broadcasting was not mentioned in article 12 of the Netherlands Copyright Act, but there is no doubt that it is covered by the right to communicate to the public [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0165551513479242">38</xref>]. The right to communicate the work to the public under the Dutch law is a very open and broad concept that is meant to cover all existing and future forms of communication to the public. After a general reference to these broad economic rights, the legislations of these countries then prescribe their content in more detail. It is important to note that the central feature of an ‘open-ended’ rights system is that the specific rights described are given only as examples of the broader right of exploitation.</p>
<p>There is one more subtle issue in categorizing and defining the dissemination right. Distribution and rental of a work also cause public dissemination of information. Should the right of distribution and right of rental be categorized into the dissemination right? Not all of the legislations or proposals categorize these two rights into the right of dissemination to the public. For example, on 26 April 2010, a group of European copyright scholars united as the Wittem Group released a scholarly drafted European Copyright Code. Focusing on the future development of European copyright law, the Code provided model provisions on the main topics of copyright legislation. Under the European Copyright Code, ‘the economic rights in a work are the exclusive rights to authorise or prohibit the reproduction, distribution, rental, communication to the public and adaptation of the work, in whole or in part’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0165551513479242">39</xref>]. Logically, this proposal is based on the Information Society Directive of 2001, which provides for three general rights: reproduction right (article 2), right of communication to the public of works and right of making available to the public other subject matter (article 3), and distribution right (article 4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0165551513479242">7</xref>]. As noted by one official report by the Commission of the European Communities, the basic principle underlying the 2001 harmonization effort was to provide the copyright holders with a high level of protection; hence the scope of exclusive rights was very broadly defined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0165551513479242">40</xref>]. The proposed European Copyright Code offers an ‘open-ended and non-exhaustive’ communication right [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0165551513479242">41</xref>]. However, the European Copyright Code has explicitly distinguished the right of distribution and right of rental from the right of communication to the public. This is consistent with the Information Society Directive of 2001, which also explicitly distinguished the right of distribution from the right of communication to the public, while apparently different from the Australian Copyright Law Review Committee’s legislative proposal.</p>
<p>Some scholars have also excluded the right of distribution and right of rental from the dissemination or communication right. For instance, one scholar commented that, ‘public communication is an umbrella term which includes two distinct rights, namely: (1) the right to broadcast the work to the public, and (2) the right to make the work available from a place and at a time individually chosen by members of the public’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0165551513479242">5</xref>]. Such a view takes a very narrow understanding of the right of public communication.</p>
<p>Thereupon, we should clarify whether the right of distribution and right of rental can be categorized into the broad and general concept of dissemination right. Usually, the right of distribution means the right to distribute to the public the original of the work or copies thereof; the right of rental means the right to make available the original of the work or copies thereof for use for a limited period of time for profit-making purposes. From a textual reading and a general understanding, distribution to the public of the original or copies of the work is a kind of dissemination; rental of the work or copies thereof is also a kind of dissemination. The right of distribution and rental can be categorized under the general and broad concept of dissemination right. Whereas distribution needs the origin or copies of the work, the distribution right is based on the reproduction right; however, through the exertion of distribution right, the quiet action of reproduction has become a live action entering into the public sphere.</p>
<p>Such a categorization is not in conflict with international treaties. At the international level, there is also no ‘general’ and open-ended dissemination right. Rather, acts of dissemination are dealt with separately, depending on the subject-matter concerned, and the type of dissemination. An exception is article 8 of WCT on the ‘right of communication to the public’. As noted earlier in this paper, article 8 has introduced a comparatively broad right of communication to the public for authors. However, it does not comprise (on the spot) public performance, but does include broadcasting and making available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0165551513479242">42</xref>]. The WIPO Performances and Phonograms Treaty (WPPT) similarly contained a comparatively broadly and inclusively defined right of communication to the public. Such a right of communication to the public embraces all means of making a work available to the public in intangible form. It can thus be seen that the WCT and the WPPT heralded an international approach to copyright reform based on simplification and technological neutrality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0165551513479242">36</xref>].</p>
<p>According to the structure of WCT, the WCT has distinguished the right of distribution and the right of rental from the right of communication to the public, and provided these three rights in separate articles. However, the WCT did not require its members to provide for exactly these three rights. A member has its freedom to decide how to implement these rights. The WCT just provides for minimum standards for national legislations. As far as a member complies with the substantial requirements under these provisions, the WCT allows a member to adjust or re-arrange the relations of these rights. Thus, the USA implemented the right of communication to the public through adjustment of the existed right of distribution. In no sense, the WCT forbids a member to design a broad and general right such as ‘dissemination right’ upon the three rights mentioned explicitly in the treaty.</p>
<p>In all, this paper prefers to categorize copyright into two broad categories, namely, the reproduction right and the dissemination right. The right of reproduction includes the right of copying (i.e. making a literal copy), the right of reproduction in a material form (i.e. making a non-literal copy), the right of adaptation and the right of translation. The right of dissemination includes the performance right, the distribution right, the rental right, the broadcasting right, the right of communication to the public and the right of making available to the public. It is important to note that such a list is not exhaustive. The dissemination right is a group of exclusive rights enjoyed by the copyright holder. For legislation, the ideal model is to provide a general concept of dissemination and further prescribe it in more detail with a non-exhaustive list of detailed rights.</p>
<p>The most important advantage of a broad concept of dissemination right is that it achieves a high level of flexibility and technological neutrality. The current copyright law has been criticized for its technological specificity. A technologically neutral solution for the internet has been called for by many scholars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0165551513479242">43</xref>]. It is an ideal model for copyright law to be drafted in a technologically neutral language. By a general concept of dissemination, it adequately addresses the need for technological neutrality. The introduction of broadly and inclusively defined categories of exclusive rights is also flexible enough to adapt to new technologies for the creation and exploitation of copyright material. It is a forward-looking legislative model. A broad and open-ended concept of reproduction and dissemination is meant to cover all existing and future methods of reproduction and dissemination, and thus reduces the need for ad hoc legislative amendments in response to technological changes. A broad concept of dissemination also achieves simplification, thus removing the extra complexity that exists in the current copyright law. Upon such a broad and open-ended concept, we can move to construct a copyright system focusing on the dissemination right.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0165551513479242">
<title>4.2. Dissemination right shall be the centre of copyright in the digital age</title>
<p>As this paper explored earlier, the central position of reproduction or copying has encountered some challenges in the digital age. Unauthorized reproduction, in some circumstances, cannot be controlled by copyright holders, and will not harm their economic interests. The mere occurrence of copying by users without dissemination of those copies does not harm publishers or authors. For a straightforward illustration, if one makes 10 copies of a work but does nothing with them other than store them in the drawer, this will not have any effect on the copyright holder’s interests and is impossible to police unless it is released to the public. Hence, the significance of copyright does not lie in the act of reproduction itself, but in what it enables – dissemination of a work. A violation occurs only if there is public dissemination of a work not granted by the copyright owner. What value does the right of reproduction have absent acts of dissemination?</p>
<p>Dissemination to the public is the very necessary element for harm to the copyright holders’ economic interests. If there is no intention and/or act to disseminate the copyrighted work to the public, the copyright holders’ economic interests will not be directly harmed. After all, it is the dissemination of copies to the public that causes the copyright owners to suffer economically. In this regard, control of dissemination can also provide sufficient incentive to authors.</p>
<p>In the digital age, the central role of dissemination as the core mechanism for copyright protection should be considered. As appealed by some scholars, the copy-centric model should be abandoned in favour of the right of public distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0165551513479242">1</xref>]. Professor Litman proposed jettisoning the notion of reproduction as the central facet of copyright law [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0165551513479242">8</xref>]. This paper agrees with such ideas. Copyright should be reconstructed by focusing on dissemination to the public. In the digital world, the centre of copyright protection and enforcement should be based on something other than the notion of control of reproduction. Controlling reproduction is less important than controlling dissemination of works. Accordingly, copyright law should be rewritten to focus on preventing dissemination to the public. The centre of copyright should be replaced by the broad and open-ended concept of dissemination right. Under this notion, the key provision is that mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public, should not be considered as a violation of copyright. Such an approach can accommodate the challenges brought by the digital technologies, and address a variety of situations faced by the copyright system, such as temporary copying, private copying and unknown copying dilemmas that may emerge in the future.</p>
<p>Such a suggested alteration to copyright law seems dramatic. However, it is consistent with the basic copyright principles and theories. One basic theory supporting the intellectual property system is the incentive theory. Control of reproduction can provide incentives to authors. Historically, control of reproduction has been a key means of providing incentives, because it has given authors and publishers control over the use of their work. In the world of physical artefacts, reproduction is a good predictor: the act is closely correlated to other acts, such as distribution, that may harm the copyright holder and reduce incentive. However, control of reproduction itself does not have an independent value; it is just the means to protect copyright and provide incentives to authors. In addition, in the digital world, reproduction of many sorts is a common, indeed technologically necessary, act with fundamental technical justification, frequently innocent of any infringement intent or effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0165551513479242">3</xref>]. As the US Committee on Intellectual Property Rights and the Emerging Information Infrastructure pointed out in its report, there are two reasons for the transformation of reproduction’s role in the copyright system. First, in the digital world, reproduction loses much of its power as a predictor of important consequences, and hence the question of whether a protected work has been copied may be considerably less important; second, in the digital world, control of reproduction is a blunt instrument whose impact reaches considerably beyond the original intent, bringing into question its use in accomplishing the goals of intellectual property law [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0165551513479242">3</xref>].</p>
<p>Further, providing incentives to authors is not the single justification for the copyright system. It also promotes the dissemination of knowledge. From the standpoint of the whole society, the knowledge dissemination function of the copyright system actually is much more important. The Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights (the TRIPS Agreement) also recognized these two objectives of the intellectual property system. Article 7 of the TRIPS Agreement, entitled ‘objectives’, provides as follows:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>The protection and enforcement of intellectual property rights should contribute to the promotion of technological innovation and to the transfer and dissemination of technology, to the mutual advantage of producers and users of technological knowledge and in a manner conducive to social and economic welfare, and to a balance of rights and obligations.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Article 7 is a core provision of the TRIPS Agreement and has important value in interpretation and understanding it, and the intellectual property system. However, as noted by some scholars, this provision expressly addresses only the technology policy aspect, since the provision speaks of ‘technical innovations’, ‘technical knowledge’ and technology, so patent law is particularly relevant in this respect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0165551513479242">44</xref>]. While article 7 of the TRIPS Agreement focuses on the technology and does not fully cover copyright, the incentive objective and dissemination objective are applicable to copyright. From such a perspective, we can say that the two most important objectives of protection and enforcement of copyright are to provide incentives for creative works and to contribute to the dissemination of knowledge. Dissemination is a key element and function of the copyright system. For the copyright holders, control of dissemination will also have significant meanings.</p>
<p>Further, the copyright system should also achieve the purpose of the balance of interests. In the digital world, since reproduction is necessary for ordinary consumption of the work, control of reproduction will affect the public’s right of access to information. Copyright and the public’s right of access to information have been presented as competing with each other, and the need to take them equally into account in the new digital environment should been emphasized. Allowing ‘normal use’ of a work is a principle that copyright has traditionally supported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0165551513479242">45</xref>]. A legal institution that would impede ‘normal use’ and technological advancement should not be promoted. According to the spirit of article 7 of the TRIPS Agreement, the protection and enforcement of copyright should also contribute to the mutual advantage of producers and users of knowledge and in a manner conducive to social and economic welfare, and to a balance of rights and obligations. Rigidly controlling reproduction will have negative effects on social welfare, and destroy the balance of rights and obligations.</p>
<p>One issue remains – if the copyright system were to be reconstructed by focusing on the dissemination right, what would reproduction’s position in this copyright system be? Some scholars have proposed a radical solution: eliminate the right to control copying as a fundamental aspect of copyright and as an organizing principle of intellectual property law [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0165551513479242">1</xref>]. Under their envisaged scheme, by eliminating the exclusive right to reproduce as an organizing principle of copyright law, and putting in its place the exclusive right to distribute, the ‘copy’ would be taken out of copyright [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0165551513479242">45</xref>]. This particular point is truly ‘radical’ and not feasible. While this author agrees with those scholars’ ultimate conclusion that we should eliminate the central place of the right of reproduction in the copyright system and focus copyright law on commercial exploitation, this author cannot concur with the idea of ‘taking copy outside copyright’. Reproduction is still one fundamental element of copyright. However, one broadly designed exception should be introduced, that is, ‘mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public, should not be considered as a violation of copyright’. This exception should become a vital principle of the copyright law.</p>
<p>Therefore, constructing a copyright system focusing on the dissemination right finally arrives at copyright exceptions. Copyright exceptions have become a highly controversial aspect of copyright law [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0165551513479242">46</xref>]. The exclusive right of an author is in fact subject to a number of limitations, the main or subsidiary aim of which is to ensure public’s access to information, which is the corollary of freedom of expression, a fundamental right [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0165551513479242">47</xref>]. It is the exceptions and limitations of copyright that ensure the dissemination of knowledge, promote social welfare and achieve copyright law’s social value. As WIPO points out: ‘In order to maintain an appropriate balance between the interests of right-holders and users of protected works, copyright laws allow certain limitations on economic rights … Due to the development of new technologies and the ever-increasing worldwide use of the Internet, it has been considered that the above balance between various stakeholders’ interests needs to be recalibrated’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0165551513479242">48</xref>]. Taking ‘mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public’ as a copyright exception is just an effort to recalibrate the balance of various stakeholders’ interests in the digital age.</p>
<p>The current copyright exception criterion is the three-step test set out in article 9(2) of the Berne Convention and, most importantly, in article 13 of the TRIPS Agreement. Article 9(2) of the Berne Convention provides that: ‘It shall be a matter for legislation in the countries of the Union to permit the reproduction of such works in certain special cases, provided that such reproduction does not conflict with a normal exploitation of the work and does not unreasonably prejudice the legitimate interests of the author.’ Article 13 of the TRIPS Agreement similarly provides: ‘Members shall confine limitations or exceptions to exclusive rights to certain special cases which do not conflict with a normal exploitation of the work and do not unreasonably prejudice the legitimate interests of the rights holder.’ Incorporated in these two most important treaties on copyright, the three-step test is therefore a key part of the international copyright framework. It establishes the conditions for any exception and limitation of the reproduction right. It has become a benchmark for all copyright exceptions and limitations.</p>
<p>Let us briefly examine ‘mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public as a copyright exception’ under the three-step test. ‘Mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public’ shall easily meet the requirements of ‘special cases’ and ‘do not conflict with a normal exploitation of the work’. The remaining issue is whether it meets the requirement of ‘do not unreasonably prejudice the legitimate interests of the rights holder’. Temporary copying is usually believed not to unreasonably prejudice the legitimate interests of the rights holder. The problem is private copying. Individual private copying will not prejudice the legitimate interests of the rights holders; however, numerous acts of private copying put together probably will have negative effect on their economic interests. Therefore, under such an exception approach, compensation to the copyright holders can also be applied in certain circumstances. Copyright levy is a comparatively efficient mechanism that allows copyright holders to be compensated for widespread copying of their works for private use. Paying equitable compensation in appropriate cases is better than imposing a duty to negotiate private uses under the burden of exclusivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0165551513479242">49</xref>]. In order to mitigate the fairness problem of levies on multi-functional devices, a primary purpose or effect standard would be helpful. For multi-functional devices, levies should be imposed only on those with a primary purpose or effect on private copying. Levies should not target general purpose devices whose accidental, incidental or unwitting use is private copying. The function of a levy would probably be limited as more and more copying devices are multi-functional. Too broad a levy imposed on devices may hamper the development of useful new technologies. A special, albeit limited, copyright levy for private use is reasonable and necessary in certain circumstances. On the other hand, a certain amount of private copying is a reasonable expectation of users, and taking it as an exception to copyright will be welcomed by most people. Most people’s needs, expectations and interests should be considered seriously by legislators and judges in the democratic society.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0165551513479242" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>5. Conclusion</title>
<p>The development of copyright law has almost always been driven by information technologies. While reproduction is a fundamental concept for copyright and plays a central role in copyright history and also in the current copyright system, it has encountered serious challenges from several categories of copying activities in the digital age, most notably temporary copying and private copying. Although reproduction is the basic and central right in copyright, in the digital world, copy control is quite difficult. It is time for us to systematically rethink the concepts and principles of current copyright law, and to formulate a renewed copyright system to accommodate the challenges posed by information technologies. For such a new legal framework, this paper defines a broad and open-ended concept of dissemination right. This dissemination right refers to a group of exclusive rights relating to the information dissemination enjoyed by the copyright holders. The ideal model of legislation is to provide a general concept of dissemination and further prescribe it in more detail with a non-exhaustive list of detailed rights. Further, this broad and open-ended concept of dissemination right should replace the reproduction as the centre of copyright. Under such an approach, the key provision is that mere reproduction, absent dissemination to the public, should not be considered as a violation of copyright. Such a proposal can accommodate the challenges raised by the digital technologies. Copying will still remain a fundamental element of copyright. However, one broadly designed exception would be introduced to limit the reproduction right. Controlling dissemination can provide sufficient incentives for creative works. Such an approach to copyright law reform in the digital age is consistent with the main theories underlying the intellectual property system.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The writing of this paper was supported by the 985 Program’s third term projects of Nanjing University.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0165551513479242">
<label>[1]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feigenbaum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Taking the copy out of copyright</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Security and privacy in digital rights management: ACM CCS-8 workshop DRM 2001</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>, pp. <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0165551513479242">
<label>[2]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>The concept of reproduction and the ‘temporary and transient’ exception</article-title>. <source>Cambridge Law Journal</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>523</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0165551513479242">
<label>[3]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Committee on Intellectual Property Rights and the Emerging Information Infrastructure</collab>. <source>The digital dilemma: Intellectual property in the information age</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>, pp. <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0165551513479242">
<label>[4]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Pike &amp; Fischer</collab>. <source>The Digital Millennium Copyright Act: Text, history, and caselaw</source>. <publisher-loc>Silver Spring, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pike &amp; Fischer Inc</publisher-name>., <year>2003</year>, p. <fpage>573</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0165551513479242">
<label>[5]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Chasing copyright infringement in the streaming landscape</article-title>. <source>International Review of Intellectual Property and Competition Law</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>, <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0165551513479242">
<label>[6]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Litman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Revising copyright law for the information age</article-title>. <source>Oregon Law Review</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>, <fpage>46</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0165551513479242">
<label>[7]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Directive 2001/29/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 May 2001 on the harmonisation of certain aspects of copyright and related rights in the information society, articles 2, 3, 4, 5(1) and 5(2)(b)</collab>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europa.eu/legislation_summaries/information_society/data_protection/l26053_en.htm">http://europa.eu/legislation_summaries/information_society/data_protection/l26053_en.htm</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0165551513479242">
<label>[8]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Litman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Digital copyright</source>. <publisher-loc>Amherst, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prometheus Books</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year>: p. <fpage>180</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0165551513479242">
<label>[9]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Thuiskopie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> and <collab>WIPO</collab>. <source>International survey on private copying, law &amp; practice 2012</source>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wipo.int/freepublications/en/copyright/1037/wipo_pub_1037.pdf">http://www.wipo.int/freepublications/en/copyright/1037/wipo_pub_1037.pdf</ext-link> (<year>2012</year>, <access-date>accessed November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0165551513479242">
<label>[10]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kretschmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Private copying and fair compensation: An empirical study of copyright levies in Europe, A report for the UK Intellectual Property Office</article-title> (<month>October</month> <year>2011</year>), p. <fpage>8</fpage>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cippm.org.uk/pdfs/copyright-levy-kretschmer.pdf">http://www.cippm.org.uk/pdfs/copyright-levy-kretschmer.pdf</ext-link> (<year>2011</year>, <access-date>accessed November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0165551513479242">
<label>[11]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lunney</surname><given-names>GS.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>The death of copyright: Digital technology, private copying, and the Digital Millennium Copyright Act</article-title>. <source>Virginia Law Review</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0165551513479242">
<label>[12]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blázquez</surname><given-names>FJC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Private copying levies at the crossroads – An extract from the publication IRIS plus 2011–4 ‘Who Pays for Private Copying?</article-title>’ <publisher-loc>Strasbourg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>European Audiovisual Observatory</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>, p. <fpage>9</fpage>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.obs.coe.int/oea_publ/iris/iris_plus/iplus4LA_2011.pdf.en">http://www.obs.coe.int/oea_publ/iris/iris_plus/iplus4LA_2011.pdf.en</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0165551513479242">
<label>[13]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karapapa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Padawan</surname><given-names>v.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>SGAE: a right to private copy?</article-title> <source>European Intellectual Property Review</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0165551513479242">
<label>[14]</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>British Copyright Council</collab>. <article-title>Independent review of intellectual property and growth response to the call for evidence</article-title>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-c4e-sub-bcc.pdf">www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-c4e-sub-bcc.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0165551513479242">
<label>[15]</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>DACS</collab>. <article-title>Independent review of intellectual property and growth, DACS Submission 2011</article-title>, p. <fpage>4</fpage>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-c4e-sub-dacs.pdf">http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-c4e-sub-dacs.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0165551513479242">
<label>[16]</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Equity</collab>. <article-title>Equity response to the Hargreaves review into intellectual property and growth</article-title>, <month>February</month> <year>2011</year>, Section 4(iv), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-c4e-sub-equity.pdf">www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-c4e-sub-equity.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0165551513479242">
<label>[17]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>ME.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Music and video private copying: An international survey of the problem and the law</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sweet &amp; Maxwell</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0165551513479242">
<label>[18]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Möller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Copyright and the new technologies – The German Federal Republic’s solution?</article-title> <source>European Intellectual Property Review</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0165551513479242">
<label>[19]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>AF.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Principle or compromise? Understanding the original thinking behind statutory licence and levy schemes for private copying</article-title>. <source>Intellectual Property Quarterly</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>422</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0165551513479242">
<label>[20]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeBeer</surname><given-names>JF.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Copyrights, federalism, and the constitutionality of Canada’s private copying levy</article-title>. <source>McGill Law Journal</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>755</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0165551513479242">
<label>[21]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>Supreme Court rejects appeal requests re: private copying levy</article-title>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cippic.ca/en/news/130/54/Supreme-Court-rejects-appeal-requests-re%3A-private-copying-levy">http://www.cippic.ca/en/news/130/54/Supreme-Court-rejects-appeal-requests-re%3A-private-copying-levy</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0165551513479242">
<label>[22]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>An overview of the proposed introduction of a private copying exception into UK copyright law</article-title>. <source>Entertainment Law Review</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>,<fpage>77</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0165551513479242">
<label>[23]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>The UK government considers introducing private copy exception without compensation</article-title>, <day>15</day> <month>January</month> <year>2008</year>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europe.ifj.org/en/articles/the-uk-government-considers-introducing-private-copy-exception-without-compensation">http://europe.ifj.org/en/articles/the-uk-government-considers-introducing-private-copy-exception-without-compensation</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0165551513479242">
<label>[24]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<comment>UK to legalize private copying of CDs</comment>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/08/02/us-britain-copyright-idUSTRE7715BP20110802">http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/08/02/us-britain-copyright-idUSTRE7715BP20110802</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0165551513479242">
<label>[25]</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<article-title>Digital opportunity, a review of IP and growth, an independent report by Professor Ian Hargreaves</article-title>, <month>May</month> <year>2011</year>, Sections 5.28 and 5.30, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-finalreport.pdf">http://www.ipo.gov.uk/ipreview-finalreport.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0165551513479242">
<label>[26]</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<article-title>The Government Response to the Hargreaves review of intellectual property and growth</article-title>, pp. <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/g/11-1199-government-response-to-hargreaves-review">http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/g/11-1199-government-response-to-hargreaves-review</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0165551513479242">
<label>[27]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Helberger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>PB.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>No place like home for making a copy: Private copying in European copyright law and consumer law</article-title>. <source>Berkeley Technology Law Journal</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1071</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0165551513479242">
<label>[28]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>JC.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Legal protection of technological measures protecting works of authorship: International obligations and the US experience</article-title>. <source>Columbia Journal of Law and the Arts</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>12</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0165551513479242">
<label>[29]</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Werra</surname><given-names>JD.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>The legal system of technological protection measures under the WIPO treaties, the Digital Millennium Copyright Act, the European Union Directives and other National Laws (Japan, Australia)</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Adjuncts and alternatives to copyright: Proceedings of the ALAI congress</conf-name>, <conf-date>13–17 June 2001</conf-date>, <conf-loc>New York</conf-loc>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kernochan Center for Law, Media &amp; the Arts, Columbia University School of Law</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>, pp. <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0165551513479242">
<label>[30]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Technical devices as a solution to private copying</article-title>. In: <source>Copyright in the new digital environment: The need to redesign copyright</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sweet &amp; Maxwell</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>, pp. <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0165551513479242">
<label>[31]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heide</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Copyright in the EU and U.S.: What ‘access-right’?</article-title> <source>Journal of the Copyright Society of the U.S.A</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0165551513479242">
<label>[32]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westkamp</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Transient copying and public communications: The creeping evolution of use and access rights in European copyright law</article-title>. <source>George Washington International Law Review</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1062</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0165551513479242">
<label>[33]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>PK.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>P2P and the future of private copying</article-title>. <source>University of Colorado Law Review</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>76</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0165551513479242">
<label>[34]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Commission on Intellectual Property Rights</collab>. <article-title>Integrating intellectual property rights and development policy: Report of the Commission on Intellectual Property Rights</article-title>, p. <fpage>7</fpage>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iprcommission.org/papers/pdfs/final_report/ciprfullfinal.pdf">www.iprcommission.org/papers/pdfs/final_report/ciprfullfinal.pdf</ext-link> (<year>2003</year>, <access-date>accessed November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0165551513479242">
<label>[35]</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<collab>The Copyright Law Review Committee</collab>. <article-title>Simplification of the Copyright Act 1968</article-title> (<month>February</month> <year>1999</year>), Part 2 (Categorisation of Subject Matter and Exclusive Rights, and Other Issues), Sections 2.04, 3.49, 5.13, 5.02, 5.65 and 5.79.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0165551513479242">
<label>[36]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>AF.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>A proposal for simplifying United Kingdom copyright law</article-title>. <source>European Intellectual Property Review</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0165551513479242">
<label>[37]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ricketson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Simplifying copyright law: Proposals from down under</article-title>. <source>European Intellectual Property Review</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>, <fpage>550</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0165551513479242">
<label>[38]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>International Literary and Artistic Association</collab>. <source>Copyright in cyberspace: Copyright and the global information infrastructure</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dellebeke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.). <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Otto Cramwinckel</publisher-name>, <year>1997</year>, p. <fpage>126</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0165551513479242">
<label>[39]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>The Wittem Group</collab>. <article-title>European Copyright Code, article 4.1</article-title>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.copyrightcode.eu">http://www.copyrightcode.eu</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0165551513479242">
<label>[40]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Commission of the European Communities</collab>. <article-title>Green paper on copyright in the knowledge economy</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>COM</publisher-name>(<year>2008</year>) 466/3, Section 2.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0165551513479242">
<label>[41]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>JC.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>European copyright code – Back to first principles (with some additional detail)</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Copyright Society of the U.S.A</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0165551513479242">
<label>[42]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eechoud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guibault</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gompel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Helberger</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Harmonizing European copyright law: The challenges of better lawmaking</source>. <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Law International</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>, p. <fpage>374</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0165551513479242">
<label>[43]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gendreau</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>A technologically neutral solution for the internet: Is it wishful thinking?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stamatoudi</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torremans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Copyright in the new digital environment: The need to redesign copyright</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sweet &amp; Maxwell</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0165551513479242">
<label>[44]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Busche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arend</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds). <source>WTO-trade-related aspects of intellectual property rights</source>. <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Martinus Nijhoff</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>, pp. <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0165551513479242">
<label>[45]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Proskine</surname><given-names>EA.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Google’ technicolor dreamcoat: A copyright analysis of the Google Book Search Library Project</article-title>. <source>Berkeley Technology Law Journal</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0165551513479242">
<label>[46]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burrell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Copyright exceptions: The digital impact</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>, p. <fpage>i</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0165551513479242">
<label>[47]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>The future of copyright in Europe: Striking a fair balance between protection and access to information</article-title>. <source>Intellectual Property Quarterly</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>, <fpage>3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0165551513479242">
<label>[48]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>WIPO</collab>, <article-title>Limitations and exceptions</article-title>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wipo.int/copyright/en/limitations/index.html">http://www.wipo.int/copyright/en/limitations/index.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0165551513479242">
<label>[49]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Promoting creativity through copyright limitations: Reflections on the concept of exclusivity in copyright law</article-title>. <source>Vanderbilt Journal of Entertainment and Technology Law</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>515</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>