<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ABS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spabs</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Behavioral Scientist</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0002-7642</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3381</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0002764211419488</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0002764211419488</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Professionalization of Political Communication? A Longitudinal Analysis of Dutch Election Campaign Posters</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Corrigall-Brown</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Vliegenthart</surname><given-names>Rens</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0002764211419488">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0002764211419488"><label>1</label>Amsterdam School of Communication Research (ASCoR), University of Amsterdam</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0002764211419488">Rens Vliegenthart, Amsterdam School of Communication Research, University of Amsterdam, Kloveniersburgwal 48, 1012 CX Amsterdam, the Netherlands Email: <email>R.Vliegenthart@uva.nl</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0002764211419488">
<p>Rens Vliegenthart is an associate professor in Political Communication at the Amsterdam School of Communication Research, University of Amsterdam. His research interests include the relationship between media and politics, social movements and comparative communication research.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue Title: The Power of Pictures: Images of Politics and Protest</issue-title>
<fpage>135</fpage>
<lpage>150</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article provides an analysis of Dutch election posters in the period from 1946 to 2006. Based on the literature on the professionalization of political communication, several hypotheses are formulated regarding changes in textual and visual elements of those posters. These hypotheses focus on over-time changes in the presence and prominence of the party leader and party logo’s as well as references to specific political issues and ideology in these posters. In total, 225 posters for 23 parties in 19 elections are analyzed. Results reveal that changes in visual elements are in line with the hypotheses, with an increased use of party logo, an increasing presence and prominence of the party leader, and a decreasing focus on ideology. The textual parts of the posters, however, show no or opposite trends. The results call for a more nuanced scientific treatment of the consequences of the professionalization of political communication and demonstrate the necessity to analyze both visual and textual elements of political parties’ communication.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>election</kwd>
<kwd>media</kwd>
<kwd>Netherlands</kwd>
<kwd>campaign posters</kwd>
<kwd>political parties</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Since the end of the Second World War, political communication in Western democracies is argued to have undergone fundamental changes. A professionalization of politics and journalism, increasing market pressures, and technological developments such as the rise of television and the Internet have led to a new way in which politics is covered by the mass media and the way election campaigns are conducted by political actors. To describe these changes, a plethora of different concepts have been coined, including “personalization” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0002764211419488">Rahat &amp; Sheafer, 2007</xref>), “professionalization” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0002764211419488">Negrine &amp; Lilleker, 2002</xref>), “Americanization” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0002764211419488">Hallin &amp; Mancini, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0002764211419488">Negrine &amp; Papathanassopoulos, 1996</xref>) and “entertainization” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0002764211419488">Van Zoonen, 2005</xref>). All these concepts implicitly or explicitly assume more or less ongoing and deterministic developments that stretch over several decades. Ultimately, they result in political campaigns that are characterized by high levels of negativity, little attention for political issues, a high focus on political leaders, and a crucial role for the political marketeer or spin doctor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0002764211419488">Blumler &amp; Gurevitch, 1995</xref>). In many instances, these developments are assumed or only illustrated with anecdotal evidence, rather than being subject to a systematic empirical analysis. If such analyses are conducted, they often focus on media coverage of election campaigns (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0002764211419488">Esser, 2008</xref>). Though indeed, in many of those processes, a crucial role is being fulfilled by the journalist, and many of the alleged developments are indeed reflected first and foremost in political news coverage, it only tells part of the story. It does not provide insight into the question of to what extent political actors themselves have changed their communication during election campaigns substantially or whether news coverage is merely a consequence of (changing) processes of gatekeeping, news selection, news values, and description bias (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0002764211419488">Shoemaker &amp; Reese, 1996</xref>) that result in coverage that can be substantially different from the message that is intended by a political actor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0002764211419488">Walter &amp; Vliegenthart, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>It is not surprising that such longitudinal analyses of political actors’ behavior during election campaigns are scarce. After all, the means by which political actors communicate have changed fundamentally. Nowadays, a lot of this communication is done via the Internet and social media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0002764211419488">Smith &amp; Rainie, 2008</xref>) or televised campaign ads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0002764211419488">Geer, 1996</xref>). In the early years after the Second World War, however, the political party was for its unmediated communication dependent largely dependent on printed party outlets. The format of those outlets and their potential audience might well affect the way the message is presented—or even the content of the message. So, the challenge lies in finding a channel of communication that is used throughout several decades and preferably targets a large part of the electorate. This article presents the analysis of such a channel. It presents a visual analysis of Dutch campaign posters for the period 1946 to 2006. In the post–World War II period, posters have been a central way for Dutch political parties to communicate with voters in the weeks before the parliamentary elections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0002764211419488">Elzinga &amp; Voerman, 2002</xref>). Throughout the country, parties are offered legal places to display these posters and—despite all kinds of alternative and new communication channels—they are still widely used.</p>
<p>The Netherlands is an example of a multiparty democracy with a system of proportional representation that—though less than many of the Anglo-Saxon countries—is argued to have indeed witnessed a strong professionalization of political communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0002764211419488">Brants &amp; van Praag, 2006</xref>). This article addresses the question of to what extent this professionalization, and related developments such as personalization, increased negativity, and a decreasing importance of ideology, is reflected in the campaign posters. In that way, it is possible to assess to what extent political parties’ unmediated communication is affected by trends that are argued to be omnipresent in modern Western election campaigns.</p>
<sec id="section1-0002764211419488">
<title>The Professionalization of Political Communication</title>
<p>This section provides a short overview of the changes that took place in the interaction between political actors, media actors, and citizens during the past six decades and that are in the broadest sense described as the professionalization of political communication. Based on those changes, explicit expectations can be formulated regarding the alteration of content and features of campaign posters. It is by no means meant as a comprehensive overview but only shortly describes those elements that can be expected to affect the way political parties communicate to the electorate.</p>
<p>During the past decades, the interaction between politicians and the electorate has changed in profound ways. Until roughly the 1960s, many Western societies were characterized by strong cleavages that divided the population in clearly disguisable groups with different ideological preferences and/or denominations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0002764211419488">Lijphart, 1999</xref>). Electoral volatility was low: Overwhelmingly, people voted for the party that corresponded to their respective group in society. This period can be considered the heydays of political parties: They were the political agenda setters, and journalists and citizens followed their lead. In this period, election campaigns were short, and parties directed their main efforts to ensuring that their own people would turn out and vote. Television played no or only a marginal role in election campaigns, with the main mass media being newspapers and to a lesser extent radio. In many countries, newspapers were still partisan with strong ties between them and specific political parties. Several authors have coined different terms for this phase of political communication: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0002764211419488">Blumler and Kavanagh (1999)</xref>, with a focus on the British case, talk about the times of premodern election campaigns; while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0002764211419488">Brants and van Praag (2006)</xref> in their analysis of historical developments in the Netherlands talk about an area of “political logic.” In line with the characteristics of this period, one could expect the communication of political parties to be ideologically driven, with more focus on the party and less so on the leader, explicitly summoning people to go out and vote.</p>
<p>With the rise of television and the disappearance of many of the cleavages that had structured societies in the previous phase, the late 1960s and 1970s witnessed considerable changes in how the political process was organized and in how the interaction between politicians, journalists, and citizens took place. Processes of secularization and modernization resulted in citizens who were not habitual voters anymore: Party membership decreased, electoral volatility went up; and consequently, election campaigns became more important, because political parties could really gain or lose electoral support during the period preceding the elections. The rise of the catchall political party (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0002764211419488">Krouwel, 2003</xref>) is just one example of the consequences of those changes. The appearance of television as the main mass medium also required politicians to have different qualities: a good physical appearance as well as, for example, strong debating skills were required to make the best impression. The direct confrontation with political opponents, who became competitors, increased in importance. Also, in media coverage, political conflict became more important at the expense of substantial issue coverage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0002764211419488">Brants &amp; van Praag, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0002764211419488">Cappella &amp; Jamieson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0002764211419488">Patterson, 1993</xref>). In those years, many Western countries faced the appearance of the first political marketeers and spin doctors, full-time professionals who advised political parties on how to conduct their campaigns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0002764211419488">Esser, Reinemann, &amp; Fan, 2001</xref>). It is not surprising that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0002764211419488">Blumler and Kavanagh (1999)</xref> label this period the “modern election campaign,” whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0002764211419488">Brants and van Praag (2006)</xref> talk about the period of “public logic,” thereby also emphasizing the increased self-confidence among journalists and their concern with the public good, acting increasingly in accordance with the independent role as the “watchdogs” of democracy. Again, one would expect to see the changes reflected in the communication of parties, that is likely to be more personalized—that is, more attention for the political leader instead of the political party, less focus on ideology, and increasing (negative) attention for political opponents.</p>
<p>In the literature, a third phase of professionalization of political communication is identified, which is labeled by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0002764211419488">Blumler and Kavanagh (1999)</xref> as “postmodern.” It arguably started in the 1990s and can in many respects be seen as characterized by an elaboration or extension of many of the phenomena that started to emerge in the modern election phase. It shows increasing levels of electoral volatility, personalization, and negativity, whereas public opinion polls—both on general electoral preferences as well as on specific policy issues—become a very important guide for journalists, politicians, and policy makers. Media are considered to have taken the center stage of politics—the reason why <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0002764211419488">Brants and van Praag (2006)</xref> identify this period to be subject to “media logic.” Increasing levels of commercialization have resulted in a disappearance of the boundaries between entertainment and politics, resulting in an increase of “infotainment” programs on television (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0002764211419488">Brants, 1998</xref>). The rise of the Internet has further intensified many of these developments. It offers politicians a means to communicate directly with the public, thereby bypassing journalists. This communication is likely to be even more personalized, as a consequence of inherent characteristics of the new medium, but also as a means to attract attention in an extremely information-dense context. It can be expected that those developments are reflected in parties’ communication by an even higher focus on persons, negative attention for opponents, and little focus on ideology but rather on specific issues that are of major concern to the public.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0002764211419488">
<title>Hypotheses</title>
<p>The previous section discussed the professionalization of political communication as a process in which various more or less time-bounded stages can be identified. However, these stages are merely reflections of ongoing processes that span over the whole or large parts of the time period under investigation and that also continue within each stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0002764211419488">Blumler &amp; Kavanagh, 1999</xref>). Therefore, the hypotheses about expected changes in campaign posters are formulated as linear developments that span the whole research period. I expect the level of professionalization to increase over time and that this professionalization is being reflected in two ways: first, an increasing consistency between images and written text in terms of their content and focus on the campaign poster, and second, a more consistent design that is being mirrored in the use of the party logo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0002764211419488">Farrell &amp; Wortmann, 1987</xref>). Therefore, the first hypotheses are</p>
<list id="list1-0002764211419488" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1a</italic>: Over time, the campaign posters show an increasing consistency in terms of content and focus between images and written texts.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1b</italic>: Over time, the campaign posters more often contain the party logo’s.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The second hypothesis focuses on the extent to which the poster provides an explicit call to go out and vote. Especially in the early years of our research period, campaign activities were focused on getting one’s own electorate to the ballot box. One can therefore expect that the posters would explicitly remind people to go and vote for the party, whereas the presence of this explicit call is decreasing over time.</p>
<list id="list2-0002764211419488" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: Over time, the presence of explicit calls to go and vote on campaign posters decreases.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The third hypothesis deals with increased levels of personalization—here conceptualized as a shift in attention from the political party to the political leaders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0002764211419488">Vliegenthart, Boomgaarden, &amp; Boumans, 2011</xref>). I expect this personalization to be reflected in three ways: in the use of pictures of the political leader, in the prominence of these pictures in terms of the part of the poster they cover, and in the mentioning of the political leader in the text. This results in the following three subhypotheses:</p>
<list id="list3-0002764211419488" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3a</italic>: Over time, the use of pictures of political leaders on campaign posters increases.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3b</italic>: Over time, the prominence of pictures of political leaders on campaign posters increases.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3c</italic>: Over time, the mentioning of political leaders in the texts on campaign posters increases.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The fourth set of hypotheses deals with the shift in party communication from ideology and more abstract political values to a stronger focus on specific and concrete political issues. I expect this shift to be reflected both in images and text. Therefore, I derive two hypotheses:</p>
<list id="list4-0002764211419488" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4a</italic>: Over time, the number of images that refer to ideology and abstract values decreases at the expense of images that refer to concrete policy issues.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4b</italic>: Over time, the number of in-text references to ideology and abstract values decreases at the expense of in-text references to concrete policy issues.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The final hypothesis deals with increased negativity directed towards political opponents. Again, this negativity might be reflected in both images and text. However, because descriptive analyses will reveal that negativity is only used in very few instances, I combine those two measures of negativity and formulate one hypothesis:</p>
<list id="list5-0002764211419488" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 5</italic>: Over time, the level of negative references to political opponents increases.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0002764211419488">
<title>The Dutch Case</title>
<p>The Netherlands is a small Western European consociational democracy with a multiparty system. It is a monarchy, with the official head of state having some influence on the political process. It has a political system that is characterized by a bicameral system. Only the 150 (until 1956, 100) members of the Lower House (Tweede Kamer) are elected directly by the population using a system of proportional representation and an open list system. People vote for candidates who belong to a specific political party. If the respective candidate receives a considerable amount of preferential votes, he or she is elected in Parliament. Otherwise, the order of the candidates on the party list is followed. Over the past decades, on average around ten parties were represented in Parliament. Elections are held once every 4 years, or earlier when majority support for the government in Parliament disappears. Governments are composed of multiple parties—usually two or three.</p>
<p>The county has traditionally been characterized by a strongly divided (“pillarized”) society that is structured by strong cleavages based on denomination and ideology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0002764211419488">Lijphart, 1968</xref>). Until the mid-1960s, members from the main groups in society (Catholics, Protestants, Socialists, and Liberals) lived largely separated in subcultures, with each of them having a self-sustaining system in terms of schools, hospitals, political parties, newspapers, and radio and television broadcast organizations. Whereas those minority groups lived with little contacts, the political system of coalition formation and thus consensus-seeking required their political leaders and elites to cooperate closely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0002764211419488">Andeweg &amp; Irwin, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The pillarized structure of the Dutch society was also reflected in low levels of electoral volatility. Until the mid-1960s, only few parliamentary seats changed party per election. This changed considerably in the mid-1960s and 1970s. A strong process of de-pillarization set in, fading out the cleavages that structured the Dutch society until then. Processes of modernization and secularization, present throughout most of the Western world, can be argued to have a profound impact on the Dutch society. Since the 1960s, a whole range of new parties appeared (and disappeared) in the Dutch political system, ranging from the Social-Liberal party Democraten 66 and the socialist Socialistische Partij, to more recently populist right-wing parties such as Lijst Pim Fortuyn and Geert Wilders’ Partij voor de Vrijheid.</p>
<p>The Dutch media system is identified as belonging to the Democratic-Corporatist model, which is traditionally characterized by strong political parallelism, high levels of state intervention to protect press freedom, a strong public broadcast system, and high levels of journalistic professionalization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0002764211419488">Hallin &amp; Mancini, 2004</xref>). It differs from the Liberal model, with the United Kingdom and the United States as the most prone examples, in having a less developed system of commercial media. Furthermore, the Liberal system is characterized by even earlier developed high standards of journalistic professionalization and a less pronounced role of the state in securing press freedom. For the Dutch case specifically, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0002764211419488">Brants and van Praag (2006)</xref> argue that professionalization of journalists, but also of election campaigning in general, only developed slowly. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0002764211419488">Hallin and Mancini (2004)</xref> demonstrate, however, the differences between the various systems are decreasing over time, and current election campaigns in countries with different models have a lot in common. Still, the Dutch case provides a conservative test of the hypotheses originating from the professionalization of political communication thesis. If the hypothesized trends are indeed found in the Dutch context, they are likely to be even more prominent in other Western countries, especially the United States and United Kingdom.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0002764211419488" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>The hypotheses are tested by means of a systematic analysis of Dutch election campaign posters for the period 1946 to 2006. Although production and use of the posters is not as widely spread and professionalized as in neighboring countries like France and Germany (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0002764211419488">Dumitrescu, 2010</xref>), it is widely used in the weeks preceding elections. The <italic>Documentatiecentrum Nederlandse Politieke Partijen</italic> (Documentation Centre Dutch Political Parties) at the University of Groningen has collected a large part of those posters. For the national parliamentary elections, the collection is close to complete from the 1960s onwards, but it also it contains a considerable number of posters for the years before.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0002764211419488">1</xref></sup> From the archive, all campaign posters for the national elections are selected from those parties that obtained at least one seat in Parliament during that election. Some parties use more than one poster per election. If that were the case, up to a maximum of four posters were coded. If the party issued more than four posters, a random selection was made. In the analysis, cases (posters) are weighted by the number of posters per party per election that is included in the sample. A total of 225 posters were selected. They cover 23 parties in 19 elections.</p>
<p>A codebook was developed that contained basic information about the posters as well as a whole range of items that dealt with the visual and textual characteristics of the poster. The relevant items for this article are the following:</p>
<list id="list6-0002764211419488" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Does the poster contain a party logo, or is the name of the party portrayed in a stylized manner? (H1b)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the text on the poster contain an explicit call to vote? (H2)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the poster contain an image of the party leader? (H3a)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Which part of the poster is used for the image of the party leader? (H3b)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0002764211419488">2</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the text on the poster refer to the party leader? (H3c)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the image on the poster refer to ideology or more abstract political values? (H4a)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the image on the poster refer to concrete policy issues or policy stances? (H4a)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the text on the poster refer to ideology or more abstract political values? (H4b)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the text on the poster refer to concrete policy issues or policy stances? (H4b)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the text on the poster refer to other political parties, politicians, or the previous government in negative terms? (H5)</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>For H1a, consistency is considered to be present if both image and text refer to either the leader, ideology, or concrete policy issues or policy stances.</p>
<p>A single coder, a native speaker with considerable knowledge of Dutch politics, coded the campaign posters. To check reliability of the codings, a second person coded a random sample of 15 posters. Pairwise agreement scores for the separate items range from 73% to 100%. The Krippendorff’s alpha score for all the coding decisions combined was .80, which is considered a good score (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0002764211419488">Hayes &amp; Krippendorff, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>All the dependent variables have a binary distribution, indicating whether a certain characteristic is absent (0) or present (1). Therefore, several logistic regressions are conducted. The main dependent variable is the year in which the election took place. A significant positive effect indicates an increase of the presence of the respective characteristic, whereas a negative effect indicates a decrease.</p>
<p>Furthermore, as a control variable, the party family to which the party belongs is included, assuming that there might be systematic differences in the character of campaign posters across parties with a different ideological background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0002764211419488">Dumitrescu, 2010</xref>). Here, I follow the classification made by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0002764211419488">Andeweg and Irwin (2005)</xref>, who classify the parties as “Christian-Democratic,” “Socialist,” “Liberals,” “Greens,”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0002764211419488">3</xref></sup> and “Populist/Extreme-Right.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0002764211419488" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The campaign posters that are used during a 60-year period show a large variation in terms of design and content. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0002764211419488">Figure 1</xref> presents a few examples of the posters that appeared throughout the research period. The first one on the left presents the campaign poster of the liberal party Volkspartij voor Vrijheid en Democratie (VVD) for the 1959 elections. Both image and text emphasize the importance of freedom, with the statue of liberty and the text “Keep freedom high.” The second poster is again emphasizing more abstract values in both image and text. The 1971 election poster of the small pacifist-socialist party Pascifistische Socialistische Partij (PSP) is considered to be a groundbreaking example that even gained some reputation outside the Netherlands. It can be considered to be a clear expression of the progressive mood that was present during that time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0002764211419488">Goslinga, Ten Hooven, &amp; Lage, 2005</xref>). The term “<italic>ontwapenend</italic>” refers both to the pacifist ideology of the party in the more literal meaning of “disarming” as reducing weaponry, as well as to the attitude of liberal life as being unconstrained by existing norms about what is appropriate and what is not.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0002764211419488" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Examples of Dutch campaign posters—from left to right: Volkspartij voor Vrijheid en Democratie (VVD) 1959; Pascifistische Socialistische Partij (PSP) 1971; Christen Democratisch Appèl (CDA) 1982; GroenLinks 2003</p>
<p>Source: Documentation Centre Dutch Political Parties, University of Groningen.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0002764211419488-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The third poster is a simple one, and throughout the research period, numerous examples of this type are present. It is used for the 1982 election by the Christian-Democratic party Christen Democratisch Appèl (CDA) and only mentions the name of the party, of the party leader (then Prime Minister Dries van Agt), and the number of the list on the ballot-paper that is occupied by that party. The final example illustrates the change to more stylized multicolor campaign posters that only took place in the 1990s. The poster contains a large close-up picture of Green Party GroenLinks leader Femke Halsema with the text referring again to more abstract values: “Fighting for what is vulnerable.” The name of the party is displayed in a stylized manner as is done in all party communications.</p>
<p>What systematic differences exist over time, and to what extent do those changes mirror the professionalization of election campaigning? <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0002764211419488">Figures 2</xref> through <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0002764211419488">4</xref> display the over-time developments in the characteristics of the posters, whereas <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0002764211419488">Table 1</xref> provides the formal tests of the hypotheses. It displays the effect of election year in terms of its odds ratio with values higher than 1 indicating a positive effect and values lower than 1 a negative effect. Furthermore, a Wald chi-square statistic is presented to indicate whether there are any systematic differences across parties from different party families, as well as the Nagelkerke (pseudo) <italic>R</italic>-squared and the percentage of correct predictions by the model.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0002764211419488" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Over-time presence of consistency, party logo, and call to vote</p>
<p>Scores range from 0 (present on none of the election posters in the election year) to 1 (present on all election posters in the election year).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0002764211419488-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0002764211419488" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Over-time levels of personalization</p>
<p>Scores range from 0 (present on none of the election posters in the election year) to 1 (present on all election posters in the election year). For the “prominent picture leader” variable, the share of those posters that include a picture of the leader is reported.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0002764211419488-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0002764211419488" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Over-time presence of ideology, policy issues, and negativity</p>
<p>Scores range from 0 (present on none of the election posters in the election year) to 1 (present on all election posters in the election year).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0002764211419488-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0002764211419488" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Predicting Features of Campaign Posters</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0002764211419488" xlink:href="10.1177_0002764211419488-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Dependent variable</th>
<th align="center">Election year</th>
<th align="center">Party family</th>
<th align="center">Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center">Predicted correctly (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Consistency (H1a)</td>
<td>0.974<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">**</xref> (.010)</td>
<td>3.623</td>
<td>.063</td>
<td>65.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Logo (H1b)</td>
<td>1.097<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">***</xref> (.014)</td>
<td>9.912<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">*</xref></td>
<td>.417</td>
<td>79.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Call to vote (H2)</td>
<td>0.991 (.011)</td>
<td>5.160</td>
<td>.042</td>
<td>77.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Image leader (H3a)</td>
<td>1.024<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">**</xref> (.010)</td>
<td>7.606</td>
<td>.087</td>
<td>64.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prominence leader (H3b)</td>
<td>1.059<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">***</xref> (.018)</td>
<td>3.294</td>
<td>.307</td>
<td>72.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Text leader (H3c)</td>
<td>0.975<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">**</xref> (.009)</td>
<td>9.368</td>
<td>.103</td>
<td>65.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Image ideology (H4a)</td>
<td>0.958<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">**</xref> (.015)</td>
<td>8.619</td>
<td>.146</td>
<td>87.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Image policy issues (H4a)</td>
<td>1.018 (.040)</td>
<td>.904</td>
<td>.233</td>
<td>98.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Text ideology (H4b)</td>
<td>1.019<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0002764211419488">*</xref> (.009)</td>
<td>4.618</td>
<td>.048</td>
<td>61.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Text policy issues (H4b)</td>
<td>0.993 (.018)</td>
<td>4.413</td>
<td>.238</td>
<td>92.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Negativity (H5)</td>
<td>0.969 (.027)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.330</td>
<td>96.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0002764211419488">
<p>For election year, odd ratios are reported with standard errors in parentheses; for party family, a Wald chi-square statistic is reported; <italic>N</italic> = 225, except for “prominence leader” (<italic>N</italic> = 68).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0002764211419488">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 (one-tailed tests).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Hypothesis 1 focuses on the professionalization in terms of increasing consistency between image and text (H1a), as well as increasing use of the party logo (H1b). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0002764211419488">Figure 1</xref> indicates that consistency seems to decrease, rather than increase over time. This observation is confirmed by <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0002764211419488">Table 1</xref>: The coefficient of .974 indicates that the chances of encountering a “consistent” poster decrease over time. Thus, Hypothesis 1a needs to be rejected. Hypothesis 1b is confirmed: As demonstrated by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0002764211419488">Figure 2</xref>, the use of a party logo is especially prevalent during the later years of the research period. This is also confirmed by the regression analysis: Each year, the odds of encountering a party logo on the campaign poster versus not encountering one increase by 9.7%. This characteristic is also the only one that shows systematic variation across parties: A more detailed analysis (not displayed here) reveals that populist/extreme-right parties use their party logo significantly less than parties belonging to another party family.</p>
<p>Hypothesis 2 deals with the explicit call to go to the ballot box. As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0002764211419488">Figure 2</xref> demonstrates, this appeal has been especially present in the first years after the Second World War and to a lesser extent in most recent years as well. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0002764211419488">Table 1</xref> reveals that whereas there might be a slight over-time decrease in explicit calls to vote, this decrease is not significant. Consequently, Hypothesis 2 needs to be rejected.</p>
<p>The personalization of politics is central in Hypotheses 3a through 3c. Here, I expect the leader to be more often present both in images (H3a) and that this presence was also more prominent (H3b). Furthermore, he or she might well be mentioned more often in the text (H3c). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0002764211419488">Figure 3</xref> displays the levels of personalization per election. It indicates that the leader was already present in pictures on the (few) posters in the premodern stage of election campaigns. Also in the later years, the leader was often present. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0002764211419488">Table 1</xref> indicates that indeed, Hypothesis 3a is confirmed: The leader is significantly more present in pictures over time. This is also true for prominence: Over time, of the posters that contain an image of the party leader, a larger share has the image covering more than half of the poster. Thus, Hypothesis 3b is confirmed. Finally, Hypothesis 3c needs to be rejected. The name of the party leader was already mentioned on the posters in the early years, and its presence decreases significantly over time (odds ratio smaller than 1; see Table 2). This might well be due to the fact that parties assume their leaders to be known and assume that a photo is sufficient—as the GroenLinks example from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0002764211419488">Figure 1</xref> shows.</p>
<p>Hypothesis 4 assumes a shift from an ideological orientation to one that focuses on concrete policy issues and stances. I assume this shift to be present both in images (H4a), as well as in text (H4b). Ideology, but especially policy issues, are only present in a small number of the images (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0002764211419488">Figure 4</xref>). For ideology, however, a significant decrease can be found: Each year, the odds of encountering a poster with an image that refers to ideology versus encountering a poster without such an image decrease by 4.2%. For policy issues, there is no significant linear trend, but this might well be due to the fact that only on 3 of 225 this characteristic was present. Thus, the data offer only partial evidence for Hypothesis 4a. There is no evidence for Hypothesis 4b: In-text references to ideology are still present to a considerable extent in the later years, and their presence has even increased over time, whereas references to specific policy issues and stances do not significantly change.</p>
<p>Finally, we look at the last hypothesis that predicted increased levels of negativity. As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0002764211419488">Figure 3</xref> indicates, campaign posters are hardly used to attack other political parties or politicians: Only in 8 of the 225 posters is a negative reference made. These references to negativity are scattered throughout the research period and no clear upward or downward trend can be detected. So, Hypothesis 5 needs to be rejected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0002764211419488" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The longitudinal visual and textual analysis of Dutch election campaign posters after World War II offers evidence for some of the changes that are ascribed to the professionalization of political communication in the literature. These changes were especially present in the visual part of the posters. On one hand, the party logo was used more often and the visual presence of the party leader increases, both in frequency and prominence. On the other hand, the visual representation of ideology decreases over time. Remarkably enough, the texts displayed on the posters often showed opposite trends: For example, they referred less often to the political leader, whereas the number of textual references to ideology actually increased over time. Furthermore, negativity was largely absent throughout the research period, whereas consistency between text and image actually decreased.</p>
<p>For some of the unexpected results, there might exist good explanations. It is likely that negative campaigning is found when considering different communication channels like media coverage or televised debates. Previous research indeed suggests that when parties have full control over their message and are not confronted with opponents directly, they are less inclined to go negative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0002764211419488">Walter &amp; Vliegenthart, 2010</xref>). The lack of consistency and decrease of in-text references to the party leader might be a consequence of a strategy that considers text and visuals as complementary rather than overlapping parts of the posters. With the increasing visual presence of the party leader, the limited amount of text is likely to be attributed to other reasons to vote for the party. More generally, the results have at least two broader implications. First, they indicate that presenting trends of professionalization, personalization, and the like as deterministic, ongoing, and omnipresent phenomena is an oversimplification of reality (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0002764211419488">Vliegenthart et al., 2011</xref>). Whether one finds personalization, for example, depends on the outlet, or even the more specific elements that are under consideration. A more refined theory needs to be developed to fully understand when and how fundamental changes in the way election campaigns are conducted alter communication by media and political actors. Second, in developing such a theory, it seems to be necessary to separate textual and visual elements of communication. The latter has received very little attention in the study of political communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0002764211419488">Grabe &amp; Bucy, 2009</xref>), whereas it is considered an important part of the current—mediated and unmediated—communication between politicians and voters. This study demonstrates that even a simple analysis of the visual aspects of party communication offers additional insights and results in strikingly different outcomes compared to a purely textual analysis.</p>
<p>This study is not without shortcomings, the main one probably being its limited focus, making it difficult to generalize its findings. First, it investigates one channel for party communication, while leaving other ones unresearched (for the Dutch case for example, party broadcast or magazines). Second, it focuses on a single country. Campaign posters are used throughout Europe and beyond as a means to communicate to the voter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0002764211419488">Dumitrescu, 2010</xref>). A comparative study could reveal whether the findings of this article also apply in other countries with similar political and media systems. There is no reason to expect that similar trends will not be found in countries such as Germany, Belgium, and the Nordic countries. In fact, one might even anticipate some of the trends, for example, increased personalization, to be stronger in countries that have a more candidate-centered political system and even higher levels of professionalization of political communication, such as the United Kingdom and the United States. Finally, the analysis of campaign posters only focused on those elements that were considered relevant in the light of the discussion of professionalization of political communication. A more detailed analysis can identify differences across parties and understand the strategies that underlie the design of the posters (for an interesting analysis of French campaign posters, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0002764211419488">Dumitrescu, 2010</xref>). However, the narrow focus did offer the opportunity to provide a detailed account of how Dutch political parties used campaign posters during the past decades. Finally, the study demonstrates how a combined visual and textual analysis can offer additional insights and provide a more comprehensive picture of the content of communication under investigation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The research was supported through a VENI-grant from the Dutch science foundation.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0002764211419488">
<label>1.</label>
<p>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rug.nl:80/dnpp/collecties/affiches/index">http://www.rug.nl:80/dnpp/collecties/affiches/index</ext-link> for a description and the archive.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0002764211419488">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Response categories range from less than a quarter to more than three quarters. For the analysis, a distinction between less than a half or more than a half is used.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0002764211419488">
<label>3.</label>
<p>The main environmental party, GroenLinks (GreenLeft), was the results a merger of various leftist parties in 1989 that did not have a clear ecological profile. Here, three of them are classified as Greens anyway (PSP, PPR, EVP), because they can not be clearly classified as belonging to any other family. The Communist Party CPN is placed in the Socialist category (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0002764211419488">Andeweg &amp; Irwin, 2005</xref>, pp. 48-57).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andeweg</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Governance and Politics of the Netherlands</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Houndmills, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blumler</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gurevitch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>The crisis of public communication</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blumler</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The third age of political communication: Influences and features</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brants</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Who’s afraid of infotainment?</article-title> <source>European Journal of Communication</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>315</fpage>-<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brants</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Praag</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Signs of media logic. Half a century of political communication in the Netherlands</article-title>. <source>Javnost/The Public</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cappella</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Spiral of cynicism: The press and the public good</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dumitrescu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Know me, love me, fear me: The anatomy of candidate poster designs in the 2007 French legislative elections</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elzinga</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voerman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Om de stembus: verkiezingsaffiches 1918-1998</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Veen</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Dimensions of political news cultures: Sound bite and image bite news in France, Germany, Great Britain, and the United States</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Press/Politics</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reinemann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Spin doctors in the United States, Great Britain, and Germany</article-title>. <source>Harvard International Journal of Press/Politics</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wortmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Party strategies in the electoral market: Political marketing in West Germany, Britain and Ireland</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Political Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>From tea leaves to opinion polls</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goslinga</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ten Hooven</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>, <month>November</month> <day>15</day>). <article-title>Echte vader van het affiche; ‘Ik wilde een typisch Hollandse foto maken’; zij van het Binnenhof</article-title>. <source>Trouw</source>, p. <fpage>11</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grabe</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bucy</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Image bite politics: News and visual framing of elections</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallin</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Comparing media systems. Three models of media and politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krippendorff</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Answering the call for a standard reliability measure for coding data</article-title>. <source>Communication Methods and Measures</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krouwel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Otto Kirchheimer and the catch-all party</article-title>. <source>West European Politics</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lijphart</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>). <source>The politics of accommodation: Pluralism and democracy in the Netherlands</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lijphart</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Patterns of democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Negrine</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lilleker</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The professionalization of political communication: Continuities and change in media practices</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Communication</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Negrine</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papathanassopoulos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The “Americanization” of political communication</article-title>. <source>Harvard International Journal of Press/Politics</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Out of order</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Knopf</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rahat</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheafer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The personalization(s) of politics: Israel, 1949-2003</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Mediating the message: Theories of influences on mass media content</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rainie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The Internet and the 2008 election</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Zoonen</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Entertaining the citizen: When politics and popular culture converge</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vliegenthart</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boomgaarden</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boumans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Changes in political news coverage: Personalization, conflict and negativity in British and Dutch newspapers</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Brants</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voltmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Political communication in postmodern democracy</source> (pp. <fpage>92</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Houndmills, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0002764211419488">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vliegenthart</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Negative campaigning across different communication channels: Different ball games?</article-title> <source>International Journal of Press/Politics</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>