<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HOL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphol</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Holocene</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0959-6836</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0911</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0959683611425551</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0959683611425551</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Revised calendar date for the Taupo eruption derived by <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-matching using a New Zealand kauri <sup>14</sup>C calibration data set</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0959683611425551">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>David J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0959683611425551">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0959683611425551">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Boswijk</surname><given-names>Gretel</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0959683611425551">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>Christopher Bronk</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0959683611425551">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0959683611425551"><label>1</label>University of Waikato, New Zealand</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0959683611425551"><label>2</label>Gondwana Tree-Ring Laboratory, New Zealand</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0959683611425551"><label>3</label>University of Auckland, New Zealand</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0959683611425551"><label>4</label>Oxford Radiocarbon Accelerator Unit, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0959683611425551">Alan G. Hogg, Radiocarbon Laboratory, University of Waikato, Private Bag 3105, Hamilton 3240, New Zealand. Email: <email>alan.hogg@waikato.ac.nz</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>439</fpage>
<lpage>449</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>13</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>11</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Taupo volcano in central North Island, New Zealand, is the most frequently active and productive rhyolite volcano on Earth. Its latest explosive activity about 1800 years ago generated the spectacular Taupo eruption, the most violent eruption known in the world in the last 5000 years. We present here a new accurate and precise eruption date of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 5 (1718 ± 5 cal. BP) for the Taupo event. This date was derived by wiggle-matching 25 high-precision <sup>14</sup>C dates from decadal samples of <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> from the Pureora buried forest near Lake Taupo against the high-precision, first-millennium <sc>ad</sc> subfossil <italic>Agathis australis</italic> (kauri) calibration data set constructed by the Waikato Radiocarbon Laboratory. It shows that postulated dates for the eruption estimated previously from Greenland ice-core records (<sc>ad</sc> 181 ± 2) and putative historical records of unusual atmospheric phenomena in ancient Rome and China (<italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 186) are both untenable. However, although their conclusion of a zero north–south <sup>14</sup>C offset is erroneous, and their data exhibit a laboratory bias of about 38 years (too young), Sparks et al. (Sparks RJ, Melhuish WH, McKee JWA, Ogden J, Palmer JG and Molloy BPJ (1995) <sup>14</sup>C calibration in the Southern Hemisphere and the date of the last Taupo eruption: Evidence from tree-ring sequences. <italic>Radiocarbon</italic> 37: 155–163) correctly utilized the Northern Hemisphere calibration curve of Stuiver and Becker (Stuiver M and Becker B (1993) High-precision decadal calibration of the radiocarbon timescale, AD 1950–6000 BC. <italic>Radiocarbon</italic> 35: 35–65) to obtain an accurate wiggle-match date for the eruption identical to ours but less precise (<sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 15). Our results demonstrate that high-agreement levels, indicated by either agreement indices or χ<sup>2</sup> data, obtained from a <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match do not necessarily mean that age models are accurate. We also show that laboratory bias, if suspected, can be mitigated by applying the reservoir offset function with an appropriate error value (e.g. 0 ± 40 years). Ages for eruptives such as Taupo tephra that are based upon individual <sup>14</sup>C dates should be considered as approximate only, and confined ideally to short-lived material (e.g. seeds, leaves, small branches or the outer rings of larger trees).</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd><sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating</kwd>
<kwd>chronostratigraphic marker bed</kwd>
<kwd>dendrochronology</kwd>
<kwd>kauri</kwd>
<kwd>late Holocene</kwd>
<kwd>New Zealand</kwd>
<kwd>non-welded ignimbrite</kwd>
<kwd>radiocarbon</kwd>
<kwd>Taupo eruption</kwd>
<kwd>Taupo tephra</kwd>
<kwd>tephrochronometry</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0959683611425551" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sec id="section2-0959683611425551">
<title>The Taupo eruption</title>
<p>Taupo caldera volcano in the central Taupo Volcanic Zone of North Island, New Zealand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0959683611425551">Figure 1</xref>), is the most frequently active and productive rhyolite volcano on Earth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0959683611425551">Wilson et al., 2009</xref>). Since the voluminous Kawakawa/Oruanui eruption <italic>c</italic>. 27 000 calendar (cal.) BP, there have been a further 28 eruptions at Taupo volcano, all but three taking place in the last 12 000 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0959683611425551">Lowe et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0959683611425551">Wilson, 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0959683611425551">2001</xref>). The most recent explosive event was the extremely powerful Taupo eruption about 1800 years ago. Known also as unit Y (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0959683611425551">Wilson, 1993</xref>), the caldera-forming silicic Taupo eruption, centered on vents in the vicinity of Horomatangi Reefs within Lake Taupo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0959683611425551">Smith and Houghton, 1995</xref>), was complex, generating ultraplinian fall units, a multiflow intraplinian ignimbrite, and the violently emplaced Taupo ignimbrite. The height of the eruption column during the ultraplinian phase (subunit Y5) exceeded ~50 km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0959683611425551">Walker, 1980</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of Taupo ignimbrite and the 10-cm isopach for tephra-fall deposits of the Taupo eruption from Taupo caldera, central Taupo Volcanic Zone, North Island, New Zealand (after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0959683611425551">Wilson and Leonard, 2008</xref>). Location of Pureora buried forest containing <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> logs shown NW of Taupo township. Dendro-dated New Zealand kauri logs were extracted from peat swamps near Dargaville in northern North Island</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The entirely non-welded, loose, Taupo ignimbrite (subunit Y7) was emplaced in about 400 seconds by an extremely energetic, hot, pyroclastic density current (flow) moving at more than 200–300 m/s over a near-circular area of ~20 000 km<sup>2</sup> around the vents with a radius of ~80 km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0959683611425551">Wilson, 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0959683611425551">1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0959683611425551">Wilson and Walker, 1985</xref>). Its temperature was about 380–500°C at more than ~40 km from vents; within ~30–40 km of the vents it was about 150–300°C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0959683611425551">Hudspith et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0959683611425551">McClelland et al., 2004</xref>). The extreme violence of the Taupo pyroclastic flow caused it to be spread thinly over the landscape to generate an archetypal low-aspect ratio ignimbrite (average thickness ~1.5 m) with a wide range of lateral variations and facies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0959683611425551">Smith and Houghton, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0959683611425551">Walker and Wilson, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0959683611425551">Walker et al., 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0959683611425551">Wilson, 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0959683611425551">1993</xref>). The ignimbrite consists of two layers (1 and 2) which were both deposited from a single-vent-derived, blast-like event (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0959683611425551">Hudspith et al., 2010</xref>). Because of its extreme violence and high energy release (≥ 150 ± 50 megatons of TNT), it is likely that this climactic ignimbrite-emplacement phase generated, via an accordant atmospheric shock wave, a volcano-meteorological tsunami that reached coastal areas worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange, 2000</xref>). The total eruptive bulk volume for the Taupo eruptives (unit Y) has been estimated at ~105 km<sup>3</sup>(~35 km<sup>3</sup> dense-rock equivalent) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0959683611425551">Wilson et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0959683611425551">
<title>Summary of previous attempts at dating the Taupo eruption</title>
<p>The Taupo ignimbrite contains numerous charred logs and charcoal. Consequently, there have been many attempts to date the Taupo eruption using the radiocarbon (<sup>14</sup>C) method. Dozens of <sup>14</sup>C ages have been obtained from charcoal and wood and from a wide range of other carbonaceous materials including peat, lake sediment, seeds, and leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe, 1990</xref>). Based on a set of seven <sup>14</sup>C ages obtained on leaves and seeds, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange (2000</xref>) most recently determined a broad calendar date (2σ-range) for the eruption of <sc>ad</sc> 130−320.</p>
<p>Because the eruption column during the ultraplinian phase exceeded ~50 km in height, the finest ash particles and sulphate-dominated aerosols would have been injected into the stratosphere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0959683611425551">Walker, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0959683611425551">Wilson et al., 1980</xref>). It has been speculated therefore that such materials would have spread to the Northern Hemisphere with little difficulty. This belief has been reinforced by the suggestion that a layer of sulphuric acid in the GISP2 (Greenland) ice sheet, dated at <sc>ad</sc> 181 ± 2, may have been derived from the Taupo-eruption-generated sulphate aerosols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0959683611425551">Zielinski et al., 1994</xref>). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0959683611425551">Wilson et al. (1980)</xref> suggested that Taupo-derived aerosols may have caused unusual atmospheric disturbances recorded in Chinese and Roman literature in <italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 186, and this date was subsequently proposed as a possible ‘historical’ date for the Taupo eruption.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> cross-matched a <sup>14</sup>C chronology from <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> (tanekaha or celery pine) against the Northern Hemisphere calibration curve of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref> and obtained an eruption date of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 15. However, the veracity of this date was debated and it was largely ignored because the purported ice-core and historical dates noted above, temporally close to each other, were widely accepted at the time. The ice-core date of <italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 181 is still in common use (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0959683611425551">Houghton et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0959683611425551">Manville, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Although the year of the Taupo eruption remains debated, the time of year (season) of the eruption has been well established through two lines of evidence. Fruit and seeds preserved in buried forests at Pureora and Bennydale near Lake Taupo (described below), and the lack of latewood on the outermost ring of trees killed by the event, indicate that the eruption took place in the austral late summer or early autumn period (typically mid-late March to early April) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0959683611425551">Clarkson et al., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0959683611425551">Palmer et al., 1988</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0959683611425551">
<title>Global importance of the Taupo eruption</title>
<p>Speculations that aerosols and possibly fine-ash sized glass shards from the Taupo eruption were distributed worldwide have led to the event gaining significance because it potentially generated a global chronostratigraphic marker. The likely generation of a global volcano-meteorological tsunami as a consequence of the violent emplacement of Taupo ignimbrite has reinforced this perception. Some researchers have even suggested that the eruption might have been responsible for worldwide climatic aberrations resulting in serious droughts and causing the Pre-classic Abandonment in Mesoamerica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0959683611425551">Gill and Keating, 2002</xref>). However, other researchers have cautioned that volcanic eruptions and climatic events further away are not always causually related (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0959683611425551">Baillie, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0959683611425551">D’Arrigo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0959683611425551">Robok et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The Taupo eruption is a key event for the international volcanological community because the resultant deposits, well preserved and easily accessible, have been the subject of intense study in the fields of physical volcanology, volcanic hazard analysis, and volcanic petrology. The seminal papers in particular of George Walker, Colin Wilson, and Paul Froggatt (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0959683611425551">Froggatt, 1981a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0959683611425551">Froggatt et al., 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0959683611425551">Walker, 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0959683611425551">1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0959683611425551">Walker and Wilson, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0959683611425551">Walker et al., 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0959683611425551">Wilson, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0959683611425551">Wilson and Walker, 1985</xref>) formed the basis of exemplar case studies in text books (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0959683611425551">Cas and Wright, 1987</xref>). Articles continue to be published about the unique Taupo deposits in wide-ranging international journals (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0959683611425551">Houghton et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0959683611425551">Hudspith et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0959683611425551">Pyle, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0959683611425551">Sutton et al., 2000</xref>). The dynamics and impacts of break-out flood deposition that followed the Taupo eruption are also relatively new topics relevant more globally to paleohydrology, sedimentology, and volcanic-hazard assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0959683611425551">Manville, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0959683611425551">Manville et al., 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0959683611425551">2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The fallout material from the Taupo eruption provides an extensive late-Holocene, pre-human stratigraphic marker bed (Taupo tephra) throughout the North Island and in the adjacent marine environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0959683611425551">Carter et al., 1995</xref>). The Taupo marker bed, forming an isochron, is thus of value in both palaeoenvironmental and archaeological research in the New Zealand region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0959683611425551">Alloway et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0959683611425551">Lowe et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0959683611425551">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0959683611425551">McFadgen, 2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0959683611425551">
<title>New approach to <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating the Taupo eruption</title>
<p>In the research reported here, we have used <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating to obtain a new calendar date for the death of large, non-carbonized trees at Pureora flattened by the initial air blast associated with emplacement of the Taupo ignimbrite. Our approach differs from that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> in that we have used high-precision <sup>14</sup>C dating both of the target trees killed by the eruption, which have an unknown age, and of kauri trees (<italic>Agathis australis</italic>) of known dendrochronological age derived from logs preserved in peat bogs in northern North Island to provide the calendar age relationships. We have thus circumvented the need to use assumed interhemispheric offsets in our calibrations because we have utilized a New Zealand-derived <sup>14</sup>C calibration data set. Although <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating has been applied elsewhere (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0959683611425551">Friedrich et al., 2006</xref>), unknown-age wood samples are generally wiggle-matched against established regional calibration curves.</p>
<p>Before describing this new wiggle-match dating of the target wood obtained from the Pureora buried forest, we firstly review in more detail the previous efforts to date the Taupo eruption (section ‘Previous estimates of the date of Taupo eruption based on <sup>14</sup>C dating and other evidence’). We examine closely the data and assumptions behind the wiggle-match date derived previously by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref>. After presenting our new wiggle-match date for the Taupo eruption (section ‘Dating the Taupo eruption using <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating and a New Zealand kauri-based calibration data set’), we then evaluate the veracity of approaches that have utilized individual <sup>14</sup>C ages to obtain eruption ages (section ‘Evaluation of ages derived for the Taupo eruption using individual <sup>14</sup>C samples’).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0959683611425551">
<title>Previous estimates of the date of Taupo eruption based on <sup>14</sup>C dating and other evidence</title>
<sec id="section7-0959683611425551">
<title><sup>14</sup>C-based dating</title>
<p>By-products of the Taupo eruption have been intensively dated by <sup>14</sup>C methods for almost 60 years, and include the first <sup>14</sup>C date to be obtained in New Zealand in 1953 (NZ-1, derived using the solid-carbon method: 1820 ± 150 <sup>14</sup>C BP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0959683611425551">Fergusson and Rafter, 1953</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0959683611425551">Grant-Taylor and Rafter, 1963</xref>). More than 50 <sup>14</sup>C dates relating to the Taupo event have been published since then. Some materials provided optimal ages with little in-built age: wood from short-lived species or twigs, small branches, seeds and leaves, or the outside tree-rings from trees killed by either the force of the eruption and preserved in bogs or carbonized by the heat of the ignimbrite flows. Other dateable material has in-built age and can only provide minimum or maximum limits on the time of emplacement. This latter group of samples includes slices of peat or lake sediment enclosing distal tephras or the inner rings of large trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>Various attempts have been made to derive calendar dates from the <sup>14</sup>C ages although the earliest were unaware of the need for calibration. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0959683611425551">Healy (1964)</xref> calculated the first weighted mean age for the Taupo tephra of 1819 ± 17 <sup>14</sup>C BP. He derived a calendar date of <italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 131 for it by simply subtracting 1819 from 1950. The <sup>14</sup>C age of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0959683611425551">Healy (1964)</xref> was subsequently updated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0959683611425551">Froggatt (1981a)</xref> to 1820 ± 80 <sup>14</sup>C BP. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe (1990)</xref> obtained a weighted mean age of 1850 ± 10 <sup>14</sup>C BP from 41 dates after assigning an ‘assessed value’ to each date (graded 1 to 3) based upon the type of material, proximity to the tephra, whether or not the date was one of a paired set, and whether any doubt existed about the sample or tephra identity (44 dates in total were listed, the weighted mean age being based on 41 dates graded 1 or 2). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange (2000)</xref> calibrated this mean age after first subtracting 27 years to account for the Southern Hemisphere offset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0959683611425551">McCormac et al. 1998a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0959683611425551">b</xref>) using IntCal98 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0959683611425551">Stuiver et al., 1998</xref>). They obtained a 2σ-calendar date range of <sc>ad</sc> 132–240. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange (2000)</xref> also calculated a mean age of 1845 ± 19 <sup>14</sup>C BP from seven samples of short-lived leaves and seeds with a calibrated 2σ -calendar date range of <sc>ad</sc> 130–320.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0959683611425551">
<title>Date based on purported historical atmospheric purturbations</title>
<p>The error-weighted mean <sup>14</sup>C age of 1819 ± 17 <sup>14</sup>C BP published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0959683611425551">Healy (1964)</xref>, and the extreme height estimated for the ultraplinian eruption column, led <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0959683611425551">Wilson et al. (1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0959683611425551">1981</xref>) to propose that aerosols from Taupo eruption created the unusual atmospheric phenomena recorded in ancient Chinese and Roman records in <italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 186, as noted earlier. This contention was disputed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0959683611425551">Froggatt (1981b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0959683611425551">Stothers and Rampino (1983)</xref>, who suspected the unusual atmospheric conditions were more probably the result of a supernova.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0959683611425551">
<title>Greenland and Antarctic ice-core based correlations and dates</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0959683611425551">Zielinski et al. (1994)</xref> used a preliminary <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match date of <sc>ad</sc> 177 (1-σ range of <sc>ad</sc> 166−195) from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe (1990)</xref> (reported on p. 98 as a personal communication from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0959683611425551">J.G. Palmer in 1988</xref>) to correlate the sulphuric acid layer in the GISP2 ice core at <sc>ad</sc> 181 ± 2 with the Taupo eruption. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange (2000</xref>: 404) pointed out that several other eruptions of a similar date range, including large-scale eruptions of volcanoes in El Salvador and Alaska, were also potential contenders for generating the GISP2 sulphate layer (which contained no associated volcanic glass shards) at <italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 181.</p>
<p>In Antarctica, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0959683611425551">Cole-Dai et al. (2000)</xref> attributed a prominent sulphate spike (event PR31) to the Taupo eruption and assigned it a calendar age of <sc>ad</sc> 186 ± 10 (based on the supposed historical date published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0959683611425551">Wilson et al., 1980</xref>). Moreover, PR31, purportedly dated at <italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 186, became a tie-point in the ice-core chronostratigraphy erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0959683611425551">Cole-Dai et al. (2000)</xref>. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0959683611425551">Traufetter et al. (2004)</xref> produced a detailed volcanic chronology covering the period <sc>ad</sc> 165 to 1997 from cores in Dronning Maud Land, Antarctica, and their sulphate spike ‘number 49’ was attributed on the basis of age alone to the Taupo eruption and assigned an age of <sc>ad</sc> 186 ± 23 (after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0959683611425551">Wilson et al., 1980</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0959683611425551">Kurbatov et al. (2006)</xref>, working on the Siple Dome core in Antarctica, also attributed a sulphate spike to the Taupo event and assigned it an ice-core-derived date of <sc>ad</sc> 176 (based on correlation to an eruption date of ‘<sc>ad</sc> 180’ for Taupo that was derived from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0959683611425551">Simkin and Siebert, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>However, in all these studies in Antarctica the sulphate spikes identified as being derived from the Taupo eruption were not confirmed by geochemical fingerprinting because no glass shards were detected in the acid layers. These approaches – correlation by assumed age alone – are risky and, if wrong, can lead to miscorrelations that are then perpetuated, potentially leading to further errors in interpretation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0959683611425551">Lowe, 2011</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0959683611425551">Blaauw, 2011</xref>). Moreover, new work on Greenland ice cores has shown that tephra-derived volcanic glass need not coincide with sulphate layers and so the potential number of volcanic signals recorded in the ice cores has been underestimated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0959683611425551">Davies et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0959683611425551">Lowe, 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0959683611425551">Narcisi et al. (2005)</xref> analysed major element compositions of glass shards from 13 tephra layers from the Antarctic EPICA-Dome C ice record and showed that Taupo tephra was absent because of the lack of rhyolitic signatures. This apparent lack of New Zealand tephras in Antarctica (and the lack of New Zealand-derived dust in the Vostok ice core) was attributed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0959683611425551">Delmonte et al. (2004)</xref> to unfavorable atmospheric paths.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0959683611425551">
<title><sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match date by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref></title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref>, working in the Rafter (formerly New Zealand) Gas-Counting Radiocarbon Laboratory (lab code = NZ), derived an eruption date for the Taupo tephra of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 15. This date was later revised statistically to <sc>ad</sc> 233 ± 13 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0959683611425551">Sparks et al., 2008</xref>). The chronology was constructed from 21 samples, spanning 270 years, from a floating <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> sequence, preserved in the Pureora buried forest (described below). The Rafter-NZ derived <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set was matched against the Northern Hemisphere calibration curve of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref> using a zero north–south offset. This zero offset was determined by measuring 42 decadal wood samples of known calendar age (<sc>ad</sc> 1335−1745) extracted from a tree (<italic>Prumnopitys taxifolia</italic>) growing in Peel Forest Park, Canterbury, New Zealand. The authors did not find a systematic difference between the Northern Hemisphere <sup>14</sup>C-ages of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref> and the Southern Hemisphere <sup>14</sup>C-ages on <italic>P. taxifolia</italic> for this time interval. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> used a least squares fit in matching the Rafter-NZ <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set to the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref> data set, and concluded that ‘any offset would be less than the standard deviation of a typical high precision measurement and would not significantly contribute to the accuracy of the result’ (Sparks et al., 1995: 159). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0959683611425551">McCormac et al. (2002)</xref> excluded the Rafter-NZ <italic>P. taxifolia</italic> measurements from the first Southern Hemisphere calibration data set, SHCal02, because they were able to demonstrate that the Rafter-NZ measurements had a substantial mean offset compared with the average of the data sets of Queen’s University Belfast Radiocarbon Dating Laboratory (lab code = UB) and of Waikato Radiocarbon Dating Laboratory (lab code = Wk), especially for the time interval <sc>ad</sc> 1335−1445, where the Rafter-NZ mean ages were 39.2 ± 6.6 years younger.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0959683611425551">
<title>Dating the Taupo eruption using <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating and a New Zealand kauri-based calibration data set</title>
<sec id="section12-0959683611425551">
<title>Pureora buried forest</title>
<p>The violent emplacement of the Taupo ignimbrite resulted in devastation of forests, with pyrolysis producing carbonized logs in situ as large as 1 m in diameter close to the vents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0959683611425551">Froggatt et al., 1981</xref>). The pyroclastic flow engulfed a volume of vegetation of around 1 km<sup>3</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0959683611425551">Hudspith et al., 2010</xref>). Further afield, the shockwave of the air blast flattened forested areas (before the trees were engulfed by the pyroclastic flow) at two sites, Pureora and Benneydale, which are ~20 km apart and ~50 km northwest of Lake Taupo, central North Island (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0959683611425551">Clarkson et al., 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0959683611425551">1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0959683611425551">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0959683611425551">Palmer et al., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0959683611425551">Wilmshurst and McGlone, 1996</xref>). The Pureora buried forest (38°30′S, 175°35′E – <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0959683611425551">Figure 1</xref>), approximately 37 ha in extent, comprises intact litter layers and uncharred, prone trees orientated radially with respect to the flow direction from the vent, with their bark intact and undamaged around their entire perimeter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0959683611425551">Hudspith et al., 2010</xref>). These trees are buried by approximately 1 m of pumice comprising layer 1 (~70−85 cm thick) overlain by layer 2 (~30 cm thick) of the Taupo ignimbrite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0959683611425551">Hudspith et al., 2010</xref>). They were preserved by peat formation resulting from constriction of pre-eruption drainage channels. The trees were initially exposed along ditches dug to drain the post-eruption wetlands; all the ditches except one were re-flooded in 1985 to preserve the forest remains. The Pureora buried forest is protected within Pureora Forest Park, which is administered by the New Zealand Department of Conservation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0959683611425551">Clarkson et al., 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>More than 190 tree cross-sections were recovered at Pureora, with the larger trees dominated by <italic>Dacrydium cupressinum</italic> and <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> with lesser amounts of <italic>Prumnopitys taxifolia, Dacrycarpus dacrydioides</italic>, and <italic>Prumnopitys ferruginea</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0959683611425551">Palmer et al. (1988)</xref>, from a sample of 128 trees, cross-matched 34 <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> trees to form the 426-year chronology used by both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> and this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0959683611425551">
<title><sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match dating and the Waikato <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> sequence</title>
<p>Carbon-14 wiggle-match dating refers to the fitting of several <sup>14</sup>C data points of unknown calendar age from a constrained sequence (e.g. tree rings) to a calibration curve. Matching of the data to the wiggles in the curve not only significantly improves the precision of the calibration but also reduces the influence of minor offsets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey et al., 2001</xref>). Wiggle-match dating of New Zealand eruptions (tephras) has been confined to three studies thus far: the Kaharoa eruption using a carbonized log (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2003</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0959683611425551">Buck et al., 2003</xref>); the Taupo eruption using wood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0959683611425551">2008</xref>); and Holocene and Late Pleistocene eruptions – recorded as tephra layers at Kaipo bog in eastern North Island – using peat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0959683611425551">Hajdas et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0959683611425551">Lowe et al., 2008</xref>). The last study at Kaipo was referred to as flexible age–depth modeling, similar to wiggle-matching, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0959683611425551">Lowe (2011)</xref>.</p>
<p>As discussed above, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> derived a calendar age for the Taupo eruption of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 15 by curve matching the Southern Hemisphere data set against a Northern Hemisphere calibration curve with a zero north–south offset and an assumption of a constant north–south offset for the first millennium <sc>ad</sc>. However, it has now been established that a north–south offset does indeed exist for the first millennium <sc>ad</sc> and it is not constant. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0959683611425551">Hogg et al. (2009)</xref> measured 20 decadal New Zealand kauri and Irish oak sample pairs and found an average north–south offset of 35 ± 6 years. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0959683611425551">Zimmerman et al. (2010)</xref> also showed a clear offset between Tasmanian huon pine and IntCal04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0959683611425551">Reimer et al., 2004</xref>) as illustrated for the interval <sc>ad</sc> 50–550 (1900–1400 cal. BP) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0959683611425551">figure 3</xref> of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0959683611425551">Zimmerman et al. (2010)</xref>. Wiggle-match dating of the New Zealand <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> sequence against the Northern Hemisphere data set of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref> without any offset should therefore result in an inaccurate calibration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey, 2001</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>High-precision <sup>14</sup>C determinations (± 1σ, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0959683611425551">Table 1</xref>) on <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> wood samples from the Pureora buried forest fitted to the Waikato kauri calibration data set (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2011</xref>) for the period 60 <sc>bc</sc> to <sc>ad</sc> 270</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) D_Sequence for high-precision dates on <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> wood samples, wiggle-matched against the Waikato kauri calibration data set (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2011</xref>). The agreement indices (<italic>A</italic>) indicate the extent to which the posterior distribution overlaps with the individual radiocarbon distributions (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey, 2001</xref>). The agreement index for the complete D_Sequence was 103.8%, with An=14.1% (<italic>n</italic> = 25), indicating that the overall fit is acceptable. (B) The wiggle-match shows the tree was killed by the eruption between <sc>ad</sc> 224–240 (at 2σ), with a mean date of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 5 yr</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>We have tested the accuracy of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> eruption date by re-dating the Pureora buried forest <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> chronology using high-precision (&lt; 2‰) <sup>14</sup>C dating. We used a single tree (FS066) and extracted 25 sequential blocks of wood ten-rings thick, starting from the incomplete ring formed during the year of the eruption.</p>
<p>All wood samples were pre-treated to α-cellulose following the procedures detailed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al. (2011)</xref>. Wood samples were ground to pass a 20-mesh sieve, and then subject to solvent extraction, bleaching with acidified NaClO<sub>2</sub>, NaOH extraction, and a final acidification step.</p>
<p>Radiocarbon activities were determined by liquid scintillation counting of benzene in Perkin Elmer Wallac 1220 Quantulus spectrometers, adapted for high precision dating (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2011</xref>, for details). We used long measurement times, high weights of benzene, and low-activity synthetic silica counting vials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0959683611425551">Hogg, 1993</xref>) to achieve a routine precision of &lt; ± 20 years. The Waikato-derived <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> results are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0959683611425551">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Waikato <sup>14</sup>C measurements on decadal samples of <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic>, from the Pureora buried forest, and killed by the Taupo eruption</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0959683611425551" xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Centre ring</th>
<th align="left">Wk no.</th>
<th align="left">Start ring</th>
<th align="left">End ring</th>
<th align="left">Centre ring (yr before eruption)</th>
<th align="left">δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰)</th>
<th align="left">Age <sup>14</sup>C yr BP</th>
<th align="left">1σ error</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1495.5</td>
<td>23140</td>
<td>1491</td>
<td>1500</td>
<td>5.5</td>
<td>−20.5</td>
<td>1874</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1485.5</td>
<td>23141</td>
<td>1481</td>
<td>1490</td>
<td>15.5</td>
<td>−20.6</td>
<td>1838</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1475.5</td>
<td>23142</td>
<td>1471</td>
<td>1480</td>
<td>25.5</td>
<td>−20</td>
<td>1907</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1465.5</td>
<td>23143</td>
<td>1461</td>
<td>1470</td>
<td>35.5</td>
<td>−20.6</td>
<td>1901</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1455.5</td>
<td>23144</td>
<td>1451</td>
<td>1460</td>
<td>45.5</td>
<td>−20.6</td>
<td>1913</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1445.5</td>
<td>23145</td>
<td>1441</td>
<td>1450</td>
<td>55.5</td>
<td>−20.4</td>
<td>1890</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1435.5</td>
<td>23146</td>
<td>1431</td>
<td>1440</td>
<td>65.5</td>
<td>−20.6</td>
<td>1866</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1425.5</td>
<td>22970</td>
<td>1421</td>
<td>1430</td>
<td>75.5</td>
<td>−21.1</td>
<td>1891</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1415.5</td>
<td>22883</td>
<td>1411</td>
<td>1420</td>
<td>85.5</td>
<td>−20.6</td>
<td>1905</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1405.5</td>
<td>22884</td>
<td>1401</td>
<td>1410</td>
<td>95.5</td>
<td>−20.7</td>
<td>1869</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1395.5</td>
<td>22971</td>
<td>1391</td>
<td>1400</td>
<td>105.5</td>
<td>−20.5</td>
<td>1908</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1385.5</td>
<td>22885</td>
<td>1381</td>
<td>1390</td>
<td>115.5</td>
<td>−20.4</td>
<td>1928</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1375.5</td>
<td>22886</td>
<td>1371</td>
<td>1380</td>
<td>125.5</td>
<td>−20.9</td>
<td>1971</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1365.5</td>
<td>22972</td>
<td>1361</td>
<td>1370</td>
<td>135.5</td>
<td>−20.6</td>
<td>1986</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1355.5</td>
<td>22887</td>
<td>1351</td>
<td>1360</td>
<td>145.5</td>
<td>−20.9</td>
<td>1949</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1345.5</td>
<td>22973</td>
<td>1341</td>
<td>1350</td>
<td>155.5</td>
<td>−20.9</td>
<td>1940</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1335.5</td>
<td>22974</td>
<td>1331</td>
<td>1340</td>
<td>165.5</td>
<td>−21.4</td>
<td>1978</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1325.5</td>
<td>22975</td>
<td>1321</td>
<td>1330</td>
<td>175.5</td>
<td>−21.5</td>
<td>2001</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1315.5</td>
<td>23147</td>
<td>1311</td>
<td>1320</td>
<td>185.5</td>
<td>−21.6</td>
<td>2022</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1305.5</td>
<td>23203</td>
<td>1301</td>
<td>1310</td>
<td>195.5</td>
<td>−21.1</td>
<td>1993</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1295.5</td>
<td>22976</td>
<td>1291</td>
<td>1300</td>
<td>205.5</td>
<td>−21.7</td>
<td>2036</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1285.5</td>
<td>22977</td>
<td>1281</td>
<td>1290</td>
<td>215.5</td>
<td>−21.8</td>
<td>2058</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1275.5</td>
<td>22978</td>
<td>1271</td>
<td>1280</td>
<td>225.5</td>
<td>−21.8</td>
<td>2041</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1265.5</td>
<td>22979</td>
<td>1261</td>
<td>1270</td>
<td>235.5</td>
<td>−21.6</td>
<td>2057</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1255.5</td>
<td>22980</td>
<td>1251</td>
<td>1260</td>
<td>245.5</td>
<td>−22</td>
<td>2074</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Inaccuracies in wiggle-match dating can arise from both geographic offsets (e.g. the north–south offset) and systematic offsets between the samples analyzed and the calibration curve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey, 2009</xref>). Both of these sources of error are mitigated through use of a calibration curve constructed from a local chronology, with both data sets obtained by the same laboratory. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al. (2011)</xref> obtained 120 decadal high precision <sup>14</sup>C measurements on known-age New Zealand <italic>Agathis australis</italic> (kauri) to extend the Southern Hemisphere calibration curve to 200 <sc>bc</sc>. This calibration data set (here referred to as ‘Waikato kauri’) covers the period 195 <sc>bc</sc>−<sc>ad</sc> 995 and is clearly the data set of choice for wiggle-match dating the Waikato-derived <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> sequence. We make the distinction between the terms ‘calibration data set’ as used here, and ‘calibration curve’, with the latter given a more robust statistical treatment by application of a random walk model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0959683611425551">Buck and Blackwell, 2004</xref>). We would expect the errors associated with use of a calibration data set as opposed to a calibration curve to be insignificant for these late-Holocene samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0959683611425551">Millard, 2008</xref>). Wiggle matching was achieved using OxCal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0959683611425551">2001</xref>) applying a resolution of 1 and interpolation between decadal data points.</p>
<p>The Waikato <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> sequence wiggle-matched against the Waikato-kauri data set is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0959683611425551">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<p>We used the D_Sequence model with 10-yr gaps, and a 6-yr gap to account for the final tree rings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0959683611425551">Figure 3A</xref>). There is high agreement for both individual analyses (<italic>A</italic> &gt;60%) and the model as a whole (model agreement index Acomb (103.8%; An = 14.1%); χ<sup>2</sup>-test statistics: d.f. = 24, <italic>T</italic> = 17.3 (5% 36.4)). The new 2σ eruption date of <sc>ad</sc> 224−240 (mean date = <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 5, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0959683611425551">Figure 3B</xref>) is strongly bimodal because of the shape of the calibration curve represented in the period of the eruption.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0959683611425551">
<title>Comparison with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> wiggle-match dates for Taupo eruption</title>
<p>The eruption date of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 15 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al., 1995</xref>) is identical within the uncertainties to the new date we have obtained here – despite the Rafter-NZ Southern Hemisphere <italic>P. taxifolia</italic> data set indicating a zero north–south <sup>14</sup>C offset when compared with the Northern Hemisphere calibration curve of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref>. Because the decadal wood samples for our work came from the same <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> chronology as the samples used in the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> study, we were able to directly compare the <sup>14</sup>C dates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0959683611425551">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Radiocarbon measurements (1σ) from the Pureora buried forest <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> chronology. Wk, Waikato Laboratory (this paper); NZ, Rafter Laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al., 1995</xref>)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The two data sets are clearly offset, with the Waikato-derived dates older. We used linear interpolation between the data points to calculate an average offset of 38 ± 10 years. Both data sets were wiggle-matched against the Southern Hemisphere atmospheric curve SHCal04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0959683611425551">McCormac et al., 2004</xref>), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0959683611425551">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Radiocarbon determinations (± 1σ) on <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> wood samples from the Pureora buried forest fitted to the Southern Hemisphere calibration curve SHCal04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0959683611425551">McCormac et al., 2004</xref>) for the period 90 <sc>bc</sc> to <sc>ad</sc> 280. Wk, Waikato Laboratory, this paper (black data points); NZ, Rafter Laboratory (red/grey data points) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al., 1995</xref>) (For interpretation of the references to colour, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Although the agreement indices (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">B</xref>) for both curves are high when plotted against SHCal04, the younger Rafter-NZ <sup>14</sup>C dates have resulted in a mean eruption date that is 35 ± 9 years younger than the Waikato-derived mean eruption date.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>OxCal agreement indices and χ<sup>2</sup> data for fitting (A) the Waikato <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set and (B) the Rafter-NZ <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set to various calibration curves</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0959683611425551" xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="6">A</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Curve</th>
<th align="left">Acomb (%)(An =14.1%)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>N A</italic> &lt;60%</th>
<th align="left"><italic>T</italic> d.f. =24 (5% 36.4)</th>
<th align="left">Eruption date (2σ age range) (yr <sc>ad</sc>)</th>
<th align="left">Mean date (yr <sc>ad</sc>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>A. Waikato kauri</td>
<td>103.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>17.3</td>
<td>224−240</td>
<td>232 ± 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B. SHCal04</td>
<td>202.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10.2</td>
<td>232−250</td>
<td>241 ± 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C. CAMS huon</td>
<td>92.9</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>22.3</td>
<td>231−240</td>
<td>236 ± 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>D. SHCal04 (0± 40)</td>
<td>361.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3.7</td>
<td>226−257</td>
<td>241 ± 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>E. IntCal09</td>
<td>12.1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>45.4</td>
<td>166−169 (3.6%)</td>
<td>179 ± 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>171−188 (91.8%)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>F. S&amp;B’93<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0959683611425551">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>40.0</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>34.6</td>
<td>181−189 (84.4%)</td>
<td>186 ± 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>193−198 (11.0%)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="6">B</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Curve</th>
<th align="left">Acomb (%) (An =15.4%)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>N A</italic> &lt;60%</th>
<th align="left"><italic>T</italic> d.f. =20 (5% 31.4)</th>
<th align="left">Eruption date (2σ age range) (yr <sc>ad</sc>)</th>
<th align="left">Mean date (yr <sc>ad</sc>)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>G. Waikato kauri</td>
<td>131.2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>12.1</td>
<td>260−281</td>
<td>271 ± 7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>H. SHCal04</td>
<td>168.8</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>258−294</td>
<td>276 ± 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>I. CAMS huon</td>
<td>110.0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>15.5</td>
<td>262−274</td>
<td>268 ± 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>J. SHCal04 (0 ± 40)</td>
<td>264.0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>5.3</td>
<td>221−290 (94.3%)</td>
<td>246 ± 15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>349−356 (1.1%)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>K. IntCal09</td>
<td>161.3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10.7</td>
<td>220−244</td>
<td>232 ± 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>L. S&amp;B’93</td>
<td>226.1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>9.4</td>
<td>227−247</td>
<td>237 ± 5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0959683611425551">
<label>a</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results of wiggle-matching the two <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data sets against various curves are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0959683611425551">Figures 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0959683611425551">7</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Eruption ages for the Taupo tephra derived from Waikato measurements on Pureora <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> wood samples fitted to various calibration curves for the period <sc>ad</sc> 155−315. Calibration curves: A, Waikato kauri (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2011</xref>); B, SHCal04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0959683611425551">McCormac et al., 2004</xref>); C, CAMS huon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0959683611425551">Zimmerman et al., 2010</xref>); D, SHCal04 with Δ_R of 0 ± 40 yr; E, IntCal09 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0959683611425551">Reimer et al., 2009</xref>); F, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref>. Preferred eruption date (curve A) bounded by vertical lines</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Eruption ages for the Taupo tephra derived from Rafter-NZ measurements on Pureora <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> wood samples fitted to various calibration curves for the period <sc>ad</sc> 155−315. Calibration curves: G, Waikato kauri (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2011</xref>); H, SHCal04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0959683611425551">McCormac et al., 2004</xref>); I, CAMS huon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0959683611425551">Zimmerman et al., 2010</xref>); J, SHCal04 with Δ_R of 0 ± 40 yr; K, IntCal09 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0959683611425551">Reimer et al., 2009</xref>); L, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref>. Preferred eruption date (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0959683611425551">Figure 6</xref>: curve A) bounded by vertical lines</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Whilst the Waikato results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0959683611425551">Figure 6</xref>) show high agreement with the Southern Hemisphere calibration curves – plots A–C (and statistically indistinguishable eruption dates) − the high-precision measurements (mean 1σ error = ± 18 years) show very low agreement with the two Northern Hemisphere curves (plots E–F).</p>
<p>The Rafter-NZ results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0959683611425551">Figure 7</xref>), which are less precise (mean 1σ error = ± 36 years), show high agreement indices against all curves (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2B</xref>), but with the Southern Hemisphere curves (plots G–I) producing eruption dates that are too young.</p>
<p>We wiggle-matched the Rafter <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set against SHCal04 and applied a reservoir function of 0 ± 40 years to compensate for the Rafter-NZ bias (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0959683611425551">Figure 7</xref>, plot J). Use of the large reservoir offset results in a more reliable but much less precise 2σ date range of <sc>ad</sc> 221−290 (94.3%) and <sc>ad</sc> 349−356 (1.1%), and a mean date of <sc>ad</sc> 246 ± 15. For the sake of completeness, we also wiggle matched the Waikato <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set against SHCal04 applying a reservoir function of 0 ± 40 years. The wiggle match also produced a high agreement index (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0959683611425551">Table 2A</xref>) and an accurate eruption age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0959683611425551">Figure 6</xref>, plot D). We note here that use of the reservoir offset function, with a large error value of ± 40 years, provided a satisfactory solution for wiggle matching both data sets against the most appropriate calibration curve (SHCal04 in this case). Use of the reservoir offset function is therefore recommended if laboratory bias is suspected.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0959683611425551">McCormac et al. (2002)</xref>, as noted above, excluded the Rafter-NZ <italic>Prumnopitys</italic> known-age data set because of the large mean offset compared with that of the Queen’s University Belfast/Waikato Radiocarbon Laboratory average, with some time intervals being up to 39 years too young. The Rafter-NZ <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set also looks too young by about the same amount. Evidence for this finding comes not only from the direct comparison with the Waikato data set but also from the young eruption ages that arise from wiggle-matching against any of the Southern Hemisphere calibration curves. The conclusion by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> of a zero north–south offset is now known to be incorrect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0959683611425551">Hogg et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0959683611425551">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0959683611425551">McCormac et al., 1998b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0959683611425551">2002</xref>). However, the close agreement between the known-age Rafter-NZ <italic>Prumnopitys</italic> measurements and the Northern Hemisphere curve of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref> justified the use of this curve by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> for wiggle-matching the Rafter-NZ <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set.</p>
<p>We therefore conclude that the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> eruption date is accurate but with lower precision because of the higher standard errors. Because the Rafter-NZ <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> data set is approximately 38 years too young, then wiggle-matching against the Northern Hemisphere curve of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref>, which is offset from the Southern Hemisphere calibration curves by a similar amount, resulted in an accurate eruption age.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0959683611425551">
<title>Evaluation of ages derived for the Taupo eruption using individual <sup>14</sup>C samples</title>
<p>Having derived a new, definitive calendar date for the Taupo eruption of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 5, we used the ‘Combine’ function of OxCal4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0959683611425551">2009</xref>) and calibration against the Southern Hemisphere atmospheric curve SHCal04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0959683611425551">McCormac et al., 2004</xref>) to reassess the accuracy of dating the eruption using each of the 41 ages listed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe (1990)</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0959683611425551">Figure 8A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig8-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) Calibrated calendar date range for combined <sup>14</sup>C dates from 41 isolated samples dating the Taupo eruption (as listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe, 1990</xref>: 108–109). Agreement indices are extremely low, with 27% (11) of the dates having an individual agreement index (A) of less than 60%. (B) Calibrated calendar date ranges for combined <sup>14</sup>C dates from 35 of the 41 isolated samples dating the Taupo eruption (as listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0959683611425551">Froggatt and Lowe, 1990</xref>). Removal of the six outliers resulted in acceptable agreement indices of 89.3% (An = 12.0%); χ<sup>2</sup>-test: d.f. = 34, <italic>T</italic> = 24.1 (5% 48.0)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig8.tif"/>
</fig> <p>The combination agreement index (Acomb) returned a value of 0.6%, considerably lower than the acceptable threshold defined by An (11.0% for 41 samples), with 27% (11) of the dates having an individual agreement index (<italic>A</italic>) of less than 60%. We removed six results for which <italic>A</italic> was &lt; 20% and re-ran the model with the remaining 35 results. This new set produced a satisfactory combination agreement index of 89.3% (An = 12.0%); χ<sup>2</sup>-test: d.f. = 34, <italic>T</italic> = 24.1 (5% 48.0) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0959683611425551">Figure 8B</xref>).</p>
<p>The combined age is, however, strongly bi-modal with a calibrated 2σ-age range of <sc>ad</sc> 238–260 (45.9%) and 285–323 (49.5%), and a mean date of <sc>ad</sc> 280 ± 29. Even with the benefit of outlier identification, the combined individual ages are too young by a considerable amount. This was an unexpected result because approximately 80% of the 35 samples are charcoal, wood, or underlying peat, with all of these sample types potentially having in-built age (and hence likely to be ‘too old’ rather than ‘too young’). We are unsure of the reasons why the combined date is younger than our new wiggle-match date. In some cases it is possible that younger (post-eruption) humic materials may have been translocated into the charcoal samples after their entombment in porous pumice of the Taupo ignimbrite, but most of the samples occur at depth, and are somewhat isolated from surface soil horizons. We record that the majority of these dates were obtained by the Rafter-NZ Laboratory, results from which appear to be approximately 38 years too young as described earlier, and so a systematic laboratory-based error might alternatively or additionally be responsible for the combined <sup>14</sup>C-based date being unexpectedly young.</p>
<p>The ages on the seven short-lived samples reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange (2000</xref>) were also calibrated against SHCal04. The modeling produced a significantly older result (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0959683611425551">Figure 9</xref>): 2σ date range = <sc>ad</sc> 138–198 (15.7%), <sc>ad</sc> 207–260 (62.8%), and 285–322 (16.9%), with a mean date of <sc>ad</sc> 239 ± 43 (Acomb = 104.2%, An = 26.7%; χ<sup>2</sup>-test: d.f. = 6, <italic>T</italic> = 3.6 (5% 12.6)). These seven short-lived samples (leaves and seeds of various trees) therefore provide a more realistic interpretation of the date of the Taupo eruption than the combined age on the other samples described above. This improved age model may be because the samples were closely associated with the emplacement of the Taupo ignimbrite which killed (short-lived) material metabolizing immediately prior to the eruption, or because the majority of these results were obtained by the Waikato laboratory rather than the Rafter-NZ laboratory, or both.</p>
<fig id="fig9-0959683611425551" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Calibrated calendar date ranges for combined <sup>14</sup>C dates from seven short-lived isolated samples of leaves and seeds dating the Taupo eruption (reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0959683611425551">Lowe and de Lange, 2000</xref>: 405). Agreement indices are high (Acomb = 104.2% (An = 26.7%); χ<sup>2</sup>-test: d.f. = 6, <italic>T</italic> = 3.6 (5% 12.6)) with a mean eruption date of <sc>ad</sc> 239 ± 43</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0959683611425551-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>It is clear that tephra ages based upon individual carbon dates should be considered as approximate only. Efforts should be made to establish accurate calendar ages for important tephra marker beds by <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-matching or flexible age–depth modeling using a Bayesian framework and multiple ages (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0959683611425551">Blaauw et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0959683611425551">Bronk Ramsey, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0959683611425551" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<list id="list1-0959683611425551" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>We report here an accurate and precise 2σ calendar date range of <sc>ad</sc> 224−240 (mean date/age = <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 5; 1718 ± 5 cal. BP) for the Taupo eruption that occurred in the austral late summer or early autumn. This definitive date was derived by wiggle-matching 25 high-precision <sup>14</sup>C-dates from decadal samples of <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> from the Pureora buried forest in North Island against the high-precision, first millennium <sc>ad</sc> Waikato-derived kauri calibration data set. Because we utilized a New Zealand-derived calibration data set, previous uncertainties in estimating interhemispheric offsets were obviated.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The new date shows that dates for the eruption ostulated previously from Greenland ice-core records (<sc>ad</sc> 181 ± 2) and putative historical records of unusual atmospheric phenomena in ancient Rome and China (<italic>c</italic>. <sc>ad</sc> 186) are both untenable. Moreover, the basis for assigning these purported dates in the first place was flawed because no direct link with the eruption (such as via electron microprobe analysis of attendant glass shards) had ever been established.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0959683611425551">Sparks et al. (1995)</xref> date for the Taupo eruption of <sc>ad</sc> 232 ± 15 (updated to <sc>ad</sc> 233 ± 13 by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0959683611425551">Sparks et al., 2008</xref>) is accurate despite the erroneous use of a zero north–south offset and calibration against the Northern Hemisphere calibration curve of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0959683611425551">Stuiver and Becker (1993)</xref>. Although the Rafter-NZ <italic>Phyllocladus</italic> and <italic>Prumnopitys</italic> data sets are both too young by 30–40 years, initial alignment of the known-age <italic>Prumnopitys</italic> samples with the Northern Hemisphere curve correctly identified it as the appropriate curve for the calibration.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>High agreement levels, as indicated by either agreement indices or by χ<sup>2</sup> data, obtained by a <sup>14</sup>C wiggle-match, do not necessarily indicate accurate results for the age model. It is important therefore to check the level of laboratory bias against the calibration curve being used before confidence can be placed in the modeling results. Use of the reservoir offset function, as demonstrated here, is recommended if laboratory bias is suspected.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Unless only short-lived material is selected for dating, age determinations for tephras by <sup>14</sup>C dating of discrete samples are unlikely to produce accurate calendar eruption dates. Bayesian programmes such as OxCal or Bpeat incorporating outlier analysis on suites of multiple ages are useful for identifying errant results.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Tephra eruption ages based upon individual <sup>14</sup>C dates should be considered as approximate only, and confined to short-lived material (e.g. seeds, leaves, small branches or the outer rings of larger trees).</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We have appreciated useful discussions with Dr Roger Sparks (former director of the Rafter Radiocarbon Laboratory) and Prof Sturt Manning (Cornell University), and comments from anonymous referees and the editor Prof Frank Oldfield. Max Oulton (University of Waikato) prepared <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0959683611425551">Figure 1</xref>. The paper is an output for objective 5 (‘Improving age models for key marker tephras’) of the INTREPID project ‘Enhancing tephrochronology as a global research tool’ (INQUA-0907), an initiative of the International Focus Group on Tephrochronology and Volcanism (INTAV) led by Prof David J. Lowe.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>This work was supported by the Marsden Fund, grant number UOW-0606, to Dr Alan Hogg at the University of Waikato, Dr Jonathan Palmer from the Gondwana Tree-Ring Laboratory, and Dr Gretel Boswijk at University of Auckland.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alloway</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>DJA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almond</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Augustinus</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Towards a climate event stratigraphy for New Zealand over the past 30,000 years (NZ-INTIMATE project)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Quaternary Science</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Proposed re-dating of the European ice core chronology by seven years prior to the 7th century AD</article-title>. <source>Geophysical Research Letters</source> <volume>35</volume> (<issue>L15813</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blaauw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Out of tune: The dangers of aligning proxy archives</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Science Reviews</source> doi:10.1016/j.quascirev.2010.11.012<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.quascirev.2010.11.012</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blaauw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Plicht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bayesian framework for age-modeling of radiocarbon dated peat deposits: Case studies from The Netherlands</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Radiocarbon calibration and analysis of stratigraphy: The OxCal program</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Development of the radiocarbon calibration program OxCal</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Depositional models for chronological research</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Science Reviews</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dealing with outliers and offsets in radiocarbon dating</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1023</fpage>–<lpage>1045</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Plicht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weninger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>‘Wiggle matching’ radiocarbon dates</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Formal statistical models for estimating radiocarbon calibration curves</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1093</fpage>–<lpage>1102</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Bayesian tools for tephrochronology</article-title>. <source>The Holocene</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neil</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Froggatt</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Correlation, dispersal, and preservation of the Kawakawa Tephra and other late Quaternary tephra layers in the southwest Pacific Ocean</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Journal of Geology and Geophysics</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cas</surname><given-names>RAF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Volcanic Successions — Modern and Ancient</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allen and Unwin</publisher-name>, <fpage>528</fpage> pp.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The pre-Taupo eruption (c. AD 130) forest of the Bennydale-Pureora district, central North Island, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society of New Zealand</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGlone</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Macrofossil and pollen representing forests of the pre-Taupo volcanic eruption (c. 1850 yr BP) era at Pureora and Bennydale, central North Island, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society of New Zealand</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Composition and structure of forest overwhelmed at Pureora, central North Island, New Zealand, during the Taupo eruption (c. A.D. 130)</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society of New Zealand</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole-Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mosley-Thompson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wight</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A 4100-year record of explosive volcanism from an East Antarctica ice core</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source> <volume>105</volume> (<issue>D19</issue>): <fpage>24 431</fpage>–<lpage>24 441</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>D’Arrigo</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seager</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>LeGrande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The anomalous winter of 1783–4: Was the Laki eruption or an analog of the 2009–10 winter to blame?</article-title> <source>Geophysical Research Letters</source> <volume>38</volume>: (<issue>L05706</issue>), doi:10.1029/2011GL046696<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2011GL046696</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wastegård</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barbante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bigler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Tracing volcanic events in the NGRIP ice-core and synchronising North Atlantic marine records during the last glacial period</article-title>. <source>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</source> <volume>294</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Delmonte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Basile-Doelsch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>J-R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Revel-Rolland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Comparing the Epica and Vostok dust records during the last 220,000 years: Stratigraphical correlation and provenance in glacial periods</article-title>. <source>Earth-Science Reviews</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fergusson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rafter</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>New Zealand <sup>14</sup>C age measurements I</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Journal of Science and Technology</source> <volume>B35</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kromer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heinemeier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talamo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Santorini eruption radiocarbon dated to 1627–1600 B.C</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>312</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Froggatt</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981a</year>) <article-title>Stratigraphy and nature of Taupo Pumice Formation</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Journal of Geology and Geophysics</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Froggatt</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981b</year>) <article-title>Did Taupo’s eruption enhance European sunsets?</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>293</volume>, <fpage>491</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Froggatt</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>A review of late Quaternary silicic and some other tephra formations from New Zealand: Their stratigraphy, nomenclature, distribution, volume, and age</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Journal of Geology and Geophysics</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Froggatt</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Orientation of logs in the Taupo Ignimbrite as an indicator of flow direction and vent position</article-title>. <source>Geology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Volcanism and Mesoamerican archaeology</article-title>. <source>Ancient Mesoamerica</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grant-Taylor</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rafter</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>New Zealand natural radiocarbon measurements I−V</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hajdas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Timing of the late-glacial climate reversal in the Southern Hemisphere using high-resolution radiocarbon chronology for Kaipo bog, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Research</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Dating of the younger volcanic eruptions of the Taupo region. Part 1</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Geological Survey Bulletin</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Performance and design of 0.3 ml to 10 ml synthetic silica liquid scintillation vials</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schonhofer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) ‘<source>Liquid Scintillation Spectrometry 1992</source>’, <conf-name>Proceedings of the International Conference on Advances in LSC</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Vienna, Austria</conf-loc>, <conf-date>Sept 14–18, 1992</conf-date>. <publisher-loc>Tuscon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Radiocarbon</publisher-name>, <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turney</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Investigating the interhemispheric <sup>14</sup>C offset in the 1st Millennium AD and assessment of laboratory bias and calibration errors</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>1176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A wiggle-match date for Polynesian settlement of New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Antiquity</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hendy</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>University of Waikato radiocarbon dates I</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCormac</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>High-precision radiocarbon measurements of contemporaneous tree-ring dated wood from the British Isles and New Zealand: AD 1850–950</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boswijk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turney</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High-precision radiocarbon measurements of tree-ring dated wood from New Zealand: 200 BC–AD 950</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cashman</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hobden</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Diverse patterns of ascent, degassing, and eruption of rhyolite magma during the1.8 ka Taupo eruption, New Zealand: Evidence from clast vesicularity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</source> <volume>195</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hudspith</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collinson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Charring of woods by volcanic processes: An example from the Taupo ignimbrite, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology</source> <volume>291</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurbatov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zielinski</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayewski</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meyerson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sneed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A 12,000 year record of explosive volcanism in the Siple Dome Ice Core, West Antarctica</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source> <volume>111</volume>, <issue>D12307</issue>. doi: 10.1029/2005JD006072<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2005JD006072</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Tephrochronology and its application: a review</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Geochronology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Volcano-meteorological tsunamis, the c. <sc>ad</sc> 200 Taupo eruption (New Zealand) and the possibility of a global tsunami</article-title>. <source>The Holocene</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McFadgen</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Tephras and New Zealand archaeology</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>859</fpage>–<lpage>870</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shane</surname><given-names>PAR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alloway</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Fingerprints and age models for widespread New Zealand tephra marker beds erupted since 30,000 years ago: A framework for NZ-INTIMATE</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Science Reviews</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manville</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Sedimentary and geomorphic responses to ignimbrite emplacement: Readjustment of the Waikato River after the A.D. 181 Taupo eruption, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Geology</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manville</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nairn</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A review of break-out floods from volcanogenic lakes in New Zealand</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Journal of Geology and Geophysics</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manville</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JDL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Paleohydrology and sedimentology of a post-1.8 ka breakout flood from intracaldera Lake Taupo, North Island, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Geological Society of America Bulletin</source> <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>1435</fpage>–<lpage>1447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bardot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Paleotemperature determinations for the 1.8-ka Taupo ignimbrite, New Zealand, and implications for the emplacement history of a high-velocity pyroclastic flow</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Volcanology</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormac</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>SHCal04 Southern Hemisphere Calibration, 0–11.0 cal kyr BP</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormac</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1998b</year>) <article-title>Variations of radiocarbon in tree rings: Southern Hemisphere offset preliminary results</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormac</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynch-Stieglitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broeker</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1998a</year>) <article-title>Temporal variation in the interhemispheric <sup>14</sup>C offset</article-title>. <source>Geophysical Research Letters</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1321</fpage>–<lpage>1324</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormac</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Calibration of the radiocarbon time scale for the Southern Hemisphere AD 1850–950</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McFadgen</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Hostile Shores: Catastrophic Events in Prehistoric New Zealand and their Impact on Maori Coastal Communities</source>. <publisher-loc>Auckland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Auckland University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>298</fpage> pp.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comment on article by Blackwell and Buck</article-title>. <source>Bayesian Analysis</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Narcisi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delmonte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Basile-Doelsch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Characteristics and sources of tephra layers in the EPICA-Dome C ice record (East Antarctica): Implications for past atmospheric circulation and ice core stratigraphic correlations</article-title>. <source>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</source> <volume>239</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A 426-year floating tree-ring chronology from <italic>Phyllocladus trichomanoides</italic> buried by the Taupo eruption at Pureora, central North Island, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society of New Zealand</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Forecasting sizes and repose times of future extreme volcanic events</article-title>. <source>Geology</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayliss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>CJH</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>IntCal04 terrestrial radiocarbon age calibration, 0–26 cal kyr BP</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1058</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayliss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>IntCal09 and Marine09 radiocarbon age calibration curves, 0–50,000 years cal BP</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1111</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ammann</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shindell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stenchikov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Did the Toba volcanic eruption of ~74 ka B.P. produce widespread glaciation?</article-title> <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source> <volume>114</volume> (<issue>D10107</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simkin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Volcanoes of the World: A Regional Directory, Gazetteer, and Chronology of Volcanism During the Last 10,000 Years</source> (<edition>2nd Edition</edition>). <publisher-loc>Tucson AZ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Geoscience Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>368</fpage> pp.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Vent migration and changing eruptive style during the 1800a Taupo eruption: New evidence from the Hatepe and Rotongaio phreatoplinian ashes</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Volcanology</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cosmic chronometers</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<comment>chiefed</comment>.) <article-title>A continent on the move: New Zealand geoscience into the 21st Century</article-title>. <source>Geological Society of New Zealand Miscellaneous Publication</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melhuish</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>JWA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>BPJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title><sup>14</sup>C calibration in the Southern Hemisphere and the date of the last Taupo eruption: Evidence from tree-ring sequences</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stothers</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rampino</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Volcanic eruptions in the Mediterranean before A.D. 630 from written and archaeological sources</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>6357</fpage>–<lpage>6371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stuiver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>High-precision decadal calibration of the radiocarbon timescale, AD 1950–6000 BC</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stuiver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>INTCAL98 radiocarbon age calibration, 24,000–0 cal BP</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1041</fpage>–<lpage>1083</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charlier</surname><given-names>BLA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Late Quaternary evolution of a hyperactive rhyolite magmatic system: Taupo volcanic centre, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Geological Society (London)</source> <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Traufetter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oerter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Spatio-temporal variability in volcanic sulphate deposition over the past 2 kyr in snow pits and firn cores from Amundsenisen, Antarctica</article-title>. <source>Journal of Glaciology</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>The Taupo plinian pumice: Product of the most powerful known (ultraplinian) eruption?</article-title> <source>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Generation and dispersal of fine ash and dust by volcanic eruptions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Lateral variations in the Taupo ignimbrite</article-title>. <source>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Froggatt</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>An ignimbrite veneer deposit: The trail marker of a pyroclastic flow</article-title>. <source>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilmshurst</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGlone</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Forest disturbance in the central North Island, New Zealand, following the 1850 BP Taupo eruption</article-title>. <source>The Holocene</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The Taupo eruption, New Zealand II. The Taupo ignimbrite</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc> <volume>A314</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Stratigraphy, chronology, styles, and dynamics of late Quaternary eruptions from Taupo volcano, New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</source> <volume>A343</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The 26.5 ka Oruanui eruption, New Zealand: An introduction and overview</article-title>. <source>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Slumbering giants</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (chiefed.) <article-title>A continent on the move: New Zealand geoscience into the 21st Century</article-title>. <source>Geological Society of New Zealand Miscellaneous Publication</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The Taupo eruption, New Zealand. I. General aspects</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc> <volume>A314</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ambraseys</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>A new date for the Taupo eruption</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ambraseys</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GPL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Did Taupo’s eruption enhance European sunsets? – Reply</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>293</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CJN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gravley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Volcanism in the central Taupo Volcanic Zone, New Zealand: Tempo, styles and controls</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Thordarson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Self</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoskuldsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <article-title>Studies in volcanology: the legacy of George Walker</article-title>. <source>Special Publications of IAVCEI (Geological Society, London)</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zielinski</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayewski</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meeker</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitlow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Twickler</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Record of volcanism since 7000 B.C. from the GISP2 Greenland ice core and implications for the volcano-climate system</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>948</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0959683611425551">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guilderson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Extension of the Southern Hemisphere atmospheric radiocarbon curve, 2120–850 years BP: Results from Tasmanian huon pine</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>887</fpage>–<lpage>894</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>