<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsjp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1403-4948</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1651-1905</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494812462460</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1403494812462460</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Social determinants for health</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Experience of violation during the past 3 months, social capital, and self-rated health: A population-based study</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lindström</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1403494812462460">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1403494812462460">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>Jakob</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1403494812462460">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosvall</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1403494812462460">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1403494812462460">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1403494812462460"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Sciences, Malmö University Hospital, Lund University, Malmö, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1403494812462460"><label>2</label>Centre for Economic Demography, Lund University, Malmö, Sweden</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1403494812462460">Martin Lindström, Department of Clinical Sciences, Social Medicine and Health Policy, Malmö University Hospital, Lund University, Malmö S–205 02, Sweden. E-mail: <email>martin.lindstrom@med.lu.se</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>753</fpage>
<lpage>760</lpage>
<history><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 the Nordic Societies of Public Health</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Associations of Public Health in the Nordic Countries Regions</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Objective</italic>: The objective was to investigate the association between experience of violation during the past 3 months and self-rated health, taking trust (social capital), economic stress, and country of birth and parents’ country of birth into account. <italic>Design/setting/participants/measurements</italic>: The 2008 public health survey in Skåne is a cross-sectional study with 55% response rate. A random sample was approached using a postal questionnaire, and 28,198 persons aged 18–80 responded. Logistic regression models investigated associations between experience of violation during the past 3 months and self-rated health. <italic>Results</italic>: A 27.4% proportion of the men and 30.0% of the women reported less than good health. Less than good health was significantly higher in older age groups, among persons born outside Sweden, with low education, economic stress, low trust in other people, and experience of violation during the past 3 months. The group with experience of violation at one occasion during the past 3 months had odds ratio 1.76 (95% CI 1.57–1.97) of less than good health among men and odds ratio 1.78 (95% CI 1.62–1.96) among women, while the group with experience of violation two or more times during the past 3 months had odds ratio 4.28 (95% CI 3.36–5.44) among men and 3.54 (95% CI 2.89–4.35) among women in the final multiple analyses. <bold><italic>Conclusions</italic>: Experience of violation during the past 3 months is significantly associated with less than good health, which is a finding with important policy implications.</bold></p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Country of birth</kwd>
<kwd>economic stress</kwd>
<kwd>self-rated health</kwd>
<kwd>social capital</kwd>
<kwd>Sweden</kwd>
<kwd>trust</kwd>
<kwd>violation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>edited-state</meta-name>
<meta-value>corrected-proof</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1403494812462460" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Discrimination and violation are closely interconnected social phenomena. Discrimination and violation may increase the risk of socially caused trauma (physical, psychological, or sexual), increase the risk of economic and social deprivation, and result in decreased access to health care. Discrimination and violation may also result in anger and fear. The physiological panic-flight reaction mobilises lipids and glucose to increase the access to energy and to raise the level of psychological preparedness. Blood pressure also increases, a physiological reaction which in instances of recurring exposure to discrimination and violation may result in chronic hypertension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812462460">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1403494812462460"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812462460">3</xref>]. Discrimination and violation may also increase the risk of poor mental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1403494812462460">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812462460">5</xref>].</p>
<p>Discrimination is “the process by which a member or members of a socially defined group is, or are, treated differently (especially unfairly) because of his/her/their membership of that group” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812462460">6</xref>]. De jure discrimination refers to discrimination sanctioned by the legal system, while de facto discrimination stems from habits and attitudes. Structural discrimination refers to how a society reproduces discrimination, while interpersonal discrimination is the experience of discrimination by individuals. All forms of discrimination hurt economic and social wellbeing as well as health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812462460">3</xref>]. Self-reported discrimination due to racism has been associated with self-rated health in studies in the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812462460">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812462460">8</xref>], although surprisingly few international studies have investigated the association between discrimination and self-rated health. Most of the literature concerning systematic experiences of discrimination and their long-term effects on health through psychosocial, psychological, and physiological mechanisms refers to ethnicity and ethnic groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812462460">9</xref>], and most studies have been conducted in the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812462460">3</xref>]. Fewer studies have been conducted concerning discrimination issues such as for instance age, gender, and sexual discrimination, respectively, and health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812462460">10</xref>], and discrimination may also occur for other reasons.</p>
<p>Violation concerns “dignity and different forms of dignity violation” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812462460">11</xref>]. Dignity may be discerned into the two phenomena human dignity and social dignity. Human dignity is the basic value attributed to being human, while social dignity is a product of the interactions between individuals, groups of individuals, organisations, and institutions. Social dignity concerns both dignity-of-self, which includes characteristics such as self-respect and self-worth and dignity-in- relation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1403494812462460">12</xref>]. Violation has for instance been investigated in relation to health in terms of effects of job insecurity as “the violation hypothesis” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812462460">13</xref>] and in terms of maltreatment of the elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1403494812462460">14</xref>]. Only few studies have investigated violation in relation to self-rated health in specific settings such as the labour market [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812462460">13</xref>], and even fewer in relation to self-rated health in the general population.</p>
<p>The aim of health policy is both to increase health and life expectancy in the population and to reduce health differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812462460">15</xref>]. Sweden is currently a multiethnic society with 1.3 million inhabitants born in other countries than Sweden. The proportion born in other countries constituted 13.8% of the 9.3 million total population in 2008 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1403494812462460">16</xref>]. The patterns of health and mortality according to country of birth are diverse. The prevalence of poor self-rated health is higher among those born in the 15 first member of the European Community countries (EU 15), other European countries, and outside Europe, compared to the category born in Sweden. In addition, the category born in Sweden but with both parents born abroad also has significantly higher prevalence of less than good self-rated health compared to the category born in Sweden. In contrast, the age- and sex-adjusted mortality in 2001–05 was higher in the category born in the EU 15 than in the category born in Sweden, while it was the same in the category born in other European countries and significantly lower in the category born outside Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812462460">15</xref>]. No de jure discrimination exists in Sweden. Furthermore, Sweden also has laws against discrimination covering most areas of human life. On the other hand, de facto discrimination seems to exist for instance within the healthcare system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1403494812462460">17</xref>].</p>
<p>In Sweden, only few studies have been conducted concerning discrimination, violation, and health. One study showed a significant association between perceived discrimination and self-rated health among Kurdish immigrants in Sweden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1403494812462460">18</xref>]. Another Swedish study found a significant association between country of birth and less than good self-rated health, mediated by socioeconomic status and discrimination among immigrants born in Poland, Turkey, and Iran [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1403494812462460">19</xref>]. Findings from the national public health survey convey a significant association between repeated discrimination and less than good mental health even after multiple adjustments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1403494812462460">20</xref>]. Some studies have displayed a significant association between expectation of discrimination on the labour market (by employer) and self-rated health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1403494812462460">21</xref>] and mental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1403494812462460">22</xref>], respectively.</p>
<p>Discrimination and violation are strongly associated with social capital. Social capital concerns the interaction between individuals, groups of individuals, organisations, and institutions rather than the characteristics of each of these entities <italic>per se</italic>. Social capital comprises reciprocity among citizens, civic engagement among citizens, social participation among citizens, generalised trust in other people, and trust in the government and other public institutions of society, and social capital thus fosters social and economic cooperation and progress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1403494812462460">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1403494812462460">24</xref>]. According to Putnam [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1403494812462460">25</xref>], the low levels of social capital and trust in the southeastern parts of the USA have origins extending far back in time from the era of slavery and the following period which entailed de jure discrimination. Social capital has been suggested to affect health by psychosocial stress mechanisms, by increased access to health care and amenities, by a decrease in crime and particularly violent crime, and by promoting benevolent norms, values, and attitudes concerning behaviours and lifestyles associated with health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1403494812462460">26</xref>]. The proponents of social capital as a determinant of health have been challenged by other scholars who state that general public welfare policies aimed at decreasing socioeconomic differences in life conditions and economic/material conditions in general are more crucial predictors of health than social capital [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1403494812462460">27</xref>].</p>
<p>Self-rated health is a compound measurement of physical and mental health. It is a significant predictor of morbidity and mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1403494812462460">28</xref>].</p>
<p>The hypothesis of this study is that a significant association exists between self-reported violation during the past 3 months and less than good self-rated health even after adjustments for country of birth and parents’ country of birth, education, economic stress, and trust. The aim of this study is to investigate the association between experience of violation during the past 3 months and self-rated health.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1403494812462460" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1403494812462460">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>The public health survey in 2008 in southern Sweden (Skåne) is a cross sectional study. A total of 28,198 persons randomly selected from the official population registers of people living in Skåne born between 1928 and 1990 answered a postal questionnaire in the period from August to September 2008 (55% response rate). Two reminder letters were also sent. Ethical permission was granted from the Ethical Committee, Lund University (Dnr. 2010/343).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1403494812462460">
<title>Definitions</title>
<sec id="section5-1403494812462460">
<title>Dependent variable</title>
<p><italic>Self-rated health</italic> was investigated by the question “How do you consider your general health status?” with five alternative answers “very good”, “good”, “neither good nor poor”, “poor”, and “very poor”. The answers were dichotomised into good (the two first alternatives) and less than good (the three latter alternatives) self-rated health.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1403494812462460">
<title>Independent variables</title>
<p><italic>Age</italic> was divided into the age categories 18–24, 25–34, 35–44, 45–54, 55–64, and 65–80 years. All analyses in the study were stratified by <italic>sex</italic>. All participants born in countries other than Sweden were merged into a single category. Respondents born in Sweden were categorised into one category with both parents born in Sweden, one category with one parent born in Sweden and one parent born abroad, or, finally, one category with both parents born abroad.</p>
<p><italic>Education</italic> was classified into the categories ≥13 years or more of education, 10–12 years of education, and ≤9 years of education or less.</p>
<p><italic>Economic stress</italic> was investigated with the question “How often during the past 12 months have you had problems paying your bills?” with the alternatives “never”, “occasionally”, “every second month”, and “every month”.</p>
<p><italic>Generalised trust in other people</italic> measures the individual’s assessment of generalised trust in other people. It was appraised by the item “Generally, you can trust other people” with the four alternatives “Do not agree at all”, “Do not agree”, “Agree”, and “Completely agree”, and was dichotomised with the two first alternatives indicating low trust and the two latter depicting high trust.</p>
<p><italic>Violation</italic> during the past 3 months was assessed with the item “Have you during the past 3 months been treated in a way that made you feel violated?” The alternative answers were “no”, “yes, on some occasion”, and “yes, several times”. The violation variable was dichotomised in an analysis with the two latter alternatives collapsed.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section7-1403494812462460">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>Prevalences of self-rated health, age, country of birth, education, economic stress, generalised trust in other people, and experience of violation were calculated. Prevalences and odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals (OR, 95% CI) of less than good self-rated health were calculated according to violation during the past 3 months, age, country of birth, education, economic stress, and generalised trust in other people. Prevalences and OR with 95% CI of self-reported experience of violation during the past 3 months were calculated according to age, country of birth, education, economic stress, and generalised trust in other people. Age-adjusted and multiple adjusted odds ratios with 95% CI of less than good self-rated health were calculated according to experience of violation, and Chi square and Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> were calculated for the models. The statistical analyses were performed using the SPSS software package version 17.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1403494812462460">29</xref>].</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section8-1403494812462460" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1403494812462460">Table I</xref> displays that 27.4% of the men and 30.0% of the women reported less than good health. The prevalence of age, country of origin, parents’ country of origin, education, economic stress, generalised trust in other people, and experience of violation variables among men and women are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1403494812462460">Table I</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1403494812462460" position="float">
<label>Table I.</label>
<caption>
<p>Prevalence (%) of self-rated health, demographic characteristics, education, economic stress, generalised trust in other people, and experience of violation during the past 3 months: the public health survey in Skåne 2008.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1403494812462460" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812462460-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Men (<italic>n</italic>=12,726)</th>
<th align="left">Women (<italic>n</italic>=15,472)</th>
<th align="left">Total (<italic>n</italic>=28,198)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Self-rated health</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Good</td>
<td>72.6</td>
<td>70.0</td>
<td>71.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than good</td>
<td>27.4</td>
<td>30.0</td>
<td>28.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(250)</td>
<td>(396)</td>
<td>(646)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Age (years)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 18–24</td>
<td>8.3</td>
<td>9.1</td>
<td>8.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 25–34</td>
<td>12.3</td>
<td>13.9</td>
<td>13.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 35–44</td>
<td>16.4</td>
<td>17.2</td>
<td>16.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–54</td>
<td>17.7</td>
<td>18.5</td>
<td>18.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–64</td>
<td>21.2</td>
<td>19.3</td>
<td>20.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–80</td>
<td>24.2</td>
<td>21.9</td>
<td>22.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>(0)</td>
<td>(0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Born in Sweden or other country/birth country of parents</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, both parents born in Sweden</td>
<td>79.6</td>
<td>78.7</td>
<td>79.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, one parent born abroad</td>
<td>4.9</td>
<td>5.3</td>
<td>5.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, both parents born abroad</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other country</td>
<td>13.9</td>
<td>14.2</td>
<td>14.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(273)</td>
<td>(282)</td>
<td>(555)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Education (years)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≥13</td>
<td>33.2</td>
<td>41.2</td>
<td>37.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 10–12</td>
<td>41.9</td>
<td>38.3</td>
<td>39.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≤9</td>
<td>25.0</td>
<td>20.4</td>
<td>22.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(1098)</td>
<td>(1631)</td>
<td>(2729)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Economic stress</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Never</td>
<td>79.5</td>
<td>76.5</td>
<td>77.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Occasionally</td>
<td>14.1</td>
<td>15.7</td>
<td>15.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Half the year</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Every month</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>3.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(307)</td>
<td>(335)</td>
<td>(642)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Generalised trust in other people</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High</td>
<td>66.1</td>
<td>64.3</td>
<td>65.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low</td>
<td>33.9</td>
<td>35.7</td>
<td>34.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(522)</td>
<td>(685)</td>
<td>(1207)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Experience of violation during the past 3 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>75.6</td>
<td>68.8</td>
<td>71.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, at some occasion</td>
<td>21.1</td>
<td>27.3</td>
<td>24.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, several times</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td>3.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(304)</td>
<td>(406)</td>
<td>(710)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1403494812462460">Table II</xref> shows that the odds ratios of less than good health were significantly higher in higher age groups, among those born in other countries than Sweden, among persons with medium and low education, with economic stress, low generalised trust in other people, and experience of violation during the past 3 months.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1403494812462460" position="float">
<label>Table II.</label>
<caption>
<p>Prevalence (%) and odds ratios (OR, 95% CI) in bivariate analyses of less than good health according to age, country of origin, education, economic stress, generalised trust in other people, and experience of violation during the past 3 months: the public health survey in Skåne 2008.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1403494812462460" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812462460-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Men (<italic>n</italic>=12,726)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Women (<italic>n</italic>=15,472)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Age (years)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 18–24</td>
<td>14.3</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>20.5</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 25–34</td>
<td>16.0</td>
<td>1.15 (0.92–1.43)</td>
<td>19.5</td>
<td>0.94 (0.79–1.11)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 35–44</td>
<td>19.2</td>
<td>1.43 (1.16–1.75)</td>
<td>23.8</td>
<td>1.21 (1.04–1.42)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–54</td>
<td>27.5</td>
<td>2.28 (1.89–2.77)</td>
<td>27.9</td>
<td>1.50 (1.28–1.74)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–64</td>
<td>33.0</td>
<td>2.96 (2.44–3.58)</td>
<td>36.2</td>
<td>2.20 (1.90–2.56)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–80</td>
<td>38.6</td>
<td>3.77 (3.12–4.56)</td>
<td>42.3</td>
<td>2.84 (2.46–3.30)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(250)</td>
<td/>
<td>(396)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Born in Sweden or other country/birth country of parents</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, both parents born in Sweden</td>
<td>26.7</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, one parent born abroad</td>
<td>23.6</td>
<td>0.85 (0.70–1.03)</td>
<td>26.7</td>
<td>0.90 (0.76–1.06)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, both parents born abroad</td>
<td>16.8</td>
<td>0.55 (0.38–0.80)</td>
<td>25.2</td>
<td>0.83 (0.63–1.10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other country</td>
<td>33.2</td>
<td>1.33 (1.19–1.48)</td>
<td>37.1</td>
<td>1.46 (1.32–1.60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(499)</td>
<td/>
<td>(682)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education (years)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≥13</td>
<td>17.7</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>20.5</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 10–12</td>
<td>25.2</td>
<td>1.57 (1.41–1.74)</td>
<td>30.0</td>
<td>1.66 (1.52–1.82)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≤9</td>
<td>41.5</td>
<td>3.31 (2.96–3.70)</td>
<td>45.7</td>
<td>3.26 (2.95–3.60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(1267)</td>
<td/>
<td>(1920)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Economic stress</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Never</td>
<td>24.1</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>26.5</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Occasionally</td>
<td>33.1</td>
<td>1.56 (1.40–1.74)</td>
<td>34.8</td>
<td>1.48 (1.34–1.63)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Half the year</td>
<td>46.2</td>
<td>2.70 (2.20–3.33)</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>2.09 (1.75–2.49)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Every month</td>
<td>59.6</td>
<td>4.66 (3.80–5.73)</td>
<td>59.1</td>
<td>4.01 (3.40–4.73)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(491)</td>
<td/>
<td>(669)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Generalised trust in other people</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High</td>
<td>22.6</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>24.1</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low</td>
<td>34.8</td>
<td>1.83 (1.69–2.00)</td>
<td>38.7</td>
<td>1.99 (1.85–2.14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(706)</td>
<td/>
<td>(1010)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Experience of violation during the past 3 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>24.3</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>26.4</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, at some occasion</td>
<td>32.6</td>
<td>1.51 (1.37–1.66)</td>
<td>34.1</td>
<td>1.44 (1.34–1.56)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, several times</td>
<td>57.3</td>
<td>4.19 (3.41–5.14)</td>
<td>54.7</td>
<td>3.37 (2.84–4.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(478)</td>
<td/>
<td>(735)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1403494812462460">Table III</xref> shows that self-reported experience of violation (one or several times) during the past 3 months was significantly more prevalent among comparatively younger respondents, among men and women born in Sweden with one or both parents born abroad, among men but not women born abroad, among men and women with higher education, among men and women who had experienced economic stress during the past year, and among men and women with low generalised trust in other people.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1403494812462460" position="float">
<label>Table III.</label>
<caption>
<p>Prevalence (%) and odds ratios (OR, 95% CI) in bivariate analyses of self-reported violation during the past 3 months according to age, country of origin, education, economic stress, and generalised trust in other people: the public health survey in Skåne 2008.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1403494812462460" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812462460-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Men (<italic>n</italic>=12,726)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Women (<italic>n</italic>=15,472)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 18–24</td>
<td>37.1</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>50.1</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 25–34</td>
<td>31.9</td>
<td>0.80 (0.67–0.94)</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>0.75 (0.65–0.86)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 35–44</td>
<td>30.6</td>
<td>0.75 (0.64–0.87)</td>
<td>37.0</td>
<td>0.58 (0.51–0.67)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 45–54</td>
<td>27.0</td>
<td>0.63 (0.53–0.73)</td>
<td>33.4</td>
<td>0.50 (0.44–0.57)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 55–64</td>
<td>22.2</td>
<td>0.48 (0.41–0.56)</td>
<td>24.7</td>
<td>0.33 (0.29–0.37)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 65–80</td>
<td>11.7</td>
<td>0.22 (0.19–0.27)</td>
<td>14.0</td>
<td>0.16 (0.14–0.19)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(311)</td>
<td/>
<td>(407)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Born in Sweden or other country/birth country of parents</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, both parents born in Sweden</td>
<td>23.0</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>29.8</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, one parent born abroad</td>
<td>30.8</td>
<td>1.50 (1.25–1.78)</td>
<td>43.4</td>
<td>1.80 (1.56–2.08)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sweden, both parents born abroad</td>
<td>34.3</td>
<td>1.75 (1.30–2.36)</td>
<td>42.5</td>
<td>1.74 (1.36–2.23)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other country</td>
<td>29.0</td>
<td>1.37 (1.22–1.54)</td>
<td>31.6</td>
<td>1.09 (0.98–1.20)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(490)</td>
<td/>
<td>(628)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Education (years)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≥13</td>
<td>27.2</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>36.9</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 10–12</td>
<td>26.4</td>
<td>0.96 (0.87–1.06)</td>
<td>31.8</td>
<td>0.80 (0.74–0.86)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≤9</td>
<td>17.1</td>
<td>0.55 (0,49–0.62)</td>
<td> 18.6</td>
<td>0.39 (0.35–0.44)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(1263)</td>
<td/>
<td>(1876)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Economic stress</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Never</td>
<td>20.7</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>26.1</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Occasionally</td>
<td>35.1</td>
<td>2.08 (1.86–2.32)</td>
<td>43.5</td>
<td>2.18 (1.99–2.39)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Half the year</td>
<td>45.2</td>
<td>3.17 (2.58–3.91)</td>
<td>55.0</td>
<td>3.46 (2.91–4.12)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Every month</td>
<td>48.6</td>
<td>3.63 (2.97–4.44)</td>
<td>54.1</td>
<td>3.34 (2.83–3.93)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(478)</td>
<td/>
<td>(607)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Generalised trust in other people</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High</td>
<td>19.3</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>25.5</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low</td>
<td>34.7</td>
<td>2.23 (2.05–2.43)</td>
<td>41.9</td>
<td>2.10 (1.96–2.26)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> (Missing, <italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>(592)</td>
<td/>
<td>(807)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1403494812462460">Table IV</xref> shows that among both men and women the significant associations between self-reported experience of violation during the past 3 months and less than good health remained throughout the multiple adjustments. The category with experience of violation at one occasion during the past 3 months had an odds ratio 1.76 (95% CI 1.57–1.97) of less than good health among men and an odds ratio 1.78 (95% CI 1.62–1.96) among women. The odds ratios of less than good health were consistently highest in the category that had experienced violation several times during the past 3 months, OR 4.28 (95% CI 3.36–5.44) among men and 3.54 (95% CI 2.89–4.35) among women.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1403494812462460" position="float">
<label>Table IV.</label>
<caption>
<p>Age-adjusted and multiple-adjusted odds ratios (OR, 95% CI) of less than good health according to experience of violation/insults during the past 3 months: the public health survey in Skåne 2008.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1403494812462460" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812462460-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1403494812462460">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812462460">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1403494812462460">c</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1403494812462460">d</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1403494812462460">e</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6"><bold>Men’s experience of violation during the past 3 months</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, at some occasion</td>
<td>1.96 (1.77–2.16)</td>
<td>1.93 (1.74–2.13)</td>
<td>2.04 (1.83–2.27)</td>
<td>1.85 (1.66–2.07)</td>
<td>1.76 (1.57–1.97)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, several times</td>
<td>6.08 (4.91–7.54)</td>
<td>5.88 (4.73–7.31)</td>
<td>6.10 (4.86–7.67)</td>
<td>4.88 (3.85–6.19)</td>
<td>4.28 (3.36–5.44)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.097</td>
<td>0.102</td>
<td>0.135</td>
<td>0.163</td>
<td>0.167</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chi square</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6"><bold>Women’s experience of violation during the past 3 months</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, at some occasion</td>
<td>1.93 (1.77–2.10)</td>
<td>1.93 (1.77–2.10)</td>
<td>2.09 (1.90–2.29)</td>
<td>1.90 (1.73–2.09)</td>
<td>1.78 (1.62–1.96)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes, several times</td>
<td>4.79 (4.01–5.72)</td>
<td>4.89 (4.08–5.86)</td>
<td>4.92 (4.05–5.96)</td>
<td>4.12 (3.38–5.04)</td>
<td>3.54 (2.89–4.35)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.086</td>
<td>0.092</td>
<td>0.121</td>
<td>0.152</td>
<td>0.160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chi square</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1403494812462460">
<label>a</label>
<p>Adjusted for age.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1403494812462460">
<label>b</label>
<p>Adjusted for age, country of origin, and parents’ country of origin.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1403494812462460">
<label>c</label>
<p>Adjusted for age, country of origin, parents’ country of origin, and education.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1403494812462460">
<label>d</label>
<p>Adjusted for age, country of origin, parents’ country of origin, education, and economic stress.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1403494812462460">
<label>e</label>
<p>Adjusted for age, country of origin, parents’ country of origin, education, economic stress, and generalised trust in other people.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1403494812462460" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The group with experience of violation at one or several occasions during the past 3 months retained significantly higher odds ratios of less than good health throughout the multiple analyses. Self-reported experience of violation (one or several times) during the past 3 months was significantly more prevalent in younger age groups, among men and women born in Sweden with one or both parents born abroad, among men but not women born abroad, among men and women with higher education, among men and women with economic stress, and among men and women with low generalised trust in other people.</p>
<p>Experience of violation during the past 3 months is significantly associated with less than good health even after adjustments for a number of relevant confounders, and the association is also stronger for those who had experienced several incidents of violation during the past 3 months. The mechanisms behind this association may be both psychological [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1403494812462460">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812462460">5</xref>] and physical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812462460">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1403494812462460"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812462460">3</xref>]. The plausible causal mechanisms connecting violation and health may include increased risks of hypertension and increased levels of blood glucose and serum lipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812462460">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1403494812462460"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812462460">3</xref>], i.e. increased risk of chronic exposure to cardiovascular risk factors particularly under conditions of repeated violation. The connection between violation and health also includes psychological and psychosocial problems and diseases such as depression caused by violation and repeated violation in particular [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1403494812462460">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812462460">5</xref>]. Previous studies have investigated the association between violation of dignity and health in the contexts of urban geography and urban neighbourhoods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1403494812462460">12</xref>], mistreatment of the elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1403494812462460">14</xref>], and exposure to temporary employment and job insecurity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812462460">13</xref>], but only the latter study measured the health outcome as self-rated health. The present study concerns a general item concerning violation as repeated violation in a random sample of a general population in southern Sweden, an item and a design which may be regarded as a strength of this study.</p>
<p>The fact that the associations in the present study remain robustly significant even after multiple adjustments as well as the high prevalence of experience of violation even among respondents born in Sweden with both parents born in Sweden (23.0% among men and 29.8% among women born in Sweden with both parents born in Sweden) suggests rather generally spread experiences of violation in Swedish society.</p>
<p>Self-perceived experience of violation during the past 3 months may have been caused by discriminatory verbal insults and other adverse treatment that may have been directed towards the respondent for reasons of gender, age, or ethnicity/country of birth and parents’ country of birth. In this study, we have analysed the association between country of birth as well as parents’ country of birth and self-rated health. We found a significant association between age, being born in another country, and parents’ country of birth, respectively, and less than good health (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1403494812462460">Table II</xref>). In the final analyses of the association between self-reported experience of violation during the past 3 months and self-rated health, we adjusted for age, country of origin and parents’ country of origin, education, economic stress, and generalised trust in other people, and stratified for gender. The association between violation and less than good self-rated health remained statistically significant with considerably higher odds ratios of less than good health among respondents with several experiences of violation. The results suggest that there may also be other reasons behind the association between experience of violation and self-rated heath than country of birth, parents’ country of birth, age, and gender.</p>
<p>The results suggest that absence of de jure discrimination and legislation directed against de facto discrimination in Sweden have not abolished experience of violation. A 24.4% proportion of all men and 31.2% of all women in our study had experienced violation/insults at one or several occasion(s) during the past 3 months. These experiences of violation are, in turn, associated with increased odds ratios of less than good health. The finding of a significant association between self-reported violation during the past 3 months and less than good self-rated health suggests that policy measures against discrimination also should be included in health policy. Such measures include education, information, and an ongoing discussion in order to increase knowledge and awareness.</p>
<sec id="section10-1403494812462460">
<title>Strengths and limitations</title>
<p>The response rate was 55%, a response level commonly found in current surveys in most Western countries, but the distribution of most social and demographic variables, with the exception of the born abroad category which was under-represented by 4 percentage units, corresponded well with the general distribution of these social and demographic characteristics in public registers. The risk of selection bias is thus probably comparatively small.</p>
<p>Confounders such as age, country of birth, parents’ birth country, education, economic stress, and trust were adjusted for in the multiple logistic regression models, and stratification was conducted for sex in all analyses.</p>
<p>Self-rated health has been studied regarding validity in a number of previous studies. It has been found to be a good and valid predictor of prospective morbidity and mortality, e.g. for incidence of cardiovascular diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1403494812462460">30</xref>]. The generalised trust in other people as well as the experience of violation items are self-reported and thus difficult to validate. The item concerning generalised trust in other people has been used in earlier international studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1403494812462460">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1403494812462460">26</xref>].</p>
<p>It is impossible to infer causality from studies with cross-sectional design, although results from such studies may well form at least some smaller part of the basis for causal inference. Furthermore, the item concerning violation refers to experience during the past 3 months while the self-rated health item concerns the feeling of general health at the point in time when the cross-sectional study was conducted. Still, fully valid conclusions concerning causality can only be drawn from future studies which are longitudinal in design.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section11-1403494812462460" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Experience of violation during the past 3 months is significantly associated with less than good self-rated health, which is a finding with important policy implications.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by the Swedish Research Council Linnaeus Centre for Economic Demography (VR 79), Swedish ALF Government (grant Dnr M 2011/1816), and the research funds of the University Hospital in Southern Sweden (SUS).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1403494812462460">
<label>[1]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Racial and gender discrimination: risk factors for high blood pressure?</article-title> <source>Social Science and Medicine</source> <year>1990</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1273</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1403494812462460">
<label>[2]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sidney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Racial discrimination and blood pressure: the CARDIA study of young black and white adults</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1370</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1403494812462460">
<label>[3]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Discrimination and health</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>, editors, <source>Social epidemiology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1403494812462460">
<label>[4]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laflamme</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self-reported discrimination and mental health status among African descendants, Mexican Americans, and other Latinos in the New Hampshire REACH 2010 initiative: The added dimension of integration</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1821</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1403494812462460">
<label>[5]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonham</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neighbors</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of racial discrimination and health behaviours on mental and physical health of middle-class African American men</article-title>. <source>Health Education Behavior</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1403494812462460">
<label>[6]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Oxford Dictionary of Sociology</source>, <edition>3rd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1403494812462460">
<label>[7]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paradies</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of empirical research on self-reported racism and health</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Epidemiology</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>888</fpage>–<lpage>991</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1403494812462460">
<label>[8]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blaney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The association between multiple domains of discrimination and self-assessed health: a multilevel analysis of Latinos and Blacks in four low-income New York City Neighborhoods</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>6 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>1735</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1403494812462460">
<label>[9]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Racial differences in mental health: socio-economic status, stress, and discrimination</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Psychology</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1403494812462460">
<label>[10]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Race, gender, and sexual orientation in hate crime victimization: identity politics or identity risk?</article-title> <source>Violence and Victims</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1403494812462460">
<label>[11]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gostin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gruskin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lazzarini</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health and human rights</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gruskin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grodin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Annas</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>, editors, <source>Health and human rights: a reader</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>1999</year>. pp.<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1403494812462460">
<label>[12]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An urban geography of dignity</article-title>. <source>Health and Place</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1403494812462460">
<label>[13]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janlert</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammarström</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Exposure to temporary employment and job insecurity: a longitudinal study of the health effects</article-title>. <source>Occupational and Environmental Medicine</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1403494812462460">
<label>[14]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is greater social support a protective factor against elder mistreatment?</article-title> <source>Gerontology</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1403494812462460">
<label>[15]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Danielsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Public health report 2009</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The National Board on Health and Welfare</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year> (in Swedish).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1403494812462460">
<label>[16]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Biterman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Social report 2010</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The National Board on Health and Welfare</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year> (in Swedish).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1403494812462460">
<label>[17]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Groglopo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahlberg</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Hälsa, vård och strukturell diskriminering</source> (<trans-source xml:lang="en">Health, Care and Structural Discrimination</trans-source>). <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statens Offentliga Utredningar (SOU) SOU</publisher-name>: <year>2006</year>. Report no. 78 (in Swedish).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1403494812462460">
<label>[18]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taloyan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kocturk</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Poor self-reported health and sleeping difficulties among Kurdish immigrant men in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Transcultural Psychiatry</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1403494812462460">
<label>[19]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wiking</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ethnicity, acculturation, and self-reported health: a population based study from Poland, Turkey, and Iran in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>574</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1403494812462460">
<label>[20]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wamala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boström</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyqvist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Perceived discrimination and psychological distress in Sweden</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1403494812462460">
<label>[21]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mohseni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindström</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ethnic differences in anticipated discrimination, generalised trust in other people and self-rated health: a population-based study in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Ethnicity and Health</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1403494812462460">
<label>[22]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lindström</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohseni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Social capital, political trust and self reported psychological health: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Social Science and Medicine</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1403494812462460">
<label>[23]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Making democracy work</article-title>. <source>Civic traditions in modern Italy</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1403494812462460">
<label>[24]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bowling alone</article-title>. <source>The collapse and revival of American community</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1403494812462460">
<label>[25]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Social capital: measurement and consequences</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Policy Research</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1403494812462460">
<label>[26]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Social capital and self-rated health: a contextual analysis</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1403494812462460">
<label>[27]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is social capital the key to inequalities in health?</article-title> <source>American Journal of Public Health</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1403494812462460">
<label>[28]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Idler</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benyamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self-rated health and mortality: a review of twenty-seven community studies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1403494812462460">
<label>[29]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Norusis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>SPSS for Windows. Advanced statistics</source>. Release 17.0. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SPSS</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1403494812462460">
<label>[30]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heistaro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jousilahti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lahelma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vartiainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self rated health and mortality: a long term prospective study in eastern Finland</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>