<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-6990</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077699012472036</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077699012472036</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: The Stewart/Colbert Effect: Essays on the Real Impacts of Fake News</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>Samuel P.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1077699012472036">University of Dayton, Dayton, OH, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>90</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>189</fpage>
<lpage>191</lpage>
<product><source>The Stewart/Colbert Effect: Essays on the Real Impacts of Fake News</source>. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Amarasingam</surname><given-names>Amarnath</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <publisher-loc>Jefferson, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McFarland</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="198"/> pp. <price>$40</price> pbk.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 AEJMC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Education in Journalism &amp; Mass Communication</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>One of my few firmly held opinions is that nothing spoils a perfectly good bratwurst like learning how it is produced. However, despite seeing episodes of <italic>Dirty Jobs</italic> and <italic>How It’s Made</italic> detailing exactly that manufacturing process in all its glory, I have managed to cling to my enjoyment of sausage (although I admit to an occasional unpleasant flashback). I have similar feelings about humor. Among the useful things I learned in a rhetorical criticism class in graduate school was that great humor can be absolutely ruined by discussion and analysis. As such, it was with more than mild trepidation that I approached <italic>The Stewart/Colbert Effect: Essays on the Real Impacts of Fake News</italic>.</p>
<p>This volume is a thoughtful collection of contributed essays, edited by Amarnath Amarasingam, a doctoral candidate at Wilfred Laurier University in Ontario, Canada, that attempts to “provide a new theoretical perspective” and to study the “overall social significance of Jon Stewart and Stephen Colbert.” The collection is divided into two parts: “New Research” and “Theoretical Considerations.” Part 1, the research portion of the book, details five academic studies focused on the following questions: Do <italic>The Daily Show</italic> and <italic>Colbert Report</italic> bring attention to science and technology issues in the same way and with the same impact as they bring to politics? To what extent does <italic>The Daily Show</italic> provide its audience with “simple rules of thumb” (heuristics) allowing it to form attitudes about issues without going to all the trouble to carefully consider the related facts? Has the impact of <italic>The Daily Show</italic> on young adults and their political engagement been overdramatized in popular culture? Are <italic>The Daily Show</italic> and <italic>Colbert Report</italic> actually the authentic (real) news and much of the mainstream political coverage inauthentic (fake)? Finally, does <italic>The Daily Show</italic> benefit democracy by holding politicians and journalists accountable, or does it undermine democracy by promoting disengagement and alienation from the political process? These are all great questions!</p>
<p>There are noteworthy strengths and weaknesses in the studies in Part 1. A significant strength of all the essays is the quality of the literature reviews and theoretical underpinnings of the studies being reported. Many provide first-rate models for making an argument supporting a research question or hypothesis. In addition, perhaps especially because I am not familiar with research in this area, the reviews provided marvelous contextual foundations for understanding the nature and importance of each study. Likewise, the methods used in the studies were very clearly described and should be clear to even novice students of research. The weaknesses sometimes can be found in the choice and/or execution of the research methods, and in some cases conclusions were speculative and tangentially connected to the reported results.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, both the strengths and the weaknesses make this book a valuable tool for classes in research methods or media analysis. It’s challenging to teach the process of crafting a well-documented and well-argued literature review that provides a strong rationale for a study, but these readings generally provide good models for illustration of those qualities. As for the weaknesses, I do not mean to imply that this work is subpar: it is not. It’s just not always perfect. Those considering using this book for a methods, criticism, or analysis class might well challenge students to critique the choices of methods or to consider others for answering the research questions posed in the studies. In addition, students could critically evaluate the conclusions reached in each study, either to justify the existing conclusions or to argue for alternatives.</p>
<p>The five essays in the theoretical portion of the book seem less “scientific” in tone. They are a bit more entertaining to read and provide depth in analysis from more of a “big picture” point of view rather than the more tightly focused studies of Part 1. Two of the essays in this section consider the psychology of the audience in the attempt to understand the appeal and the potential impact of the Stewart and Colbert programs, two of the essays read much like insightful rhetorical criticism, and the final essay is a call for thoughtful consideration of the ethical responsibilities of this genre (faux news) of programming. All the essays in Part 2 are engaging and provocative, and all should provide exceptional starting points for dialog and debate. Students of media analysis, research methods, journalism, rhetorical criticism, and cultural studies (among others) should benefit from the insight of the contributors as well as be motivated to challenge the conclusions and attempt their own analyses.</p>
<p>A theme that occurs across many of the essays concerns the question of the makeup of the Stewart/Colbert audience and the effect of the programs on it. Is this audience one that is brighter and more well informed about political, scientific, and journalistic issues, or does regular exposure to the programs merely make the audience <italic>believe</italic> that it is brighter and more well informed? Are the members of this audience more politically active and engaged than nonwatchers of the shows? Does regular exposure to Stewart and Colbert create a culture of cynicism in viewers? The essay “Stoned Slackers or Super Citizens?” challenges the assumption of a bright, informed, and politically engaged audience. This is a stimulating and confrontational question. I found myself coming down on both sides of the issue. On one hand, heavy viewers of the programs who do not make the effort to be well informed on the issues may not be politically engaged and may even be cynical of the political process. However, by not being informed through attending to multiple sources of news, this class of viewer misses much of the humor. To “get” the joke of parody and satire, a viewer needs to know the “real” story to see the contrast. So it is likely that the viewers who appreciate the programs the most are those who are better informed and perhaps more truly engaged in the process. If this kind of question can stir debate within one reader, how provocative would the question be to a room full of graduate students or upper-level undergrads?</p>
<p>I had a great time reading and arguing with the essays and with myself. The good news is that the collection provided a series of thoughtful analyses of the humor without spoiling it for me. I appreciate that! Even so, I wonder if Stewart and Colbert are actually as deep and strategic in their humor and intentions, as some of the essays imply, or are we just attributing that quality to them?</p>
</body>
</article>