<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NVS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnvs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0899-7640</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7395</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0899764012473385</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0899764012473385</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Religious Affiliation, Religious Attendance, and Participation in Social Change Organizations</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0899764012473385">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>Natalie J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0899764012473385">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Abzug</surname><given-names>Rikki</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0899764012473385">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>Laura R. A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0899764012473385">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0899764012473385"><label>1</label>Indiana University-Purdue University Indianapolis, Indianapolis, IN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0899764012473385"><label>2</label>Defense Resources Management Institute, Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0899764012473385"><label>3</label>Ramapo College, Mahwah, NJ, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0899764012473385"><label>4</label>Abt Associates Inc., Bethesda, MD, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0899764012473385">Chao Guo, Indiana University School of Public &amp; Environmental Affairs, IUPUI, 801 W. Michigan Street, Indianapolis, IN 46202, USA Email: <email>chaoguo@iupui.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>34</fpage>
<lpage>58</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association For Research On Nonprofit Organizations And Voluntary Action</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>How does religion affect an individual’s likelihood of volunteering for social change causes? This study reports on findings from an analysis of the 2005 wave of the COPPS supplement to the PSID to examine the effects of religious tradition (affiliation) and religious attendance (religiosity) on social change volunteering. We find that adherents to the more liberal Christian denominations—mainline Protestant and Catholic—are more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are Evangelicals. We also find that adherents to other minority religions such as Judaism and Buddhism and individuals with no religious belief are all more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are Evangelicals. We find a positive and significant relationship between religious attendance and social change volunteering, but find little difference in the effect of religious attendance on social change volunteering between Evangelicals and other religious traditions (except for Catholics).</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>religious affiliation</kwd>
<kwd>religious attendance</kwd>
<kwd>social change</kwd>
<kwd>volunteering for social change</kwd>
<kwd>advocacy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Since Alexis de Tocqueville visited the Jacksonian America of the 19th century, the United States has been described as a nation of volunteers. From singing in the church choir to coaching a baseball game for school kids, from assisting the museum in giving tours to visitors to participating in fund-raising for the local library, from feeding the poor to caring for the elderly, volunteerism has played an important role in American society throughout history. A recent study by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0899764012473385">Bureau of Labor Statistics (2010)</xref> finds that more than 63 million American people—nearly 27% of the population—volunteered for an organization in the previous year.</p>
<p>In this study, however, we look at a small percentage of volunteers who appear to “march to a different drummer” than the “good-deed doers” mentioned above: they work for a political party, participate in neighborhood governance, rally for gay and lesbian rights, protest against or for the war in Iraq, and the list goes on. We know relatively little about these individuals other than the fact that they volunteer to voice their concerns about issues and participate in political processes, often through organizations for advocacy and social change. In our view, participation in advocacy and social change includes not only political advocacy, which focuses on influencing government policy, but also social advocacy, which involves a broader focus on issues and institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0899764012473385">Reid, 2000</xref>). Who are these individuals who take up volunteering for social change? Why do they do so while others do not? A better understanding of social change volunteers will help establish a dialogue between two important streams of research in nonprofit and voluntary action: the existing volunteerism literature that focuses predominantly on service-oriented volunteer work and a growing body of literature on nonprofit advocacy that largely ignores the individual-level analysis.</p>
<p>While it is useful to examine the personality or disposition factors that may distinguish people based on their propensity to volunteer for social change, we focus on the influence of religion. Religion is an important source of values of benevolence and civic engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0899764012473385">Uslaner, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Janoski, 1995</xref>). The United States has a strong tradition of religiosity, and its religious diversity has increased as the non-Judeo-Christian population grew in recent decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0899764012473385">Smith, 2002</xref>). According to a <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0899764012473385">2007</xref> Pew Research Center survey on the religious composition of America, the vast majority of Americans (78.5%) identified themselves as Christians, mostly with Protestant and Catholic denominations (51.3% and 23.9% respectively). Judaism accounted for about 1.7% of the population. Non-Judeo-Christian religions (e.g., Buddhism, Islam, and Hinduism, etc.) collectively accounted for about 3% of the population.</p>
<p>Prior research generally shows that religion as a form of cultural and social capital promotes volunteering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0899764012473385">Borgonovi, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012473385">Paik &amp; Navarre-Jackson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0899764012473385">Park &amp; Smith, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Musick, 1997</xref>). In a recent methodological paper, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0899764012473385">Cnaan, Jones, Dickin, and Salomon (2011)</xref> provide quantification of the oft-cited idea that faith-based organizations are a primary avenue for volunteering. Some research further indicates that one’s level of religious attendance, rather than one’s particular religious tradition, more fully accounts for varying <italic>levels</italic> of volunteering (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0899764012473385">Campbell &amp; Yonish, 2003</xref>). Yet it remains unclear if the same holds true for different <italic>types</italic> of volunteer efforts. In other words, do one’s particular religious tradition and religious attendance have a stronger impact on some types of volunteer work than others? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012473385">Paik and Navarre-Jackson (2011)</xref> summarize the literature as suggesting that frequency of church attendance is related to volunteering for specifically religious causes, whereas participation in church-based activities, organizations, and social networks is more predictive of volunteering for nonreligious causes. In turn, we specifically aim to answer the following question: Do religious traditions and religious attendance vary in their influence on an individual’s likelihood of volunteering for social change?<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0899764012473385">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Using the 2005 wave of the Center on Philanthropy’s Panel Study data (COPPS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0899764012473385">Wilhelm, Brown, Rooney, &amp; Steinberg, 2005</xref>), a supplement to the Panel Study of Income Dynamics (PSID), we examine the effects of religious tradition (affiliation) and religious attendance on an individual’s likelihood of volunteering through social change nonprofit organizations. We find that adherents to the more liberal Christian denominations—mainline Protestant and Catholic—are more likely to volunteer for social change organizations than are Evangelicals. We also find that adherents to other minority religions (Jewish, Islam, Hindu, Buddhism, etc.) and individuals with no religious belief are all more likely to volunteer for social change organizations than are Evangelicals. While we find a positive and significant relationship between religious attendance and social change volunteering, we find a difference in the effect of religious attendance on social change volunteering only between Evangelicals and Catholics but not on other religious traditions.</p>
<p>The rest of the article is organized into four sections. We begin with a literature review of the effects of religious affiliation and religious attendance on people’s volunteer activities for social change from which we derive a number of specific hypotheses. We then discuss the data and methods. The third section presents results of our data analysis and a discussion of those findings. We conclude the article with a discussion of the theoretical and practical implications of the study.</p>
<sec id="section1-0899764012473385">
<title>Theory and Hypotheses</title>
<p>First, we make a distinction between volunteer activities for social change and other types of volunteer activities. For the purpose of this article, we find <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0899764012473385">Marullo and Edwards’ (2000)</xref> discussion of the difference between charity and social justice helpful. They wrote,
<disp-quote>
<p>Charity refers to the provision of help or relief to those in need. It consists of an individual or an institution acting voluntarily to transfer some of its resources (money, food, shelter, knowledge, labor, time, etc.) to an individual or group that has few resources. . . Social justice, on the other hand, refers to the state of institutional or structural arrangements in which there are no inequalities that are unjustifiable in terms of the greater social good or that are imposed unfairly. When one’s goal is social justice, one attempts to alter the structural or institutional practices that produce excessive or unjustified inequalities among individuals or that treat people unfairly—for example, discriminating among people on the basis of race, sex, social class, religion, nationality, ethnicity, sexual orientation, or disability status. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0899764012473385">Marullo &amp; Edwards, 2000</xref>, p. 899)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Although individuals may act alone in carrying out social change or social justice activities, most of them do so through nonprofit and voluntary organizations. In the political science literature, there has been a long tradition of research into the contribution of voluntary organizations to democratic governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0899764012473385">Berger &amp; Neuhaus, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0899764012473385">Putnam, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0899764012473385">Tocqueville, 1956</xref>). Since the middle of the 20th century, various American pluralist theorists have discussed the democratic role of voluntary associations by emphasizing their representational effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0899764012473385">Warren, 2001</xref>); that is, associations serve as a primary means of representing the interests of citizens and influencing public policy. Following this tradition, recent nonprofit studies have looked more closely at the role played by nonprofit organizations in influencing public policy and “facilitating the public voice that sustains a democratic civil society” through their advocacy and lobbying activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0899764012473385">Boris &amp; Mosher-Williams, 1998</xref>, p. 488; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0899764012473385">Child &amp; Gronbjerg, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0899764012473385">Guo &amp; Saxton, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0899764012473385">Jenkins, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0899764012473385">LeRoux &amp; Goerdel, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0899764012473385">Reid, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0899764012473385">Saidel, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0899764012473385">Suárez &amp; Hwang, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Among the various kinds of resources that nonprofits use in carrying out advocacy and lobbying activities, volunteers stand out as perhaps most important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0899764012473385">Saidel, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0899764012473385">Salamon, 1995</xref>). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0899764012473385">Salamon (1995)</xref> points out, much nonprofit advocacy activity is voluntary in nature, and “a greater proportion of voluntary activity is associated with higher levels of advocacy involvement” (p. 14; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0899764012473385">Saidel, 2002</xref>). In contrast to the growing scholarly interest in nonprofit advocacy, surprisingly little theoretical or empirical attention considers why and how individuals choose to volunteer with advocacy and social change organizations. Most of the existing research on volunteerism focuses on service-oriented volunteer activities, with little attention paid to social change volunteering.</p>
<p>Recent research on religion and volunteering has made important progress toward providing a more specific and sophisticated theoretical underpinning of the relationship between religious tradition, religious participation, and volunteering. The literature shows that religious values and participation in religious organizations promote volunteering (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0899764012473385">Musick &amp; Wilson, 2008</xref>). Here we discuss findings from that research to examine the effect of American religious traditions and religious attendance on volunteering in general and volunteering for social change in particular.</p>
<sec id="section2-0899764012473385">
<title>Religious Tradition and Volunteering for Social Change</title>
<p>Researchers have long recognized the effect of religiosity on volunteering. Although a consensus has yet to emerge, existing research findings suggest a positive relationship between the two (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0899764012473385">Greeley, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0899764012473385">Park &amp; Smith, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0899764012473385">Perks &amp; Haan, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Janoski, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Musick, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0899764012473385">Wuthnow, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0899764012473385">1999</xref>). Beyond this general observation, however, evidence finds systematic differences in volunteer behavior based on religious tradition, which is commonly proxied by denomination. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012473385">Steensland and colleagues (2000)</xref> develop a classification system that divides Americans who indicate a religious affiliation into six nominal religious traditions: Catholic, Black Protestant, Evangelical Protestant, Mainline Protestant, Jewish, and Other. This classification system captures essential differences between American religious traditions by considering “theological criteria derived from denominational creeds and associational criteria taken from denominational membership status in national religious organizations” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012473385">Steensland et al., 2000</xref>, p. 297).</p>
<p>Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012473385">Steensland and colleagues’(2000)</xref> classification system, we argue that individuals affiliated with more liberal Christian denominations such as mainline Protestant and Catholic are more likely to volunteer for social change organizations than are more conservative Christian denominations such as evangelical Protestant. In terms of theology, the more liberal Christian denominations maintain an external orientation and are associated with “social activism,” while the more conservative denominations maintain an internal theological orientation and focus more on “saving souls” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0899764012473385">Mock, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Janoski, 1995</xref>). In particular, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0899764012473385">Musick and Wilson (2008)</xref> discuss the key differences between mainline Protestants and Evangelicals and the reflection of such differences in volunteer work:
<disp-quote>
<p>In the nineteenth century, guided by a theology emphasizing progressive social betterment through public campaigns and legislation, [mainline Protestants] helped found many benevolent associations, such as the YMCA. In contrast, evangelical Protestant churches, which emerged at the beginning of the twentieth century, emphasized individual piety as the path to social betterment. Most of their “volunteer” work was targeted at improving the spiritual lives of their members and whomever they could convert to their cause. This denominational divide persists to this day. (p. 90)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>There is accumulating evidence that mainline Protestants and Catholics are more trusting of strangers, have public concerns, and are more likely to volunteer in other organizations and activities beyond their congregations. In contrast, evangelical Protestants are less trusting of others, are more likely to volunteer in church maintenance work of their congregations but less likely to be involved in the wider community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0899764012473385">Beyerlein &amp; Chaves, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0899764012473385">Beyerlein &amp; Hipp 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0899764012473385">Hoge, Zech, McNamara, &amp; Donahue, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0899764012473385">Putnam, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0899764012473385">Uslaner, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Janoski, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0899764012473385">Wuthnow, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0899764012473385">2002</xref>).</p>
<p>We further argue that Black Protestants are also more likely than evangelical Protestants to participate in civic engagement activities and social justice volunteering. The Black church has a long tradition of engagement with social and political issues in Black communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0899764012473385">Harris, 1994</xref>). During the 1950s and 1960s, the Black church played an important spiritual and political leadership role in the civil rights movement. Historically, the Black church was the center of activity in its community: “the church [acted] simultaneously as a school, a bank, a benevolent society, a political organization, a party hall, and a spiritual base” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0899764012473385">Pattillo-McCoy, 1998</xref>, p. 769). As such, the Black church provided a means of civic and political engagement for a socially marginalized constituency when it was excluded from broader political culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0899764012473385">Lincoln &amp; Mamiya, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0899764012473385">Loveland, Jones-Stater, &amp; Parker, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0899764012473385">Patillo-McCoy, 1998</xref>). With a “social gospel” orientation, the Black church encouraged members to volunteer for community building and political participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0899764012473385">Musick &amp; Wilson, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>We therefore offer the following hypotheses on religious affiliation and social change volunteering:</p>
<list id="list1-0899764012473385" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1a</italic>: Adherents to the more liberal Christian denominations—mainline Protestant and Catholic—are more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are Evangelicals.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1b</italic>: Black Protestants are more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are Evangelicals.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0899764012473385">
<title>Religious Attendance and Volunteering for Social Change</title>
<p>Local houses of worship such as churches, synagogues, and mosques function as an important form of mediating structures between individuals and “mega-structures” (i.e., government and large corporations), giving audible “voice” to individual concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0899764012473385">Berger &amp; Neuhaus, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0899764012473385">Bucholtz, 1998</xref>). At the individual level, the role of religious life in fostering social and political participation can be understood in the following ways. Church involvement helps generate social capital (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0899764012473385">Putnam, 1993</xref>) in the form of dense social networks, norms of generalized reciprocity, and generalized trust (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0899764012473385">Campbell &amp; Yonish, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0899764012473385">Jones, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012473385">Paik &amp; Navarre-Jackson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0899764012473385">Park &amp; Smith, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0899764012473385">Smidt, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Musick, 1997</xref>). The social networks accessed through their churches might draw individuals in public affairs. Church involvement also fosters the development of citizens’ political behaviors and attitudes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0899764012473385">Almond &amp; Verba, 1963</xref>) and “civil skills” such as letter writing and organizing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0899764012473385">Verba, Schlozman, &amp; Brady, 1995</xref>). In this sense, churches might serve as “schools of democracy” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0899764012473385">Tocqueville, 1956</xref>) where citizens gain a sense of efficacy, obtain relevant information, develop civic virtues, and learn political skills and critical skills (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0899764012473385">Warren, 2001</xref>, pp. 70-77). These civic virtues and skills might allow individuals to engage in other groups and the political process and thus promote volunteering for social change causes.</p>
<p>The rather limited body of research on the relationship between religious attendance and political engagement activities has produced mixed findings. On one hand, evidence suggests that religious attendance increases the likelihood of voting (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0899764012473385">Verba et al., 1995</xref>), memberships in voluntary associations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0899764012473385">Smidt, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0899764012473385">Wuthnow, 1999</xref>), and even the likelihood of engaging in disruptive political action such as protesting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0899764012473385">McVeigh &amp; Smith, 1999</xref>). Using data from the Independent Sector surveys, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0899764012473385">Musick and Wilson (2008</xref>, p.279) find that church attendance has a positive yet differentiated effect on various kinds of volunteer work. It does have a positive effect on environmental volunteering and political volunteering, both of which fit into our definition of social change volunteering; however, it has its most powerful effect on church-related volunteering.</p>
<p>On the other hand, some studies have shown negative or null results. For instance, in a study of secular volunteering and charitable giving in a sample of 800 Indiana residents, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0899764012473385">Jackson, Bachmeier, Wood, and Craft (1995)</xref> find no relationship between religious attendance and secular volunteering. Using data from Queen’s University’s 1996 “God and Society in North America” survey based on a representative sample of Canadian and American adults, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0899764012473385">Lam (2002)</xref> finds a negative relationship between religious attendance and voluntary association membership. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0899764012473385">Anderson (1996)</xref> finds that religious attendance has a negative effect on unconventional forms of political volunteering (e.g., picketing, demonstrating, participating in wildcat strikes, etc.), though it has a positive effect on more conventional forms of volunteer activities. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0899764012473385">Park and Smith (2000)</xref> find that, among churchgoing Protestants, higher levels of church attendance reduce the odds of volunteering for a non-church-related local community organization. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0899764012473385">Paik and Navarre-Jackson (2011)</xref> summarize the literature suggesting that higher levels of religious service attendance is correlated with specifically religious volunteering while engagement in church-related activities and organizations is more related to secular volunteering.</p>
<p>In sum, although findings are limited and mixed in terms of the effect of religious attendance on social change volunteering, there is theoretical and empirical evidence that suggests a positive relationship between the two. We thus propose that religious attendance has a positive effect on an individual’s decision to volunteer for social change causes.</p>
<list id="list2-0899764012473385" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: The frequency of religious attendance is associated with a higher likelihood of volunteering for social change.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0899764012473385">
<title>Interaction of Religious Affiliation and Religious Attendance</title>
<p>The impact of religious attendance on social change volunteering likely varies by religious tradition. Using data from the Social Capital Community Benchmark Survey, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0899764012473385">Loveland et al. (2008)</xref> find that the effect of religious participation (religious service attendance and congregational involvement beyond attendance) on civic engagement is not equivalent across the major U.S. religious traditions: congregation participation is positively associated with civic membership, but the degree of the relationship is moderated by religious tradition. Variation among religious traditions is strongest for people who nominally affiliate but do not frequently attend religious services; this variation declines as religious attendance increases.</p>
<p>Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0899764012473385">Beyerlein and Hipp (2006)</xref> argue that religious tradition moderates the extent to which religious participation channels bridging civic engagement (defined as participation in civic organizations that provide resources to those who are in need and establish other positive linkages with those in the wider community). Based on data from the American Citizen Participation Study survey, their findings show that religious service attendance has a greater effect on bridging civic engagement for Evangelicals than for Black Protestants, mainline Protestants, and Catholics. Put differently, an increase in religious service attendance tends to close the gap in bridging civic engagement between evangelical Protestants and members of the other religious traditions. They suggest that these differences might result from variation in congregation-based civic mobilization efforts for the different religious traditions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0899764012473385">Wuthnow (1999)</xref> finds that the positive effect of religious attendance on volunteering is stronger for mainline Protestants and Catholics than evangelical Protestants. The more frequently mainline Protestants and Catholics participate in congregations, the more likely they are to volunteer not only for religious organizations but also for organizations focused on improving communities; no such effects exist for evangelical Protestants.</p>
<p>Despite the discrepancies among the above studies, they all share the observation that the impact of religious attendance likely varies by religious tradition. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0899764012473385">Beyerlein and Hipp (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0899764012473385">Loveland et al. (2008)</xref>, we argue that the relationship between religious attendance and volunteering for social change is significantly moderated by religious tradition. More specifically, the frequency of religious service attendance has a greater effect on the likelihood of participation in social change activities for Evangelicals than for other more liberal Christian denominations. In other words, we expect the positive effect of religious service attendance on social change volunteering to be stronger for Evangelicals than for mainline Protestants, Black Protestants, and Catholics.</p>
<list id="list3-0899764012473385" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: The frequency of religious service attendance has a greater effect on the likelihood of social change volunteering for Evangelicals than for mainline Protestants, Black Protestants, and Catholics.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0899764012473385" sec-type="methods">
<title>Data and Method</title>
<p>This section describes the source of our data, specific measures, and our analytic approach.</p>
<sec id="section6-0899764012473385">
<title>Data Source</title>
<p>To estimate the effects of religious tradition and religious attendance on social change volunteering, we use the 2005 COPPS, which collects data on charitable giving and volunteering as a module added to the PSID. The COPPS elicits volunteering data based on the following survey question: “Now think about last year, January through December of 2004. Did you do any volunteer activity through organizations?” In addition, it collects data on volunteering through various types of organizations: religious organizations (i.e., churches, synagogues, or mosques); organizations for children and youth; organizations for senior citizens; organizations for people in poor health; organizations for people in need of basic necessities; organizations for social change; and others. We analyze volunteering behavior of heads of household focusing specifically on volunteering with social change organizations.</p>
<p>In addition to these key indicators, the data set contains demographic and religion information. Our sample is the 7,822 heads of households that comprise the 2005 COPPS. The observations are weighted to better approximate U.S. population data. Missing data resulted in a final sample of 7,674 heads of household.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0899764012473385">
<title>Variables</title>
<sec id="section8-0899764012473385">
<title>Dependent variables</title>
<p>We use two dummy variables: <italic>Whether Volunteered</italic> (whether an individual volunteered to any charitable organization in 2004), and <italic>Whether Volunteered for Social Change</italic> (whether an individual volunteered through organizations for social change in 2004). We also use two continuous variables: <italic>Hours Volunteered</italic> (the sum of an individual’s time donated to any charitable organization in 2004), and <italic>Hours Volunteered for Social Change</italic> (the sum of an individual’s time donated to organizations for social change in 2004).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0899764012473385">
<title>Independent variables</title>
<p>Following prior research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0899764012473385">Beyerlein &amp; Hipp, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012473385">Steensland et al., 2000</xref>), we first define an explanatory variable for religious tradition. We construct a dichotomous measure for each of the four major U.S. religious traditions: <italic>Black Protestantism, Mainline Protestantism, Evangelical Protestantism</italic>, and <italic>Catholicism</italic>. Using classification employed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0899764012473385">Steensland et al. (2000)</xref>, we partition denomination affiliations to make the above four variables. We construct a dummy—<italic>No Religion</italic>—for those individuals who stated they have no religion, and we combine other individuals in an <italic>Other Religion</italic> category (dummy variable) that includes any other religious affiliation such as Judaism and Buddhism.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0899764012473385">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0899764012473385">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>Our second explanatory variable measures another type of religious activity, <italic>Religious Attendance</italic>, which is defined as the frequency of an individual’s attendance at religious services during 2004.</p>
<p>Along with religious attendance, we examined the relationship between religious attendance and different religious traditions by constructing interaction terms between each religion category and frequency of attendance at religious services: <italic>Mainline</italic> × <italic>Attendance, Black Protestant</italic> × <italic>Attendance, Catholic</italic> × <italic>Attendance, Other Religion</italic> × <italic>Attendance</italic>, and <italic>No Religion</italic> × <italic>Attendance</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0899764012473385">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>We include demographic control variables found in past studies to be important predictors of volunteering, which we believe to be reasonably related to social change volunteering. We included measures of age and age-squared to account for our prediction that volunteering increases as age increases but at a decreasing rate.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0899764012473385">5</xref></sup> We also included dummy variables for whether the head of household is married, has children below the age of 5 living at home, is male or female, and attained at least a high school degree. We included a count of the number of children below age 18 currently living at home.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0899764012473385">6</xref></sup> Due to the high correlation between African American heads of household and heads affiliated with Black Protestant denominations (0.723), we left out the indicator of “being African American.” Finally, we included a measure of labor income.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0899764012473385">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0899764012473385">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Our unit of analysis is the head of household. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0899764012473385">Table 1</xref> presents definitions of the control variables.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0899764012473385" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Definitions of Control Variables</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0899764012473385" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012473385-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Definition</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>The age of the head of household</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex (female)</td>
<td>A binary variable that equals 1 if the household head’s sex is female; 0 otherwise</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Marital status (married)</td>
<td>A binary variable that equals 1 if the household head is married; 0 otherwise</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of children</td>
<td>Number of children below 18 years of age in the household</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Children younger than 5</td>
<td>A binary variable that equals 1 if the household has children younger than age 5; 0 otherwise</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education (≤ high school)</td>
<td>A binary variable that equals 1 if the household head has no more than a high school education; 0 otherwise</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Labor income</td>
<td>The sum of the household head’s and spouse’s labor income (e.g., wage, salaries, etc.)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0899764012473385">
<title>Analytic Approach</title>
<p>We analyze the effects of religion on the household head’s likelihood of volunteering for social change. Since the first two dependent measures—<italic>Whether Volunteered</italic> and <italic>Whether Volunteered for Social Change</italic>—are binary variables, we estimate our first set of models using logistic regression.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0899764012473385">9</xref></sup> Our next two dependent measures—Hours volunteered (ln) and Hours volunteered for Social Change Causes (ln)—are continuous, are truncated at zero, and include relatively large numbers of observed zeroes. Prior research has shown that charitable giving and volunteering data may have a nonnormal and heteroskedastic error structure (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0899764012473385">Rooney, Steinberg &amp; Schervish, 2004</xref>). Under these circumstances, Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) regression coefficients are biased and inconsistent. In line with the existing literature (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0899764012473385">Guo &amp; Peck, 2009</xref>), we estimate our second sets of models using Tobit, a censored regression technique.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0899764012473385">10</xref></sup> We specify both sets of models as follows:</p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0899764012473385">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0899764012473385">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0899764012473385" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012473385-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p>where</p>
<p><italic>Y</italic> is our outcome of interest (e.g., whether volunteered for social change);</p>
<p><italic>R</italic> is a vector of indicators of religiosity;</p>
<p><italic>Z</italic> is a vector of demographic controls;</p>
<p>ε is a random disturbance term; and</p>
<p>the subscript <italic>i</italic> indexes individuals.</p>
<p>We examine the sample of household heads in 2004, comparing those who volunteered for social change with those who volunteered for other causes.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0899764012473385">
<title>Findings</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0899764012473385">Table 2</xref> presents summary statistics for the overall sample. For ease of interpretation, we report the descriptive statistics of the variables in their original units in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0899764012473385">Table 2</xref>; our analyses use the natural log (<italic>ln</italic>) of <italic>Hours Volunteered, Hours Volunteered for Social Change</italic>, and <italic>Labor Income</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0899764012473385">11</xref></sup></p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0899764012473385" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Statistics, Overall Sample (Unweighted), 2004</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0899764012473385" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012473385-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Obs.</th>
<th align="center">Mean</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">Min.</th>
<th align="center">Max.</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Volunteering variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Volunteered, 2004</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Volunteered for social change, 2004</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hours volunteered</td>
<td>7,726</td>
<td>49.53</td>
<td>181.67</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3,276</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hours Volunteer for social change</td>
<td>7,736</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>27.00</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1,170</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Religion variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Religious attendance</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>46.60</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>780</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline Protestant</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black Protestant</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical Protestant</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other religion</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No religion</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Missing</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Control variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>44.6</td>
<td>15.8</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sex (female)</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.30</td>
<td>0.46</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Number of children</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Children below age 5</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Education (≤ high school)</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>0.32</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Labor income</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>46,930</td>
<td>72,166</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2,810,000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0899764012473385">
<p>Note: Religious categories do not sum to 100% due to rounding.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0899764012473385">Table 2</xref>, 27% of the household heads volunteered for any charitable cause while about 3% of heads volunteered with social change organizations in 2004. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0899764012473385">Table 3</xref> presents the summary statistics for the sample and two subgroups: those who volunteered and those who volunteered through social change organizations.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0899764012473385" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Statistics, by Subgroups (Unweighted), 2004</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0899764012473385" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012473385-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Sample</th>
<th align="center">Volunteered</th>
<th align="center">Volunteered for social change organizations</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Sample size</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>2,048</td>
<td>215</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Religion variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Religious attendance (times) per year</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>33.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mainline Protestant (%)</td>
<td>12.4</td>
<td>16.0</td>
<td>17.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black Protestant (%)</td>
<td>21.4</td>
<td>17.3</td>
<td>14.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Evangelical Protestant (%)</td>
<td>24.1</td>
<td>28.5</td>
<td>18.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Catholic (%)</td>
<td>18.4</td>
<td>17.2</td>
<td>17.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other religion (%)</td>
<td>8.4</td>
<td>7.8</td>
<td>11.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No religion (%)</td>
<td>12.4</td>
<td>10.3</td>
<td>16.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Missing religion (%)</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>4.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Demographic variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>44.6</td>
<td>45.1</td>
<td>45.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sex (female) (%)</td>
<td>30.2</td>
<td>30.7</td>
<td>35.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married (%)</td>
<td>50.4</td>
<td>56.5</td>
<td>46.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Number of children</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>0.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Children below 5 (%)</td>
<td>6.5</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>5.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Education (≤ high school)</td>
<td>32.5</td>
<td>26.2</td>
<td>18.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Labor income</td>
<td>46,930</td>
<td>58,992</td>
<td>61,261</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Comparing the columns of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0899764012473385">Table 3</xref>, one observes that heads of household who do not volunteer attend religious services on average 29 times a year; heads who volunteer for any cause attend an average of 46 times a year, and heads who volunteer for social change attend an average of 33 times a year.</p>
<p>Mainline Protestants make up 12.4% of the sample, but make up 16% of heads who volunteer and 17.7% of heads who volunteer for social change. Somewhat similarly, those who state an “other” religion make up 8.4% of the sample, 7.8% of heads who volunteer, and 11.6% of heads who volunteer for change. Conversely, Black Protestants make up 21.4% of the sample, but only 17.3% of heads who volunteer and 14.4% of heads who volunteer for social change. Catholics make up approximately the same percentage of each category: 18.4% for the sample, 17.2% of heads who volunteer, and 17.2% of heads who volunteer for social change. Interestingly, evangelical Protestants, who make up 24.1% of the sample, make up 28.5% of those who volunteer. However, they make up only 18.1% of those heads who volunteer for social change. Finally, those who state no religion make up 12.4% of the sample, 10.3% of heads who volunteer, and 16.3% of heads who volunteer for social change.</p>
<p>Heads who volunteer are slightly older (45.1 years of age) than the average head (44.6) and slightly younger than the average head who volunteers for social change (45.4). Female heads make up approximately 30% of the sample, 31% of the subsample of heads who volunteer are female, and 35% of heads who volunteer for social change are female. Approximately 50% of the heads in the sample are married, whereas nearly 57% of heads who volunteer are married. Only 46% of heads who volunteer for social change are married. The average number of children for all heads is 0.86; in the volunteering subsample, it is 0.96, and for heads in the social change subsample, it falls to 0.63. Heads with children below age 5 make up 6.5% of the entire sample, 4.3% of the heads who volunteer and 5.1% of heads who volunteer for social change.</p>
<p>Education and income vary widely among the average head and heads who volunteer, both for all causes and for social change. In the sample, 32.5% have no high school degree and average family income is US$46,930. Among heads who volunteer, 26.2% did not finish high school and average income is US$58,992. Heads who volunteer for social change tend to be well educated and better paid: only 18.1% did not finish high school and average income is US$61,261.</p>
<p>In sum, without controlling for the effects of demographic variables, heads who volunteer for social change are more likely to be mainline Protestants or of “other” or no religious affiliation and are likely to attend religious services more often than the average head of household. In addition, heads who volunteer for social change are more likely to be (a bit) older, female, unmarried, better educated, better paid, and have fewer children than the average head.</p>
<p>We now turn to our multivariate analyses to examine the effect of the religiosity and control variables on volunteering for social change.</p>
<sec id="section12-0899764012473385">
<title>Multivariate Analyses</title>
<sec id="section13-0899764012473385">
<title>Logistic regression analyses</title>
<p>Our first two dependent measures—<italic>Whether Volunteered</italic> and <italic>Whether Volunteered for Social Change</italic>—are binary variables, so we estimate our first set of models using logistic regression. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0899764012473385">Table 4</xref> summarizes the results of our logistic regression analyses. We first present the logistic regression results in relation to the head’s propensity to volunteer in general (Models 1 and 2) and then to volunteer for social change causes (Models 3 and 4). Odds ratios (ORs) estimate the strength of the association between variables of interest and report the ratio of the odds of an event occurring in one group to the odds of it occurring in another group. For example, if the odds ratio equals two, then the odds of an event occurring in one group are twice the odds of the event occurring in the other group. An odds ratio of one indicates that there is no statistically significant difference between the reference category, Evangelicals, and the comparison group. An odds ratio greater than one indicates that the comparison group has higher odds of volunteering for social change causes, while an odds ratio of less than one indicates that the comparison group has lower odds of volunteering for social change causes than the reference category.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0899764012473385" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistics Regressions, Weighted</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0899764012473385" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012473385-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">(1)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">(2)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">(3)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">(4)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Volunteering, no interaction<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Volunteering, interaction between religion and attendance<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Social change volunteering, no interaction<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Social change volunteering, interaction between religion and attendance<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Variables</th>
<th align="center">Odds ratios</th>
<th align="center">Odds ratios</th>
<th align="center">Odds ratios</th>
<th align="center">Odds ratios</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Religious attendance</td>
<td>1.011<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.014<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.001</td>
<td>1.005<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.002)</td>
<td>(0.001)</td>
<td>(0.001)</td>
<td>(0.002)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mainline Protestant</td>
<td>1.403<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.159</td>
<td>2.011<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>2.302<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.146)</td>
<td>(0.165)</td>
<td>(0.534)</td>
<td>(0.696)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mainline × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>1.011<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>0.998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Black Protestant</td>
<td>0.650<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.832</td>
<td>1.044</td>
<td>1.136</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.091)</td>
<td>(0.172)</td>
<td>(0.411)</td>
<td>(0.496)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Black × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>0.994</td>
<td/>
<td>0.998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Catholic</td>
<td>0.839<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td>1.119</td>
<td>1.718<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>2.394<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.085)</td>
<td>(0.143)</td>
<td>(0.455)</td>
<td>(0.721)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Catholic × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>0.992<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>0.990<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.003)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other religion</td>
<td>0.971</td>
<td>1.121</td>
<td>2.592<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>3.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.128)</td>
<td>(0.172)</td>
<td>(0.769)</td>
<td>(0.955)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>0.996</td>
<td/>
<td>0.998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No religion</td>
<td>1.101</td>
<td>1.245<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td>2.745<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>3.289<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.136)</td>
<td>(0.165)</td>
<td>(0.740)</td>
<td>(0.966)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">No Religion × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>0.996</td>
<td/>
<td>0.996</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.03)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>1.016</td>
<td>1.019</td>
<td>1.066<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>1.066<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.013)</td>
<td>(0.013)</td>
<td>(0.033)</td>
<td>(0.033)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age squared</td>
<td>1.000</td>
<td>1.000</td>
<td>0.999<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>0.999<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex (female)</td>
<td>1.570<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.536<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.662<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td>1.650<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.174)</td>
<td>(0.170)</td>
<td>(0.434)</td>
<td>(0.429)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Married</td>
<td>1.435<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.404<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.047</td>
<td>1.028</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.145)</td>
<td>(0.141)</td>
<td>(0.268)</td>
<td>(0.263)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of children</td>
<td>1.076<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>1.071<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>0.685<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.682<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.033)</td>
<td>(0.033)</td>
<td>(0.064)</td>
<td>(0.0642)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Children below 5</td>
<td>0.568<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.573<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.956</td>
<td>0.972</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.086)</td>
<td>(0.087)</td>
<td>(0.356)</td>
<td>(0.362)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Education (≤ high school)</td>
<td>0.620<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.621<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.495<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.490<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.111)</td>
<td>(0.109)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Labor income</td>
<td>1.061<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.061<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.039</td>
<td>1.040</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.013)</td>
<td>(0.014)</td>
<td>(0.035)</td>
<td>(0.035)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>0.092<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.080<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.003<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.028)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>7,674</td>
<td>7,674</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0899764012473385">
<p>Note: Robust errors in parentheses.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0899764012473385">
<label>*</label>
<p>p &lt; .1. **p &lt; .05. ***p &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Hypothesis 1 examines the effect of religious tradition on an individual’s propensity to volunteer for social change causes. We predict that adherents to the more liberal Christian denominations—mainline Protestant and Catholic—are more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are evangelical Protestants (the reference group). Consistent with our prediction, our results indicate that mainline Protestants and Catholics are more likely to volunteer for social change causes. More specifically, mainline Protestants are more likely than Evangelicals to volunteer in general and volunteer for social change in particular. The odds of volunteering to any cause among mainline Protestants are estimated to be 1.4 times the odds of volunteering among Evangelicals. (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0899764012473385">Table 4</xref>, Model 1: odds ratio of 1.403, significant at 1%. All findings, below, are presented as odds ratio, significance.) The odds of social change volunteering among mainline Protestants are estimated to be twice the odds of social change volunteering among Evangelicals (Model 3: 2.011, 1%; Model 4: 2.302, 1%). Catholics, however, are less likely than Evangelicals to volunteer in general but more likely to volunteer for social change in particular. The odds of volunteering to any cause among Catholics are 0.8 times the odds of volunteering among Evangelicals (Model 1: 0.839, 5%). The odds of social change volunteering among Catholics are 1.7 to 2.4 times the odds of social change volunteering for Evangelicals (Model 3: 1.718, 5%; Model 4: 2.394, 1%).</p>
<p>We also predict that Black Protestants are more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are Evangelicals. The results do not support our prediction. The odds of volunteering among Black Protestants are estimated to be 0.6 times the odds of volunteering among Evangelicals (Model 1: 0.650, 1%). The odds of social change volunteering among Black Protestants are not significantly different from the odds of social change volunteering among Evangelicals.</p>
<p>We find that the odds of evangelical Protestants volunteering and the odds of those with no religious or a minority religion (“other”) affiliation are not statistically different. Yet interestingly, those with no or “other” religious affiliation have much greater odds of volunteering for social change. The odds of social change volunteering among those with no religious affiliation are 2.7 to 3.3 times the odds of social change volunteering among Evangelicals (Model 3: 2.745, 1%; Model 4: 3.289, 1%). Similarly, the odds of social change volunteering among those with “other” religious affiliation are 2.6 to 3 times the odds of social change volunteering among the reference group (Model 3: 2.592, 1%; Model 4: 3.000, 1%).</p>
<p>Hypothesis 2 examines the effect of religious participation on an individual’s propensity to volunteer for social change causes. We predict that the frequency of religious attendance is positively associated with the likelihood of volunteering for social change. Consistent with our prediction, the analyses show that the odds of volunteering among those who attend religious services are slightly greater than the odds of volunteering among all heads (Model 1: 1.011, 1%; Model 2: 1.014, 1%). Similarly, the odds of social change volunteering among those who attend religious services are also slightly greater than the odds of volunteering among all heads (Model 4: 1.005, 1%).</p>
<p>Hypothesis 3 examines the moderating role of religious tradition in the relationship between religious attendance and social change volunteering. We predict that the frequency of religious attendance has a greater effect on the likelihood of social change volunteering for Evangelicals than for mainline Protestants, Black Protestants, and Catholics. In other words, we expect a negative interaction effect of religious attendance and religious tradition on social change volunteering. Our results provide little support to our prediction. Among the four interaction terms, only “Catholic × Attendance” is significant and negative, showing that attendance has a greater effect on the likelihood of social change volunteering for Evangelicals than Catholics.</p>
<p>Findings associated with the control variables are in line with our prior expectations. <italic>Sex</italic>: The odds of volunteering among women heads of household are estimated to be nearly 1.6 times the odds of volunteering among male heads, in general, and for social change organizations (Model 1: 1.570, 1%; Model 3: 1.662, 10%). <italic>Education</italic>: The odds of volunteering among those who completed high school are approximately 1.6 times the odds of volunteering among those who did not attain a high school degree (Model 1, 1/0.62 = 1.613, 1%). Similarly, the odds of volunteering for social change organizations among heads who graduated from high school are twice the odds of volunteering for social change among heads who did not graduate (Model 3, 1/0.49 = 2.02, 1%). <italic>Age</italic>: The analyses show that age has no effect on volunteering in general but it does have a curvilinear effect on social change volunteering (Model 3 Age, 1.066, 5%; Age squared: 0.999, 5%). The results imply that for every 1-year increase in age, the odds of volunteering for social change increase with age up to a point then begin to decrease with age. <italic>Marital status</italic>: The odds of married heads of household volunteering are 1.4 times the odds that unmarried heads volunteer (Model 1: 1.435, 1%; Model 2: 1.404, 1%). The odds of married heads volunteering for social change are not statistically different from the odds for unmarried heads. <italic>Number of children below 18 living at home</italic>: The odds of volunteering increase by a factor of 1.1 with each additional child living at home (Model 1: 1.076, 5%; Model 2: 1.071, 5%). Interestingly, the opposite is true for social change volunteering: additional children living at home decreases the odds of the head volunteering decrease by a factor of 1.5 for each additional child (Model 3, 1/0.685 = 1.460, 1%). <italic>Children below age 5</italic>: The odds of the head volunteering among families with young children at home (below age 5) are estimated to be about half the odds of volunteering among families with no young children (Model 1: 0.568, 1%; Model 2: 0.573, 1%). The odds of volunteering for social change are not significantly different among households with and without young children. <italic>Labor income</italic>: labor income seems to matter for volunteering but not for volunteering for social change causes. The odds of volunteering increase by a factor of 1.01 for a one-unit change in log income (1.061, 1%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0899764012473385">
<title>Tobit regression analyses</title>
<p>For our next two dependent measures—Hours volunteered (ln) and Hours volunteered for Social Change Causes (ln), we estimate our models using Tobit regression. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0899764012473385">Table 5</xref> summarizes the results of our Tobit regression analyses, based on the weighted sample. We first present the Tobit results in relation to the head’s hours volunteered for any charitable organization (Models 5 and 6), and then to hours volunteered for social change causes (Models 7 and 8). Because Tobit coefficients are not directly interpretable, we report the mean (regression-adjusted) dependent variable and marginal effects (evaluated at the explanatory variables’ mean values and reported in parentheses) to judge the relative importance and size of estimated effects.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0899764012473385" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Tobit Results, Weighted</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0899764012473385" xlink:href="10.1177_0899764012473385-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">(5)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">(6)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">(7)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">(8)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="center">Parameter estimate (Marginal effect), no interaction</th>
<th align="center">Parameter estimate (Marginal effect), interaction between religion and attendance</th>
<th align="center">Parameter estimate (Marginal effect), no interaction</th>
<th align="center">Parameter estimate (Marginal effect), interaction between religion and attendance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Religious attendance</td>
<td>0.028<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>0.020<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mainline Protestant</td>
<td>0.835<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.733<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td>2.201<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>2.693<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.302)</td>
<td>(0.388)</td>
<td>(0.872)</td>
<td>(1.039)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Mainline × attendance</td>
<td>0.014</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.016)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Black Protestant</td>
<td>−1.289<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.622</td>
<td>−0.050</td>
<td>0.335</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.426)</td>
<td>(0.582)</td>
<td>(1.246)</td>
<td>(1.432)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Black × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.015</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.010)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.012)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Catholic</td>
<td>−0.695<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>0.333</td>
<td>2.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>3.165<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.295)</td>
<td>(0.346)</td>
<td>(0.831)</td>
<td>(0.966)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Catholic × Attendance</td>
<td>−0.025<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−0.033<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.014)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other religion</td>
<td>−0.256</td>
<td>0.267</td>
<td>3.432<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>4.020<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.387)</td>
<td>(0.441)</td>
<td>(0.973)</td>
<td>(1.083)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other × Attendance</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td/>
<td>−0.011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.017)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No religion</td>
<td>0.0610</td>
<td>0.576</td>
<td>3.373<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>4.044<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.356)</td>
<td>(0.384)</td>
<td>(0.901)</td>
<td>(1.007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">No Religion × Attendance</td>
<td>−0.010<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−0.016</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td/>
<td>(0.017)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>0.055</td>
<td>0.0517</td>
<td>0.167<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td>0.165<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.038)</td>
<td>(0.038)</td>
<td>(0.099)</td>
<td>(0.099)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age squared</td>
<td>−0.000</td>
<td>−0.000</td>
<td>−0.002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.001)</td>
<td>(0.001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex (female)</td>
<td>1.477<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.394<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>2.139<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>2.101<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.329)</td>
<td>(0.320)</td>
<td>(0.830)</td>
<td>(0.823)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Married</td>
<td>1.205<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>1.076<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.625</td>
<td>0.564</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.308)</td>
<td>(0.299)</td>
<td>(0.837)</td>
<td>(0.835)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of children</td>
<td>0.226<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>0.212<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">**</xref></td>
<td>−1.389<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−1.398<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.092)</td>
<td>(0.091)</td>
<td>(0.299)</td>
<td>(0.300)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Children below 5</td>
<td>−1.673<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−1.618<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−1.062</td>
<td>−0.988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.458)</td>
<td>(0.456)</td>
<td>(1.383)</td>
<td>(1.389)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education (≤ HS)</td>
<td>−1.473<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−1.490<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−2.153<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−2.180<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.224)</td>
<td>(0.223)</td>
<td>(0.681)</td>
<td>(0.679)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Labor income</td>
<td>0.155<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.156<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>0.110</td>
<td>0.111</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.106)</td>
<td>(0.106)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−7.032<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−7.366<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−20.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
<td>−20.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0899764012473385">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.898)</td>
<td>(0.892)</td>
<td>(2.369)</td>
<td>(2.392)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>7,648</td>
<td>7,648</td>
<td>7,657</td>
<td>7,657</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0899764012473385">
<p>Note: The marginal effect (dy/dx) is reported in parentheses.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0899764012473385">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .1. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Of central interest here are the effects of religious affiliation and religious attendance variables. The Tobit results are generally consistent with the Logistic results presented in the previous section: Religious attendance is positively and significantly associated with both overall volunteer hours and hours volunteered for social change causes in all models except in Model (7; positive but not significant). Religious tradition matters: in particular, identifying as mainline Protestant is positively associated with both overall volunteer hours and hours volunteered for social change causes, but identifying as Catholic is negatively associated with volunteering in general and positively with social change volunteering. Identifying as “other religion” or “no religion” is not associated with overall volunteer hours, but it is positively associated with hours volunteered for social change causes. Again, the only interaction term with significance is “Catholic × Attendance.”</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0899764012473385" sec-type="discussion |conclusions">
<title>Discussion and Conclusions</title>
<p>In this study, we used the 2005 wave of the COPPS supplement to the PSID to examine the effect of religion on people’s volunteer activities in social change organizations. This article makes several significant contributions to the existing literatures. First, it fills an important void in the volunteerism literature by focusing on volunteering for social change causes. In the past few decades, extensive research has been dedicated to understanding the antecedents, correlates, and consequences of volunteering (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0899764012473385">Smith, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0899764012473385">Wilson, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0899764012473385">Wilson &amp; Musick, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0899764012473385">1999</xref>). Despite its theoretical and empirical contributions, this body of research is preoccupied with service-oriented volunteer work, paying only passing attention to volunteer work related to changing “the system.” Our findings suggest that advocacy-oriented volunteers might differ from service-oriented volunteers in some important ways and thus highlight the need for additional research.</p>
<p>Second, and related to the first, this study adds to the existing literature on the relationship between religion and volunteering. Our findings indicate that religious affiliation and religious attendance influence not only the <italic>levels</italic> but also the <italic>types</italic> of volunteer efforts. More specifically, some religious traditions might have a stronger impact on social change volunteering than others. We find that adherents to the more liberal Christian denominations—mainline Protestant and Catholic—are more likely to volunteer with social change organizations than are Evangelicals; they also tend to volunteer more hours. Adherents to other minority religions (Jewish, Islam, Hindu, Buddhism, etc.) and individuals with no religious belief are also more likely to volunteer with social change organizations—and tend to volunteer more hours—than are Evangelicals. We find a positive relationship between religious attendance and social change volunteering, but we find little difference in the effect of attendance on social change volunteering between Evangelicals and each tradition (except for Catholics).</p>
<p>The findings and nonfindings on the attendance–tradition interactions deserve further attention. The significant Catholics interaction effect indicates that the frequency of religious attendance has a greater effect on the likelihood of social change volunteering for Evangelicals than for Catholics. This finding echoes prior research, which shows that frequent church attendance does not increase the volunteer rate of Catholics as much as it does Protestants in general and Evangelicals in particular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0899764012473385">Bowen, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0899764012473385">Musick &amp; Wilson, 2008</xref>, p. 280). Perhaps this is because the Catholic Church, with its emphasis on collective identity and participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0899764012473385">Greeley, 2000</xref>), discourages individual voluntary action toward social change; or perhaps the Catholic Church offers fewer outlets for social change volunteering to its adherents. Yet the insignificant mainline Protestant and Black Protestant interaction effects suggest that outlets for social change volunteering do not differ across Protestant traditions so that increased religious attendance does not increase exposure to opportunities differently by tradition. Further research is needed in this area.</p>
<p>This study also contributes to the growing body of literature on nonprofit advocacy. Much of this emerging research has mainly focused on organizational-level analysis (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0899764012473385">Berry &amp; Arons, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0899764012473385">Boris &amp; Mosher-Williams, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0899764012473385">Child &amp; Gronbjerg, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0899764012473385">Guo &amp; Saxton, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0899764012473385">LeRoux &amp; Goerdel, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0899764012473385">Saidel, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0899764012473385">Suárez &amp; Hwang, 2008</xref>), while individual-level analysis of staff and volunteers who are the “life-blood” of nonprofit advocacy activities has been largely ignored (for an exception, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0899764012473385">Kunreuther, 2003</xref>). In view of an increasing reliance of nonprofit advocacy organizations on professional staff, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0899764012473385">Jenkins (2006</xref>, p. 308) reminds us that “[p]rofessionalized advocacy is a weak substitute for broader civic engagement.” The use of volunteers to carry out advocacy activities provides a means to sustain the organization with direct participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0899764012473385">Jenkins, 2006</xref>) and to ensure that it represents an accurate voice for its constituents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0899764012473385">Guo, 2007</xref>). Yet, to effectively involve volunteers in nonprofit advocacy, it is imperative that we obtain a better understanding of those individuals who are willing to contribute their time and skills to advocacy activities and the various factors that influence their decision to get involved.</p>
<p>Finally, we note an important limitation of our study. The limitation lies in the definition and use of the concept of “volunteering for social change causes.” Following COPPS, we define volunteering for social change causes as volunteering through organizations to bring about social change (e.g., civic or community action, working for a political party or advocacy group, etc.). This is a rather narrow specification because volunteering for social change causes certainly occurs via other venues: for instance, volunteers may participate in advocacy activities with religious organizations or charitable organizations, whose primary purpose is not advocacy. Moreover, there are much more divisive forms of volunteering such as taking part in a protest, a march, sit-in, hunger strike, writing letters, etc. There are also different levels of volunteering in any organization. In addition, since our study used the 2005 data, we cannot capture more recent developments in citizen participation for social change inspired by the campaign of Barack Obama and the subsequent reaction of the Tea Party and the Occupy Wall Street protests. While our study serves as a good start, future studies along this line of research could further explore the nuances of how various religious traditions affect an individual’s propensity to participate in different forms and levels of political actions and social change activities.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>We would like to thank Morgan Marietta, Charlotte Ren, Keely Jones-Stater, and Mark Wilhelm for valuable comments and suggestions. Thanks also go to the agencies that fund the Panel Study of Income Dynamics (PSID), Atlantic Philanthropies for funding the collection of data in the first three waves of the Center on Philanthropy Panel Study (COPPS), and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation for funding the 2007 and 2009 data collection of the Center Panel as well as the dissemination of the 2005 data.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>We presented earlier versions of this article at the 2008 and 2009 annual meetings of the Association for Research on Nonprofit Organizations and Voluntary Action.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0899764012473385">
<label>1.</label>
<p>For the purpose of this study, we define “volunteering for social change” as the donation of time to organizations for social change (e.g., civic or community action, political parties, advocacy groups, etc.). As noted later in the article, this definition is consistent with the definition provided by the Center on Philanthropy Panel Study (COPPS), though it is a rather narrow definition in that it excludes volunteering for social change causes via other venues such as religious organizations whose primary purpose is not advocacy or social change.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0899764012473385">
<label>2.</label>
<p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0899764012473385">Beyerlein and Hipp (2006</xref>, p. 103) note, “the heterogeneity of this [other] measure rendered it substantively meaningless. However, including it allowed a direct comparison of the effects of the four major U.S. religious traditions.” Beyerlein and Hipp combined individuals with “other” religions with those who stated no religious affiliation. We believe “other” should be a separate category distinguishing those who do state a nondominant religious affiliation from those who state no affiliation.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0899764012473385">
<label>3.</label>
<p>We also tested models including dummy variables for Jewish and other separate religious groups. Because there are such a small number of observations for each group, we did not find any significant effects. The main results of our models were not affected by the exclusion of these variables.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0899764012473385">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Note that we include an interaction term “No Religion × Attendance.” The average number of times of attendance for those who claim no religious affiliation is 10.72 although the median is 0. Our interpretation is that some of those who do not claim a religion might go with a partner or on a holiday. The reference category was evangelical, so we left out an interaction term of “Evangelical × Attendance.”</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0899764012473385">
<label>5.</label>
<p>We controlled for both “age” and “age squared” to account for a possible curvilinear effect of age due to physical infirmity among the elderly. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0899764012473385">Campbell and Yonish (2003)</xref> note that “[i]t is probable that while there is a generally monotonic increase in volunteering as someone ages, volunteering falls off sharply for the elderly as they become less physically able to perform volunteer work” (n14, p. 233).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0899764012473385">
<label>6.</label>
<p>We examined interaction terms between sex of head and children below 5, sex and high school attainment, sex and religious affiliation, married/single heads with children below 5 and married/single heads and high school attainment. These variables added no explanatory value and the results of our models were not affected by their exclusion.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0899764012473385">
<label>7.</label>
<p>We also used each head’s reported wealth, not including home value. We tested the variable’s contribution to the set of independent variables and found that the variable does not add significant explanatory power to the model. It is also fairly highly correlated with labor income.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0899764012473385">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Other variables used in past studies included health of the head of household (“good,” “fair,” etc.), heads who live in urban or rural areas, and length of time at current residence, all trying to control for circumstances that may affect volunteering. These variables added no explanatory value and the results of our models were not affected by their exclusion.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0899764012473385">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Logit choice models (logit, logistic, etc.) estimate the probability that an individual (head of household) volunteered. We chose logistic because we can assume a nonlinear relationship among dependent and independent variables, and because we have a dichotomous dependent variable. Thus our model uses the independent variables to build a model of the probability of choice. Note that COPPS data come from a survey where each family has a weighted value to better represent the U.S. population as a whole. We ran logistics regressions using weights and survey procedures in STATA.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0899764012473385">
<label>10.</label>
<p>It should be noted that, while Tobit accommodates the large number of zeroes in the dependent variable, it is not robust to either nonnormality or heteroskedasticity. However, a recent study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0899764012473385">Wilhelm (2006)</xref> provides support for using Tobit with this particular data, arguing that despite rejection of the underlying assumptions of Tobit at higher levels of statistical significance, the Tobit estimates are numerically close to more robust methods.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0899764012473385">
<label>11.</label>
<p>The value of the variable was adjusted by adding an arbitrary but small constant (1) to zero values so that the logged values are zero as appropriate for our analysis.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Chao Guo</bold> is an associate professor and director of International Programs at Indiana University School of Public &amp; Environmental Affairs, IUPUI. His research interests focus on the intersection between nonprofit and voluntary action and government. More specifically, he conducts research on representation in nonprofit organizations, nonprofit advocacy, nonprofit governance, collaboration within and across sectors, social entrepreneurship, and volunteerism.</p>
<p><bold>Natalie J. Webb</bold> is an associate professor of economics in the Defense Resources Management Institute at the Naval Postgraduate School. She conducts research on nonprofit, defense and other applied economics topics and management issues.</p>
<p><bold>Rikki Abzug</bold> is a professor of management at the Anisfield School of Business, Ramapo College of NJ. She conducts research on management and administration issues, nonprofit and nongovernmental organizations, and human resources.</p>
<p><bold>Laura R. Peck</bold> is a principal scientist in the Social &amp; Economic Policy Division at Abt Associated Inc. Prior to joining Abt in 2011, she was a tenured associate professor in the School of Public Affairs at Arizona State University. Her research focuses on the effects of U.S. social policy on the well-being of children and families, and on research methods and program evaluation.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Almond</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>). <source>The civic culture: Political attitudes and democracy in five nations</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Political action and social integration</article-title>. <source>American Politics Quarterly</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <source>To empower people: The role of mediating structures in public policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Enterprise Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arons</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>A voice for nonprofits</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institution</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beyerlein</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The political activities of religious congregations in the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beyerlein</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hipp</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>From pews to participation: The effect of congregation activity and context on bridging civic engagement</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Borgonovi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Divided we stand, united we fall: Religious pluralism, giving, and volunteering</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boris</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mosher-Williams</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Nonprofit advocacy organizations: Assessing the definitions, classifications, and data</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>488</fpage>-<lpage>506</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Religion, participation, and charitable giving</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Ontario</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Canadian Centre for Philanthropy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bucholtz</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Reflections on the role of nonprofit associations in a representative democracy</article-title>. <source>Cornell Journal of Law &amp; Public Policy</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>555</fpage>-<lpage>603</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Bureau of Labor Statistics</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Volunteering in the United States, 2009</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/news.release/volun.nr0.htm">http://www.bls.gov/news.release/volun.nr0.htm</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yonish</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Religion and volunteering in America</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Religion as social capital: Producing the common good</source> (pp. <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Waco, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Baylor University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Child</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gronbjerg</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Nonprofit advocacy organizations: Their characteristics and activities</article-title>. <source>Social Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cnaan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dickin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Estimating giving and volunteering: New ways to measure the phenomena</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>-<lpage>525</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greeley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The other civic America: Religion and social capital</article-title>. <source>American Prospect</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greeley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>The Catholic imagination</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>When government becomes the principal philanthropist: The effect of public funding on patterns of nonprofit governance</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>-<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Giving and getting: Charitable activity and welfare receipt</article-title>. <source>Administration &amp; Society</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>600</fpage>-<lpage>627</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saxton</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Voice-in, voice-out: Constituent participation and nonprofit advocacy</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit Policy Forum</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), Article 5. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bepress.com/npf/vol1/iss1/5">http://www.bepress.com/npf/vol1/iss1/5</ext-link>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/2154-3348.1000</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Something within: Religion as a mobilizer of African American political activism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Politics</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zech</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The value of volunteers as resources for congregations</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>470</fpage>-<lpage>481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bachmeier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Volunteering and charitable giving: Do religious and associational ties promote helping behavior?</article-title> <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Nonprofit organizations and political advocacy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The nonprofit sector: A research handbook</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Giving and volunteering as distinctive forms of civic engagement: The role of community integration and personal resources in formal helping</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kunreuther</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The changing of the guard: What generational differences tell us about social-change organizations</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>450</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P.-Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>As the flocks gather: How religion affects voluntary association participation</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>-<lpage>422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LeRoux</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goerdel</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Political advocacy by nonprofit organizations: A strategic management explanation</article-title>. <source>Public Performance &amp; Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>514</fpage>-<lpage>536</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mamiya</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. <source>The black church in the African-American experience</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loveland</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones-Stater</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Religion and the logic of the civic sphere: Religious tradition, religious practice, and voluntary association</article-title>. <source>Interdisciplinary Journal of Research on Religion</source>, <volume>4</volume>, Article 7.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marullo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>From charity to justice: The potential of university-community collaboration for social change</article-title>. <source>American Behavioral Scientist</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>895</fpage>-<lpage>912</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McVeigh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Who protests in America: An analysis of three political alternatives—Inaction, institutionalized politics, or protest</article-title>. <source>Sociological Forum</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>685</fpage>-<lpage>703</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Congregational religious styles and orientation to society: Exploring our linear assumptions</article-title>. <source>Review of Religious Research</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Musick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Volunteers: A social profile</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Navarre-Jackson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Social networks, recruitment, and volunteering: Are social capital effects conditional on recruitment?</article-title> <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>476</fpage>-<lpage>496</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>“To whom much has been given . . .”: Religious capital and community voluntarism among churchgoing Protestants</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pattillo-McCoy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Church culture as a strategy of action in the black community</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>-<lpage>784</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perks</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Youth religious involvement and adult community participation: Do levels of youth religious involvement matter?</article-title> <source>Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Pew Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life</collab>. (<year>2007</year>). <source>Religious composition of the U.S.: U.S. Religious Landscape Survey</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/affiliations-all-traditions.pdf">http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/affiliations-all-traditions.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Making democracy work: Civic traditions in modern Italy</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Bowling alone: America’s declining social capital</article-title>. <source>Journal of Democracy</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Nonprofit advocacy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Boris</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steuerle</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Nonprofits and government: Conflict or collaboration?</source> (pp. <fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Urban Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Understanding the word “advocacy”: Context and use</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Structuring the inquiry into advocacy</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Urban Policy Institute</publisher-name>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.urban.org/pdfs/structuring.pdf">http://www.urban.org/pdfs/structuring.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schervish</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Methodology is destiny: The effect of survey prompts on reported levels of giving and volunteering</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>628</fpage>-<lpage>654</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saidel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Nonprofit organizations, political engagement, and public policy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montilla</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Exploring organizations and advocacy</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Urban Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salamon</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>, <month>March</month>). <source>Explaining nonprofit advocacy: An exploratory analysis</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the Independent Sector Spring Research Forum</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Alexandria, VA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Religion and civic engagement: A comparative analysis</article-title>. <source>ANNALS, AAPSS</source>, <volume>565</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Determinants of voluntary association participation and volunteering: A literature review</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Religious diversity in America: The emergence of Muslims, Buddhists, Hindus, and Others</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>577</fpage>-<lpage>585</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steensland</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Regnerus</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woodberry</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The measure of American religion: Toward improving the state of the art</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suárez</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Civic engagement and nonprofit lobbying in California, 1998-2003</article-title>. <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tocqueville</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1956</year>). <source>Democracy in America</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New American Library</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Uslaner</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Religion and civic engagement in Canada and the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schlozman</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Voice and equality: Civic voluntarism in American politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Democracy and association</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abzug</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Do occupational group members vary in volunteering activity?</article-title> <source>Nonprofit &amp; Voluntary Sector Quarterly</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>-<lpage>708</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Practical considerations for choosing between Tobit and SLCS or CLAD estimators for censored regression models with an application to charitable giving</article-title>. <source>Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>559</fpage>-<lpage>582</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The center on philanthropy panel study</source> [machine-readable data file]/Director and Principal Investigator, Mark O. Wilhelm; Coprincipal Investigators, Eleanor Brown, Patrick M. Rooney, and Richard Steinberg; Sponsored by Atlantic Philanthropies. In the <italic>Panel Study of Income Dynamics Wave XXXIV</italic> [machine-readable data file]/Director and Principal Investigator, Frank P. Stafford; Associate Director and Principal Investigator Robert F. Schoeni; Co-Principal Investigators, Jacquelynne S. Eccles, Katherine McGonagle, Wei-Jun Jean Yeung, and Robert B. Wallace. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute for Social Research, The University of Michigan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Volunteering</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janoski</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The contribution of religion to volunteer work</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Religion</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Musick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Who cares? Toward an integrated theory of volunteer work</article-title>. <source>American Sociology Review</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>694</fpage>-<lpage>713</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Musick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The effects of volunteering on the volunteer</article-title>. <source>Law &amp; Contemporary Problems</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wuthnow</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Acts of compassion</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wuthnow</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Mobilizing civic engagement: The changing impact of religious involvement</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fiorina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skocpol</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Civic engagement in American democracy</source> (pp. <fpage>331</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0899764012473385">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wuthnow</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Beyond quiet influence? Possibilities for the Protestant Mainline</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wuthnow</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). <source>The quiet hand of God: Faith-based activism and the public role of mainline Protestantism</source> (pp. <fpage>381</fpage>-<lpage>403</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>