<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Discourse Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1461-4456</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7080</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1461445613480588</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1461445613480588</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An exploration of interactive metadiscourse markers in academic research article abstracts in two disciplines</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Khedri</surname><given-names>Mohsen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>Chan Swee</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>Seyed Foad</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1461445613480588">Universiti Putra Malaysia, Malaysia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1461445613480588">Mohsen Khedri, Faculty of Modern Languages and Communication, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 43400, UPM Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia. Email: <email>khedri295@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>319</fpage>
<lpage>331</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A generic analysis of research article abstracts can cover issues of different types; among them are linguistic features. An integral part of linguistic features of research article abstracts is interactive metadiscourse usage that can assist to make the text persuasive and unfolding to a discourse community. The main principle behind applying interactive metadiscourse is the view of writing as socially engaging; specifically, it indicates the ways writers project themselves into their arguments to declare their attitudes and commitments to the readers. This study aimed to explore how interactive metadiscourse markers are deployed by research article abstract writers belonging to different disciplinary communities within the soft sciences, while trying to reach the audience by creating a well-organized discourse. Hyland’s (2005) interpersonal model of metadiscourse was adopted to analyze 60 research article abstracts written in Applied Linguistics and Economics. Based on the results, there were marked variations found across the two disciplines in terms of interactive metadiscourse markers.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Genre</kwd>
<kwd>interactive metadiscourse markers</kwd>
<kwd>linguistic features</kwd>
<kwd>metadiscourse</kwd>
<kwd>research article abstracts</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1461445613480588" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The abstract serves as the point of departure of most research articles and has progressively become a pivotal part in the writing of the research article. It is the first section to be read and, as opined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1461445613480588">Pho (2008</xref>: 231), it more or less ‘sells’ the article. Very few journals would not entail an abstract forwarded along with the main research article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1461445613480588">Martin-Martin, 2003</xref>). To illustrate the importance of the communicative appeal of an abstract, many journals publishing in languages other than English also see the need to append an English version of the abstract as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1461445613480588">Lorés, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1461445613480588">Ventola, 1994</xref>). Faced with information explosion in the world, members in each academic research community have become more and more reliant upon abstracts to enable them to be updated. In view of its importance, abstract writing skills are therefore essential, especially to novice research article writers who are seeking entry into the discourse community of their fields of knowledge.</p>
<p>A discussion of competent abstract writing can begin with the American National Standards Institute’s (ANSI) definition of an abstract, which is ‘an abbreviated, accurate representation of the contents of a document, preferably prepared by its author(s) for publication with it’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1461445613480588">1979</xref>: 1). Complementing the definition is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1461445613480588">Huckin’s (2006</xref>: 93) elaboration on its functions, which characterizes the abstracts as ‘Stand-alone mini-texts’; ‘Screening devices’; ‘Previews’; and ‘Aids to indexing’. Through the first function, abstracts provide readers with a quick summary of topic, method and results of a work. The second helps readers to decide on whether they wish to read the entire article, focusing especially on the body for the thrust of the information. The third function shapes an interpretive scheme which guides the reading process. Finally, through the fourth function, abstracts assist indexing for large database services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1461445613480588">Huckin, 2006</xref>) to facilitate information access.</p>
<p>In addition, a research article abstract (hereafter, RA abstract), as part of an article, acts as a ‘time-saving device’, allowing readers to decide on whether the whole article is worth reading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1461445613480588">Martin-Martin, 2003</xref>: 26). Owing to the competitive nature of doing and publishing research, RA abstracts serve also as a means of advertising to readers about the research carried out, thus encouraging readers to pursue the reading of the entire article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1461445613480588">Dahl, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1461445613480588">Hyland, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1461445613480588">Hyland and Tse, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1461445613480588">Lindeberg, 2004</xref>). This has implications on broadening the possibility of citation as an added value in research dissemination of results and impact.</p>
<p>Due to the versatile significance of an RA abstract, research focus on it has been captured by a number of genre analysts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1461445613480588">Ghadessy, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1461445613480588">Gillaerts and Van de Velde, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1461445613480588">Hu and Cao, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1461445613480588">Huckin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1461445613480588">Hyland and Tse, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1461445613480588">Lorés, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1461445613480588">Martin-Martin, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1461445613480588">Pho, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1461445613480588">Samraj, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1461445613480588">Santos, 1996</xref>). Some researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1461445613480588">Berkenkotter and Huckin, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1461445613480588">Lindeberg, 2004</xref>) believe that the abstract, as a specific genre in academic contexts, is fast gaining significance and prominence as a subject for investigation since it is replete with much potential for analysis. Among the different features investigated are the use of interactional linguistic features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1461445613480588">Hyland, 2000</xref>) which include metadiscourse. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1461445613480588">Graetz (1985)</xref> states that, more than 20 years ago, this to a great extent underlined the salience of comprehending of journal abstracts. He postulates that if readers are able to distinguish the various functions of linguistic features of an abstract (which include that of metadiscourse), they are then given a clear direction of message intention and this would enable readers (and writers as well) to contribute their own opinions in a more effective way.</p>
<p>On another plane, metadiscourse can be regarded as ‘self-reflective linguistic expressions referring to the evolving text, to the writer and to the imagined readers of that text’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1461445613480588">Hyland, 2004</xref>: 133). As such, metadiscourse markers also have a social function in communication which contributes to the effective dissemination of knowledge in a discipline; however, owing to the divergent nature of disciplines, metadiscourse usage is expected to be varied and distinctive across disciplines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445613480588">Hyland, 2005</xref>: 143). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1461445613480588">Crismore et al. (1993)</xref> have highlighted, metadiscoursal features equip writers to be able to make judgment about what they write and convince audiences about the significance of the position adopted in the abstract and conveyed in the whole study.</p>
<p>Thus far, some scholars have given much insight into the status of interactional metadiscourse in RA abstracts; for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1461445613480588">Gillaerts and Van de Velde (2010)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1461445613480588">Hu and Cao (2011)</xref> scrutinized the essence of two interactional metadiscourse markers – hedges and boosters – in RA abstracts written by applied linguists, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1461445613480588">Lindeberg (2004)</xref> explored the same metadiscourse markers not only in RA abstracts, but also in other rhetorical sections of articles in three business fields. Beyond these cited works, to our knowledge, little is known about the status of interactive metadiscourse markers (henceforth IMMs) in RA abstracts. Thus, this study seeks to plug the gap, to some extent, by investigating a wide range of IMMs and to situate their use in different disciplinary structures. It is hypothesized that discipline has a role to play in the use of IMMs. Therefore, cross-disciplinary study on IMMs in RA abstracts could offer insights into the application of metadiscourse as a persuasive tool possibly in different ways and, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1461445613480588">Garcia-Calvo’s (2002)</xref> statement, this could lead to greater awareness of how abstracts can be written more effectively according to disciplinary needs. A major aim of the present research is to accentuate the possible similarities and differences across disciplinary communities in terms of how discourse members deploy IMMs to facilitate knowledge construction in their own fields. Within the confines of this study, two disciplines are arbitrarily chosen: Applied Linguistics (AL) and Economics (Eco). Both, based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1461445613480588">Becher’s (1989)</xref> taxonomy of disciplines, belong to the category of soft sciences. AL is chosen primarily because the researchers are English as a second language (ESL) teachers who teach writing, which includes technical writing of this nature and, as with AL, Eco represents an area which falls within soft sciences. Moreover, quite a few studies have focused on the comparison of soft sciences with AL as representative of soft sciences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1461445613480588">Hyland, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1461445613480588">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1461445613480588">Khedri et al., in press</xref>). Thus, the present comparison ventures into another dimension of exploring cross-disciplinary genre features within a particular field of sciences (soft) as stated. Overall, the following research questions are addressed to form the purpose of our study:</p>
<list id="list1-1461445613480588" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>What are the types of IMMs used in RA abstracts in AL and Eco?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Is there a significant difference between the two disciplines in focus with regards to the manifestation of IMMs?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1461445613480588" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-1461445613480588">
<title>The corpus</title>
<p>The corpus of this comparative and contrastive research consists of 60 RA abstracts. The details of the corpus are as follows:</p>
<list id="list2-1461445613480588" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Discipline</italic>: Applied Linguistics and Economics.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Number of RA abstracts</italic>: sixty RA abstracts were selected (30 from each discipline).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Year of publication</italic>: all articles from which the abstracts were extracted were published between 2000 and 2011.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Journal</italic>: after consulting with informants in each discipline and asking them to nominate highly prestigious leading journals, AL abstracts were sourced from <italic>Journal of Pragmatics</italic> and <italic>English for Specific Purposes</italic>, and all Eco abstracts were taken from <italic>Oxford Economic Papers</italic>.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Following the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1461445613480588">Grabe (1987)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1461445613480588">Paltridge (1996)</xref>, the corpus selection was based on three criteria: genre, English for specific purposes (ESP) and text type. RA abstracts qualify as a genre on its own satisfying the first criterion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1461445613480588">Dahl, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1461445613480588">Hyland, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1461445613480588">Lorés, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1461445613480588">Samraj, 2005</xref>). To meet the second, RA abstracts from the two disciplines are ESP in character. Lastly, to meet the third criterion, this study focused on the abstract section of RAs as a text type which contains peculiar linguistic features, as discussed earlier. The initial details of the RA abstract corpus are summed up in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1461445613480588">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1461445613480588" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Description of RA abstract corpus.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1461445613480588" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445613480588-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Applied linguistics sub-corpus</th>
<th align="left">Economics sub-corpus</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>No. of RA abstracts</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of journals from which abstracts were taken</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of RA abstracts taken from each journal</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Length of RA abstracts (range)</td>
<td>98–270</td>
<td>78–150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total number of words of RA abstracts</td>
<td>5372</td>
<td>3643</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total number of tokens</td>
<td>288</td>
<td>159</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1461445613480588">
<title>The analytical categories</title>
<p>Based on the taxonomy of metadiscourse provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445613480588">Hyland (2005)</xref>, the five IMMs <italic>transition markers, endophoric markers, frame markers, evidentials</italic> and <italic>code glosses</italic> built the categories for analysis. Each marker and its functions are explained below accompanied by examples obtained from the corpus. Illustrations of the IMMs are italicized.</p>
<p>As defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445613480588">Hyland (2005)</xref>, transition markers refer to conjunctions and adverbial phrases that aid readers to make pragmatic connections between stages in discourse development and they can be functionally interpreted. Such metadiscoursal features could project additive, consequential or contrastive connections between ideas. Transition markers are characterized through lexical constructions, such as <italic>and, furthermore, equally, in the same way, thus, therefore, however</italic> and <italic>in contrast</italic>.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 1</bold></p>
<p>The attempt <italic>also</italic> led to a new classification of metadiscourse <italic>and</italic> added two new metadiscourse strategies of collapsers and disclaimers. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 2</bold></p>
<p><italic>However</italic>, my model includes two periods, with demand growth between periods. [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The second category of IMMs, endophoric markers, relates to expressions which signal the connection of information presented in the different parts of the text. These markers equip readers with extra propositional content to assist them to better grasp writers’ preferred meanings. <italic>See Figure 2, refer to the next section</italic> and <italic>as noted above</italic> are illustrations of endophoric markers. Other examples include:
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 3</bold></p>
<p><italic>In the discussion section</italic>, we try to arrive at an explanation for the changes that have occurred . . . . [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 4</bold></p>
<p>The goal of <italic>this paper</italic> is to assess the impact of the euro on the relationship between firm size and exports. [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Through the use of frame markers, the next category analyzed, writers indicate the text boundaries through labeling, sequencing, announcing and altering the direction of arguments so as to clarify the propositional content for readers. Some linguistic resources that writers can utilize as indicators of the schematic structure of a text are: <italic>First, then, next, 1/2</italic> and <italic>a/b</italic>, etc., are sequencers; <italic>to summarize, in sum</italic> and <italic>by way of introduction</italic> are labels; <italic>I argue here, my purpose is, the paper proposes, I hope to persuade</italic> and <italic>there are several reasons why</italic> are discourse goals announcer; and <italic>well, right, OK, now</italic> and <italic>let us return to</italic> serve as signals to topic shifts. The following are examples of actual use.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 5</bold></p>
<p><italic>The second</italic> point is that the use of interactional metadiscourse in abstracts has undergone interesting changes . . . . [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 6</bold></p>
<p>The paper <italic>first</italic> shows that gains from growth between 1995 and 2003 were much smaller for…; it <italic>then</italic> shows that . . . . [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Concerning evidentials, the fourth category, these are linguistic expressions which represent ideas taken from sources out of the text. These markers help writers build up the authorial command of the subject and support their positioning. One worthy point of evidentials is their contribution to the achieving of a persuasive goal. Evidentials require the writer to state an attitude and also take responsibility for the position taken. Evidentials are exemplified by expressions such as <italic>X states that . . .</italic> and <italic>according to</italic>. Text examples are:
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 7</bold></p>
<p>Building on <italic>previous research</italic> that suggests notable cross-cultural and cross-linguistic differences in . . . . [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 8</bold></p>
<p>However, <italic>recent contributions</italic> have shown that the effects on home economies are rarely negative. [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The final category is code glosses, which are markers that provide extra information to pave the way for readers to be acquainted with the writers’ preferred meanings. Writers could convey meaning by describing, elaborating, paraphrasing and restating their aforementioned arguments, using phrases that include <italic>this is called, such as, in other words, that is, this can be defined as</italic> and <italic>for example</italic>, or resorting to punctuation marks such as <italic>parentheses</italic> and <italic>comma</italic> as found in:
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 9</bold></p>
<p>Two statistical measures <italic>such as</italic> UNANOVA and Matched T-Test were run. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 10</bold></p>
<p>We then explore welfare effects of ownership restrictions imposed by a developing country (<italic>the South</italic>) with . . . . [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1461445613480588">
<title>The analytical procedure</title>
<p>This study is mainly quantitative in approach and the analysis is based on comparison and contrast of the selected RA abstracts from the perspective of IMMs. In the case of text analysis commenced metadiscursively, there is a common belief among scholars that metadiscourse is an inborn fuzzy and functional category. Lexicogrammatical features which serve as metadiscourse can be multifunctional and context dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1461445613480588">Ädel, 2006</xref>). Such multifunctionality and context-dependency imply that metadiscursive elements can be considered not strictly as a linguistic feature, but also as a pragmatic and rhetorical feature with socio-contextual meaning. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445613480588">Hyland (2005)</xref> opines, metadiscourse is a relative notion in which textual devices solely act as metadiscourse concerning another part of the text. Thus, what may be regarded as metadiscourse in a particular context may serve the function of propositional information in another. That is why the need arises to explicate the strategies applied by writers in creating metadiscourse elements at specific points in their arguments. In the current research, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445613480588">Hyland’s (2005)</xref> taxonomy is relied on for a rigorous analysis of IMMs, taking in particular the functional meaning into account.</p>
<p>To this end, the current research was carried out through the following steps. First, all the selected RA abstracts were either obtained directly from the electronic versions of the relevant journals or were manually scanned and then converted into Rich Text format for computer storage. Next, a word count was run on them. All the data were then traversed in search of IMMs electronically through the use of MonoConc Pro, a text analysis and concordance program. The tokens of the five categories of IMMs were carefully analyzed individually and manually, based on the context in which they occur, in order to be certain about their functions as metadiscourse. Finally, to control length variation and also to allow comparison across corpora of unequal size, the number of metadiscourse elements was computed per 1000 words.</p>
<p>Furthermore, to counter the threat of unreliability and misinterpretation in the analysis and to have concordance on the method of analysis, obtained data from a small subset of the corpus – 10 RA abstracts (five from each discipline) – was subject to a double blind review by two experts in applied linguistics.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1461445613480588" sec-type="results|discussion">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<p>In order to identify the possible similarities and variations in the distribution of the five categories of IMMs in AL and Eco abstracts, the frequency of IMMs in each category was computed per 1000 words. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445613480588">Table 2</xref> reports on the distribution of IMMs in the disciplines concerned. A closer look at the findings revealed that the IMMs were most commonly used by applied linguists. Based on figures illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445613480588">Table 2</xref>, there was an overall similarity between AL and Eco abstracts in regards to the hierarchy of occurrence of IMMs. Transition markers acted as the leading category, with a total of 94 tokens (17.49 per 1000 words) in AL and 84 tokens (23.05 per 1000 words) in Eco, respectively. The second most frequent category was code glosses (66 cases or 12.28 per 1000 words in AL, and 32 cases or 8.78 per 1000 words in Eco). This is followed by endophoric markers as the third most used category. These were used 56 times (10.42 per 1000 words) by applied linguists and 21 times (5.76 per 1000 words) by economists. Frame markers were placed in the fourth position in the two disciplines, totaling 50 cases (9.30 per 1000 words) found in the corpus of AL and only 12 cases (3.29 per 1000 words) in Eco. Finally, it was found that amongst the IMMs, evidentials had the lowest frequency of use not only in AL (22 tokens or 4.09 per 1000 words), but also in Eco (10 tokens or 2.47 per 1000 words). The detailed status of each category in the two disciplines and the communicative purposes they fulfill are discussed below.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1461445613480588" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Frequency analysis of IMMs in each discipline per 1000 words.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1461445613480588" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445613480588-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">AL<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Eco<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Raw no.</th>
<th align="left">Freq. (per 1000 words)</th>
<th align="left">Raw no.</th>
<th align="left">Freq. (per 1000 words)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Transition markers</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>17.49</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>23.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Endophoric markers</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>10.42</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>5.76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frame markers</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>9.30</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Evidentials</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>4.09</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Code glosses</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>12.28</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>8.78</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>One of the common features of academic discourse is the high use of transition markers, signaling the need for making internal cognitive connection in discourse. Based on figures illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445613480588">Table 2</xref>, it was found that there is a significant difference between the two disciplines in the case of how RA abstract writers organize their argumentations using transition markers to guide readers to their intended proposition. Concerning the frequency rate, results revealed that economists showed a greater inclination towards the use of transitive devices. Such a disposition among economists indicated their concerns about aiding audiences to interpret and grasp their claims with least ambiguity. This might also reflect the more discursive nature of RA abstracts written in Eco and a greater reliance on a more explicit crafting of a cohesive and persuasive argumentation.</p>
<p>Transition markers were deployed to serve the shared communicative purposes in both AL and Eco, which were to: a) add propositional information given (example 11); b) inform readers that a conclusion has been portrayed or justified (example 12); and c) signal the similarity or difference of arguments (example 13). Even though Eco and AL abstract writers mapped transition markers in an identical way for communicative or discursive purposes, they acted differently. As data analysis showed, the majority of transition markers used in RA abstracts written by applied linguists were enacted to ease cognitive relations between information chunks using <italic>and, also</italic> and <italic>as well as</italic>. On the other hand, economists preferred signals that indicate logical relations as revealed in the use of comparative devices; the most used were <italic>however</italic> and <italic>but</italic>.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 11</bold></p>
<p>The interpersonal categories were <italic>also</italic> broken down into subtypes depending on the linguistic items used, <italic>and</italic> analyzed for distribution in the conclusion sections. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 12</bold></p>
<p><italic>In consequence</italic>, the firm distorts production by its employees with low ability, or it excludes workers with low ability and a high propensity for social comparisons. [Eco]</p>
<p><bold>Example 13</bold></p>
<p>The use of e-commerce does nothing to boost entry into export markets, <italic>but</italic> the intensity of its use is associated with increased export intensity. [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Endophoric markers acted as the second leading category in both corpora. The possible explanation for such a preference in both disciplinary communities may be due to their emergence from the category of soft sciences (based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1461445613480588">Becher’s 1989</xref> taxonomy). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445613480588">Hyland (2005)</xref> also remarked that the use of endophoric markers in soft disciplines, to a larger extent, is a means of reinforcing discourse to consciously enable readers to have immediate and quick access to relevant information found between parts of the text. As data analysis clarified, the communicative purposes of this kind of IMMs, as used by applied linguists and economists, were somewhat the same. Both groups of writers appealed to endophoric markers while introducing their study (example 14), applied experimental procedure (example 15) and interpreted their obtained results (example 16). It is obvious that they did so to relate readers to descriptive materials found in different parts of the text, and in particular could assist readers to relate to the main body of the RA more easily (in terms of the study’s purpose, the methodology and the findings).</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 14</bold></p>
<p>…, <italic>this paper</italic> analyses the stability of fiscal rules for EMU countries before and after the Maastricht Treaty. [Eco]</p>
<p><bold>Example 15</bold></p>
<p>Three groups of students were selected to participate in <italic>the study</italic>. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 16</bold></p>
<p><italic>The results of the study</italic> revealed differences in the manifestation, number and type of explicit evaluations in the abstracts belonging to different disciplines in the field of the humanities, social and natural sciences. [AL]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Besides the found similarities, it was disclosed that there are strong differences between two disciplinary communities regarding the manifestation of endophoric markers. Despite the major use of endophoric markers in both corpora to introduce the study, AL abstract writers, compared to their counterparts in Eco, applied endophoric markers more frequently, particularly when they saw the need to build a trial to connect details about the nature and process of their works. It may be one of the applied linguists’ disciplinary propensities to be inclined to connect propositional information to readers’ implicit knowledge so as to facilitate a smooth engagement with the text and to enable readers to accept the propositions.</p>
<p>Another dominant feature in our corpus refers to the narrowing and repetition of endophoric expressions such as <italic>this study, this paper, this research</italic> and <italic>this article</italic>. Such a tendency may be rooted in the nature of RA abstracts themselves, which in essence function as a device that focuses on economy of words in order to save the reading time and that facilitates the abstract as a stand-alone compact text. RA abstracts having these characteristics may rule out the use of other forms of endophoric markers that serve to refer readers to propositional content given in different parts of the text, namely, <italic>see Figure 2, as noted above</italic> and <italic>this will be described in the next section</italic>.</p>
<p>Results also indicated that frame markers mapped in the two disciplines were quite different from each other. The manifested variations show that applied linguists had a strong preference in the use of frame markers to mark text boundaries to show discourse organization and the manner of unfolding the discourse. They did so through three discursive strategies: 1) sequencing devices (example 17); 2) announcing discourse goals (example 18); and 3) shifting in topic (example 19). Economists, on the other hand, had a functional propensity mostly towards sequencing ideational information with the aid of frame markers (example 20). The different ways of framing are shown below:
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 17</bold></p>
<p>The study came to significant findings: (<italic>1</italic>) More DMs meant better comprehension. (<italic>2</italic>) Levels of proficiency did not display clashing results when dealing with a fewer number of DMs. (<italic>3</italic>) Manipulation of the passages was significant. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 18</bold></p>
<p>…, this study <italic>aims to</italic> identify which metadiscourse categories predominate in this type of newspaper discourse and how they are distributed according to cross-cultural or cross-linguistic preferences. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 19</bold></p>
<p><italic>Regarding</italic> the persuasive effect of metadiscourse, informants were in agreement that a balanced number of both textual and interpersonal markers was necessary to render the text persuasive and reader-oriented. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 20</bold></p>
<p>The paper <italic>first</italic> shows that gains from growth between 1995 and 2003 were much smaller for the (near) landless than for the landed; it <italic>then</italic> shows that . . . . [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>As for evidentials, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445613480588">Table 2</xref> shows that both AL and Eco abstract writers were quite reliant upon citing researchers’ works to detail the relationship between their own study and previously conducted studies. Such a shared disposition may refer to the nature of both disciplines as representatives of the same soft science. To <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1461445613480588">Becher (1989)</xref>, evidentials are more substantial in the discourses of these disciplines where issues are more detached from the immediately prior developments and are less reliant upon a single line of text development. This is supported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1461445613480588">Hyland (2004)</xref>, who reiterates that the main reason behind the prominence of evidentials in soft disciplines is the avoiding of mitigating strong certainty in claim-making. Unlike hard sciences, soft sciences research is less based on rigorous standards to support claims. The avoidance is likely to reveal the presence of a greater subjectivity in argument as divergent opinions are common in soft sciences. As found in the data, writers of both groups exercised the choice of appealing to greater use of evidential resources and citations in order to: a) signal reasonable and convincible foundation for their claims (example 21); b) make their works outstanding by announcing the extant gap in the literature (example 22); c) project and secure their new contribution based on the frameworks developed by evidentials (example 23); as well as d) compare and contrast their new findings with earlier studies (example 24).</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 21</bold></p>
<p>Conventional wisdom on abstracts has strongly supported by the guidelines provided by international abstracting standards (<italic>American National Standards for Writing Abstracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1461445613480588">1979</xref>) New York: American Standards Institute</italic>). [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 22</bold></p>
<p><italic>Although several studies</italic> have tried to describe the distribution and nature of metadiscourse marking across disciplines and languages, no systematic attempt was made, to our knowledge, to introduce a practical model that presumably guides the users in the real time of writing. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 23</bold></p>
<p>The construct of theme (<italic>Halliday, 1994; Halliday &amp; Matthiessen, 2004</italic>) as a structure crucial for rhetorical unfolding of texts is used to examine these changes. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 24</bold> This result contradicts <italic>the previous findings of Galí and Perotti</italic>. [Eco]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Finally, code glosses, as with evidentials, were used by both groups of writers. The writers helped readers uncover the preferred meanings by predicting readers’ existing knowledge and by giving additional information to facilitate the desired interpretation. Data analysis demonstrated that both AL and Eco abstract writers supplied additional information in their texts mainly via reformulating aforementioned ideational meanings by using punctuation marks, among which are <italic>parenthesis</italic> and <italic>comma</italic> (example 25) and lexical items such as <italic>especially, that is</italic> and <italic>namely</italic> (example 26). Apart from the use of such code glosses, another set of lexical features like <italic>e.g., i.e., such as</italic> and <italic>including</italic>, termed as ‘exemplification markers’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1461445613480588">Hyland, 2007</xref>), were evident to expand on the notion of code glosses (example 27). In addition it could be said that ensuring readers grasp writers’ preferred meanings is one of the propensities and conventions established in both communities which, as results showed, both applied linguists and economists were aware of.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><bold>Example 25</bold></p>
<p>Two institutional arrangements are considered, control rights lying either with the firm or the government (<italic>traditional procurement</italic>). [Eco]</p>
<p><bold>Example 26</bold></p>
<p>Although research articles (RAs) have been frequently characterized by impersonal language, which entails the use of nominalizations and passive sentences, self mentions, <italic>that is</italic>, explicit references to the RA author(s), are found to intermingle with those impersonal constructions. [AL]</p>
<p><bold>Example 27</bold></p>
<p>It aims at analyzing to what extent the different contexts, <italic>i.e.</italic> the US international and the Spanish national, influence the strategic use of metadiscourse features in this discipline. [AL]</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In all, as results indicated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445613480588">Table 2</xref>), though all IMM categories were found in both corpora, their frequency of use was more pronounced in the AL corpus. This could suggest that applied linguists felt more keenly the need to clarify their action in claim making and to avoid any unsustainable interpretations of fuzzy concepts so as to minimize miscommunication.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1461445613480588" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In this study, it was observed that some textual practices were manifested differently across the two selected disciplinary communities in IMMs. This suggests that each disciplinary community within the broad domain of the soft sciences has social authorization and contextual restriction for metadiscoursal occurrence. The data obtained reveal in concrete terms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1461445613480588">Hyland’s (2004)</xref> claim that the significance of metadiscursive elements as textual devices lies in their close relation with the contexts in which they are realized and with the public aims, norms and conventions of specific professional discourse communities as well.</p>
<p>Here, we portrayed a cross-disciplinary picture of metadiscourse in academic writing accentuating IMMs in RA abstracts. No doubt, there were operating confines that limited generalization of the results. For one, the corpus was small and limited to only two disciplines in a large array of the soft science disciplines. In addition, the current research leaned towards a quantitative approach and this could be moderated by more qualitative investigation to cast greater light on IMMs.</p>
<p>It is, however, maintained that the reported findings have specific value to abstract writing, especially for AL and Eco which, in their own right, have wide academic readership. In view of this, the writers should be informed of characteristics, conventions and discursive strategies for best practices. Additionally, the analyses serve to illustrate the preferences of the discourse communities evidenced through peer-reviewed publications in the fields. A final point made is the strong presence of social communication grounded in IMMs in a genre of academic writing, in which writers should have the knowledge and awareness of how devices could be used to orientate readers to the appropriate and formal intended research message.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Mohsen Khedri</bold> is a PhD candidate in Applied Comparative Linguistics, Universiti Putra Malaysia (UPM), Malaysia. His main areas of research are genre analysis and discourse studies such as metadiscourse and thematicity. To date, he has published several articles in various internationally refereed journals worldwide.</p>
<p><bold>Chan Swee Heng</bold> works at Department of English Language, Faculty of Modern Languages and Communication, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Malaysia.</p>
<p><bold>Seyed Foad Ebrahimi</bold> is a PhD candidate in Applied Comparative Linguistics, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Malaysia.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ädel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Metadiscourse in L1 and L2 English</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American National Standards Institute (ANSI)</collab> (<year>1979</year>) <source>The American National Standard for Writing Abstracts</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ANSI Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Becher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Academic Tribes and Territories: Intellectual Inquiry and the Cultures of Disciplines</source>. <publisher-loc>Milton Keynes</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berkenkotter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huckin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Genre Knowledge in Disciplinary Communication: Cognition/Culture/Power</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crismore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markkanen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steffensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Metadiscourse in persuasive writing: A study of texts written by American and Finnish university students</article-title>. <source>Written Communication</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Some characteristics of argumentative abstracts</article-title>. <source>Akademisk Prosa</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Author identity in economics and linguistics abstracts</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Suomela-Salmi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dervin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Cross-linguistic and Cross-cultural Perspectives on Academic Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garcia-Calvo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Use of metadiscourse in research article abstracts for scientific events</article-title>. <source>Revista Letras Curitiba</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ghadessy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Thematic organization in academic article abstracts</article-title>. <source>Estudios Ingleses de la Universidad Complutense</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillaerts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van de Velde</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Interactional metadiscourse in research article abstracts</article-title>. <source>Journal of English for Academic Purposes</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grabe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Contrastive rhetoric and text type research</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ulla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Writing across Languages: Analysis of L2 Texts</source>. <publisher-loc>Redwood, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Addison-Wesley</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graetz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Teaching EFL students to extract structural information from abstracts</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ulijn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Reading for Professional Purposes: Studies and Practices in Native and Foreign Languages</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann Educational Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Hedging and boosting in abstracts of applied linguistics articles: A comparative study of English- and Chinese-medium journals</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pragmatics</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>2795</fpage>–<lpage>2809</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huckin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Abstracting from abstracts</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hewings</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Academic Writing in Context: Implications and Applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Birmingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Birmingham University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Persuasion and context: The pragmatics of metadiscourse</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pragmatics</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Disciplinary Discourses: Social Interactions in Academic Writing</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Education Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Humble servants of the disciplines? Self-mention in research articles</article-title>. <source>English for Specific Purposes</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Disciplinary interactions: Metadiscourse in L2 postgraduate writing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Second Language Writing</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Metadiscourse: Exploring Interaction in Writing</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Continuum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Applying a gloss: Exemplifying and reformulating in academic discourse</article-title>. <source>Applied Linguistics</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Hooking the reader: A corpus study of evaluative <italic>that</italic> in abstracts</article-title>. <source>English for Specific Purposes</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khedri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>in press</year>) <article-title>Patterning of interactive metadiscourse markers in result and discussion sections of academic research articles across disciplines</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social Sciences and Humanities</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lindeberg</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Promotion and Politeness: Conflicting Scholarly Rhetoric in Three Disciplines</source>. <publisher-loc>Finland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Abo Akademi University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lorés</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>On RA abstracts: From rhetorical structure to thematic organization</article-title>. <source>English for Specific Purposes</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin-Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A genre analysis of English and Spanish research paper abstracts in experimental social sciences</article-title>. <source>English for Specific Purposes</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paltridge</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Genre, text type, and the language learning classroom</article-title>. <source>ELT Journal</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pho</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Research article abstracts in applied linguistics and educational technology: A study of linguistic realizations of rhetorical structure and authorial stance</article-title>. <source>Discourse Studies</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Samraj</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>An exploration of a genre set: research article abstracts and introductions in two disciplines</article-title>. <source>English for Specific Purposes</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MBD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The textual organization of research paper abstracts in applied linguistics</article-title>. <source>Text</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1461445613480588">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ventola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Abstracts as an object of linguistic study</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cmejrkova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Havlova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Writing vs Speaking: Language, Text, Discourse, Communication</source>. <conf-name>Proceedings of the Conference held at the Czech Language Institute of the Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Prague</conf-loc>, <conf-date>14–16 October 1992</conf-date>. <publisher-loc>Tubingen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>G. Narr</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>