<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WJN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwjn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">West J Nurs Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Western Journal of Nursing Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0193-9459</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8456</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0193945913483881</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0193945913483881</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Methods</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Adolescent-Friendly Remedies for the Challenges of Focus Group Research</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>Alison Moriarty</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0193945913483881">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0193945913483881">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0193945913483881">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0193945913483881"><label>1</label>Yale University School of Nursing, New Haven, CT, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0193945913483881"><label>2</label>Yale-New Haven Hospital Adolescent Clinic &amp; Hill Regional Career School-Based Health Center, New Haven, CT, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0193945913483881"><label>3</label>University of Connecticut, School of Nursing, Storrs, CT, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0193945913483881">Alison Moriarty Daley, Yale University School of Nursing, 100 Church Street South, New Haven, CT 06536-0740, USA. Email: <email>alison.moriartydaley@yale.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>1043</fpage>
<lpage>1059</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Focus groups are an increasingly popular method of qualitative research; however, as with any research method, limitations emerge that were not anticipated. This article reviewed the limitations reported in 21 research studies, published between 2002 and 2012, to identify the common concerns of researchers in focus group studies with adolescents. Limitations focused on methodological concerns, recruitment challenges, and the potential influences of peers and the moderator on research results. Remedies are suggested for modifying the focus group method to address these potential challenges within the context of adolescent development and adolescent-friendly care.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>adolescent-friendly</kwd>
<kwd>focus group</kwd>
<kwd>limitations</kwd>
<kwd>qualitative research</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The use of focus groups in qualitative research with adolescents has become increasingly popular since the 1990s. Recent focus group research has provided greater understanding on a diverse variety of topics, including the provision of health services and education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0193945913483881">Britto, Tivorsak, &amp; Slap, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0193945913483881">Cornelius et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0193945913483881">Ellis et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0193945913483881">Schwartz, Pyle, Dowd, &amp; Sheehan, 2010</xref>) and the care of specific chronic illnesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0193945913483881">Carroll, Marrero, &amp; Swenson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0193945913483881">Hoppe et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0193945913483881">Rao, Kekwaletswe, Hosek, Martinez, &amp; Rodriguez, 2007</xref>). Focus group research provides the opportunity to gain in-depth understanding from several individuals about a research topic. The strength of this type of research rests in the interaction among participants that occurs within the group context and provides depth of understanding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). However, as is the case with any research method, challenges can emerge. The purpose of this article is to explore the limitations reported in published focus group research studies conducted with adolescents and to suggest adolescent-friendly remedies to address these challenges.</p>
<sec id="section1-0193945913483881">
<title>Adolescent Development and Adolescent-Friendly Care</title>
<p>Adolescence represents a transition from childhood to adulthood. During this time, adolescents undergo the physical changes associated with puberty as well as changes in the way they think and interact with the world around them. The onset and tempo of these changes vary greatly among adolescents. Cognitively, teens are transitioning from concrete to more abstract reasoning abilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0193945913483881">Piaget, 1969</xref>). With this transition comes the imaginary audience, the intense belief that others are interested in what they are thinking, doing, and feeling and the personal fable, the belief that their specialness or uniqueness protects them from the potential harm associated with risk-taking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0193945913483881">Elkind, 1967</xref>). Privacy is important for many adolescents during this time. The prefrontal cortex, the area of the brain that is responsible for advanced planning and decision making, is “under construction” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0193945913483881">Giedd, 2004</xref>, p. 83) throughout adolescence and may hinder a teen’s ability to anticipate and prevent the consequences of their choices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0193945913483881">Giedd, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0193945913483881">Giedd et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0193945913483881">Sowell, Thompson, Holmes, Jernigan, &amp; Toga, 1999</xref>). However, as with the physical changes of puberty, there is individual variation in the decision-making capacity of teens. Decisions are influenced by a variety of factors, including the situation, social, and peer influences, as well as the teen’s “individual values and beliefs, intentions and intuitions, emotions and self-awareness” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0193945913483881">Albert &amp; Steinberg, 2011</xref>, p. 220; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0193945913483881">Blakemore &amp; Robbins, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0193945913483881">Kambam &amp; Thompson, 2009</xref>). Socially, peers become increasingly important especially in early and middle adolescence and influence behaviors in positive and negative ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0193945913483881">Pugh &amp; Hart, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>The literature provides many suggestions regarding how clinical services can be provided in a manner that is “adolescent-friendly,” and tailored to the unique health and developmental needs of this population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0193945913483881">National Research Council and Institute of Medicine of the National Academies [NRC/IOM], 2009</xref>). The literature highlights confidentiality, developmental appropriateness, and accessibility as important factors to consider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0193945913483881">Fox, Philliber, McManus, &amp; Yurkiewicz, 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0193945913483881">Sadler &amp; Moriarty Daley, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0193945913483881">Tylee, Haller, Graham, Churchill, &amp; Sanci, 2007</xref>). Adolescent health care is most effective when these key elements are integrated into the practice or clinical setting. Parallels can be drawn between the delivery of adolescent-friendly health care services and conducting focus group research. The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0193945913483881">NRC/IOM (2009)</xref> has advocated for a research agenda to improve health care services for adolescents through the evaluation of existing models and the development of new systems that reflect the World Health Organization criteria of services characterized as accessible, acceptable, appropriate, effective, and equitable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0193945913483881">McIntyre, 2002</xref>). Adolescents have an important perspective to add to the planning and implementation of clinical services provided for them. Applying these concepts to the reported limitations found in completed focus group research studies has the potential to lessen common pitfalls and maximize the quality of research results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0193945913483881" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>A literature search of published studies that used the focus group method was conducted through the use of CINHAL, PsycINFO, PubMed, Ovid, and Google Scholar online databases using the keywords of adolescent, teen, and focus group in various combinations. Focus groups have become an increasingly popular and recognized method of qualitative research since the 1990s. Therefore, the search was limited to studies published in the past 10 years (2002-2012) to identify the more current concerns of researchers and those conducted in the United States to eliminate potential differences in consent and/or assent procedures and confidentiality laws. The search was further narrowed by choosing only those studies that conducted focus groups with adolescents. The researcher then examined each identified article for a discussion of limitations encountered that were specific to focus group method with adolescent participants. Studies that either did not identify limitations or described limitations not specific to focus group research with adolescents were eliminated from the analysis. Manuscripts that addressed the focus group method with adolescents but were not original research articles were also eliminated from the analysis. Twenty-one research studies were identified that met the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The researcher then examined the limitations presented in each study and identified common themes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0193945913483881" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The limitations discussed in the 21 studies were grouped into three overarching themes: methodological concerns, recruitment issues, and moderator/peer influences. The limitations identified by the author(s) of each study are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0193945913483881">Table 1</xref> and are described below. Adolescent-friendly remedies for the challenges commonly encountered by researchers conducting focus group research with adolescents are suggested in the “Discussion” section of this article.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0193945913483881" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Limitations of Focus Group Research With Adolescents as Reported by Authors.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0193945913483881" xlink:href="10.1177_0193945913483881-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Study</th>
<th align="center">Methodological concerns</th>
<th align="center">Recruitment issues</th>
<th align="center">Moderator/peer influences</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0193945913483881">Bauer, Yang, and Austin (2004)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Occurred during school day; homogeneous sample; lack of diversity</td>
<td>Participants knew each other</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0193945913483881">Bergin, Talley, and Hamer (2003)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Selective sample</td>
<td>Method may silence or limit discussion because of tendency to conform to peers; same-sex groups</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0193945913483881">Britto et al. (2004)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Recruitment from one hospital; underrepresentation of Hispanic teens</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0193945913483881">Britto, Tivorsak, and Slap (2010)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Peer pressure may have limited views expressed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0193945913483881">Carroll, Marrero, and Swenson (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Data collected at single point in time</td>
<td>Small convenience sample; relationship with providers/institution</td>
<td>Group consensus may have limited opinions; experiences that were perceived as personal or less socially desirable may not have been described</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0193945913483881">Cornelius et al. (2012)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Small purposive sample</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0193945913483881">Dworkin, Larson, and Hansen (2003)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Small purposive sample</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0193945913483881">Ellis et al. (2010)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Gender imbalance may have limited understanding</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0193945913483881">Gilliam, Warden, Goldstein, and Tapia (2004)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Homogeneous population</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0193945913483881">Ginsburg, Alexander, Hunt, Sullivan, and Cnann (2002)</xref></td>
<td>Wording of research question limited responses</td>
<td>In school population</td>
<td>Unintentional investigator bias</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0193945913483881">Hoppe et al. (2004)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Convenience sample; low response rate</td>
<td>Same gender moderator and participants</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0193945913483881">Kulwicki and Rice (2003)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Convenience sample; all males</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0193945913483881">Logsdon, Gagne, Hughes, Patterson, and Rakstraw (2005)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Few young adolescents</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0193945913483881">Marcell, Raine, and Eyre (2003)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Voluntary sample; minimal diversity</td>
<td>Mixed groups of sexually active/nonsexually active teens; freelisting activity may have increased participant awareness of issues</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0193945913483881">Mmari, Roche, Sudhinarast, and Blum (2008)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Location of recruitment determined by agency</td>
<td>Potential bias of responses related to location of groups</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0193945913483881">Molock et al. (2007)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Selection bias; confidentiality concerns</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0193945913483881">Patten et al. (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Member checks not performed</td>
<td>Small group size may have limited range of responses</td>
<td>Teens may not have participated equally; moderator influence on responses; educational sessions prior to group</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0193945913483881">Rao, Kekwaletswe, Hosek, Martinez, and Rodriguez (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Open to interpretive bias of researcher</td>
<td/>
<td>Social pressures of speaking in front of peers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0193945913483881">Ross, Potter, and Armstrong (2004)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Convenience sample; only English speaking</td>
<td>Only most confident/articulate likely participated</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0193945913483881">Salazar, Napolitano, Scherer, and McCauley (2004)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Skills of moderator to facilitate discussion time allotted to questions; moderator influence</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0193945913483881">Schwartz, Pyle, Dowd, and Sheehan (2010)</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>Self-selection of participants</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section4-0193945913483881">
<title>Methodological Concerns</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0193945913483881">Ginsburg, Alexander, Hunt, Sullivan, and Cnann (2002)</xref> reported that the wording of the research question used in their study may have limited the depth of responses generated in the focus groups and identified that the question used in the focus groups was too specific and therefore limited the breath of potential responses. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0193945913483881">Rao and colleagues (2007)</xref> expressed concerns that the data generated from their exploratory study addressing HIV positive adolescents attitudes toward highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) may have been affected by interpretative bias. The lack of member checks following data interpretation was identified as a possible limitation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0193945913483881">Patten et al.’s (2007)</xref> study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0193945913483881">
<title>Recruitment</title>
<p>The recruitment of the sample was a limitation identified by most of the researchers (19) and resulted from a variety of concerns ranging from the location utilized for recruitment to the characteristics of the research samples. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0193945913483881">Mmari, Roche, Sudhinarast, and Blum (2008)</xref> discussed their concerns that the agency they were collaborating with determined both the recruitment location and where the focus groups were ultimately conducted and as a result may have influenced the responses of participants. Similarly, two of the studies included recruitment efforts that occurred in schools and did not include teens who were not attending the school or those who were absent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0193945913483881">Bauer, Yang, &amp; Austin, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0193945913483881">Ginsburg et al., 2002</xref>) and thus limited those teens who were recruited to participate.</p>
<p>The use of a convenience sample resulted in samples that had unequal representation of males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0193945913483881">Kulwicki &amp; Rice, 2003</xref>) or females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0193945913483881">Ellis et al., 2010</xref>), younger teens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0193945913483881">Logsdon, Gagne, Hughes, Patterson, &amp; Rakstraw, 2005</xref>), racial or ethnic groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0193945913483881">Britto et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0193945913483881">Gilliam, Warden, Goldstein, &amp; Tapia, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0193945913483881">Marcell, Raine, &amp; Eyre, 2003</xref>), sexual experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0193945913483881">Marcell et al., 2003</xref>), and English-speaking teens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0193945913483881">Ross, Potter, &amp; Armstrong, 2004</xref>). A small sample size was reported as a limitation by three studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0193945913483881">Dworkin, Larson, &amp; Hansen, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0193945913483881">Hoppe et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0193945913483881">Patten et al., 2007</xref>). The willingness to participate in a study because of the teens’ relationship with a provider or health care agency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0193945913483881">Carroll et al., 2007</xref>) and confidentiality concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0193945913483881">Molock et al., 2007</xref>) were also identified as limitations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0193945913483881">
<title>Influences of the Moderator and Peers</title>
<p>Several of the focus group studies cited limitations related to the moderators. Specifically, those limitations included the skill of the moderator to facilitate the discussion and manage the time allotted for the group to introduce and discuss the research questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0193945913483881">Salazar, Napolitano, Scherer, &amp; McCauley, 2004</xref>) and the use of a moderator that was the same gender as the group participants in one study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0193945913483881">Hoppe et al., 2004</xref>). Three studies identified concerns regarding the unintentional introduction of bias into the focus group discussion by the moderator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0193945913483881">Ginsburg et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0193945913483881">Patten et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0193945913483881">Salazar et al., 2004</xref>). For example, the moderator in one study needed to exclude questions because of time limit placed on the focus group session (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0193945913483881">Salazar et al., 2004</xref>), and in another study, the responses of the moderator to participants were identified as potentially influencing the responses of participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0193945913483881">Patten et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The interactions of the adolescents in the focus groups were described in the limitations of seven studies. Researchers described concerns related to the equity of contributions among the teens in each group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0193945913483881">Molock et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0193945913483881">Ross et al., 2004</xref>), less socially desirable or personal experiences being withheld from conversations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0193945913483881">Rao et al., 2007</xref>), and group consensus possibly limiting the diversity of opinions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0193945913483881">Carroll et al., 2007</xref>). The social pressures associated with adolescents in groups were also identified as influencing the results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0193945913483881">Bauer et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0193945913483881">Bergin, Talley, &amp; Hamer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0193945913483881">Britto et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0193945913483881">Rao et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0193945913483881">Ross et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0193945913483881" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Health care services are often tailored to meet the specific developmental needs, preferences, and concerns of teens. Similarly, research with adolescents also benefits from considering their unique needs and preferences. The challenges of the focus group studies conducted with adolescents included in this review center on methodological concerns, recruitment challenges, and the potential influence of the moderator and peers on the focus group interactions. Remedies for each of these challenges are discussed next within the context of adolescent development and adolescent-friendly care.</p>
<sec id="section8-0193945913483881">
<title>Methodological Concerns</title>
<p>Choosing the research question is an essential decision in any research endeavor and guides the research process. A careful match between the question(s) and the research method is particularly important with focus group research. Seeking input from teens similar to the target sample by having them preview the focus group interview questions and then asking for their interpretation of the questions may provide valuable clarity and help avoid misinterpretations. Questions that are dichotomous (yes, no), incriminating, or question the teen’s freedom of choice or independence from parents should be avoided (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). Researchers should be very familiar with the mandated reporter statutes in the area where the research study is conducted and carefully consider proposed research questions and the possible responses of participants in the focus groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0193945913483881">English, Bass, Boyle, &amp; Eshragh, 2010</xref>). The research protocol should specifically address how reportable information, if shared in the group context, will be handled by the research team. Determining the reading level of the questions may help determine the appropriateness of the question for the participants. Medical jargon, slang, and convoluted questions may cause ambiguity or confusion. The researcher should be able to rephrase the questions, if necessary, to assure understanding during the focus group. Younger teens or those who are in the concrete operational stage of cognitive development may have difficulty considering hypothetical situations, the perspectives of others, multiple choices, or what may happen in the future. Consequently, their answers to open-ended questions may be brief or may prevent them from participating as fully in the discussion. The moderator can assist these teens by providing carefully planned and developmentally appropriate questions and probes that reword the research question(s) and allow these teens to express their thoughts or views (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0193945913483881">Mack, Giarelli, &amp; Bernhardt, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0193945913483881">Piaget, 1969</xref>). The questions can be worded to be more specific and ask about a single aspect of an experience or compare one idea with another. For example, a research question such as “Please describe the resources available in your community for teens that need a physical exam for school?” could be reworded “What is it like to have a physical exam at the school-based clinic?” The moderator could then probe further by asking for an additional example or about another aspect of the research question. Conversely, questions that are too simple may not provide the depth of explanation from more mature teens who are capable of contemplating complex situations, their personal preferences, and voicing opinions. It is recommended that the time allotted for focus groups with adolescents be similar to the length of a typical class at school, 45 to 60 min, with fewer questions than groups with adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Trustworthiness of results can be enhanced by the researcher and moderator understanding the focus group method and testing the questions prior to conducting the group. This facilitates the generation of findings that answer the research questions and accurately reflect the opinions of the participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). “Attention to both process and product, art and science, contribute to validity and subsequently quality in qualitative research” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0193945913483881">Whittemore, Chase, &amp; Mandle, 2001</xref>, p. 534). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger and Casey (2009)</xref> suggested running a practice group with colleagues to determine the flow and length of time is needed prior to the actual focus group. Alternatively, conducting a pilot of the focus group with a few teens similar to the desired sample can assist to fine-tune the research questions and flow of the group prior to conducting the study. Final questions that allow the researcher to summarize the group discussion or encourage teens to provide additional information may be particularly useful, especially if the teens have changed their opinions or the researcher needs further clarification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). Another option is to perform member checks, in which the results are presented to and then verified by the focus group participants to minimize potential interpretation bias (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0193945913483881">Morgan, 1997</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0193945913483881">
<title>Recruitment</title>
<p>Recruitment efforts should be concentrated at locations where teens are likely to frequent or gather. Teens are more likely to attend a focus group if the location is easily accessible by walking, public transportation, or is a short distance away if they need to ride a bicycle or they will need someone to drive them. The research team can also look for other scheduled events (e.g., club meeting, support group, or clinic session) and plan a focus group to occur either before or after the scheduled event. Advertisements that are generic and do not provide teens or parents with information about a focus group or who will be conducting the research are likely not to be as effective as personalized, detailed invitations to participate. Posters or advertisements should be eye-catching, include images or art that reflect the topic of the study, appeal to teens, and clearly provide information about the research aims, researcher’s name, affiliation, eligibility requirements, date and time of the proposed group, and clear instructions for accepting an invitation to participate via telephone, email, or text message. Recruitment can be enhanced by a member of the research team explaining the focus of the study and then allowing teens/parents the opportunity to ask questions. Meeting a member of the research team may provide a familiarity and connection to the study for potential participants. This individual needs to be approachable and knowledgeable about study and able to answer questions asked by potential participants, parents, and other gatekeepers. If the planned location and times are not convenient for interested adolescents, the researcher should remain flexible so that alternative locations and times can be made available for a group. If recruitment is done with a large group of teens, for example, in a classroom, sign-up sheets for those who are interested can be made available and offers the researcher the added benefit of obtaining contact information for follow-up. Details about the study and consent forms can be distributed during the recruitment meeting to facilitate conversations with parents/guardians and completion of the consent/assent procedure prior to participation. This also allows teens the opportunity to think about participation or to opt out without embarrassment for those who are feeling pressured to participate. Teens who feel coerced into focus group participation by friends, family members, or the research team are not being given the ethical consideration they deserve as research subjects. In addition, if teens feel coerced to join a focus group, their participation can have a negative impact on the group dynamics and the study findings.</p>
<p>Reminders by email, text, or phone in the days leading up to a scheduled group can also promote attendance at a scheduled focus group. School schedules, sports, and work schedules need to be carefully considered prior to scheduling a focus group. Competing exciting events or family obligations such as going to a football game or watching a sibling after school may adversely affect attendance at a scheduled focus group. It is always wise to ask interested teens what dates and times would work best for them. Likewise, adhering to the promised time frame for the group is important because teens may be dependent on a bus schedule or a parent to pick them up. Ending late can cause problems with the flow of the group and personally for the teen.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0193945913483881">
<title>Moderator and Peer Influences</title>
<p>The willingness for adolescents to participate in a research study may also be influenced by who the researcher is and the relationship they may have with members of the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0193945913483881">Clark, 2009</xref>). The research team needs to carefully consider how they will introduce themselves and how they wish to be addressed by the teens in the focus group to avoid an unintentional imbalance of power. The role of the research team is secondary to that of the group participants and aims to facilitate the group process and conversation. This is also influenced by how “sensitive” the focus group topic may be. Teens vary greatly in how they may wish to share information and while some prefer strangers, others are comforted by knowing the moderator. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0193945913483881">Molock and colleagues (2007)</xref> found that some of the adolescents who participated in her study did so because of “a familiar face” (p. 60). For some teens, a familiar moderator may be a plus, for others they may not want to share their opinions with an adult especially if they are in a position of authority (e.g., teacher, provider, role model; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0193945913483881">Clark, 2009</xref>). An alternative may be to let the teen choose what group would be most convenient to attend and provide different groups, at different times, led by different moderators. Most focus group research utilizes three to five groups, so multiple possibilities exist for scheduling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). However, in a research study in which different moderators are used, consistency in how the groups are conducted must be monitored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Homogeneity of focus group participants is an important consideration. The participants need to “share some social and cultural backgrounds or have similar lived experiences or some combination” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0193945913483881">Liamputtong, 2011</xref>, p. 34; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0193945913483881">Peterson-Sweeney, 2005</xref>) to enhance full participation in the conversation. The power of the focus group method is the diversity of opinion and synergy that is generated by the conversations that occur within the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0193945913483881">Morgan, 1997</xref>). Teens enjoy activities that involve their friends, so recruitment may be enhanced by allowing teens to bring a friend or if they know others in the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0193945913483881">Liamputtong, 2011</xref>). However, focus group researchers caution that a “collective” voice may emerge instead of the desired diversity of opinion because of the influence of the most outspoken teens in the group and the established relationships of peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0193945913483881">Peterson-Sweeney, 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger and Casey (2009)</xref> warned, “Listening to a clique of six teens is about the same as listening to the leader” (p. 156). To avoid this potential pitfall, Krueger and Casey suggested making it very clear to participants that they are allowed to talk to each other during the group and are encouraged to share all their thoughts and feelings. The experience of the focus group is likely very different from how they interact in a classroom setting; there are no correct or incorrect answers and raising a hand is not required prior to sharing an opinion or point of view in a focus group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). Rather, the discussion should be similar to the conversations they have with their peers during a group assignment or at lunchtime in the cafeteria. The moderator’s role is to encourage all the teens to participate and to avoid one teen from dominating the conversation. Opportunities can be provided by the moderator for those who may be quiet or hesitant by asking what they think or why they agree or disagree with the discussion.</p>
<p>Mixed groups of male and female adolescents may also influence conversations. The consensus of focus group researchers is to hold single-sex groups of unfamiliar teens, whose ages differ by less than 2 years to provide diverse opinions and more fruitful conversations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0193945913483881">Clark, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0193945913483881">Punch, 2002</xref>). Researchers also advocate for smaller groups of adolescents (3-6), also called mini focus groups, to be used to facilitate conversation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0193945913483881">Heary &amp; Hennessy, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0193945913483881">Punch, 2002</xref>). A smaller focus group is particularly important if the participants are likely to have strong opinions or a lot of expertise related to the research topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). Mini-focus groups are easier to recruit for and can be held at locations that larger groups cannot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). Icebreaker activities have been found to be particularly useful to start focus groups and to help teens actively engage in the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0193945913483881">Peterson-Sweeney, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0193945913483881">Punch, 2002</xref>). Suggestions of icebreakers for small groups are available in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0193945913483881">Figure 1</xref>; however, the possibilities are endless, and icebreakers can easily be modified to fit any focus group topic. Teens who participate in a focus group can be a valuable source for telling other teens about opportunities for participation. Providing recruitment flyers to participants at the end of a group may be a useful mechanism for finding additional research subjects.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0193945913483881" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Icebreaker suggestions for teens in focus groups.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0193945913483881-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Confidentiality is important to most teens regardless of whether it is in conversations with peers, health care providers, or in focus groups. If the focus group interview questions ask teens to discuss private issues or opinions, assurances need to be made that individuals outside the group will not overhear the focus group discussion and that the content of the group conversation will remain between those in the group. In addition, the teens need to be informed that their confidentiality will be honored as the data are transcribed, analyzed, and reported. This contract needs to be discussed with participants prior to starting the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0193945913483881">Peterson-Sweeney, 2005</xref>). Teens often require reassurance that they can say whatever they feel is important without judgment, but the moderator needs to hold true to that agreement. In primary care, teens come in for a variety of private concerns and a confidentiality agreement is made between the teen and the provider; however, if the safety of the individual is in question, this agreement must be broken. The same should be upheld with focus group research. The moderator should also provide examples to the teens to illustrate the confidentiality agreement during the focus group introduction. For example,<disp-quote>
<p>What is said in this group is between the members of this group and the research team that consists of the moderator (me), the note taker, and the person who will be typing our words from the recording. Both the recorded and the typed version will only be used by the research team and locked up when we are not using them. Your name or any other identifying information will not be included in the transcripts or later in the research report. If someone, like your teacher, asked me what you said in the group, I would tell her that the information was private and cannot be shared.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Providing examples and a possible script for how they may address the questions of peers about what was said in the group may help the participants to more fully understand this agreement and have a response prepared if someone should ask them about the group. For example, the moderator may say to the group during the discussion about the ground rules for the focus group:<disp-quote>
<p>Everyone has agreed to not discuss our conversation outside of this group, so that means if your friend asks you what Susie said in this group, an appropriate response would be “I am sorry I cannot share that information with you, it was one of the rules I agreed to.”</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Alternatively, the moderator could ask the participants for ideas of what they could say if asked by others to share information from the focus group. This exercise also allows the moderator to confirm the understanding of group members and can provide a mechanism to allow participants to start talking.</p>
<p>The skill of the moderator is the key to the success of this type of research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0193945913483881">Clark, 2009</xref>). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger and Casey (2009)</xref> pointed out, a moderator who enjoys teens and likes to interact with them increases the likelihood of success in focus groups. The goal is to ask questions and interact with participants in a conversational manner. The moderator should balance encouraging members of the group to participate while avoiding putting individuals “on the spot.” The moderator may need to remind teens, more than once, that everyone is encouraged to share his or her opinions and that there are no right or wrong answers.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>We would like all of you to participate in the group discussion today. Please be respectful of each other. There is no right or wrong answers to the questions we are going to ask. We want to hear from everyone. If you need me to repeat a question, I am happy to do so. Do you have any questions?</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In some situations, the moderator may provide an opportunity for a quiet teen to participate by asking what he or she thinks or if he or she agrees with the conversation. This is a delicate task that needs to be done in a supportive and encouraging manner. If the teen declines the invitation to offer his or her thoughts, this needs to be respected. In some instances, an older teen or college student trained to moderate focus groups may be the perfect choice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0193945913483881">Morgan (1997)</xref> emphasized, “There is no hard evidence that the focus group moderator’s impact on the data is any greater than the researcher’s influence on participant observation or individual interviewing” (p. 14). Focus groups may provide a more relaxed atmosphere and be less intimidating than an individual interview for adolescents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0193945913483881">Liamputtong, 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0193945913483881">Punch (2002)</xref> found teens prefer focus groups more than in-depth interviews because “they were in the supportive company of peers” (p. 46) even if they did not know the other members of the group personally. A few of the studies in this review identified the introduction of unintentional bias by the moderator as a study limitation. Teens especially may be vulnerable to a perceived opinion of a moderator. The moderator’s actions, such as nonverbal encouragements or empathy (e.g., nodding or facial expressions) as well as verbal acknowledgments, need to remain as neutral as possible to not influence the responses of participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0193945913483881">Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0193945913483881">Owens, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>The focus group method is an effective strategy for generating diverse opinions about a variety of research questions. It is essential to recognize the goals and assumptions of this type of research and carefully match research questions with the methodology to maximize the generation of quality data. Focus groups hold tremendous potential for providing a voice for adolescents in health care research. The unique developmental characteristics and needs of adolescents ought to be considered to minimize potential limitations during the design and while conducting focus group research.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The author would like to thank E. Carol Polifroni, EdD, RN, CNE, NEA-BC, and Lois S. Sadler, PhD, PNP-BC, FAAN, for their inspiration, encouragement, and critical review of this manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Judgment and decision making in adolescence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research on Adolescence</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-7995.2010.00724.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>“How can we stay healthy when you’re throwing all of this in front of us?” Findings from focus groups and interviews in middle schools on environmental influences on nutrition and physical activity</article-title>. <source>Health Education &amp; Behavior</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1090198103255372</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bergin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Prosocial behaviors of young adolescents: A focus group study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adolescence</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blakemore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Decision-making in the adolescent brain</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1184</fpage>-<lpage>1191</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3177</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeVellis</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeFriese</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slap</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Health care preferences and priorities of adolescents with chronic illnesses</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>114</volume>, <fpage>1272</fpage>-<lpage>1280</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2003-1134-L</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tivorsak</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slap</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Adolescents’ needs for health care privacy</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>126</volume>, <fpage>e1469</fpage>-<lpage>e1476</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marrero</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swenson</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Why do adolescents with type 1 diabetes and their parents participate in focus groups?</article-title> <source>Research and Theory for Nursing Practice: An International Journal</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Focus group research with children and youth</article-title>. <source>Journal for Specialists in Pediatric Nursing</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St. Lawrence</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Adolescents’ perceptions of a mobile cell phone text messaging-enhanced intervention and development of a mobile cell phone-based HIV prevention intervention</article-title>. <source>Journal for Specialists in Pediatric Nursing</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Adolescents’ accounts of growth experiences in youth activities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Youth and Adolescence</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elkind</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <article-title>Egocentricism in adolescence</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1025</fpage>-<lpage>1034</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>H. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klunck-Gillis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strunin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Discrimination and mental health among Somali refugee adolescents: The role of acculturation and gender</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Orthopsychiatry</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>-<lpage>575</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>English</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eshragh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>State minor consent laws: A summary</source>. <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Adolescent Health &amp; the Law</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Philliber</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yurkiewicz</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Adolescents’ experiences and views on health care</source> (Report No. 2). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://thenationalalliance.org/pdfs/Report3.%20Parents’%20Perspectives%20on%20Health%20Care%20for%20Adolescents.pdf">http://thenationalalliance.org/pdfs/Report3.%20Parents’%20Perspectives%20on%20Health%20Care%20for%20Adolescents.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Structural magnetic resonance imaging of the adolescent brain</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>1021</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>N. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>F. X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zijdenbos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Brain development during childhood and adolescence: A longitudinal MRI study</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>861</fpage>-<lpage>863</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilliam</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Concerns about contraceptive side effects among young Latinas: A focus group approach</article-title>. <source>Contraception</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>305</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cnann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Enhancing their likelihood for a positive future: Focus groups reveal the voice of inner-city youth</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>e95</fpage>-<lpage>e103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heary</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The use of focus group interviews in pediatric health care research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pediatric Psychology</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilsdon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nahom</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Teens speak out about HIV/AIDS: Focus group discussions about risk and decision-making</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adolescent Health</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>e27</fpage>-<lpage>e35</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2003.12.002</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kambam</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The development of decision-making capacities in children and adolescents: Psychological and neurological perspectives and their implications for juvenile defendants</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Sciences &amp; the Law</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Focus groups a practical guide for applied research</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kulwicki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Arab American adolescent perceptions and experiences with smoking</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nursing</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liamputtong</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Focus group methodology principals and practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Logsdon</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rakstraw</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Social support during adolescent pregnancy: Piecing together a quilt</article-title>. <source>Journal of Obstetric, Gynecologic &amp; Neonatal Nursing</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>606</fpage>-<lpage>614</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0884217505280194</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giarelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The adolescent research participant: Strategies for productive and ethical interviewing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pediatric Nursing</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>448</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedn.2008.07.009</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marcell</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raine</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eyre</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Where does reproductive health fit into the lives of adolescent males?</article-title> <source>Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>186</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Adolescent friendly health services: An agenda for change</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mmari</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sudhinarast</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>When a parent goes off to war: Exploring the issues faced by adolescents and their families</article-title>. <source>Youth &amp; Society</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>-<lpage>475</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Molock</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barksdale</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cammack</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Qualitative study of suicidality and help-seeking behaviors in African-American adolescents</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Community Psychology</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Focus groups as qualitative research</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Research Council and Institute of Medicine of the National Academies</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Adolescent health services: Missing opportunities</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The practical, methodological and ethical dilemmas of conducting focus groups with vulnerable clients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>652</fpage>-<lpage>658</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Enoch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Offord</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nevak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Focus groups of Alaska native adolescent tobacco users: Preferences for tobacco cessation intervention on and barriers to participation</article-title>. <source>Health Education &amp; Behavior</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>-<lpage>723</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peterson-Sweeney</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The use of focus groups in pediatric and adolescent research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pediatric Health Care</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piaget</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <article-title>The intellectual development of the adolescent</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Caplan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lebovici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Adolescence: Psychological perspectives</source> (pp. <fpage>22</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Identity development and peer group participation</article-title>. <source>New Directions for Child and Adolescent Development</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Punch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Interviewing strategies with young people: The “secret box”, stimulus material and task-based activities</article-title>. <source>Children &amp; Society</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kekwaletswe</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hosek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Stigma and social barriers to medication adherence with urban youth living with HIV</article-title>. <source>AIDS Care</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09540120600652303</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Improving patient educational literature: An understandable patient package insert for “the pill.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Obstetric, Gynecologic, &amp; Neonatal Nursing</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>208</lpage>. doi:10/1177/ 0884217504262969</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sadler</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moriarty Daley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A model of teen-friendly care for young women with negative pregnancy test results</article-title>. <source>Nursing Clinics of North America</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>523</fpage>-<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Hispanic adolescent farmworkers’ perceptions associated with pesticide exposure</article-title>. <source>Western Journal of Nursing Research</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0193945903259579</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Attitudes and beliefs of adolescents and parents regarding adolescent suicide</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>125</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2008-2248</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sowell</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jernigan</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toga</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>In vivo evidence for post-adolescent brain maturation in frontal and striatal regions</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>859</fpage>-<lpage>861</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tylee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanci</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Youth-friendly primary-care services: How are we doing and what more needs to be done?</article-title> <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>369</volume>, <fpage>1565</fpage>-<lpage>1573</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0193945913483881">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandle</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Validity in qualitative research</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>522</fpage>-<lpage>537</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>