<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaph</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Asia Pac J Public Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Asia-Pacific Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1010-5395</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2479</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1010539512453255</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1010539512453255</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special section on Island Health and Disaster</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Lessons Learned From the Great East Japan Earthquake</article-title>
<subtitle>Impact on Child and Adolescent Health</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Kenji</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1010539512453255">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>Naoko</given-names></name>
<degrees>MA</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1010539512453255"><label>1</label>National Institute of Public Health, Saitama Prefecture, Japan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1010539512453255">Kenji Hayashi, National Institute of Public Health, Saitama Prefecture 351-0104, Japan Email: <email>saitamaKH@niph.go.jp</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>681</fpage>
<lpage>688</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 APJPH</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Asia-Pacific Academic Consortium for Public Health</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Great East Japan Earthquake (the Tohoku Earthquake) was one of the most devastating natural disasters ever to hit Japan, and its social impact was so enormous that Japan may never be the same again. This was an unprecedented triple disaster: an earthquake followed by a devastating tsunami and, finally, the destruction of a major nuclear power plant with the leaking of large amounts of radiation. The destruction occurred despite the presence of a 10-m protection wall and the effects of the tsunami were seen as high as 40 m above sea level. About 78 000 residents from areas within a 20-km radius of the Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant were evacuated together with another 10 000 residents from areas with elevated levels of radiation. In the afflicted area, 30% of the population was older than 60 years of age, but more than 60% of the deaths were in this age cohort. Children and adolescents younger than 19 years accounted for 6.5% of the deaths, and there were 229 survivors younger than 18 years who lost both their parents in the disaster and 1295 who lost one of their parents. The long-term psychological effects on children and adolescents remain uncertain.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Great East Japan Earthquake</kwd>
<kwd>child and adolescent health</kwd>
<kwd>PTSD</kwd>
<kwd>radioactive contamination</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1010539512453255" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The Great East Japan Earthquake (hereinafter referred to as the “Tohoku Earthquake”) was one of the most devastating natural disasters ever to hit Japan, and its social impact was so enormous that Japan may never be the same again. Japanese society as a whole is greatly concerned about the earthquake’s impact, including radioactive contamination, on the health of children and adolescents in particular. However, as of this date, there is not enough scientific evidence to assess the impact of the disaster on the younger generation, and overall assessment of the impact of the earthquake is continuing. In this article, we will identify the salient features of the disaster caused by the earthquake and discuss the problems unique to children and adolescents in the afflicted areas to draw public health lessons from the disaster.</p>
<p>The disaster triggered by the Tohoku earthquake can be summed up in terms of the following 6 characteristics: first, it was an unprecedented triple disaster with an earthquake followed by the tsunami and destruction of a nuclear power plant; second, it was a large-scale disaster that occurred in a developed nation and claimed the lives of a disproportionately large number of elderly persons; third, the collapse and resulting paralysis of the administrative functions of municipalities greatly hampered the relief effort; fourth, members of both the Ground Self-Defense Force and also those of the US military were mobilized in the rescue operation; fifth, in the aftermath of the Tohoku earthquake, volunteer activities, including those by private organizations, played a greater role than in past disasters; and sixth, many countries extended cooperation, not only to rescue disaster victims but also to provide technical assistance. In this article, we will discuss these 6 characteristics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1010539512453255">
<title>Characteristics of the Great East Japan Earthquake</title>
<sec id="section3-1010539512453255">
<title>Triple Disaster</title>
<p>Being a part of the Pacific Ring of Fire, Japan is frequently hit by earthquakes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1010539512453255">Figure 1</xref>). In the sea near Japan, there is a deep oceanic trench, the Japan Trench. Earthquakes in the trench are often accompanied by tsunamis because vertical displacements of the seafloor displace huge quantities of seawater, and there is an enormous conversion of potential energy to kinetic energy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1010539512453255">1</xref></sup> In addition, the shape of the Sanriku Coast has a property that further amplifies the energy conversion, resulting in massive destruction and accelerated flood rates. Thus, in the Tohoku earthquake, it took less than 30 minutes after the tsunami warning was sounded for it to reach land, engulfing thousands of victims<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1010539512453255">2</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1010539512453255">Table 1</xref>). Not even the tsunami wall, more than 10 m high, was able to hold back the waves and prevent the accident at the Tokyo Electric Power Company’s Fukushima Dai-ichi Nuclear Power Plant.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1010539512453255" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Pacific Rim of Fire</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1010539512453255-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-1010539512453255" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Number of Victims, Buildings Damaged, and Inundations<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1010539512453255">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1010539512453255" xlink:href="10.1177_1010539512453255-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Number of Victims<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Number of Buildings Damaged<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Number of Inundations<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Prefecture</th>
<th align="center">Dead</th>
<th align="center">Missing</th>
<th align="center">Injured</th>
<th align="center">Fully Destroyed</th>
<th align="center">Half Destroyed</th>
<th align="center">Partially Damaged</th>
<th align="center">Above Floor Level</th>
<th align="center">Below Floor Level</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Iwate</td>
<td>4667</td>
<td>1368</td>
<td>188</td>
<td>20 184</td>
<td>4552</td>
<td>7316</td>
<td>1761</td>
<td>323</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Miyagi</td>
<td>9472</td>
<td>1805</td>
<td>4015</td>
<td>84 062</td>
<td>136 712</td>
<td>212 974</td>
<td>7900</td>
<td>11 299</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fukushima</td>
<td>1925</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>181</td>
<td>19 781</td>
<td>61 925</td>
<td>142 166</td>
<td>1053</td>
<td>340</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total in Japan</td>
<td>16 131</td>
<td>3240</td>
<td>5994</td>
<td>128 497</td>
<td>240 090</td>
<td>677 502</td>
<td>12 918</td>
<td>13 961</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1010539512453255">
<label>a</label>
<p>Fire and Disaster Management Agency of the Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communication (2012).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1010539512453255">2</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The radioactive contamination triggered by the Fukushima nuclear accident is being dealt with in accordance with a list of recommendations prepared by the International Commission on Radiological Protection (ICRP).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1010539512453255">3</xref></sup> ICRP’s recommendations draw from the experience of past nuclear accidents at Chernobyl, Three Mile Island, and Tokaimura. The ICRP recommendations are therefore not necessarily suitable for dealing with the low level of radioactive contamination caused by the Fukushima nuclear accident and expected to remain there over a long period of time. About 78 000 residents from areas within a 20-km radius of the Fukushima Dai-ichi Nuclear Power Plant were evacuated, and 10 000 residents from areas where more than 20 mSv per year of radiation was detected were asked to evacuate voluntarily.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1010539512453255">
<title>Large-Scale Disaster</title>
<p>The run-up height, that is, the maximum vertical height onshore reached by the tsunami was 40-m above sea level in the Tohoku Earthquake, and as a result, tsunami waves made their way farther inland and spread more widely than in previous earthquakes. This disaster occurred in a developed nation in an area of high population density with a rapidly aging population, which made it more devastating. Whereas 30% of the population was aged more than 60 in the entire afflicted area, more than 60% of those who died were in this same age cohort.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1010539512453255">4</xref></sup> Even those who were fortunate enough to survive have been forced to live in evacuation shelters. Also, there are those who not only lost their homes or jobs but also suffer from severe posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) as a result of loss of family and friends.</p>
<p>The first reference to a tsunami in Japanese history is the <italic>Jougan</italic> tsunami of 869, which is mentioned in <italic>Sandai Jitsuroku</italic> (sixth of the 6 classical Japanese history texts purportedly written by Fujiwara-no-Michizane in the 10th century). Since then, there have been more than 20 recorded tsunamis centering on the Tohoku district. The death toll in the 1896 tsunami reached 26 360 compared with 20 000 or so in the 2011 Tohoku earthquake.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1010539512453255">5</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1010539512453255">
<title>Administrative Dysfunction</title>
<p>Disaster relief and rescue were affected by the extensive damage to local municipalities, both physical and human, leading to a complete breakdown of administrative functions. In Japan, under the Basic Law on Natural Disasters, municipalities have the primary responsibility of dealing with disasters. If the scale of a disaster is too large for a municipality to handle, it calls on the prefectural government for reinforcements, and if the disaster is beyond the latter’s relief and rescue capacity, then the prefectural government is required to ask the central government for help. The municipality’s inability to carry out its administrative functions leads to disruption in the flow of primary information, which will in turn hamper rescue efforts. Indeed, this is what happened in the 2011 Tohoku earthquake.</p>
<p>Along with the Basic Law on National Disasters, the Nuclear Disaster Special Measure Law also applies to nuclear accidents. Under the latter law, it is the power company concerned that is responsible for notifying the appropriate authorities when a disaster occurs. Regardless of whether the local government asks for help, the central government may unilaterally launch a rescue operation if it deems the situation urgent enough to require such an action. However, because the naked eye cannot detect radiation leaks, how fast the government is able to respond ultimately depends on whether a structure is in place that will enable the power company to swiftly detect radiation leaks and distribute information when an accident occurs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1010539512453255">
<title>Rescue Activities of the Ground Self-Defense Force and the US Military</title>
<p>Members of Japan’s Self-Defense Forces are commonly dispatched whenever a major disaster strikes. In the 2011 Tohoku earthquake, because of its sheer scale, Ground Self-Defense Force personnel members were mobilized from all over the country to carry out relief efforts, including taking care of those living in evacuation shelters. They also searched for bodies of victims, wrapped them in tapelines and blankets, and hauled them to crematories. With so many bodies to handle, this part of the relief effort took a heavy toll on the mental health of these soldiers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1010539512453255">6</xref></sup> The US Armed Forces personnel members not only carried out relief efforts, “Operation Friendship,” including mobilization of planes and warships, but also provided technical assistance related to radioactive contamination. Moreover, in the immediate aftermath of the disaster, staff members of the National Institute of Public Health, Japan, exchanged information on measurements of radioactivity in breast milk, vegetables, and water with US Armed Forces personnel members and FDA experts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1010539512453255">
<title>Prominence of Volunteers</title>
<p>The Hanshin-Awaji earthquake (1995) and the Mid-Niigata Prefecture earthquake (2004) occasioned the growth of volunteers and volunteer organizations. Thanks to lessons learned from these disasters, in the Tohoku earthquake, many teams of volunteers rushed to the stricken areas. However, because of the dysfunction of local governments, it was difficult to coordinate their activities. Responding to requests from the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare (MHLW), local governments throughout Japan dispatched public health nurses to the stricken areas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1010539512453255">7</xref></sup> Also noteworthy were the invaluable contributions made by medical professionals dispatched jointly by professional associations, including the Disaster Medical Assistance Team and the Japan Primary Care Association. The relief efforts of the various teams of volunteers, including those by international health personnel, were especially appreciated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1010539512453255">
<title>International Cooperation</title>
<p>In addition to the US Armed Forces, some 142 countries and 39 international organizations, including the International Atomic Energy Agency, offered material and human assistance. This was the biggest international assistance Japan has received since the end of World War II. On a technical level, United States and France extended valuable assistance. The former provided robotics technology for surveying conditions inside the Fukushima Dai-ichi Power Plant and the latter, the technology for restoring the nuclear reactor coolant pumps.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1010539512453255">
<title>Characteristics of Earthquake Disasters and Health Problems of Children and Adolescents</title>
<p>Those who died in the disaster that struck the 3 prefectures of the Tohoku district—Iwate, Miyagi, and Fukushima—were mostly elderly residents, but children and adolescents younger than 19 years also accounted for 6.5% of the dead.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1010539512453255">4</xref></sup> There were 229 survivors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1010539512453255">8</xref></sup> younger than 18 who lost both their parents in the disaster and 1295 who lost one of their parents (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1010539512453255">Table 2</xref>). Adolescents shared many of the disaster-related health and social issues that affected adults. However, given the characteristics of adolescents, who are still in the process of growing up, there are issues unique to them. These include the following: (1) problems related to the mental health of survivors as a direct result of the disaster; (2) uncertainty, both physical and psychological, about their life brought on by human and material loss; and (3) fear of radiation disease, which makes the Tohoku earthquake disaster unique.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1010539512453255" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Numbers of Children (Age &lt;18 years) Orphaned by the Earthquake<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1010539512453255">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1010539512453255" xlink:href="10.1177_1010539512453255-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Prefecture</th>
<th align="center">Lost 1 Parent</th>
<th align="center">Lost Both Parents</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Iwate</td>
<td>445</td>
<td>91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Miyagi</td>
<td>711</td>
<td>117</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fukushima</td>
<td>139</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>1295</td>
<td>229</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1010539512453255">
<label>a</label>
<p>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare (2011)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1010539512453255">8</xref></sup>; numbers are as of July 29, 2011.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section10-1010539512453255">
<title>Direct Impact on the Mental Health of Survivors</title>
<p>The sight of the horrendous tsunami waves approaching the shore no doubt filled children and adolescents with deep anxiety. Right after the earthquake, a magazine collected compositions by school children ranging in grade from elementary to high school. Their compositions had titles like “Tsunami was black and smelly” (written by a second grader) and “The rumble in the earth” (written by a fifth grader). These compositions express the fear these children felt as a sensory experience, whereas the composition titled “Listlessness, nausea, and a funny feeling” (by a sixth grader) represents a physical response triggered by fear. The composition titled “Now I don’t know what I want” (by a fourth grader) expresses an inability to respond as a result of intense stress. And the one titled “It would be so nice if this were a dream” (by a third grader) can be regarded as a form of psychological defense mechanism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1010539512453255">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>Symptoms that appear immediately after an individual sustains a psychological wound are collectively referred to as an acute stress disorder, and in most cases, they disappear soon after the individual’s condition stabilizes. If the injured individual continues to show psychological symptoms after a period of 3 months, the condition is referred to as PTSD. Children’s brains are able to process information several times faster than an adult’s, which means they are able to learn faster than adults. Children also learn to fear what they have experienced much faster than adults. As a result, it is believed that the onset of PTSD symptoms is several times faster in children than in adults.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1010539512453255">10</xref></sup> It is not clear when the compositions collected by the magazine were written, but given the publication date of the magazine, it is reasonable to assume that they were written 2 to 3 months after the earthquake, which means some of the children who wrote the compositions may have already developed PTSD.</p>
<p>Children develop a sense of fear not only through direct experience but also by observing the disturbed behavior of their parents. As is evident in the Fukushima nuclear accident, even residents not directly affected by the tsunami were forced to evacuate, and the anxiety of these adults, uncertain of when they would be able to return to their home, may have led to the children developing PTSD symptoms, as experts point out.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1010539512453255">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>The US National Center for PTSD has designed a PTSD screening model for implementing psychological first aid. A Japanese translation of the model is currently being used to screen PTSD patients in Japan. However, considering the disparateness in the psychological responses of Japanese and that of Americans grounded in cultural differences, a version of the screening model modified to better suit the Japanese mentality is needed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1010539512453255">11</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1010539512453255">
<title>Psychological Anxiety and Uncertainty About Life, Triggered by Loss</title>
<p>The losses suffered included property, parents and relatives, and the family home. For children, the loss of parents is particularly devastating; for the younger they are, the more dependent they are on their parents for psychological protection and daily life. As they approach adolescence, they begin to develop a direct awareness of their relationship with their parents. And if they lose their parents, the way they respond depends on whether they regard the loss as something inevitable or something that should not have been allowed to happen.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1010539512453255">10</xref></sup> Moreover, when children are unable to confirm the death of their missing parents, their fears are aroused more acutely than if they are able to come to terms with their parents’ death. In Japan, the sentence “So and so died” but not “So and so is dead” is used when someone close dies. However, generally speaking, if one sees a dead insect, one will use the expression, “There’s a dead insect.” To the Japanese, it is psychologically important to have a conscious new beginning by making a clean break with the deceased. Fortunately, 91 out of 229 children who lost both their parents in the Tohoku earthquake were adopted by their grandfather or siblings of their parents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1010539512453255">8</xref></sup> Society needs to provide adequate assistance to help alleviate the uncertainty they feel about their present and future situation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1010539512453255">
<title>Concerns About Radiation Disease</title>
<p>A month after the Fukushima nuclear accident, personnel of the National Institute of Public Health (NIPH), Japan, detected radioactive iodine (<sup>131</sup>I) and radioactive cesium (<sup>134</sup>Cs, <sup>137</sup>Cs) among nursing mothers (27 selected samples) residing in areas where it was feared that breast milk might be contaminated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1010539512453255">12</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1010539512453255">Table 3</xref>). A low level of <sup>131</sup>I was found in 7 breast milk samples, and an extremely small amount of radioactive cesium (<sup>137</sup>Cs), 2.4 Bq/kg, was detected in one. All 7 mothers continued breastfeeding and were tested for radioactive cesium a month later, when none was found. With these studies, the MHLW and academic societies such as the Japanese Society of Nuclear Medicine and the Japan Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology announced that continued breastfeeding was safe for mothers and their infants.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1010539512453255" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Measured Value of Radiological Materials in Breast Milk<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1010539512453255">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1010539512453255" xlink:href="10.1177_1010539512453255-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Prefecture</th>
<th align="center">City</th>
<th align="center">Distance From Fukushima Dai-ichi Nuclear Power Plant</th>
<th align="center">Radioactive Iodine (<sup>131</sup>I)</th>
<th align="center">Radioactive Cesium (<sup>134</sup>Cs)</th>
<th align="center">Radioactive Cesium (<sup>137</sup>Cs)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Fukushima</td>
<td>Iwaki</td>
<td>Within 50 km</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Hitachiomiya</td>
<td>Within 120 km</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>ND</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ibaraki</td>
<td>Mito</td>
<td>Within 150 km</td>
<td>8.0</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>ND</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Kasama</td>
<td>Within 150 km</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>ND</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Kasama</td>
<td>Within 150 km</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>ND</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Shimozuma</td>
<td>Within 180 km</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>ND</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chiba</td>
<td>Chiba</td>
<td>Within 230 km</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>ND</td>
<td>ND</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1010539512453255">
<p>Abbreviation: ND, not detectable.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1010539512453255">
<label>a</label>
<p>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare (2011).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1010539512453255">12</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Although only low levels of radioactive contamination were found, the likelihood that the Fukushima Dai-ichi Nuclear Power Plant will continue to emit radiation for a long time has sparked an intense debate. This is because, from the beginning, the government relied on the safety standard that was established by the ICRP, which is based on data from past nuclear accidents at Chernobyl (1986) and Three Mile Island (1979) and the JOC critical accident in Tokaimura (1999).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1010539512453255">3</xref></sup> In all 3 cases, vast amounts of radioactivity were released in the initial phase of the accident. Unlike the Fukushima accident, in the 3 earlier accidents, radiation emission lasted a relatively short time.</p>
<p>In addition to thyroid cancer, which is well known historically as the main consequence of radiation exposure in children, other health problems have been reported, including type 1 diabetes and various forms of developmental disorders and delay of sexual maturation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1010539512453255">13</xref></sup> Until results of longitudinal cohort studies are available, we may not know the full extent of the impact of the Fukushima nuclear accident on children.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1010539512453255">
<title>The Role of the NIPH in the Tohoku Earthquake</title>
<p>The NIPH has played an important role as an arm of government to implement its mission in its own right and carry out activities in the field to aggregate the scientific information from the disaster area. In the initial stage of the current disaster, the NIPH team with expertise in health crisis management and radiology was sent to headquarters established in the MHLW, which coordinated the activities of rescue teams organized in the affected municipalities. In addition, radiation experts were required to monitor contamination of breast milk, vegetables, and drinking water and to assess risks. A nursing team was dispatched to assist local government officials with management of shelters. The NIPH has gathered and collated information from all channels available to it and from official documents prepared by the public sector. Although the immediate effects of the disaster have been stabilized, the aftermath still remains. The NIPH will continue to monitor health effects and has started a 10-year cohort study targeting 30 000 people in the affected areas to study long-term impacts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1010539512453255" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The Tohoku earthquake and the subsequent tsunami caused significant damage to Japan, resulted in the deaths of many residents, and caused the evacuation of far more. The long-term psychological impacts of the disaster and the health effects of radiation are still uncertain. Though breastfeeding has been proven to be safe by the studies undertaken, the long-term effects of the Fukushima nuclear accident on child and adolescent health remain uncertain. Further scientific research, including the ongoing 10-year cohort study being conducted by NIPH will assist in documenting and managing any long-term effects.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1010539512453255">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tsunamis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Disaster Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1010539512453255">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Fire and Disaster Management Agency of the Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communication</collab>. <article-title>Touhokuchihou Taiheiyouoki Jishin, Dai 143 Hou</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="EN">Report on the Great East Japan Earthquake, No 143</trans-title>]. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fdma.go.jp/bn/higaihou/pdf/jishin/143.pdf">http://www.fdma.go.jp/bn/higaihou/pdf/jishin/143.pdf</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 6, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1010539512453255">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lochard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogdevitch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>ICRP Publication 111: Application of the Commission’s recommendations to the protection of people living in long-term contaminated areas after a nuclear accident or a radiation emergency</article-title>. <source>Ann ICRP</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>, 7-62.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1010539512453255">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>Higashi Nihon Daishinsai Giseisya no Danjyo, Nenrei Kousei</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="EN">Age and sex composition of mortality in the Great East Japan Earthquake</trans-title>]. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.ttcn.ne.jp/honkawa/4363f.html">http://www2.ttcn.ne.jp/honkawa/4363f.html</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 6, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1010539512453255">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Sanrikukaiigan Otsunami (Bunshun Bunko)</source>. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bungeishunjyu</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1010539512453255">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>PAHO/WHO</collab>. <source>Management of Dead Bodies in Disaster Situations</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PAHO/WHO</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1010539512453255">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>Shukanhoken-eisei News, No. 1624</source>. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Shakaihoken Jitsumu Kenkyusho</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1010539512453255">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare</collab>. <source>Background paper prepared for the upper house Tohoku Reconstruction Committee on 1 August</source>; <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1010539512453255">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>Tsunamihisaichi no Kodomo Hachijyunin no Sakubunshu</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="EN">A Collection of Compositions by 80 Children of the Areas Affected</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bungeishunju</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1010539512453255">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>Konkai no Daishinsai no Tokuchou</article-title> [<trans-title>Characteristics of the disaster caused by the Great East Japan Earthquake</trans-title>]. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://for-supporters.net/campcolumn4.html">http://for-supporters.net/campcolumn4.html</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 6, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1010539512453255">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Hyogo Institute for Traumatic Stress</collab>. <article-title>Psychological first aid: field operations guide</article-title>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> [<comment>in Japanese</comment>]. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.j-hits.org/psychological/pdf/pfa_complete.pdf#zoom=100">http://www.j-hits.org/psychological/pdf/pfa_complete.pdf#zoom=100</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 6, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1010539512453255">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare</collab>. <article-title>Bonyu no Housyasei Busshitsu Noudo Tounikannsuru Cyousakekka</article-title> [<trans-title>Result of the survey of radiological materials in breastmilk</trans-title>]. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/houdou/2r9852000001azxj.html">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/houdou/2r9852000001azxj.html</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 6, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1010539512453255">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Yablokov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nesterenko</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nesterenko</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Chernobyl, Consequence of the Catastrophe for People and Environment</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York Academy of Sciences</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nyas.org/publications/annals/Detail.aspx?cid=f3f3bd16">www.nyas.org/publications/annals/Detail.aspx?cid=f3f3bd16</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 6, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>