<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppic</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part C: Journal of Mechanical Engineering Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4062</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2983</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954406212447485</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954406212447485</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special Issue Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Vibration suppression and energy transfer by parametric excitation in drive systems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>Horst</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954406212447485">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954406212447485"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pumhössel</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0954406212447485">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954406212447485"><label>1</label>Institute of Mechanics and Mechatronics, Vienna University of Technology, Vienna, Austria</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0954406212447485"><label>2</label>Institute of Computer-Aided Methods in Mechanical Engineering, Johannes Kepler University, Linz, Austria</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954406212447485">Horst Ecker, Institute of Mechanics and Mechatronics, Vienna University of Technology, Vienna, Austria. Email: <email>horst.ecker@tuwien.ac.at</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<issue-title>Includes a special section on Parametric Excitation: Applications in science and engineering</issue-title>
<fpage>2000</fpage>
<lpage>2014</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Drive systems may experience torsional vibrations due to various kinds of excitation mechanisms. In many engineering systems, however, such vibrations may have a negative impact on the performance and must be avoided or reduced to an acceptable level by all means. Self-excited vibrations are especially unwanted, since they may grow rapidly and not only degrade the performance but even damage machinery. In this contribution it is suggested to employ parametric stiffness excitation to suppress self-excited vibrations. In the first part of the article we study the basic energy transfer mechanism that is initiated by parametric excitation, and some general conclusions are drawn. In the second part, a hypothetic drivetrain, consisting of an electrical motor, a drive shaft and working rolls is investigated. A self-excitation mechanism is assumed to destabilize the drive system. Parametric excitation is introduced via the speed control of the electrical drive, and the capability of stabilizing the system by this measure is investigated. It is shown that the damping available in the system can be used much more effectively if parametric stiffness excitation is employed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Parametric anti-resonance</kwd>
<kwd>enhanced damping</kwd>
<kwd>self-excited vibrations</kwd>
<kwd>stability</kwd>
<kwd>Tondl effect</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954406212447485" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Engineering systems with time-periodic parameters, also known as <italic>parametrically excited systems</italic>, have been of interest for a long time. Research on such systems has been conducted already in the 19th century, by M Faraday who was investigating sloshing liquids in a container. Still more than hundred years ago, Émilie L Mathieu gave his name to a most simple but nevertheless famous differential equation with a harmonically varying coefficient. Since then, parametric excitation (PE) has attracted much interest, mainly because it may lead to a unique type of instability that is referred to as <italic>parametric resonance</italic>.</p>
<p>From the abundant literature on this topic,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212447485">1</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212447485">5</xref></sup> it is known that a linear time-periodic (TP) system
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0954406212447485"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
may exhibit <italic>Primary Parametric Resonances</italic> at frequencies <inline-formula id="ilm1-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>pr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>Parametric Combination Resonances</italic> at frequencies <inline-formula id="ilm2-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the PE-frequency η equal to
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0954406212447485"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Symbols Ω<sub><italic>j</italic></sub> and Ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> denote the <italic>j</italic>-th (<italic>k</italic>-th) element of the diagonal (<italic>n</italic> × <italic>n</italic>)-matrix <bold>Ω</bold>, which represent the natural frequencies of the undamped system without parametric excitation. The denominator <italic>m</italic> represents the order of the parametric resonance. Depending on the (<italic>n</italic> × <italic>n</italic>)-matrices <bold>Γ</bold> and <bold>P</bold> for the damping parameters and parametric excitation amplitudes, respectively, mainly first order resonances <italic>m</italic> = 1 of the lowest frequencies Ω<sub>1</sub>, Ω<sub>2</sub> are significant. Since the nature of a parametric resonance is that of an instability, such resonances may be hazardous for an engineering system. Fortunately, not all PE-resonance frequencies predicted by equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0954406212447485">2</xref>) really lead to an instability. Higher order primary resonances and also certain parametric combination resonances are usually benign, frequently termed <italic>non-resonant</italic>, and do not at all cause excessive vibrations in engineering systems. Consequently, for many years the focus of research has been on the critical instabilities in order to predict and avoid potentially dangerous operation of a machine.</p>
<p>The lack of interest for parametric resonance frequencies with non-resonant behavior changed when A. Tondl found out about an interesting phenomenon associated with this special category of frequencies. In his paper,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954406212447485">6</xref></sup> Tondl shows early simulation results obtained by means of an analog computer. He investigated an unstable, non-linear, parametrically excited system that, much to his surprise, exhibited a frequency interval of the parametric excitation frequency, where the self-excited vibration amplitudes of the system were completely suppressed. Due to the fact that this interval occurred near the frequency of a parametric resonance, the phenomenon was named <italic>parametric anti-resonance</italic>.</p>
<p>This ground-breaking work was the starting point for several research initiatives and led to a growing number of contributions related to this phenomenon by various authors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954406212447485">7</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954406212447485">12</xref></sup> A first comprehensive investigation was published by Ecker,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954406212447485">13</xref></sup> summarizing results obtained for parametric stiffness variation in various mechanical systems by numerical and analytical methods. Parametric resonances and anti-resonances generated by more general kinds of parametric excitation were studied by Tondl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406212447485">14</xref></sup> and by Dohnal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954406212447485">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>Aside from studies on the theoretical aspects of this phenomenon, possible practical applications have also been considered. Several papers have dealt with the application in rotor systems,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954406212447485">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954406212447485">16</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0954406212447485">19</xref></sup> suggest a new kind of vibration absorber,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0954406212447485">20</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0954406212447485">21</xref></sup> and study enhanced damping of beam structures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0954406212447485">22</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0954406212447485">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Only very recently, drive systems have been considered as engineering systems that may also benefit from vibration suppression by parametric excitation. In Pumhössel et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954406212447485">25</xref></sup> they investigate a drive system that is also subject to parametric excitation, and indeed torsional vibrations can be affected positively. The following treatise is also focused on torsional vibration systems and will start out from a generic system. In the first part, the underlying mechanism of parametric vibration suppression is studied. Based on the newly gained insight, the second part demonstrates the possibility of using parametric excitation to stabilize an otherwise unstable drive system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954406212447485"><title>Model of a 3-dof torsional vibration system</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212447485">Figure 1</xref> shows a schematic of a simple torsional system of chain topology with three degrees of freedom (dof) <bold>q</bold> = [<italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>3</sub>]<sup><italic>T</italic></sup> that is pinned on one end. The system is fully defined by the mass moments of inertia <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, the torsional stiffness parameters <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub>, the relative torsional damping parameters <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub>, and the parametric stiffness excitation <italic>k</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> + <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic></sub> cos(η<italic>t</italic>) with <italic>i</italic> = 1, 2, 3. For such a system the following equations of motion written in matrix notation hold
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0954406212447485"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
with
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0954406212447485"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
In the following, we will carry out a basic study with the focus on comparing vibration levels, on tracking the flow of kinetic and potential energy quantities and on analyzing vibration frequencies. To facilitate this study and the interpretation of the results, we want to simplify the system by reducing the number of parameters, but without changing the order or modifying the structure of the system. This can be done by defining identical parameters for the torsional subsystems (<italic>I</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub>, <italic>i</italic> = 1, 2, 3) that build up the entire 3-dof system. Based on this assumption, we can go one step further and scale the equations of motion by relating system parameters to reference quantities like a reference mass moment <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>ref</italic></sub> and a torsional stiffness <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>ref</italic></sub>.
<fig id="fig1-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Generic 3-dof torsional vibration system with linear time-periodic stiffness <italic>k</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> + <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic></sub>cos(η<italic>t</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>For the scaled system that will be used now, the following relations shall hold
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0954406212447485"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0954406212447485">3</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0954406212447485">4</xref>) are still valid, but all symbols denote dimensionless quantities, including time <italic>t</italic> and deflections <italic>q</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>. Damping parameters <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub> will be defined and introduced later, since the first study will be carried out for a conservative system.</p>
<p>For the conservative system without parametric excitation the eigenvalue problem
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0954406212447485"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
is defined. The eigenfrequencies <inline-formula id="ilm3-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the corresponding eigenvectors <bold>Φ</bold> = [Φ<sub>1</sub>, Φ<sub>2</sub>, Φ<sub>3</sub>] can be calculated numerically from equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0954406212447485">6</xref>) by standard routines. For the parameter set as defined by equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954406212447485">5</xref>) one obtains the following results
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0954406212447485"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0954406212447485"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0954406212447485"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0954406212447485"><title>Conservative system with parametric excitation</title>
<p>So far, parametric excitation near parametric anti-resonance frequencies has been studied only for systems with dissipation. A good reason for including dissipative effects in the models is found in Tondl's study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954406212447485">6</xref></sup> where it is proven that vibration suppression near a parametric anti-resonance frequency is only possible if damping is present in the system. However, to get more insight into the <italic>Tondl Effect</italic> it is educational to study a conservative system.</p>
<p>For the consideration of a conservative system we set <bold>C</bold> = <bold>0</bold> in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0954406212447485">3</xref>). All other parameters and symbols are non-dimensional quantities according to definitions in equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954406212447485">5</xref>). First, we will analyze the torsional vibration system in the time domain, starting from chosen initial conditions.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212447485">Figure 2</xref> shows time series of the nodal deflections <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>q</italic><sub>3</sub> of the system. For the results in the left column, the mode shape of the first vibrational mode was chosen as the initial condition (IC). Within the first 200 time units undamped free vibrations occur at Ω<sub>1</sub> = 0.445, with vibration amplitudes <italic>q</italic><sub>3,max</sub> &gt; <italic>q</italic><sub>2,max</sub> &gt; <italic>q</italic><sub>1,max</sub> because of the specific shape of the first mode. Then, at <italic>t</italic> = 200 = <italic>t</italic><sub>200</sub> parametric stiffness excitation <italic>k</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = 1 + 0.2 cos(η<italic>t</italic>) is turned on, with frequency <inline-formula id="ilm4-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>802</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> being an anti-resonance combination frequency of difference type and first order. Immediately, the vibration signals change at all nodes and strong amplitude and frequency modulations occur. In the right column of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212447485">Figure 2</xref> the same signals are plotted, but the second vibrational mode is used as the initial condition of the system. Since the natural frequency Ω<sub>2</sub> = 1.247 is larger than Ω<sub>1</sub>, more vibration cycles are visible within the first 200 time units. When parametric excitation (PE) is initiated at <italic>t</italic><sub>200</sub>, again massive amplitude and frequency modulations prevail.
<fig id="fig2-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Undamped system, parametric excitation with frequency η<sub>(2−1)/1</sub> = Ω<sub>2</sub> − Ω<sub>1</sub> starts at <italic>t</italic> = 200. Time series of node deflections <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>3</sub> (top to bottom) Left column: first mode initial condition. Right column: second mode initial condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>It is a noteworthy result of the simulation results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212447485">Figure 2</xref> that the torsional vibrations in the system, after PE has been turned on, are stationary quasi-periodic oscillations that neither grow nor decay. This is in agreement with Tondl's proof that vibration suppression is not possible in a conservative system. On the other hand, it is quite obvious that PE has a significant impact on the system. In order to better demonstrate how PE affects the system, a transformation
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0954406212447485"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
is carried out, where <bold>Φ</bold> represents the modal matrix as defined in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0954406212447485">6</xref>).</p>
<p>This relation can be used to perform a coordinate transformation. Without PE the motion of the system is determined by the natural mode shapes, because the system equations are linear and not coupled. The vibration signals <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub> represent modal deflections. When PE is switched on, the equations are coupled and hence the motion of the system cannot be described in terms of these modal vibration signals. Since equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-0954406212447485">10</xref>) is still valid, it is more convenient to describe <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub> as the deflections with respect to the natural mode shapes of the time-invariant system. From that point of view, it becomes clear that the coupling of the equations of motion by PE represents the basic mechanism to transfer energy from one mode of the corresponding system without PE to another one, and vice versa. However, for the sake of simplicity, in both cases (with and without PE) the terminology ‘modal deflection’ is used, although one has to keep in mind the specific differences.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212447485">Figure 3</xref> is based on the same simulation study as used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212447485">Figure 2</xref>. However, from the nodal deflections signals <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>q</italic><sub>3</sub> the modal vibration signals <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub> were extracted. Again, the left column shows the result for a first mode IC and the right column for a second mode IC. The initial conditions can now be verified easily by examination of the respective modal vibration signal. In the left column, within the first 200 time units, only signal <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub> of the first vibrational mode is not zero, in the right column the same holds for the signal <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> of the second vibrational mode. After PE is switched on with a PE-frequency of <inline-formula id="ilm5-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>802</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, vibrations of the respective other mode are initiated. It is now easy to recognize that while one mode reaches peak amplitudes the amplitudes of another mode are decreasing and may almost vanish for a short period of time. This alternating increase and decrease of the vibration level of one mode while the other mode shows the same behavior but with opposite phase, suggests that a periodic energy transfer takes place between two associated modes. Signal <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub> for the third mode becomes non-zero when PE is turned on, but stays very low and does not play a role in the vibration exchange.
<fig id="fig3-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Undamped system, parametric excitation with frequency η<sub>(2−1)/1</sub> = Ω<sub>2</sub> − Ω<sub>1</sub> starts at <italic>t</italic> = 200. Time series of modal deflections <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub> (top to bottom) Left column: first mode initial condition. Right column: second mode initial condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Having the modal deflections <bold>u</bold> and velocities <inline-formula id="ilm6-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> readily available, it is a simple task to calculate kinetic and potential energy contained in each mode at any point in time. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212447485">Figure 4</xref> shows accordingly arranged results, based on the time series shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212447485">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212447485">3</xref>. The diagrams on top show the dimensionless energy contained in the first vibrational mode, the diagrams below hold for the second mode. The energy content of mode #3 is very minor and therefore not shown. At the bottom, the total energy of the system is plotted, which basically is the sum of the energies contained in all three modes.
<fig id="fig4-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Undamped system, parametric excitation with frequency η<sub>(2−1)/1</sub> = Ω<sub>2</sub> − Ω<sub>1</sub> starts at <italic>t</italic> = 200. Time series of vibrational energy <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub> of mode 1, 2 and of total energy <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub> (top to bottom). Left column: first mode initial condition. Right column: second mode initial condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In agreement with the previous results one can see that the energy contained in one mode peaks when the energy contained in the other mode vanishes. This energy exchange is quasi-periodic with a frequency of ω<sub><italic>EE</italic></sub> = 0.0335, which is much lower compared with the natural frequencies of the system or the PE-frequency applied. The time history of the total energy reveals a very interesting detail. In the diagram on the left, which holds for first mode initial condition, the total energy starts at a value of <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic> = 0) = 0.1. At <italic>t</italic><sub>200</sub>, when PE is turned on, the total energy increases rapidly and reaches a peak value of about <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub> = 0.32. The initial increase of energy to this high value occurs because the second mode not only absorbs the energy contained in the first mode, but is also pumped up with additional energy provided by the parametric stiffness excitation. What follows is a quasi-periodic cycle of decrease and increase of the total energy contained in the system, caused by the time-periodic stiffness variation. During that period energy is not only transferred between the first and the second mode. Since the total energy also changes periodically within the interval <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = [0.08,…, 0.32], energy is periodically pumped into and retrieved from the system by the time-periodic change of the stiffness parameter. The average value of the total energy during the cyclic energy variation remains constant at approximately <inline-formula id="ilm7-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>tot</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>avg</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, but is increased to about twice the energy level <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub>(0) = 0.1 before PE is activated.</p>
<p>Basically, the interpretation of results as discussed for the left diagram also holds for the total energy diagram on right hand side. However, there is one interesting difference to be mentioned. The initial value of energy introduced to the system by using the mode shape of the second mode as initial conditions is almost the peak value when PE is activated and energy variation starts. In fact, during parametric excitation the average value of the total energy drops from <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub>(0) = 0.8 down to approximately <inline-formula id="ilm8-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>tot</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>avg</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This result shows that the quasi-periodic energy cycle may be established on a higher or a lower energy level, compared to the total energy initially contained in the system.</p>
<p>In the previous analysis the modal parameters of the time-invariant (TI) system were used for the modal decomposition of the vibration signals <italic>q</italic><sub>1,2,3</sub> of the conservative time-periodic (TP) system. While in the autonomous TI-system only the three natural frequencies Ω<sub>1,2,3</sub> can exist, other frequencies may be generated in the TP-system by parametric stiffness excitation. Therefore, the signals <italic>u</italic><sub>1,2,3</sub> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212447485">Figure 3</xref> may not be single-frequency signals after PE was activated. In order to look at the frequency content of the vibration signals, spectrograms were computed from the deflection signals. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212447485">Figure 5</xref> shows such diagrams for the deflection signal <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub> at node 1. As with the previous figures, the diagram to the left holds for first mode IC and the diagram to the right for second mode IC. Signal amplitudes are represented by color intensity, with dark color indicating high and light color low amplitudes.
<fig id="fig5-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Undamped system, parametric excitation with frequency η<sub>(2−1)/1</sub> = Ω<sub>2</sub> − Ω<sub>1</sub> starts at <italic>t</italic> = 200. Spectrogram of deflection signal <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub> at node 1. Left: first mode initial condition. Right: second mode initial condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Within the time period before PE is activated at <italic>t</italic><sub>200</sub>, the spectrograms show that the signals are single frequency signals according to the respective mode that was used as initial condition. After <italic>t</italic><sub>200</sub> the two other natural frequencies appear in the spectrogram, with Ω<sub>3</sub> having significantly lower amplitudes than Ω<sub>1,2</sub>. It is typical that the bandwidth on the frequency axis becomes wider for the initial vibration frequency as soon as PE is activated. This shows that some frequency modulation occurs in the TP-system. However, amplitude modulation is much more pronounced and can be seen easily from the periodic change of color when following a single frequency along the time axis. From the spectrograms it is also easy to recognize the alternating increase and decrease of amplitudes for different frequencies.</p>
<p>So far, the study was carried out for the PE-frequency <inline-formula id="ilm9-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math9-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that is a combination of the first and the second natural frequency of the TI-system. To verify that the conclusions drawn are also valid for other anti-resonance frequencies, now <inline-formula id="ilm10-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math10-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>357</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is used as the PE-frequency. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406212447485">Figure 6</xref> shows the deflection signals <italic>q</italic><sub>1,2,3</sub> in the left column of plots and the modal signals <italic>u</italic><sub>1,2,3</sub> in the right column. Again, the first mode shape is used as the initial deflection. As expected, alternating vibrations now occur between the first and the third mode while the second mode participates only very little. From the amplitude modulation, which is nearly perfectly periodic for both modes, one can assume that an almost ideal vibration energy transfer occurs in that case. Hence, this result is another good example to demonstrate that parametric excitation at a combination resonance frequency of the difference type basically initiates alternating vibrations and vibration energy exchange of the two modes involved.
<fig id="fig6-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Undamped system, parametric excitation with frequency η<sub>(3−1)/1</sub> = Ω<sub>3</sub> − Ω<sub>1</sub> starts at <italic>t</italic> = 200, initial condition is first mode. Left column: Time series of node deflections <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>3</sub> (top to bottom) Right column: Time series of modal deflections <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub> (top to bottom).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>At the end of this section on the conservative system, a final instructive study is presented. The purpose is to demonstrate that parametric stiffness excitation can be used to transfer vibration energy from one mode to another, and to keep it there. The first part, namely the energy transfer, has been demonstrated already. Therefore, we use again <inline-formula id="ilm11-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math11-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the PE-frequency and the first mode shape as initial condition. But other than with the results shown in the left column of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212447485">Figures 2</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212447485">5</xref>, parametric excitation is turned off at <italic>t</italic> = 1050, just when the modal deflection <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub> is almost zero and <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> reaches a maximum value. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406212447485">Figure 7</xref> shows the time series of the modal deflections and the total energy, along with the spectrogram of signal <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub>. As expected, after turning off PE, the system behaves again as a TI-system, with vibrations according to the vibration levels just when PE was turned off. Since at this point in time almost all energy was contained in the second mode, the system continues to vibrate almost exclusively in the second mode. This can be seen from the time series as well as from the spectrogram. Some first and third mode vibrations also continue to persist, since energy is preserved in the system. Due to the fact that PE is switched off when the total energy reaches a peak value, not only has the vibration energy of the first mode been transferred to the second mode, also an increase of energy in the system has occurred because PE had pumped energy into the system just before switching off.
<fig id="fig7-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Undamped system, parametric excitation with frequency η<sub>(2−1)/1</sub> = Ω<sub>2</sub> − Ω<sub>1</sub> within interval <italic>t</italic> = 200/1050. Initial condition is first mode. Left: Spectrogram of deflection signal <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub> at node 1. Right column: Time series of modal deflections <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> and of total energy <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub> (top to bottom).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>So far it was shown that parametric excitation can be used to transfer energy from one mode to another. Extensive work on targeted energy transfer was done by Vakakis and others,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954406212447485">26</xref></sup> who successfully used essentially nonlinear elements to bring about the transfer of vibration energy in a mechanical system. To analyze the capabilities of parametric excitation to effectively suppress vibrations, the effect of damping is included in the mechanical model for the following investigations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954406212447485"><title>Damped system with parametric excitation</title>
<p>The system under investigation is the same as in the previous section, but viscous damping elements are added between the nodes of the model. The parameters of the relative damping elements are chosen to be all the same <italic>c</italic><sub>01</sub> = <italic>c</italic><sub>12</sub> = <italic>c</italic><sub>23</sub> = 0.025. This leads to damping ratios ξ<sub>1</sub> = 0.0056, ξ<sub>2</sub> = 0.0156 and ξ<sub>3</sub> = 0.0225 of the three modes. For this system damped free vibrations are computed, starting from the mode shape of the first mode. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212447485">Figure 8</xref>.
<fig id="fig8-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>System with damping <italic>c</italic><sub>01</sub> = <italic>c</italic><sub>12</sub> = <italic>c</italic><sub>23</sub> = 0.025, initial condition is first mode. Time series of modal deflections <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub> and of total energy <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub> (top to bottom). Left column: No parametric excitation. Right column: PE-frequency <inline-formula id="ilm12-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math12-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The left column of plots holds for the TI-system with no parametric excitation and is included primarily for comparison. The vibration signal <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub> of the first mode shows the familiar exponential decay, and so does the total energy <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>tot</italic></sub>. Other modes are not excited by the IC and therefore the deflection signals are zero and these modes do not contribute to the overall energy in the system.</p>
<p>The diagrams in the right column of plots are obtained by the same procedures as for the results in the previous section. After an initial period of 200 time units, parametric excitation with frequency <inline-formula id="ilm13-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math13-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and amplitude <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic></sub> = 0.2<italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> is activated and stays on for the remaining period. Immediately after <italic>t</italic><sub>200</sub>, second mode vibrations start to grow, while first mode vibrations change only a little. Energy transfer also starts immediately and at first energy is extracted from the system, but this changes quickly and subsequently some energy is pumped into the system by PE. However, as more and more energy is transferred from the first to the second mode, energy dissipation increases rapidly due to the higher damping ratio of the second mode. As a consequence, at <italic>t</italic> = 400 the total energy of the system is reduced to almost zero and only very small vibrations of the first mode remain. Since PE is still active, energy transfer continues and second mode vibrations grow again to some extent, only to decay quickly. At <italic>t</italic> = 600, vibrations have practically vanished and all signals are down to zero level.</p>
<p>Obviously, the benefit from initiating an energy transfer by parametric stiffness excitation lies in the increased capability of energy dissipation of the second mode, compared to the first mode. This advantage even compensates for the energy that is temporarily pumped into the system by parametric excitation. The gain in vibration suppression is significant if one compares the results from the TI-system and the TP-system. At <italic>t</italic> = 600, amplitudes of signal <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub> are still about 25% of the initial deflection, whereas vibrations in the TP-system have vanished. Even at <italic>t</italic> = 1000, the amplitudes exceed the local maximum of amplitudes at <italic>t</italic> = 400 of the parametrically excited system.</p>
<p>As the underlying main mechanism of parametric vibration suppression has been explained, one aspect must not be overlooked. If the initial conditions of the system are dominated by vibrations of a mode with higher damping, only little benefit, if at all, can be expected when energy transfer between this mode and another mode with lower damping capabilities is initiated. Therefore, a study using parametric excitation with frequency <inline-formula id="ilm14-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math14-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> will not give as good results as above, if the second mode shape is used as the IC. Nevertheless, other anti-resonance frequencies may exist that can be used in such cases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954406212447485"><title>Drivetrain with parametric excitation and self-excitation</title>
<p>In the previous section we demonstrated that energy transfer based on parametric excitation (PE) can improve the decay of free vibrations in damped mechanical systems with chain topology. Serious problems in actual drive systems, however, may be caused by self-excited vibrations. In Tondl,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954406212447485">6</xref></sup> Tondl and Ecker<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954406212447485">7</xref></sup> and Nabergoj and Tondl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0954406212447485">8</xref></sup> and other references it was already shown that PE can also be used to suppress self-excited vibration. We will now investigate how PE can be utilized to avoid self-excited vibrations in drivetrains.</p>
<p>Drivetrains experience torsional vibrations caused by various reasons, with self-sustained vibrations due to a self-excitation mechanism being one of them. Frequently, such a self-excitation mechanism is based on a stick-slip motion phenomenon that may be very persisting and difficult to deal with. As an example, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212447485">Figure 9</xref> shows the sketch of a mechanical system representing a typical configuration of a drivetrain of a rolling mill. It consists of the electrical drive engine, the drive shaft and the mill stand. Typically, the self-excitation mechanism is situated where a linear and an oscillatory motion are interconnected. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212447485">Figure 9</xref> this location would be between the ingot, which is threaded in or out, and the upper and lower work roll. Other drivetrains in paper mills, conveying systems, etc. have a similar structure.
<fig id="fig9-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of a drivetrain of a rolling mill.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig9.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>For the sake of simplicity, only three torsional degrees of freedom, representing drive engine, shaft and work rolls, are taken into account, see Roberts,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954406212447485">27</xref></sup> for example. A sketch of the mechanical model is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406212447485">Figure 10</xref>, which is basically an extension of the previously employed model of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212447485">Figure 1</xref>. To take self-excitation into account, a damping element <italic>SE</italic> with negative parameter <inline-formula id="ilm15-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math15-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>&lt;0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is inserted between node 3 and the inertia reference frame. Since self-excitation is basically a mechanism to feed energy into the system, negative damping is a commonly used and simple way to model such a mechanism. New damping elements <italic>c</italic><sub>0<italic>i</italic></sub> are introduced to represent not only relative damping in the drivetrain but also absolute damping between rotating and stationary parts.
<fig id="fig10-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Minimal model of a drivetrain under the influence of a self-excitation (SE) mechanism, driven by a PD-controlled electrical motor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In the model of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406212447485">Figure 10</xref> node 1 represents the electrical motor and <italic>I</italic><sub>1</sub> its mass moment of inertia. Torque is generated between the rotor and the stator via magnetic forces. For speed control these forces need to be controlled by a feedback loop. Depending on the type of electrical motor and operation requirements various kinds of controllers are used. A widely used simple but nevertheless capable controller is the PID-controller. The control error is computed by comparing the measured signal with a reference variable. The proportional part of the control algorithm determines the required torque directly from the control error by multiplying the error with the proportional gain. The derivative part uses the time derivative of the error together with a time constant. The integral part calculates the control signal from the integrated control error over time. The mechanical analogy of the P-term of the PID-controller is stiffness, and of the D-term it is viscous damping. There is no analogy for the I-term.</p>
<p>Since the proportional gain of a P-controller can be interpreted as a generalized stiffness parameter, it is quite obvious how to realize parametric excitation in such a drive system. Usually the proportional gain is a constant parameter. By using a time-periodic proportional gain it is rather simple to introduce parametric stiffness excitation to the system. As this is the only PE considered, the derivative gain remains a constant parameter. Parametric excitation via damping is not effective, see Dohnal,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954406212447485">15</xref></sup> and also beyond the scope of this study.</p>
<p>The P-term and the D-term of the PID-controller represent the fast dynamics, whereas the response of the I-term is slow and only needed to compensate a permanent control error. For this basic study with the focus on self-excited vibrations and dynamic stability it is therefore acceptable to disregard the I-term and employ PD-control only.</p>
<p>For the drivetrain model as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954406212447485">Figure 10</xref> and as described above, the equations of motion equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0954406212447485">3</xref>) are still valid and only the system matrices as given in equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0954406212447485">4</xref>) need to be modified accordingly. In the stiffness matrices <bold>K</bold> and <bold>K</bold><sub><bold><italic>pe</italic></bold></sub> the variable <italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> is equivalent to the effective proportional gain of the controller <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>PE</italic></sub> ≡ <italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub>. The newly introduced absolute damping elements require additional terms in the main diagonal of the damping matrix <bold>C</bold>. Equivalent damping <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> generated by the D-term of the controller needs to be added in the appropriate matrix element, which becomes <italic>C</italic>(1,1) = (<italic>c</italic><sub>01</sub> + <italic>c</italic><sub>12</sub> + <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>). Finally, self-excitation is accounted for in the same way by adding SE-parameter <inline-formula id="ilm16-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math16-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to matrix element <inline-formula id="ilm17-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math17-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>23</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>Since no specific drivetrain is under investigation and in order to make results comparable, we simply continue to use the non-dimensional parameters <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub> as defined in equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954406212447485">5</xref>). The damping parameters <italic>c</italic><sub>0<italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>−1,<italic>i</italic></sub>, and the self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm18-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math18-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> will be set when needed.</p>
<p>First, we investigate the time-invariant system <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> = const. with self-excitation and calculate stability limits as a function of various damping parameters. A numerical method based on Floquet theory is used, where the eigenvalues of the monodromy matrix are computed, see Verhulst<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954406212447485">28</xref></sup> for example. The largest eigenvalue determines whether the system is stable or not. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406212447485">Figure 11</xref> shows two stability maps. The map to the left shows the damping parameter <italic>c</italic><sub>02</sub> (broken line) as a function of the self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm19-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math19-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on the stability threshold. The solid line holds for all dampers <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> = <italic>c</italic><sub>12</sub> = <italic>c</italic><sub>23</sub> ≠ 0 having the same value. All other dampers are set to zero, <italic>c</italic><sub>0<italic>i</italic></sub> = 0. Left to the respective threshold lines parameter combinations (<italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,<italic>j</italic></sub>, <inline-formula id="ilm20-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math20-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) for an unstable system are obtained, to the right the combinations lead to a stable system. The diagram to the right is similar to read, holding for single damping parameter <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> and for single relative damping <italic>c</italic><sub>12</sub>. Results for a single damper <italic>c</italic><sub>23</sub> are not shown since the stability area is even smaller than that for damper <italic>c</italic><sub>12</sub>. For a single damper <italic>c</italic><sub>03</sub> it is clear that the stability threshold is defined by <inline-formula id="ilm21-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math21-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.
<fig id="fig11-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>System without parametric excitation. Self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm22-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math22-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>se</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the stability limit as a function of various damping parameters. Other damping parameters are set to zero.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig11.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Obviously, absolute dampers are more effective than relative dampers, and the closer an absolute damper is installed to the source of self-excitation the better. In a drive system, absolute dampers are in general difficult to install and/or increase the power needed for the drive. Therefore, one prefers to rely on material damping in shafts and couplings, and on damping provided by the D-part of the controller. Since structural damping may be very low, we set all damping parameters <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,<italic>j</italic></sub> = 0 except for <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> ≠ 0 and study how much damping has to be provided by the PD-controller to stabilize the system. For the TI-system this result is plotted in both diagrams of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954406212447485">Figure 12</xref> as a dashed line, being the same as the solid line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406212447485">Figure 11</xref> (right). One can conclude that damping provided by the PD-controller is definitely one of the least effective options for the time-invariant system.
<fig id="fig12-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>System with parametric excitation. Self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm23-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math23-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>se</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the stability limit as a function of damping parameter <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>. Left: <inline-formula id="ilm24-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math24-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Right: <inline-formula id="ilm25-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math25-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig12.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The activation of parametric excitation by introducing a time-periodic proportional gain parameter of the PD-controller, just as the TP-stiffness parameter in the previous sections, changes the picture significantly. Since we now deal with a LTP-system, a different procedure is needed to determine the stability of the system. The following results are obtained by calculating the eigenvalues of the monodromy matrix, see Verhulst<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954406212447485">28</xref></sup> for details. The diagram to the left in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954406212447485">Figure 12</xref> holds for a parametric stiffness excitation of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = 1 + 0.2 cos(η <italic>t</italic>) with a PE-frequency <inline-formula id="ilm26-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math26-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. As one can see, the stability threshold (solid line) drops down and the region of stability (white area) increases significantly. Especially for damping parameters near <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> = 0.1 it is possible to stabilize the system even if the self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm27-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math27-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> increases by more than three times from −0.02 to −0.07. While there is clearly an optimal value for the damping parameter <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>, PE is beneficial within the entire range of the damping parameter. The figure to the right holds for another anti-resonance frequency <inline-formula id="ilm28-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math28-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that was effective in the study shown in the previous section. Again, the stability area can be increased significantly for all values of <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>, but the gain is less compared to using the PE-frequency <inline-formula id="ilm29-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math29-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>To study which PE-frequencies can be applied to reduce the necessary damping <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>, the stability threshold was calculated as a function of the PE-frequency η and <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954406212447485">Figure 13</xref>. The diagram holds for a fixed value of the self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm30-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math30-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Except for <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> no other damping is active in the system. One can see that only the anti-resonances <inline-formula id="ilm31-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math31-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="ilm32-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math32-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> lead to reduced requirements for the damping parameter <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>. Parametric resonances can also be identified in the diagram. The main parametric resonance is 2Ω<sub>1</sub>, but also two combination resonances <inline-formula id="ilm33-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math33-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="ilm34-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math34-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> require additional damping to stabilize the TP-system.
<fig id="fig13-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>System with self-excitation <inline-formula id="ilm35-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math35-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and parametric excitation. Damping parameter <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub>, at the stability limit as a function of PE-frequency η<sup><italic>PE</italic></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig13.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Until now, the amplitude of the parametric excitation has always been set to <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic></sub> = κ<italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> = 0.2. As the parametric stiffness excitation is realized by a time-periodic gain of the controller, the only limitation to the amplitude is due to saturation of the actuating variable. Therefore one is interested in the possible performance of PE as a function of the PE-amplitude. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0954406212447485">Figure 14</xref> two diagrams show the relation between the PE-amplitude and the critical SE-parameter <inline-formula id="ilm36-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math36-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the stability threshold. In the diagram to the left, one can see that for single damping <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> the PE-amplitude can be increased up to κ<italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> ≤ 0.38 for maximum performance. A further increase is not advised, since the parametric resonance <inline-formula id="ilm37-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math37-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>pr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is close to the anti-resonance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0954406212447485">Figure 13</xref>) is also enhanced and conflicts with the anti-resonance. The diagram to the right holds for <inline-formula id="ilm38-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math38-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. For small PE-amplitudes the performance is almost the same as for <inline-formula id="ilm39-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math39-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, but with increasing amplitude the performance rate is not as good. Nevertheless, also this PE-frequency may be used to suppress self-excited vibrations.
<fig id="fig14-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p>System with damping <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> = 0.2 and parametric excitation η<sup><italic>PE</italic></sup>. Self-excitation parameter <inline-formula id="ilm40-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math40-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the stability limit as a function of PE-amplitude <inline-formula id="ilm41-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math41-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>01</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> . Left: <inline-formula id="ilm42-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math42-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Right: <inline-formula id="ilm43-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math43-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig14.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>So far, the analysis of this hypothetic drivetrain relied on stability studies. To demonstrate the vibration suppression capabilities, we carry out a final study in the time domain, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0954406212447485">Figure 15</xref>. To facilitate the comparison with previous simulation results, the parameters <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> = 0.2 (equivalent to <italic>c</italic><sub>01</sub>) and <inline-formula id="ilm44-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math44-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are chosen such that the self-excited system operates at the stability threshold, see the right diagram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954406212447485">Figure 11</xref>. Since the first mode is at the stability limit, first mode vibrations occur initially. Parametric excitation is activated only in the time interval [200 ≤ <italic>t</italic> ≤ 500]. To also demonstrate the possibility of multi-frequency parametric excitation, both anti-resonance frequencies <inline-formula id="ilm45-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math45-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="ilm46-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math46-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are in use, with each PE-amplitude set to <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic></sub> = κ<italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub> = 0.2.
<fig id="fig15-0954406212447485" position="float"><label>Figure 15.</label><caption><p>System with damping <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>PD</italic></sub> = 0.2, self-excitation <inline-formula id="ilm47-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math47-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>03</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and dual parametric excitation <inline-formula id="ilm48-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math48-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="ilm49-0954406212447485"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math49-0954406212447485"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> within interval <italic>t</italic> = 200 to 500. Initial condition is first mode. Left: Spectrogram of deflection signal <italic>q</italic><sub>1</sub> at node 1. Right: Time series of modal deflections <italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>3</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212447485-fig15.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>From the plots of the modal deflections <italic>u</italic><sub>1,2,3</sub> one can see that vibrations in the first mode decay rapidly when PE is activated, while second and third mode vibrations start and increase first. However, due to the higher damping ratio of mode #2 and #3 these vibrations also decay quickly, and almost all vibrations have vanished when PE is turned off. In the spectrogram one can also see an increase and decrease of amplitudes for the natural frequencies Ω<sub>1,2,3</sub>, but temporarily also some amplitudes at other frequencies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954406212447485" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In the first part results are obtained and discussed from a study on free vibrations of a generic conservative time-periodic torsional vibration system with parametric stiffness excitation. A more realistic, but still hypothetical drive system is investigated in the second part of this contribution. Negative damping is introduced as a simple but commonly used mechanism to generate self-excitation that may cause the system to become unstable. It is shown that in a conventional time-independent drive system, a comparatively significant amount of damping is needed to stabilize the self-excited system. Especially when positive damping can only be provided by material damping of shafts and couplings it may be difficult to generate sufficient damping to compensate for the equivalent negative damping introduced by self-excitation. Absolute damping between rotating parts and the environment would be more effective, at least when installed close to the source of self-excitation, but has the disadvantage of additional energy consumption with all consequences.</p>
<p>Therefore, making maximum use of available damping must be the ultimate goal. If the drivetrain is powered by an electrical engine, the necessary requirements are available to employ parametric excitation in order to make effective use of the damping available to the system. No matter how the speed-control of the electric motor is designed, if a deflection-proportional time-periodic drive torque can be generated, then one can mimic a time-periodic mechanical stiffness. In the case of a standard PID-controller this can be done easily by affecting the proportional gain accordingly.</p>
<p>The results of numerical studies obtained for a hypothetical drivetrain are quite impressive. Since the location of a self-excitation mechanism in a real-world drivetrain is nearly always such that the first torsional vibration mode becomes unstable, energy transfer to vibration modes with higher modal damping is possible. Parametric excitation via the control of the electrical motor is a relatively simple method to initiate that energy transfer. Since this mechanism works very effectively and has a small power consumption, it can be expected that the idea offers quite some potential for improving the dynamic behavior of drivetrain applications.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec7-0954406212447485"><title>Funding</title>
<p>The work of Dr Thomas Pumhössel was kindly supported by the Austrian Center of Competence in Mechatronics (ACCM), a K2-Center of the COMET/K2 program, which is aided by funds of the Republic of Austria and the Provincial Government of Upper Austria. The authors thank all involved partners for their support.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954406212447485"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Yamamoto T and Saito A. <italic>On the vibrations of “summed and differential types” under parametric excitation</italic>. Memoirs of the Faculty of Engieering, Nagoya University, Japan, 1970, vol. 22, No. 1, pp.54–123</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954406212447485"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Applications of the theory of impulsive parametric excitation and new treatments of general parametric excitation problems</article-title>. <source>J Appl Mech</source> <year>1973</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954406212447485"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayfeh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mook</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Nonlinear oscillations</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Interscience</publisher-name>, <year>1979</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954406212447485"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartmell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Introduction to linear, parametric and nonlinear vibrations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954406212447485"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayfeh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Linear and nonlinear structural mechanics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954406212447485"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>To the problem of quenching self-excited vibrations</article-title>. <source>Acta Technica ČSAV</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954406212447485"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Tondl A and Ecker H. Cancelling of self-excited vibrations by means of parametric excitation. In: <italic>Proceedings of ASME Design Engineering Technical Conferences (DETC)</italic>, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, 12–15 September 1999</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954406212447485"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nabergoj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-excited vibration quenching by means of parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>Acta Technica ČSAV</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954406212447485"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatimah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bifurcations in dynamical systems with parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>Dissertation</source>. <publisher-name>Utrecht University</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954406212447485"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pumhössel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A study on parametric excitation for suppressing self-excited rotor vibrations</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of Sixth International Conference on Rotor Dynamics</source>. <publisher-loc>IFToMM</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sydney, Australia</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954406212447485"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abadi</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonlinear dynamics of self-excitation in autoparametric systems</article-title>. <source>PhD Dissertation</source>. <publisher-name>Utrecht University</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954406212447485"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stability analysis of open loop stiffness control to suppress self-excited vibrations</article-title>. <source>J Vibr Control</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>643</fpage>–<lpage>669</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954406212447485"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Ecker H. <italic>Suppression of self-excited vibrations in mechanical systems by parametric stiffness excitation</italic>. ASIM Fortschrittsberichte Simulation, vol. 11, 2005</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954406212447485"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systems with periodically variable masses</article-title>. <source>Acta Technica ČSAV</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954406212447485"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Damping of mechanical systems by parametric excitation: parametric resonance and anti-resonance</article-title>. <source>Südwestdeutscher Verlag für Hochschulschriften</source> <year>2009</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954406212447485"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-excited vibration quenching in a rotor system by means of parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>Acta Technica ČSAV</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0954406212447485"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stabilization of a rigid rotor by a time-varying stiffness of the bearing mounts</article-title>. <source>Vibrations in Rotating Machinery (ed. IMechE)</source>. <publisher-loc>Suffolk, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Professional Engineering Publishing Limited</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0954406212447485"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increasing the stability threshold of a rotor by open-loop control of the bearing mount stiffness</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sawicki</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Muszynska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Proceedings of the Third International Symposium on Stability Control of Rotating Machinery</source>. <publisher-loc>Cleveland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>USA</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0954406212447485"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Beneficial effects of parametric excitation in rotor systems</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Proceedings of IUTAM Symposium on Emerging Trends in Rotor Dynamics</source>. <publisher-loc>Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>India</publisher-name>, <year>23–26 March 2009</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0954406212447485"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Supression of flow-induced vibrations by a dynamic absorber with parametric excitation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brauchli</surname></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Proceedings of 7th International Conference on Flow-Induced Vibrations – FIV2000</source>. <publisher-loc>Lucerne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Switzerland</publisher-name>, <year>19–21 June 2000</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0954406212447485"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A parametric absorber for friction-induced vibrations</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Shabana</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Proceedings of the ASME Design Engineering Technical Conference DETC2003</source>. <publisher-loc>Paper VIB-48474, Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IL</publisher-name>, <year>2–6 September 2003</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0954406212447485"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enhanced damping of a beam structure by parametric excitation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>van Campen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazurko</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Oever</surname><given-names>WPJM</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Proceedings ENOC-2005</source>. <publisher-loc>Eindhoven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Netherlands</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0954406212447485"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pumhössel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Active damping of vibrations of a cantilever beam by axial force control</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tzou</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalili</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Proceedings of 2007 ASME Design Engineering Technical Conference, ASME Paper No. IDETC2007-34638</source>. <publisher-loc>Las Vegas</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nevada</publisher-name>, <year>4–7 September 2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0954406212447485"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enhanced damping of a cantilever beam by a periodic axial force</article-title>. <source>Arch Appl Mech</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0954406212447485"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pumhössel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hehenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preserving stability properties in reduced models of time-periodic systems using proper orthogonal decomposition</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of ASME 2011 International Mechanical Engineering Congress, ASME Paper No. IMECE2011-63435</source>. <publisher-loc>Denver</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Colorado</publisher-name>, <year>11–17 November 2011</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0954406212447485"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vakakis</surname><given-names>A.F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendelman</surname><given-names>O.V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>L.A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Nonlinear targeted energy transfer in mechanical and structural systems I, II</source>. <publisher-loc>New York-Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0954406212447485"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Roberts W.L. <italic>Hot rolling of steel</italic>. New York: Marcel Dekker, 1983</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0954406212447485"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhulst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Nonlinear differential equations and dynamical systems</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>