<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EJW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spejw</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Women's Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1350-5068</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7420</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1350506812455994</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1350506812455994</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Challenging gender practices: Intersectional narratives of sibling relations and parent–child engagements in transnational serial migration</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Erel</surname><given-names>Umut</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>Helma</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Phoenix</surname><given-names>Ann</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1350506812455994">University of London, UK</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>Elaine</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1350506812455994">London South Bank University, UK</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1350506812455994">Ann Phoenix, Thomas Coram Research Unit, Institute of Education, University of London, 20 Bedford Way, London, WC1H 0AA, UK. Email: <email>a.phoenix@ioe.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Gender and Transnationalism</issue-title>
<fpage>490</fpage>
<lpage>504</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article aims to contribute to the currently sparse literature on transnational families and gender. It focuses on the retrospective accounts of Caribbean-born adults who as children were serial migrants, joining their parents in the UK following a period of separation. It considers aspects of their relationships with their siblings and with their mothers and fathers. The article illuminates what the serial migrants viewed as contradictory everyday practices that produced ‘non-shared environments’. It discusses three ways in which transnationalism appeared to be a central part of the serial migrants’ family lives. First, it was embodied. Second, it was lived as cultural difference between Caribbean-born and UK-born siblings. Third, it was reported to be evident in parental practices. The article illustrates the importance of viewing gendered narratives in a psychosocial intersectional perspective.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Intersectionality</kwd>
<kwd>narratives</kwd>
<kwd>parent–child relationships</kwd>
<kwd>psychosocial serial migrants</kwd>
<kwd>siblings</kwd>
<kwd>transnational families</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Since 1990, when <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1350506812455994">Glick Schiller and Fouron (1990)</xref> first linked the term ‘transnational’ with ‘family matters’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1350506812455994">Skrbis, 2008</xref>), there has been a steady increase in publications on ‘multi-sited’ family lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1350506812455994">Grillo, 2010</xref>) and in recognition that gender is central to transnational flows and relations. The work of emotional (and often economic) maintenance across national borders often falls to women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1350506812455994">Levitt and Glick Schiller, 2004</xref>). Feminist work on ‘transnational motherhood’, where mothers migrate in search of a better life for their families, leaving their children behind and improvising strategies for mothering at a distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1350506812455994">Hondagneu-Sotelo and Avila, 2003</xref>), has highlighted the difficulty of mothering while forging new lives in an unfamiliar country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1350506812455994">Lutz, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>As the field develops, valuable insights into the ways in which mothers and families are implicated in processes of transnational migration are being supplemented by understandings that a full picture also requires attention to children. Desires to improve children’s lives and prospects are sometimes an important reason for parental or family decisions about migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1350506812455994">Boehm, 2008</xref>). Children are also important agents within transnational families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1350506812455994">Foner, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1350506812455994">Parreñas, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1350506812455994">2005</xref>). It is now clear that experiences of transnational migration are differentiated by a number of factors, including generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1350506812455994">Foner, 2009</xref>), gender (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1350506812455994">Lutz, 2011</xref>), historical period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1350506812455994">Goulbourne et al., 2010</xref>) and nation-state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1350506812455994">Bauer and Thompson, 2006</xref>), all of which have an impact on the ways in which family lives are lived across borders. Yet, much work in the new field of transnational families treats the concept as self-evident and, as a result, has limited its analytical usefulness by obscuring its complexities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1350506812455994">Goulbourne et al., 2010</xref>). The literature on children and transnational migration remains sparse, with little research into the variety of experiences and practices at play as children and parents ‘do’ family relations. Relatively little is currently known about the place of gender in, or children’s perspectives on, the everyday practices of transnational families. There is, therefore, a need for further work on the complexities of transnational families.</p>
<p>Serial migration is quintessentially transnational. It has a long history, and continues to and from many regions of the world, often for family economic reasons. It has always been a feature of Caribbean migration both internally and externally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1350506812455994">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). The terminology in this area is confusing in that the process analysed in this article is sometimes described as ‘chain migration’. However, the metaphor of chain migration foregrounds the existence of chains linking immigrants in networks of mutual aid with each other across regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1350506812455994">Lever-Tracy and Holton, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1350506812455994">MacDonald and MacDonald, 1964</xref>), while serial migration foregrounds sequence. In the discussion that follows, serial migration is the process that occurs when parents migrate singly or together and send for other family members at a later date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350506812455994">Crawford-Brown and Rattray, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1350506812455994">Jokhan, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1350506812455994">Pottinger and Brown, 2006</xref>). Thus, the first stage in serial migration is the separation of children from their parents who migrate, and the second stage is their reunification in the new country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1350506812455994">Smith et al., 2004</xref>: 109). Since children are left behind in the care of extended families, parents maintain multiple connections (familial and societal) with their birth country. Serial migration is thus related to transnational migration because ties are maintained across nations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1350506812455994">Bauer and Thompson, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1350506812455994">Goulbourne et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1350506812455994">Levitt, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1350506812455994">2002</xref>). It is this relationship with transnational migration that is at the heart of the concept of serial migration as used in the study that informs this article.</p>
<p>This article aims to bring together the under-researched areas of Caribbean transnational families, sibling relations and adult evaluations of their childhood experiences of families reconstituted after transnational separation. It focuses on adult retrospective accounts of their gendered relationships with their siblings and with their mothers and fathers. It uses a psychosocial intersectional lens (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1350506812455994">Phoenix, 2011</xref>) to contribute to understanding of the complexity of family relations constituted through transnationalism. The article first briefly discusses the contribution that intersectionality can make to such analyses, before presenting the study that informs the article. The main part of the article discusses examples from adult retrospective narratives of their childhoods.</p>
<sec id="section1-1350506812455994">
<title>Psychosocial intersectionality as a framework for analysing complexity</title>
<p>Intersectionality as a theory has gained popularity partly because it allows an engagement with the complexity and multi-layered nature of everyday life and social categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1350506812455994">Lutz et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1350506812455994">McCall, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1350506812455994">Yuval-Davis, 2006</xref>). It eschews the notion of given ‘groups’ or ‘categories’ (such as of gender, ethnicity and class), which then intersect and instead pays attention to the fact that people are always simultaneously positioned in many categories so that there is no essence to any category. A focus on any one social category can, therefore, only be understood in the context of other categories and of differences, as well as commonalities, within groups. Experiences and life chances differ according to ‘race’, ethnicity, sexuality and social class, so that gender and sexuality are class-based and racialized social relations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1350506812455994">Anthias and Yuval-Davis, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1350506812455994">Brah, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1350506812455994">Lewis, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Intersectionality is thus a heuristic reminder that all categories are associated with power relations and cannot be neutral (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1350506812455994">Brah and Phoenix, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1350506812455994">Collins, 1998</xref>). It is a social theory of knowledge in that it is predicated on the notion of knowledge as situated and so differentiated since people occupy different social positions. At the same time, knowledge is subject to change since people always occupy multiple social positions, and positioning changes over time and according to circumstances.</p>
<p>A major site of debate among those doing intersectional analysis concerns the question of whether or not the categories that should be analysed are those that are emergent in analyses or those such as gender, racialization and social class that are predefined on the basis that they are already known to have marked effects on social positioning and power relations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1350506812455994">Tatli and Ozbilgin, 2012</xref>). This can, to some extent, be linked with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1350506812455994">Prins’s (2006)</xref> distinction between ‘systemic’ (structural) and ‘constructionist’ interpretations of intersectionality. According to Prins, the systemic approach foregrounds the impact of system or structure on the formation of identities and power relations, whereas the constructionist approach focuses on the dynamic and relational aspects of identities and power relations (and so is more likely to consider emergent categories). These approaches are not, however, necessarily antithetical in that intersectionality continues to be widely used in ways that resist standardization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1350506812455994">Crenshaw, 2011</xref>). It is possible to think of intersectionality as a productive nodal point, ‘a discursive site where different feminist positions are in critical dialogue or productive conflict with each other’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1350506812455994">Lykke, 2011</xref>: 208).</p>
<p>This article contributes to such debates by examining adult reconstructions of sibling relationships and the ways in which these are gendered, where gender is both emergent in specific transnational family contexts and an a priori category intersecting with other a priori categories such as racialization, migration and nationality. An intersectional analysis of sibling relationships allows the interrogation of commonalities and differences in the experiences of siblings living in families marked by transnational migration. While it might be considered that, as people of the same generation brought up by the same parents, only some of whom differ on gender, they are likely to share experiences, the use of an intersectional lens draws attention to the importance of treating categories and identities in non-essentialist ways. This approach is psychosocial in analysing psychological and social processes as mutually constitutive in non-determinist and non-reductionist ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1350506812455994">Psychosocial Studies Network, n.d</xref>.). Intersectionality fits with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1350506812455994">Olwig’s (2007)</xref> argument that migration has to be understood within specific contexts of interpersonal relations that impact on life trajectories and shape migrants’ attachments to place.</p>
<p>The article argues that gender is sometimes lived in stereotypic ways but, because siblings encounter varied contexts and experiences, it is also emergent in lived relations as siblings ‘do’ gender.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1350506812455994">
<title>The study</title>
<p>The narrative accounts analysed below come from a UK Economic and Social Research Council Professorial Fellowship programme of work called ‘Transforming Experiences: Re-conceptualising identities and “non-normative” childhoods’. The fellowship was concerned with the ways in which adults from different family backgrounds re-evaluate their earlier experiences over time. It aimed to help understand the factors that produce adult citizens who lead ‘normal’ lives despite having childhood experiences that are often not recognized because they do not fit expected patterns. It focused on adults from varied ethnicized groupings who grew up in three kinds of ‘non-normative’ contexts, one of which is serial migration, where the adults came as children from the Caribbean to Britain to rejoin parents (<italic>N</italic> = 53).</p>
<p>The interviews were thematically analysed to provide an overview of the findings, and some were selected for detailed narrative analysis on the basis of the particular issues they raised. Narratives are most likely to be developed when lives are ‘interrupted’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1350506812455994">Riessman, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1350506812455994">2008</xref>). This makes narrative analysis particularly suited to the study of non-normative lives. Narrative analysis also makes it possible to analyse canonical narratives about the way life ought to be lived (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1350506812455994">Bruner, 1990</xref>) and the narrative identities that are normative for a generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1350506812455994">McAdams, 2006</xref>). It has been successfully employed in research conducting intersectional analyses (see, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1350506812455994">Buitelaar, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1350506812455994">Prins, 2006</xref>). All the participants are given pseudonyms.</p>
<p>With few exceptions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1350506812455994">Chamberlain, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1350506812455994">Olwig, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1350506812455994">Olwig and Gulløv, 2003</xref>), there is little literature about Caribbean transnational childhood. Yet, there is a long historical legacy of complex family formations and movements that were initiated in the period of enslavement and, while they are dynamic, have continued to be central in the Caribbean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1350506812455994">Besson and Olwig, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1350506812455994">Goulbourne, 2002</xref>). Current Caribbean family narratives arise from this history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1350506812455994">Olwig, 2007</xref>). Children are central to many of these processes, which include child fostering and family separations and reunification, within Caribbean nations as well as transnationally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1350506812455994">Olwig and Gulløv, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Caribbean migration to the UK in relatively large numbers occurred in two main phases from the 1940s onwards. The first began during the Second World War, when Britain recruited thousands of ‘West Indians’ in support of the war effort. These recruits were predominantly men, but included a smaller number of women. While most returned to the Caribbean when the war ended in 1945, some remained. The second phase of mass Caribbean migration to the UK occurred partly in response to Britain’s labour shortages in its postwar reconstruction programme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1350506812455994">Peach, 1968</xref>), and also as a result of the deteriorating economic conditions in the ‘West Indies’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1350506812455994">Byron and Condon, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1350506812455994">Patterson, 1965</xref>). The majority of these migrants were again young males. However, the gender imbalance shifted in the 1950s, when British Rail, London Transport and the new National Health hospitals actively recruited in the Caribbean countries for both men and women staff. Subsequently, in the next few years many of those already in Britain paid for other family members to join them. In Britain, they encountered harsh racism and hostility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1350506812455994">Glass, 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1350506812455994">Patterson, 1965</xref>) and consequently began to forge a new and common ‘West Indian’ identity (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1350506812455994">Byron and Condon, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1350506812455994">Goulbourne, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>All the parents of the participants in the ‘Transforming Experiences’ study left the Caribbean between the early 1950s and mid-1960s at a time when their labour was solicited in the UK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1350506812455994">Bauer and Thompson, 2006</xref>), where they hoped to be able to make a more prosperous life, with better opportunities for their children than were open to them in their countries of birth. The age at which the participants were left behind ranged from eight months to seven years, and they rejoined their parents in the UK between the early 1960s and mid-1970s, when they were between the ages of 15 months and 17 years. The period of separation ranged between six months and 14 years. At the time of interview the mean age of these men and women was 50 years.</p>
<p>Since serial migration was common in Caribbean countries at the time, it was not considered ‘non-normative’ in the countries in which the participants had been born, or in their social circles. The impact of serial migration is mostly still poorly understood, but is reported to have marked (often negative) impacts on children and their family relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1350506812455994">Arnold, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1350506812455994">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1350506812455994">Chamberlain, 2006</xref>). There is some North American evidence that many children who have experienced it feel a degree of unhappiness in childhood, sometimes have difficult relationships with their parents and attain poorly in education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1350506812455994">Smith et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1350506812455994">
<title>Predefined categorical gender narratives</title>
<p>Many participants who had been serial migrants reported gender-differentiated sibling experiences. Their experiences fit with findings from the general population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1350506812455994">Bonke, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350506812455994">Crouter et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1350506812455994">Edwards et al., 2006</xref>) in that women generally said that their brothers had been privileged by being given fewer housework tasks and that their parents frequently justified this by appeal to gender differences (although several of the men reported that they had done housework as children). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1350506812455994">Reynolds (2005)</xref> found similar ideologies for African Caribbeans in the UK coexisting with ‘non-traditional’ gender practices, where mothers were employed outside the home and/or were predominantly responsible for home and childcare. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1350506812455994">Chamberlain (2006)</xref> suggests that some stories constitute formulaic genre that are part of cultural templates prescribing how life should be lived. While it may seem contradictory that ‘traditional’ gender narratives persist in the face of long-established cultural practices that would seem more gender equal, the African Caribbean psychoanalyst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1350506812455994">Barbara Fletchman Smith (2011)</xref> offers a psychosocial reading. Her analysis illuminates the historical roots of this contradiction and its contemporary legacies. Central to the system of slavery was the separating of procreation from maternity and paternity, which entailed the cruel and enforced separation of couples and of infants from their mothers. This forced women to be self-reliant and made them both resentful of, and sympathetic to, their menfolk, most of whom were not able to protect, or provide for, women and children. This cruelty-induced trauma led to the development of new kinds of family patterns in the Caribbean that began during slavery and have persisted since. The emotional legacy Smith identifies is contradictory, consisting of valorization and denigration of black boys and men and contradictory gender narratives and practices. While there have been many changes in Caribbean family life since slavery ended, the legacy of enslavement continues to affect family structures, the psychological life of Caribbean people and the relationships between African Caribbean men and women and parents and children. Smith’s conceptualization of this trauma as circular provides an explanation for why ‘traditional’ gender patterns are stubbornly persistent and narratives of gender difference are canonical. Gendered patterns thus have to be viewed in intersection with historical and geographical processes and positioning in relation to legacies of enslavement as well as racialization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1350506812455994">
<title>Psychosocial gendered intersections in serial migration</title>
<p>While there are contradictions in Caribbean gender relations, gender is not the only category of relevance to sibling relations in serial migration. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1350506812455994">Smith et al. (2004</xref>: 111) suggest that:
<disp-quote>
<p>In addition to age, the presence of siblings born to parents in the new country or of new spouses may complicate reunion. Having strangers present in the home may add to the child’s discomfort. . . . The emigrant child may feel separated from the family unit. . . . He or she may have to contend with preferential treatment by parents of the children born in the host country, feelings of jealousy toward new siblings, and sibling conflicts over cultural differences. Furthermore, the emigrant child may be rejected by the stepparent or, conversely, he or she may reject the stepparent’s authority. . . . The new arrival may come to feel unwanted and become distrustful and resentful of family members. . . . Strained relations between the child and new family members may contribute to the failure of reunion.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In the study reported here three, sometimes overlapping, factors of relevance to gender in transnational families were presented in narratives about relationships with parents and siblings: familiarity with parents and/or siblings; jealousy between siblings; and cultural differences between Caribbean-born and UK-born siblings.</p>
<sec id="section5-1350506812455994">
<title>Familiarity with parents and siblings</title>
<p>One of the major shifts in work on siblings over the last three decades concerns the theorization of sibling environments as non-shared (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1350506812455994">Dunn and Plomin, 1990</xref>). Gender is central to sibling relationships (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1350506812455994">Edwards et al., 2005</xref>) and, because gendered sibling configurations are patterned in a variety of ways and intersect with other categories such as age, social class, ethnicization and racialization, there are multiple cross-cutting commonalities and differences in sibling experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1350506812455994">Edwards et al., 2006</xref>). These are complicated for serial migration, which frequently differentiates siblings in terms of how well they know their parents and each other. In consequence, how children ‘do’ gender in relation to their mothers, fathers and siblings partly depends on familiarity. Gender is relevant, but is continually decentred by other social positions.</p>
<p>In the extract below, the woman speaker accounts for the difference between her close relationship with her father and her brother’s distance from him by explaining that she had established a relationship with her father before he left:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Shirley:</speaker>
<p>My brother was born a month after my father left and he was 12 years old when he met his father and they had no relationship at all, and I had my father for the first five years of my life, so I had a really close relationship with him when he was in Jamaica. And I was left with his mother who idolises him so arriving here, I knew him, I just can’t imagine how my father must have felt about his son that he hadn’t met for 12 years. So it must have been really difficult. (Serial migration study, Focus Group 2)</p>
</speech>
<p>A crucial category intersecting with serial migration here then is familiarity and opportunities to keep parents positively in mind, through contact or family myths. In the extract below, Monica draws distinctions between her poor relationship with her brother and her better relationship with her sister, but attributes this to how they are positioned in relation to shared histories and racialization, rather than gender:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Monica:</speaker>
<p>I followed my parents . . . I was almost 13 and yes, I have a brother who was born here who, apart from his black skin, he’s white. And he thinks he’s everything British about him and you can’t say anything. He thinks I’m a racist but that’s the thing about it, he doesn’t understand where we’re coming from. And he was treated very differently and we see that. My sister and I get on great ’cos we can relate to growing up at home with our grandparents and also partly with my mum, because my mum came back to Jamaica and then came back. (Serial migration study, Focus Group 1)</p>
</speech>
<p>The woman in the above extract counterposes her comfortable familiarity with her sister to the lack of understanding between herself and her brother, who have little shared history and no shared culture because she is Jamaican and he is British. They are also differentiated in terms of how they position themselves in relation to racialization, so that Monica disapproves of her brother and feels that she cannot speak to him.</p>
<p>The two examples above show how starting with an intersectional category such as gender does not necessarily lead to the privileging of that category if it is not oriented to by research participants. They also show that other categories, such as shared history, familiarity, being kept in mind and racialization, can be emergent. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1350506812455994">Prins’s (2006)</xref> ‘systemic’ and ‘constructionist’ approaches can both be employed within the same research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1350506812455994">
<title>Jealousy between siblings</title>
<p>As we have seen in the examples above, lack of familiarity with siblings resulted from, and was exacerbated by, their separation. The little known about children who join families where they meet younger siblings indicates that this is a difficult process marked by jealousy and lack of relationship (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1350506812455994">Arnold, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350506812455994">Cervantes et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1350506812455994">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). In the example below Pauline shows awareness of the viewpoint of her UK-born younger sister and illustrates how siblings brought together for the first time could have unfounded expectations:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Pauline:</speaker>
<p>I was really excited when I heard we were going to have a sister, a new baby /. . . /and we, the children that were there, started talking together and thinking she was going to be white because she was born in England . . . So we were all really excited and wanting to see her and when we came over and saw her, she was the darkest of all of us . . . and I remember her standing behind my mum . . . and looking up and saying ‘Not my tisters, not my tisters’. She must have been . . . nearly three. And she looked at us and she just didn’t want us there, but mum and dad worked on all of us until we became friends and we were good friends but she was like ‘Who are you coming here to take my mum and dad away?’ (Focus Group 1)</p>
</speech>
<p>This remembered childhood episode demonstrates the importance of taking a psychosocial intersectional approach since Pauline’s disappointment with her youngest sister seems to have been as much because her expectations were dashed as because of the younger child’s negative reaction. The older sisters had become very excited because they equated being born in England with being white, and in the Caribbean post-slavery, colonial context, chromatism (assigning value on the basis of shade of skin) makes whiteness highly valued. Although Caribbean people have shared histories of European and North American colonization and of enslavement and indenture, the islands are widely scattered, vary in size, and have unique traditions, senses of individuality and particular views of the other islands and islanders. Their colonial histories have, however, produced common ideologies linked with colour-based social-class hierarchies of prejudice and privilege, with the lightest-coloured people at the top and the darkest at the bottom (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1350506812455994">Henriques, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1350506812455994">Hoetink, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1350506812455994">Lowenthal, 1972</xref>). The ‘West Indian’ middle class and elite are modelled on the British middle class, and differentiated from their working-class counterparts (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1350506812455994">Henriques, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1350506812455994">Lowenthal, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1350506812455994">Smith, 1965</xref>).</p>
<p>Pauline’s narrative is poignant because it constitutes a microcosm of societal narratives that have deep histories and socioeconomic consequences. The disappointment of meeting her sister reflects the fact that, far from enhancing their status by being white, she was the ‘darkest of all of us’. Pauline’s was a well-worn narrative in that the wording in the focus group was almost identical to that in the individual interview that preceded it by many months. Its emotional significance is shown by the vividness of the description, which treats the event almost as if it is contemporaneous, conveying both excitement and disappointment. In the individual interview, the salience and significance of chromatism to the sibling relationship was indicated in accounts of how the two older sisters teased the youngest about her darkness, which always had the desired effect of upsetting her. Both ‘sides’ of this sibling division were reported to show their dislike by tormenting each other. Luckily, however, their parents were said to have recognized the problem and worked hard to try to heal the breach by making sure they all did things together and by treating each in ways designed to show that they were highly valued members of the same family.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1350506812455994">
<title>Cultural differences between Caribbean-born and UK-born siblings</title>
<p>Academic work has moved away from viewing siblings as growing up in the same environments to focusing on ‘non-shared environments’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1350506812455994">Plomin et al., 2001</xref>). Siblings separated in serial migration are recognized to have experienced ‘non-shared environments’. In this study, those serial migrants with siblings born in the UK reported cultural differences between them as well as differences in parental treatment. This recurrent theme was generally said to have detrimental effects, as in the following extract from a focus group:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Claudette:</speaker>
<p>You see, for me, my brother was born after we came here and when I speak, my school friends, every one of them born at home [the Caribbean] had the same experience. You see, I go to my granddad, . . . and I hug, and I hug mummy [grandmother] and that. My parents never hugged. There’s none of that cuddly thing, whereas my brother, go on up to my parents, hug them up and all my friends whose siblings are born here, they have that same closeness with parents. . . .</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Frank:</speaker>
<p>Right, well the closeness, I describe it as ‘spoiltness’ because, as I said, five of us were born in [the Caribbean] and, as children, we were friends of each other. Our parents were not exclusive to any one of us. And the minute we got here – because I remember I was eleven when my sister was born – and I was really looking forward to it, I remember running home from school to see this baby in the cot. And it was the start of a little nightmare to tell the truth . . . Because all the discipline and the rules that we were brought up with didn’t apply to her at all . . . They seem to have taken away rules and boundaries that we had . . . And I remember, it created lots of divisions and that’s just how it was. (Serial migration study, Focus Group 1)</p>
</speech>
<p>In the above extract, Claudette identifies herself as part of a Caribbean-born generation and brings her peers into the conversation in order to lend support to her account that, in relation to their parents, Caribbean-born children were positioned differently than their British-born siblings. Frank amplifies her theme by suggesting that UK-born siblings were ‘spoilt’. Once again, gender remains silent in favour of intersections of place of birth, culture, migration status and parents’ differential treatment of, and attachment to, their children.</p>
<p>The following two extracts highlight that such feelings of difference produced divisions between siblings, particularly because Caribbean-born siblings felt that they were expected to do much more household work than were their British-born siblings (and sometimes given less freedom). For Corinne (in the extract below), those differences, together with differences of shared experience meant that she constructed her siblings as falling into two groups:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Corinne:</speaker>
<p>Like I mean it must happen in large families because my eldest brother (.) In fact yes it was three and three. It was definitely three and three. Because the three older ones would talk and the three little ones would talk. And the three older ones are close and the three little ones are close. Although we’re all close, but there are definitely two families in that one family.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Interviewer:</speaker>
<p>And it’s not that the four girls are close and the two boys are close? It’s not that?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Corinne:</speaker>
<p>No it isn’t . . . (Serial migration study, individual interview)</p>
</speech>
<p>Corinne’s explanation for this fissure related to whether or not the siblings had been Caribbean-born. For her, as for many of the serial migrants, Caribbean identity was important and central to their transnational experiences. As with gender, their identity constructions reflect deep historical rootedness in their countries of origin, with their sense of belonging described partially through their ‘roots’, as Hally suggests:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Hally:</speaker>
<p>I am a Bajan . . . I think you know, you should never deny your roots . . . <underline>it’s what make you who you are</underline>. If you don’t know your roots and know where you come from, I don’t think you’ll ever be (.) settled and happy . . . you’ve got to know that. And it’s something inside of you . . . It’s part of your <italic>identity</italic>. If you don’t know where you come from I think you’re <italic>lost</italic>.</p>
</speech>
<p>Jenny also signalled the importance of being born in the Caribbean for cultural practices and identity. Her extract (below) is unusual in that she mentions that her mother directly told her that her brother’s male gender exonerated him from doing housework:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Jenny:</speaker>
<p>My brother was . . . totally spoiled rotten but then he had two older sisters to spoil him. But then as you’re growing up you thought, ‘Well OK, get him to do little things around the house.’ . . . [Her mother would say] ‘Leave him alone. He’s a boy’ . . . You’d think, ‘Wait a minute. When we were <underline>his age we had to do it</underline>. Why can’t he?’. ‘No. Leave him alone’. . . . The ones born here – get away with murder, especially if they were boys. They’d do nothing . . . And the girls certainly got off a lot lighter than the girls born at home [the Caribbean], you know. And as <underline>far as our parents are concerned</underline>, no <underline>they don’t treat them any different</underline>, they <underline>don’t see it</underline>. But we do . . . that’s how it is with <underline>all</underline> my friends who I speak to. (Individual interview)</p>
</speech>
<p>From Jenny’s report, gender is relevant to the familial cultural practices that result in Caribbean-born girls being expected to do more housework than their brothers. This is not, however, the whole story and within a few sentences, Jenny’s account shows the importance of an intersectional view in that she invokes age, place of birth, birth order and shared understanding (‘<underline>all</underline> my friends’) as well as gender, as explanatory. She may be said to be drawing on an intersectional sensibility as a heuristic for explaining her childhood familial world and recognition of social complexity. In concert with many of those who reported that their parents treated Caribbean-born children less well than their British-born siblings, Jenny points out that their parents deny this difference. In order to warrant her claim, she suggests that ‘all’ her friends have the same experience. In the focus groups, when serial migrants met, they frequently co-constructed narratives about unequal treatment of this sort. Yet, they were generally sympathetic to the dilemmas and difficulties their parents had faced as migrants. They suggested, for example, that British culture, together with their social and familial circumstances, had impacted negatively on their parents’ ability to parent:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Yvonne:</speaker>
<p>Part of it, I would say, is the early impact of British culture on our parents so they were getting mixed messages about parenting. And the idea of parenting in this country was about not letting your children do anything and unfortunately for them, they didn’t always bring a balance possibly to . . . the children from the Caribbean and the children in England . . . And I suppose where children from the Caribbean knew about doing chores or whatever, they were put upon or used, called upon more heavily ’cos they had that sense of responsibility within them.</p>
<p>/. . ./Well, I suppose it [racism] broke some people down and then people started to adopt this model of parenting that was seen as ‘oh, they’re England children and in England, children, they don’t do this and they don’t do that’ . . . and so you start building up a form of exclusion and boundaries within your home anyway and coupled with bad parenting, wherever it may be, and you have these disastrous stories . . ., but it’s complex.</p>
</speech>
<p>There is one potentially amusing implication of the above discussion. While children are frequently said to be ‘caught between two cultures’, these adults constructed their parents as having been pulled between two cultures and used this to explain why parents treated their Caribbean-born and UK-born children differently. In the discussion above, as in many others, gender does not feature because other intersecting social categories (place of birth, perceptions of culture, racism and contradictory models of parenting) were viewed as more relevant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1350506812455994">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This article contributes to the currently sparse literature on both the variety of ways in which families constitute transnational spaces and the place of gender in transnational sibling relationships. In the accounts of adult serial migrants looking back on their childhoods, gender was sometimes identified as important, and occasionally as central. A psychosocial reading of participants’ accounts that foreground gender helps to historicize Caribbean gender relations and indicate why contradictory gender patterns are persistent and narratives of gender difference are canonical. However, in discussing their sibling relationships, gender was frequently decentred, in favour of other social categories and pragmatic considerations in everyday family life. Social categories (including gender) constituted resources the participants deployed in evaluating and explaining their family relations and the complex positionalities, loyalties and divisions that operated.</p>
<p>Although many of the serial migrants have become ‘British’ citizens, most also thought of themselves as belonging to a Caribbean island and had multiple identities and loyalties (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1350506812455994">Bryceson and Vuorela, 2002</xref>). Many of those with British-born siblings used differences in national identity as a resource to explain cultural differences between them. Their narratives show the historical rootedness of their views of what constitutes a ‘good’, ‘normative’ or ‘proper’ childhood, and the sustained ‘multi-stranded social relations that link together their societies of origin and settlement’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1350506812455994">Glick Schiller et al., 1995</xref>: 48) . They make the Caribbean a point of reference against which to measure their experiences in Britain and differences between themselves and their UK-born siblings.</p>
<p>The findings are consistent with research that is beginning to be done on transnational families in general and serial migration in particular. They emphasize the complexity of transnational family lives and help to take forward understanding of ‘non-shared environments’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1350506812455994">Plomin et al., 2001</xref>). In particular, they show that transnational families can be riven with contradictions in which some children experience (or are perceived to experience) privilege and preferential treatment, while others report painful experiences of unfairness and/or unsatisfactory treatment on the basis of intersections of gender and birthplace. While such feelings and experiences also divide some siblings who are not members of transnational families, they appear to be heightened in families where some of the siblings meet only when the serial migrants arrive in Britain.</p>
<p>Transnationalism appeared to be a central part of the serial migrants’ family lives in three ways. First, it was embodied as difference in, for example, reports that physical affection between parents and children was confined to British-born siblings. Second, it was lived as cultural difference in families where the simultaneity of Caribbean and UK cultures is experienced as division between siblings. Third, it was evident in parental practices that are reported to privilege UK-born children in comparison with Caribbean-born children. It seems then that for many of the reconstituted serial migrant families reported here, transnationalism is lived as difference and division. This seems contradictory, when parents have worked hard to bridge physical transnational separation by bringing their children to join them. Psychic and social differences produced through transnationalism are, however, more difficult to bridge and were reported to require time and effort to heal.</p>
<p>The findings reported here challenge essentialist understandings of gender and illuminate the fruitfulness of psychosocial intersectional approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1350506812455994">Lutz et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1350506812455994">Yuval-Davis, 2011</xref>) for analysing complex emotional positioning in sociohistorical processes. While the focus of this analysis was on gender as a predefined social category, a psychosocial intersectional sensibility also elucidated emergent categories at play in transnational serial migration.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research was funded by ESRC Professorial Fellowship, Award number: RES-051-27-0181. It is one of the data sets used for secondary analysis in the ESRC-funded Novella (Narratives of Varied Everyday Lives and Linked Approaches) node of the National Centre for Research Methods (NCRM) by Ann Phoenix, Julia Brannen and Heather Elliott. Ann Phoenix was the professorial fellow and Elaine Bauer and Stephanie Davis-Gill were research fellows on the project.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anthias</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuval-Davis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Contextualizing feminism: Gender, ethnic and class divisions</article-title>. <source>Feminist Review</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Separation and loss through immigration of African Caribbean women to the UK</article-title>. <source>Attachment and Human Development</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Working with Families of African Caribbean Origin: Understanding Issues around Immigration and Attachment</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jessica Kingsley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Jamaican Hands Across the Atlantic</source>. <publisher-loc>Kingston, Jamaica</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ian Randle</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Besson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olwig</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2005</year>) <source>Caribbean Narratives of Belonging: Fields of Relations, Sites of Identity</source>. <publisher-loc>Basingstoke</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>‘For my children’: Constructing family and navigating the state in the U.S. Mexico transnation</article-title>. <source>Anthropological Quarterly</source> <volume>81</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Children’s housework – Are girls more active than boys?</article-title> <source>International Journal of Time Use Research</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eijtur.org/pdf/volumes/eIJTUR-7-1-1_Bonke.pdf">www.eijtur.org/pdf/volumes/eIJTUR-7-1-1_Bonke.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 24 March 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Cartographies of Diaspora: Contesting Identities</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phoenix</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ain’t I a woman? Revisiting intersectionality</article-title>. <source>Journal of International Women’s Studies</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bruner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Acts of Meaning</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bryceson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vuorela</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Transnational families in the twenty-first century</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bryceson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vuorela</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Transnational Family: New European Frontiers and Global Networks</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berg</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Migration in Comparative Perspective: Caribbean Communities in Britain and France</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buitelaar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>‘I am the ultimate challenge’: Accounts of intersectionality in the life-story of a well-known daughter of Moroccan migrant workers in the Netherlands</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Women’s Studies</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cervantes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mejia</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mena</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Serial migration and the assessment of extreme and unusual psychological hardship with undocumented Latina/o families</article-title>. <source>Hispanic Journal of Behavioral Sciences</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Family Love in the Diaspora: Migration and the Anglo-Caribbean Experience</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>It’s all in the family: Intersections of gender, race, and nation</article-title>. <source>Hypatia, Journal of Feminist Philosophy</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crawford-Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rattray</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Parent–child relationships in Caribbean families</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Culturally Diverse Parent–Child and Family Relationships</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crenshaw</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Postscript</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vivar</surname><given-names>MTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Supik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Framing Intersectionality: Debates on a Multi-Faceted Concept in Gender Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Farnham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crouter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Head</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bumpus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McHale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Household chores: Under what conditions do mothers lean on daughters?</article-title> <source>New Directions for Child and Adolescent Development</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plomin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Separate Lives: Why Siblings Are So Different</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lucey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauthner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Sibling Identity and Relationships: Sisters and Brothers</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauthner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Children’s Understanding of their Sibling Relationships</source>. <publisher-loc>York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JRF</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2009</year>) <source>Across Generations: Immigrant Families in America</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1961</year>) <source>London’s Newcomers: The West Indian Migrants</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>George Allen and Unwin Ltd</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glick Schiller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fouron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>‘Everywhere we go, we are in danger’: Ti Manno and the emergence of a Haitian transnational identity</article-title>. <source>American Ethnologist</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glick Schiller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Basch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szanton</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>From immigrant to transmigrant: Theorizing transnational migration</article-title>. <source>Anthropological Quarterly</source> <volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goulbourne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Caribbean Transnational Experience</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goulbourne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Solomos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zontini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Transnational Families: Ethnicities, Identities and Social Capital</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grillo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Preface</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Goulbourne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Solomos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zontini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Transnational Families: Ethnicities, Identities and Social Capital</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>vii</fpage>–<lpage>viii</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <source>Family and Colour in Jamaica</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MacGibbon and Kee</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoetink</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>‘Race’ and color in the Caribbean</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Caribbean Contours</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>‘I’m here, but I’m there’: The meanings of Latina transnational motherhood</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Gender and US Immigration: Contemporary Trends</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>548</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jokhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Parental absence as a consequence of migration: Exploring its origins and perpetuation with special reference to Trinidad</article-title>. In: <conf-name>8th Annual Conference at the Sir Arthur Lewis Institute of Social and Economic Studies</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Trinidad</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>‘Race’, Gender, Social Welfare: Encounters in a Postcolonial Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lever-Tracy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Social exchange, reciprocity and amoral familism: Aspects of Italian chain migration to Australia</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Transnational Villagers</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The ties that change: Relations to the ancestral home over the life cycle</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Changing Face of Home: The Transnational Lives of the Second Generation</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage> .</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glick Schiller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Conceptualizing simultaneity: A transnational social field perspective on society</article-title>. <source>International Migration Review</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>145</issue>): <fpage>1002</fpage>–<lpage>1039</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowenthal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>West Indian Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The New Maids: Transnational Women and the Care Economy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vivar</surname><given-names>MTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Supik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2011</year>) <source>Framing Intersectionality: Debates on a Multi-Faceted Concept in Gender Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Farnham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lykke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Intersectional analysis: Black box or useful critical feminist thinking technology?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vivar</surname><given-names>MTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Supik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Framing Intersectionality: Debates on a Multi-Faceted Concept in Gender Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Farnham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>The Redemptive Self: Stories Americans Live by</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The complexity of intersectionality</article-title>. <source>Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1771</fpage>–<lpage>1800</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Chain migration, ethnic neighbourhood formation and social networks</article-title>. <source>The Milbank Memorial Fund Quarterly</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olwig</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Narratives of the children left behind</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olwig</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Caribbean Journeys: An Ethnography of Migration and Home in Three Family Networks</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC and London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Olwig</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gulløv</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2003</year>) <source>Children’s Places: Cross-Cultural Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parreñas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mothering from a distance: Emotions, gender, and intergenerational relations in Filipino transnational families</article-title>. <source>Feminist Studies</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parreñas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Long distance intimacy: Class, gender and intergenerational relations between mothers and children in Filipino transnational families</article-title>. <source>Global Networks</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <source>Dark Strangers: A Study of West Indians in London</source>. <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <source>West Indian Migration to Britain: A Social Geography</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phoenix</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Psychosocial intersections: Contextualising the accounts of adults who grew up in visibly ethnically different households</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vivar</surname><given-names>MTH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Supik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Framing Intersectionality: Debates on a Multi-Faceted Concept in Gender Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Farnham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plomin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asbury</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Why are children in the same family so different? Nonshared environment a decade later</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Psychiatry</source> <volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pottinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Understanding the impact of parental migration on children: Implications for counseling families from the Caribbean</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://counselingoutfitters.com/Pottinger.htm">counselingoutfitters.com/Pottinger.htm</ext-link> <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage> (accessed <day>29</day> <month>June</month> <year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prins</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Narrative accounts of origins: A blind spot in the intersectional approach?</article-title> <source>European Journal of Women’s Studies</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Psychosocial Studies Network</collab> (n.d.) <article-title>The Psychosocial Studies Network</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.psychosocial-network.org/">www.psychosocial-network.org/</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 30 June 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Caribbean Mothers: Identity and Experience in the U.K</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tufnell Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riessman</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Analysis of personal narratives</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jaber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook of Interview Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>710</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riessman</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Narrative Methods for the Human Sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skrbis</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Transnational families: Theorising migration, emotions and belonging</article-title>. <source>Journal of Intercultural Studies</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Serial migration and its implications: A retrospective analysis of the children of Caribbean immigrants</article-title>. <source>Cultural Diversity and Ethnic Minority Psychology</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Transcending the Legacies of Slavery: A Psychoanalytic View</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karnac Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <source>The Plural Society in the British West Indies</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tatli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozbilgin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An emic approach to intersectional study of diversity at work: A Bourdieuan framing</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Management Reviews</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yuval-Davis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Intersectionality and feminist politics</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Women’s Studies</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1350506812455994">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yuval-Davis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The Politics of Belonging: Intersectional Contestations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>