<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ASQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spasq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Administrative Science Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0001-8392</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0001839212447600</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0001839212447600</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Nina Eliasoph: Making Volunteers: Civic Life after Welfare’s End</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>57</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>162</fpage>
<lpage>164</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eliasoph</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name>
</person-group>: <source>Making Volunteers: Civic Life after Welfare’s End</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="308"/> pp. <price>$39.50</price>, <comment>hardcover</comment>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Johnson Graduate School, Cornell University</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In <italic>Making Volunteers</italic>, Nina Eliasoph provides a rich, fascinating interpretation of organizations engaged in “empowerment projects,” that is, attempts to produce personal transformation through volunteering and civic engagement. Such organizations and their “morally magnetic missions” promise to simultaneously deliver social services and provide a transformative civic education for volunteers. Through an ethnographic study of several empowerment projects focused on youth in a Midwestern city (“Snowy Prairie”), Eliasoph unpacks the tensions between their various goals and the “organizational style” that results, that is, “patterned ways of harmonizing predictable discords between an organization’s varied missions” (p. xii).</p>
<p>These tensions are substantial, and they mostly keep empowerment projects from being either empowering or especially good at delivering social services. For instance, although empowerment projects speak of intense, transformative experiences, they undermine the conditions for these by chasing funding through short-term projects, avoiding conflict, and relying on short-term volunteers. Furthermore, their commitments to open-ended planning and to the intrinsic value of volunteer work often keep them from providing effective services for their youth participants. Though empowerment projects celebrate diversity and put disadvantaged and non-disadvantaged kids together to work on projects, they fail to generate real integration, deep discussion of inequality, or meaningful discoveries about the “other.” Instead, the organizational style of empowerment projects emphasizes surface-level similarities, avoids politics, and values innovation and future potential over continuity. As Eliasoph puts it, “Empowerment Projects offer many chances to feel ambivalence and doubt—about one’s culture, one’s intimate relationships, one’s inspiring volunteer spirit—but almost no chance to express, discuss, and possibly untangle the ambivalence and doubt” (p. 234).</p>
<p>Not all is lost, though. Although the youth volunteers at Community House, Casa Latina, the Regional Youth Empowerment Project, and several other programs that Eliasoph studied typically do not undergo a deep civic education, they do get exposure to complex, albeit often perverse, aspects of decision making and funding in nonprofit organizations and to ways of conveying organizational information “rapidly and transparently to multiple, distant audiences” (p. 234). Although celebrations of diversity prove thin, the projects do provide volunteers with experience in navigating inequality and foster a “cool, respectfully distant politeness” (p. 180) toward difference. Occasionally, when a paid staff member with a long-term commitment (exemplified by “Emily” from Community House) can carve out space that is stable, safe, and shielded from completely open participation (by short-term adult volunteers, for instance), youth volunteers can travel a path that does allow them to develop as students and citizens. Unless this safe situation is created, Eliasoph argues, empowerment projects are poorly suited for personal development (let alone transformation) among either youth or adult volunteers but are better suited for tasks like picking up roadside trash, since “litter has no feelings and never disagrees with the volunteer who picks it up” (p. 54).</p>
<p>Eliasoph does a wonderful job of taking the reader into the world of youth-oriented empowerment projects, in which all youth are deemed “leaders” in hopes that they will eventually fulfill the prophecy, in which talk of “choices” (rather than “needs”), “community,” and “diversity” go together all too seamlessly, and in which non-disadvantaged youth think about solving other people’s problems while disadvantaged youth learn that they <italic>are</italic> the problem (and that their volunteering is the solution). Her most important accomplishment is to develop a nuanced but forceful critique of empowerment projects while still seeking to understand what they <italic>do</italic> accomplish, what happens in the “detours from their original plans,” and how they might be improved. Her suggestions for improvement, which include stabilizing resource streams, allowing more honest dialogue about inequality and difference, and dropping short-term “plug-in volunteering” altogether, have just about the right balance of sociological insight and practicality, although she has less to say about the conditions under which these reforms might be plausible. There are also the seeds here of very interesting arguments about time and organizational style. Not only temporal cycles of funding and participation but also organizational scripts about time (here, an obsessive focus on future potential) clearly shape what empowerment projects can achieve. In addition, this book extends Eliasoph’s earlier arguments about how attempts to “avoid politics” impoverish civic life. Across all these issues, the analysis is well grounded in compelling and rich ethnographic material, and Eliasoph’s reflexive style of reporting fieldnotes nicely situates her presence in the sites without distracting from her settings and characters.</p>
<p><italic>Making Volunteers</italic> is an engaging ethnography and a stunning critique of empowerment projects, as well as related attempts to replace bureaucratic capacities with voluntarism and participatory governance. Its weaknesses largely involve some unanswered questions about the broader context and significance of the study. First, although Eliasoph provides examples of how empowerment projects like those she studied are increasingly common around the world, it is unclear exactly how widespread this particular model is and how much the tensions she observed translate into other settings. In particular, most of the projects she studied were committed to bringing youth from different racial, ethnic, and socioeconomic backgrounds together. Others may not have this commitment, which should both change their organizational style and minimize some of the indirect benefits of dealing (however imperfectly) with inequality and diversity. A stronger analysis of variation in organizational styles would be a useful complement to this interpretation. Second, the analysis is rich but sometimes belabored, particularly in a chapter on the meanings of food and several sections that slice diversity talk from similar angles. Some additional tightening might enhance the book’s appeal to students and practitioners. Finally, the decision to relegate most theoretical material to the endnotes makes the links between this study and other treatments of nonprofits, diversity talk, and organizational culture somewhat opaque.</p>
<p>The book is written to appeal to a general audience but should be of particular interest to many organizational scholars and practitioners. It is especially relevant to those studying or leading organizations that seek to blend multiple missions, to integrate participants across racial, ethnic, or class boundaries, or to empower their participants in some way. For these readers, the book provides many valuable interpretive nuggets, as well as exhibiting a keen eye for detecting empty talk and gesture. The book would also make an excellent addition to syllabi on contemporary nonprofit organizations, especially if used in tandem with material on the resource streams that underlie the tensions of empowerment projects. Finally, the book should be required reading for anyone contemplating a short-term service learning component for a course; “plug-in volunteering” does not fare well in this thoughtful and convincing analysis.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold>Tim Bartley</bold><break/>
Department of Sociology<break/>
Indiana University<break/>
Bloomington, IN 47405<break/>
bartleyt@indiana.edu</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>