<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TTJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spttj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Theology Today</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5736</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2044-2556</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040573612453228j</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040573612453228j</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Scribe Well-Trained: Archibald Alexander and the Life of Piety by James M. Garretson</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>Sean Michael</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040573612453228j">Senior Minister, The First Presbyterian Church, Hattiesburg, Missouri</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>69</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>361</fpage>
<lpage>362</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Princeton Theological Seminary/Theology Today</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>A Scribe Well-Trained: Archibald Alexander and the Life of Piety</italic> (Profiles in Reformed Spirituality)</p>
<p>James M. Garretson</p>
<p>Grand Rapids: Reformation Heritage Books, 2011. 185 pp. $10.00</p>
<p>In 1983 Princeton Seminary’s church history professor, Lefferts Loetscher, titled his biography of Archibald Alexander, <italic>Facing the Enlightenment and Pietism</italic>. In that biography, Loetscher did a splendid job outlining the contours of Alexander’s commitments to Enlightenment philosophy, which in turn shaped “the Princeton theology” of the nineteenth century. However, the “pietism” side of Alexander’s life was more difficult for Loetscher to describe. Into that gap comes this little book edited by James Garretson, a Presbyterian Church in America pastor who had previously written a book on Alexander’s views on preaching and ministry. <italic>A Scribe Well-Trained</italic>, in line with the other books in the Profiles in Reformed Spirituality series, has a short introduction on Alexander’s understanding of piety followed by 56 selections from the Princeton theologian’s writings that serve to illustrate, inspire, and inculcate piety.</p>
<p>Garretson’s introduction offers a brief biographical overview of Alexander’s life and a sketch of what Alexander thought piety was: “Piety in practice, is, therefore, a combination of discipleship and devotion energized with a doxological focus” (14). While that definition might be helpful, there is little attempt actually to spell out the doctrinal or ritual aspects of Alexander’s practice of piety. What was the nature of piety? Did Alexander root communion with Christ into a prior theological commitment to union with Christ? How much emphasis did he place on Christian ritual—Word, sacrament, prayer—in developing piety? What about catechesis? None of these questions find a place in Garretson’s introduction.</p>
<p>Thankfully, the 56 Alexander selections give a sense of his understanding of piety. In particular, Alexander taught that piety, or religious experience, was driven forward by the right apprehension and impression of truth upon the human mind (27). In fact, “the true and only method of growing in grace” came through “increasing daily in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ” (30). This intellectual approach to Christian experience is consistent throughout the selections: truth and piety always are connected together (see, for instance, 59–60).</p>
<p>Such an intellectual approach did not exclude, however, “the sense of the heart.” Genuine prayer is viewed as “the secret breathing of the heart” (37). Word and Spirit always go together for “external teaching, however correct, is not sufficient; humans need internal illumination by the Spirit” (44). A truly happy Christian life comes as one cultivates “a devotional spirit” (66). As the mind is illuminated and truth cherished, changes come to the heart; the heart is moved and the will engaged so that the Christian lives differently. Above all, love of God comes to permeate the Christian’s soul and characterize one’s actions: “Love, unless reciprocated, would not fill up the cup of human happiness. But to love, and be beloved, this is heaven. And ‘we love because he first loved us’” (77).</p>
<p>And so, Christian practices result from this being loved by God and loving God. Prayer is the chief of these practices: “Prayer is holy converse—a fellowship with God” (103). Sabbath observance also is vital, for it is a day set aside for growth in knowledge of the divine in corporate and private worship and biblical study (108–11). Strikingly, the selections offer little about the importance of preaching or the sacraments, both of which are vital in most Reformed understandings of piety. However, there are many selections on the importance of developing Christian assurance, the need for cultivating love for God while young, and the promise to the aged to die well if they die “in the Lord.”</p>
<p><italic>A Scribe Well-Trained</italic> has real value for ministers and historians alike. In the selections that Garretson offers of Alexander’s perspective on piety, there is plenty that is suggestive for one’s heart and mind in the development of “a devotional spirit, a constant breathing after God, the living God.” Especially during this anniversary year for Princeton Seminary, returning to consider how Alexander was both a man of the Enlightenment and a man of piety would give new insight into the historical trajectory of the school and American Presbyterianism.</p>
<p>Sean Michael Lucas</p>
<p>Senior Minister, The First Presbyterian Church</p>
<p>Hattiesburg, Missouri</p>
</body>
</article>