<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptpj</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Prison Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0032-8855</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7522</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0032885512467316</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0032885512467316</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Rape and Consensual Sex in Male Israeli Prisons</article-title>
<subtitle>Are There Differences With Western Prisons?</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Einat</surname><given-names>Tomer</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0032885512467316">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0032885512467316"><label>1</label>Bar-Ilan University, Ramat-Gan, Israel</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0032885512467316">Tomer Einat, Department of Criminology, Bar-Ilan University, Ramat-Gan 52900, Israel Email: <email>einat@mail.biu.ac.il</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>93</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Prisons deprive male inmates of heterosexual relationships and, thus, prevent them from asserting their masculinity via “traditional” means. Accordingly, many prisoners experience extreme emotional, psychological, and physical distress, which can lead to intimidation, aggression, and reestablishment of their sense of dominance through homosexual activities with consenting or coerced partners. This quantitative and qualitative study, based on research undertaken in a random sample of 30% of the male prisons in Israel, analyzes the neglected issue of homosexual relationships in Israeli prisons. The findings indicate that sexual harassment or homosexual rapes rarely take place in Israeli prisons and consensual homosexual relationships are rare. Furthermore, Israeli inmates view homosexual relationships in prison as disgusting and disgraceful and conceptualize them in highly negative emotional terms.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>rape</kwd>
<kwd>consensual sex</kwd>
<kwd>male prisoners</kwd>
<kwd>Israeli homosexuality</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0032885512467316" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Deprivation of basic human needs and the search for alternative sources of gratification are the forces that shape the world of the prison—its culture, way of life, and values, and the roles of those within. In a culture that places the quest for power and dominance at the forefront, male inmates are deprived of heterosexual relationships and stripped of various traditional means of asserting their masculinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0032885512467316">Einat &amp; Einat, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0032885512467316">Sykes, 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0032885512467316">Toch, 1992</xref>). All this creates “extreme emotional, psychological, and perhaps physical distress” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0032885512467316">Tewksbury &amp; West, 2000</xref>, p. 369), which turns many male inmates to intimidation and aggression, reestablishing their sense of dominance through same-sex sexual activities with consenting or coerced partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0032885512467316">Dumond, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0032885512467316">Man &amp; Cronan, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>There is general agreement on the importance of researching same-sex sexual activity in prisons. Consensual and coerced same-sex sexual relationships have been shown to be central to daily prison life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0032885512467316">Cotton &amp; Groth, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0032885512467316">Fagan, Wennerstorm, &amp; Miller, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0032885512467316">Kaminski, 2004</xref>), and their study may deepen our understanding of prison culture and inmate behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0032885512467316">Tewksbury &amp; West, 2000</xref>). More important, it is hoped that greater knowledge and awareness of this issue can help reduce sexual violence behind prison walls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0032885512467316">Struckman-Johnson, Struckman-Johnson, Rucker, Bumby, &amp; Donaldson, 1996</xref>) and address related health problems that have severe implications for prisoners, institutional staff, and the general public alike (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0032885512467316">Maruschak, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Although much attention has been paid to the research of consensual and coerced same-sex sexual activity in male prisons, three research topics have received insufficient academic attention or have often been overlooked: (a) inmates’ attitudes toward same-sex sexual relationships in male prisons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0032885512467316">Richmond, 1978</xref>), (b) analysis of the role of same-sex sexual relationships in the male prison subculture and its impact on inmate conduct, and (c) sociolinguistic analyses of prison sex narrative (a major source of information about prison sex and sexual violence; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0032885512467316">Castle, Hensley, &amp; Tewksbury, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0032885512467316">Krienert &amp; Fleisher, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0032885512467316">O’Donnell, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>The present research seeks to fill these gaps in our understanding of sex in male prisons. It focuses on three main themes: inmates’ views about same-sex sexual relationships (voluntary or forced), prison argot used to describe them, and the role of same-sex sexual relationships in the prisoners’ social world.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0032885512467316">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>By design, prisons are single-gender institutions. Deprivation of heterosexual relationships constitutes one of the most significant “pains of imprisonment” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0032885512467316">Einat, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0032885512467316">Irwin &amp; Owen, 2005</xref>), and the replacement of heterosexual relationships (at least temporarily) with same-sex sexual ones, as well as their permanent psychological impact on prisoners, have been widely documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0032885512467316">Saum, Surratt, Inciardi, &amp; Bennett, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0032885512467316">Struckman-Johnson et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0032885512467316">Sykes, 1958</xref>). To date, the majority of the criminology-penology literature refers to two main categories of same-sex sexual relationships in prison: consensual relationships and same-sex sexual rape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0032885512467316">Struckman-Johnson et al., 1996</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section3-0032885512467316">
<title>Consensual Homosexuality Among Inmates</title>
<p>Research on consensual sex in male correctional facilities has been sparse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski, Hensley, Wright, &amp; Tewksbury, 2002</xref>) and has yielded inconsistent findings.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0032885512467316">1</xref></sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0032885512467316">Nacci and Kane’s (1984)</xref> study reveals that approximately 29% of a random sample of 330 inmates had a same-sex sexual experience while incarcerated. Tewksbury discovered that more than 19% of a random sample of 150 prisoners had engaged in same-sex sexual activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0032885512467316">Tewksbury, 1989</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0032885512467316">Hensley (2001)</xref>, who examined the actual number of consensual same-sex sexual acts in multiple-security-level prisons in Oklahoma found that while incarcerated 18% of the prisoners had kissed another inmate, 23% had rubbed their body part against a fellow inmate in a sexual manner or allowed another inmate to rub a body part of theirs against him in a sexual manner, 24% had allowed another man to touch their penis or touched another man’s penis, 23% had performed or received oral sex from another inmate, and 20% had engaged in anal intercourse with another inmate. In contrast, Strang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0032885512467316">Strang, Heuston, &amp; Gossop, 1998</xref>) revealed that only about 2.1% of a random sample of 1,009 prisoners in 13 prisons in England and Wales reported “ever having sexual contact with a man in prison” (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0032885512467316">O’Donnell, 2004</xref>, p. 247), whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0032885512467316">Saum et al.’s (1995)</xref> interviews with 101 prisoners in a medium-security prison in Delaware indicate that 2% had engaged in sexual activity with another inmate the previous year.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0032885512467316">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>Traditionally, inmates engaging in consensual same-sex sexual relationships in prison have been categorized into two dichotomous groups: “true homosexuals” and “situational homosexuals” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0032885512467316">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0032885512467316">Sykes, 1958</xref>). The first group is composed of men “who had a homosexual orientation prior to incarceration—men who ‘imported’ their behavior from the streets to prison” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0032885512467316">Eigenberg, 2000</xref>, p. 418). These individuals engaged in same-sex sexual activity because “they were born that way . . . and adopted the same role in prison as they would have in the free community” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski et al., 2002</xref>, p. 16). Prisoners generally refer to them in negative terms, such as “exceptional characters” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0032885512467316">Clemmer, 1958</xref>), “fish” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2002</xref>), “fags” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0032885512467316">Donaldson, 1993</xref>), “queens” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0032885512467316">Kirkham, 1971</xref>), “woman-like” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0032885512467316">Sagarin, 1976</xref>), and “fuck-boys” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0032885512467316">Fleisher, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>In comparison, “situational homosexuals” are heterosexual men who demonstrate same-sex sexual conduct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski et al., 2002</xref>). These men engage in sexual activities with fellow inmates mainly due to the social structure of prison that produces and promotes homosexual conduct within its walls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0032885512467316">Ibrahim, 1974</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0032885512467316">3</xref></sup> Moreover, in many situations, the individual’s sexual conduct contrasts with his sexual identity: “The fact that an individual engages in sexual relationships with a person of one gender or the other does not make that individual heterosexual or homosexual” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski et al., 2002</xref>, p. 112). Consequently, many researchers believe that most situational homosexual men will return to heterosexual sexual conduct once they are in a two-gender environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>“Situational homosexuals” were often categorized into various subgroups according to different criteria, for example: (a) the dominance/submissiveness of the sexual partners (i.e. “inserter” and “insertee” [“bitches,” “sissies,” “queens,” and “broads”] <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski et al., 2002</xref>); (b) the subjective perception of sexual identity (“aggressive wolfs”—inmates who entered prison with a heterosexual orientation, keep their heterosexual identity in prison, and maintain their masculinity by sexually assaulting younger, weaker inmates, and “nonaggressive wolfs”/“teddy bears”—prisoners who entered prison with a heterosexual identity, maintain their masculine self-image by taking active roles during sex, but perceive themselves as bisexual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2001</xref>); and (c) the motivation for engaging in same-sex sexual activity (“fags”—prisoners who engage in same-sex sexual activity because that is their sexual preference, and “punks”—inmates who choose to engage in same-sex sexual conduct in self-defense or in self-defense or in return for goods and services; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0032885512467316">Donaldson, 1993</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0032885512467316">
<title>Same-Sex Sexual Rapes in Prison</title>
<p>In keeping with the gravity of the issue, considerable research has been devoted to the study of sexual harassment and same-sex sexual rapes in prison. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0032885512467316">Lockwood’s (1980)</xref> survey of prisoners in two correctional facilities in New York discovered that 28% were the targets of sexual aggression and 1.3% had been raped. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0032885512467316">Donaldson (1993)</xref> estimated that in the United States, more than 290,000 males were sexually assaulted behind bars each year. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0032885512467316">Hensley (2000)</xref> revealed that 14% of a sample of male inmates in Oklahoma were sexually intimidated and 1% were raped, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0032885512467316">Struckman-Johnson et al. (1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0032885512467316">1996</xref>) found that 22% of male prisoners in medium- and maximum-security prisons and 16% of male inmates in minimum-security facilities experienced coerced sexual activity during confinement. The most updated and comprehensive data regarding same-sex sexual rapes in American prisons was published by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0032885512467316">U.S. Department of Justice (2005)</xref>. According to the study, the total average rate of inmate-on-inmate nonconsensual sexual acts was 1.16 per 1,000 inmates (0.11 per 1,000 inmates in public federal prisons, 1.05 per 1,000 inmates in public state prisons, and 0.43 per 1,000 inmates in private prisons). A 2006 Bureau of Justice Statistics survey found more than 6,500 prison sexual violence “official” allegations filed with U.S. correctional officials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0032885512467316">Beck, Harrison, &amp; Adams, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Rape has also been studied in European prisons, although quite meagerly. Of 590 prisoners interviewed in various English penal institutions, less than 2% said they had been sexually attacked while in custody (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0032885512467316">Edgar, O’Donnell, &amp; Martin, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0032885512467316">Power et al. (1991)</xref>, who studied 559 Scottish prisoners, were the only researchers in the past four decades who did not uncover a single case of sexual assault in male prisons.</p>
<p>The bulk of criminological-sociological studies regarding same-sex sexual rape in general and same-sex sexual rape in prison in particular perceive rape as an act of power, violence, and politics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0032885512467316">O’Donnell, 2004</xref>). According to this perspective, prison rape is a sexual manifestation of aggression rather than an aggressive demonstration of sexuality. Therefore, it serves, practically as well as symbolically, as a statement of one’s masculinity and strength. The rape of male inmates occurs for the same reasons it takes place in the community: to hurt, humiliate, dominate, control, and degrade; to strip the raped inmate of his status as a “man” and force him to assume the role of a “woman” and become a slave in the fullest meaning of the word (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0032885512467316">Rideau &amp; Wikberg, 1992</xref>).</p>
<p>The majority of male rape victims in prison suffer from an acute disruption of physiological, psychological, social, and sexual life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0032885512467316">Scacco, 1982</xref>). Some victims experience difficulty in telling family and friends about the rape, others encounter disruption in male-female relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0032885512467316">Walker &amp; Brodsky, 1976</xref>: 45), and several turn to suicide to escape the trauma and fear of rape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0032885512467316">Dooley, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0032885512467316">Haycock, 1991</xref>). Increased understanding of the nature of prison sex may assist in comprehending the dynamics of the male prison subculture.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0032885512467316" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>To explore the way inmates view prison sex and attach meaning to the experience, a flexible design was employed. This approach allows access to contents that are not anticipated a priori as well as exploration of the research topic from the standpoint of the research population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0032885512467316">Briggs, 1986</xref>).</p>
<p>Qualitative methodology and the phenomenological semistructured interview were used to collect and analyze information from the inmate participants. The final stage of the analysis is a generalization of the main trends that emerge from the findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0032885512467316">Stake, 1995</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section6-0032885512467316">
<title>Participant Selection</title>
<p>A sample of 151 adult inmates (approximately 1.5% of the Israeli criminal prisoner population; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ips.gov.il/Data/data.asp.2005">http://www.ips.gov.il/Data/data.asp.2005</ext-link>) participated in the study.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0032885512467316">4</xref></sup> The prisoners were selected randomly from two maximum-security and two medium-security male prisons in Israel (also chosen randomly). Research participants have been in prison from 1.6 years to more than 20 years.</p>
<p>Of the inmates who participated in the study, 18.5% had been sentenced for human-life offenses, 25.3% for sexual offenses, 16.5% for drug offenses, 19.1% for theft, 7.3% for assault, 3.3% for fraud, 6% for public order, and 4% for blackmail.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0032885512467316">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>Moreover, 51.5% of the inmates were first-timers, 19.6% were incarcerated for the 2 times, 9.7 were incarcerated for 3 times, 5.9% were incarcerated for 4 times, 4.2% were incarcerated for the 5 times, and 9.1% were incarcerated for 6 and more times. Last, 67% of the interviewees were Jews and 33% were Muslims.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0032885512467316">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>The researcher met Israeli Prison Service (IPS) educational officers at their respective prison facilities. During these initial contacts, he described the type and purpose of the research project and requested their assistance in notifying as many inmates as possible about the study, as well as encouraging them to voluntarily participate in it. In the course of the following month, the researcher met with all inmates willing to participate in the study within the prison facilities, explained the nature and objectives of the study, and requested voluntary participation. In the 4 months that followed, 460 hours of in-depth semistructured interviews were conducted with 151 prisoners all of whom were randomly selected. These were held in the education wings of the respective prisons during the morning and afternoon hours, each session lasting approximately 2.5 hours.</p>
<p>The prisoners were encouraged to share their experiences and attitudes with the interviewer in a setting conducive to a sense of interpersonal involvement. Given that definitions of same-sex sexual relationships vary considerably (genital fondling, failed attempts at intercourse, verbal harassment, sexual extortion, kissing, implicit references to fellatio and/or anal sex, intercourse; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0032885512467316">Hensley, Tewksbury, &amp; Wright, 2001</xref>), the interviewees were asked to refer to conduct (invited or uninvited) made by and directed at male inmates that included contact between the penis and the penis or anus including penetration, however slight; or contact between the mouth and the penis, or anus; or penetration of the anus of another person by a hand, finger, or other object (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0032885512467316">U.S. Department of Justice, 2005</xref>). All interviews were audio-recorded with the consent of the interviewees.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0032885512467316">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>It should be mentioned that many researchers have noted that same-sex sexual activity is likely to be underreported by male inmates, because of fears of reprisal, unwillingness to become a “snitch,” and fear of being labeled as <italic>weak</italic> and <italic>coward</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0032885512467316">Eigenberg, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0032885512467316">Krienert &amp; Fleisher, 2005</xref>). Hence, prisoners were given the opportunity to <italic>anonymously</italic> report whether they had heard, seen, and/or participated (actively or passively) in any same-sex sexual act in the prison where they were interviewed and/or in some other prison facility.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0032885512467316">
<title>Research Tool</title>
<p>The phenomenological semistructured interview was chosen as the most appropriate research tool to achieve the research main objectives. This type of interview is based on general guidelines, to ensure that all those interviewed are subject to similar stimuli, thereby allowing for a common base for data analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0032885512467316">Briggs, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0032885512467316">Pogrebin, 2003</xref>). The design of the interview was tentative; it was modified in correspondence with new findings that emerged from the flexible method of questioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0032885512467316">Rubin &amp; Rubin, 1995</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0032885512467316">7</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="section9-0032885512467316">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>In view of their essentially qualitative nature, the data were subjected to content analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0032885512467316">Strauss &amp; Corbin, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0032885512467316">Weber, 2001</xref>). Content analysis is generally applied to narrative texts such as transcribed interviews and published works. This type of analysis seeks to expound what can be learned through respondents’ and authors’ understanding of happenings and terminology through close examination of the content and language of texts. The objective is to get at aspects of meaning by examining the data qualitatively. In effect, content analysis is used to examine how respondents or authors view and understand certain issues, as well as help to shed light on their beliefs.</p>
<p>To analyze and code the data, interviews were studied extensively. Themes within the inmates’ responses emerged naturally, with emphasis being placed on the idea that weight was not given to any preconceived themes that the researcher may harbor. The transcript data were, therefore, analyzed thematically first, and only after themes were identified were they examined in light of the questions already identified.</p>
<p>The analysis is based on the frequency with which given subjects appear in the data, which indicates the respondents’ attention to these particular subjects in certain situations, and the intensity with which they relate to these subjects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0032885512467316">Pogrebin, 2003</xref>). In this research, intensity was measured by the level of importance that the respondents ascribed to the respective topics, based on the words they used to refer to them. The analysis is, then, essentially thematic and based on categorization of content areas.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0032885512467316">
<title>Findings</title>
<sec id="section11-0032885512467316">
<title>Consensual Same-Sex Sexual Relationships</title>
<p>According to the findings of this study, and in contrast to most research findings regarding consensual sex in male correctional facilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0032885512467316">Nacci &amp; Kane, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0032885512467316">Tewksbury, 1989</xref>), consensual same-sex sexual relationships (either “situational” or “by nature”) are rare in Israeli prisons. Only three interviewees reported to have heard a same-sex sexual act, and all participants have stated that such relationships are dishonorable and prisoners participating in them are morally disgraceful.</p>
<p>The system of norms among Israeli inmates highlights the prisoners’ unnecessary engagement in same-sex sexual activity. Their code of conduct characterizes a “good inmate” as one who controls his impulses and temper (including sexual desires) and remains a <italic>jeda</italic> (a real man). They perceive “true” or “situational homosexuals” who chose or were coerced into same-sex sexual relationships in prison as mentally and physically “broken,” and relegate them to one of the lowest positions in the prisoner hierarchy. These inmates are stigmatized and labeled with a wide range of derogatory terms (e.g., “mufflers,” “wallpaper,” “deep sea divers”) and are usually deemed outcasts (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0032885512467316">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0032885512467316" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Terms for Sexual Relationships in Israeli Prison Argot</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0032885512467316" xlink:href="10.1177_0032885512467316-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Argot (phonetics)</th>
<th align="center">Literal translation</th>
<th align="center">Meaning</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Bole’a</td>
<td>Swallower</td>
<td>Homosexual; inmate fond of oral sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Exhaust</td>
<td>Muffler</td>
<td>Homosexual</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Helikopter</td>
<td>Helicopter</td>
<td>Inmate who has frequent sexual relationships with other prisoners</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kusit</td>
<td>Good-looking woman [slang]</td>
<td>Male (inmate) prostitute</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Le’halel</td>
<td>To play the flute</td>
<td>To perform oral sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Malkat ha‘ta</td>
<td>Queen of the cell</td>
<td>Male (inmate) prostitute</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mitkofef</td>
<td>Bender</td>
<td>Homosexual</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ochlata</td>
<td>A man/woman eating</td>
<td>Prisoner frequently experiencing homosexual intercourse</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sandwich</td>
<td>Sandwich</td>
<td>Homosexual intercourse</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Shagrir</td>
<td>Ambassador</td>
<td>Homosexual</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tapet</td>
<td>Wallpaper</td>
<td>Man who has homosexual relationships</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tsolel</td>
<td>Deep-sea diver</td>
<td>Man practising oral sex</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Zonda</td>
<td>Intragastric tube</td>
<td>Homosexual rape</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>To cite several inmates:</p>
<list id="list1-0032885512467316" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Inmate RS</italic>: This prison, unlike other maximum-security facilities, is like a carrot and a stick. . . . The good part is that the cells are cleaner and smaller and there are many educational activities. . . . The bad part is that you are housed with homosexual prisoners—inmates who are ostracized in every men’s prison in Israel. The feeling of being with them every day in the same prison wing, observing them and sometimes even touching them, is disgusting and terrible. . . . I wish one of us would eventually have enough courage to harm them [even though that would exact] the price of being thrown into a bad prison facility.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Inmate YF</italic>: This is a men’s prison . . . not a women’s facility . . . inmates who want to behave like women and “play the flute” [have oral sex] should do it at home.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Inmate RH</italic>: You can find some homosexual activity and prostitution in juvenile facilities because these teenagers are full of hormones and energy . . . but we [adult prisoners] are tired of this shit. I’d be more than surprised to hear about an inmate fucking another inmate because most inmates reject this kind of conduct, and if it does happen, then those two sluts are doomed. . . . The other inmates will blow them apart.</p></list-item></list>
<p>As the citations indicate, Israeli prisoners perceive consensual same-sex sexual relationships as a degrading element of behavior and gay inmates as morally unworthy. Although inmates are subject to strict control and deprived of heterosexual relationships, there is clear peer pressure to control their sexual desires and refrain from participating in voluntary same-sex sexual relationships. The argot related to this aspect of prison subculture has negative connotations, expressing abhorrence and contempt. Sexual conduct and inmates involved in sexual activities are rejected by the inmate code of norms and values, and they are consistently labeled with degrading tags.</p>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0032885512467316">Dumond (2000)</xref>, prison argot defines sexual tendencies and inmate status simultaneously, “using homosexuality as a means of placing individuals within the inmate caste system . . . and helps to define the treatment which an inmate is likely to receive from other inmates” (p. 138). Hence, the relatively few “true” and “situational” homosexual inmates in Israeli prisons face sanctions ranging from verbal aggression to social isolation and physical violence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0032885512467316">
<title>Same-Sex Sexual Rape</title>
<p>There appears to be a vast difference between the average rate of same-sex sexual rape in American and British prisons and that of Israeli facilities. According to inmates’ medical files, prisoners’ disciplinary records, and the IPS Head of Security and Prisoner Administration (the formal body that investigates and handles all prisoner complaints), only two same-sex sexual rapes, and no sexual assaults or sexual harassment in Israeli prisons were reported during the years 1997 to 2005.</p>
<p>Moreover, in addition to the official reports, nearly all the participants stated that they had never participated (actively or passively) and/or witnessed (e.g., heard or saw) any same-sex sexual rape and/or assault in prison. Only one participant claimed to have heard (in real time) a same-sex sexual rape, involving an Israeli-Arab prisoner who sexually raped a fellow Israeli-Jew inmate because the latter had collaborated with the prison staff and revealed that the rapist’s brother (who was also an inmate) possessed a knife and was planning on stabbing another Israeli Jewish inmate.</p>
<p>In the interviews, the participants offered several reasons for the scarceness of same-sex sexual rape, the main one being the fear of HIV/AIDS:
<disp-quote>
<p><italic>Inmate AU</italic>: I think one of the reasons for not having homosexual rapes in [Israeli] prison . . . is AIDS. . . . All prisoners are really afraid of the disease.</p>
<p><italic>Inmate HG</italic>: The idiotic Israel Prison Service has this stupid policy of housing healthy inmates with inmates suffering from AIDS in the same wing . . . and it’s quiet scary and disgusting. We try not to mingle with them or be near them. Yeah, I know it does not make sense but it [the AIDS disease] is so scary that we cannot ignore it. . . . I am sure this is one of the reasons for the scarcity of homosexuality in [Israeli] prisons today.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>HIV/AIDS among prison inmates has been a growing worry in American penal systems since the mid-1980s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2002</xref>). This concern, in addition to common perceptions regarding modes of transmission, risks of infection, and mass screening, and many prison officers’ assertion of their “right to know,” have led to a demand for mandatory testing of all incoming inmates, separate housing for those tested positive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0032885512467316">Gido, 2002</xref>), distribution of condoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0032885512467316">Blumberg &amp; Laster, 1999</xref>), and disclosure of prisoner HIV/AIDS status to correctional personnel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0032885512467316">Mahoney, 1988</xref>). Moreover, many correctional institutions have implemented universal precautions among all staff dealing with inmates (e.g., treating all prisoners as if they are HIV/AIDS infected; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0032885512467316">Hensley, 2002</xref>) and have provided comprehensive and intensive educational and prevention programs aimed at identification of high-risk behavior as well as antiviral therapy.</p>
<p>In comparison with the importance that various American correctional systems ascribe to health care of inmates, and particularly HIV/AIDS prevention, the IPS provides prisoners with almost no information, education, or means of HIV/AIDS prevention available to the public outside. More specifically, none of the 21 prison facilities make condoms available to inmates, and there is no mandatory HIV/AIDS testing. By doing so, the IPS fails miserably at protecting prisoners and their families from acquiring and then transmitting HIV/AIDS and demonstrates its incapability to deal with HIV/AIDS. It seems reasonable to assume that this increases the inmates’ fear of the disease and their aggressive stance against same-sex sexual behavior. If so, this may suggest a possible correlation between ignorance and stereotypes related to HIV/AIDS and lack of same-sex sexual activity—coerced and consensual—in Israeli prisons, and, ironically, a desirable outcome—the reduction of same-sex sexual activity in prison.</p>
<p>Beyond the issue of HIV/AIDS, Israeli inmates seem to view same-sex sexual rape in prison as repellent and disgraceful and to conceptualize it in highly negative emotional terms. Together with those convicted of rape, child molestation, and incest, same-sex sexual aggressors in prison occupy the lowest rung on the prison social ladder. Hence, they are continually humiliated, mocked, and harmed by fellow inmates:</p>
<list id="list2-0032885512467316" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Inmate HI</italic>: During the last 10-15 years, prisoners tend to expose “maniacs” [prisoners who do not act according to the inmates’ code of conduct] who rape fellow inmates and negatively stigmatize them. I do not know what caused this change, but nearly all inmates consider homosexual rape [in prison] as disgusting.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Inmate OA</italic>: You know that inmates hate rapists more than anything else, so imagine what our attitude is towards those who tried to rape fellow inmates in prison. . . . It’s the worst of the worst . . . sick people . . . scum.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Inmate RB</italic>: I’ve been incarcerated three times for an accumulated period of 17 years, and the last time I heard of a [homosexual] rape in prison was 10 years ago. . . . I think [homosexual] rapes in prison ended because many inmates “grew up” and got tired of this bullshit. . . . If you want to take revenge on or hurt an inmate, or if you want to humiliate a fellow prisoner, all you have to do is to meet him face to face and injure him.</p></list-item></list>
<p>Most penological-criminological research conceives of same-sex sexual rape in prison as a violent expression of dominance, status, and intimidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0032885512467316">Man &amp; Cronan, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0032885512467316">Welch, 2004</xref>). Accordingly, nonconsensual sex in prison is a main policy matter for correctional administrators and a major area of concern for prisoners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0032885512467316">Kunselman, Tewksbury, Dumond, &amp; Dumond, 2002</xref>). At the same time, and in spite of a relatively high frequency of violent behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0032885512467316">Einat, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0032885512467316">Einat &amp; Einat, 2000</xref>), Israeli prisons lack almost any same-sex sexual assaults. Moreover, the majority of Israeli inmates delegitimize this type of conduct. In other words, although Israeli prisoner ideology embraces violent behavior (verbal and physical) and considers it a legitimate way of gaining power, the same code dramatically rejects any form of sexual aggression.</p>
<p>The fact that same-sex sexual rape rarely occurs in Israeli prisons whereas violent behavior is frequent and is perceived as a justifiable way of gaining power and status is both puzzling and challenging. The answer to this paradox could be related, as discussed earlier, to the increasing rates of HIV/AIDS within Israeli society, inmates’ ignorance regarding the disease, and public fear concerning it. Alternatively, the explanation may possibly lie in the modification and renewal of the Israeli prisons’ ideological and normative order due to sociopolitical and sociodemographic changes during the past 15 years (namely, massive immigration from the former Soviet Union and Ethiopia). The challenge is thus to produce more research concerning same-sex sexual rape in Israeli prisons and explore it on micro and macro levels (i.e., inmate subculture and research on rape in the community, respectively).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0032885512467316">
<title>The Nonsexual Use of Sexual Prison Argot</title>
<p>The same derogatory sexual labels that inmates attach to peers engaged in same-sex sexual activity are also widely applied to nonsexual situations. They are used to express extreme contempt and anger, with the purpose of imposing stigmas on other inmates. Such argot is primarily used in reference to inmates who were convicted of rape or otherwise abused the weak and vulnerable (the elderly, women, children), as well as those considered prison collaborators and informers.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><italic>Inmate CA</italic>: All the inmates housed in the wing across from ours are dirty <italic>sharshukhot</italic> [sluts] that were incarcerated for violent crimes against “weak populations” or rape. These <italic>sharmutot</italic> [prostitutes] were separated from other inmates ‘cause everybody knows that housing them together with us [i.e., the general inmate population] will almost automatically lead to severe injury.</p>
<p><italic>Inmate MO</italic>: These stinking “benders” [homosexuals] in the “protected” wing are fucking <italic>kusiot</italic> [i.e., women working as prostitutes] that cooperated with the prison staff . . . they are considered nothing . . . zero . . . people with no shame or integrity.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In line with the illegitimacy of same-sex sexual activity in Israeli prisons, sexual argot is used nonsexually in a highly intense manner—a clear indication that this is about contempt and power. Given that Israeli inmates continuously attempt to achieve machismo status through violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0032885512467316">Einat, 2005</xref>), and yet perceive same-sex sexual harassment—a means of seeking supremacy of fellow inmates—as an indication of mental feebleness, sexual slang terms are used to humiliate other prisoners and demonstrate their weakness and inferiority. Correspondingly, prisoners labeled by one of the humiliating sexual terms have two options, either to fight and defend their honor, thereby improving their social status, or to submit to constant and long-lasting contempt on the part of their fellow inmates.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0032885512467316" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>It appears that Israeli male prisoners reject both consensual and forced same-sex sexual behavior. During the period 1997 to 2005, there were only two same-sex sexual rapes and no sexual assaults or sexual harassment in Israeli prisons. Even consensual sex relationships—a practice that is firmly rooted in Western prison life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0032885512467316">Ross &amp; Richards, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0032885512467316">Toch, 1992</xref>)—were very rarely cited by the study participants. Although a sexual invitation rate reported by approximately 1.5% of the total population of Israeli inmates in three prison facilities cannot be considered a true and certain reflection of the actual sex rate in male prisons, the random selection of male prisoners and prisons does enable some kind of generalization.</p>
<p>Unlike the prison subcultures in many Western male facilities, where same-sex sexual relationships are experienced as a practical way of obtaining “appropriate substitutes” for women, Israeli inmates conceive of same-sex sexual rapists, sexual aggressors, and gay offenders in prison as mentally and physically weak and, thus, contemptible. They are socially isolated, stigmatized, and given humiliating labels. In fact, to minimize prison violence, gay inmates are often housed separately from heterosexual inmates in Israeli prisons (although this “segregation policy” is unofficial). Argot terms are used derogatively to express negative views of same-gender sex.</p>
<p>These findings are arguably exclusive to Israeli prisons and stand in contrast to parallel results from research in most Western prisons. Two questions emerge in this regard: (a) What are the main reasons for the scarcity of same-sex sexual relationships in Israeli prisons and their irrelevancy as a means of social control? and (b) what is the relevance of argot in this regard?</p>
<p>The answers to the first question are ample. For one thing, and <italic>merely</italic> in regard to consensual homosexuality, Israeli prisoners have considerable opportunities for heterosexual relationships. Of all Israeli inmates, 49.8% are sentenced to a maximum of 3 years, and, like all prisoners, are entitled to a monthly 48-hour leave after completing one quarter of their sentence. In other words, for almost half the prison population, heterosexual relationships are only denied for a maximum of 9 months. Moreover, in keeping with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0032885512467316">Ibrahim’s (1974)</xref> arguments for decreasing prison violence, as well as the findings presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0032885512467316">Carlson and Cervera (1991)</xref> regarding the impact of conjugal meetings on reducing same-sex sexual behavior and sexual assaults, as well as increasing family stability and/or maintaining family ties, the IPS permits conjugal visits inside the prison facility. In addition, the authorities also allow special leave for inmates who were married when incarcerated, those married with no children, those receiving fertility treatments, and those sentenced to at least 15 years and having one child.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0032885512467316">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Furthermore, HIV/AIDS among Israeli prisoners has been a growing concern over the past two decades for a variety of reasons, particularly in light of the worldwide spread of the disease and the increasing rates of incarceration of high-risk prisoners (drug users and tattoo makers). Nevertheless, theoretically it might be argued that education and training of inmate populations and staff are the primary tools for addressing HIV/AIDS in correctional facilities and reducing the anxiety in this respect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0032885512467316">Gido, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0032885512467316">Saum et al., 1995</xref>). It is clear that currently most Israeli inmates lack any knowledge regarding the disease and are anxious of being infected. Accordingly, the majority of Israeli prisoners indulge in negative stereotyping of HIV/AIDS inmates, socially marginalize gay prisoners, and classify same-sex sexual behavior in prison as misconduct. It seems that this psychosocial dynamic has virtually stopped prisoners from performing (or even contemplating) any same-sex sexual act. This is consistent with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0032885512467316">Starchild (1990)</xref> and Saum et al. that HIV/AIDS has reduced the incidence of same-sex sexual rape in American prisons considerably.</p>
<p>In addition, 96.8% of Israeli criminal prisoners are Jews (38.2%), Muslims (52.3%), or Christians (6.3%;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ips.gov.il/Data/data.asp">http://www.ips.gov.il/Data/data.asp</ext-link>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0032885512467316">9</xref></sup> Considering the absolute objection to any form of same-sex sexual relationships by the three monotheistic religions, and in light of the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0032885512467316">Hensley et al. (2001)</xref>, which identifies religion and race as the most salient predictor variables of same-sex sexual behavior in prison, a possible connection (casual or correlated) could arguably exist between sexual activity in Israeli prisons and religion.</p>
<p>Last, in light of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0032885512467316">O’Donnell’s (2004)</xref> tentative suggestions of a possible correlation between the extent of same-sex sexual rape and its usage as an instrument of social control, on the one hand, and high levels of deadly violence in society, on the other (<italic>n</italic> = 249), one might speculate that the scarcity of coerced same-sex sexual relationships in Israeli prisons may be indicative of low levels of violent behavior in the society. Unfortunately, Israel’s average homicide rate per million between 1997 and 2004 was 28.19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0032885512467316">Israeli Central Bureau of Statistics, 2004</xref>)—indeed low compared with 62.6 in the United States, but relatively high compared with 14.5 in England and Wales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0032885512467316">Barclay, Tavares, &amp; Siddique, 2001</xref>). Accordingly, it can be argued that the lack of consensual and forced same-sex sexual activities in Israeli prisons has less to do with general characteristics of Israeli society and more to do with the Israeli prison subculture today. In other words, the explanation for the existence of sex-free prisons should be prisoner oriented.</p>
<p>As for the relevance of prison argot, it appears that the terms once used cynically to mock homosexual rapists, as well as inmates engaged in same-sex sexual behavior in prison, are now used mainly to humiliate collaborators, informers, submissive inmates, and those who perpetrate violent crimes against weak populations. The “deep-sea diver,” the “muffler,” the “swallower,” and the like are all caricatures of antisocial types applied to inmates who do not adhere to the unspoken code of prisoner behavior.</p>
<p>Building upon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0032885512467316">Irwin and Owen’s (2005)</xref> argument that adult prisoners perceive inequality and unfairness rooted in corruption and class bias in the way they were handled by law enforcement agencies in the court, I believe that Israeli inmates see coerced same-sex sexual relationships and other betrayals of the prisoners’ code as a perverse symbol of their own abuse by society. In their eyes, the state doubly victimizes them, both because of the social inequality into which they were born, grew up, and competed as adults and because of discrimination and injustice they suffered at the hands of the criminal law enforcement system. In turn, as a symbol of coolness and masculinity, the prisoners condemn same-sex sexual conduct in prison and humiliate gay inmates and rapists verbally and socially. Furthermore, they transfer this intense contempt for same-sex sexual behavior to other prisoners who have broken the code, stigmatizing them as womanized individuals. In the eyes of the prison population, deprivation of heterosexual relationships is bad, but conversion of a man into a woman is horrible.</p>
<p>In closing, the focus of this study is twofold: to understand why Israeli prisoners reject both consensual and forced male prison sex almost absolutely, and to examine the significance of sexual argot in the prison culture. This analysis suggests that same-sex sexual activity is perceived as a feminine type of behavior, reflecting mental as well as physical weakness. Inmates who initiate same-sex sexual relationships are perceived as men who have been “broken,” and they are stigmatized by a wide range of contemptuous and humiliating terms. Same-sex sexual rape is currently conceived as disreputable and has been replaced by other forms of conduct, mainly physical violence and social isolation. Argot is used derogatively to express negative views of such behavior as well as of unacceptable nonsexual conduct.</p>
<p>Most important, and in contrast to the pessimistic stance of some writers regarding the possibility of eradicating inmate rape and the relatively disappointing impact of various attempts to devise preventive programs in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0032885512467316">Rideau &amp; Sinclair, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0032885512467316">Tewksbury &amp; West, 2000</xref>), the Israeli experience proposes a possible effective solution for minimizing male prison sex. This involves a combination of conjugal visits and relatively frequent home furlough programs (preferably, after serving a rather short portion of the sentence).</p>
<p>As a final note, it should be emphasized that prison sex research in Israel and worldwide is seriously lacking and fails to adequately address the policy needs of correctional authorities. Most research has involved male offenders and ignored female inmates, neglecting the distinction between men and women in terms of their sexual behavior and attitudes. There is no solid data regarding the most marginalized prisoners (sex offenders, prisoners participating in same-sex sexual behavior, and other vulnerable inmates) and their subjective perception of prison life or, alternatively, prison survival. We know very little of how prisoners create characterizations of sexuality. Few studies have concentrated on similarities or differences in sexual argot terms and roles in prisons in different countries or regions; this means that significant variations and discrepancies are sometimes ignored. There is a dearth of research and lack of accurate data regarding sexual victimization and manipulation of prisoners by correctional officers. The existing literature on male prison sex hardly touches upon any of these areas. There is a great need for additional research that addresses the above, so that we can begin to explore the answers to these types of questions and possibly achieve a satisfactory solution to the problem of prison sex.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0032885512467316">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Variations in the range of findings may reflect cultural differences in the prison institutions, differences in definitions and reporting criteria, as well as variations in procedures for recording allegations (Bureau of Justice Statistics, 2005).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0032885512467316">
<label>2.</label>
<p>It is noteworthy, however, that according to the author, this finding “greatly contradicted the respondents’ opinions of the frequency of consensual homosexual activity within their institution. For example: almost 70 percent of the sample reported that consensual sex in prison occurred every day” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0032885512467316">Koscheski, Hensley, Wright, &amp; Tewksbury, 2002</xref>, pp. 116-117).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0032885512467316">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Specifically, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0032885512467316">Ibrahim (1974)</xref> presents six aspects of prison’s social structure: (a) unisex community, (b) inmates’ and officials’ tolerant attitudes regarding deviant sexual behavior, (c) insufficient work opportunities in prisons, (d) overcrowding, (e) lack of a practical classification system, and (f) complete detachment from the world outside the prison walls.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0032885512467316">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Initially, 160 inmates were recruited to the study, but 9 chose to drop out after being informed about the purpose of the study and its procedures.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0032885512467316">
<label>5.</label>
<p>The study is limited to prisons for adult males and does not include the one women’s prison and the one juvenile detention centre in Israel, as well as the three prison facilities for terror criminals—mainly due to the inaccessibility of security prison facilities for research purposes.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0032885512467316">
<label>6.</label>
<p>The main advantage of such an interview is that it enables the interviewee to correct misunderstandings and vagueness in the course of the interview. This flexibility contributes to the quality and credibility of the interview (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0032885512467316">Rubin &amp; Rubin, 1995</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0032885512467316">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Preference was given to recording rather than taking notes during the conversation because (a) detailed note-taking can distract both researcher and interviewee and disrupt the conversation; (b) it is mentally exhausting to listen closely to everything said while taking accurate notes; (c) it is important to keep data collection and analysis separate and avoid premature conclusions before all of the data are in, while taking notes requires the researcher to make judgments about what is <italic>important</italic> during the interview; and (d) like any other research effort, it is desirable to keep the original data complete and intact, so that both the researcher and other interested researchers can refer to it, if necessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0032885512467316">Doyle, 2001</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0032885512467316">
<label>8.</label>
<p>It should be noted however that numerous studies have found conjugal visits to be an unsatisfactory means to prevent prison rape, since such visits tend to be more about sexual pleasure whereas the latter tend to be more about power gratification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0032885512467316">Hensley, Rutland, &amp; Gray-Ray, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0032885512467316">Hensley, Struckman-Johnson, &amp; Eigenberg, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0032885512467316">Hensley, Tewksbury, &amp; Wright, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0032885512467316">Knowles, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0032885512467316">Lockwood, 1980</xref>). Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0032885512467316">Bennett (1989)</xref> found that more than 50% of prison administrators did not believe that conjugal visitation programs could reduce homosexual behavior and sexual assaults.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0032885512467316">
<label>9.</label>
<p>1.06% are Druze and 2.07% are categorized as “others” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ips.gov.il/Data/data.asp">http://www.ips.gov.il/Data/data.asp</ext-link>).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Tomer Einat</bold> is a faculty member in the Department of Criminology in Bar-Ilan University, Israel. His research areas are prisons, the psychosocial effects of prison on male and female inmates, criminal justice, alternatives to incarceration, and intellectual disabilities and criminal behavior.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barclay</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>International comparisons of criminal justice statistics: 1999</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Research, Development and Statistics Directorate, The Home Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>, <month>August</month>). <source>Sexual violence reported by correctional authorities, 2006</source> (Special Report: NCJ 218914). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Correctional administrators’ attitudes toward private family visiting</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>110</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laster</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The impact of HIV/AIDS on corrections</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The dilemmas of corrections: Contemporary perspectives</source> (Chapter 38, pp. <fpage>574</fpage>-<lpage>591</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Prospect Heights, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Waveland Press, Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Learning how to ask: A sociolinguistic appraisal of the role of the interview in social science research</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cervera</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Inmates and their families: Conjugal visits, family contact, and family functioning</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice and Behavior</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>318</fpage>-<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Argot roles and prison sexual hierarchy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Prison sex: practice &amp; policy</source> (pp. <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clemmer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1958</year>). <source>The prison community</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rinehart</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groth</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault in correctional institutions: Prevention and intervention</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Victims of sexual aggression: Treatment of children, women and men</source> (pp. <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Van Nostrand Reinhold</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Prisoner rape education program: Overview for administrators and staff</source>. <publisher-loc>Brandon, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Safer Society Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Unnatural deaths in prison</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Criminology</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Opportunities for learning and engagement: Approaches from participatory and rapid rural appraisal in environmental education</source>. Unpublished master’s thesis, <publisher-name>Cornell University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dumond</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Inmate sexual assault: The plague that persists</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>414</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Donnell</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Prison violence: The dynamics of conflict, fear and power</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eigenberg</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Male rape in prisons: Examining the relationship between correctional officers’ attitudes toward male rape and their willingness to respond to acts of rape</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Braswell</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>L. X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Prison violence in America</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>166</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cincinnati, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Anderson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eigenberg</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Correctional officers and their perceptions of homosexuality, rape, and prostitution in male prisons</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>433</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Einat</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Soldiers’, ‘sausages’, and ‘deep sea diving’: Language, culture and coping in Israeli prisons</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Liebling</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maruna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.), <source>The effects of imprisonment</source> (pp. <fpage>285</fpage>-<lpage>305</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cullompton, Devon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Einat</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Einat</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Inmate argot as an expression of prison subculture: The Israeli case</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wennerstorm</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault of male inmates: Prevention, identification and intervention</article-title>. <source>Journal of Correctional Health Care</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleisher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Warehousing violence</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gido</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Inmates with HIV/AIDS: A growing concern</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Prison sex: Practice and policy</source> (pp. <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haycock</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Capital crimes: Suicides in jail</article-title>. <source>Death Studies</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>433</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Attitudes toward homosexuality in a male and female prison: An exploratory study</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>434</fpage>-<lpage>441</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Consensual homosexual activity in male prisons</article-title>. <source>Corrections Compendium</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Prison sex: Practice and policy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Boulder</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gray-Ray</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Conjugal visitation programs: The logical conclusion</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Prison sex: Practice and policy</source> (pp. <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Struckman-Johnson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eigenberg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Introduction: The history of prison sex research</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Exploring the dynamics of masturbation and consensual same-sex sexual activity within a male maximum security prison</article-title>. <source>Journal of Men’s Studies</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>Deviant sexual behavior in men’s prisons</article-title>. <source>Crime and Delinquency</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Harm and the contemporary prison</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Liebling</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maruna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The effects of imprisonment</source> (Chapter 5, pp. <fpage>94</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press, Criminal Justice Series</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Israel Central Bureau of Statistics</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www1.cbs.gov.il/shnaton55/st11_03">http://www1.cbs.gov.il/shnaton55/st11_03</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Games prisoners play: The secret worlds of Polish jail</source>. <publisher-loc>Irvine</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kirkham</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>Homosexuality in prison</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Henslin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Studies in the sociology of sex</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Appleton-Century-Crofts</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Male prison rape: A search for causation and prevention</article-title>. <source>The Howard Journal</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koscheski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Consensual sexual behavior</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Prison sex: Practice and policy</source> (pp. <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krienert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleisher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>It ain’t happening here: Working to understand prison rape</article-title>. <source>The Criminologist</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kunselman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dumond</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dumond</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Nonconsensual sexual behavior</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Prison sex: Practice and policy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <source>Prison sexual violence</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier/North Holland</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Correction Chief’s AIDS remark upsets Prison Guard Union</article-title>. <source>Times Union</source>, p. <fpage>B-2</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cronan</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Forecasting sexual abuse in prison: The prison subculture of masculinity as a backdrop for “deliberate indifference.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology</source>, <volume>92</volume>(<issue>127</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maruschak</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>HIV in prisons, 1997</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nacci</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>The incidence of sex and sexual aggression in federal prisons: Inmate involvement and employee impact</article-title>. <source>Federal Probation</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Donnell</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Prison rape in context</article-title>. <source>The British Journal of Criminology</source>, <volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pogrebin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Qualitative approaches to criminal justice perspectives from the field</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowlands</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anslow</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kilfedder</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Sexual behavior in Scottish prisons</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>302</volume>, <fpage>1507</fpage>-<lpage>1508</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Fear of homosexuality and modes of rationalization in male prisons</article-title>. <source>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rideau</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Prison: The sexual jungle</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Scacco</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Male rape: A casebook of sexual aggressions</source> (pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AMS Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rideau</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wikberg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Life sentences: Rage and survival behind bars</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Time Books, Random House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Behind bars: Surviving prison</source>. <publisher-loc>Indianapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Alpha</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Qualitative interviewing: The art of hearing data</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sagarin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Prison homosexuality and its effect on post-prison sexual behavior</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saum</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Surratt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inciardi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Sex in prison: Exploring the myths and realities</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>75</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>430</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scacco</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The scapegoat is almost always white</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Scacco</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Male rape: A casebook of sexual aggressions</source> (pp. <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AMS Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stake</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>The art of case study research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Starchild</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Rape of youth in prisons and juvenile facilities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychohistory</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heuston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gossop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>HIV/AIDS risk behavior among adult male prisoners: Research findings 82</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Home Office Research, Development and Statistics Directorate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Basics of qualitative research: Grounded theory procedures and techniques</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Struckman-Johnson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Struckman-Johnson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rucker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bumby</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>A survey of inmate and staff perspectives on prisoner sexual assault</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the Midwestern Psychological Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Chicago, IL</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Struckman-Johnson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Struckman-Johnson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rucker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bumby</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Sexual coercion reported by men and women in prison</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sex Research</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1958</year>). <source>The society of captives</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Fear of sexual assault among prison inmates</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Research on sex in prison during the late 1980s and early 1990s</article-title>. <source>The Prison Journal</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>368</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Toch</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Mosaic of despair</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>U.S. Department of Justice</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>Sexual violence reported by correctional authorities, 2004</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <source>Sexual assault: The victim and the rapist</source>. <publisher-loc>Lexington, KY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Basic content analysis</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0032885512467316">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Corrections: A critical approach</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>