<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SLG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spslg</journal-id>
<journal-title>State and Local Government Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0160-323X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1943-3340</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0160323X12441373</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0160323X12441373</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Governance Matters</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Social Media Sites at the State and Local Levels</article-title>
<subtitle>Operational Success and Governance Failure</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Perlman</surname>
<given-names>Bruce J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0160323X12441373">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0160323X12441373"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0160323X12441373">
<label>1</label>School of Public Administration, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0160323X12441373">Bruce J. Perlman, School of Public Administration, University of New Mexico, Social Sciences Bldg, 3rd Floor, Room 3004, MSC05 3100, Albuquerque, NM 87131, USA Email: <email>bperlman@unm.edu</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0160323X12441373">
<p>
<bold>Bruce J. Perlman</bold> is a professor and former Director of the School of Public Administration at the University of New Mexico where he has held the Hatch Chair in Law and Public Policy and has been a Presidential Lecturer. He has served as Chief Administrative Officer of the City of Albuquerque and Deputy Chief of Staff to the Governor of New Mexico. He has consulted widely with all levels and many types of governments and businesses both in the United States and with other nations.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This essay reviews some of the recent research on operational uses of Social Media Sites (SMS) in state and local governments throughout the world. Also, it assesses the recent research on the employment of SMS for the tasks of governance at the state and local level as distinguished from service delivery. Finally, it discusses the opportunity and need for further research in this latter area and concludes with a call for research in four areas.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>citizen participation</kwd>
<kwd>emergency management governance</kwd>
<kwd>policy formulation</kwd>
<kwd>government operations</kwd>
<kwd>public safety</kwd>
<kwd>social media sites</kwd>
<kwd>transportation management</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0160323X12441373">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>It is opportune to discuss Social Media Sites (SMS) in these pages, given that their possibly most notable icon, Facebook, has only recently opted for an initial public offering that is estimated to net it billions of dollars in capital (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0160323X12441373">Raice 2012</xref>). In addition, another key player on the SMS field, Google, has recently issued a new privacy policy, from which users may not opt out, that ties together its various offerings to more closely track users’ preferences and make their experience more satisfying and productive across its products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0160323X12441373">Ohsumi 2012</xref>). These social media platforms are becoming increasingly important for many citizens in the roles they play in their daily lives as friends and consumers: it is in fact impossible to access some commercial Internet products or services without using them. These tools are being used extensively in local governments as well. At least one survey by the Public Technology Institute found that 72 percent of responding Chief Information Officers claimed to be using or planned on using Facebook or Twitter in outreach efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0160323X12441373">Trenker 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>However, as these programs have become ubiquitous, the study of their place in and impact on our lives has grown but not apace in the effects on governance. Because of the relative recentness of widespread participation in social media technologies, research on social media use in government has been limited. Specifically, the study of and commentary on their effective use in state and local government has increased, but only in some areas. It is the purpose of this essay to review what do know about the effective use of social media at the state and local levels of government and to examine what we do not know and need to know as well. It is this latter area that highlights the focus of this regular section of the State and Local Government Review: Governance.</p>
<p>Accordingly, this essay opens with a working definition of SMS in the context of computer supported networking. It then proceeds to an examination of successful SMS use in government at the state and local levels as well discussing some challenges to that effective use. After that, the essay examines the limited research on use of SMS for governance tasks at the state and local levels. Finally, it closes with some conclusions about the two foregoing areas and a call for further research on SMS related to state and local governance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0160323X12441373">
<title>SMS: A Working Definition</title>
<p>Social and Market Media (SMM) is a Computer Mediated Communication (CMC) that allows users to connect for both social and market exchanges. Unlike other familiar CMC instruments, for example e-mail, SMM tools focus on connections made by a site and the distribution of information, goods, and services rather than on messages or statements. Mirroring the non-CMC world, these exchanges may be purely social or may be market based. SMM includes both SMS and Market Network Sites (MNS). MNS are web-based services used by individuals to qualify, offer, or purchase goods and services with other users connected to the sites and to guarantee delivery and payment when necessary. The most notable and well-known example of an MNS is E-bay, but it includes others such as Craigslist or Angie’s List.</p>
<p>The focus of this essay is SMS. SMS are web-based services used by individuals to construct public or limited profiles within a defined system which list the other users that share connections to the site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0160323X12441373">Boyd and Ellison 2007</xref>). This allows users to do two things. First, users can see and navigate their own list of connections. Second, depending on the permissions given by other users, they may see and navigate the lists of other users within the system. SMS focus on the network of connections made by a site and the distribution of and access to information. The most notable examples of these are Facebook, Twitter, and Google, but they include others as well such as reddit, LinkedIn, flicr, and even MySpace.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0160323X12441373">
<title>Successful SMS Use in State and Local Government Operations</title>
<p>Increasingly SMS are being used, or at least experimented with, in the day-to-day tasks of state, regional, county, and municipal governments. Most of this use is for operations: the communications, direction, and coordination of service delivery and the numerous specific tasks and activities that make it up. Successful use has been reported in three key operational areas: public safety, transportation, and infrastructure and environmental management.</p>
<sec id="section4-0160323X12441373">
<title>Public Safety</title>
<p>Innovative and successful use of SMS have been reported across several areas of public safety, including, police-citizen communications, firefighting, and emergency management. These uses go beyond the most common method of hosting a Facebook page and collecting “Likes” for an agency or program. Some examples of innovative and effective use are from the United States while others are from the United Kingdom.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0160323X12441373">
<title>Police and the Community</title>
<p>For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0160323X12441373">Crump (2011</xref>) has reported the growth in the use of Twitter by U.K. police forces since 2008. By analyzing network structure and message content, his paper presents how U.K. police have employed one particular SMS platform, Twitter, as reinforcement for existing means of communication to collect information from citizens and to alert them to incidents. However, he concludes that the constraints of police culture have led to a limited and cautious one-way use of Twitter making it effective for sending information, but dampening the potential for innovation and its being used only warily and in a controlled manner.</p>
<p>The U.K. Association of Chief Police Officers has attempted to promote the use of SMS as a way to engage uninvolved citizens in conversations about local policing and in consideration of local priorities for policing. Their goal is to increase public participation in crime reduction and encourage it as a shared responsibility as well as enhancing public trust in the police. Unfortunately, this has not been a wholly successful endeavor most probably due to the hierarchical, command, and control nature of police organizations: they are less able to take advantage of the possibilities for user-created content and the freely networked nature of SMS as opposed to a more traditional “push-pull” model of Internet communication.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0160323X12441373">
<title>Disaster and Emergency Management</title>
<p>Emergency communication at the county and city levels has seen the effective employment of SMS. This is especially true in the transmitting of information to the public about emergencies, although the use of SMS in collecting information about the epidemiology of disease has also been reported. An International City/County Management Association (ICMA) report by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0160323X12441373">Chavez, Repas, and Stefaniak (2010</xref>) presents six cases of U.S. local government SMS use for emergency communication: Evanston, Illinois; Fort Bend, Texas; Johnson County, Kansas; City of Moorhead, Minnesota; City of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and Alexandria, Virginia.</p>
<p>The City of Alexandria used both Twitter and YouTube for citizen emergency communications during the H1N1 influenza outbreak; the epidemiological use of Twitter for tracking disease was particularly notable and innovative. Also, that city has used Twitter for citizen communications in severe winter weather emergencies and to track and route the operation of snow plows during such winter emergencies. Philadelphia has employed SMS for communicating with citizens during critical power outages, although the dependence of SMS on electricity makes this a somewhat counterintuitive example. During the Red River Flood, the City of Moorhead, employed SMS effectively and Johnson County, Kansas, uses both blogs and podcasts to keep citizens informed about tornadoes and the methods for coping with them.</p>
<p>In addition, SMS has been employed by the public in local emergencies in less structured and more emergent ways. SMS use in disaster management outside of official sites is an example of emerging communication networks that have yet to be reflected in state and local operations and in actual organizational arrangements for emergency response. As the U.K. police example illustrates, local agencies themselves may not be able to exploit these networks effectively until they have greater experience with and integration of the SMS tools available. When they do they may become better managers of the tools and forge more effective communication with the public. However, it is clear that hierarchy, control, and trust will continue to be impediments.</p>
<p>One example of emergent rather than structured network use of SMS is found in the 2007 Southern California Wild fires. In this case, SMS for local communications was not led by but emerged as complementary to the operations of local governments. As one study suggests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0160323X12441373">Sutton, Palen, and Shklovski  2008</xref>), SMS sites expanded public participation during this wildfire disaster that crossed multiple jurisdictions. Public participants were able to post, exchange, and update information in a timely way that led to public fears being allayed and public order more effectively preserved. In this instance, it was not the use of SMS by authorities that was effective, but rather the use by citizens: through the use of “backchannel” communications community information resources were mobilized by SMS. The result of these broad, cross jurisdictional interactions was the generation of information that was not always readily available to citizens through official sources.</p>
<p>As would be expected, some concern has been expressed by public safety officials about the accuracy of such emergency information shared through public networking and its potential for creating problems or panic. Nevertheless as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0160323X12441373">Klang and Nolan (2011)</xref> point out, if SMS-based disaster communication efforts are hampered by municipal regulations, this risks dampening one of the most effective uses of SMS: citizen networking. Put baldly, the trade-off may be between the desire of local public safety officials for procedural regulation and the saving of lives.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0160323X12441373">
<title>Transportation Management</title>
<p>SMS has been widely used at the state and local level to facilitate transportation both in the United States and abroad. Transportation does not include the maintenance of road infrastructure which is discussed in the third section below. However, it does include two key components of transportation management: Highway Safety and Traffic Management.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0160323X12441373">
<title>Highway Safety</title>
<p>U.K. and Australian state and local agencies have embraced social media approaches in the effective promotion of road safety and injury prevention, specifically the use of YouTube and the targeting of youth through the use of games (Murray and Lewis, September 1–2, 2011). In some cases, like the “Embrace Life” seatbelt campaign from the Sussex Safer Roads Partnership in the United Kingdom, road safety–related campaigns have been devised specifically for dissemination through SMS in that case, a YouTube commercial targeting seatbelt use. That video and the accompanying campaign attracted worldwide notice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0160323X12441373">Osocio 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Similarly, in Australia, a video montage of television commercials produced by the Victorian Transport Accident Commission (TAC) was launched in late 2009 on YouTube and also on broadcast television; the TAC’s YouTube channel became the third most viewed sponsored channel on YouTube postcampaign (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0160323X12441373">Campaign Brief 2010</xref>). Further, the Queensland Department of Transport and Main Roads developed the CityGTiPhone application 4 designed to look like a regular driving game and not a road safety campaign. It was ranked in the top three “hottest Apps” on iTunes, and was one of 2009’s most popular free Apps on the Australian iTunes store (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0160323X12441373">Australia 2011</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0160323X12441373">
<title>Traffic Management</title>
<p>Arlington County, Virginia government has maintained a Facebook page since early 2010. A content analysis of the posts and responses (comments) from the public during a two-month period (August–September 2010) revealed that the most common posts by the County on the Facebook page were about traffic (e.g., conditions, closures, metro outages). The public comments were predominantly related to traffic as well, followed by miscellaneous events (i.e., events that do not fall into other “event” categories, such as food, exercise, music, and film). Interestingly, other related exercise events (city-sponsored bikes and walks) that have an impact on traffic also, generated the next most frequent number of comments from the public (Kavanaugh and Nastev, March 11, 2011).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0160323X12441373">
<title>Infrastructure and Environmental Management</title>
<p>One area in which SMS has been effective in pulling information from citizens to monitor government services and operations has been for reporting infrastructure that needs either repair or maintenance and for reporting environmental lapses. This is a key part of citizen participation in government functioning and a source of valuable service and maintenance information. It is an underpinning to the movement to create “smart” cities wherein citizens and their mobile devices are transformed from civic participants only into “sensors” for local government infrastructure and environmental management systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0160323X12441373">Ratti and Townsend 2011</xref>). These arrangements facilitate a “just in time” delivery of repairs that makes the maintenance of infrastructure more efficient.</p>
<p>“Apps” have been developed for smart phones that allow citizens of local governments to report highway and road infrastructure failings such as potholes directly to public works departments and to have work orders generated to fix them. These applications combine the ubiquity of smart phones and their internal GPS with the ability of the phones to communicate directly with SMS over the Internet to both report and locate needed repairs. Along these lines, other smart phone enabled SMS interactions have been developed such as noise pollution monitoring that makes use of the ability of the phone to “hear,” measure, and report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0160323X12441373">Participatory noise pollution monitoring using mobile phones, 2010</xref>). Another useful application of the smart phone SMS link at the local level has been the reporting of graffiti to removal teams making use of the smart phones’ camera, as well as its GPS facility and Internet connectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0160323X12441373">Jayakanthan 2011</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0160323X12441373">
<title>Governance and SMS at the State and Local Level</title>
<p>As the first part of this essay makes clear, SMS have been employed throughout the world and effectively used to improve the delivery of services by getting information to and from citizens about problems, emergencies, and maintenance. Service delivery and the usefulness of SMS is a component of state and local governments’ relationship with their citizens that has been well studied and, in some areas, found to be highly effective and admitting of even greater promise. Nevertheless, there is another element of state and local government for which the promises of SMS—greater connectivity among citizens themselves in the coalescence of policy preferences, faster iteration and communication of these preferences between citizens and representatives, and higher citizen participation in representative forums—have been touted but not yet delivered or well studied. That is the second “building block” of state and local government which this essay examines: the use of SMS in “governance” rather than operational arrangements.</p>
<sec id="section12-0160323X12441373">
<title>Citizen Engagement and Participation</title>
<p>One arena in which there has been some experimentation in and great hope for the broad connectivity offered by SMS is in the potential for increasing public participation in the formulation of public policy at the state and local levels. The ease of use and connectivity of SMS has implied a route to alleviating the physical difficulties and time pressures of travel, crowds, and fixed hours for participation in traditional public meetings at which policy and policy changes are hammered out. In addition, the leveling factor of lateral connectivity among citizens seems to imply the possibility of a less hierarchal approach to their participation in decision making at the state and local level.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0160323X12441373">
<title>Citizen Engagement and Power Sharing</title>
<p>Only a little study has taken place of the impact of SMS on citizen engagement in policy and allowing for expressive input on important policy framing matters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0160323X12441373">Lyons 2011</xref>). However, at least one study has looked at the power dynamics of the use of Facebook pages in this regard. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0160323X12441373">Hand and Ching (2011</xref>) examined the usefulness of Facebook pages as a way to connect citizens with each other (many-to-many) for policy input versus the utilization of those SMS to transmit to and receive from government to citizens (one-to-many) in a more authoritative manner. What the authors encountered in their exploratory study in the Phoenix area is that the city governments studied use Facebook to maintain power relations and inform citizens about their views (speaking-from-power) rather than using the platform for the sort of connectivity for which it was intended: that is flat, egalitarian networked communications or even iterated and critical feedback (speaking-to-power) exchanges.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0160323X12441373">
<title>Citizen Engagement and SMS Usage Policy</title>
<p>SMS can be seen as a resource for increased interaction between municipal authorities and citizens. However, as authorities attempt to employ SMS, they may become trapped by their own traditional regulatory frameworks that emphasize openness and transparency rather than citizen interaction. Rather than being a largely innovative endeavor that attempts to extend public participation, provide an alternative to other mechanisms, or replace traditional local government forums, SMS use at the local level may be challenged by existing constraints and legal frameworks.</p>
<p>A study of the SMS policies of twenty-six Swedish municipalities is interesting in this regard. It reveals that these SMS regulatory polices do not take a united view on the usefulness of SMS and some treat it as a problem rather than a possibility. In general across the municipal policies examined, the tendency was to take a “command and control” stance and to establish clear goals and routines for SMS use and to discipline activities to adhere to this order. Moreover, the authors offer that such an approach does not merely err on the side of transparency instead of citizen interaction, but that it most often explicitly disallows activity that promotes local government innovation and adaptation to citizen needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0160323X12441373">Klang and Nolin 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>This focus on regulating and the controlling innovation in using SMS to engage citizens in policy formulation seems to be found in the United States as well. In a recent study designed to help fill the gap in what is known about social media policy in U.S. government, the Center for Technology in Government undertook a content review of SMS policies. The study was a “best practices” effort designed to produce a new resource to guide government social media policy development efforts. The study found that there are eight core elements of local government social media policy in the United States: (1) employee access, (2) account management, (3) acceptable use, (4) employee conduct, (5) content, (6) security, (7) legal issues, and (8) citizen conduct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0160323X12441373">Hrdinová, Helbig, and Peters, May 2010</xref>). It is not surprising that nearly all of these elements are restrictive and concerned with regulation of conduct and content, and that they do not speak to the issues of SMS innovation, use in policy networks, or citizen participation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0160323X12441373">
<title>Elections and Electoral Campaigns</title>
<p>SMS have been used for voter participation, mobilization, and fund-raising in various national elections. Some have credited them with a significant role in the 2008 U.S. Presidential victory of Barack Obama. However, other research has cast some doubt on this premise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0160323X12441373">Kushin and Yamamoto 2010</xref>). Also, in the 2010 national elections in the Netherlands, politicians with higher SMS engagement got relatively more votes within most political parties. However, SMS did not significantly influence voting behavior during the 2010–2011 local elections (Picazo-Velazquez n. d.). Other studies of local SMS roles played in state and local elections have not been forthcoming.</p>
<p>Another component of elections, campaign financing and candidate wealth information, has been affected by SMS-like applications if not by SMS themselves. Most states in the United States, many counties and municipalities, and similar jurisdictions in other countries, for example Mexico, use some sort of Internet-based platform for the collection and publication of electoral financing. In many cases, these sites receive only financial information inputs from the campaigns of candidates who must post them. However, most often the information posted is “crowd sourced,” that is, accessible to anyone who cares to access it. In some states, this includes digitized affidavits, brochures, receipts, or other documents. In addition, most election results down to the precinct level are available online, post election.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0160323X12441373">
<title>Conclusion: The Undelivered Promise of SMS for State and Local Governance</title>
<p>SMS are all the rage today: the staple of daily communication and commerce for many; the source of new fortunes for a few. In state and local governments throughout the world, they have played a significant role in helping to put the eyes of citizens on operations that range from filling cracks in the sidewalk to tracking the money collected by local officials in their runs for office. Like other technological innovations in the commercial world from the steamroller to the personal computer, SMS has changed the way government does its business: new tools for private business mean new business and operations and this always means the same for the public sector as well as new regulatory responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0160323X12441373">Dadashzadeh 2010</xref>). After all, as Allison points out, the two sectors are just alike in all “unimportant respects” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0160323X12441373">Allison 1979</xref>).</p>
<p>Conversely, it is in these “important respects” of state and local government—citizen engagement and participation, policy input, elections, and representation; the stuff of local governance if not government—where SMS has not played a noteworthy role (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0160323X12441373">Lampe et al. 2011</xref>). Furthermore, this is an area where some hope might be held out for its development as a tool specifically of government and not business: replacing real town halls with virtual ones; tracking citizen policy preferences in real time (Mentzas et al. 2011); issue-based coalition formation and dissolution among networked citizens rather than interest group formation as the norm; enhanced citizen connectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0160323X12441373">Taylor-Smith and Lindner 2010</xref>). Virtual business is a reality, but virtual government is not.</p>
<p>Obviously, this sort of SMS use would be transformational and thus not without transaction costs, risks, and difficulties of fitting technology to task (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0160323X12441373">Lampe et al. 2011</xref>). Replacing the old with the new is never costless and the regulatory frameworks that we have now present both cost and risk in the widespread use, availability, and archiving of SMS and the records they generate. This is why the preponderance of the articles on the topic of SMS use for government are about either using them as tools in current operations or controlling them: strategies for use, best practices and policies, or rules for effective employment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0160323X12441373">Mergel 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Clearly then, what is lacking in the study of SMS at the state and local level is examination of their effective use in governance. How can we successfully employ SMS to link citizens together and with business and with government? How to make the “governing” part of government easier and more connected in order for citizens to engage in it and not just government operations? How to link business more effectively with government and vice versa? What is needed is further research, building on the successful research conducted already, in at least four areas:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Making the actual virtual: What are the ideas, experiments, and efforts to reinvent local forums, meetings, and other essential gatherings using SMS to better and more easily connect citizens with local government in the formulation of public policy? This includes the discussion, design, and testing of policy and not just comments on proposals. This is not merely a suggestion for more research into the already commonly used broadcast or collection of information by local governments.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Best transformational practices: What are state and local governments doing to promote innovative use of SMS in governance and to reduce the risks, opportunity costs, and transaction costs for SMS adoption? Some of this research should focus on who is innovating, where, and in what in SMS supported governance arrangements at the local level. Other parts of this research should focus on the legal aspects of innovative SMS use possibly examining proposals to differentiate networked communications from standard ones governed (and limited) by transparency and other strictures that make them too costly and risky for local government. Other research in this area might focus on the way to incentivize or at least remove disincentives for SMS use in governance innovation.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Emergent-cies: What are citizens doing with SMS to communicate about local government policy, representation, and service that local government can learn from and employ? One of the tenets of SMS is connectivity and one of the tenets of this is “laterality,” the notion that there is no hierarchy in effective networks. If SMS is to be used to engage citizens in their governments, especially in a nonhierarchical way, some of the best ideas may emerge from the practices of citizens themselves. This is one of the ingredients least studied by political scientists, students of public administration, and practitioners because they tend to study stable government institutions and not emergent citizen-driven ones.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Electoral connections: How can SMS be used to more effectively mobilize citizens at the state and local levels to participate in the selection of their representatives, communicate with them, and increase their satisfaction with this process? Again, this is not the mere automation of existing processes and procedures in e-government, but their lateralization and transformation. It includes studying the use of SMS in all aspects of elections to improve the willingness and ability of citizens to volunteer to support candidates, or to participate in poll watching or registration, or other local electoral tasks and activities.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>These suggestions may not exhaust the areas in which SMS research on state and local governance needs to be carried out. However, they are a start that is based on the perceived holes in current research. One hopes that the pages of the State and Local Government Review will be an outlet where some of this new research is debuted. Certainly, one hopes also that it will be one of the places credited with spurring it.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-0160323X12441373">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-0160323X12441373">
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Allison</surname>
<given-names>Jr</given-names>
<suffix>G. T</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1979</year>. <source>Public and private management: Are they fundamentally alike in all unimportant respects? Proceedings for the public management research conference</source> (pp. <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of Personnel Management</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Australia</surname>
<given-names>P. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2011, May</year>. <source>CityGT iPhone Application</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pria.com.au/resources/government/citygt-iphone-application">http://www.pria.com.au/resources/government/citygt-iphone-application</ext-link> <comment>(accessed January 17, 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boyd</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ellison</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Social network sites: Definition, history, and scholarship</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computer Mediated Communication</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Campaign Brief, 2</collab>. <year>2010, March 2</year>. <source>TAC ad montage now third most viewed sponsored Australian YouTube channel</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.campaignbrief.com/2010/03/tac-ad-montage-draws-internati.html">http://www.campaignbrief.com/2010/03/tac-ad-montage-draws-internati.html</ext-link> <comment>(accessed January 15, 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chavez</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Repas</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stefaniak</surname>
<given-names>T. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <source>A new way to communicate with residents: Local governments’ use of social media to prepare for emergencies</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ICMA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Crump</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2011</year>. <article-title>What are the police doing on Twitter? Social media, the police and the public</article-title>. <source>Policy &amp; Internet</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dadashzadeh</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Social media in government: From egovernment to egovernance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business and Economics Research</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hand</surname>
<given-names>L. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ching</surname>
<given-names>B. D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>You have one friend request: An exploration of power and citizen engagement in local governments’ use of social media</article-title>. <source>Administrative Theory &amp; Praxis</source> <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>362</fpage>—82.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hrdinová</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Helbig</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>.<year>2010, May</year>. <source>Designing social media policy for Government: Eight Essential Elements</source>. <publisher-loc>Albany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Technology in Government, SUNY</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jayakanthan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Community engagement through social media</article-title>. <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<source>Proceedings of the Fifth International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM-11)</source>, pp. <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AAAI Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kavanaugh</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nastev</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>.<year>2011</year>, <comment>March 11</comment>. <source>Final grant report for VT CCSR: Social media for cities counties and communities</source>. <publisher-loc>Arlington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Virginia Tech Center for Community Center and Resilience</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Klang</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nolin</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Disciplining social media: An analysis of social media policies in 26 Swedish municipalities</article-title>. <source>First Monday: Peer Reviewed Journal on the Internet</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kushin</surname>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yamamoto</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Did social media really matter? College students’ use of online media and political decision making in the 2008 election</article-title>. <source>Mass Communication and Society</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lampe</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LaRose</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steinfield</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DeMaagd</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Inerent barriers to the use of social media for public policy informatics</article-title>. <source>The Innovation Journal</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lyons</surname>
<given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2011</year>, <comment>May 7–8</comment>. <source>Facebook as a site of public deliberation on local sustainability policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Vancouver, BC, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute for Resources Environment and Sustainability, University of British Columbia</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mentzas</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Apostolou</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bothos</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Magoutas</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Information markets for social participation in public policy design and implementation</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Fifth International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM-11)</source>, pp. <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AAAI Press</publisher-name>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mergel</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Gov 2.0 Revisited: Social media strategies in the public sector</article-title>. <source>PA TIMES Summer</source>, <volume>33(3)</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>I. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>.<year>2011, September 1–2</year>. <source>Is there an app for that? Social media uses for road safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACRS National Conference</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ohsumi</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <year>2012</year>. <article-title>The Washington post business</article-title>. <source>The Washington Post</source> with <comment>Bloomberg, January 24</comment>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/google-moves-to-integrate-user-data-across-services/2012/01/24/gIQAmv8GOQ_gallery.html#">http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/google-moves-to-integrate-user-data-across-services/2012/01/24/gIQAmv8GOQ_gallery.html#</ext-link> <comment>(accessed January 24, 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Osocio</collab>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Round table: How a local campaign went global—Embrace Live</article-title>, <comment>February 22.Social advertising and non-profit campaigns from around the globe</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://osocio.org/message/embrace_life_always_wear_your_seatbelt/">http://osocio.org/message/embrace_life_always_wear_your_seatbelt/</ext-link> <comment>(accessed January 15, 2012)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Participatory noise pollution monitoring using mobile phones</collab>. <year>2010</year>. <source>Information Polity</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.3233/IP-2010–0200</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Picazo-Velazquez</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>n.d</year>. <article-title>Social media in the public sector: perceived benefits, costs and strategic alternatives</article-title>. <comment>Proceedings of the 12th Annual International Digital Government Research Conference: Digital Government Innovation in Challenging Times</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Raice</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012, February 2</year>). <article-title>Facebook sets historic IPO</article-title>. <source>The Wall Street Journal</source>, <issue>p. A12</issue>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ratti</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Townsend</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2011, August 16</year>. <article-title>The social nexus</article-title>. <source>Scientific American</source> <volume>305</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sutton</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Palen</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shklovski</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2008, May</year>. <article-title>Backchannels on the front lines: Emergent use of social media in the 2007 Southern California wildfires</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Proceedings of the 5th International ISCRAM Conference</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taylor-Smith</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lindner</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <source>Social networking tools supporting constructive involvement throughout the policy-cycle</source>. <publisher-loc>International conference on electronic democracy, centre for E-government, Danube-university. Krems</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Austrian Computer Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0160323X12441373">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trenker</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2010, January</year>). <article-title>Social media: Friend or foe?</article-title> <source>Governing</source>, pp. <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>