<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Textile Research Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5175</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1746-7748</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040517512464290</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040517512464290</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Surface roughness and wettability of wool fabrics loaded with silver nanoparticles: Influence of synthesis and application methods</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>Hossein</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0040517512464290">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0040517512464290">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>Majid</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0040517512464290">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Calvimontes</surname><given-names>Alfredo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0040517512464290">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Dutschk</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0040517512464290">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0040517512464290"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040517512464290"><label>1</label>Department of Carpet, Faculty of Art, University of Birjand, Birjand, Iran</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0040517512464290"><label>2</label>Textile Engineering Department, Amirkabir University of Technology, Center of Excellence, Hafez Avenue, Tehran, Iran</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0040517512464290"><label>3</label>Leibniz Institute of Polymer Research Dresden, Germany</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0040517512464290"><label>4</label>Engineering of Fibrous Smart Materials, Faculty of Engineering Technology, University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0040517512464290">Victoria Dutschk, Engineering of Fibrous Smart Materials, Faculty of Engineering Technology, University of Twente, PO Box 217, 7500 AE Enschede, The Netherlands. Email: <email>v.dutschk@utwente.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>83</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>1310</fpage>
<lpage>1318</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Hydrophilization of wool fabrics was performed by silver nanoparticles with different surface charge using three different methods: exhausting, pad–dry–cure and in situ synthesis. Dynamic wetting measurements and surface topography analysis were used to evaluate surface changes on wool fabrics. The wool samples in situ loaded revealed the highest fabric roughness and porosity, while the use of the pad–dry–cure method leads to the lowest fabric porosity, and its roughness values approximately were the same as those for samples loaded with the exhaustion method. The results revealed that loading silver nanoparticles with high surface charges onto wool fabrics via the exhaustion method can significantly improve the hydrophilicity of wool fibre surface. The possible reasons for this improvement are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>wool fabric</kwd>
<kwd>silver nanoparticles</kwd>
<kwd>hydrophilicity</kwd>
<kwd>roughness</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Wool fibre is a protein fibre composed of keratin and its outer surface is covered by a fatty acid layer. The presence of this layer creates a hydrophobic surface, preventing water drop absorption and sweat venting, which affects the wearing comfort of wool textiles.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0040517512464290">1</xref></sup> It is well known that the chemical composition and surface topography<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512464290">2</xref></sup> affect the fabric wettability. Surface roughness has different effects on the hydrophobic and hydrophilic surfaces. On hydrophilic surfaces, the wetting time decreases with increasing roughness, while on hydrophobic surfaces, it increases with increasing roughness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512464290">3</xref></sup> Several techniques were applied to create hydrophilic wool fibre surface, which can be classified into two major types: decomposing the fatty surface layer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0040517512464290">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0040517512464290"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0040517512464290">6</xref></sup> and coating the fatty surface layer of wool fibres with hydrophilic materials.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0040517512464290">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0040517512464290"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0040517512464290"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0040517512464290">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>Applying nanoparticles onto fabric surfaces is a versatile method providing multifunctional textile materials. It was reported that applying nanoparticles can improve the substrate wettability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0040517512464290">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0040517512464290">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512464290">12</xref></sup> Silver nanoparticles commonly applied as antibacterial agents<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512464290">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517512464290">14</xref></sup> are often used as a modifying substance to improve the fabric wettability,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512464290">12</xref></sup> simultaneously providing a wool fabric with two additional properties, hydrophobicity and antibacterial effect. Owing to the high surface energy of silver nanoparticles, the wettability of a loaded substrate can be increased. However, the presence of a stabilizing agent has an influence on this effect. In general, loading silver nanoparticles onto the fabric structure can be conducted by pad–dry–cure,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512464290">12</xref></sup> exhaustion methods,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0040517512464290">15</xref></sup> and in situ synthesis as well as loading simultaneously onto fabrics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0040517512464290">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0040517512464290">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the present study, a wool fabric was loaded with colloidal silver nanoparticles at different concentrations of lecithin as a stabilizing agent. Lecithin is a phospholipid,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517512464290">18</xref></sup> which stabilizes silver nanoparticles in a dispersion. The stability of silver nanoparticles in an aqueous dispersion depends on the lecithin concentration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512464290">13</xref></sup> Lecithin molecules can easily be absorbed by wool fibre<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0040517512464290">19</xref></sup> and, therefore, change the permeability of the wool fibre structure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0040517512464290">20</xref></sup> Different physico-chemical methods were used to quantify topographic modification effects on nano- and macro-scales as well as the wettability of the wool fabric. It was shown that the loading methods applied and the nanoparticles concentration used have different effects on the fatty layer surface.</p>
<sec id="sec1-0040517512464290" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec2-0040517512464290"><title>Reagent and wool fabric</title>
<p>All chemical agents used in this study were of analytical grade. Millipore water was used throughout the studies. Silver nitrate (AgNO3 extra pure, &gt;99.8%) and sodium borohydride (NaBH4, 99.9%) were purchased from Merck (Germany). Lecithin was provided by Lipoid (Lipoid® S 75, Germany). The standard wool fabric was purchased from wfk Testgewebe (Germany). The structure information of the wool fabric used is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0040517512464290">Table 1</xref>. The 2D and 3D images of the wool fabric structure and its type of weave are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0040517512464290">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="fig1-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Two- and three-dimensional images of an untreated wool fabric: (a) untreated wool fabric (scan area of 4 mm × 4 mm); (b) type of weave; (c) 3D image of untreated wool fabric (scan area of 4 mm × 4 mm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the wool fabric used</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0040517512464290" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Area weight (g/m<sup>2</sup>)</th>
<th>Warp density (Count/cm)</th>
<th>Weft density (Count/cm)</th>
<th>Type of weave</th>
<th>Yarn fineness (dtex)</th>
<th>Fibre mean diameter<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0040517512464290">*</xref> (µm)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>125</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>plain 1/1</td>
<td>300/300</td>
<td>19 ± 3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0040517512464290"><label>*</label>
<p>The mean wool fibre diameter was calculated using 2D microscopic images of 20 samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0040517512464290"><title>Silver nanoparticles loading methods</title>
<p>Silver nanoparticles were synthesized as described in details elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512464290">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0040517512464290">21</xref></sup> The colloidal solution of silver nanoparticles was prepared at various lecithin concentrations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0040517512464290">Table 2</xref>). Their surface charges were determined with a Zetasizer Nano ZS (Malvern, UK) at 25℃. The synthesized silver nanoparticles were loaded onto wool fabric by three different methods: exhaustion, pad–dry–cure and in situ synthesis. By using exhaustion method, the scoured wool fabric samples were immersed in an aqueous solution containing silver nanoparticles (liquor ratio of 40:1) at 40℃ with different lecithin-to-silver ratio as listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0040517512464290">Table 2</xref>. The temperature was gradually increased up to 90℃ in 25 min. In pad–dry–cure method, the scoured wool fabrics were immersed into the colloidal solution of silver nanoparticles (400 ppm) with different lecithin concentrations for 15 min at room temperature. After that, the soaked wool fabrics were squeezed using a laboratory padder machine to adjust solution take up to 80% wet pickup. The padded samples were dried at 80℃ for 20 min, followed by curing at 130℃ for 5 min. By the in situ synthesis method, the silver nanoparticles were synthesized in the wool fibre structure. Wool acts as a template for silver nanoparticles. The scoured wool fabric samples were immersed in a silver nitrate solution (400 ppm, liquor ratio of 40 :1) with various lecithin-to-silver ratios at room temperature for 1 h. After that, the treated sample was immersed in the reducing agent bath (800 ppm, liquor ratio of 40 :1) at room temperature for 20 min. Finally, the wool fabric loaded with silver nanoparticles was rinsed and dried in an oven at 80℃ for 20 min. The samples loaded were coded according to the method applied as follows: exhaustion method EhK<sub>a</sub>, in situ synthesis method ISK<sub>a</sub> and pad–dry–cure method PDCK<sub>a</sub>; the subscript shows the lecithin-to-silver ratio.
<table-wrap id="table2-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Preparation of colloidal silver nanoparticles with their surface charge</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0040517512464290" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Sample code</th>
<th>[Lecithin]/ [Ag]</th>
<th>Ag (ppm)</th>
<th>NaBH<sub>4</sub> (ppm)</th>
<th>Surface charge (mV)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>K<sub>0</sub></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>400</td>
<td>800</td>
<td>−26.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>K<sub>0.2</sub></td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>400</td>
<td>800</td>
<td>−48.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>K<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>400</td>
<td>800</td>
<td>−49.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>K<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>2</td>
<td>400</td>
<td>800</td>
<td>−63.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0040517512464290"><title>Topography analysis</title>
<p>The surface topography of samples was examined at the nano- and macro-scales. A non-contact stereophotogrammeter TraceIt (Innowep, Germany) was used as an optical imaging instrument to analyze the macro-topography of wool fabric samples. FRT Mark III software (Version 3.8.10) was used to calculate the roughness parameters from images of 4 mm × 4 mm size. Surface roughness parameters such as <italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic>, <italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic>, and <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> as well as a hybrid parameters (<italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic>) and functional parameters (<italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub>) were obtained from the topographical measurements according to ISO/DIS 25178-2.</p>
<p>The parameter <italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic> is the arithmetic mean surface roughness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0040517512464290">22</xref></sup> being the arithmetic average of all distances between <italic>Z</italic>-value and mean height inside a range of captured area. The parameter <italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic> is usually used for describing the surface roughness. The parameter <italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic> is the root mean square surface roughness between the <italic>Z</italic>-value and the mean surface height. The parameter <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> is the maximum height, between the highest and lowest points in the evaluation area. The parameter <italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic> is a hybrid parameter which was introduced by Wenzel.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0040517512464290">23</xref></sup> The Wenzel roughness factor is defined as the ratio between measured (real) area and projected area. The parameter <italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> is a volumetric characteristic to present the free volume available at the textile surfaces through evaluating porosity or filling quantities as a function of depth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0040517512464290">22</xref></sup> According to Stout et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0040517512464290">24</xref></sup> <italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> is the valley fluid retention index, a topographical parameter that characterizes the porosity of rough surfaces such as textiles. This is the ratio of the void volume of the unit sampling area at the valley zone over the <italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic> deviation.</p>
<p>A high-resolution scandisk confocal microscope µsurf explorer (NanoFocus, Germany) was used to analyze the nano-topography of the wool fibres surface. The 60 × objective lens was used for measuring field size of 260 µm × 260 µm with a 100 nm vertical resolution. Nano Explorer premium software (Version 4.1) was used to calculate the roughness parameters from images by profiling in lengths of approximately 100 µm. Arithmetic mean roughness parameters (<italic>R<sub>a</sub></italic>) of wool fibres were calculated from 10 different positions of each sample.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0040517512464290"><title>Dynamic contact angle measurement</title>
<p>A contact angle value is an indicator for the wetting behaviour of a liquid droplet on a solid surface. A FibroDAT 1122 device (Fibro system, Sweden) was used for measuring contact angles of water as a function of time on different treated wool fabrics. A drop of 17 µl volume was applied on the surface of wool fabric sample (1 cm × 1 cm) by a minimal pulse stroke which leads to lowest oscillation, measuring details of which were described elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0040517512464290">25</xref></sup> A water droplet on the wool fabric surface was recorded and captured for 8 seconds by 4000 frames with a high-speed video camera. The dynamic contact angle measurements were repeated five times for each sample in a laboratory with controlled temperature and relative humidity of 23 ± 1℃ and 50 ± 4%, respectively.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0040517512464290" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec7-0040517512464290"><title>Influence of the silver nanoparticles loading method on the macro-topography of wool fabrics</title>
<p>Macro-topographical characteristics of wool fabrics treated with colloidal silver nanoparticles by three various methods are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0040517512464290">Table 3</xref>. Loading silver nanoparticles onto the wool fabric increased the surface roughness of all treated wool fabrics. The samples loaded with the in situ method revealed the highest surface roughness parameters <italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic>, <italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic>, <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic>, <italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic> (as averages) and <italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub>. All treatments show a significant roughness increase after treatment.
<table-wrap id="table3-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Surface roughness and porosity characteristics of wool fabrics loaded with silver nanoparticles</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0040517512464290" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Sample</th>
<th><italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic> (µm)</th>
<th><italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic> (µm)</th>
<th><italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> (µm)</th>
<th><italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic></th>
<th><italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> (µm<sup>3</sup>/µm<sup>2</sup>)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Untreated</td>
<td>17.7</td>
<td>21.3</td>
<td>122.6</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>0.135</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EhK<sub>0</sub></td>
<td>23.2</td>
<td>28.4</td>
<td>163.5</td>
<td>1.072</td>
<td>0.591</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EhK<sub>0.2</sub></td>
<td>20.4</td>
<td>24.8</td>
<td>152.3</td>
<td>1.125</td>
<td>0.414</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EhK<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>23.3</td>
<td>28.2</td>
<td>156.8</td>
<td>1.154</td>
<td>0.506</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EhK<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>23.5</td>
<td>28.3</td>
<td>154.0</td>
<td>1.126</td>
<td>0.371</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ISK<sub>0</sub></td>
<td>32.9</td>
<td>40.3</td>
<td>246.6</td>
<td>1.142</td>
<td>1.075</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ISK<sub>0.2</sub></td>
<td>35.2</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>272.7</td>
<td>1.152</td>
<td>0.793</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ISK<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>32.7</td>
<td>40.0</td>
<td>264.3</td>
<td>1.142</td>
<td>0.923</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ISK<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>34.2</td>
<td>41.7</td>
<td>268.0</td>
<td>1.148</td>
<td>0.943</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PDCK<sub>0</sub></td>
<td>22.0</td>
<td>26.6</td>
<td>147.2</td>
<td>1.106</td>
<td>0.279</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PDCK<sub>0.2</sub></td>
<td>23.1</td>
<td>27.9</td>
<td>153.0</td>
<td>1.132</td>
<td>0.272</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PDCK<sub>1</sub></td>
<td>23.3</td>
<td>28.1</td>
<td>152.9</td>
<td>1.128</td>
<td>0.411</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PDCK<sub>2</sub></td>
<td>24.1</td>
<td>29.0</td>
<td>168.8</td>
<td>1.189</td>
<td>0.366</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The wool fabric sample treated with silver colloidal solution without stabilizing agent (EhK<sub>0</sub>) using the exhaustion method shows the largest <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> value (maximum height between the highest and lowest points of the surface) compared with that treated with lecithin solutions. This colloidal solution has the lowest stability,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512464290">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517512464290">18</xref></sup> easily agglomerated on the wool fabric and cannot diffuse into the wool fibre structure. Then it can be assumed that the silver nanoparticles were only deposited on the yarns surface and did not diffuse into the wool fibre surface. However, EhK<sub>0</sub> shows the lowest developed surface ratio <italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic> by the exhaustion method, confirming silver nanoparticles agglomeration on the wool fibre surfaces. The samples loaded with the pad–dry–cure and in situ methods without lecithin present the lowest value of <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> and <italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic> because the uptake of unstable silver nanoparticles was low due to the short immersion time and lead to the lowest roughness parameters. In addition, the presence of lecithin by using in situ method can enhance the uptake of silver ions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0040517512464290">26</xref></sup> so the sample without lecithin presents the lowest value of <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> and <italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic>.</p>
<p>An increase of lecithin concentration in the formulation of silver nanoparticles aqueous dispersion resulted in rougher surface (<italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic>, <italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic>, <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> and <italic>S<sub>rl</sub></italic>) of PDCK samples. For EhK and ISK no precise trend for surface roughness was found. The porosity of the <italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> of the wool sample, which was loaded by exhaustion and in situ methods, tends to be reduced by increasing lecithin concentration. As <italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> characterizes the fabric void spaces, i.e. inter-yarn spaces, with the result that the lecithin molecules and silver nanoparticles were also deposited onto the porous structure of wool fabrics. In addition, the samples prepared with in situ synthesis and pad–dry–cure methods, have the highest and the lowest porosity, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0040517512464290">Figure 2</xref>). As by in situ synthesis the wool fibre is swollen by absorbing silver ions and, finally, converted into the silver nanoparticles. In woven structures, fibre swelling results in an increase in weave angle and thickness of yarn cross-section due to the wet relaxation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0040517512464290">27</xref></sup> Therefore, swelling of fibres leads to larger <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> and, as a consequence, larger <italic>S<sub>V</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> values (larger and deeper inter-yarn spaces). However, the fabric was basically squeezed using the pad–dry–cure method and has the lowest porosity value and lower thickness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512464290">Figure 3</xref>). The height histogram presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512464290">Figure 3</xref> helps to compare the thickness between the fabrics treated by the three different methods.
<fig id="fig2-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Images of wool fabric loaded with silver nanoparticles without lecithin using different methods: (a) untreated; (b) EhK<sub>0</sub>; (c) ISK<sub>0</sub>; and (d) PDCK<sub>0</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Heights histogram of wool samples treated with silver nanoparticles using different loading methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Macro-topography of the wool fabric is altered dependent on the loading methods applied. A schematic presentation of changes in the wool fabric cross-section after loading silver nanoparticles is schematically shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512464290">Figure 4</xref>. According to the value of <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> for each sample loaded, it can be confirmed that the sample loaded in the pad–dry–cure method is compressed, while the sample prepared in situ synthesis causes vertical swelling.
<fig id="fig4-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of a cross-section of the wool fabric loaded.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0040517512464290"><title>Influence of the silver nanoparticles loading method on the nano-topography of wool fibres</title>
<p>Wool fibre is a natural fibre which intrinsically has a rough surface. A 3D reconstructed image of wool fibre presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512464290">Figure 5</xref> shows that it has an average roughness value of 138 nm. This is in agreement with other data reported,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0040517512464290">28</xref></sup> which were collected using 3D scanning electron microscopy. However, this value depends on the wool fibre type as well as applied characterization methods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0040517512464290">29</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig5-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Optical image of the untreated wool fibre and treated with different methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Profiled arithmetical mean roughness (<italic>R<sub>a</sub></italic>) of all samples is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517512464290">Figure 6</xref>. Loading silver nanoparticles at various lecithin concentrations by exhaustion and pad–dry–cure methods lead to increasing the average nano-roughness of wool fibres. The highest concentration of lecithin in the colloidal solution can cause a higher affinity to wool fibre due to higher surface charges.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0040517512464290">30</xref></sup> Loading at the highest lecithin concentration by exhaustion and pad–dry–cure methods causes the higher fibre roughness, which confirms the higher uptake of silver nanoparticles by the methods mentioned at the nanometer scale. However, in case of the in situ method, the wool fibre roughness decreased with lecithin presence. The differences observed between roughness parameters at the nano- and macro-topographical scales are discussed in Section 4.
<fig id="fig6-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Roughness characteristics of the wool fibres loaded with silver nanoparticles using different methods. The <italic>R<sub>a</sub></italic> values presented are average values of 10 measurements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0040517512464290"><title>Wetting dynamics results</title>
<p>The wettability results are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512464290">Figure 7</xref>. The contact angle value is reported at 0.2 s after applying a water droplet on the fabric surface in order to reduce the effect of drop oscillation on the contact angle measured. The spreading rates of water droplets on wool fabrics were calculated from the slope of the linear part of the drop base curve versus time. Contact angles for EhK<sub>1</sub> and EhK<sub>2</sub> were measured as 24° and 12°, respectively. The higher porosity of EhK<sub>1</sub> compared with that of EhK<sub>2</sub> leads to a higher spreading rate. No spreading was observed on untreated samples, K<sub>0</sub> and K<sub>0.2</sub>.
<fig id="fig7-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Effects of various modification methods and lecithin concentrations on (a) contact angle and (b) spreading rate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Loading silver nanoparticles by exhaustion method with a higher lecithin concentration (samples EhK<sub>1</sub> and EhK<sub>2</sub>) results in a hydrophilic surface in terms of the water contact angle and spreading rate.</p>
<p>The use of the pad–dry–cure method leads to a slight surface hydrophilization. The in situ method used shows a different trend. In this case, silver nanoparticles were synthesized inside wool fibres and had little effect on the fatty layer of the wool fibre surface. Loading silver nanoparticles onto wool fibres, measured as an increase of <italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic> and <italic>S<sub>q</sub></italic>, cannot change the native hydrophobicity of wool surface. However, an increase of <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic>, i.e. yarn amplitude, leads to a decrease of the amount of wool contact points with a water droplet resulting in a much hydrophobic fabric.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512464290">3</xref></sup> The relationship between the water contact angles measured and fibre roughness is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0040517512464290">Figure 8</xref>. Creating roughness on the hydrophobic substrate of micrometre dimensions can enhance hydrophobicity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0040517512464290">30</xref></sup> An increase in fibre roughness by the in situ method leads to an increase of the water contact angle, because the fatty layer was not altered and only its roughness was increased; at the same time, an increase of yarns amplitude <italic>S<sub>t</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0040517512464290">Table 3</xref>) seems to control the hydrophobic character of the fabric. On the other hand, in the use of the pad–dry–cure method, an increase of fibre roughness slightly reduces their hydrophobicity. However, when using the in situ method, the yarn amplitude seems to control the hydrophobic character.
<fig id="fig8-0040517512464290" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Correlation between water contact angle and wool fibre roughness <italic>R<sub>a</sub></italic> (a) and arithmetic mean surface roughness <italic>S<sub>a</sub></italic> and wool fibre roughness <italic>R<sub>a</sub></italic> (b) for different application method: (*) exhaustion method; (▪) pad–dry–cure method; and (□) in situ synthesis method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512464290-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The fabric loaded by the exhaustion method shows a completely different trend. The treatment increases surface smoothness and opens the spaces between yarns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0040517512464290">Figure 2</xref>) maintaining the yarn amplitudes almost unchanged. This effect leads to water spreading and penetrating into the fabric structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512464290">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0040517512464290" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Loading stabilized silver nanoparticles on wool surface using exhaustion method creates a surface which is more hydrophilic than the untreated one due to opening inter-yarn spaces despite to an increase of the fibres roughness. By concentrations equal or smaller than 1 [Lecithin]/[Ag], lecithin prevents agglomeration and penetration of nanoparticles into nanopores of the fibres. At larger lecithin concentrations, nanoparticles agglomerate and the fibre nano-roughness increases.</p>
<p>The wool samples loaded by the in situ method revealed the highest value for roughness and porosity and the smoothest fibre surfaces. Topographical changes on both length scales, nano and macro, compensate for each other, however, with a predominance of fabric roughness in controlling wetting. For this reason, a slight increase of hydrophobicity is observed.</p>
<p>The use of different methods to load silver nanoparticles revealed different effects on the contact angle. The sample loaded with silver nanoparticles using the pad–dry–cure method shows a smaller water contact angle on the wool fabric by covering the fatty surface layer with silver nanoparticles; the presence of lecithin enhances this effect. There is a stronger electrostatic interaction between stabilized silver nanoparticles with lecithin and wool fabric, due to their higher zeta potential. For the loaded sample, a reverse trend was observed by using in situ synthesis method. The water contact angle slightly increased due to silver nanoparticles loaded. Loading silver nanoparticles into the wool fibre structure cannot alter the fatty surface layer of wool fibres and only increases their roughness. This higher roughness leads to a more hydrophobic surface. Loading stabilized silver nanoparticles using the exhaustion method can alter the surface of wool fibres and create a more hydrophilic surface due to three combined effects: (i) smoothening of fibres by filling the gaps with silver nanoparticles; (ii) opening inter-yarn spaces; and (iii) decreasing or maintaining the yarn amplitudes. Lecithin prevent nanoparticles agglomeration and their penetration into the fibres nano-pores.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec11-0040517512464290"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research was supported by the University of Twente (Netherlands) and Leibniz Institute of Polymer Research Dresden (Germany).</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0040517512464290"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The science of clothing comfort</article-title>. <source>Textile Prog</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0040517512464290"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>MMB</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvimontes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Synytska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutschk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of topographic structure on wettability of differently woven fabrics</article-title>. <source>Textile Res J</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>996</fpage>–<lpage>1003</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0040517512464290"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvimontes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutschk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in topographic characterization of textile materials</article-title>. <source>Textile Res J</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1004</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0040517512464290"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jovančić</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jocić</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Erra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surface characterization of keratin fibres treated by water vapour plasma</article-title>. <source>Surf Interface Anal</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0040517512464290"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morent</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Geyter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Verschuren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Clerck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiekens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-thermal plasma treatment of textiles</article-title>. <source>Surf Coatings Technol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>202</volume>: <fpage>3427</fpage>–<lpage>3449</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0040517512464290"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dadashian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmatinejad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Farhoudi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of wool with laccase and dyeing with madder</article-title>. <source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>693</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0040517512464290"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malkov</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pulsed plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition of poly(allyl alcohol) onto natural fibers</article-title>. <source>Plasma Process Polym</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0040517512464290"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fabricating superhydrophilic wool fabrics</article-title>. <source>Langmuir</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>4675</fpage>–<lpage>4679</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0040517512464290"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ristić</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jovančić</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Canal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jocić</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of corona discharge and chitosan surface treatment on dyeing properties of wool</article-title>. <source>J Appl Polym Sci</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>2487</fpage>–<lpage>2496</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0040517512464290"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meade</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Covalent modification of the wool fiber surface: the attachment and durability of model surface treatments</article-title>. <source>Textile Res J</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1097</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0040517512464290"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakdel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghadam</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of nano colloid of TiO2 and butane tetra carboxylic acid on the alkali solubility and hydrophilicity of proteinous fibers</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf A Physicochem Eng Aspects</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>375</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0040517512464290"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dastjerdi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahsavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A novel technique for producing durable multifunctional textiles using nanocomposite coating</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0040517512464290"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toliyat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Samadi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Synthesis of Ag-liposome nano composites</article-title>. <source>J Liposome Res</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0040517512464290"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Application of anisotropic silver nanoparticles: Multifunctionalization of wool fabric</article-title>. <source>J Colloid Interface Sci</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>356</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0040517512464290"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierlot</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Absorption of nanoparticles by wool</article-title>. <source>Coloration Technol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0040517512464290"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Shishtawy</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Asiri</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdelwahed</surname><given-names>NAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Otaibi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In situ production of silver nanoparticle on cotton fabric and its antimicrobial evaluation</article-title>. <source>Cellulose</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0040517512464290"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In situ depositing silver nanoclusters on silk fibroin fibers supports by a novel biotemplate redox technique at room temperature</article-title>. <source>J Phys Chem B</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>17429</fpage>–<lpage>17434</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0040517512464290"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review on applications of liposomes in textile processing</article-title>. <source>J Liposome Res</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0040517512464290"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maleki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma and ultrasonic process in dyeing of wool fibers with madder in presence of lecithin</article-title>. <source>J Dispersion Sci Technol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1191</fpage>–<lpage>1199</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0040517512464290"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>ALF</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PJG</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>MECDR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>JINR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lipid interaction with textile fibres in dyeing conditions</article-title>. <source>Prog Colloid Polym Sci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0040517512464290"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Samadi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Toliyat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nano silver entrapped in phospholipids membrane: Synthesis, characteristics and antibacterial kinetics</article-title>. <source>Mol Membrane Biol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0040517512464290"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvimontes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Volumetrical characterization of sheet molding compounds</article-title>. <source>Materials</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>5083</fpage>–<lpage>5096</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0040517512464290"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surface roughness and contact angle</article-title>. <source>J Phys Colloid Chem</source> <year>1949</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1466</fpage>–<lpage>1467</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0040517512464290"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Stout KJ, Sullivan PJ, Dong WP, et al. The development of methods for the characterization of roughness on three dimensions. Publication number EUR 15178 EN, Commission of the European Communities, Luxembourg, 1994</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0040517512464290"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutschk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabbatovskiy</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudoy</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Unusual wetting dynamics of aqueous surfactant solutions on polymer surfaces</article-title>. <source>J Colloid Interface Sci</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0040517512464290"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Montazer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toliyat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Samadi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In situ synthesis of nano silver/lecithin on wool: Enhancing nanoparticles diffusion</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0040517512464290"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><comment>Carr CM. <italic>Chemistry of the Textiles Industry</italic>. New York: Springer-Verlag</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0040517512464290"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulijn</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surface characterization of chemically modified wool</article-title>. <source>Textile Res J</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0040517512464290"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wortmann</surname><given-names>F-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cuticle scale heights of wool and specialty fibers and their changes due to textile processing</article-title>. <source>Textile Res J</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0040517512464290"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jachowicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wis-Surel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between triboelectric charging and surface modification of human hair: polymeric versus monomeric long alkyl chanin quaternary ammonium salts</article-title>. <source>Textile Res J</source> <year>1987</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>