<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PLT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spplt</journal-id>
<journal-title>Planning Theory</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1473-0952</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3052</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1473095212451043</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1473095212451043</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Searching for the just city: Debates in urban theory and practice</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Storper</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1473095212451043">University of California, <italic>Los Angeles, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>215</fpage>
<lpage>219</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Marcuse</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novy</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olivo</surname><given-names>Ingrid</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>Cuz</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steil</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Searching for the just city: Debates in urban theory and practice</source>, <publisher-loc>Abingdon, UK and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>. <page-count count="283"/> pp.<price>GB£90.00/US$166</price> (hbk) ISBN <isbn>978-0-415-77613-4</isbn>; <price>GB£24.95/US$42.95</price> (pbk) ISBN <isbn>978-0-415-68761-4</isbn>; <price>GB£85.00</price> (e-book) ISBN <isbn>978-0-203-87883-5</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1473095212451043">Susan Fainstein (2010)</xref> has given a boost to reflections about the role of “justice” as a goal for urban planning, as a tool for evaluating urban policies and dynamics, and as a meta-norm that could be used for political mobilization and coalition-building. Fainstein’s approach is groundedly pragmatic: she defines a “Just City” as being concerned with achieving the right relationships between growth, distribution and equity, between process and outcome, and between universal principles and situated, context-sensitive action and goals. This book contains a set of very good papers, based on a conference, that explore Fainstein’s work, enlarge upon it, and critique it.</p>
<p>The papers take on the positive, normative, and political dimensions of justice and a Just City. They also explore in some detail the complex and often contradictory positions of planning and planners – as agents of the status quo, as hemmed in by bureaucracy, as oriented to small problems and unable to link to big processes, and all this in a profession largely populated by individuals who went into planning because they are basically interested in making better cities and better lives for people. And all this takes place in a world where processes unfold at scales other than the city – technological and labor market change, tax and welfare policy, globalization – but that visit their effects right on the desks of the planners. But planners are mostly deprived of tools with which meaningfully to affect the impacts of these forces on justice for people or places. This creates the risk that planners become low-level technocrats who at best do no harm or clean up a little bit of the mess, or at worst actually smooth the way for implementing policies that perpetuate injustices.</p>
<p>This is not a pretty picture, neither for our cities, nor for the profession. The papers in this book are too rich for me to summarize them one by one, so instead I will just try to evoke some of the rich debate they engage in and refer to author names in parentheses.</p>
<p>Some papers ask whether the Just City can be defined, as it has been by Fainstein, as a set of outcome standards, or whether, instead, the city is more of a field in which social processes that affect justice unfold. The outcome perspective is one in which we use process to do place-making; the process view is more one in which the city is an instrument of wider social and economic change itself (Harvey; Dikec). These are not necessarily opposed, but they’re very different.</p>
<p>On the issue of the role of planners and planning, a number of the papers inquire into the problem of scale. Cities are sites at which larger-scale processes unfold, so can cities be sites at which justice can be defined or attained? Planners are largely unable to change these big processes, so should the planner set herself up as a rebel, rather than a collaborator? A chapter on New Orleans claims that planners did harm there, both before Hurricane Katrina, and then in basically setting up further barriers to the victims seeking redress, or even comfort (Thompson). One major theme cutting into this depressing picture is that planners do, to at least some extent, control the discourse. They label processes and problems. So one thing they can do is add levels to the discourse, introducing judgments as to whether a policy or decision is consistent with wider normative principles, making those norms more transparent, engaging in social and political critique (Fischer). This means that planners themselves have to avoid becoming the mouthpieces of bureaucrat-speak, and this is a problem when one works in a bureaucracy and a risk-averse culture of avoiding responsibility.</p>
<p>Whether discourses are enough to do something about large-scale processes that generate injustice is open to question. Maybe the reconstruction of these discourses has, itself, to start upstream of the situations in which planners are expected to act; by the time we are down in the trenches, their actions and discourses are already too limited (Wolf Powers). So that means that planners have to do work upstream, in the universities, think-tanks, and political processes that define programs and policies and the language used to justify them. That, of course, means that academic planning schools have a potentially big role to play, and that they are largely failing at it, at the moment, if we are to judge by what goes on in the streets and the corridors of government and administration.</p>
<p>Fainstein, I think, would not say that academic planning schools are ignoring justice altogether, but that their approaches are too woolly and academic ever to make any difference down in the streets or in the corridors of bureaucracies. That’s why she insists on a pragmatic approach that gets rather specific about what a Just City is, as a set of outcomes. Others in this book prefer more abstract approaches, such as emphasizing the “right to the city”(Dikec, Wolf Powers). They think that this is a political rallying cry that mobilizes citizens to see just what it is that they are being denied: the right to urban interaction, the urban good life. This has the advantage of defining the city as a public good, rather than a collection of private properties and private interests; but it has the disadvantage of lacking any concrete criteria for defining what kind of public space and good it should be. It’s undeniable that in the past, cities have been the places of revolutionary uprisings (as well as pogroms, race riots, and such). The relationship of rights to the city and of urban space in general as inputs to justice-seeking behavior or political movements remain to be spelled out.</p>
<p>A number of papers take on Fainstein’s idea of a Just City: Amsterdam. They claim that it’s not as great as she feels it is. It has very nice public space and services, but it is caught up in the same spiral of tensions about divergence between private interests and public space, of downsizing of the welfare state, of inequality created in the economy and society that hits the streets of the cities and frustrates its residents, of the need to use urban space to satisfy the requirements of technological change and global capitalism (Novy and Mayer). The Dutch probably do better than the Americans, but it’s hardly a template, say some. Others in the book go further and dispute Fainstein’s argument that we have to seek a Just City within the general parameters of our economic system. For them, neoliberalism in particular, and market capitalism in general, are incompatible with justice in general or just cities in particular (Harvey). So we are back to the notion that the problem is less the city as “just”, as the use of the city as a political instrument to transform the system; the planner has to be a rebel or even a revolutionary (Steil and Connolly). And we are back to the question: what to do with professional planners, as opposed to street or academic militants?</p>
<p>Still other papers center on ideas of how to get around this contradiction, through logics of how the here-and-now of planning and urban politics can possibly contribute to building the movements for justice. Some argue that small-scale interventions in community mobilization can be part of broader counter-hegemonic strategies (Steil and Connolly). We have heard this since Paulo Freire and Saul Alinsky. We have certainly seen alternative power bases emerge at the urban scale in some cities, and these have indeed helped shape some positive outcomes that would not otherwise have existed. On the other hand, they have not sufficed to build anything like “counter-hegemony” in the face of wider political and economic forces. Is this enough?</p>
<p>Still others argue that planners have to be engaged in “changing the culture” entirely.Its values are not compatible with social and economic justice, they say; wedded to competition, aggression, masculinism, and materialism, the culture cannot be harnessed to justice; it must be changed (Marcuse). But what can planners do to change it? In part we are back to changing the discourses, to learning in small-scale situations, in trying to scale them up, in labeling our rights to the city and opposing such rights to the way the society defines rights, including many of the individual identity-based groups, who divide us and particularize interests instead of creating a general focus on cross-group, cross-place justice. These issues are raised in the excellent introductory chapter by Connolly and Steil and the insightful conclusion by Potter and Novy.</p>
<p>So, clearly the field is thinking and thinking creatively. This book succeeds pretty well at giving us the critique, or the state of things. This state of things is that (a) we are in a system that seriously goes against the grain of justice; and (b) planners have not figured out, for the most part, how to act as agents of justice; and (c) we are not yet in agreement about what a Just City would look like. That’s a pretty good, if somewhat depressing start.</p>
<p>At the same time, this set of excellent papers also makes me think that planning needs to engage better with social science in dealing with the justice question. There are three areas where this engagement needs to be deepened.</p>
<p>First, contemporary social science has an enormous body of theory and evidence on the “positive” aspects of efficiency, distribution, and politics. Spatial and urban economics, for example, has a big literature on the relationship between uneven spatial development and efficiency. Political science and sociology and economics have theories of interest groups, of social choice, of public choice, of distribution in relation to growth, of conflict, about how law and administrative rules affect group life and voice, about how urban economies work as distributive mechanisms, and much more. If urbanists and urban planners want to come up with theories of urban justice as a political process or as an outcome, there is a lot out there on which they could draw. If this book is any evidence, they aren’t especially conversant with most of this.</p>
<p>Second, contemporary philosophy has a lot of work on the normative issues. Susan Fainstein’s book has extensive discussion of Rawls, Nisbet, and others. In this book though, beyond some references to Rawls, I was surprised that there is no detailed working out of what a Rawlsian (or any other) system would actually mean for planning process or outcomes. Rawls suggests a rather simple rule (the maximin rule: we shouldn’t do anything that makes anyone worse off in absolute terms, and that if there’s an efficiency surplus from more inequality, it can be used to compensate losers). Why hasn’t anyone translated this into working rules and practices for practicing planners on the ground, as they evaluate projects or regulations, or as they facilitate interactions between groups?</p>
<p>Third, modern social science has a lot to say about group process (inter-group cooperation, rather than large-scale political cooperation/conflict, to which we refer above).This book makes a convincing case that communicative or facilitative planning is a failure when it comes to promoting justice. This is because it places the planner in the role of being neutral with respect to outcomes; essentially a content-less bureaucrat, where everyone’s claims are equal. Or, if the communicative planner is on the side of justice, s/he basically has to fake it when it comes to groups that are interested in just getting theirs, whether these be elite groups out to increase their take, or NIMBY-style communities out to protect their land values. Planners need to drop this goody-two-shoes stuff about facilitating process and re-engage themselves in getting the process to deliver up good substantive decisions and resource allocations. A couple of the papers in this book emphasize changing the language we use to label things correctly (Fischer, Wolf Peters). This is a good start to what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1473095212451043">Amartya Sen (2009)</xref> would call a “messy social choice process.” The planner has to help reveal what the stakes are in decisions, what their distributive and justice effects are. S/he has to facilitate dialogue, but it can’t be “anything goes.” There is a material reality and there are facts. But the planner needs a sophisticated understanding of these things in order to play the role of helping the powerless and the powerful to see what is on the table. Hopefully, the planner can also use techniques to bring those whose interests lie on the side of injustice, around to cooperating, or at least compromising, in the direction of justice. Or, failing that, to help the victims to tell the powerful that they listened to them but didn’t buy what they had to say, and that if they want political cooperation, they will need to do better, or face conflict.</p>
<p>Every area of urban analysis and practice needs to engage with normative or justice issues. This starts with those who study substance and generate the doctrines that run the society – urban and land economists, housing economists, spatial economists, infrastructure economists, public goods economists. The second fundamental theorem of welfare economics – mostly ignored by them – tells us that aggregate welfare outcomes shift in the face of different distributions. It continues to practicing professionals: lawyers, developers, planners, architects. They should be trained to understand issues of justice and distribution and they should be held to a higher standard of literacy about these issues.Citizens’ groups and politicians, too, need to have their knowledge and language upgraded and changed to reflect justice concerns, not in a woolly and romantic way, but with much greater rigor and logic, and planners should be there to help them do this. We have a lot to do as a field.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1473095212451043">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fainstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The Just City</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1473095212451043">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Idea of Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard/Belknap</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>