<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SPA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spspa</journal-id>
<journal-title>State Politics &amp; Policy Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1532-4400</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1946-1607</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1532440013484478</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1532440013484478</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Measuring State House Speakers’ Formal Powers, 1981–2010</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>Christopher Z.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1532440013484478">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1532440013484478"><label>1</label>University of Illinois, Springfield, IL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1532440013484478">Christopher Z. Mooney, Institute of Government and Public Affairs, One University Plaza, PAC 451, University of Illinois, Springfield, IL 62703-5407, USA. Email: <email>cmoon1@uis.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>262</fpage>
<lpage>273</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">State Politics and Policy Organized Section of the American Political Science Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The cross-sectional variation among state legislative leaders’ formal powers provides a unique opportunity to test a variety of hypotheses of the American legislative process that involve the causes and effects of these powers. But to date, measures of these powers have been developed primarily for single years or biennia, limiting their applicability, especially for drawing causal conclusions. In this note, I develop an index of state House speakers’ formal powers for each biennia from 1981 to 2010 (for even-year-election states) and from 1982 to 2009 (for odd-year-election states).</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>parties in legislatures</kwd>
<kwd>parties and interest groups</kwd>
<kwd>legislative politics</kwd>
<kwd>measurement</kwd>
<kwd>legislative leadership</kwd>
<kwd>legislative behavior</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The concept of majority party leadership power is at the center of a range of theories about lawmaking in the United States. Most prominently, a variety of arguments have been developed to explain why these leaders are sometimes strong and sometimes weak. For example, Conditional Party Government theory holds that legislative leaders are strongest when their respective caucuses are internally homogeneous and ideologically distinct from their rival caucuses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1532440013484478">Aldrich and Rohde 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1532440013484478">Cox and McCubbins 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1532440013484478">Rohde 1991</xref>). Even more general lines of thought about political behavior, such as collective action theory, new institutionalism, and principal-agent theory, have been tested using legislative leadership power as a dependent variable. In addition, leadership power has frequently been used as an independent variable to explain other legislative phenomena, such as committee system structure and power, roll call voting, and even general policy outputs (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1532440013484478">Ansolabehere, Snyder, and Stewart 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1532440013484478">Binder 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1532440013484478">Evans 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1532440013484478">Lazarus and Monroe 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1532440013484478">Monroe and Robinson 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1532440013484478">Owens 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1532440013484478">Rohde 1991</xref>).</p>
<p>These theories and hypotheses have typically been developed in the context of behavior in a single legislative body—the U.S. Congress. But robust empirical tests of these are difficult to conduct in that body because of the limited variation in congressional leadership power. At any given time, there is only one speaker of the U.S. House and only one majority party leader in the U.S. Senate. Even over time, these positions and individuals display restricted variation in their powers.</p>
<p>For over a decade, scholars have been dealing with this problem by using the variation in state legislative leadership power to contribute to this literature. In his seminal 2001 article, Richard Clucas tested a principal-agent interpretation of legislative leadership power using an index of the formal powers of state House speakers in 1995. Clucas’s study led to a flurry of related work, assessing leadership power as both a dependent and an independent variable (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1532440013484478">Burden 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1532440013484478">Hedlund et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1532440013484478">S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1532440013484478">Overby, Kazee, and Prince 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1532440013484478">Richman 2010</xref>). Many of these studies have used either Clucas’s 1995 index, or some modification of it, to great effect.</p>
<p>But because these studies have almost exclusively used cross-sectional analyses, they have not taken advantage of the full variation in state legislative leadership powers. This cross-sectional approach has been taken because of understandable data collection limitations—with a single year’s measure of state speakers’ powers available, scholars have had to make do. But limiting ourselves to cross-sectional research designs seriously hampers our ability to test causal hypotheses, especially when the direction of causation is potentially ambiguous, as is often the case in the legislative process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1532440013484478">N. M. Miller and Hedlund 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>Scholars have long used documentary data to develop overtime indicators of institutional characteristics of state government. In this note, I develop such an indicator of the formal powers of state House speakers for 15 biennia (1981–82 to 2009–10) for states with even-year-legislative elections and for 14 biennia (1982–83 to 2008–09) for states with odd-year-legislative elections. This index is based on, and well correlated with, the cotemporal single-year indices developed by Clucas (for 1995) and S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty (for 2002), but it only uses indicators that are consistently available in <italic>The Book of the States</italic> (BOS; Council of State Governments [CSG], various years) in recent decades. This index is a reasonably valid and reliable indicator of speakers’ formal powers, and as such can be used to create better tests of their causes and effects.</p>
<sec id="section1-1532440013484478">
<title>Measuring State Speaker Power</title>
<p>While the concept of majority leader power is central to much legislative theory, precious little consideration has been given to the underlying concept. First, it is important to understand that what is under discussion here is not the sway a legislative leader has over the entire political system. This broader conception of legislative leadership power is influenced by many factors outside the purview of the relevant legislative theories in this literature, such as the formal and informal powers of the governor, and the strength of other actors in a polity, such as interest groups and major industries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1532440013484478">Hrebenar and Thomas 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1532440013484478">Jewell and Whicker 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1532440013484478">Klarner and Karch 2008</xref>). Theories about leadership power typically focus on the relationship between leaders and the led, and as such, leadership power within a given legislative chamber is the concept under consideration here.</p>
<p>In this context, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1532440013484478">Mooney (forthcoming)</xref> has recently differentiated between legislative leaders’ “influence” within their own chamber, that is, their ability to control the lawmaking process, and their “tools,” those formal powers with which their colleagues have endowed them. Of course, there is a hypothetical causal relationship between these dimensions of leadership power, but they are certainly not the same thing. And as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1532440013484478">Battista (2011)</xref> showed, their empirical correlation is actually quite weak. This begs the questions of which of these dimensions scholars care about and whether an indicator of one would be a valid surrogate for the other. The answers to these depend on the theoretical context of a study. While there are good reasons for exploring the causes and effects of actual influence, the causes and effects of the formal powers granted a leader by the led are at the heart of much legislative and general political theory, including Conditional Party Government theory, principal-agent theory, and collective action theory. Measuring leadership influence has been approached most often through the use of surveys of rank-and-file legislators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1532440013484478">Clucas 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1532440013484478">S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1532440013484478">Mooney, forthcoming</xref>). This approach severely limits the potential for overtime comparison with, at best, those few years when such surveys have been done (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1532440013484478">Carey et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1532440013484478">Carey, Niemi, and Powell 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1532440013484478">Francis 1985</xref>). Furthermore, these surveys may be noncomparable in question wording, sampling approach, or other important methodological details. Other approaches, such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1532440013484478">Battista and Richman’s (2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1532440013484478">2011</xref>) use of roll call voting and Project Vote Smart information or <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1532440013484478">Anzia and Cohn’s (2013)</xref> use of majority roll rates, are theoretically replicable over time, but the intensity of effort involved in doing so poses a practical impediment.</p>
<p>However, state legislative leaders’ formal powers, or “tools,” are institutional features of the legislative landscape, many of which are visible and well documented, typically residing in legislative rules or state statutes or constitutions, and as such can feasibly be assessed over time. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1532440013484478">Clucas (2001)</xref> was the first to develop a comprehensive index of state House speaker powers, using data mainly from 1995. The Clucas index is composed of subindices measuring a speaker’s powers to appoint committee chairs and chamber leaders; control over the number of, and assignments to, committees; control over bill referral and floor activities; limits on tenure; and control over staff and campaign resources. Thus, this index covered the range of dimensions of legislative leadership powers commonly discussed in the literature. Scholars have used it or its components successfully as both a dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1532440013484478">Richman 2010</xref>) and an independent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1532440013484478">Burden 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1532440013484478">Hedlund et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1532440013484478">S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1532440013484478">Overby, Kazee, and Prince 2004</xref>) variable, further demonstrating its criterion-related validity.</p>
<p>But the fact that the Clucas index only assesses speakers’ powers in a single year is a significant limitation, restricting studies using it to a cross-sectional design and limiting a researcher’s ability to draw causal conclusions. The key reason for the nonreplicability of the Clucas index in other years is its use of irregular surveys done by the National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL) for data on staff control and speaker tenure limits, along with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1532440013484478">Jewell and Whicker’s (1994)</xref> one-time assessment of speakers’ control over campaign resources. Indeed, even the NCSL’s periodic surveys of state House clerks and Senate secretaries inquire about different aspects of legislative rules in different years, and the responses are far from complete.</p>
<p>Of course, if the powers of a given state’s speaker do not change from year to year, or even if they just change slightly, an indicator of them developed in one year might be validly used in the analysis of data from other years. But the very theories of the legislative process that give rise to our original interest in leadership powers suggest otherwise. For example, Conditional Party Government theory holds that as legislative parties become more internally homogeneous and externally polarized, their leaders will be endowed with more powers by the rank and file (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1532440013484478">Aldrich and Rohde 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1532440013484478">Cox and McCubbins 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1532440013484478">Rohde 1991</xref>). Likewise, scholars have argued that legislative professionalism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1532440013484478">Clucas 2007</xref>), public policy problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1532440013484478">Richman 2010</xref>), and other nonconstant factors influence leaders’ powers. Each of these potential influences on leadership powers varies not only cross-sectionally among the states but also dramatically over time in a given state. Indeed, theories of the causes and effects of leadership powers in Congress would be moot if there was not some expectation and observation that those powers changed over time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1532440013484478">
<title>An Overtime Measure of State Speakers’ Formal Powers</title>
<p>To take full advantage of the variation in how state legislative chambers empower the leaders of their majority parties, we need a measure of these formal powers across space and time. I develop such a measure by modifying <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1532440013484478">Clucas’s (2001)</xref> index for state House speakers using only data gathered regularly by the CSG in the BOS. The five subindices in this index are: committee chair appointment power, committee assignment power, the percentage of other leaders appointed by the speaker, bill referral power, and control of professional staff for standing committees (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-1532440013484478">appendix</xref> for details). Each component of this index is a policy decision made explicitly by a state legislature in its rules, the state’s statutes or, in a few cases, its constitution. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1532440013484478">Table 1</xref> displays these data for the 45 state House speakers in states with even-year-legislative elections for 15 biennia (1981–82 to 2009–10), and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1532440013484478">Table 2</xref> displays these data for the 4<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1532440013484478">1</xref></sup> states holding their legislative elections in odd-numbered years for 14 biennia (1982–83 to 2008–09).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1532440013484478" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>State House Speakers’ Formal Powers Index, 1981–2010: States with Even-Numbered-Year Legislative Elections.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1532440013484478" xlink:href="10.1177_1532440013484478-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">States</th>
<th align="center">1981–82</th>
<th align="center">1983–84</th>
<th align="center">1985–86</th>
<th align="center">1987–88</th>
<th align="center">1989–90</th>
<th align="center">1991–92</th>
<th align="center">1993–94</th>
<th align="center">1995–96</th>
<th align="center">1997–98</th>
<th align="center">1999–2000</th>
<th align="center">2001–02</th>
<th align="center">2003–04</th>
<th align="center">2005–06</th>
<th align="center">2007–08</th>
<th align="center">2009–2010</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>AL</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AK</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AZ</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AR</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>1.92</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.95</td>
<td>1.95</td>
<td>1.95</td>
<td>1.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CA</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>2.11</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>1.64</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CO</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>3.03</td>
<td>3.03</td>
<td>3.34</td>
<td>3.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CT</td>
<td>2.81</td>
<td>2.79</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>2.88</td>
<td>2.95</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.20</td>
<td>3.31</td>
<td>3.31</td>
<td>3.36</td>
<td>3.14</td>
<td>3.14</td>
<td>1.14</td>
<td>1.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DE</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FL</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.15</td>
<td>3.20</td>
<td>3.20</td>
<td>3.13</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.46</td>
<td>3.46</td>
<td>3.46</td>
<td>3.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GA</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HI</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>1.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ID</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IL</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.17</td>
<td>3.24</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.97</td>
<td>2.97</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IN</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.33</td>
<td>3.33</td>
<td>3.33</td>
<td>3.56</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>3.40</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IA</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>KS</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>KY</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ME</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.70</td>
<td>2.70</td>
<td>2.70</td>
<td>2.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MD</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.32</td>
<td>3.32</td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>3.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MA</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.94</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>2.17</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>2.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MI</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MN</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.32</td>
<td>3.32</td>
<td>3.34</td>
<td>3.30</td>
<td>3.31</td>
<td>3.45</td>
<td>3.45</td>
<td>3.45</td>
<td>3.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MO</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>2.42</td>
<td>2.42</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MT</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NV</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NH</td>
<td>4.00</td>
<td>3.90</td>
<td>4.00</td>
<td>4.00</td>
<td>3.80</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>3.99</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>2.86</td>
<td>2.99</td>
<td>2.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NM</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NY</td>
<td>3.68</td>
<td>3.70</td>
<td>3.85</td>
<td>3.85</td>
<td>3.85</td>
<td>3.77</td>
<td>3.77</td>
<td>3.52</td>
<td>3.52</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.52</td>
<td>3.53</td>
<td>3.78</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>3.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NC</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ND</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OH</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>1.67</td>
<td>2.17</td>
<td>2.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OK</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.43</td>
<td>3.41</td>
<td>4.28</td>
<td>4.28</td>
<td>4.28</td>
<td>4.28</td>
<td>4.28</td>
<td>3.46</td>
<td>3.21</td>
<td>3.21</td>
<td>3.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OR</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PA</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RI</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td>3.35</td>
<td>3.35</td>
<td>3.10</td>
<td>3.10</td>
<td>3.10</td>
<td>3.10</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SC</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SD</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TN</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TX</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.33</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>3.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UT</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.13</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.92</td>
<td>2.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VT</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WA</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>3.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WV</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>3.57</td>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.18</td>
<td>3.43</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>3.83</td>
<td>3.83</td>
<td>3.83</td>
<td>3.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WI</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WY</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1532440013484478" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>State House Speakers’ Formal Powers Index, 1981–2010: States with Odd-Numbered-Year Legislative Elections.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1532440013484478" xlink:href="10.1177_1532440013484478-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">States</th>
<th align="center">1982–83</th>
<th align="center">1984–85</th>
<th align="center">1986–87</th>
<th align="center">1988–89</th>
<th align="center">1990–91</th>
<th align="center">1992–93</th>
<th align="center">1994–95</th>
<th align="center">1996–97</th>
<th align="center">1998–99</th>
<th align="center">2000–01</th>
<th align="center">2002–03</th>
<th align="center">2004–05</th>
<th align="center">2006–07</th>
<th align="center">2008–09</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>KY</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LA</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MS</td>
<td>4.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NJ</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>3.25</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>0.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VA</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>2.08</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>3.61</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1532440013484478">
<p>Note: This index is developed as discussed in the <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-1532440013484478">appendix</xref> with data drawn from <italic>The Book of the States</italic> (Council of State Governments, various years). Data on the underlying components of this index are available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spa.sagepub.com/">http://spa.sagepub.com/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Ideally, we would assess the validity of these data with some criterion-related comparison, but as is often the case for social science variables, there exists little in the way of a gold standard for House speaker formal powers. The closest that may come to this are the single-year indices developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1532440013484478">Clucas (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1532440013484478">S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty (2011)</xref>, both based on some BOS data along with other data from one-off sources, like the surveys done by the NCSL. The scores for even-year-election states for my index in 1995–96 correlate at .66 with Clucas’s index drawn mainly from 1995 data; the correlation between the S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty index with data mainly from 2000 and 2002 and my index is .64 for 1999–2000 and .71 for 2001–02. These are strong positive correlations, but not perfect ones. They may not be higher due to both the facts that these indices do not have precisely the same components and that certain components of the Clucas and S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty indices (i.e., the assessment of power over committees and control of staff) were drawn from the NCSL surveys, not from the BOS. Clucas also uses data gathered in years prior to 1995 to assess speaker control over campaign resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1532440013484478">Jewell and Whicker 1994</xref>), and S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty use some data published in 2010. Without a gold standard criterion to compare these indices to, it is impossible to know whether the imperfect correlation between them is due to bias or random error in any of them. However, in addition to their face validity, the fact that they are so well correlated indicates that they each tap robustly into the same underlying concept. And while Clucas and S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty may incorporate an additional dimension of speaker power or two, the fact that they collect these data from irregular sources severely limits their usefulness for overtime research.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1532440013484478">Table 1</xref> also shows that there is significant overtime variation in some speakers’ formal powers within the respective states. In short, some state Houses change their speakers’ formal powers from time to time. For example, the formal powers of the speaker of the California Assembly start the study period moderately strong, drop off sharply in the early- and mid-1990s (during the transition to term limits), but then increase again by the end of the period. The formal powers of the Connecticut speaker follow the opposite path. However, some speaker’s formal powers are remarkably consistent across the study period, such as those in Wisconsin and Vermont. Indeed, while this institutional characteristic is relatively stable, fully 28.9% of the observed transitions in a given state from one biennium to another in this data set show a change in this speaker power index. At the same time, the average score for the 49 state speakers changes very little over this period, suggesting little in the way of a national trend. Thus, these within-state, overtime changes justify both the use of this variable measured at the theoretically correct time relative to other variables in a given analysis and the exploration of the causes and effects of these changes over time.</p>
<p>As with any empirical indicator of a social science concept, this index has its limitations. First, it only assesses speakers’ formal “tools,” not their actual influence in their respective chambers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1532440013484478">Mooney, forthcoming</xref>). Regardless, given scholarly interest in the causes and effects of legislative institutions, this measure could still have wide applicability in the discipline. Second, as with any measure, it is only as good as the data that go into it. The BOS contains data gathered and aggregated by the CSG each year. The CSG is a respected nonpartisan trade association of state government officials of longstanding, and the BOS is its flagship publication. The BOS dates from the 1930s, but its current extensive level of data presentation dates only to 1980, which is why my index begins when it does. A vast number of scholarly and applied works have used data from the BOS, because it provides a convenient, consistent, 50-state source of data on a wide array of state government characteristics. However, this comprehensiveness undoubtedly leads to an unknown level of random error. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1532440013484478">Klarner (2003)</xref> identified a small but nonzero number of mistakes in BOS data on the partisan balance in state legislatures over many years. Likewise, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1532440013484478">Burns et al. (2008)</xref> found that very early editions of the BOS overestimated legislative turnover. Finally, at a conceptual level, my attention to components of House speakers’ formal powers that are consistently reported in the BOS means that the potential for bias in this index exists if those dimensions of speakers’ powers not included in it do not correlate with those that have been included. For example, speakers vary in their control over campaign spending, extra salary for committee chairs and other leadership positions, and the disposition of legislative offices, parking spaces, and other perquisites of the job. As these factors have not been consistently tracked over time, they are not included in this index.</p>
<p>Perhaps most worrisome, this focus on data reported consistently in the BOS results in my index containing no assessment of a speaker’s powers to control the flow of legislation on the floor of the House. While I do include half of the “procedural power index” used by Clucas and S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty (bill referral control), those scholars also include a partial subindex indicating whether the speaker prepares the calendar, decides questions, and/or directs the chamber on the floor. These data were gathered through irregular NCSL surveys; reliable biennial data are not readily available for them. Scholars particularly interested in this component of leadership powers could perhaps gather it from the legislative manuals of the 49 state Houses over the decades (assuming that these manuals are available and that they contain comparable information on these floor powers). This would be a great contribution to this line of work, but it was beyond the scope of this note. But realize also that these floor powers comprise only 10% of the total Clucas and S. M. Miller, Nicholson-Crotty, and Nicholson-Crotty indices.</p>
<p>In the end, these shortcomings are likely to affect the bias and reliability of this index no more severely than do problems with other state-level data used by scholars in the field. While there is certainly room for improvement here, the ability to track state House speakers’ formal powers over time and space makes the availability of these data a valuable practical contribution to scholarship on the legislative process.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1532440013484478">
<title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="section3-1532440013484478">
<title>House Speakers’ Formal Powers Index</title>
<p>The index of state House speakers’ formal powers discussed in this note and displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1532440013484478">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1532440013484478">2</xref> is the sum of five subindices, each with a score ranging from 0 to 1. All the data used to develop these subindices were taken from <italic>The Book of the States</italic> (BOS; Council of State Governments [CSG], various years), allowing for their replication across legislative sessions. These subindices were equally weighted and summed to create the index displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1532440013484478">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1532440013484478">2</xref>. The five subindices were calculated as follows, with the relevant table numbers in the 2010 BOS (for the 2009–10 biennium) in parentheses. For more detail on these procedures, see the online data set and codebook at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spa.sagepub.com">http://spa.sagepub.com</ext-link>/</p>
<list id="list1-1532440013484478" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Committee chair appointment (Table 3.23):<list id="list2-1532440013484478" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>speaker appoints committee chairs = 1</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker is involved with committee chair appointments, but not the sole authority = .5</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker has no committee chair appointment authority = 0</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Committee member assignment (Table 3.23):<list id="list3-1532440013484478" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>speaker makes committee assignments = 1</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker makes majority party committee assignments = .67</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker is involved with committee assignments, but not the sole authority = .33</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker has no committee assignment power = 0</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Chamber leadership appointment (Table 3.7):<list id="list4-1532440013484478" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>proportion of House leaders (not including the speaker) who are appointed by the speaker</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Bill referral (Table 3.14):<list id="list5-1532440013484478" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>speaker has complete control over bill referral = 1</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker controls referral, but with restrictions = .75</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker shares power over referral; no restrictions on referrals = .50</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker shares power over referral; restrictions on referrals = .25</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>speaker is not formally involved in bill referral = 0</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Control over legislative committee staff (Table 3.22):<list id="list6-1532440013484478" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>“caucus or leadership” is the only “source of professional [committee] staff services” = 1</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“caucus or leadership” plus one other agency/category are listed as a “source of professional [committee] staff services” = .75</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“caucus or leadership” plus two other agencies/categories are listed as a “source of professional [committee] staff services” = .50</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“caucus or leadership” plus three other agencies/categories are listed as a “source of professional [committee] staff services” = .25</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“caucus or leadership” is not listed as a “source of professional [committee] staff services” = 0</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack>
<p>In addition to their valuable published works, the development of this measure of House speakers’ formal powers has benefited from insightful comments from Richard Clucas, James Battista, and Jesse Richman. I also wish to thank Matthew Schaefer, Brian Bartoz, and Michael Snyder for their research assistance on this and related projects.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1532440013484478">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Prior to 1982, Kentucky also elected its legislators in odd-numbered years, but a constitutional change in 1979 led to those Kentucky House members being elected in 1981 serving three-year terms, with the next election being held in 1984, and in even-numbered years beginning in 1984 (see Kentucky Acts 1978, ch. 440, § 1).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Christopher Z. Mooney</bold> is the W. Russell Arrington Professor in State Politics at the University of Illinois, Springfield, and the Institute of Government and Public Affairs. His recent research interests include legislative decision making, legislative leadership, and morality policy making.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>John H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2000</year>. “<article-title>The Republican Revolution and the House Appropriations Committee</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Politics</source> <volume>62</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ansolabehere</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>James W.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names><suffix>III.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>The Effects of Party and Preferences on Congressional Roll Call Voting</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>26</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anzia</surname><given-names>Sarah F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>Molly J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2013</year>. “<article-title>Legislative Organization and the Second Face of Power: Evidence from the U.S. State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Politics</source> <volume>75</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Battista</surname><given-names>James Coleman</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>Formal and Perceived Leadership Power in U.S. State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>State Politics and Policy Quarterly</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Battista</surname><given-names>James Coleman</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>Jesse T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Votes, Preference Estimates, and Party Power: Measuring Party Pressure in the States.” Presented at the Annual Meetings of the American Political Science Association, Toronto</article-title>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Battista</surname><given-names>James Coleman</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>Jesse T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>Party Pressure in U.S. State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>Sarah A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Parties and Institutional Choice Revisited</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burden</surname><given-names>Barry C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Institutions and Policy Representation in the States</article-title>.” <source>State Politics and Politics Quarterly</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gamm</surname><given-names>Gerald</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McConnaughy</surname><given-names>Corrine</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Pockets of Expertise: Institutional Capacity in Twentieth-Century State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Studies in American Political Development</source> <volume>22</volume> (<season>Fall</season>): <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>John M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemi</surname><given-names>Richard G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>Lynda W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2000</year>. <source>Term Limits in the State Legislatures</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>John M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemi</surname><given-names>Richard G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>Lynda W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gary</surname><given-names>Moncrief</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. “<article-title>State Legislative Survey [Computer file]</article-title>.” ICPSR20960-v1. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research</publisher-name> [distributor], 2008-03-25.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clucas</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>Principal-Agent Theory and the Power of State House Speakers</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>26</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clucas</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>Legislative Professionalism and the Power of State House Leaders</article-title>.” <source>State Politics and Policy Quarterly</source> <volume>7</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clucas</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>The Contract with America and Conditional Party Government in State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Political Research Quarterly</source> <volume>62</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Council of State Governments. various years</collab>. <source>The Book of the States</source>. <publisher-loc>Lexington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CSG</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>Gary W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCubbins</surname><given-names>Mathew D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <source>Setting the Agenda: Responsible Party Government in the U.S. House of Representatives</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C. Lawrence</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. “<article-title>Legislative Structure: Rules, Precedents, and Jurisdictions</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>Wayne L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1985</year>. “<article-title>Leadership, Party Caucuses, and Committees in U.S. State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>Ronald D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martorano</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>Keith E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Partisan Stacking on Legislative Committees</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>34</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hrebenar</surname><given-names>Ronald J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Clive S.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <year>2004</year>. <source>Interest Group Politics in the Northeastern States</source>. <publisher-loc>State College</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penn State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>Malcolm E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whicker</surname><given-names>Marcia Lynn</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1994</year>. <source>Legislative Leadership in the American States</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klarner</surname><given-names>Carl E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2003</year>. “<article-title>The Measurement of the Partisan Balance of State Government</article-title>.” <source>State Politics and Policy Quarterly</source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klarner</surname><given-names>Carl E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Why Do Governors Issue Vetoes? The Impact of Individual and Institutional Influences</article-title>.” <source>Political Research Quarterly</source> <volume>61</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>574</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>Jeffrey</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>Nathan W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>The Speaker’s Discretion: Conference Committee Appointments in the 97th through 106th Congresses</article-title>.” <source>Political Research Quarterly</source> <volume>60</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Nancy Martorano</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>Ronald D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2012</year>. “<article-title>One Tough Nut: The Development of Legislative Structure and Procedure in the Constitution of the Buckeye State</article-title>.” <conf-name>Presented at the 12th Annual State Politics and Policy Conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Rice University, Houston, TX</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Susan M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicholson-Crotty</surname><given-names>Jill</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicholson-Crotty</surname><given-names>Sean</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>Reexamining the Institutional Effects of Term Limits in U.S. State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>Nathan W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>Gregory</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Do Restrictive Rules Produce Nonmedian Outcomes? A Theory with Evidence from the 101st-108th Congresses</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Politics</source> <volume>70</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal"><person-group>
<name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>Christopher Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> Forthcoming. “<article-title>Explaining Legislative Leadership Influence: Simple Collective Action or Conditional Explanations?</article-title>” <source>Political Research Quarterly</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Overby</surname><given-names>L. Marvin</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazee</surname><given-names>Thomas A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. “<article-title>Committee Outliers in State Legislatures</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>29(1)</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>John E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1997</year>. “<article-title>The Return of Party Government in the U.S. House of Representatives: Central Leadership-Committee Relations in the 104th Congress</article-title>.” <source>British Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>Jesse</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>The Logic of Legislative Leadership: Preferences, Challenges, and the Speaker’s Powers</article-title>.” <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>35</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1532440013484478">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1991</year>. <source>Parties and Leaders in the Postreform House</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>