<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Sch Nurs</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Journal of School Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1059-8405</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1546-8364</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059840511429003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1059840511429003</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Adolescent Obesity Prevention in Botswana</article-title>
<subtitle>Beliefs and Recommendations of School Personnel</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shaibu</surname>
<given-names>Sheila</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1059840511429003">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holsten</surname>
<given-names>Joanna E.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, MPH, RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1059840511429003">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stettler</surname>
<given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, MSCE</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1059840511429003">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maruapula</surname>
<given-names>Segametsi D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1059840511429003">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>Jose C.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1059840511429003">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Malete</surname>
<given-names>Leapetswe</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-1059840511429003">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mokone</surname>
<given-names>George</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-1059840511429003">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wrotniak</surname>
<given-names>Brian H.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-1059840511429003">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Compher</surname>
<given-names>Charlene W.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, RD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1059840511429003">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1059840511429003"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1059840511429003">
<label>1</label>School of Nursing, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1059840511429003">
<label>2</label>School of Nursing, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1059840511429003">
<label>3</label>The Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, the Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1059840511429003">
<label>4</label>Department of Family and Consumer Sciences, Home Economics, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana</aff>
<aff id="aff5-1059840511429003">
<label>5</label>Centre for Scientific Research, Indigenous Knowledge and Innovation (CesrIKi), University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana</aff>
<aff id="aff6-1059840511429003">
<label>6</label>International Education and Partnerships, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana</aff>
<aff id="aff7-1059840511429003">
<label>7</label>Center for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff8-1059840511429003">
<label>8</label>School of Medicine, University of Botswana</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1059840511429003">Charlene W. Compher, School of Nursing, University of Pennsylvania, Room 134 Fagin Hall, 418 Curie Blvd, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA Email: <email>compherc@nursing.upenn.edu</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Sheila Shaibu</bold>, PhD, RN, is a senior lecturer at the School of Nursing, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Joanna E. Holsten</bold>, PhD, MPH, RN, University of Pennsylvania.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Nicolas Stettler</bold>, MD, MSCE, is with the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, the Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, and Exponent, Engineering and Scientific Consulting.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Segametsi D. Maruapula</bold>, PhD is lecturer in the Department of Family and Consumer Sciences, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Jose C. Jackson</bold>, PhD, is a food scientist at the Centre for Scientific Research, Indigenous Knowledge and Innovation (CesrIKi), University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Leapetswe Malete</bold>, PhD, is a senior lecturer in sport psychology, and director of International Education and Partnerships, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>George Mokone</bold>, PhD, is a senior lecturer in exercise physiology at the School of Medicine, University of Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Brian H. Wrotniak</bold>, PhD, associate professor of epidemiology at D’youville college, Albany, New York and adjunct scholar at the Center for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of Pennsylvania.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1059840511429003">
<p>
<bold>Charlene W. Compher</bold>, PhD, RD, is an associate professor of Nutrition Science at the School of Nursing, University of Pennsylvania.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>229</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">National Association of School Nurses</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The study’s objectives were to gain school personnel’s (1) perceptions on diet, physical activity, body size, and obesity, (2) description of school food and physical activity practices, and (3) recommendations for programs to prevent adolescent obesity. The study took place in six junior secondary schools of varying socioeconomic status in Gaborone, Botswana. Using a qualitative descriptive design, semistructured interviews were conducted with key school personnel. Directed content analysis was used to summarize the findings. School personnel believed that obesity was an important problem. They felt that school food was unhealthy and that physical activity was provided insufficiently. Participants shared enthusiasm for a school-based health-promoting intervention that must be fun and include active engagement and education on healthy lifestyles for all students. Participants supported on-site food shop inventory changes and physical activity programs. Potential barriers listed were schools’ financial resources, interest of students, and time limitations of all involved.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>obesity</kwd>
<kwd>overweight</kwd>
<kwd>Botswana</kwd>
<kwd>school</kwd>
<kwd>intervention</kwd>
<kwd>qualitative</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1059840511429003">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Lower- and middle-income countries are experiencing community-wide shifts in diet and activity patterns, leading to rapid changes in body composition and health outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1059840511429003">Joubert et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511429003">Popkin, 2006</xref>). In countries with emerging economies, obesity and overweight coexist with undernutrition. Therefore, in addition to infectious diseases caused by undernutrition, these populations are now struggling with chronic disorders, like diabetes and heart disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511429003">Popkin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1059840511429003">Satia, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1059840511429003">Sibai et al., 2010</xref>). Childhood overweight and obesity are emerging as critical public health issues in African countries undergoing increased social and economic transformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1059840511429003">Baalwa, Byarugaba, Kabagambe, &amp; Otim, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1059840511429003">Onywera, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Botswana is an upper-middle-income country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1059840511429003">World Bank, 2011</xref>) with rapid economic growth, which makes the transition from undernutrition and infectious diseases to overnutrition and chronic diseases a pressing public health challenge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1059840511429003">Joubert et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511429003">Popkin, 2006</xref>). Botswana’s nutrition transition is characterized by a change from a healthier traditional diet consisting of sorghum, samp (chopped dehulled dried maize/corn kernels), maize, beans, groundnuts, green leaves, and meat to westernized foods such as rice, bread, savory snacks, sweet beverages, and candies. The changing lifestyle also requires less physical activity due to increased vehicle transportation and decreased manual labor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1059840511429003">Maruapula et al., 2011</xref>), a pattern typical of Southern Africans in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1059840511429003">Walker, Adam, &amp; Walker, 2001</xref>). Consequently, there are cases of both adult obesity (15% women and 3% men), overweight (23% women and 13%men), and undernutrition (19% women and 12% men) in Botswana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1059840511429003">Letamo, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>In our previous study of adolescent secondary school students in Botswana (<italic>n</italic> = 780), 16% of adolescents were overweight/obese, but still 5% were underweight, with greater prevalence of overweight/obesity in adolescents from higher socioeconomic status (SES) and cities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1059840511429003">Wrotniak et al., 2009</xref>). These findings stress the importance of obesity prevention for youth in urban centers and the need for a prevention strategy as more rural areas undergo urbanization in the near future.</p>
<p>Schools offer an enabling environment and established infrastructure to reach youth in Botswana. Interventions that use existing social structure of communities, such as schools, can reduce the barriers to implementation of obesity prevention interventions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1059840511429003">Anderson et al., 2009</xref>). Since school infrastructure, physical environments, food policies, curricula, and staffing can positively or negatively influence children’s health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1059840511429003">Brown &amp; Summerbell, 2009</xref>), an integrative and collaborative approach for effective programming to address overweight/obesity is essential. According to the World Health Organization, the most effective programs in school settings include a focus on diet and/or physical activity with components that included curricular content, supportive administrative environments, physical activity programs, parental involvement, and healthy foods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1059840511429003">Anderson et al., 2009</xref>). While similar interventions may be helpful in urban centers of Botswana, the literature currently available is based on non-African nations and the results may not be generalizable to African countries in transition like Botswana.</p>
<p>Understanding the beliefs of key stakeholders within their sociocultural context is critical in designing and implementing any intervention. In order to develop culturally tailored school-based interventions in Botswana, a qualitative investigation of beliefs and barriers to change around the issue of adolescent obesity is needed. Focusing on the school setting, the key stakeholders for an obesity prevention intervention include students, parents, and school personnel. Although, preference for larger bodies has been reported in some African countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1059840511429003">Beune, Haafkens, Agyemang, &amp; Bindels, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1059840511429003">Walker et al., 2001</xref>), sociocultural factors that underpin obesity among adolescents in Botswana have not been explored.</p>
<p>An inductive qualitative exploration of student, parent, and school personnel’s views on overweight/obesity, dietary habits, physical activity, and body image was conducted. This article focuses on the beliefs and recommendations of school personnel. Three objectives of this qualitative study were to elicit from key stakeholders: (1) perceptions and attitudes on diet, physical activity, body size, and obesity, (2) information about school food and physical activity practices, and (3) recommendations for program components that could prevent obesity among adolescents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1059840511429003">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-1059840511429003">
<title>Design</title>
<p>A qualitative descriptive study design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1059840511429003">Sandelowski, 2000</xref>) was used to explore student, parent, and key school personnel perceptions of health beliefs and barriers to behavioral change that could help to design a school-based intervention to prevent adolescent obesity. Semistructured interviews were conducted with school administrators, physical education (PE) teachers, and on-site food shop managers. This study is situated within a larger research program aiming to assess and improve adolescent obesity in Botswana. The Botswana Ministry of Education and the University of Pennsylvania Institutional Review Board approved the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1059840511429003">
<title>Setting and Participants</title>
<p>The study took place in school settings across Gaborone, the most urbanized and capital city of Botswana. Gaborone was selected based on our research team’s earlier prevalence findings, which demonstrated highest rates of obesity in schools within urban centers and higher socioeconomic circumstances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1059840511429003">Wrotniak et al., 2009</xref>). Six secondary schools were purposefully sampled to represent a variation in socioeconomic levels: 2 high-fee private schools, 2 moderate-fee private schools, and 2 government (public/no fee) schools. All the schools represented potential sites for an obesity prevention intervention. Within each school, administrators arranged the opportunity for study staff to interview one of each type of key informant: school administrators, PE teachers, and tuckshop (on-site food vendors) managers. These informants were selected because they represent key stakeholders in a potential obesity prevention intervention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1059840511429003">
<title>Interview Guides</title>
<p>Semistructured interview guides were used to assess the perceptions of diet, physical activity, body size, and obesity. The guides included questions about the design of a potential obesity prevention intervention. School administrators were asked how key stakeholders perceive obesity and the overall feasibility of a multicomponent obesity prevention intervention. PE teachers were asked about current and potential physical activity components during the students’ day. Tuckshop managers were asked questions regarding food sales including cost and popularity of food products. Each guide included 11 to 15 main questions followed by probing questions to obtain more detailed responses. In order to discuss body size, participants were shown female and male silhouettes of different body sizes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1059840511429003">Williamson, Greenway, White, &amp; Whisenhunt, 2007</xref>) during the interview (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1059840511429003">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059840511429003">2</xref>

). The questions were based on current overweight/obesity literature and a guide previously used to explore the nutrition transition in Cameroon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1059840511429003">Holsten, Morssink, &amp; Compher, 2011</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1059840511429003" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Body size silhouettes from body image assessment tool (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1059840511429003">Williamson, Greenway, White, &amp; Whisenhunt, 2007</xref>) used to assess perceptions of body size in the interviews.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig1-1059840511429003" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511429003-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-1059840511429003" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Male body size silhouettes from body image assessment tool (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1059840511429003">Williamson, Greenway, White, &amp; Whisenhunt, 2007</xref>) used to assess perceptions of body size in the interviews.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig2-1059840511429003" xlink:href="10.1177_1059840511429003-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1059840511429003">
<title>Data Collection</title>
<p>A total of 18 subjects participated in separate semistructured interviews conducted from June to November 2009. School administrators approached each contributor separately about study participation. Written informed consent took place at the beginning of each interview. Trained researchers (S.S. and J.E.H.) and a research assistant conducted the interviews in English or Setswana, as preferred by the participants. The interviews followed the interview guides, were voice recorded, and transcribed verbatim. All interviews were conducted predominantly in English except for one, which was done completely in Setswana, transcribed in Setswana, and translated into English before analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1059840511429003">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>A qualitative-directed content analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1059840511429003">Graneheim &amp; Lundman, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1059840511429003">Hsiech &amp; Shannon, 2005</xref>) provided a complete summary of the informational content of the interviews. Interviews were read through several times to gain a sense of the whole and then summarized to determine perceptions of diet, physical activity, obesity, body size, and recommendations for school-based obesity prevention programs. The data were represented in a straight descriptive summary of the informational content. Differences between schools of varying income levels were assessed through constant comparison of responses within each group of informants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1059840511429003">Strauss &amp; Corbin, 1998</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1059840511429003">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>The participants’ beliefs about overweight/obesity, school food availability, and physical activity opportunities at the schools will be discussed to provide a context of these major issues in the school setting. The second section reports the participants’ suggestions regarding the formation of school-based programs that could potentially prevent and/or reduce adolescent obesity.</p>
<sec id="section9-1059840511429003">
<title>Obesity and Overweight</title>
<sec id="section10-1059840511429003">
<title>Importance</title>
<p>Personnel from all schools agreed that obesity was considered an important issue and many participants highlighted the related health consequences. However, most participants stated that obesity was not an issue in their schools or that they only had a few cases. In response to the body silhouettes, almost every administrator, PE teacher, and tuckshop manager said that Image 1 was thin, sickly, or starving, Image 2, 3, or 4 were the best body sizes, and Images 6–10 were unhealthy for an adolescent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1059840511429003">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1059840511429003">2</xref>). Two participants expressed different opinions: one administrator perceived Image 1 was ideal for an adolescent, and one tuckshop manager perceived Silhouette 5 was an acceptable body size for a male adolescent. In reflecting on the silhouettes, one administrator also shared her perspective that body size does not matter as long as adolescents remain active, healthy, and feel good about themselves.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1059840511429003">
<title>Social stigma</title>
<p>When asked how others viewed obese students, four out of six administrators and all PE teachers expressed strong concern about the students’ negative treatment of each other with regard to obesity. School personnel observed empathically that obese youth encounter ridicule and marginalization from their classmates, with girls experiencing more embarrassment or injured self-esteem than boys. In reference to obese youth, one administrator stated, <italic>“I think they struggle for recognition and friendship. I think they get sympathy, but I don’t think they become part of the … accepted.”</italic> A PE teacher described how students “<italic>always tease the obese students calling them names and stuff.”</italic> One PE teacher shares how bigger students feel uncomfortable, <italic>“most of them with bigger bodies … don’t feel comfortable undressing and getting into the swimming pool …. So it does a lot of damage to their self esteem.”</italic>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1059840511429003">
<title>Socio-cultural factors associated with obesity</title>
<p>School administrators reflected on many sociocultural factors that promote obesity in Botswana and therefore influence their students. These factors included a general lack of understanding about the importance of physical activity, the belief that you have to eat a lot of food to have strength and power, and the lack of financial resources among many poorer families for purchasing healthier foods, such as fruits and vegetables. Several participants described the cultural perceptions that extra body weight suggests affluence and/or the absence of HIV infection. An administrator stated, “<italic>it’s culturally accepted here to be overweight because it is associated with affluence, so I would say there is far less … judgment of overweight.”</italic> One administrator also reflected on moving from scarcity to abundance affecting students’ perception of food availability. She noted, “<italic>people will take a huge plate and then not finish it …. The culture is fill your plate and eat what you can, rather than take a small portion, and … go for seconds.”</italic>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1059840511429003">
<title>Parental challenges</title>
<p>Both administrators and PE teachers often commented about how parents contributed to overweight/obesity by denying or downplaying weight problems. One PE teacher described that <italic>“its very difficult for a parent to really notice that their children are overweight. We tend to … cover [overlook] that, you know obesity, and maybe feel it’s not a problem.”</italic> In addition, a few school personnel identified with the challenge of dealing with obesity being parents themselves. A PE teacher stated, <italic>“When we see that our children are growing very big, very few of us will try to control that because we are the ones that feed our children. We are the ones that give them the type of lifestyle.”</italic> Since many school personnel attributed the problem largely to the parents’ influence, there was a tendency, especially among the administrators, to minimize the school’s responsibility. Further, some school personnel observed that parents with higher incomes often provide their children with more daily access to unhealthy fast foods. An administrator noted, <italic>“the more income people have … the more they tend to eat the rubbish … how many pizza deliveries, things parents send for their children … and Kentucky chicken.”</italic>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1059840511429003">
<title>School Food Availability</title>
<p>Overall, food was available from cafeterias and tuckshops. While every school had a tuckshop, only three schools (two public and one high-fee private) served meals, so students brought lunch from home or ate tuckshop food. In making food availability decisions, many schools described committees composed of school staff and sometimes parents and students. These committees considered students’ preferences, food affordability, and to a more limited degree the nutritional value of meals.</p>
<sec id="section17-1059840511429003">
<title>School food provision</title>
<p>Three schools (two public and one high-fee private) provided mid-morning “tea” and lunch. “Tea” included tea and bread (public schools) or sandwiches (private school). One administrator noted that the amount of sugar put in tea was concerning. Another administrator explained that soft drinks were substituted for tea in the summer time. For lunch, schools provided chicken and rice and more traditional foods, such as samp and beans. The private school had a salad bar option, but public schools had more limited fruit and vegetable availability. A public school administrator noted with regret only offering fruits once a month due to budget limitations: <italic>“There are times when we give our students a fruit, but it’s not like every day. Yes, it may be once in a month.”</italic>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1059840511429003">
<title>Tuckshops</title>
<p>All of the schools have a tuckshop (food shop) on the school premises where students purchase food for main meals, supplements to school lunches, or additional snacks. The school’s Parent–Teacher Association (PTA) manages tuckshops in public schools, and outside vendors managed the shops in private schools. The profits from the shops raised money for school programs, such as the student council. In the government schools profits go to the school, but in one instance the school had hired someone to run the tuckshop, and therefore, had to pay a salary to the hired employee. If teachers run the tuckshop, all profits go the school. In the private schools, tuckshops were rented to tuckshop managers by the school. The schools owned the tuckshop and there was profit sharing between the school and the managers.</p>
<p>The most common foods available were fried meat and cheese pies, potato chips, hot dogs, candy, biscuits, fizzy drinks (soft drinks), and sweet juices. Fried pies cost between 6.00 and 7.50 Botswana Pula ([BWP]; 7 BWP = 1 USD). Drinks typically cost 5.50–6.00 BWP. Other snack foods such as chips and cookies cost 1.00–6.00 BWP. Small single candies could be purchased for 0.10–0.20 Thebe (100 Thebe =1 BWP). Tuckshops at high-fee private schools provided salads and sandwiches. One of the high-fee private schools had recently switched to a healthier inventory, eliminating soft drinks and fried savory pie and providing options like sandwiches, flavored water, and juices. This tuckshop also provided hot meals at about 20.00 BWP. The school did not serve meals if they were not previously ordered by the students. According to the tuckshop manager, the students made a fuss about the transition initially, but they finally accepted the changes. Another high-fee private school tuckshop manager shared that she priced healthy foods like sandwiches (6.50 BWP) lower than less healthy foods like fried savory pie (7.50 BWP) and took a loss on her profits to encourage children to choose healthier items.</p>
<p>Schools that offered fried savory pie listed it as the most popular item purchased by students. Most inventories were based on students’ purchasing habits and came either from wholesalers or directly from the manufacturers, including fried savory pie companies. If schools had difficulties with transportation, the fried savory pie companies offered to deliver the pies directly to the shop. Other popular purchases included drinks, chips, and sweet snacks. Staff at the public schools noted that students did not like the school’s food and often purchased from the tuckshop instead.</p>
<p>Most of the school administrators and the tuckshop managers themselves agreed that students are receiving unhealthy foods from the tuckshops. Participants noted that food from the tuckshop is often preferred over school meals: <italic>“For instance, today they have prepared beans at the kitchen. Most students in this school don’t like beans, hence most of them will come and buy from here [the tuckshop].”</italic> In addition, it was reported that purchasing food from the tuckshop was a social status symbol in one public school. A tuckshop manager described the link between tuckshop purchases and social status for the students: <italic>“they want other students to recognize that they do have money…when they buy at the tuckshop on Monday, having 100 BWP (and) the following day 100 BWP.”</italic>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1059840511429003">
<title>Physical Activity and Education</title>
<p>The schools offer many opportunities for physical activity. Administrators described several voluntary extracurricular activities including sports and clubs including netball, football, rugby, volleyball, softball, dance, running, basketball, swimming, tennis, and so on. Every school offered PE classes. All schools besides one public school require students to take some level of PE. PE was only optional for students in one public school as stated by the teacher, <italic>“You know they have a choice … they might choose home economics, some … choose physical education.”</italic> The time and frequency of PE classes varied ranging from 30 to 80 min 1–4 times per week. For all private schools, the time in PE class declined as the students entered higher grades, with some schools eliminating PE requirements entirely at the highest grades. Some schools required participation in sports rather than PE for older students. One moderate-fee private school PE teacher stated, “<italic>Ah! Physical education is not offered as a subject to the older students from form 3 to form 6 [sophomore to seniors].”</italic> Most teachers, five out of six defined PE holistically as involving both the mind and body to create health. One public school teacher described PE as <italic>“developing an individual mentally, physically, socially and even spiritually.”</italic> All PE teachers believed that PE played an important role in preventing obesity, but the amount of PE time was not sufficient, and nutrition and health messages should be integrated into other classes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1059840511429003">
<title>Intervention Program Recommendations</title>
<p>All participants expressed active support, enthusiasm, and willingness to participate in the formation of school-based integrative programs to prevent overweight/obesity. Reflecting this positive interest and motivation, a number of common ideas emerged in their recommendations. Concerns rose about the affordability of healthy foods, transportation access for after school programs, and requirements for compulsory PE. These concerns varied by the SES of the school. Government schools raised most concerns due to their financial circumstances.</p>
<sec id="section23-1059840511429003">
<title>Education and engagement</title>
<p>School personnel discussed the need for both education and engagement in an intervention. All administrators stressed the need to educate students about the importance of a healthy lifestyle and/or the dangers of obesity. PE teachers and some administrators also strongly supported actively engaging adolescents in programs that interested the students. All administrators and PE teachers believed that successful interventions must be fun and stimulating. Such activities would include aerobic exercise, dance with contemporary music, and a wider range of both competitive and noncompetitive team sports, such as soccer, netball, tennis, badminton, swimming, basketball, and rugby. Participants suggested that celebrity athletes and motivational speakers be invited to support this positive framing of the program. An administrator captured these ideas by stating, “… <italic>ok, so the fun, the teamwork, the variety. The other things which I was looking to introduce are … contemporary, … like competitive dance, … street dance, the hip-hop … these physical activities which are not traditionally part of the school curriculum, but are gaining popularity worldwide and linking sport and music. I think (this) really captures children’s attention, so any form of vigorous dance.”</italic>
</p>
<p>In addition, half of the administrators spoke about how successful programs should promote a sense of community for the school as a whole, emphasizing achievement within a group context above that of the individual. One administrator described this communal spirit, “<italic>obviously the team sports, you know they [create] the sense of community. For me, its’ all about making things fun, making them (the students) enjoy it so that you realize that sport is much more than getting sweaty, it’s teamwork, its communication ….”</italic> The participants greatly opposed making the program mandatory. Half of the PE teachers and school administrators listed forcing students to participate as a strong disincentive for students.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1059840511429003">
<title>Avoid stigma in naming the intervention program</title>
<p>All administrators stressed the importance of minimizing the risk of stigmatization of overweight/obesity children by including <italic>all</italic> of the adolescents of the school, and not targeting overweight/obesity students. Administrators from both high-fee private schools strongly discouraged labeling the program “obesity” prevention and suggested framing the intervention more generally toward healthy lifestyles and using a positive spin. One administrator stated, <italic>“calling it obesity it’s going to put people off immediately.”</italic> In all areas of the programming, an emphasis would be placed upon healthy, active lifestyles, and good nutrition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-1059840511429003">
<title>Gender issues in an intervention program</title>
<p>In response to a direct question about including males and females in the same or separate activities, participants were divided. Four administrators and three PE teachers felt that instructional sessions and physical activities should be primarily coeducational, because as one teacher voiced<italic>, “they [the students] live in a world where they will never separate from each other.”</italic> Although several of the PE teachers felt that the adolescents should be separated by gender, either because of their religious customs (e.g., the presence of a number of Muslim children in the schools) and to respect the sensitivity they may have about their changing bodies, <italic>“at this time they are becoming aware of their own body, I think it’ll be much better to separate them.”</italic>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-1059840511429003">
<title>Parental involvement</title>
<p>School personnel stated that parents would be in favor of such programs, <italic>if</italic> parents were fully informed, the program was not too demanding of parental time or household budgets, and if geared toward “healthy lifestyles” rather than obesity, thereby avoiding possible stigmatization of their children. Two administrators suggested that some parents might even want to teach lessons about healthy lifestyles and/or participate with their children in sponsored walks or exercise.</p>
<p>Participants noted that parents would need to be effectively oriented to the program and educated about good nutrition through PTA meetings, letters, and other outreach. As a PE teacher suggested, it would be very important for good nutrition to be understood as a companion to exercise in talking with parents, <italic>“I think you’d have to start off with diet first. Very, very detailed discussion on diet because it’s no good doing a physical activity exercise and letting the child go home and eat chocolate cake, then you’re defeating the purpose.”</italic>
</p>
<p>Lastly, school administrators and PE teachers communicated that providing parents with a complete orientation to the program from the beginning would be necessary, especially if the parents were to approve of their children’s additional after school involvement. It would be important to show that the adolescent’s school performance is not adversely affected. Concerning logistics, school personnel reported that many parents would need to arrange for later pick up of the children or consent to alternate transportation arrangements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-1059840511429003">
<title>Intervention program logistics</title>
<p>All administrators and PE teachers indicated the importance of creating well-designed and enjoyable in-school or after school physical exercise programs to enhance nutritional and lifestyle information that would be interwoven into regular courses. The suggested amount of after school time and frequency varied (PE teachers 20–90 min, 1–4 times weekly vs. administrators 40–120 min, 1–5 times weekly). Most PE teachers and administrators recommend a student-to-staff ratio of 10–20 to 1 for programming.</p>
<p>Finding inspired leadership from the staff that would then engage other teachers was seen as an important challenge, especially since staff may not be paid extra for after school time. Nevertheless three of the six administrators felt confident that a number of additional teachers could be motivated to participate voluntarily after school if they are given supportive training for the program from experts and if they themselves enjoy recreational sports. Both in-school and after school teacher’s time were listed as important barriers to an intervention. As one administrator stated about instructors contributing time after school, <italic>“It will depend on how much time. If it’s a heavy burden of time then they can’t do it. If it costs extra money, I don’t think they can.”</italic> In addition, two administrators noted that teachers who struggle with overweight/obesity themselves may feel embarrassed and not want to participate.</p>
<p>Administrators, PE teachers, and tuckshop managers commented on the need for support and resources for staff training in order to implement an intervention. Administrators from the two government schools cited financial concerns for creating changes at the tuckshop and facilities for physical activity. One tuckshop manager asked for advice on healthier inventory alternatives and asked for more information. Most tuckshop managers cited the uncertainty of student’s purchases and the potential loss in profit as the greatest barriers to changing their inventory.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-1059840511429003">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The study helped describe the school personnel’s perceptions of overweight/obesity, diet and activity practices of schools, and recommendations for obesity prevention interventions. The findings illustrated that obesity was recognized as an important problem. Some participants placed a considerable degree of responsibility for overweight/obesity, perhaps defensively, upon the students’ parents. The influence of the Botswana culture was acknowledged as potentially contributing to some of the unhealthy lifestyles of adolescents, especially attitudes toward body size. While almost all participants, identified healthy body sizes as ideal for adolescents, school personnel also discussed cultural perceptions that larger bodies were associated with affluence and thin bodies were at times associated with having HIV/AIDS, as also reported in other research with participants in Moroccan and South African communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1059840511429003">Dapi, Omoloko, Janlert, Darlgren, &amp; Haglin, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1059840511429003">Puoane &amp; Hughes, 2005</xref>). In neighboring South Africa, overweight and obese body sizes were perceived as attractive, dignified, respected, and affluent by women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1059840511429003">Pouane, Fourie, Shapiro, Rosling, &amp; Tshaka, 2005</xref>) and respectable and strong by obese girls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1059840511429003">Puoane, Tsolekile, &amp; Steyn, 2010</xref>). Despite describing supportive cultural attitudes toward larger body sizes, many school personnel reported that obese students were teased and ridiculed by peers. Weight stigma by peers has been reported as a problem for obese youth in the United States, for children of all racial and ethnic backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1059840511429003">van den Berg, Neumark-Sztainer, Eisenberg, &amp; Haines, 2008</xref>). The reported social stigma of obese children reinforced the importance of sensitivity in obesity prevention efforts.</p>
<p>The current findings also revealed information about the school food, nutrition, and physical exercise practices. Unlike most schools in the United States, food provision was more variable with only three out of six schools providing a lunch meal outside a tuckshop. Most participants were aware that the foods provided to students at schools, particularly government schools, were unhealthy. The tuckshops <italic>on-site</italic> at these schools sell primarily fizzy drinks, sweets, cookies, fried savory pies, and potato chips. These types of shops in U.S. cities provide children with 357 kcal per day, an amount that can easily support weight gain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1059840511429003">Borradaile et al., 2009</xref>) by increasing energy intake while replacing nutrient-dense foods in the diet. For these reasons, changes in the food inventory of the tuckshops would be very important, notwithstanding the potential resistance that most of the participants anticipate from the adolescent customers and/or the shop managers themselves. It is encouraging that one school independently instituted healthy tuckshop changes <italic>and</italic> found that students adjusted well to the change. In addition, profits from these small businesses maintain the shop managers <italic>and</italic> support other programming in the school (e.g., student council activities). It is suggested elsewhere that school vendors should not be permitted to raise revenue for schools due to potential conflicts of interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1059840511429003">Foster et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1059840511429003">Temple, Steyn, Myburgh, &amp; Nel, 2006</xref>). It may be important to find other fundraising opportunities to replace tuckshop profits or to devise cost subsidies for more expensive healthy food items that will prevent loss of profit. In addition to food provision, PE practices were also variable between schools. Like schools in the UnitedStates, time for and requirements of PE decreased with age of students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1059840511429003">Johnston, Delva, &amp; O’Malley, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The findings also highlighted many recommendations for program components that could prevent obesity among adolescents. As the administrators and PE teachers in this study emphasized, the programs for reducing overweight/obesity would need to provide fun, informative, community-building opportunities for the adolescents. From an Afro-centric orientation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1059840511429003">Metz &amp; Gaie, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1059840511429003">Ndebele, Mfutso-Bengo, &amp; Masiye, 2008</xref>), administrators suggested that the programs should promote a sense of community and teamwork rather than western-style individual achievement and competition. The programs would be framed as enhancing healthy lifestyles, while avoiding stigmatization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1059840511429003">Draper et al., 2010</xref>). Obesity was not thought to be an issue within the participants’ specific schools, yet they were very supportive of an intervention. This is similar to responses of school administrators in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1059840511429003">Nollen et al., 2007</xref>). The participants of this qualitative study expressed an active interest and often enthusiasm for developing such programs in their schools. They articulated the belief that school-based interventions can succeed in Botswana and should be approached. They also noted that the assistance of experienced nutritionists and expert health educators and the inclusion of tuckshop managers, parents, and the student representatives would be essential.</p>
<p>While all schools reported potential challenges in carrying out an obesity prevention intervention, public schools highlighted additional obstacles related to resources. For instance, in public schools of this study, an administrator expressed regret that they could provide fruit to their students, sometimes only <italic>once</italic> a month. Personnel from public schools would also have to plan carefully for transportation for the youth who stayed for after school activities, in contrast to high- and moderate-fee schools, where pick up by a parent or driver could be anticipated. Lastly, while all of the participants in the study strongly agreed on the high value of PE for all adolescents, the students at one of the public schools were given an option to take either PE or home economics, many of them choosing the latter. Policy change to promote PE would require funding for additional resources for the purchase of equipment, athletic uniforms, and additional trained staff.</p>
<p>The Botswana current school health policy focuses on health assessment, environment, and health education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1059840511429003">Ministry of Health, 2006</xref>). Nurses are responsible for the implementation of the school health program. The role of the school health nurse is very important in health promotion related to obesity prevention in schools. However, given the shortage of school nurses in Botswana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1059840511429003">Shaibu &amp; Phaladze, 2010</xref>), the school nurse would have to mobilize other stakeholders who can assist with health education of both students and parents in line with the multisectoral approach to health that underpins primary health care in Botswana. The proposed new school health policy will also focus on nutrition education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1059840511429003">Ministry of Health, 2009</xref>), and with better staffing of the school health program would expand the current role of the nurses and allow them more time to be advocates for obesity prevention through the health education component of the school health policy.</p>
<sec id="section30-1059840511429003">
<title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
<p>Our study is the first to explore perceptions of overweight/obesity, dietary habits, physical activity, and body image in secondary schools, and to elicit recommendations for obesity prevention. The interviews were conducted in either English or Setswana to be inclusive of all potential participants and translated into English by a native speaker. While our qualitative descriptive study design only allows for low-abstraction in analysis, it is a highly recommended design for informing intervention development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1059840511429003">Sullivan-Bolyai, Bova, &amp; Harper, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Important voices, especially students, parents, and policy makers, were not described in these findings, representing a limitation. Student and parent perspectives were explored in focus groups and will be published separately. Government policy makers were not interviewed. In addition, the questions used for interview guides were gleaned from the recent overweight/obesity literature, and informed by our prior cross-sectional quantitative data on overweight/obesity prevalence and food intake and physical activity patterns; however, they may not be comprehensive for issues surrounding adolescents in Botswana. The inclusion of some open-ended questions provided opportunities for the participants to express related concerns not directly included in the questions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-1059840511429003">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The current data illustrate that key school personnel are aware of the unhealthy food environments in their schools and the importance of physical activity for adolescents. They also expressed their interest in participating in an intervention and shared suggestions for an intervention advising a fun, stimulating program including active engagement and education on healthy lifestyles for all students. Participants supported several components including tuckshop inventory changes and physical activity programs. Parental involvement was seen as important, but there is a need to find creative ways to address parents’ schedules and their potential lack of concern over overweight/obesity. Potential challenges include financial resources of schools, interest of students, and time limitations of all involved. The results of this study will be critical to develop culturally tailored school-based interventions in Botswana or other similar countries experiencing the important public health challenges of the nutrition transition. This is important, given the increase in adolescent obesity in some northern African countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1059840511429003">Blouza-Chabchoub, Rached-Amrouche, Jamoussi-Kammoun, &amp; Bouchaa, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1059840511429003">Salazar-Martinez et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1059840511429003">Sibai et al., 2010</xref>) eastern African countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1059840511429003">Baalwa et al., 2010</xref>), South Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1059840511429003">Joubert et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1059840511429003">Kruger, Kruger, &amp; MacIntryre, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1059840511429003">Reddy et al., 2008</xref>), and the projected increases in many other developing nations when the nutrition transition occurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1059840511429003">Popkin, 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn10-1059840511429003">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn11-1059840511429003">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research received funding from the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia’s Metabolism, Nutrition and Development Grant.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steyn</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grimsrud</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kolbe-Alexander</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mciza</surname>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Interventions on diet and physical activity: What works</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baalwa</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Byarugaba</surname>
<given-names>B. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kabagambe</surname>
<given-names>K. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Otim</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of overweight and obesity in young adults in Uganda</article-title>. <source>African Health Sciences</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beune</surname>
<given-names>E. J. A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haafkens</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Agyemang</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bindels</surname>
<given-names>E. J. P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Inhibitors and enablers of physical activity in multiethnic hypertensive patients: Qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Hypertension</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blouza-Chabchoub</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rached-Amrouche</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jamoussi-Kammoun</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bouchaa</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Frequency and risk factors of obesity in Tunisian adolescent</article-title>. <source>La Tunisie Medicale</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>714</fpage>–<lpage>716</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Borradaile</surname>
<given-names>K. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vander Veur</surname>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCoy</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandoval</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nachmani</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Snacking in children: The role of urban corner stores</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>124</volume>, <fpage>1293</fpage>–<lpage>1298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Summerbell</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Systematic review of school-based interventions that focus on changing dietary intake and physical activity levels to prevent childhood obesity: An update to the obesity guidance produced by the national institute for health and clinical excellence</article-title>. <source>Obesity Reviews</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dapi</surname>
<given-names>N. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Omoloko</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Janlert</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Darlgren</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haglin</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>“I eat to be happy, to be strong, and to live.”: Perceptions of rural and urban adolescents in Cameroon, Africa</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nutrition and Educational Behavior</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Draper</surname>
<given-names>C. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Kock</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grimsrub</surname>
<given-names>A.T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rudolph</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nemutandani</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alexamder</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>E.V.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of a school-based physical activity intervention in Alexandra Township</article-title>. <source>South African Journal of Sports Medicine</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Borradaile</surname>
<given-names>K. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grundy</surname>
<given-names>K. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vander Veur</surname>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nachmani</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shults</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A policy-based school intervention to prevent overweight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>e794</fpage>–<lpage>e802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Graneheim</surname>
<given-names>U. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lundman</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Qualitative content analysis in nursing research: Concepts, procedures and measures to achieve trustworthiness</article-title>. <source>Nurse Education Today</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holsten</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morssink</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Compher</surname>
<given-names>C. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Exploring the socio-ecological context of over-nutrition in rural Cameroon: A qualitative descriptive study</article-title>. <source>Manuscript submitted for publication</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hsiech</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shannon</surname>
<given-names>S. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Three approaches to qualitative content analysis</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1277</fpage>–<lpage>1288</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>L. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Delva</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Malley</surname>
<given-names>P. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Sports participation and physical education in American secondary schools: Current levels and Racial/Ethnic and socioeconomic disparities</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>S195</fpage>–<lpage>S208</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Joubert</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bradshaw</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boedecke</surname>
<given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steyn</surname>
<given-names>N. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Puoane</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <collab collab-type="author">The South African Comparative Risk Assessment Collaborating Group</collab>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Estimating the burden of disease attributable to excess body weight in South Africa in 2000</article-title>. <source>South African Medical Journal</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kruger</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kruger</surname>
<given-names>H. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacIntyre</surname>
<given-names>U. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The determinants of overweight and obesity among 10-to 15-year-old school children in the North West Province, South Africa—the THUSA BANA (Transition and Health during Urbanisation of South Africans; BANA, children) study</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutrition</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Letamo</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The prevalence of, and factors associated with overweight and obesity in Botswana</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biosocial Science</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lobstein</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baur</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uauy</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <collab collab-type="author">IASO International Obesity TaskForce</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Obesity in children and young people: A crisis in public health</article-title>. <source>Obesity Reviews</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maruapula</surname>
<given-names>S. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holsten</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shaibu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Malete</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wrotniak</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname> Compher</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Food patterns, socioeconomic status and urbanization are associated with obesity in adolescents in Botswana, an African country in rapid nutrition transition</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutrition</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Metz</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gaie</surname>
<given-names>J. B. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The African ethic of Ubuntu/Botho: Implications for research on morality</article-title>. <source>Journal of Moral Education</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Ministry of Health</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Botswana National Health School Health Policy and Procedure Manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Gaborone, Botswana</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government Printers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Ministry of Health</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>The National School Health Policy: Draft 6</source>. <publisher-loc>Gaborone, Botswana</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government Printers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ndebele</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mfutso-Bengo</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Masiye</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>HIV/AIDS reduces the relevance of the principle of individual medical confidentiality among the Bantu people of Southern Africa</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Medicine and Bioethics</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nollen</surname>
<given-names>N. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Befort</surname>
<given-names>C. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snow</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daley</surname>
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ellerbeck</surname>
<given-names>E. F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahluwalia</surname>
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The school food environment and adolescent obesity: Qualitative insights from high school principals and food service personnel</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Onywera</surname>
<given-names>V. O.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Childhood obesity and physical inactivity threat in Africa: Strategies for a healthy future</article-title>. <source>Global Health Promotion</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Popkin</surname>
<given-names>B. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Global nutrition dynamics: The world is shifting rapidly toward a diet linked with noncommunicable diseases</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pouane</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fourie</surname>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosling</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tshaka</surname>
<given-names>C. N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Big is beautiful—an exploration with urban black community health workers in a South African township</article-title>. <source>South African Journal of Clinical Nutrition</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puoane</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hughes</surname>
<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Impact of the HIV/AIDS pandemic on non-communicable disease prevention</article-title>. <source>South African Medical Journal = Suid-Afrikaanse Tydskrif Vir Geneeskunde</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>230</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puoane</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tsolekile</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steyn</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Perceptions about body image and sizes among black African girls living in Cape Town</article-title>. <source>Ethnicity &amp; Disease</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>S. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Resnicow</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>James</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kambaran</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Omardien</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mbewu</surname>
<given-names>A. D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Underweight, overweight and obesity among South African adolescents: Results of the 2002 National Youth Risk Behaviour Survey</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutrition</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Salazar-Martinez</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fernandez-Ortega</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torres-Mejia</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Galal</surname>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lazcano-Ponce</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Overweight and obesity status among adolescents from Mexico and Egypt</article-title>. <source>Archives of Medical Research</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sandelowski</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Whatever happened to qualitative description?</article-title>. <source>Research in Nursing &amp; Health; Research in Nursing &amp; Health</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Satia</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Dietary acculturation and the nutrition transition: An overview</article-title>. <source>Applied Physiology Nutrition and Metabolism</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shaibu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phaladze</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>School Health: The challenges to service delivery in Botswana</article-title>. <source>Primary Health Care Research and Development</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sibai</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nasreddine</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mokdad</surname>
<given-names>A. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adra</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tabet</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hwalla</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Nutrition transition and cardiovascular disease risk factors in Middle East and North Africa countries: Reviewing the evidence</article-title>. <source>Annals of Nutrition and Metabolism</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Strauss</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Corbin</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Basics of Qualitative Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sullivan-Bolyai</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bova</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harper</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Developing and refining interventions in persons with health disparities: The use of qualitative description</article-title>. <source>Nursing Outlook</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Temple</surname>
<given-names>N. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steyn</surname>
<given-names>N. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Myburgh</surname>
<given-names>N. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nel</surname>
<given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Food items consumed by students attending schools in different socioeconomic areas in Cape Town, South Africa</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van den Berg</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Neumark-Sztainer</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eisenberg</surname>
<given-names>M. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haines</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Racial/Ethnic differences in weight-related teasing in adolescents</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>S3</fpage>–<lpage>S10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>A. R. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adam</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>B. F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>World pandemic of obesity: The situation in Southern African populations</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source>, <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenway</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>White</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whisenhunt</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Food Craving Inventory</source>. <publisher-loc>Baton Rouge, LA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pennington Biomedical Research Center—LSU System</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">World Bank</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>How we Classify Countries</source>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://data.worldbank.org/about/country-classifications/">http://data.worldbank.org/about/country-classifications/</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1059840511429003">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wrotniak</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Malete</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Compher</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Malete</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stettler</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shaibu</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maruapula</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of obesity in adolescent students in Botswana, an African country in rapid nutrition transition</article-title>. <source>Obesity, 2009</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>S218</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>