<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VCU</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spvcu</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Visual Culture</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1470-4129</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2994</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1470412912444187m</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1470412912444187m</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Lesson One: Venus in the Light of Visual Culture</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Guins</surname><given-names>Raiford</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>Juliette</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pui San Lok</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>Louis</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1470412912444187">Department of Visual Studies University of Toronto [email: <email>louis.kaplan@utoronto.ca</email>]</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: The Ways of Seeing 40th Anniversary Issue</issue-title>
<fpage>166</fpage>
<lpage>169</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In the beginning was the cut. If we return to the primal scene of visual cultural studies, it begins with a virtual act of decapitation. Here we witness a playful brand of violence committed by John Berger against the goddess Venus. Turn on the television and you will see that the very first lesson that Berger teaches us is that the visual culture theorist must play the role of performance artist at times. This is the way that he makes his mark and sharpens his points. By invoking the space of performance, I am not just referring to his starring role as the suave TV host and critical commentator who is the direct object of the camera’s gaze and who guides the viewers through the four episodes of <italic>Ways of Seeing</italic> with his special blend of brilliant insights and riveting intensity. Rather I am referring to a particular and peculiar action that goes beyond the usual activities of the screen actor’s scripted recitation. Let us not forget the impressive bit of guerrilla theater that opens the program as Berger strikes the renegade pose of the vandal set loose in the temple of art. This silent museological move is telling and it functions as a type of institutional critique circa 1972. One notices that our teacher holds no chalk or laser pen in hand. Instead, the pedagogical device is a razor-sharp blade that descends on what looks to be a Renaissance masterpiece – Sandro Botticelli’s <italic>Venus and Mars</italic>.</p>
<p>Holy iconoclasm! The home audience witnesses what appears to be a criminal act of aggression against this most revered painting hanging in the British National Gallery and basking in its cult value. This cutting gesture hearkens back to Canadian suffragette Mary Richardson’s violent slashing of Velasquez’s <italic>Rokeby Venus</italic> in the National Gallery in 1914 as a feminist defacement of the mythological nude. It is also aligned to that typically avant-garde emphasis on shock value as the knife cuts out and removes a rectangular piece of canvas that composes the goddess’s head. Berger’s attack also acts out the anger often felt by the multitudes against the privileged defenders of the masterpiece and the aura of the original artwork. With this bold move, the Marxist theorist is already declaring class warfare on the elitist and moribund discipline of fine art history and its complicity with the bourgeois values of property, propriety, and identity. As the ripping and tearing of the canvas ripples in our ears, Berger states his mission: ‘This is the first of four programs in which I want to question some of the assumptions usually made about the tradition of European painting.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1470412912444187">1</xref></sup> What does this questioning of the assumptions of European painting entail from a visual cultural perspective? Acknowledging Walter Benjamin’s ‘Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470412912444187">1969 [1935]</xref>), Berger’s post-mortem autopsy of the painterly tradition sounds the death knell of art’s historical values of originality, uniqueness, and aura. Thus, the first program is aptly entitled ‘Art and Reproduction’.</p>
<p>But the art police never arrive at the scene to arrest Berger because our presumed vandal turns out to be a playful art prankster. (Ways of) seeing are not always (ways of) believing. This primal cut becomes his Brechtian way of enacting before the camera one of the elementary lessons derived from Benjamin. In other words, the punch line is that we are seeing the work of art as nothing other than a mechanical reproduction. It is a canvas copy of the original inhabiting a room that may very well be a television studio miming the museum. We are reminded again that the study of visual culture relies on denaturalization and estrangement as a major mode of pedagogy.</p>
<p>When the camera moves to show this same detail of the Botticelli image as one of many postcards in the process of being printed on large sheets of paper, then the lesson becomes even clearer. It underscores what Berger says about reproduction and this work in particular in <italic>Ways of Seeing</italic> (2008[1972]: 25):
<disp-quote>
<p>It is a question of reproduction making it possible, even inevitable, that an image will be used for many different purposes … Reproduction isolates a detail of a painting from the whole. The detail is transformed. An allegorical figure becomes a portrait of a girl.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>We witness the means of reproduction transforming the unique cult object into the mass dissemination of the reproducible and transmittable image, thereby converting fine art history into visual cultural studies. Berger’s choice of Venus is no accident when we recall how Benjamin invokes her in his own text as an expression of aura:
<disp-quote>
<p>An ancient statue of Venus, for example, stood in a different traditional context with the Greeks, who made it an object of veneration, than with the clerics of the Middle Ages who viewed it as an ominous idol. Both of them, however, were equally confronted with its uniqueness, that is, its aura. (p. 223)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Transfiguring an allegorical goddess into a girl’s portrait, Berger’s reframing may be viewed as another Marxist act of demystification. Or we can see it as enacting what Jean-Luc Nancy calls the interruption of myth in seeking to undo myth’s totalizing and totalitarian work. Either way, this cut welcomes the viewer to engage with the ‘multiverse’ of montage and to acknowledge a modern world constructed in and through fragments. Berger’s cut thereby already anticipates his later appropriation of a scene from Dziga Vertov’s <italic>Man with the Movie Camera</italic> that extols the ‘camera-eye’, mechanical reproduction, and montage as modern ways of seeing.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the story of Venus and Mars does not stop with Berger’s act of televisual guerrilla theater. For we learn that this painting was again in the news on account of a recent discovery. The masterpiece grows in stature through the detective work of an art historian and his iconographic sleuthing. On 27 May 2010, <italic>The Telegraph</italic> reported in its eye-catching headline: ‘Botticelli’s Venus and Mars are “high on drugs”’. For David Bellingham, program director at Sotheby’s Institute of Art, has uncovered ‘new evidence’ which he made ‘while carrying out a study of the depiction of Venus in art’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1470412912444187">Collins, 2010</xref>). This revisionist historical account allies ‘high art’ with ecstatic experience so that a new type of mystification enters the scene. It is no longer the Marxist depiction of religion as opiate of the masses. Instead, this mystification is derived from Botticelli’s Venus and Mars reclining under the influence of a drug’s hallucinatory effects. Rather than letting his subjects enjoy their spaced-out state of unworking, Bellingham is committed to verifying that Venus and Mars were in fact ‘druggies’. He labors to identify the plant as such and such a variety – <italic>Datura stramonium</italic>, ‘a plant which causes madness and the urge to take one’s clothes off’. As <italic>The Telegraph</italic> reports: ‘the horticulturalists at Kew Gardens identified the plant also known as thorn apple and Devil’s trumpet.’ In this way, horticultural experts are enlisted to support the original’s cult value. The denaturalizing demands that come with ‘ways of seeing’ and the legacy of Benjamin and Berger are nowhere in sight. There is no questioning of the assumptions of the tradition of European painting. Bellingham’s auratic reading has no interest in challenging the cult value of the work of art whether on display in the temple of art or on the art commodity auction block. In giving a new iconographic twist to Botticelli’s masterpiece, there is no acknowledgment of the age of mechanical or let alone digital reproduction. And while there may be a multiplication of the meaning of the image in this case, there is no consideration of how reproduction destroys its uniqueness.</p>
<p>This is yet another recuperative attempt to assert aura and restore the high in art at a moment marked by the conversion of everything into data and information or what can be transmitted and distributed instantly via digital media. Berger’s remarks are prescient at the point when Botticelli’s <italic>Venus and Mars</italic> enters <italic>Ways of Seeing</italic>:
<disp-quote>
<p>In the age of pictorial reproduction, the meaning of paintings is no longer attached to them; their meaning becomes transmittable: that is to say it becomes information of a sort, and like all information, it is either put to use or ignored; information carries no special authority within itself. (p. 24)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Benjamin’s exhibition value is remediated into Berger’s transmission value when confronted with broadcast television, and, subsequently, digital media and information systems. From this perspective, Bellingham’s iconographic account relies upon the privileging of certain information that has been propped up as high art when, to recite Berger, such information carries no special authority within itself. This is the wildly and radically democratic credo at the root of visual cultural studies that remains one of the pedagogical pillars and legacies derived from <italic>Ways of Seeing</italic>. The enactment of this credo against the auratic impulse demands an ongoing vigilance and it encourages the transmission and dissemination of Berger’s questioning and challenging lesson anew.</p>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1470412912444187">
<label>1.</label>
<p>John Berger, <italic>Ways of Seeing</italic>, Episode 1 can be viewed in its entirety on Ubu Web Film and Video. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ubu.com/film/berger_seeing1.html">http://www.ubu.com/film/berger_seeing1.html</ext-link> (consulted 29 December 2011).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1470412912444187">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969[1935]</year>) ‘<article-title>The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Arendt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Illuminations: Essays and Reflections</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Zohn</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, pp. <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Schocken Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1470412912444187">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) ‘<article-title>Botticelli’s Venus and Mars “high on drugs”</article-title>’, <source>The Telegraph</source>, <day>27</day> <month>May</month>. <comment>URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/art/art-news/7770099/Botticellis-Venus-and-Mars-high-on-drugs.html">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/art/art-news/7770099/Botticellis-Venus-and-Mars-high-on-drugs.html</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>consulted 29 December 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>