<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SEX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsex</journal-id>
<journal-title>Sexualities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1363-4607</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7382</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1363460712466013b</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1363460712466013b</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Chandan Reddy, <italic>Freedom with Violence: Race, Sexuality, and the US State,</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>Chandra</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1363460712466013b">University of California Santa Barbara, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Winant</surname><given-names>Howard</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1363460712466013b">University of California Santa Barbara, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>1020</fpage>
<lpage>1022</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1363460712466013b"><title>Chandan Reddy, <italic>Freedom with Violence: Race, Sexuality, and the US State,</italic> Duke University Press: Durham, NC, 2011; 303pp.: ISBN 13: 978 0822351054, $23.95</title><disp-quote>
<p>If you are a conservative, how could you be against a relationship in which people who love one another want to publicly state their vows … and engage in a household in which they are committed to one another and become part of the community and accepted like other people? (Ted Olson, attorney – with David Boies – opposing California's Proposition 8)</p></disp-quote>
<p>In this ambitious book, Reddy examines the coupling of freedom and violence under the modern state. He untangles literary texts, legal structures and social practices to argue that the state legitimizes further racial violence through granting freedom. Reddy finds hope in the ‘excesses’ of radical resistance that he suggests ‘haunt’ the edges of our epistemological and political formations and can be found through a queer of color critique.</p>
<p>Reddy ranges over racism and homophobia as they give shape to the modern state. Racial slavery shaped concepts of labor and imprisonment; heteronormativity organizes family, gender, sexuality. Reddy is a critic of a new form of racial and sexual hegemony, though he does not use this term. Much as Gramsci’s old hegemony squelched revolution through state reform, today a new hegemony incorporates race- and sexuality-based conflict through the state as well: ‘equality,’ ‘rights,’ or the recognition of ‘difference’ are central features of contemporary social control strategies. They always require enforcement, the use of force, regulation, and legibility. That is the state violence that Reddy is talking about.</p>
<p>In some ways <italic>Freedom Through Violence</italic> is very familiar. It synthesizes not only Foucault, Spivak, Nikhil Singh, Lisa Lowe, or Mahmood Mamdani, but also harks back to Marx, Weber, Mill, and of course Du Bois. The contradictions of state violence and legitimacy, of democracy and despotism, are among the best-known tropes in social theory. Reddy brings not so much new insights as a very determined and systematic critique of the limits of the liberal/neoliberal state and of its circumscription of the radical dimensions of raciality and sexuality.</p>
<p>Reddy opens with an examination of the Sheppard-Byrd Hate Crimes Prevention Act, passed as an amendment to the National Defense Authorization Act (NDAA) of 2010. Sheppard-Byrd protects individuals from interpersonal violence based on gender identity, sexuality and disability. Its passage under the auspices of the NDAA was understood as an act of political genius by Democrats, and as an unfortunate compromise by anti-war progressives. However, Reddy argues, this seeming odd-couple legislation is in fact iconic of US state-making, granting freedom from individual violence as a means for allowing the state to deploy further racial violence.</p>
<p>Reddy focuses on both the first and last quarter of the 20th century as moments of ‘vigorous state making.’ But his analysis of the marriage equality movement is relevant to today's headlines. He argues that this struggle makes demands on the state for rights (or freedoms) while remaining blind to the violences that inhere. The appeal for marriage rights, often demanded by white middle-class gays, flattens the complex, intertwined histories of race and sexuality in the USA. He criticizes gay rights activists who have suggested that other aggrieved subjects, such as undocumented workers, need to ‘get in line’ behind gays in their struggle for marriage equality. Here, rights function not just to discipline the multiplicity of the subject but like goods to be possessed under consumer capitalism.</p>
<p><italic>Freedom with Violence</italic> concludes by rejecting state reform as a way to reduce or end racism and homophobia. ‘What formations of struggle and knowledge must we build when our sexuality mediates the global racial violence that is part of the nation's constitutive conditions of possibility?’ (p. 246) Reddy asks. That is a hard sentence to interpret; much of the book is written like that. But Reddy seems to suggest that there is an alternative type of popular struggle that can avoid the clutches of the state.</p>
<p>The book's conclusion leaves us in the common conundrum of radical leftist critique. If ‘true’ resistance rejects the state, what does that mean in practice? Of course, working through the state is a limited endeavor and should not be the only means for generating change. When the state accedes to movement demands, movements lose control: You wanted civil rights, you get ‘reverse racism.’ You wanted gay marriage, you get Ted Olsen.</p>
<p>However, a politics that does not address the state ever, for any reason, even if it is to refuse its authority, is difficult to imagine. State-based reforms – civil rights laws, hate crimes laws, family law, and marriage law – can in limited ways generate and fortify freedom.</p>
<p>Yes, winning is losing. But losing is also winning. By winning state reforms we reveal, and move beyond, the narrow conceptions of LGBTQ/straight; black/white/brown/yellow/red; and gender as well. (Note: Reddy has little to say about gender outside the race frame. Think of what he could have said about abortion!) All the gains we have made, all the (limited of course) partial democracy and partial freedoms we have achieved, are the outcomes of struggle. We need to see the relationship between freedom and violence as unstable and processual, situated in history and propelled by desire: the desire for freedom perhaps most of all. Reddy does not take us all the way there, but he does explore these questions in a good way.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>