<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Contemp Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Contemporary Sociology: A Journal of Reviews</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0094-3061</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-8638</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0094306113491547</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0094306113491547</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Critical-Retrospective Essays</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sex and Relationships among Youth</article-title>
<subtitle>An Intersectional Gender Lens</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>England</surname><given-names>Paula</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0094306113491547">New York University</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ronen</surname><given-names>Shelly</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0094306113491547">New York University</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0094306113491547"><email>pengland@nyu.edu</email></corresp>
<corresp id="corresp2-0094306113491547"><email>sronen@nyu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>503</fpage>
<lpage>513</lpage>
<product>
<source>Hooking Up: Sex, Dating, and Relationships on Campus</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bogle</surname><given-names>Kathleen A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>. <page-count count="225"/>pp. <price>$21.00</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780814799697</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Black Sexual Politics: African Americans, Gender, and the New Racism</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>Patricia Hill</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Theatre Arts Books</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>. <page-count count="374"/>pp. <price>$29.95</price> cloth. ISBN: <isbn>9780415930995</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Promises I Can Keep: Why Poor Women Put Motherhood Before Marriage</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edin</surname><given-names>Kathryn</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kefalas</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>. <page-count count="293"/>pp. <price>$45.00</price> cloth. ISBN: <isbn>9780520241138</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Between Good and Ghetto: African American Girls and Inner City Violence</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Nikki</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="211"/>pp. <price>$24.95</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780813546155</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Getting Played: African American Girls, Urban Inequality, and Gendered Violence</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Jody</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>. <page-count count="292"/>pp. <price>$24.00</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780814756980</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Dude, You’re A Fag: Masculinity and Sexuality in High School</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>. <page-count count="227"/>pp. <price>$19.95</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780520252301</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Premarital Sex in America: How Young Americans Meet, Mate, and Think about Marrying</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Regnerus</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uecker</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="295"/>pp. <price>$24.95</price> cloth. ISBN: <isbn>9780199743285</isbn>.</product>
<product>
<source>Wannabes, Goths, and Christians: The Boundaries of Sex, Style, and Status</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>Amy C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>. <page-count count="281"/>pp. <price>$25.00</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780226898438</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Over the last decade, while the popular press was abuzz with hyperbolic portrayals of youth sexuality, sociologists offered more accurate and thoughtful portraits. Here we explore sex and relationships among youth and young adults, using material from seven exciting books of the last decade. Without providing a thorough review of any of the books, we highlight what they tell us about selected themes. Discussions of gender permeate these books, and several authors highlight how gender intersects with class and race. Most authors find interesting ways to combine both culture and economic matters in their explanatory accounts.</p>
<p>Premarital sex is ubiquitous now, but there was a time when sex before marriage was not the norm, and most of what existed was among engaged couples. At some point, the typical standard morphed to an acceptance of sex in any relationship of affection. What is newer is the institution of the “hookup,” described in Kathleen Bogle’s <italic>Hooking Up: Sex, Dating, and Relationships on Campus</italic> (2008), based on a qualitative interview study of students and alumni from two eastern four-year universities. As students typically use the term, a “hookup” occurs when two students, usually not strangers, encounter each other, often at a party, and something sexual happens between them that night. The sexual behavior can be anything from making out to intercourse; the term “hookup” is very vague. An interest in a relationship is neither assumed nor precluded in a hookup. Our research from an online survey from 21 four-year universities shows that about 40 percent of hookups entail intercourse, about 15 percent involve oral sex but not intercourse, and the rest involve “making out” or other touching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0094306113491547">England et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>The sexual state of play among teens and young adults defies easy summary because it is heterogeneous. Our online study of college students showed that, among seniors, while more than two-thirds of students had had at least one hookup, fully 20 percent of students were still virgins. Clearly, some acceptance has been gained for casual sex; yet, it is not uncontested. Mark Regnerus and Jeremy Uecker’s <italic>Premarital Sex in America: How Young Americans Meet, Mate, and Think About Marrying</italic> (2011) draws from statistical analysis of several surveys and qualitative interviews. The authors note that the most common sexual script is serial monogamy in relationships, but that a significant amount of sex happens outside relationships as well. They show that those from more privileged backgrounds, as well as better students and those who are college bound, start sex somewhat later, and end up with fewer sexual partners. Youth who are very religious report a later age at first intercourse and fewer partners. Christians from conservative denominations are a minority in believing that sex before marriage is wrong. Yet Regnerus and Uecker show that they often have premarital sex anyhow, although they delay it longer, and keep it more in relationships. Conservative Christians are one of the three groups of white youth which Amy Wilkins pinpoints in her <italic>Wannabes, Goths, and Christians: The Boundaries of Sex, Style, and Status</italic> (2008). The members of a Christian organization on a university campus that she studied take abstinence from sex until marriage as an important part of their more general concept of goodness. Another one of the groups that Wilkins studied, goths, embraced in-your-face expressions of transgressive sexuality, including sexualized attire for women, bisexuality, polyamory (i.e., relationships defined as nonmonogamous), and acting out themes of bondage and domination at dance parties. Wilkins’ groups show some of the extremes of the heterogeneous state of affairs.</p>
<p>Recent research points to two forms of gender inequality in the heterosexual college sexual scene, and they operate outside the college environment as well. One is that men’s pleasure is prioritized over women’s; an indicator of this is that men have orgasms much more often in hookups than women. In boyfriend-girlfriend relationships the gap exists but is much smaller than in hookups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0094306113491547">Armstrong et al. 2012</xref>). A common style of sexualized dancing at college parties also illustrates the prioritization of men’s pleasure; it entails the woman’s buttocks “grinding” into the male genital area, and thus seems more designed to produce male than female pleasure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0094306113491547">Ronen 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>While the sex gap in pleasure is not discussed in these books, the authors point to a second related form of gender inequality. Regnerus and Uecker as well as Bogle point out the double standard, under which women are judged more harshly than men for having casual sex or multiple partners. As one man interviewed by Bogle says, “Well it’s kind of a bad thing if you’re a girl and you hook up with a lot of guys, then that’s looked down upon… by both genders, yeah. But if you’re a guy and you hook up with a lot of people… you’re the man!” (p. 103). It is not surprising, then, that women withhold sex in order to signal respectability or romantic interest. One woman Bogle talked to said, “If I know I like this person, [then] maybe [I won’t do] anything [sexually] because I want this person to respect me and maybe not just look at it as a hookup” (p. 38).</p>
<p>One of our critiques of Regnerus and Uecker is their treatment of the double standard. Their statistical analysis finds that the total number of sexual partners a young adult has had (probably indicative of more casual liaisons) is associated with depression for women but not men. They fail to consider the major reason that multiple partners or casual sex have negative effects on women and not men may be that women and not men are socially denigrated for doing so. Regnerus and Uecker also treat the double standard as inevitable without offering a compelling argument for why it could not be changed. Even if we were to accept their view that men are evolutionarily wired to want as much sex as possible, why would that wiring also stigmatize partners who give them what they want?</p>
<p>The women Bogle talked to often claimed to want relationships rather than hookups, and to be frustrated that men did not share that interest. Indeed, Bogle portrays a “war of the sexes” over relationships versus casual sex—and she thinks men have inexplicably won. We suspect Bogle exaggerates how homogeneous women’s preferences are, but other evidence also suggests that, <italic>on average</italic>, women want relationships more than men, and men are more interested in casual sex. Regnerus and Uecker discuss the same phenomenon, saying that the “price” men have to “pay” in commitment and attention in order to get sex has gone down. The two works portray a similar reality, but Bogle conjectures that women want relationships more and casual sex less than men because of the double standard, while Regnerus and Uecker lean toward the view that these preferences are hard-wired.</p>
<p>In a recent article, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0094306113491547">Hamilton and Armstrong (2009)</xref> dissent from the common view that durable relationships are better than hookups for women. Based on their ethnographic and interview study of women students at a midwestern four-year public university, they conclude that women are more often harmed by bad relationships than by casual hookups gone awry. For women from upper middle-class backgrounds, relationships interfere with what they see as the main goals of college—schoolwork and meeting people. They believe that relationships create a risk of being married too early. For women from working-class backgrounds, relationships with guys back home who did not go to college sometimes pull them out of college. Both groups of women complained about boyfriends who tried to control the time they spent with friends. Even in their small sample of 53, they had one report each of men responding to women’s breakups with a suicide attempt, stalking, and tire slashing. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0094306113491547">Armstrong et al. (2010)</xref> say, “Bad hookups were isolated events, while bad relationships wreaked havoc with whole lives.”</p>
<p>Regnerus and Uecker point to the high women-to-men sex ratios on today’s college campuses as one reason for the move toward nonrelational sex. The idea is that the higher the ratio of women to men, the more power men have to get what they want in heterosexual partnerships. So if men are more interested in casual sex, and women in relationships, there will be more casual sex and fewer relationships when there is a surplus of women. As evidence that sex ratios matter, Regnerus and Uecker show that women attending schools with a lower ratio of men to women were <italic>less</italic> likely to have a boyfriend but <italic>more</italic> likely to have had sex. If women in schools with fewer men per woman had been less likely to have a boyfriend <italic>and</italic> less likely to have sex, we could conclude simply that there just were not enough men available, so some women had to forego either relationships or sex. But when women are having more sex and fewer men are available, it suggests that men can get sex more easily because too many women are competing for too few men.</p>
<p>Granting that sex ratios explain some between-school variation in how much men have to offer a relationship to get sex, we nonetheless doubt that sex ratios explain long-term trends toward uncommitted sex or class differences. As for the trend, at least for whites, sex ratios in the overall population have not changed that much. As for class differences, a consequence of the fact that there are now more women than men in college and among recent college graduates, is that there are more men than women among youth not completing college. So if sex ratios were the only factor operating, those not going to college would be having less casual sex and more of their sex in relationships than those going to college. But we know of no evidence showing this. One test of this would be whether lower SES youth and those not going to college were less likely to move to sex within two weeks of meeting; one recent analysis showed that these groups did not differ significantly on this measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0094306113491547">England et al. 2011</xref>:31).</p>
<p>The big class difference is not whether youth are having sex, but whether the sex leads to early births outside marriage or even stable relationships. A vivid description of the transition to early, unmarried motherhood is offered by Kathryn Edin and Maria Kefalas’ <italic>Promises I Can Keep: Why Poor Women Put Motherhood Before Marriage</italic> (2005), based on in-depth interviews of poor white, black, and Puerto Rican women living in neighborhoods of concentrated poverty in the Philadelphia area. Edin and Kefalas find that poor women revere marriage, but see it as out of reach. The authors’ account of why it is out of reach blends economics and culture. Clearly, the job prospects of the men in poor communities are dismal and have deteriorated, but they review compelling quantitative evidence that declining male employment and earnings explain no more than a fifth of the downturn in marriage. They believe that the culturally dictated economic and relational bars to marriage are now elevated as early marriage has come to be seen as optional. Currently, the middle class and the poor agree that both partners should have a satisfying relationship, stable jobs, and financial security before marriage. But this new cultural standard is out of reach for the poor.</p>
<p>Elevated cultural standards for marriage, combined with bad economic opportunities, can explain the retreat from early marriage, but not why poor women still have early first births. While the teen birth rate has plummeted since the early 1990s, and many nonmarital births are to women in their 20s, the typical woman having a nonmarital birth still has her <italic>first</italic> birth as a teen. The average age at first birth among the women Edin and Kefalas interviewed was 18. Their pregnancies were seldom explicitly planned, but only about a third of the women said they were entirely unplanned, and about half said they were “in between planned and unplanned.” Lack of access to low price contraceptives is not a common complaint, thanks largely to the presence of Planned Parenthood. Couples often use condoms early on, and later shift to a hormonal method, then at some point, often only months into the relationship, contraception becomes inconsistent or is abandoned. The authors interpret the unprotected sex to reflect ambivalence between wanting a baby now and thinking this is not the right situation for one. They argue that the poor value their children more highly than those in the middle class because they have few other sources of meaning in their lives, in part because of the distrust that characterizes high-poverty neighborhoods. They also offer a version of economists’ opportunity-cost argument—women who have lucrative careers that might get derailed by the arrival of a child have high incentives to delay fertility, while poor women have little earning power to lose. Indeed, the women they interviewed spoke more often of their children saving them than derailing their plans. Motherhood, in one common narrative, forced them to be responsible, and saved them from the ruin of “rippin’ and runnin’” the streets.</p>
<p>In our view, Edin and Kefalas exaggerate the extent to which women wanted to get pregnant before they conceived. Telling respondents that their study was about motherhood, and talking to women after they had their babies probably evoked responses that exaggerated how much the women had wanted to get pregnant before the fact. It is telling that the mothers they interviewed, just like their mothers before them, do not want <italic>their</italic> children to have babies at 18. They prefer that their kids finish school, go to college, get a good job, and find a partner with a good job before having a child.</p>
<p>If Edin and Kefalas’ explanation of young, poor women’s pregnancies is inadequate, what is a better one? Avoiding pregnancy requires consistently following a regimen. For example, to use the birth control pill, one must make an appointment with a doctor, fill a prescription, and take pills at the same time each day. To do these onerous practices, one must have developed the skill of self-regulation and confidence in the future, and one must trust institutional medical actors. We hypothesize that the class gradient on early, unplanned pregnancies reflects the fact that growing up poor makes it harder to develop self-regulation, confidence in the future, and trust in institutional actors. This may be part of why many upper middle-class youth are sexually active for a decade with no unplanned pregnancy, while poor women more often have unplanned pregnancies and early births.</p>
<p>Most of the births Edin and Kefalas reported on were to couples in a romantic relationship. Often there was conflict during the pregnancy, but later pregnancy and birth typically drew couples together. Yet most relationships ended within a few years. By the women’s telling, this was seldom because the men were not providing much money, although that was a common grievance. Rather the women attributed the breakups to men’s using or selling drugs, incarceration, sexual cheating, and/or violence. Most of the women still aspire to marriage someday, but their distrust of men is palpable.</p>
<p>Indeed, when one reads about the fabric of relationships between men and women in poor communities, it makes the tribulations of college women pale by comparison. Like their richer counterparts, poor women do encounter a double standard and other norms that privilege men’s sexual agency, but on top of that they encounter high levels of rape and other violence. This is the topic taken up in <italic>Between Good and Ghetto: African American Girls and Inner City Violence</italic> (2010) by Nikki Jones and <italic>Getting Played: African American Girls, Urban Inequality, and Gendered Violence</italic> (2008) by Jody Miller. Jones conducted an ethnography of teen girls in Philadelphia, while Miller combined a closed-ended survey and qualitative interviews with teen girls and boys in St. Louis. Both authors studied only African Americans, and prioritized talking to youths who were, themselves, engaged in crime or violence, and in dangerous neighborhoods. Indeed, about half the youths Miller studied had been involved in selling drugs. The young women these two authors talked to are thus at the extreme end of economic and social disadvantage.</p>
<p>The violence experienced by the poor, black girls studied by Miller and Jones is harrowing. The boys Miller interviewed talk about grabbing girls’ “butts” at school to show off to other boys; half the girls said they had been grabbed and touched in ways that made them feel uncomfortable. Both authors mention how often young women get blamed when men hit them. Jones overhears one girl tell another about a friend hit by her boyfriend. “That’s what she get” is the response. A man symbolically loses face if a woman hits him in the face, so many youth see it as understandable if a man hits a woman who does this, even when they claim the general belief that men should not hit women. Miller notes that stories of boys’ violence against girls often evoked laughter—more so than stories of male-on-male violence.</p>
<p>By Miller’s account, men are in control of public spaces. Faced with harassment in public, girls have unfortunate options: they can avoid going out at all, ignore abuse, retaliate with violence, or seek third party help. However, fraught relations with police, the reluctance to send another black man to jail, and school administrators who ignore abuse make reliance on outside intervention unpromising. Nor do bystanders witnessing violence typically help—Miller describes a norm of noninterference: even a man publicly beating a woman, while frowned upon, will be seen as “none of our business.” Both authors find that girls often feel very much on their own in dealing with violence from men or boys.</p>
<p>Some violence with boyfriends happens indoors. Jones tells the poignant story of one 19-year-old woman who kept trying to keep a relationship going with the drug-selling father of her baby. She could tolerate it when he grabbed or pushed her, but she drew the line at him hitting her with his fist and trying to choke her. Then she called the police, and this time (unlike previously) showed up at her court date. Yet, she did not really want him to go to jail, or even to end the relationship—she just wanted to be safe from the violence.</p>
<p>As for sex, the double standard that Bogle described among college students seems similar to what Miller describes among poor black youth involved in crime. Among the latter, girls who have casual sex or give guys oral sex get a reputation as “nasty.” Just as in college, women can get the “slut” label from sexy styles of dress. In both contexts, women with such reputations are not respected by either men or women. But the disrespect translated into more coercive behaviors in the neighborhoods Miller studied, such as publicly grabbing a girl’s “butt” or making sexual comments to her. As one young man put it, “I don’t treat my girl like no hood rat, but I treat a rat like a rat… If I’m disrespecting a female [it’s] because they nasty… It’s some girls that are just wild and don’t care who they sleep with or who they have oral sex with.”</p>
<p>Sexual coercion abounds in the world Miller describes. Indeed, 45 percent of the teen boys Miller surveyed said they had been involved in “running trains” on girls, where several guys have intercourse with one girl in succession. The boys claimed these events were consensual, but we have our doubts. Analogous events occur at college fraternity parties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0094306113491547">Armstrong et al. 2006</xref>). Yet our sense is that young, poor women of color experience more sexual coercion than college women. In her survey, Miller asked about sexual coercion, and as it happens, we used some similar questions in our online survey of four-year college students, so we can compare reports from the two populations. We asked women, “Since you started college have you had sexual intercourse that was physically forced on you?” Among seniors, who thus had about four years at risk, 10 percent replied yes. Miller asked “Have you ever been sexually assaulted, molested, or raped?” and 26 percent responded yes. While her question references a girl’s whole life, not just the college years, Miller’s respondents averaged 16 years of age, so most would have had no more than four years of exposure to boyfriends, dating, and so forth. We also asked if the women had, during college, had sexual intercourse that they did not want because someone verbally pressured them, and 14 percent of seniors said yes. Miller asked if the girls had ever been pressured to have sex when it was not wanted, and 37 percent said yes. While the questions are not fully comparable, they seem to suggest that coercive sex is a worse threat for these most disadvantaged women.</p>
<p>Though the college scene, with its privileging of male pleasure, its double standard, and its occasional party rape, is no feminist panacea, the works above convince us that male dominance is much more coercively and violently deployed by disadvantaged men. Why is this? Jones explains this by “the lack of resources available to help young men take on a masculine identity in ways that do not involve physical domination or violence” (p. 110). This is hinted at by Miller and many other authors. The idea is that masculinity is culturally defined in terms of some kind of mastery, power, or dominance. Men can experience mastery through academic success, athletics, a high status job, making money, providing for a family, and so on. Absent these sources of respect, men turn to forms of masculinity that are based on violence and physical domination. Lower-class men, especially men of color, in this view, are like their more privileged counterparts when seeking to enact a masculinity defined by power, but they have fewer noncoercive means available. This intersectional hypothesis deserves further study. Although none of these authors makes it explicit, this is a view in which culture interacts with economic realities: different forms of men’s behavior result from a combination of a culture defining masculinity in terms of power, and class and race creating differential economic opportunity for accomplishing nonviolent types of power.</p>
<p>Not only men are violent in rough neighborhoods. Jones’ ethnography shows that girls growing up surrounded by violence often fight physically as well. She divides their survival strategies into two types: “good girls” and “fighters.” The “fighters” use their intimidating reputations to protect themselves, and thereby sacrifice respectable black femininity, while the “good girls” define themselves in opposition to “fighters,” hoping for protection. But Jones says that the resulting distinction between “good” and “ghetto” is a bit misleading, as both groups of girls sometimes fight, and both have some yearning for respectability. Both groups, in the words of Jones’ title, are between good and ghetto.</p>
<p>C.J. Pascoe’s <italic>Dude, You’re a Fag: Masculinity and Sexuality in High School</italic> (2007) digs into the connection between gendered aggression and masculinity. Her book is based on an ethnography of a racially diverse, largely working-class high school in a suburban town in California. Pascoe reveals how boys prove their masculinity through interactions imbued with sexual meanings. Boys constantly call each other “fag” in order to indicate that they are heterosexual, to neutralize the threat of being seen as a fag, and to confirm masculinity. This homophobic discourse is not entirely about sexual orientation, in Pascoe’s view. Boys explained that the fag discourse is a generic insult for “being stupid or incompetent, dancing, caring too much about clothing, being too emotional, or expressing interest (sexual or platonic) in other guys” (p. 57). Anything deemed feminine, when exhibited by boys, led to the fag label. Thus Pascoe sees it as more about policing and enacting masculinity on a stage than about the denigration of gay boys. She presents the suffering experienced by gender-nonconforming boys, whether gay or not, as collateral damage to other boys’ accomplishment of masculinity. Pascoe relays the story of Ricky, a white junior who identifies as gay and has a gender-nonconforming presentation of self. He experiences name-calling, violence, and exclusion. School authorities observing his torment often do nothing. He eventually drops out of school.</p>
<p>Girls also pay a price for boys’ enacting of masculinity. Domination of girls seems written into the implicit cultural rules for accomplishing masculinity. Pascoe teases out the gendered meanings of “locker-room talk”: “heterosexual innuendo, sexual bravado, and sexual one-upmanship,” from which boys derive confidence in their masculinity (p. 85). Here too, as with the fag discourse, the talk is ultimately not about sexual orientation and desire, but seems to be intended to prove a masculine “mastery and dominance literally or figuratively over girls’ bodies” (p. 86). In addition to talk among the boys, this dominance takes the form of leering and staring at girls, making sexual comments about their bodies, calling them “whores” when they ignore overtures, kissing them against their will, and “touching rituals,” that vary from flirtatious to violent.</p>
<p>When Pascoe interviews them individually, boys speak touchingly about their affectionate feelings toward and insecurities about girlfriends, but these things are not revealed publicly to other boys. Similarly, the poor, black young men Miller studied are denigrated as “soft” if they admit such feelings to their male peers. Our interviews with privileged fraternity men in college have found similarly that, although exclusive relationships with girls are common, in male peer dialogue, men in relationships are teased as being “pussy whooped.”</p>
<p>In recent decades, the “doing gender” perspective has become almost hegemonic in gender studies. It sees gendered behavior as acts performed in order to conform to others’ normative expectations, rather than a reflection of deeply internalized gendered cultural norms or preferences. We are critical of authors who presume one or the other of these two views (gender as performance or as internalized norms and preferences) without providing any evidence allowing adjudication between the two views. Pascoe, too, uses the language of “enactment of masculinity” throughout her book without explicitly considering an alternative. The work of Miller and Jones reminds us that enactment of masculinity does not limit coercive practices to public displays: women experience victimization in private as well. We nonetheless find Pascoe’s evidence more convincing than anything we have read on her point that a good portion of young men’s public behavior related to sexuality is to display masculinity to their male peers. The nature of the behavior she describes, combined with the differences between what boys say to her in private and what they display to other boys, convinces us that the “doing gender” view is apt. This motivation for hookups, which often start in public spaces, was not considered by Bogle, or Regnerus and Uecker.</p>
<p>Pascoe’s analysis might lead us to believe that masculinity is enacted in all social classes in ways that denigrate “fags” for their putative femininity and that assert sexualized domination over young women. But her study site was a working-class high school. When we have talked to relatively privileged college students about Pascoe’s findings, they often find the dominance and denigration behavior more extreme than what they remember in their own high schools. Perhaps they are deluded. But we suspect, following Jones and Miller, that while most groups define masculinity in terms of some kind of power, the enactments are more coercive in less privileged class locations. We need careful studies like Pascoe’s in settings of greater class privilege to know how general her conclusions are.</p>
<p>In <italic>Wannabes, Goths, and Christians: The Boundaries of Sex, Style, and Status</italic>, introduced above, Wilkins sets out to investigate three subcultural “identity projects” each of which is partly defined by a stance taken toward sexuality. The goths, Christians, and Puerto Rican wannabe subcultures show the ways that young people take on identities to be accepted and to be seen as cool; these are two problems she considers to be central for all youth.</p>
<p>Goths are youth who might otherwise be seen as geeky or unattractive. As mentioned above, these young adults take on shocking, edgy self-presentations and claim a transgressive identity of freakiness in order to be seen as cool. Goths talk about their transgressive sexuality as pro-feminist. As one woman explains, “in the gothic subculture, this old symbol of female restriction has been turned into an empowering one” (p. 66). The women clearly see themselves as agentic, not victims. Even the men talk explicitly about gender equality. Even so, Wilkins highlights instances of gender inequality in matters of sex and relationships. While goths claim that women are liberated because they can dress in a sexually provocative way and have sex freely, Wilkins thinks the flip side is that appearing sexy and accepting unwanted sexual advances seems somewhat compulsory. As an example, at a goth club one night, Greg, a goth insider, initiates Jamie, a relative newcomer, by sucking on her neck. He later explains he wanted to “break the ice” between her and another goth woman, Beth. Neither woman perceived it this way, and both said they would have rather be left alone but felt uncomfortable discouraging Greg. Moreover, while heavy-set goth women find more acceptance than in mainstream culture as desirable sexual beings, Wilkins observed goths ridiculing women when their outfit accentuated their heaviness.</p>
<p>Goths engage in bisexuality and polyamory (relationships open to nonmonogamy), and see these practices as inherently empowering to women. But Wilkins claims that, as they actually play out, these practices benefit men more than women, and are less queer-friendly than goth ideology would suggest. As in the larger society, more women than men in the goth community are drawn to sex and romance with both sexes. Goth men accept their female partners’ having sexual relationships with women, but this is partly because the men like the opportunity to watch two women having sex, and also the men sometimes get to have sex with the other woman. Men seem sufficiently dismissive of the seriousness of relationships between women not to see them as a threat, as they might a sexual relationship with a man, and indeed, long-term goth relationships are mostly heterosexual. Some women who had previously seen men on the side in heterosexual relationships claimed to have moved to monogamy “because they didn’t want to hurt their boyfriends” (p. 83). Overall, in Wilkins’ view, goths think that their arrangements of sex and relationship are more gender egalitarian than they in fact are.</p>
<p>Wilkins also studied members of a conservative Christian youth organization on the campus of a large state university in the Northeast. Some of these youth were, like the goths, at risk of being uncool in high school, and some were hungry for meaning in their lives. Some men found that the church offered a place “where there would be nice and good-looking girls” (p. 98). These Christian students valorize what Wilkins calls “goodness”: behaviors and emotions achieved through hard work and self-discipline, both valued in mainstream culture. As examples of discipline, they study hard, and avoid temptations to have sex, such as going to mainstream parties and drinking. For men who would otherwise be denigrated in mainstream male culture as wimpy for not having sex, the pro-abstinence culture transforms their behavior into a symbol of discipline and resolve, things seen as admirable and even manly. Women get less credit for abstinence because they are presumed to be less driven by sexual desire; thus to prove their goodness some seek to meet a higher standard of “purity” which requires them to forego romantic relationships altogether. One form the double standard takes in this group is that women who previously had sex compensate with expressions of shame, whereas men who have had sex express only regret.</p>
<p>So far our depiction of Wilkins’ study of cultural identity projects focuses on the gendered way that sexuality plays out. But Wilkins explicitly set out to look at how race, class, and gender constrain and provide opportunities for each of the three groups. Analyzing the Puerto Rican Wannabes, intersectionality had to take center stage. Wannabes is the derogatory term used (by those outside the group) for white women who dress and talk in a style common to lower-class Puerto Rican women, have relationships with Puerto Rican or black men involved in the hip-hop culture, and sometimes end up having a child by one of these boyfriends. According to Wilkins, the white women who do this are mostly lower- or working-class women likely to be seen as “white trash” by middle-class whites, and wanting to avoid this stigma is part of what motivates their enactment of the wannabe role. She argues that the role also allows women to push against the constraints of white femininity that disallow roughness and their “fuck-the-world attitude” (p. 163). By identifying as Puerto Rican, they can enjoy the excitement of sexy clothes, and tough, aggressive talk. This is the up side—but like Miller’s women of color, many of these women get played. Wannabes risk downward mobility, getting embroiled in drug use, and unstable relationships with “thugs,” who treat them badly, cheat on them, or steal their possessions. Unlike the goths whose transgressive sexual behavior seldom leads to pregnancies because they contracept assiduously, and who can outgrow their identity project and succeed as middle-class adults, wannabes are often left alone with children they cannot outgrow and without supportive strong ties to women in either the Puerto Rican or white community. White working-class girls see them as “loud and obnoxious… [and] too proud of their sexuality” (p. 162), while young women of color ask “Why are you trying to be down with a culture that’s not yours?”</p>
<p>We find it admirable that Wilkins explicitly sets out to investigate how gender and sexuality were structured by race and class for each of the three subcultural groups. Sometimes the analysis seems forced, coming more from her <italic>a priori</italic> commitment to make everything fully intersectional than from important themes in the data. All three groups are white, and her discussion of race sometimes consists of inferring racial beliefs that were not even hinted at by the people she studied. For example, when goths tell her proudly that they use condoms routinely, have HIV screenings, and often use hormonal birth control as well, she interprets their strategies as “linked…less consciously, to the performance of race and class” (p. 85). Noting that “early, unwed childbearing…and sexual promiscuity are denigrated as social problems plaguing the poor and people of color” (p. 86), she concludes that “the goth strategy remakes these symbolic oppositions, even if unintentionally” (p. 86). Racism is often subconscious or unstated, but this seems to read a lot into taking pride in safe sex! In other places her assertions about race seem contradictory. She speculates that goths are able to get away with some of their transgressive sexual practices without completely losing respectability because they are white and mostly upper middle class. She also suggests that wannabes are motivated in part by wanting to escape stifling definitions of white femininity which preclude overt sexiness. Can whiteness give young women a pass on sexualized displays, but also contain a norm of femininity that precludes such displays?</p>
<p>“Controlling images” that disparage racial groups because of their real or imagined sexual practices are center stage in Patricia Hill Collins’ <italic>Black Sexual Politics: African Americans, Gender, and the New Racism</italic> (2004). This book differs from the others we review in that it does not draw upon interviews or ethnography, but is a work “of critical social theory” (p. 8) that draws on historical sources, and also the empirical materials of black popular culture, especially mass media songs, music videos, television, and movies. Her main thesis is that the “controlling images” that went with older racial formations (e.g., slavery and Jim Crow) are refracted through the “new racism” and affect actual sexual and gender relations in the black community. Under the controlling images of the new racism, “Black people carry the stigma of promiscuity or excessive or unrestrained heterosexual desire” (p. 97). Such images create fear of black men, and disdain for black women’s childbearing.</p>
<p>We are quite convinced by the evidence presented to support her claim that there is a continuity across very different racial formations in the content of racialized sexual images. The fear of black men as rapists of white women legitimized lynching during the Jim Crow period; today the gangsta rap image depicts black men as playahs. In the case of women, Collins shows the continuities between European men’s fascination in the 1800s with a caged African woman’s large buttocks (p. 26), the popularity in the early 1900s in Paris of an African American entertainer doing a “rump-shaking” dance (p. 26), and the emphasis on “booty” in recent hip hop music. Collins teases out the meanings of the term <italic>booty</italic>, showing that it both conjures masculine ownership over the plunders from warfare, and refers to black female buttocks, genitals, and racialized casual sex.</p>
<p>Collins shows that controlling images suggest black women are either aggressive and sexual “bitches,” or poor and abusive “bad mothers.” These femininities, of course, rely on notions of black men, since bitches and bad mothers both imply an absence of upstanding men to dominate or support them. In that sense, black men are viewed as too weak, but they are also seen as physically and sexually powerful. The latter is consistent with what Pascoe observes among African American boys using the fag discourse. Black boys tease each other for being white, where “white” stands in for “fag.” In Pascoe’s opinion, this is evidence of the role of race in shaping meanings that undergird discourse: since “African American men are so hypersexualized in the United States, white men are, by default, feminized” (p. 71). The bodies of black athletes inspire admiration, while urban “thugs” embody deviance and violence that arouse fear. Ironically, some of these images are promulgated today by black rap artists.</p>
<p>Collins decries the fact that, in reacting to these images and trying to salvage a more respectable image, middle-class blacks, and black churches sometimes denigrate gays and lesbians, as if admitting their presence in the black community will add to the stigmatization of the community. Her claim that this is a source of homophobia in the black church is conjectural; it could be that its source is the same interpretation of scriptural passages that give rise to declaring homosexuality a sin in white-dominated conservative Protestant denominations. The feminist in her does not like efforts to make blacks look more respectable by upholding mainstream gender norms dictating that men have the power in heterosexual relationships. And she wishes that black men who avoid the controlling image of themselves as “weak” would realize that “Good Black men need not rule their families with an iron hand, assault one another, pursue endless booty calls, and always seem to be ‘in control’” (p. 200). But does she think these modern controlling images actually cause infidelity and coercion in relationships between black men and black women? As we read it, she does suggest this, and it is plausible, but she gives no evidence. Although presented as a work of theory, Collins’ book contains convincing empirical work on the content of historical and contemporary cultural discourse, but it offers no empirical work to adjudicate how much these cultural images affect behavior in today’s black community. Such work is still to be done.</p>
<p>Collins’ explanations of the worst behavior of black men toward black women also include the lack of economic opportunity and mass incarceration. Here her arguments are very similar to those of Miller and Jones—that black men have accepted the same definition of masculinity to be about power as seen in the white middle class, but they do not have nonphysical, noncoercive ways to get it. Her explanation is one part economics (race and class disprivilege in the economy) and two parts culture—mainstream images of masculinity as dominance, and racist controlling images of black men as economically weak but powerfully hypersexual.</p>
<p>The works reviewed here contribute to an understanding of heterosexual relationships and sex among youth and young adults. They focus on gender dynamics, and take an intersectional approach, examining how gendering varies by race or class. As an example of the latter, the books suggest that gendered coercion is more extreme in less privileged class and race locations. In exploring explanations of meanings and behavior around sexuality, including how gendering varies by race and class, they provide a refreshing willingness to combine economic and cultural accounts.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>England</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alison</surname><given-names>Fogarty</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2012</year>. “<article-title>Accounting for Women’s Orgasm and Sexual Enjoyment in College Hookups and Relationships</article-title>.” <source>American Sociological Review</source> <volume>77</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laura</surname><given-names>Hamilton</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>England</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Is Hooking Up Bad for Young Women?</article-title>” <source>Contexts</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Sexual Assault on Campus: A Multi-level, Integrative Approach to Party Rape</article-title>.” <source>Social Problems</source> <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>England</surname><given-names>Paula</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>Emily Fitzgibbons</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>Alison C.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Hooking Up and Forming Romantic Relationships on Today’s College Campuses</article-title>.” Pp. <fpage>531</fpage>-<lpage>547</lpage> in <source>The Gendered Society Reader</source> (<edition>Third Edition</edition>) by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimmel</surname><given-names>Michael S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name>
</person-group>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>England</surname><given-names>Paula</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McClintock</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>Birth Control Use and Early, Unintended Births: Evidence for a Class Gradient</article-title>.” Pp. <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage> in <source>Social Class and Changing Families in an Unequal America</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>Marcia</given-names></name>
<name><surname>England</surname><given-names>Paula</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Double Binds and Flawed Options: Gendered Sexuality in Early Adulthood</article-title>.” <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>-<lpage>616</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0094306113491547">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ronen</surname><given-names>Shelly</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Grinding On the Dance Floor: Gendered Scripts and Sexualized Dancing at College Parties</article-title>.” <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>