<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-6990</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077699012442827</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077699012442827</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Newspaper Titan: The Infamous Life and Monumental Times of Cissy Patterson by Amanda Smith</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Beasley</surname><given-names>Maurine</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1077699012442827">University of Maryland, College Park, MD, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>89</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>337</fpage>
<lpage>339</lpage>
<product><source>Newspaper Titan: The Infamous Life and Monumental Times of Cissy Patterson</source>. <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Alfred A. Knopf</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="696"/> pp. <price>$37.50</price> hbk.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 AEJMC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Education in Journalism &amp; Mass Communication</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Once upon a time some mainstream newspapers reaped huge circulations with content that tantalized, trivialized, and even brutalized those with whom opinionated editors and publishers disagreed. This kind of journalistic fare made moralists weep, but the general public lapped it up as daily entertainment. The newspaper business was populated by bizarre characters who were not like you and me, but who had a rare ability to connect with readers.</p>
<p>At the top of this pantheon of notables in the first half of the twentieth century stood Eleanor Medill “Cissy” Patterson, a dominant figure in Washington journalism from 1930 until her death in 1948. A scion of the <italic>Chicago Tribune</italic> publishing empire, as Amanda Smith points out in this comprehensive biography, Patterson followed her family recipe of giving readers, “Dogs! Cats! Murder!” along with sexual titillation, personal vindictiveness, isolationism, and mistrust of Franklin D. Roosevelt.</p>
<p>In the 1940s, <italic>Collier’s</italic> magazine called Patterson, who is virtually forgotten today, “probably the most powerful woman in America,” and “perhaps the most hated.” Also known as the Countess Gizycka due to her ill-fated marriage to a depraved Polish nobleman who kidnapped her child to force her family to give him money, Patterson, a glittering socialite, lived a life that actually outdid the fiction that she tried to write about it. Finding herself at loose ends at the age of forty-eight, in 1930 she persuaded press magnate William Randolph Hearst to let her take over his ailing <italic>Washington Herald</italic>, even though she had almost no newspaper experience.</p>
<p>To everyone’s surprise, except perhaps her own, as Smith explains in this well-researched work, Patterson succeeded in reinvigorating the <italic>Herald</italic>. In 1939, she bought not only the morning <italic>Herald</italic> from Hearst but also his floundering afternoon <italic>Washington Times</italic>. She merged the two into an around-the-clock newspaper with ten editions a day and a commanding circulation lead in the capital. Having inherited immense wealth as the granddaughter of Joseph Medill, principal owner of the <italic>Chicago Tribune</italic>, Patterson demonstrated that she, too, had printer’s ink in her veins—like her brother, Joe Medill Patterson, founder of the <italic>New York Daily News</italic>, her cousin, the redoubtable Colonel Robert McCormick, who ran the <italic>Chicago Tribune</italic>, and her niece, Alicia Patterson, who founded <italic>Newsday</italic>. In doing so, Patterson scored as the first woman editor-in-chief and publisher of a major metropolitan daily newspaper in the twentieth century.</p>
<p>Smith, a Washington, D.C., historian who is a graduate of Harvard College, previously edited the letters of her grandfather, Joseph P. Kennedy, and devoted years of research to this carefully written book. She offers detailed accounts of the feuding in the Medill family and the friction among Patterson, her only child, Felicia, and Felicia’s ex-husband, columnist Drew Pearson. The book ends with a lengthy examination of the questions surrounding Patterson’s unexpected death and the fighting over her will, which left her Times-Herald to seven executives, nicknamed the “seven dwarves.” Unable to operate the newspaper profitably, they sold it to McCormick, who in turn sold it in 1954 to the <italic>Washington Post</italic>, which added <italic>Times-Herald</italic> to its nameplate for a couple of decades before dropping it, marking the final end of Patterson’s domain.</p>
<p>While documenting Patterson’s fits of pique and quixotic hiring and firing, Smith does not provide as much information as the journalism historian would like on exactly how she maintained control of the operation that made her such a formidable figure in journalism in spite of her excessive drinking and apparent drug use. In fact, Patterson’s journalism itself plays something of a secondary role in contrast to extensive accounts of her Victorian upbringing in a world in which a woman’s place was measured by her beauty and ability to acquire a suitable, preferably titled, husband. A long section on Patterson’s unfortunate marriage to the fortune-hunting Count Gizycka follows. Next comes examination of her second marriage to a lawyer, Elmer Schlesinger, who died a few years later, when she was tiring of him. It is not until page 310, after discussion of her two novels, roughly based on her own experiences, that the <italic>Herald</italic> enters the biography (aside from brief mentions in the prologue).</p>
<p>Since Patterson dies on page 506, leaving some seventy more pages of arguments over her will, one can conclude that journalism is not the focus of the work in spite of its title. Smith makes references to Patterson running a “women’s paper,” but the journalism historian would like to know more about the demographics of Patterson’s audience and the content of the various columns that presumably attracted a female audience. Still, perhaps it is too much to expect a twenty-first-century biographer to relate in depth to an earlier era when a newspaper may not have been ethical but presumably afforded a somewhat crazed, antic view of the world that appealed to both its staff and its readers.</p>
</body>
</article>