<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JDR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjdr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Dent Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Dental Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0345</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1544-0591</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034512440450</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022034512440450</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Reports</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Clinical</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Deciduous Molar Hypomineralization and Molar Incisor Hypomineralization</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Elfrink</surname><given-names>M.E.C.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022034512440450">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0022034512440450">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0022034512440450">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>ten Cate</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022034512440450">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaddoe</surname><given-names>V.W.V.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0022034512440450">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0022034512440450">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0022034512440450">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0022034512440450">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0022034512440450">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0022034512440450">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>J.S.J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022034512440450">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0022034512440450"><label>1</label>Department of Cariology, Endodontology and Pedodontology, Academic Centre for Dentistry Amsterdam (ACTA), University of Amsterdam and VU University Amsterdam, Gustav Mahlerlaan 3004, 1081 LA Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0022034512440450"><label>2</label>The Generation R Study Group Erasmus Medical Centre - Sophia Children’s Hospital, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0022034512440450"><label>3</label>Department of Pediatrics, Erasmus Medical Centre - Sophia Children’s Hospital, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0022034512440450"><label>4</label>Department of Epidemiology, Erasmus Medical Centre - Sophia Children’s Hospital, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022034512440450"><label>*</label><email>m.elfrink@acta.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>91</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>551</fpage>
<lpage>555</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>28</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>31</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>2</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 International &amp; American Associations for Dental Research</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International &amp; American Associations for Dental Research</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study was embedded in the Generation R Study, a population-based prospective cohort study from fetal life until young adulthood. This study focused on the relationship between Deciduous Molar Hypomineralization (DMH) and Molar Incisor Hypomineralization (MIH). First permanent molars develop during a period similar to that of second primary molars, with possible comparable risk factors for hypomineralization. Children with DMH have a greater risk of developing MIH. Clinical photographs of clean, moist teeth were taken with an intra-oral camera in 6,161 children (49.8% girls; mean age 74.3 mos, SD ± 5.8). First permanent molars and second primary molars were scored with respect to DMH or MIH. The prevalence of DMH and MIH was 9.0% and 8.7% at child level, and 4.0% and 5.4% at tooth level. The Odds Ratio for MIH based on DMH was 4.4 (95% CI, 3.1-6.4). The relationship between the occurrence of DMH and MIH suggests a shared cause and indicates that, clinically, DMH can be used as a predictor for MIH.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>pediatric dentistry</kwd>
<kwd>primary dentition</kwd>
<kwd>permanent dentition</kwd>
<kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
<kwd>dental enamel hypoplasia</kwd>
<kwd>tooth demineralization</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0022034512440450" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Developmental defects of dental enamel are common in both deciduous and permanent dentitions and are classified into hypomineralization and hypoplasia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Norén, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0022034512440450">William <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Enamel hypoplasia is a quantitative defect of the enamel, resulting from a disturbance to the ameloblasts during matrix formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Norén, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022034512440450">Fearne <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Enamel hypomineralization is a qualitative defect of the enamel because of a disturbance during initial calcification and/or during maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Norén, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). Hypomineralized parts of teeth are weaker and the enamel may chip off easily, resulting in post-eruptive loss of enamel. It can be difficult to distinguish between hypoplasia and post-eruptive enamel loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022034512440450">Fearne <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>In the primary dentition, the second primary molar generally presents with more caries than the first primary molar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022034512440450">Holt, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022034512440450">Gizani <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). A recent study showed that hypomineralization was an important risk factor for caries in the primary dentition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Also, in the permanent dentition, rapid caries progression was observed in hypomineralized molars (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Klingberg, 2002</xref>). Hypomineralized permanent molars are frequently combined with hypomineralized incisors. Molar Incisor Hypomineralization (MIH) is defined as hypomineralization of systemic origin of 1 to 4 permanent first molars combined with affected incisors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022034512440450">Weerheijm, 2003</xref>). MIH-like defects are also seen on second primary molars and permanent cuspids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). These MIH-like defects in the primary molars are now described as Deciduous Molar Hypomineralization (DMH) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022034512440450">2010</xref>). In the Netherlands, the prevalence of DMH has been reported at 4.9% at child level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>) while the prevalence of MIH was higher (6-14%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0022034512440450">Jasulaityte <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>The severity of MIH as well as DMH varies between patients, but also within a patient. Opacities are considered the mildest form of MIH and DMH, and atypical extractions as the most severe manifestation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). MIH can cause serious pain due to post-eruptive enamel loss, rapid caries progression, and pain during restorative treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Klingberg, 2002</xref>). Children with MIH need more dental treatments and – probably as a consequence – are generally more fearful than their peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Klingberg, 2002</xref>). Therefore, it is important to diagnose MIH as early as possible to reduce the vulnerability of the MIH-affected molars by focusing on their restorative and preventive needs.</p>
<p>The development of the second primary molars starts at around the same time as the development of the first permanent molars and permanent incisors, but the maturation of the permanent teeth occurs more slowly (see Appendix) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022034512440450">Butler, 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0022034512440450">Profitt and Fields, 2000</xref>). If a risk factor occurs during this overlapping period, hypomineralization might occur in the primary as well as in the permanent dentition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0022034512440450">Aine <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). Therefore, DMH might be used as a predictor for MIH. The parallel development of the second primary molar and the first permanent molar, both developmentally and with respect to their location in the jaw, might be indicative of a common cause for the hypomineralization process. Our aim was therefore to study the association between DMH in the second primary molars and MIH in the first permanent molars.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0022034512440450" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials &amp; Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0022034512440450">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>This study was embedded in the Generation R Study, a population-based prospective cohort study from fetal life until young adulthood. The Generation R Study was designed to identify early environmental and genetic determinants of growth, development, and health and has previously been described in detail (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022034512440450">Jaddoe <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022034512440450">2010</xref>). Briefly, the cohort included 9,778 mothers and their children living in Rotterdam, the Netherlands. Enrollment of mothers occurred in their early pregnancy (gestational age &lt; 18 wks). All children were born between April 2002 and January 2006 and formed a prenatally enrolled birth-cohort. Of all eligible children in the study area, 61% were enrolled in the study at birth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022034512440450">Jaddoe <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). The Medical Ethics Committee of the Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam, approved the study. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p>
<p>For the post-natal phase of the study, 7,893 children were available. About half of the mothers (51.0%) and the children were of Dutch origin (54.8%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022034512440450">Jaddoe <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). At the age of 5 to 6 yrs, the children were invited for a check-up visit at the Erasmus Medical Center. From March 2008 until November 2011, 154 children (77 twins) visited the Erasmus Medical Center. As part of this visit, intra-oral photographs of the teeth were made, which was successfully done in 6,161 children (95.0%). In cases where a few teeth could not be scored, only the teeth visible on the photographs were used in the analysis. A flowchart of the participants is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0022034512440450">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0022034512440450" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Flowchart of the participants.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512440450-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0022034512440450">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>After teeth were brushed, photographs of clean and moist teeth were taken by trained nurses and dental students (excess saliva was removed with a cotton roll). It took 1-2 min to take approximately 10 photographs of all teeth of the child. For this purpose, an intra-oral camera was used [Poscam USB intra-oral autofocus camera (Digital Leader PointNix), 640 × 480 pixels]. An example of such a photograph is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0022034512440450">Fig. 2</xref>. The minimal scene illumination was f 1.4 and 30 lx. In an earlier study, the validity of this camera for visualizing DMH was shown to be high (sensitivity 72.3% and specificity 92.8%). The reliability was good for inter-observer agreement (kappa 0.62) and excellent for intra-observer agreement (kappa 0.95) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0022034512440450" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Tooth 26 (1st permanent molar upper left) showing MIH (yellow opacity) and tooth 65 (2nd primary molar upper left) showing DMH (yellow opacity and post-eruptive enamel loss).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512440450-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>DMH and MIH were scored on the intra-oral photographs according to the EAPD criteria (see Appendix) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>If the tooth, or the place where the tooth should be, was not shown on the photographs, the tooth was scored as ‘not able to be judged’. A first permanent molar or a second primary molar was diagnosed as having MIH or DMH when at least one of these criteria or a combination was found. If in a child one or more DMH molars were scored as severe, the child was scored as having a severe form of DMH.</p>
<p>On the photographs, the number of shed teeth was also measured (for criteria, see Appendix).</p>
<p>The photographs were shown on a computer in full-screen mode and were scored by one calibrated dentist (ME). To test the interobserver agreement in this study, another calibrated dentist (JV) independently scored the data for 648 children. The Cohen’s kappa score in this study for DMH was 0.60 and for MIH 0.69. In the event of disagreement, the photographs were studied again and a joint consensus decision made. A separate group of 649 children was scored again by the first dentist (ME), at least 6 wks after the first scoring. The intra-observer agreement reached the following Cohen’s kappa scores: 0.82 (DMH) and 0.85 (MIH).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0022034512440450">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>Statistical analyses were made with SPSS version 18.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). To test if children with DMH also had MIH more often, the odds ratio was computed (logistic regression analysis).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0022034512440450" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>From the 6,487 participating children, in 95.0% a good series of photographs was made, in 2.9% only one photograph was made, and in 2.1% no photographs were made. In this study, on a child level the data from 6161 children were used (49.8% girls; mean age 74.3 mos, SD ± 6.1). On tooth level, the data from 5,561 children could be used for DMH diagnosis and from 2,327 children for MIH diagnosis, mostly due to limitations in the judging of individual teeth. The prevalence of DMH was 9.0% (n = 499) and of MIH was 8.7% (n = 203) at child level. Of all eligible second primary molars (n = 23,722), DMH was present in 4.0% (n = 955) of the teeth, and of all eligible first permanent molars (n = 6,545), MIH was present in 5.4% (n = 355). Most children with DMH had a severe form of DMH (302 out of 499). Of the children with DMH, 76.6% (n = 382) had opacities, 31.9% (n = 159) post-eruptive enamel loss, 14.6% (n = 73) atypical caries, 19.4% (n = 97) atypical fillings, and 11.2% (n = 56) atypical extractions. Often children had only 1 molar affected; the mean number of affected molars <italic>per</italic> child was 1.9 for DMH and 1.7 for MIH. These results are described in more detail in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512440450">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0022034512440450" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of DMH and MIH at Child Level and Tooth Level</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0022034512440450" xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512440450-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Distribution</th>
<th align="center">DMH n (%)</th>
<th align="center">MIH n (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Children</td>
<td>499/5,561 (9.0%)</td>
<td>203/2,327 (8.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Molars</td>
<td>955/23722 (4.0%)</td>
<td>355/6,545 (5.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of affected molars <italic>per</italic> child <italic>per</italic> dentition</td>
<td>DMH n = 499</td>
<td>MIH n = 203</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> One molar</td>
<td>216 (43.3%)</td>
<td>105 (51.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Two molars</td>
<td>157 (31.5%)</td>
<td>59 (29.1%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Three molars</td>
<td>79 (15.8%)</td>
<td>24 (11.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Four molars</td>
<td>47 (9.4%)</td>
<td>15 (7.4%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean number of affected molars (SD)</td>
<td>1.9 (1.0)</td>
<td>1.7 (0.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Severity of hypomineralization</td>
<td>DMH n = 499</td>
<td>MIH</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mild</td>
<td>197 (39.5%)</td>
<td>Not scored</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Severe</td>
<td>302 (60.5%)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Affected molars <italic>per</italic> quadrant</td>
<td>DMH n = 955</td>
<td>MIH n = 355</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Maxillary right</td>
<td>245 (4.1%)</td>
<td>96 (5.0%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Maxillary left</td>
<td>221 (3.7%)</td>
<td>87 (4.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mandibular left</td>
<td>265 (4.5%)</td>
<td>92 (6.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mandibular right</td>
<td>224 (3.8%)</td>
<td>80 (6.0%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Children with DMH in more than 1 molar had a higher odds ratio of developing MIH molars when compared with children with only 1 molar affected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022034512440450">Table 2</xref>). The odds ratio seemed to increase when more molars were affected with DMH, and for children with 3 DMH molars, the odds ratio was lower (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022034512440450">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0022034512440450" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of DMH in Children with and without MIH</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0022034512440450" xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512440450-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Without Selection</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">One or More 1<sup>st</sup> Permanent Molars Erupted and All Molars Able to Be Judged</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">All 4 1<sup>st</sup> Permanent Molars Erupted and All Molars Able to Be Judged</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Children without MIH (n = 2,124)</th>
<th align="center">Children with MIH (n = 203)</th>
<th align="center">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="center">Children without MIH (n = 1,748)</th>
<th align="center">Children with MIH (n = 138)</th>
<th align="center">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="center">Children without MIH (n = 799)</th>
<th align="center">Children with MIH (n = 57)</th>
<th align="center">OR (95% CI)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No DMH molars</td>
<td>1742</td>
<td>154</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>1,639</td>
<td>106</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>758</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>Reference</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One or more molars with DMH</td>
<td>136</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>4.4 (3.1-6.4)</td>
<td>109</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>4.2 (2.7-6.6)</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2.8 (1.2-6.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One molar with DMH</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>3.9 (2.3-6.8)</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3.8 (1.9-7.5)</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4.8 (1.5-15.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Two molars with DMH</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>5.4 (3.0-10.0)</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>5.3 (2.6-10.8)</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3.1 (0.9-11.0) ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Three molars with DMH</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>4.1 (1.7-9.8)</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>3.4 (1.1-10.3)</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2.2 (0.3-18.3) ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Four molars with DMH</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>6.1 (2.6-14.3)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>6.6 (2.5-17.6)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0 (0-0) ns</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Of the children with DMH, 49 (26.5%) children were also diagnosed as having MIH. Children with DMH had an odds ratio (OR) of 4.4 (95% CI: 3.1-6.4) for MIH compared with children without DMH. Analysis on tooth level did not show statistically significant differences.</p>
<p>Children with mild DMH (n = 197) had an odds ratio (OR) of 5.3 (95% CI: 2.9-9.4), and children with severe DMH had an odds ratio (OR) of 4.0 (95% CI: 2.6-6.3).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0022034512440450" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The prevalence of DMH found in this group was higher than the prevalence previously reported for 5-year-olds in the Netherlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The prevalence of MIH was in line with earlier studies performed in the Netherlands and abroad (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0022034512440450">Jasulaityte <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022034512440450">Jälevik, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>This paper is the first to present data on the relationship between DMH and MIH, showing that patients with DMH have an odds ratio of 4.4 for developing MIH. There is a tendency that odds ratios increase when the number of DMH-affected molars goes up. Caution must be taken, since the number of children with 3 or 4 DMH-affected molars are rather small, resulting in considerably large confidence intervals.</p>
<p>Most DMH-affected molars were scored as ‘severe’, meaning that they not only had opacities but also showed post-eruptive enamel loss, atypical restoration, or atypical caries, or had been extracted. The age of the children probably influenced the severity. At the age of 5 or 6, the second primary molars have been in function for 3-4 yrs, thus increasing the likelihood of enamel breakdown or caries. The difference in odds ratio found between the children with mild and those with severe DMH is interesting. This difference can possibly be explained by the onset and period of influence of possible etiological factors. When the onset is early, the second primary molar is most actively formed (see Appendix). When the onset of the causative factor is later, the maturation in the second primary molar is already at a later stage, and the influence is less. In the first permanent molar, in contrast, the maturation process is more active and more influenced by the etiological factor(s).</p>
<p>For the results to be appreciated, some limitations need to be discussed. The percentages of mothers from different ethnicities and lower socio-economic status were lower among the participants than expected from the population figures in Rotterdam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022034512440450">Jaddoe <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>).The trend toward a more affluent and healthy population might influence the generalizability of the results.</p>
<p>The inter- and intra-observer agreements were adequate for DMH, but good agreement was found for the interobserver agreement for MIH. The Cohen’s kappa scores for DMH were similar to those found in the previous study for interobserver agreement, but were somewhat lower for the intra-observer agreement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). After the photographs were discussed with no initial disagreement, agreement was reached in all cases. Most discussions arose concerning partly erupted first permanent molars.</p>
<p>In some of these young children, it was difficult to take the photographs. Unsuccessful pictures were generally seen in cases where the children were not able to breathe nasally, <italic>e.g</italic>., from common colds, thus creating moisture on the lens of the camera. Due to the limited numbers of missing photographs, the results are considered representative.</p>
<p>In the present study, DMH was scored on intra-oral photographs, while in previous studies, DMH was scored clinically. The difference in prevalence of DMH between this study and a previous study in the Netherlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512440450">Elfrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>) should not be attributed to the scoring method, because the validity and reliability of scoring DMH on intra-oral photographs were good.</p>
<p>The second primary molar and first permanent molar have a shared period of development and mineralization (see Appendix 1), and an observed relationship between DMH and MIH has already been hypothesized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). The development of the second primary molar and the first permanent molar start at the same time, but the maturation phase of the permanent molar is considerably longer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022034512440450">Butler, 1967</xref>). If a risk factor occurred during this overlapping period, hypomineralization might occur in the primary as well as in the permanent dentition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0022034512440450">Aine <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>A genetic predisposition for hypomineralization or a chronic or frequent recurrent disease within a particular time span, instead of only one risk factor, might affect, first, the second primary molars and, later, the first permanent molars.</p>
<p>Because the second primary molars erupt 4 yrs earlier in life than first permanent molars, DMH might clinically be used as an indicator for MIH. Whether this will lead to clinical consequences such as more tooth destruction or pain in deciduous teeth is subject to further research. If MIH can be diagnosed as early as possible, a greater effect of preventive measures (<italic>e.g</italic>., fluoride applications and CPP-ACP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0022034512440450">Lygidakis <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>) can be expected.</p>
<p>The relationship between DMH and MIH found in this study is an additional tool in the study of possible etiological factors such as exposure to dioxins from breastfeeding, antibiotic use, perinatal problems, infectious diseases, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022034512440450">Alaluusua <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512440450">1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0022034512440450">Whatling and Fearne, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0022034512440450">Laisi <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>), because they might lead to both DMH and MIH.</p>
<p>MIH-affected molars are typically in need of restoration soon after eruption, and they may cause pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512440450">Weerheijm <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022034512440450">Jälevik and Klingberg 2002</xref>). Therefore, in clinical practice, extra attention needs to be paid to children with DMH in the period when their permanent molars and incisors are erupting, given their increased risk of having MIH. The use of DMH as a predictor for MIH could help with this important early diagnosis.</p>
<p>This study shows an association between the prevalence of DMH and MIH in 5- to 6-year-old children. This relationship suggests a shared cause and indicates that, especially, mild DMH can clinically be used as an indicator for MIH.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>The Generation R Study was conducted by the Erasmus MC in close collaboration with the Erasmus University Rotterdam, School of Law and Faculty of Social Sciences, the Municipal Health Service Rotterdam area, Rotterdam, the Rotterdam Homecare Foundation, Rotterdam, and the Stichting Trombosedienst &amp; Artsenlaboratorium Rijnmond (STAR), Rotterdam. We gratefully acknowledge the contribution of general practitioners, hospitals, midwives, and pharmacies in Rotterdam. The first phase of the Generation R Study was made possible by financial support from the Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, Erasmus University Rotterdam, and the Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development (ZonMw).</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="supported-by">
<p>The present study was supported by an additional and unrestricted grant from <grant-sponsor>GABA</grant-sponsor>, Therwil, Switzerland.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="supplementary-material">
<p>A supplemental appendix to this article is published electronically only at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jdr.sagepub.com/supplemental">http://jdr.sagepub.com/supplemental</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Backström</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mäki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuusela</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koivisto</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ikonen</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Enamel defects in primary and permanent teeth of children born prematurely</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>-<lpage>409</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alaluusua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lukinmaa</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koskimies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pirinen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holtta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kallio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Developmental dental defects associated with long breast feeding</article-title>. <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source> <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>497</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alaluusua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lukinmaa</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torppa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tuomisto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vartiainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Developing teeth as biomarker of dioxin exposure</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>353</volume>:<fpage>206</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <article-title>Comparison of the development of the second deciduous molar and first permanent molar in man</article-title>. <source>Arch Oral Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1245</fpage>-<lpage>1260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elfrink</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalsbeek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Caries pattern in primary molars in Dutch 5-year-old children</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elfrink</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schuller</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weerheijm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Hypomineralized second primary molars: prevalence data in Dutch 5-year-olds</article-title>. <source>Caries Res</source> <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>282</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elfrink</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aartman</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>ten Cate</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Validity of scoring caries and primary molar hypomineralization (DMH) on intraoral photographs</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source> <issue>10</issue>(<supplement>Suppl 1</supplement>):<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elfrink</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schuller</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poorterman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>ten Cate</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Factors increasing the caries risk of second primary molars in 5-year-old Dutch children</article-title>. <source>Int J Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fearne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>3D x-ray microscopic study of the extent of variations in enamel density in first permanent molars with idiopathic enamel hypomineralisation</article-title>. <source>Br Dent J</source> <volume>196</volume>:<fpage>634</fpage>-<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gizani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vinckier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Declerck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Caries pattern and oral health habits in 2- to 6-year-old children exhibiting differing levels of caries</article-title>. <source>Clin Oral Investig</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The pattern of caries in a group of 5-year-old children and in the same cohort at 9 years of age</article-title>. <source>Community Dent Health</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaddoe</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackenbach</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steegers</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tiemeier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verhulst</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The Generation R Study: design and cohort profile</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>475</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaddoe</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Duijn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackenbach</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steegers</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). The Generation R Study: design and cohort update <year>2010</year>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>-<lpage>841</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jälevik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Prevalence and diagnosis of molar-incisor-hypomineralisation (MIH): a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jälevik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klingberg</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Dental treatment, dental fear and behaviour management problems in children with severe enamel hypomineralization of their permanent first molars</article-title>. <source>Int J Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jälevik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norén</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Enamel hypomineralization of permanent first molars: a morphological study and survey of possible aetiological factors</article-title>. <source>Int J Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>-<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jasulaityte</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weerheijm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). Prevalence of molar-incisor-hypomineralisation among children participating in the Dutch National Epidemiological Survey (<year>2003</year>). <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>-<lpage>223</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laisi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ess</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sahlberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arvio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lukinmaa</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alaluusua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Amoxicillin</article-title> <month>may</month> <article-title>cause molar incisor hypomineralization</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source> <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lygidakis</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jälevik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vierrou</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alaluusua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Espelid</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Best clinical practice guidance for clinicians dealing with children presenting with Molar-Incisor-Hypomineralisation (MIH): an EAPD Policy Document</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Profitt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Contemporary orthodontics</article-title>. <source>St</source>. <publisher-loc>Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weerheijm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Molar incisor hypomineralisation (MIH)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weerheijm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beentjes</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poorterman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of cheese molars in eleven-year-old Dutch children</article-title>. <source>ASDC J Dent Child</source> <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>, <fpage>229</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weerheijm</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mejàre</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papagiannoulis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Judgement criteria for molar incisor hypomineralisation (MIH) in epidemiologic studies: a summary of the European meeting on MIH held in Athens, 2003</article-title>. <source>Eur J Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whatling</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fearne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Molar incisor hypomineralization: a study of aetiological factors in a group of UK children</article-title>. <source>Int J Paediatr Dent</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0022034512440450">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>William</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burrow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Molar incisor hypomineralization: review and recommendations for clinical management</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Dent</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>