<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spemr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Emotion Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1754-0739</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1754-0747</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1754073911421391</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1754073911421391</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special Section: Empathy</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comment: Empathy and Participation—A Response to Fritz Breithaupt’s Three-Person Model of Empathy</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Söffner</surname><given-names>Jan Georg</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1754073911421391">Internationales Kolleg Morphomata, Universität zu Köln, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1754073911421391">Jan Georg Söffner, Internationales Kolleg Morphomata, Universität zu Köln, Albertus-Magnus-Platz, 50923 Köln, Germany. <italic>Email</italic>: <email>reliquienbueste@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>94</fpage>
<lpage>95</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© ISRE and SAGE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">ISRE and SAGE</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Fritz Breithaupt’s “Three-Person Model of Empathy” (2012) offers a brilliant approach to relate empathy to side-taking. By thereby grounding empathy in subjective observation though, it becomes difficult to focus on how empathy interferes with phenomena of shared and embedded activity. This comment therefore raises the question of how Breithaupt’s theory of empathy can be related to phenomena of participatory sense-making and second-person interaction.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>empathy</kwd>
<kwd>participatory sense-making</kwd>
<kwd>second-person interaction</kwd>
<kwd>sympathy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In its literal and etymological meaning, the word empathy is not very clear about its object: Is empathy just about putting oneself into the shoes of others, or is it also about establishing a feeling relation with objects or the surrounding world? When <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1754073911421391">Edward B. Titchener (1909)</xref> retranslated the German term “<italic>Einfühlung</italic>” as “empathy” (the Ancient Greek <italic>empatheia</italic> means “affection” or “passion”), it still held much of the Romantic implication of building up a felt relation with an aesthetic phenomenon (such as a work of art). Only in recent usage has the term been limited to questions of understanding other persons.</p>
<p>The advantage of this limited usage of the term is clear: It allows for precise questions about how we emotionally understand others approached either in terms of “theory theory (TT)” (understanding others by building mental models of them) or “simulation theory (ST)” (understanding others by subliminally simulating them), not in terms of “interaction theory (IT)” (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1754073911421391">Gallagher &amp; Zahavi, 2007</xref>). This limitation makes for a highly convincing and neat definition of empathy. But three kinds of liminal phenomena also raise the question of how “feeling oneself into” other persons relates to other forms of “feeling oneself into” the surrounding world, and how important henomena on the verge of empathy yet do not exactly converge with concepts of taking another person’s perspective. These three liminal phenomena are: (a) transitional objects (e.g., a child feeling empathy for and interacting with a teddy bear—cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1754073911421391">Winnicott, 1971</xref>, pp. 1–25); (b) swarm phenomena (e.g., mass panic uniting a group of individuals in a shared emotion and action); and (c) cooperation with assigned roles (e.g., three people washing dishes together). If we consider the fact that emotions can be considered intrinsic evaluations or better—orientations of human activity, these liminal phenomena become extremely important. Accordingly, in the first case it is obvious that empathy with persons and empathy with objects can take place on very similar scales—empathy here seems to be a way of constructing the object as another “person,” rather than being an effect of such a construction. The second case shows that empathy can be felt within a shared situation, and not only with a singular person. The third case indicates that feeling empathy in an interaction might have a shared focus instead of separating into personal perspectives: enactivist thinkers (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1754073911421391">De Jaegher &amp; Di Paolo, 2007</xref>) would argue that, to grasp the plate in the right moment to dry it, one feels within the intrinsic logic of the interaction rather than putting oneself into the shoes of the other. Accordingly, the mentioned phenomena imply that emotions are not necessarily bound to a subjective perspective: Their focus is shared, participatory, and interactive rather than being bound to the divergent stances of self and other. And thereby they raise the question opposed to the question of how we feel ourselves into other persons: How do we feel ourselves out of a shared interactive emotionality and gain or take perspectives?</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1754073911421391">Fritz Breithaupt (2012)</xref> raises the related question of how empathy in the person-based meaning of the word <italic>arises</italic>—and offers a highly interesting and persuasive answer. He starts with the empathetic person as an observer rather than a participant. If one understands empathy as putting oneself into the shoes of somebody else, a clear delineation between two persons is required; the other person must be opaque to the feeler of empathy. This requires distinct perception of a self and other; it therefore requires observation instead of enactive embeddedness. Empathy accordingly requires a state wherein the “problem of other minds” occurs. This leads either to “hot empathy,” due to simulation of the other (ST), or “cold empathy,” due to theory building about the other (TT). Accordingly, empathy is grounded in the relation between first-person feelings and third-person observation, avoiding second-person interaction or IT. In making his point, Breithaupt brilliantly grounds empathy in a triangular constellation. Instead of describing empathy as taking place in an immediate two-person interaction, he explains it as an effect or aspect of side-taking rather than partaking; empathy requires a judgment made from outside rather than one intrinsic in shared interaction (as would be intrinsic in taking a plate, referring to the earlier example).</p>
<p>To accordingly make conflict rather than cooperation the core aspect of empathy might, at first glance, seem a weakness of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1754073911421391">Breithaupt’s (2012)</xref> theory, as evolutionary anthropology increasingly agrees that the human species is highly cooperative, and that this cooperativeness is the prime ground for and effect of language and culture. Nevertheless, this complementary premise allows for understanding the divergent aspects of empathy as sympathetic compassion on the one hand and <italic>schadenfreude</italic> on the other.</p>
<p>This is highly convincing for the narrow term of empathy. But, to return to the broader and etymological meaning of the word, the argument does not thoroughly account for phenomena of participatory sense-making, shared interaction, swarm phenomena, or interaction with transitional objects. Making a teddy bear live works through the interaction with it and it requires much more than side-taking. And to give another example: Breithaupt’s account is extraordinarily fruitful for explaining how the emotional perception of a soccer match changes from the moment the spectator takes sides and feels positively for one team and negatively against the other. On the other hand, a different, participatory dimension of feeling with others that can only be described in terms of IT seems very important as well. It seems to be extremely important, for example, for describing the shared and swarm-like behavior of soccer fans (and the common emotion organizing this swarm), or the cooperative feelings addressed in team building and required for the coordinated interaction of a team.</p>
<p>Future exploration might focus on how <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1754073911421391">Breithaupt’s (2012)</xref> three-person model of empathy and the model of emotional cooperation and participation intersect, interfere with, or imply each other. Evidently, the latter concept needs a new term; etymologically speaking, this term would be sympathy, “feeling with” instead of “feeling (oneself) into.” However, the shift in the meaning of “sympathy” itself undermines its application in this context.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1754073911421391">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breithaupt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A three-person model of empathy</article-title>. <source>Emotion Review</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1754073911421391">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Jaegher</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di Paolo</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Participatory sense-making: An enactive approach to social cognition</article-title>. <source>Phenomenology and the Cognitive Sciences</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1754073911421391">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zahavi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>The phenomenal mind—An introduction to phenomenology and philosophy of mind</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1754073911421391">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Titchener</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1909</year>). <source>Lectures on the experimental psychology of thought processes</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1754073911421391">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winnicott</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <source>Playing and reality</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>