<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppia</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part A: Journal of Power and Energy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0957-6509</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2967</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0957650911424025</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0957650911424025</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The importance of flow and turbulence characteristics for hydrokinetic energy development on the Tanana River at Nenana, Alaska</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0957650911424025">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fochesatto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0957650911424025">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Toniolo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0957650911424025">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0957650911424025">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0957650911424025"><label>1</label>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of Alaska Fairbanks, Fairbanks, Alaska, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0957650911424025"><label>2</label>Department of Atmospheric Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks, Fairbanks, Alaska, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0957650911424025">*Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of Alaska Fairbanks, PO Box 755900, Fairbanks, AK 99775-5900, USA. email: <email>hatoniolo@alaska.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>299</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Authors 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The site selection for the installation of hydrokinetic devices along a river reach is an issue of fundamental importance. While it is acknowledged that multiple factors such as accessibility, navigation, safety, and hydraulics, among many others, must be considered in the final decision, this article focuses on the influence of river morphology on turbulence flow parameters. Specifically, continuous high-resolution velocity measurements from a hydrokinetic resource assessment on the Tanana River near Nenana in the interior of Alaska are analysed to estimate, kinetic energy (KE), turbulent kinetic energy (TKE) as well as KE partition at particular locations. To accomplish these tasks, two different methods used to rotate the coordinate systems into the main flow direction are correlated and compared in order to extract the turbulent parameters from the main flow. The coordinate system methods include the streamline coordinate rotation and the extraction of statistical fluctuations from the average flow. The streamline coordinate rotation method is chosen to extract the TKE in temporal series. The calculated TKE was up to 30 per cent of the total flow KE in measurements located in pools and dissipated downstream, beyond the highly turbulent locations of bathymetric depressions and river bends. The overall KE increased over a bed free of major macro-obstacles and reduced depth, where the TKE fraction accounted for only 2 per cent of the total KE. The visualizations of the KE and TKE are compared with the river morphology, leading to identification of helical flow, flow separation, and turbulent flow structures along the river bend and in pools to help the decision-making process in hydrokinetic planning.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>turbulence</kwd>
<kwd>kinetic energy</kwd>
<kwd>helical flow</kwd>
<kwd>detachment</kwd>
<kwd>vortex tube development</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0957650911424025"><title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>Much analysis is done in engineering and hydraulic work with the average velocity values from acoustic Doppler current profiler (ADCP) measurements. However, useful flow information on small-scale turbulent flow structures is not retained when the data are not fully detailed in space and time. Fluctuations in velocity magnitude, velocity direction, associated kinetic energy (KE), and turbulent kinetic energy (TKE) are not fully visualized when average values are considered. Thus, it is important to include the temporal analysis and the energy distribution of flow measurements when designing river structures and location of hydrokinetic turbines. If the infrastructure is not designed to withstand the fluctuating river energy, the hydraulic structures and river turbines may not perform as designed.</p>
<p>Dynamic perturbations such as eddies occurring in a timescale from seconds to minutes can easily be observed on the free water surface in natural (stream) and artificial (flume) settings. These fluctuations provide insight to the macro-turbulence characteristics and associated energy fluctuations where turbulent flow structures accelerate and decelerate in time. Previous turbulence research hasincluded three regions of depth that include the free surface, bulk of fluid, and wall or bottom regions [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650911424025">1</xref></bold>]. Short-timescale turbulent flow structures are developed in the form of bursts of the fluctuating flow energy due to interactions with the bed morphology within the bottom region. These bursts migrate upwards towards the free surface introducing deviation in the flow streamline and introducing mixing on the flow interface through sweeps and ejections [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650911424025">2</xref></bold>]. Generally, with simple morphology, the bottom region closest to the boundary (i.e. river bed) will typically contain most of the turbulent structures [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650911424025">1</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650911424025">3</xref></bold>]. Nevertheless, it is possible to observe turbulence located within the bulk-of-fluid region. These low-frequency oscillations can be developed upstream the measurement location from flow–bed interactions and can be transported along the entire water column.</p>
<p>This article presents the methodologies of processing ADCP data for turbulence analysis, which in turn can improve the site selection for the installation of hydrokinetic devices along a river reach. It provides analysis of the flow/surface interactions within the approximate 15 min recording time of this study. The timescale of turbulent processes observed in this study ranges from scales of seconds to minutes. This study represents a continuation on the turbulence analysis previously reported by Toniolo <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>]. The assessment of energy partition (turbulent/mean) flow KE can in fact be useful as a decision element upon different available choices in hydrokinetic devices. The selection of any type of hydrokinetic devices is beyond the scope of this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0957650911424025"><title>2 STUDY SITE</title>
<p>The study site is located on the Tanana River at Nenana, Alaska (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0957650911424025">Fig. 1</xref>). The Tanana River is a braided river that is initially fed by numerous glaciers in the Alaska Range. Its headwaters begin near Northway, Alaska, flowing northwest to eventually join with the Yukon River near Tanana, Alaska. The Tanana River contains high amounts of suspended sediment load carried from its glacial headwaters. At the site location, the river is a single channel. Additional details on the study site were reported by Toniolo <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>].
<fig id="fig1-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study site: Tanana river near Nenana</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0957650911424025"><title>3 AVAILABLE DATA AND BACKGROUND ON ADCP RIVER MEASUREMENTS</title>
<sec id="sec4-0957650911424025"><title>3.1 Available data</title>
<p>The velocity measurements used in this study were recorded by ADCPs during late August of 2009 for a project focused on hydrokinetic resource assessment [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>]. Twelve locations of stationary ADCP data along six transects were recorded for approximately 15 min. These transects were separated by approximately 200 m of distance, beginning with transect 000 (upstream end) and ending with transect 1100 (downstream end). The ADCP units were moored on the river bottom looking skyward. The units recorded velocity data between the free surface and 1 m above the river bed. The instruments were configured to a high sampling rate (i.e. 1.6 Hz sampling rate), with minimal averaging, 2 pings. The instrument configuration, the recording time, and the river characteristics circumvent any spectral aliasing features. In addition to the ADCP measurements, a bathymetric survey was completed in August 2009 [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>]. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650911424025">Figure 2</xref> shows the ADCP locations and the contour map generated from the bathymetric survey.
<fig id="fig2-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Contour map of bathymetric data with ADCP locations</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>At each transect, river velocity data were recorded in two points: (a) the thalweg, which represents the deepest point in each river cross-section and (b) the maximum velocity outside the thalweg. The thalweg typically did not contain the maximum current velocity within each transect. The following nomenclature was used: ### identifies transect and ###-Max or ###-Thalweg describe the particular location of each measurement (i.e. maximum or thalweg points in a given transect).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0957650911424025"><title>3.2 ADCP background</title>
<p>ADCPs are very powerful instruments used in open channel engineering, allowing a column of river velocity to be recorded at high frequency without the disruption of the water column. As the availability of ADCP technology increases, the need for methodologies that provide access to turbulent variables in rivers become necessary [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650911424025">5</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650911424025">6</xref></bold>]. For instance, bed scour by particle saltation and suspension in highly turbulent areas is part of the process of thalweg migration and channel meandering [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957650911424025">7</xref></bold>]. Therefore, accurate turbulence data quantification could help predict future channel evolution. ADCP recordings have been analysed using statistical tools; yet, the statistical applications of the data are limited to either average values or a single-depth time series in the ADCP profile [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650911424025">2</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650911424025">6</xref></bold>]. Adhering to this type of methodology creates a crossroads of either calculating turbulence parameters from velocity averages orfocusing on a particular depth. This limits the ability to analyse turbulent interactions and scales throughout the entire depth.</p>
<p>ADCP river studies generally have a different recording time and recording frequency depending on what features are to be analysed. High sampling rates provide information across the turbulent spectrum (i.e. including the inertial subrange), while low sampling rates record the mean flow motion without any particular information about turbulent eddies. On the other hand, the time length of the data collection will provide the opportunity to measure the contribution of eddies in the turbulent spectra (e.g. subinertial range) and for extended periods of time it can provide information of the flow injection of energy and momentum. Optimum recording times have been previously identified, but they are considered for particular sites and they adhere to statistical methods [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650911424025">5</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650911424025">6</xref></bold>].</p>
<p>The ADCPs themselves have their disadvantages, which includes Doppler noise and other backscatter phenomenon. Near-bed ADCP measurements commonly require despiking followed by data smoothing [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957650911424025">8</xref></bold>]. As the recording frequency of ADCPs increases, the Doppler noise increases as well.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0957650911424025"><title>4 METHODOLOGY</title>
<sec id="sec7-0957650911424025"><title>4.1 Data collection</title>
<p>At each ADCP location (12 along the river reach), the instrument was moored on the river bed which recorded approximately 15 min of velocity components in three directions. The Teledyne RDI Rio Grande 1200 kHz model instrument used in the data collection was configured at a sampling rate period of 0.6 s. This ADCP model previously yielded good results for similar studies [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650911424025">6</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650911424025">9</xref></bold>]. The instruments recorded north (<italic>u</italic>), east (<italic>v</italic>), and vertical (<italic>w</italic>) components of the flow velocity. Raw velocity data were downloaded from the ADCP; no processing was done using internal ADCP firmware. The vertical resolution (here indicated as bin) was 0.25 m, with the first data point located at 1 m above the river bottom [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>]. In this study, a Savitzky–Golay smoothing filter was applied [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957650911424025">10</xref></bold>].</p>
<p>Past research has shown that as the depth of the river increases, it is important to extend the ADCP recording time. Sukhodolov <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650911424025">2</xref></bold>], using the SI system, reported that temporal scales for sweeps and ejections were in some cases up to 1.5 times the flow depth. The Tanana River in this section is over 15 m deep. Therefore, the recording interval (approximately 15 min) was appropriated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0957650911424025"><title>4.2 Average flow conditions</title>
<p>The initial techniques used to quantify the ADCP data involved computing average values of flow magnitude, TKE, and horizontal and vertical flow angles. These averages provide a general indication of the recorded flow characteristics that include the main flow and its fluctuations. The average values can also provide supporting evidence for flow characteristics such as helical flow and outer-bank downwelling. The majority of the published open channel research studies on ADCP data use averaged depth profiles as a foundation for further analysis [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650911424025">11</xref></bold>–<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650911424025">13</xref></bold>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0957650911424025"><title>4.3 Kinetic energy</title>
<p>Analysis of the average kinetic energy (AKE), which is defined in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0957650911424025">equation (1)</xref>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0957650911424025"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>u</italic>(<italic>k</italic>), <italic>v</italic>(<italic>k</italic>), and <italic>w</italic>(<italic>k</italic>) are the instantaneous velocities in the north, east, and vertical directions, respectively, <italic>T</italic> the recording period, and <italic>k</italic> an instantaneous sample. AKE in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0957650911424025">equation (1)</xref> provides a general understanding of the total flow. However, more information about KE fluctuation in time is provided when the flow quantities are temporally displayed over the entire recording time. The KE is introduced in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0957650911424025">equation (2)</xref>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0957650911424025"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0957650911424025"><title>4.4 Coordinate rotation</title>
<p>To analyse the turbulent quantities exclusively, a main flow direction must be defined and it must be removed to analyse the fluctuations from the main flow [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>]. In particular, two different methods were applied to extract the turbulent quantities: (a) the statistical mean (Method 1) and (b) the coordinaterotation (Method 2).</p>
<sec id="sec11-0957650911424025"><title>4.4.1 Method 1 – variation from the average</title>
<p>This statistical method is commonly used in open channel hydraulics. For hydraulic applications, see, for instance references [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>], [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650911424025">13</xref></bold>], and [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957650911424025">14</xref></bold>]. This methodology assumes a fixed orientation between the instrument’s Cartesian coordinate system and the associated flow velocities in <italic>u</italic>, <italic>v</italic>, and <italic>w</italic> or north, east, and up directions (corresponding to <italic>x</italic>-, <italic>y</italic>-, and <italic>z</italic>-axes). Fluctuations are calculated by subtracting the statistical average from each instantaneous velocity measurement. The equations used in this method take the following form
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0957650911424025"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0957650911424025"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0957650911424025"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="ilm1-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>  </mml:mi><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mi>  </mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the instantaneous velocity fluctuations. This method is generally accepted for steady flow conditions in a constant flow direction. However, it has limitations due to the fact that is bounded by a fixed Cartesian coordinate system and therefore does not consider changes in flow direction. This limitation is particularly important inareas containing high channel curvature and bathymetric depressions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0957650911424025"><title>4.4.2 Method 2 – Streamline coordinate rotation</title>
<p>Three-dimensional (3D) temporal flow analysis is commonly used in atmospheric sciences where the air flow direction is constantly changing [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650911424025">15</xref></bold>]. This method is usually known as streamline coordinate rotation and was developed to analyse air flow velocities to account for the effect of sloping terrain [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650911424025">15</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957650911424025">16</xref></bold>]. This method allows for the extraction of turbulent variables measured by the ADCP through a linear transformation projecting the 3D coordinate system of the instrument into the flow direction. After the linear transformation (i.e. coordinate rotation) is applied, the turbulent fluctuations can be calculated in the same way as Method 1 for each depth. By rotating into the direction of the main flow, the new system is not limited by the Cartesian coordinate system. The streamline coordinate rotation method allows the flow fluctuations to be compared where variations in average flow angles exist throughout the depth. The first step in this method is to calculate the horizontal average flow direction for each depth (given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0957650911424025">equation (6)</xref>). Next, the horizontal plane of the <italic>u</italic> and <italic>v</italic> velocities is rotated into the flow direction given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-0957650911424025">equations (7)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0957650911424025">8</xref>).
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0957650911424025"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0957650911424025"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0957650911424025"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0957650911424025"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
where θ is the angle of the main flow direction in the horizontal plane and <inline-formula id="ilm2-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <italic>w</italic><sub>1</sub> the intermediate components for the horizontal rotation of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0957650911424025">equations (6)</xref> through (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0957650911424025">9</xref>). The vertical velocity component, <italic>w</italic><sub>1</sub>, remains invariant in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0957650911424025">equations (5)</xref> through (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0957650911424025">9</xref>) because it is the axis of rotation. The second step isto rotate to the average flow direction in the verticaldirection. In this case, <italic>v</italic><sub>1</sub> remains invariant, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula12-0957650911424025">equation (12)</xref>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0957650911424025"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-0957650911424025"><label>(11)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0957650911424025"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0957650911424025"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
where ϕ is the main flow direction in the vertical plane which will be rotated to in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-0957650911424025">equations (10)</xref> through (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0957650911424025">13</xref>) and <inline-formula id="ilm3-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>and <italic>w</italic>′ the finalvalues where instantaneous fluctuations are calculated by repeating the procedure in Method 1.</p>
<p>In theory, if the main flow was travelling along the direction of <italic>u</italic>, only turbulent fluctuations would be recorded in the orthogonal axes <italic>v</italic> and <italic>w</italic>. In this condition, both methods provide the same results. In section 5, a comprehensive analysis by transects to correlate Methods 1 and 2 is presented.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0957650911424025"><title>4.5 Turbulent kinetic energy</title>
<p>The coordinate rotation (Method 2) has been applied to the data in order to remove the main flow quantity.The fluctuations from the main flow remain, allowing the analysis of the average turbulent kinetic energy (ATKE) and TKE
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0957650911424025"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-0957650911424025"><label>(15)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The ATKE in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula14-0957650911424025">equation (14)</xref> and the TKE in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0957650911424025">equation (15)</xref> are the basic magnitudes for characterizing turbulence [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650911424025">2</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650911424025">13</xref></bold>]. Method 1 was previously applied to the data [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>]. Here, Method 2 is applied because it provides a robust way of extracting peak fluctuations originated by changes in flow direction.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0957650911424025"><title>5 RESULTS</title>
<sec id="sec15-0957650911424025"><title>5.1 Bathymetric surface</title>
<p>The 12 ADCP locations are displayed on the contour map in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650911424025">Fig. 2</xref> where the maximum and thalweg velocities were recorded. The reader should note the differences in bathymetry between the locations. For instance, the locations of 000-Max and 000-Thalweg are in a pool roughly 14 m deep; 440-Thalweg is in a similar bathymetric configuration (i.e. pool) with a depth of 11 m. In general, the thalweg measurements are closer to the left bank and the maximum measurements to the right bank. However, at transect 1100, the locations of thalweg and maximum havechanged. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Figure 3(a)</xref> shows the longitudinal bathymetric profile of the thalweg, which contains large variations in depth along the river reach. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Figure 3(b)</xref> shows the longitudinal profile along the maximum locations. This profile presents similarities and differences with the profile along the thalweg. For instance, the deep pool at transect 000 is depicted in both graphs. A general trend of decreasing water depth is clearly shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Fig. 3(b)</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0957650911424025">Figure 4</xref> shows the cross-sectional areas along transects. The form drag generated by a bed configuration composed oflarge bedforms (i.e. pools) is high [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650911424025">17</xref></bold>], which is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Fig. 3(a)</xref>. Energy dissipated near bed forms is alsoseen in the flume experiments [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650911424025">3</xref></bold>]. When macro-bathymetric features (i.e. pools) disappear in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Fig. 3(b)</xref> beyond transect 000-Max, the form drag is reduced. Then, higher velocities and AKE in the maximum locations should be expected. The flow is also expected to develop helical characteristics and flow separation in the vicinity of pools.
<fig id="fig3-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Longitudinal bed profiles of thalweg and maximum ADCP locations: (a) thalweg; (b)maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig4-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>River cross-sections: (a) thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650911424025">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">3</xref>(b) indicate that maximum flow occurs across a streamlined bed profile in all points except 000-Max. In fact, transect 000 is very different when compared to the rest of the ADCP locations. Before 000, the river has just finished joining two braided channels around an island. One channel is finishing a bend of a 180° and 550 m radius corner, entering in flowing initially south, and the other channel is smaller and serpentine, flowing east upon entry. The flows join and travel around the corner and into our ADCP location (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0957650911424025">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0957650911424025"><title>5.2 Average flow angles, KE, and TKE conditions</title>
<p>The average horizontal flow angles from the north direction show that the deep thalweg pool and preceding river bend at transect 000 create a widely distributed main flow from the bed to the free surface(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650911424025">Fig. 5</xref>). The flows at 000-Thalweg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650911424025">Fig. 5(a)</xref>) and 000-Max (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650911424025">Fig. 5(b)</xref>) fluctuate in direction by 50° and 10°, respectively, from the lowest recorded depths to the free surface. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650911424025">Figure 6</xref> shows the averagevertical flow angles from the horizontal plane. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650911424025">Figure 6(b)</xref> shows that 000-Max has the greatest flow angle separation due to the fact that it is less confined by the deep thalweg contour of 000-Thalweg near the bottom region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0957650911424025">Fig. 4</xref>).
<fig id="fig5-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Average horizontal flow angle <italic>versus</italic> dimensionless depth: (a) thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Average vertical flow angle <italic>versus</italic> dimensionless depth: (a) thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The departure angles from horizontal are caused by helical flow at transect 000. Helical flow is the ‘cork-screw-like’ flow that is rotating in the plane that is transverse to the main flow. It is typically encountered during momentum transfer at meandering bends of open channel flow [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650911424025">18</xref></bold>], which develops transverse mixing beyond river bends. The comparison of the vertical −5° flow angle from horizontal at 000-Thalweg and the +9° angle at 000-Max defines a rotating flow in the <italic>v–w</italic> plane (rotated into main flow by Method 2). Previous flume research on helical flow observed increasing velocity towards the outer bank [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957650911424025">19</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650911424025">20</xref></bold>]. The AKE (which is derived from the velocity) increases at the outer bank of 000-Thalweg, supporting the behaviour described in references [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957650911424025">19</xref></bold>] and [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650911424025">20</xref></bold>]. The average vertical flow angle from horizontal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650911424025">Fig. 6</xref>) also shows that the greatest vertical departures are observed at transect 000 and 440-Thalweg. These areas contain both the deepest bathymetric depressions along the study reach.</p>
<p>Higher AKE in 000-Thalweg, which is near the outer bank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650911424025">Fig. 7(a)</xref>), supports the conditions of helical flow [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957650911424025">19</xref></bold>]. Van Balen <italic>et al</italic>. [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650911424025">20</xref></bold>] reported that areas ofriver bed helical flow are also areas where highbottom-region outer-bank ATKE is found. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650911424025">Figure 7(b)</xref> shows that all, but one (000-Max), profiles are similar. The figure also indicates that the maximum AKE is located at 800-Max. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650911424025">Figure 8(a)</xref> shows the high ATKE at 000-Thalweg due to the helical flow. Helical flow has also been reported [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650911424025">18</xref></bold>], which was identified as outer-bank downwelling. Like the name suggests, these researchers found that in areas of helical flow, the outer bank tended to have a negative deflected vertical flow angle. Thus, the negative average vertical flow angle in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650911424025">Fig. 6</xref> at 000-Thalweg agrees with the findings previously reported [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650911424025">18</xref></bold>]. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650911424025">Figure 8(b)</xref> shows limited development of ATKE in all transects with the exception of 000-Max. The AKE and ATKE in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650911424025">Figs 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650911424025">8</xref> are moderately high at transect 000. AKE is reduced from transect 000 to 440-Thalweg. Beyond the bathymetric depression at 440-Thalweg, the ATKE is dissipated and the AKE is increased.
<fig id="fig7-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>AKE: (a) thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig8-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>ATKE: (a) thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<sec id="sec17-0957650911424025"><title>5.2.1 Kinetic energy</title>
<p>In order to quantify fluctuations, the KE is analysed at each location (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650911424025">Fig. 9</xref>). The scales in the figures are different to facilitate the visualization of turbulent structures in each transect. A similar figure using a common scale is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ine.uaf.edu/temp/toniolo">http://ine.uaf.edu/temp/toniolo</ext-link>.
<fig id="fig9-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>KE distance from river bed <italic>versus</italic> recorded ADCP time. Non-uniform colour scale: (a)thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig9a.tif"/><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig9b.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>As defined earlier, previous turbulence research has included three regions that include: the free surface, bulk-of-fluid, and wall- or bottom regions. The maximum values of each transect were first analysed to identify flow characteristics from one ADCP recording to the next. KE events are oscillations at 000-Max, which are more random and separated compared to downstream measurements that typically contain KE event structures mainly in the bottom region. At 000-Max, the KE is distributed throughout the depth and separated in time. This is likely due to flow detachment from the morphology upstream from transect 000. Fluctuating KE exists inthe bulk-of-fluid region, as well as the free-surface, which follows slightly random sinusoidal-like patterns.</p>
<p>The occurrence of KE oscillations at 000-Max ranges from 0.17 to 1.36 min (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0957650911424025">Table 1</xref>). The maximumpeak-to-peak amplitude is approximately 0.6 (m<sup>2</sup>/s<sup>2</sup>)<italic>ρ</italic>, and the duration of a KE event is approximately 20–80 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650911424025">Fig. 9(b)</xref>). Moving downstream from 000-Max to 220-Max, the KE events do not originate in the bulk-of-fluid region as seen in 000-Max. From 000-Max to 220-Max, the KE magnitude is reduced. The turbulent structures identified in 220-Max are vertically developed in the entire water column. Similar flow fluctuations could be created by local bathymetric conditions. In the case of fluid physics, they are referred to as periodic boundary condition [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0957650911424025">21</xref></bold>]. The magnitude of KE events at 220-Max is much less than 000-Max, approximately 0.4 (m<sup>2</sup>/s<sup>2</sup>)<italic>ρ</italic>. The majority of events occur within the bottom half of the 5.60 m depth over a 1 min period. The approximate duration of higher KE events is 30–60 s. Large KE events are most apparent near the free surface at 440-Max, changing from 0.5 to 2.0 (m<sup>2</sup>/s<sup>2</sup>)<italic>ρ</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650911424025">Fig. 9(b)</xref>). The KE events are longer than upstream transects andits amplitude, 0.4 (m<sup>2</sup>/s<sup>2</sup>)<italic>ρ</italic>, is the greatest in themiddle of the 4.80 m depth. The Main-Max location is similar to 440-Max, but has larger structure groups of KE events. Some of these events last approximately 2 min.
<table-wrap id="table1-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>KE events</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0957650911424025" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Location</th>
<th rowspan="2">Recording time (min)</th>
<th rowspan="2">Number of events</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Time between events (min)<hr/></th>
<th rowspan="2">Recorded depth (m)</th>
<th rowspan="2">Average event magnitude (m<sup>2</sup>/s<sup>2</sup>)</th>
</tr>
<tr><th>Minimum</th>
<th>Average</th>
<th>Maximum</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>000-Thalweg</td>
<td>18.54</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>2.01</td>
<td>12.2</td>
<td>3.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>000-Max</td>
<td>16.60</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>1.36</td>
<td>13.6</td>
<td>1.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>220-Thalweg</td>
<td>19.65</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>6.7</td>
<td>1.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>220-Max</td>
<td>20.61</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.45</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>5.6</td>
<td>1.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>440-Thalweg</td>
<td>18.11</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>1.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>440-Max</td>
<td>15.86</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>4.8</td>
<td>1.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Main-Thalweg</td>
<td>20.84</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>7.4</td>
<td>1.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Main-Max</td>
<td>21.05</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>1.88</td>
<td>2.49</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>1.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>800-Thalweg</td>
<td>18.81</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1.43</td>
<td>2.13</td>
<td>2.84</td>
<td>6.4</td>
<td>1.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>800-Max</td>
<td>12.12</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1.21</td>
<td>2.35</td>
<td>2.72</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>2.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1100-Thalweg</td>
<td>11.97</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>2.12</td>
<td>4.51</td>
<td>7.2</td>
<td>2.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1100-Max</td>
<td>12.72</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>2.24</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>1.80</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Further downstream, at 800-Max and 1100-Max, the KE event frequency begins to dissipate as the duration of oscillations becomes longer and a typical boundary layer flow distribution is encountered [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650911424025">20</xref></bold>]. Beyond transect 800, the thalweg and max velocities intersect, switching sides of the river. The shallow wide cross-section where the thalweg is transitioning is typical of meandering rivers at the inflection point of river bends [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957650911424025">7</xref></bold>].</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0957650911424025">Figure 10</xref> indicates that the maximum KE is located at 000-Thalweg. High KE is sustained at the free surface and through the bulk-of-fluid regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650911424025">Fig.9(a)</xref>). The KE available at depths lower than 75per cent of the total water depth is reduced as the flow encounters form drag from the bed configuration [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650911424025">17</xref></bold>]. It can be reasonably assumed that KE events in the surface- and bulk-of-fluid regions are driven by the upstream flow.
<fig id="fig10-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Maximum KE events</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>A comparison of KE events at transect 000 (i.e. 000-Max and 000-Thalweg) indicates a different energy level in this area, especially above 4 m from the river bed. It is important to mention that these measurements are located approximately 15 m apart along the river cross-section. Downstream from 000-Thalweg to 220-Thalweg, the KE magnitude is reduced. Downstream, at 440-Thalweg, the KE magnitude is reduced further. The next transect (i.e. Main) shows an increasing KE signature. The KE fluctuations remain at 800-Thalweg and 1100-Thalweg. However, the occurrence decreases beyond 440-Thalweg to 1100-Thalweg. When the KE vertical distribution along transects is compared, one could argue that the KE along the water column is evenly distributed, at 1100 in contrast, for example, with Main and 800-Thalweg.</p>
<p>Downstream transect 440, the KE increases as theform drag is reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Figs 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650911424025">9</xref>). Wedge-like structures, identified as vortex tube development [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957650911424025">22</xref></bold>], can be recognized at 220-Max, 440-Max, Main-Thalweg, Main-Max, 800-Thalweg, and 1100-Max. These structures represent an inrush of fluid towards the river bed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-0957650911424025"><title>5.2.2 Coordinate rotation</title>
<p>The <inline-formula id="ilm4-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>w</italic>′ components obtained from Methods 1 and 2 were correlated for each ADCP measurement. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0957650911424025">Figures 11</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0957650911424025">12</xref> provide limiting examples of these results. These figures indicate that the correlation (<italic>r</italic> value) between the methods is directly related to the average flow direction. The correlation is reduced when the average-horizontal and/or vertical flow deviates from a particular axis.For instance, at transect 000 where the departure of the main flow from the axis is the largest, the correlation falls to 0.33 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0957650911424025">Fig. 11</xref>). Conversely, when the main flow sustains a departure angle less than 20° from north, this yields a correlation higher than 0.95 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0957650911424025">Fig. 12</xref>). High correlations were also found at transects Main and 800. Kaimal and Finnigan [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650911424025">15</xref></bold>] stressed the importance of coordinate rotation when flows deviate from the main axis. The methods of correlation define what was discussed earlier when the main flow travels in the direction of <italic>u</italic> in an ideal situation. The ATKE was calculated using Method 2 to extract the main flow. It is necessary to identify the correlation of the two turbulent extraction methods described in section 4 so that theresults can be compared with other flow analyses that may choose to use either of the two methods.
<fig id="fig11-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Correlation plots for Methods 1 and 2, transect 000</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig11.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig12-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Correlation plots for Methods 1 and 2, transect 1100</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig12.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In addition, when the horizontal flow angle significantly changes along the river depth (see, for instance, 000-Max in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650911424025">Fig. 5(b)</xref>), a single coordinate rotation for the entire depth will not suffice. Thus, the coordinate system should be rotated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec19-0957650911424025"><title>5.2.3 Turbulent kinetic energy</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0957650911424025">Figure 13</xref> shows the calculated TKE from Method 2 <italic>versus</italic> time and depth. In this figure, the TKE events are displayed on a different scale to improve the visibility of events. A similar figure with a common scale is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ine.uaf.edu/temp/toniolo">http://ine.uaf.edu/temp/toniolo</ext-link>.
<fig id="fig13-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>TKE distance from river bed <italic>versus</italic> recorded ADCP time. Non-uniform colour scale: (a)thalweg; (b) maximum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig13a.tif"/><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig13b.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>TKE is high in the areas of 000-Thalweg, 000-Max, and 440-Thalweg. The peak TKE events of 000-Thalweg and 000-Max account for roughly 15 per cent of the overall peak KE at each location. At 000-Max, high TKE events are found in the bulk-of-fluid region where KE events were also previously found. Itis speculated that large bathymetric depressions (see, for instance, locations in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Fig. 3</xref> and 000-Max, 000-Thalweg, and 440-Thalweg plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0957650911424025">Fig. 13</xref>) play an important role in developing high TKE in the bulk-of-fluid region. TKE events last 30–60 s and account for over 30 per cent of the overall KE present in the water column at 440-Thalweg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650911424025">Fig. 8(a)</xref>). Once the river flow reaches 1100-Thalweg, the TKE presents a very small value, approximately 2 per cent of the total KE along the water column (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650911424025">Fig. 8(a)</xref>). It is speculated that the dissipation of TKE in the downstream area isdirectly related to the lack of significant features inthe bathymetry.</p>
<p>The longitudinal variation of TKE events is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0957650911424025">Table 2</xref>. This table indicates an increase in the duration (and a decrease in the number) of events as one moves downstream. The maximum values of TKE events at each ADCP location are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0957650911424025">Fig. 14</xref>. This figure indicates a reduction in TKE as the longitudinal profiles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650911424025">Fig.3</xref> show a reduction in water depth as well as the absence of large depressions. Experiments by Albers and Steffler [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957650911424025">23</xref></bold>], which were based on dispersion oftracers, also identified dissipation in turbulence beyond river bends and obstacles in their flume experiments and numerical methods.
<fig id="fig14-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Maximum TKE events</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-0957650911424025" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>TKE events</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0957650911424025" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650911424025-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Location</th>
<th rowspan="2">Recording time (min)</th>
<th rowspan="2">Number of events</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Time between events (min)<hr/></th>
<th rowspan="2">Recorded depth (m)</th>
<th rowspan="2">Average event magnitude (m<sup>2</sup>/s<sup>2</sup>)</th>
</tr>
<tr><th>Minimum</th>
<th>Average</th>
<th>Maximum</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>000-Thalweg</td>
<td>18.54</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>1.17</td>
<td>2.19</td>
<td>12.2</td>
<td>0.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>000-Max</td>
<td>16.60</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>13.6</td>
<td>0.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>220-Thalweg</td>
<td>19.65</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>1.51</td>
<td>3.53</td>
<td>6.7</td>
<td>0.15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>220-Max</td>
<td>20.61</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>1.44</td>
<td>2.48</td>
<td>5.6</td>
<td>0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>440-Thalweg</td>
<td>18.11</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>2.58</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>0.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>440-Max</td>
<td>15.86</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>2.32</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>4.8</td>
<td>0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Main-Thalweg</td>
<td>20.84</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1.43</td>
<td>2.44</td>
<td>3.22</td>
<td>7.4</td>
<td>0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Main-Max</td>
<td>21.05</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>0.81</td>
<td>1.72</td>
<td>3.77</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>0.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>800-Thalweg</td>
<td>18.81</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0.71</td>
<td>1.38</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>6.4</td>
<td>0.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>800-Max</td>
<td>12.12</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1.95</td>
<td>3.18</td>
<td>3.93</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1100-Thalweg</td>
<td>11.97</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>7.2</td>
<td>&lt;0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1100-Max</td>
<td>12.72</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1.29</td>
<td>2.21</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec20-0957650911424025"><title>6 DISCUSSION</title>
<sec id="sec21-0957650911424025"><title>6.1 Flow pattern</title>
<p>The analysis of the average flow angle data indicatesthe presence of helical flow at transect 000 in thalwegand max locations. Data at 440-Thalweg also indicate similar helical flow conditions, but without channel curvature, which has been a characteristic of the previous definition of helical flow [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650911424025">18</xref></bold>–<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650911424025">20</xref></bold>]. The bathymetric depression at 440-Thalweg also creates the same helical flow conditions due to flow separation originated by upstream conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650911424025">Fig. 2</xref>). It is expected that helical flow will promote the generation of additional turbulence in these areas.</p>
<p>Flow configurations in terms of vertical and horizontal flow angles are different in 000-Max and 000-Thalweg due to the river curvature in that area. For instance, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650911424025">Fig. 5</xref> shows large distributed angles along the entire river depth. Moreover, the vertical angles are basically opposite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650911424025">Fig. 6</xref>) in these locations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec22-0957650911424025"><title>6.2 Kinetic and turbulent kinetic energies</title>
<p>In comparing <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650911424025">Figs 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0957650911424025">13</xref>, it is identified that in transects Main, 800, and 1100, where KE and TKE fluctuations begin to dissipate, greater AKE and less ATKE are produced. AKE is reduced while ATKE is increased within the depth of the bathymetric depression of 440-Thalweg. Changes detected along transects agree with basic concept of mass conservation. For instance, most of the flow is located on 000-Thalweg, which is located in the outside bend. The distribution of energy is similar in thalweg and max along transects 220, 440, and Main. An uneven distribution of KE is observed in 800 and 1100 transects, which is consistent with the argument of a dynamic (and unstable) river channel near the downstream end of the study reach.</p>
<p>The TKE has been calculated after applying the coordinate rotation Method 2. Results suggest that it is important to include coordinate rotation for each depth, especially in measurements located in the vicinity of river bends. Rotating the system based on a single average flow angle per ADCP will develop excess turbulent parameters that are inaccurate. The areas of higher ATKE and fluctuating TKE are found when the flow is redirected around the cornerof transect 000 or when the flows encounter obstructions or bathymetric depressions [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650911424025">20</xref></bold>]. This supports the theory that large-scale bed forms are directly related to the development of macro-scale turbulence [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957650911424025">24</xref></bold>].</p>
<p>From the data presented, it is shown that the turbulent energy dissipates from 30 per cent to less than 2 per cent as the flow travels downstream beyond large-scale bed forms. The change in the energy partition (from turbulent to AKE) and the fact that turbines are designed for extracting energy from average flow conditions suggest that more energy could be harvested by turbines installed in areas where the river bed is relatively uniform and the reach is approximately straight. These areas are located downstream transect 440. It is worthy to notehere that bathymetry/flow interactions are key elements affecting the KE; therefore, careful attention needs to be paid to the energy partition of the flow, inorder to define the emplacement of the turbines and the optimization of the energy extraction.</p>
<p>Additional information on flow velocities can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uaf.edu/acep/facilities/alaska-hydrokinetic-energ/technical-information/tanana-turbulence/Tanana_turbulence_web.xlsx">http://www.uaf.edu/acep/facilities/alaska-hydrokinetic-energ/technical-information/tanana-turbulence/Tanana_turbulence_web.xlsx</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec23-0957650911424025"><title>7 CONCLUSIONS</title>
<p>The available ADCP data can be analysed to obtain average and turbulent flow characteristics. When instruments are strategically deployed in the field, they can provide flow quantities that can be related to physical properties of the river bathymetry. The interactions between the bathymetry and the flow were initially described by comparing the contour map and longitudinal profiles to the average horizontal and vertical flow angles, AKE, and ATKE. Attributes of flow along the study reach included the occurrence of helical flow around river bends and the dissipation of TKE along the reach.</p>
<p>Velocity profiles of 000-Max and 440-Thalweg did not adhere to the typical velocity profiles due to their locations in deep bathymetric depressions and river bends. Results indicated that ATKE increased in these areas. Helical flows at transect 000 and 440-Thalweg explained some of the previously reported findings (i.e. unusual velocity profiles) [<bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650911424025">4</xref></bold>].</p>
<p>Plots of KE and TKE showed variable structures in all the transects. Some of these structures were mainly located in the bulk-of-fluid region. Major TKE fluctuations were found in areas of bathymetric depressions and river bends. As the river bathymetry becomes free of macro-depressions, the TKE is dissipated and the KE fluctuations reduced. Specifically, the data showed a change in the partition of turbulent over AKE from 30 per cent to 2 per cent.</p>
<p>Results indicated that coordinate rotation should be done in areas where the flow is changing directions such as river bends and pools. In general, the correlation between methods was good in areas where the river was straight.</p>
<p>The knowledge gained here, in terms of energy partition as well as its spatial variation, could be applied to aid the process of turbine site selection along the river reach. In fact, results suggested that the best location to consistently capture the energy source exists downstream from transect 440 and upstream from transect 800.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec24-0957650911424025"><title>FUNDING</title>
<p>Data used in this study were obtained from the project supported by the Alaska Energy Authority, contract 2195437/G00005572.</p></sec>
<ref-list>
<title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0957650911424025"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An investigation of pulsating turbulent open channel flow by large eddy simulation</article-title><source>Comput. Fluids</source><year>2006</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>74102</fpage>–<lpage>74102</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0957650911424025"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sukhodolov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bungartz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Turbulence structure in a river reach with sand bed</article-title><source>Water Resour. Res.</source><year>1986</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1317</fpage>–<lpage>1334</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0957650911424025"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Stoesser, T., Frohlich, J., and Rodi, W. Identification of coherent flow structures in open-channel flow over rough bed using large eddy simulation. In Proceedings of the 30th IAHR Congress, Thessaloniki, Greece, 24–29 August 2003, pp. 25–31</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0957650911424025"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toniolo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvoy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlesberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling and field measurements in support of the hydrokinetic resource assessment for the Tanana river at Nenana, Alaska</article-title><source>Proc. IMechE, Part A: J. Power and Energy</source><year>2010</year><volume>224</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1139</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0957650911424025"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buffin-Bélanger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One minute in the life of a river: selecting the optimal record length for the measurement of turbulence in fluvial boundary layers</article-title><source>Geomorphology</source><year>2005</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1–2</issue><fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0957650911424025"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical aspects of ADCP data use for quantification of mean river flow characteristics; part II: fixed-vessel measurements</article-title><source>Flow Meas. Instrum.</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0957650911424025"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Leopold, L. and Wolman, G. River channel patterns: braided, meandering and straight, physiographic and hydraulic studies of rivers. US Geological Survey Professional Paper 282-B, 1957, pp. 39–61</comment></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0957650911424025"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikora</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Despiking acoustic Doppler velocimeter data</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>2002</year><volume>128</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0957650911424025"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of streamflow measurements made with acoustic Doppler current profilers</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>2007</year><volume>133</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1432</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0957650911424025"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Press</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Teukolsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetterling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Numerical recipes in C++: the art of scientific computing</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>1002</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0957650911424025"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemmin</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acoustic velocity profiler for laboratory and field studies</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>1997</year><volume>123</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1089</fpage>–<lpage>1098</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0957650911424025"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nystrom</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of mean velocity and turbulence measurements with ADCPs</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>2007</year><volume>133</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1310</fpage>–<lpage>1318</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0957650911424025"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Storchenegger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Turbulent and advective momentum fluxes in streams</article-title><source>Water Resour. Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>W12518</fpage>–<lpage>W12518</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0957650911424025"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurnell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Soar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Numerical modeling of river flow for eco-hydraulic applications: some experiences with velocity characterization in field and simulated data</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>2010</year><volume>136</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1033</fpage>–<lpage>1041</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0957650911424025"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaimal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Finnigan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Atmospheric boundary layer flows: their structure and measurement</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0957650911424025"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Massman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Handbook ofmicrometeorology: a guide for surface flux measurement and analysis</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0957650911424025"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Elger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Engineering fluid mechanics</source><year>2009</year><edition>edition 9</edition><publisher-loc>Ames, Iowa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name><fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0957650911424025"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peakall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Amos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The orientation of helical flow in curved channels</article-title><source>Sedimentology</source><year>2006</year><volume>53</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0957650911424025"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanckaert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Momentum transport in sharp open-channel bends</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>2004</year><volume>130</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0957650911424025"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Balen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Uijttewaal</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanckaert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-eddy simulation of a curved open-channel flow over topography</article-title><source>Phys. Fluids</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>075108</fpage>–<lpage>075108-18</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0957650911424025"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masanori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Convective instability of flow in a symmetric channel with spatially periodic structures</article-title><source>Phys. Fluids</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>024105</fpage>–<lpage>024105-10</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0957650911424025"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinematics, topology and significance of dune-related macroturbulence: some observations from the laboratory and field</article-title><source>Spec. Publ. Int. Ass. Sediment.</source><year>2005</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0957650911424025"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating transverse mixing in open channels due to secondary current-induced shear dispersion</article-title><source>J. Hydraul. Eng.</source><year>2007</year><volume>133</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage></citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0957650911424025"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Size and effect on the mean flow of large-scale horizontal coherent structures in open-channel flows: an experimental study</article-title><source>Can. J. Civ. Eng.</source><year>2009</year><volume>36</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>1655</lpage></citation></ref>
</ref-list><app-group><app id="app1-0957650911424025">
<title>APPENDIX</title>
<sec id="sec25-0957650911424025">
<title/>
<sec id="sec26-0957650911424025">
<title>Notation</title>
<p><def-list id="duolist1-0957650911424025"><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm5-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>step 1 in the streamline rotation coordinate <italic>u</italic>, and <italic>v</italic> values for the streamline coordinate rotation method</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm6-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>step 2 in the streamline rotation coordinate <italic>u</italic>, and <italic>v</italic> values for the streamline coordinate rotation method</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm7-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>  </mml:mi><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mi>  </mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>average velocity per depth</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>u</italic>′, <italic>v</italic>′, and <italic>w</italic>′</term><def>
<p>turbulent velocity components</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>u</italic>, <italic>v</italic>, and <italic>w</italic></term><def>
<p>instantaneous velocity recording from ADCP</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><inline-formula id="ilm8-0957650911424025"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-0957650911424025"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></term><def>
<p>Cartesian coordinates</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>θ</term><def>
<p>streamline coordinate rotation angle in the horizontal plane</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ρ</term><def>
<p>density of water</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ϕ</term><def>
<p>rotation angle around the <italic>v-</italic>direction for the streamline coordinate rotation method</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>