<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CDY</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcdy</journal-id>
<journal-title>Cultural Dynamics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0921-3740</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7048</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0921374013482348</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0921374013482348</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Preface</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Preface to the Special Issue</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Adrián</surname><given-names>Francisco-J Hernández</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0921374013482348">Durham University, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0921374013482348">Francisco-J Hernández Adrián, Durham University, Durham, UK. Email: <email>f.j.adrian@durham.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>2-3</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Lived Cosmopolitanisms</issue-title>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>106</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>July/November 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The essays in ‘“Lived Cosmopolitanisms” in Littoral Asia’ ask us to consider some of the key junctures at which cosmopolitanism must be posed as a critical project. While they address cosmopolitanism’s European and universalist underpinnings, they also circumvent the logic of universal necessity and ask us instead to think through the linked knowledges of the Global South. To the question of what it may entail to contemplate cosmopolitanism from the South, they reply by specifically demarcating the unique complexities of one of Asia’s largest archipelagic zones. ‘Lived cosmopolitanisms’ names the common programmatic perspectives that the editors of this special issue choose at this moment in the neo-liberal re-constitution of Asia, by ‘situating the history of South, Southeast, and East Asia within the context of linked histories’ (Introduction, p. 118).</p>
<p>By engaging the littoral cosmopolitanisms of India and Southeast Asia, this collection alters the very notion of <italic>cosmopolitheia</italic> that Spivak traces from Plato to Kant’s 1784 essay and, in the conclusion to her Foreword, to Derridean thought. As she has done in the past, Spivak reads Derrida’s concept of the <italic>supplement</italic> into the excess of those postcolonial and regional alignments discussed in the collection. She asks, ‘[h]ow do we construct our objects of knowledge now, in the moving global now-time?’ (Spivak, p. 112). In the aftermath of Kantian universalism, Alexander von Humboldt’s views on universal geography and total scientific knowledge in a work called <italic>Kosmos</italic> comes to mind as an example of how capitalist desires were once shaped by an ambitious awareness of geopolitical difference (most notably in its Atlantic and pan-American dimensions) and continue to operate today in a changing world constitution.</p>
<p>These essays show an exacting awareness that the ‘now’ of the lived cosmopolitical is being thought from the South by means of an astute intersection of divergent histories, cultural genealogies, and spaces. Indeed, one of the most fruitful facets of this dialogue is the provocative conceptualization of the littoral as an image for the tidal zones, expanding port-cities, and interiors that make up the simultaneously fragmented and convergent ‘Malay world’. The unfolding imaginaries and connected subregions of neo-liberal capitalism demand a new cosmopolitical thinking, no less than a new, self-consciously pluri-regional critique of cosmopolitanism’s colonial pasts.</p>
<p>Through these littoral essays, cosmopolitanism confronts its Enlightenment and imperial renditions as a critical concept that scrutinizes colonial archives and engages global practices while attending to the linguistic and institutional practices of the present in the changing environments of its ‘linked histories and geographies’ (Introduction, p. 123). Clearly, this confrontation will yield new and intersecting dialogues between cosmopolitical and ecocritical projects.</p>
<p>As the editors of this special issue make clear in their ‘Introduction’, the essays ‘come together to form a nucleus of thinking that expresses epistemic self-reflexivity in the approach to cosmopolitanism’ (p. 117). Together, they are also important for the ways in which they frame the fraught dialectics of metropolitan/local and rooted/uprooted scholarship, theorizing and critique. It is not only the location of cultural production and the lived social experience that counts but also the local articulation of self-reflexive critical discourses and the unique lives of the scholars who produce them. This collection speaks from those cosmopolitical littorals, as well as from a consciousness of the invaluable position that they facilitate – a position of excess in which, as Spivak writes, ‘the supplement introduces the incalculable’ (p. 113).</p>
<p>As mappings of global cosmopolitanism are transformed in the work of local and transnational scholars who listen actively to each other, the need for what Spivak calls ‘the gift of tongues’ becomes all the more urgent (p. 113). This lived gift of tongues, and the capacity to articulate its multiple translations in littoral Asia, has long exceeded the very limits of the Kantian imagination and is now questioning its present and future possibilities.</p>
</body>
</article>