<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsi</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Studies in International Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1028-3153</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7808</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1028315311431064</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1028315311431064</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Leask</surname><given-names>Betty</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>16</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>4</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Nuffic 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Nuffic</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In this first edition of the journal for 2012, as we look back on the previous year, we are reminded that this journal over the past 15 years has published research and commentary on international education that is vast, has been conducted in many countries, and has assumed many forms. It has been undertaken by scholars in multiple fields, including education, business, economics, marketing, applied linguistics, foreign languages, sociology, history, and political science. Topics and issues that have been investigated have been of immediate and long-term interest to academics, practitioners, and administrators. In the last year, as in previous years, we are confident that the articles published in the journal have made valuable contributions to the field.</p>
<p>It is also timely to look further back into the past. We were reminded, at the Australian International Education Conference in Adelaide last October, that 2011 was not only the 15th Anniversary of the <italic>Journal of Studies in International Education</italic> but also the 25th Anniversary of the fee-paying international student program in Australia, a significant milestone. This milestone has provided a stimulus for reflection on the challenges that have been faced, what has been learned, what has been achieved, and what international education might look like in Australia in the future. These matters are therefore, not surprisingly, covered in some depth in a publication that was launched at the Australian Parliament in Canberra, on the 22nd November 2011. The book, <italic>Making a Difference: Australian International Education</italic>, is a critical review of international education in Australia, which in fact extends back over one hundred years. The book however is focused particularly on the last 25 years, the period when Australia came into its own as an international study destination. <italic>Making a Difference</italic> is analytical and reflective, looking to the past as well as to the future. It includes contributions from a range of people, whose roles, responsibilities, and perspectives are varied, reflecting the broad scope of activity and people involved in international education. The book has been edited by Dorothy Davis and Bruce Macintosh, guided by an expert editorial committee, and includes much of interest to researchers and practitioners both within and beyond Australia.</p>
<p>Proceeds of the sale of the book will go to the Tony Adams Fund, established in memory of Tony Adams, who died suddenly earlier this year. In a wide range of roles, including as coeditor of this journal until his death, Tony made many significant contributions to international education in and well beyond Australia. The Tony Adams Fund will provide scholarships supporting activities in the areas of research, professional development, and student mobility. This will ensure that Tony’s legacy continues because through this fund, individuals will be provided with the opportunity to pursue their interest in and passion for international education. Recipients of the scholarships may be from anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>Further details of the Tony Adams fund are available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ieaa.org.au/tonyadamsfund">http://www.ieaa.org.au/tonyadamsfund</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Readers wishing to purchase a copy of <italic>Making a Difference</italic> may do so online through the International Education Association of Australia (IEAA) at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ieaa.org.au/">http://www.ieaa.org.au/</ext-link> (click link at bottom of page).</p>
<p>Finally, looking forward, we are pleased to report that we already have as diverse and interesting a range of articles scheduled for publication in 2012 as we did in 2011. The articles in this edition reflect a range of perspectives on important issues. We hope you enjoy reading them as much as we have. In the editorial of the next issue we will also inform you on changes in our editorial advisory board.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>
Hans de Wit and Betty Leask<break/>
Co-editors
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>