<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546512447792</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546512447792</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>11</subject>
<subject>23</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Risk Factors for Medial Meniscus Posterior Root Tear</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Byoung-Yoon</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512447792">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546512447792">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Sung-Jae</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546512447792">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sang-Won</given-names></name>
<degrees>RS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512447792">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546512447792">‡</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Ha-Eun</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512447792">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Choon-Key</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512447792">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>David J.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MBBS, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0363546512447792">§</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Kwang-Am</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512447792">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546512447792">‖</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546512447792"><label>*</label>Joint &amp; Arthritis Research, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Himchan Hospital, Seoul, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546512447792"><label>†</label>Arthroscopy and Joint Research Institute, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Yonsei University Health System, Seoul, Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0363546512447792"><label>‡</label>Deerfield Academy, Deerfield, Massachusetts</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0363546512447792"><label>§</label>Rheumatology Department, Royal North Shore Hospital and Northern Clinical School, University of Sydney, NSW, Australia</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0363546512447792">Investigation performed at Joint &amp; Arthritis Research, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Himchan Hospital, Seoul, Korea</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546512447792"><label>‖</label>Kwang-Am Jung, MD, Joint &amp; Arthritis Research, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Himchan Hospital, 20-8, Songpa-dong, Songpa-gu, 138-172, Seoul, Korea (e-mail: <email>kwangamj@gmail.com</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>1606</fpage>
<lpage>1610</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0363546512447792">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Medial meniscus posterior root tears (MMPRT) have a different clinical effect from other types of meniscal tears. These tears are very common among Asian people and may be related to the frequent use of postures such as the lotus position or squatting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546512447792">
<title>Purpose:</title>
<p>The present study was designed to identify the risk factors for MMPRT among an Asian sample.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546512447792">
<title>Study Design:</title>
<p>Cohort study; Level of evidence, 3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546512447792">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>An observational study was performed of 476 consecutive patients undergoing an arthroscopic procedure on their medial meniscus from January 2010 to December 2010. One hundred four patients had MMPRT (group 1), and the other patients had other types of medial meniscal tears (group 2). Demographic characteristics (age, sex, body mass index [BMI]), radiographic features (mechanical axis angle, tibia vara angle, tibial slope angle, Kellgren-Lawrence grade [KLG]), and environmental factors (occupation, trauma history, sports activity level, table use or not, bed use or not—variables that are representative of the oriental lifestyle of lotus position and squatting) were surveyed. We assessed the relation of these risk factors to the type of meniscal tear (group 1 or 2).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546512447792">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>In group 1, there were 7 male and 97 female patients, with an average age of 58.2 years (range, 39-78 years) and BMI of 26.7 ± 3.4 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. In group 2, there were 136 male and 236 female patients (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01 compared with group 1), with an average age of 54.3 years (range, 17-77 years; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) and a BMI of 24.9 ± 3.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). With regard to radiographic features, the mechanical axis angle demonstrated a significantly increased varus alignment in group 1 (4.5° ± 3.4°) compared with group 2 (2.4° ± 2.7°; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), and the KLG was 1.4 ± 0.8 in group 1 and 0.9 ± 0.6 in group 2 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Environmental factors showed no differences in occupation, table use or not, and bed use or not, except sports activity level. There were 41 patients (42.7%) in group 1 and 77 patients (20.6%) in group 2 who did not participate in any recreational activity (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Multiple logistic regression analysis showed that female sex was associated with a 5.9-fold increase in risk (95% confidence interval [CI], 2.138-16.575), a varus mechanical axis angle with a 3.3-fold increase (95% CI, 1.492-7.153), a BMI more than 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> with a 4.9-fold increase (95% CI, 1.160-20.955), and lower sports activity level with a 2.7-fold increase (95% CI, 1.011-7.163) for MMPRT.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546512447792">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>Persons with MMPRT had significantly increased age, female sex predominance, higher BMI, increased KLG, greater varus mechanical axis angle, and lower sports activity level compared with persons with other types of meniscal tear. After adjusting for other factors, sex, BMI, mechanical axis angle, and lower sports activity level remained strong determinants of MMPRT. Interestingly, oriental postural positions including the lotus position and squatting showed no contribution to increased risk of MMPRT. This suggests that intrinsic risk factors (similar to those that predispose to osteoarthritis) predispose to MMPRT.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>medial meniscus</kwd>
<kwd>root tear</kwd>
<kwd>risk factor</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Meniscal damage is very common in the general community<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512447792">3</xref></sup> and is an important risk factor predisposing to the development of osteoarthritis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546512447792">8</xref></sup> Despite knowledge that meniscal tears can predispose to osteoarthritis, we know little about what predisposes to meniscal tears. Efforts to identify modifiable risk factors for disease should focus on risk factors early in disease genesis.</p>
<p>The most frequent location of meniscal damage is the posterior horn of the medial meniscus,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512447792">3</xref></sup> and radial tears of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus are very common among Asian people.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512447792">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512447792">18</xref></sup> Medial meniscus posterior root tear (MMPRT) results in 2 separate pieces of menisci with attachment to the tibia at only one end. This permits the meniscus to be displaced peripherally, to lose hoop stress and functional load distribution,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512447792">19</xref></sup> which may predispose to development of osteoarthritis due to altered joint contact stress.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512447792">15</xref></sup> This type of tear is more common than previously considered, with rates of 10.1% to 10.5% of all meniscal tears in prior studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512447792">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512447792">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>Several risk factors for MMPRT have been proposed, including age, body mass index (BMI), sex, injury, and cultural environment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512447792">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512447792">12</xref></sup> However, the relative importance of these risk factors has not been systematically investigated, although there are several previous reports that together present somewhat confusing evidence for apparent relationships between selected variables and MMPRT.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512447792">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512447792">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>The purpose of this retrospective observational study was to contribute to the epidemiologic understanding of risk factors (demographic, anatomic [or radiographic], and environmental factors) for MMPRT.</p>
<sec id="section7-0363546512447792" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Method</title>
<sec id="section8-0363546512447792">
<title>Patients</title>
<p>We retrospectively reviewed the records of 564 patients who underwent arthroscopic meniscectomy or meniscal repair for tears of the medial meniscus between January 2010 and December 2010, excluding those with ligament laxity, lateral meniscal tear, systemic arthritis, osteonecrosis, or other combined ligament injury. The final group included 121 patients with MMPRT and 443 patients with other types of medial meniscal tear identified by an experienced musculoskeletal radiologist using 1.5-T magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and also confirmed during arthroscopic surgery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546512447792">Figure 1</xref>). The sensitivity of MRI in diagnosing MMPRT was 73%. Of these patients, it was possible to review all pertinent information and obtain informed consent in 104 patients (86%) with MMPRT (group 1) and 372 patients (84%) with other types of meniscal tear (group 2) from their medical records, phone, or clinic visit. Hospital Ethic Committee approval was obtained. The surgical indication was persistent medial joint area pain despite 3 months of nonoperative treatment.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0363546512447792" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) Coronal fat-saturated T2-weighted image showing a root tear of the medial meniscus (arrow) and (B) arthroscopic view showing the posterior root tear of the medial meniscus (asterisk).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512447792-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0363546512447792">
<title>Risk Factors</title>
<p>Demographic factors included in this study were age, sex, and BMI. Radiographic factors included mechanical axis angle, tibia vara angle, tibial slope angle, and Kellgren-Lawrence grade (KLG),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512447792">13</xref></sup> which was graded as 0 (normal), 1 (doubtful narrowing of joint space and possible osteophytic lipping), 2 (definite osteophytes and definite narrowing of joint space), 3 (moderate multiple osteophytes, definite narrowing of joint space, some sclerosis, and possible deformity of bone contour), or 4 (large osteophytes, marked narrowing of joint space, severe sclerosis, and definite deformity of bone contour). Environmental factors included occupation, trauma history, sports activity level, table use or not, and bed use or not. Variables about table use or not and bed use or not are representative of the oriental lifestyle of lotus position (knee flexed and internally rotated) and squatting. Table use implies use of a chair and hence not sitting in the lotus, and no bed use implies a sedentary lifestyle that includes lots of squatting and sitting in the lotus position in activities of daily living.</p>
<p>Preoperative standing hip-knee-ankle radiographs were taken, and mechanical axis angle was measured. Mechanical axis angle is the angle between a line from the center of the femoral head running distally to the midcondylar point between the cruciate ligaments (femoral mechanical axis) and a line from the center of the tibial plateau extending distally to the center of the tibial plafond (tibial mechanical axis) in radiographs of the entire lower limb.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512447792">6</xref></sup> Tibia vara angle is the angle between the tibial plateau tangent and the tibial mechanical axis (a line from the center of the tibial plateau extending distally to the center of the tibial plafond). On lateral radiographs, the tibial slope angle is measured as the angle between the posterior tibial anatomic axis (a line from the center of the cortex between 5 cm distal to the tibial tubercle and 15 cm distal to proximal joint facet) and the line tangential to the proximal joint facet of tibia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546512447792">22</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546512447792">Figure 2</xref>). The KLG was measured on extension weightbearing views. Type of occupation was categorized as white/blue collar. Trauma history was categorized as present/none. Sport activity level was categorized as lower or higher (participation more than 2-3 times per week).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0363546512447792" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) The mechanical axis angle is the angle between a line from the center of the femoral head to the midcondylar point between the cruciate ligaments and a line from the center of the tibial plateau to the center of the tibial plafond. (B) The tibia vara angle is the angle between the tibial plateau tangent and a line from the center of the tibial plateau to the center of the tibial plafond. (C) The tibial slope angle is the angle between a line from the center of the cortex between 5 cm distal to the tibial tubercle and 15 cm distal to the proximal joint facet and the line tangential to the proximal joint facet of tibia.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512447792-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>To assess the reliability of radiographic assessment, each evaluation (KLG, mechanical axis angle, tibia vara angle, and tibial slope angle) was measured on the PACS system (INFINITT PACS, INFINITT Healthcare Co Ltd, Seoul, Korea) by 2 experienced raters (B.-Y.H., H.-E.L.) under supervision of K.A-.J., who has 10 years of musculoskeletal radiology experience. All raters were blinded to the information of the patients. The average of the 2 individual mean values was used. Overall ratings were determined by consensus when necessary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546512447792">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>The principal analysis was to compare risk factors between the 2 groups of meniscal tears. For continuous data, a paired sample <italic>t</italic> test was used to compare the 2 groups. A chi-square test was employed to compare the categorical ordinal data of the 2 groups. Multiple logistic regression analysis was performed on variables thought to be associated with root tear according to the bivariate analyses (entry criterion, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). Odds ratios (ORs) and confidence intervals (CIs) were reported for variables significantly associated with the outcome as defined by the Wald test. The interobserver reliability in measuring KLG, mechanical axis angle, tibia vara angle, and tibial slope was evaluated using the intraclass correlation set at a 95% CI. A level of significance was set at &lt;.05. Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS version 12.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546512447792" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Bivariate analysis of variables is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546512447792">Table 1</xref>. With regard to demographic factors, there were 7 male and 97 female patients in group 1 and 136 male and 236 female patients in group 2 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). The average age at the time of surgery was 58.2 years (range, 39-78 years) in group 1 and 54.3 years (range, 17-77 years) in group 2 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Body mass index was 26.7 ± 3.4 in group 1 and 24.9 ± 3.1 in group 2 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). With regard to radiographic factors, only mechanical axis angle showed significantly increased varus alignment in group 1 (4.5° ± 3.4°) from group 2 (2.4° ± 2.7°; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01; the intraclass correlation coefficient for intertester reliability was 0.833). The KLG was 1.4 ± 0.8 in group 1 and 0.9 ± 0.6 in group 2 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Environmental factors showed no differences in occupation, trauma history, table use or not, and bed use or not. There were 41 patients (42.7%) in group 1 and 77 patients (20.6%) in group 2 who had a lower level of sports activity (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546512447792" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographics<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512447792"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546512447792" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512447792-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Group 1 (n = 104)</th>
<th align="center">Group 2 (n = 372)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mean age (range), y</td>
<td>58.2 (39-78)</td>
<td>54.3 (17 to 77)</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex, M/F</td>
<td>7/97</td>
<td>136/236</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td>
<td>26.7 ± 3.4</td>
<td>24.9 ± 3.1</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kellgren-Lawrence grade</td>
<td>1.4 ± 0.8</td>
<td>0.9 ± 0.6</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mechanical axis angle, deg</td>
<td>4.5 ± 3.4</td>
<td>2.4 ± 2.7</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tibia vara angle, deg</td>
<td>4.9 ± 2.3</td>
<td>4.2 ± 2.5</td>
<td>.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tibial slope angle, deg</td>
<td>10.4 ± 3.0</td>
<td>9.8 ± 3.7</td>
<td>.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bed use</td>
<td>49/96 (51.0%)</td>
<td>198/372 (53.2%)</td>
<td>.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Table use</td>
<td>41/96 (42.7%)</td>
<td>156/372 (41.9%)</td>
<td>.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Occupation, blue-collar/total</td>
<td>33/96 (34.4%)</td>
<td>101/372 (27.2%)</td>
<td>.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sports activity level, lower/total</td>
<td>41/96 (42.7%)</td>
<td>77/372 (20.6%)</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546512447792">
<label>a</label>
<p>Group 1, medial meniscus posterior root tear; group 2, other type of medial meniscus tear.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The multiple logistic regression model provided estimates of the magnitude of association for risk factors of interest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0363546512447792">Table 2</xref>). Female sex was associated with a 5.9-fold increase in risk (95% CI, 2.138-16.575), a varus mechanical axis angle with a 3.3-fold increase (95% CI, 1.492-7.153), a BMI more than 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> with a 4.9-fold increase (95% CI, 1.160-20.955), and lower sports activity level with a 2.7-fold increase (95% CI, 1.011-7.163). However, advancing age was not associated with any increase in risk between MMPRT and other type of medial meniscal tear.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0363546512447792" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression Model of the Potential Risk Factors for Medial Meniscus Posterior Root Tear<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0363546512447792"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0363546512447792" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512447792-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Adjusted Odds Ratio</th>
<th align="center">Lower 95% Confidence Interval</th>
<th align="center">Upper 95% Confidence Interval</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Age, y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &lt;50</td>
<td align="center">Reference (1.0)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 50-60</td>
<td>2.172</td>
<td>0.688</td>
<td>6.849</td>
<td>.186</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 60-70</td>
<td>2.767</td>
<td>0.821</td>
<td>9.321</td>
<td>.101</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≥70</td>
<td>1.818</td>
<td>0.381</td>
<td>8.681</td>
<td>.454</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female sex</td>
<td>5.953</td>
<td>2.138</td>
<td>16.575</td>
<td>.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &lt;25</td>
<td align="center">Reference (1.0)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 25-30</td>
<td>1.746</td>
<td>0.821</td>
<td>3.713</td>
<td>.148</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≥30</td>
<td>4.929</td>
<td>1.160</td>
<td>20.955</td>
<td>.031</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Mechanical axis angle</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Neutral (0-2)</td>
<td align="center">Reference (1.0)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Varus (&lt;0)</td>
<td>3.267</td>
<td>1.492</td>
<td>7.153</td>
<td>.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Valgus (≥2)</td>
<td>2.174</td>
<td>0.445</td>
<td>10.615</td>
<td>.337</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Sports activity level</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Higher</td>
<td align="center">Reference (1.0)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lower</td>
<td>2.691</td>
<td>1.011</td>
<td>7.163</td>
<td>.048</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0363546512447792">
<label>a</label>
<p>Group 1, medial meniscus posterior root tear; group 2, other type of medial meniscus tear.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0363546512447792" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, we confirmed that female sex is an important risk factor for MMPRT. Higher BMI, radiographic factors (varus mechanical axis angle, increased KLG), and decreased sports activity level also contributed as risk factors for MMPRT. Radiographic factors representing regional knee geometry, such as tibia vara angle and tibial slope angle, revealed no differences between the 2 groups. However, overall lower limb geometry, such as mechanical axis angle, did contribute to the development of MMPRT.</p>
<p>Thus, the predominant risk factors for MMPRT (female sex, older age, and higher BMI) are consistent with those for development of osteoarthritis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512447792">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512447792">12</xref></sup> The posterior horn of the medial meniscus endures most of the stress applied to the medial compartment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546512447792">1</xref></sup> The posterior horn region has little mobility because of its strong attachment to the tibia at the meniscal root. Hence, the medial meniscus posterior horn is particularly vulnerable to injury, including microinjury, which can lead to degeneration and tearing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512447792">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0363546512447792">23</xref></sup> Ford et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512447792">10</xref></sup> demonstrated a significant association between increasing BMI and meniscal tears leading to surgery. Moreover, our study demonstrated that MMPRT was more positively associated with higher BMI than other types of medial meniscal tear. Also, increased KLG and varus mechanical axis angle have the same effect on MMPRT as high BMI does.</p>
<p>Medial meniscus posterior root tears have attracted renewed attention in recent years, mainly because of concerns of significant loss of primary biomechanical meniscus functions in preventing extrusion of the medial meniscus and preserving normal medial meniscal position and function, leading to a condition biomechanically similar to a total meniscectomy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512447792">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512447792">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512447792">15</xref></sup> However, clinical features, characteristics, and risk factors have not been systematically investigated, although there are several previous reports focusing on surgical technique and clinical outcome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546512447792">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546512447792">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546512447792">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>This study was conducted to investigate the epidemiologic characteristics of MMPRT and relevant risk factors. The incidence of MMPRT has not been thoroughly investigated. Several studies have suggested that up to 27.8% of all medial meniscal tears are MMPRT.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512447792">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512447792">18</xref></sup> Our series demonstrated that 21.5% (121 of 564) of the patients who were treated for medial meniscal tear were diagnosed with MMPRT.</p>
<p>Consistent with our study, prior research indicates that MMPRT occurs in persons of older age and female predominance. Bin et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512447792">4</xref></sup> reported that among their patients with MMPRT, 81 of 96 (84.4%) patients were female and 75 of 96 (78.1%) patients were older than 50 years. Ozkoc et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512447792">18</xref></sup> reported that in their study, 47 of 67 (70.1%) patients were female, 54 of 67 (80.6%) patients were older than 50 years, and 54 of 67 (80.6%) patients were obese (BMI of more than 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Despite no data to support the assertion, they postulated that the lifestyle of lotus position and squatting was responsible for the high incidence of MMPRT and explained that these postures lead to the high incidence of MMPRT in Asian people.</p>
<p>Inconsistent with other reports, we found that advancing age and oriental lifestyle with use of the lotus position and squatting (not using a bed or a table) showed no differences between the 2 groups. Bivariate analysis showed that 96 of 104 (92.3%) patients in group 1 and 271 of 372 (72.9%) patients in group 2 were older than 50 years (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). However, advancing age did not have a weighted effect on MMPRT compared with other types of medial meniscal tear. We found that age has an even effect on medial meniscal tears regardless of location of the tear.</p>
<p>Interestingly, lifestyle showed no differences between the 2 groups. Bin et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512447792">4</xref></sup> said that oriental lifestyle might lead to impingement of the posterior meniscal segment more often, and eventually the resultant degenerated posterior horn would be prone to tear, based on the kinematic analysis showing that menisci are dynamic structures that move anterior with extension and posterior with flexion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0363546512447792">21</xref></sup> Considering that Asian people adopt the lotus position and squatting in activities of daily living from a young age, knee structures (including musculature and ligament structure) may adapt to these circumstances.</p>
<p>We acknowledge that the present study has some limitations. First, enrolled patients in this study underwent an arthroscopic procedure, which may impose a selection bias. Therefore, it may be inappropriate to translate the present findings into asymptomatic or nonoperative managed meniscal tears and end-stage osteoarthritis patients associated with meniscal tears. Second, we did not subdivide the type of meniscal tear. Medial meniscus posterior root tear was defined as location (posterior horn) and type (radial tear) of medial meniscal tear. In this study, we focused only on the location, not on tear type. Interestingly, most MMPRTs are caused by a degenerative process,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512447792">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512447792">16</xref></sup> although the tear type of MMPRT is radial tear (commonly, most radial tears of the body and posterior horn are caused by trauma). Third, because of this study’s retrospective study design, missing patients were not included; therefore, this study included 84.4% of all included patients. However, there were no systematic differences between those patients who were included and those who were not.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0363546512447792" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This study demonstrates that advancing age, female sex, higher BMI, increased KLG, varus mechanical axis angle, and lower sports activity level are all associated with MMPRT. Of these, the most potent risk factors are sex, BMI, and mechanical axis angle. Interestingly, oriental-specific lifestyles such as the cross-legged position and kneeling show no contribution to increased MMPRT. This suggests that intrinsic risk factors (similar to those that predispose to osteoarthritis) predispose to MMPRT.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared that they have no conflicts of interest in the authorship and publication of this contribution.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546512447792">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>In-vitro measurement of static pressure distribution in synovial joints—part I: tibial surface of the knee</article-title>. <source>J Biomech Eng</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546512447792">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baratz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mengato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal tears: the effect of meniscectomy and of repair on intraarticular contact areas and stress in the human knee: a preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546512447792">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dewire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The clinical importance of meniscal tears demonstrated by magnetic resonance imaging in osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546512447792">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radial tears of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546512447792">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Victoroff</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic all-inside repair for a tear of posterior root of the medial meniscus: a technical note</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>891</fpage>-<lpage>893</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546512447792">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scudamore</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiographic assessment of bony contributions to knee deformity</article-title>. <source>Orthop Clin North Am</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546512447792">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carrino</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medial meniscus extrusion on knee MRI: is extent associated with severity of degeneration or type of tear?</article-title> <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>183</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546512447792">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guermazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roemer</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal tear in knees without surgery and the development of radiographic osteoarthritis among middle-aged and elderly persons: the Multicenter Osteoarthritis Study</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>831</fpage>-<lpage>839</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546512447792">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Felson</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An update on the pathogenesis and epidemiology of osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Radiol Clin North Am</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>, <fpage>v</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546512447792">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hegmann</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>GL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Associations of body mass index with meniscal tears</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>-<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546512447792">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fukubayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kurosawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The contact area and pressure distribution pattern of the knee: a study of normal and osteoarthrotic knee joints</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>871</fpage>-<lpage>879</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546512447792">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Best Pract Res Clin Rheumatol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>801</fpage>-<lpage>814</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546512447792">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kellgren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiological assessment of osteo-arthrosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. <year>1957</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>-<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546512447792">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Posterior root tear of the medial meniscus in multiple knee ligament injuries</article-title>. <source>Knee</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546512447792">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurosawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fukubayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Load-bearing mode of the knee joint: physical behavior of the knee joint with or without menisci</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0363546512447792">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of degenerative medial meniscus extrusion: radial component and knee osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>229</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0363546512447792">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic pullout suture repair of posterior root tear of the medial meniscus: radiographic and clinical results with a 2-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>951</fpage>-<lpage>958</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0363546512447792">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ozkoc</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Circi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonc</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Irgit</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pourbagher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tandogan</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radial tears in the root of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>849</fpage>-<lpage>854</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0363546512447792">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seedhom</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dowson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Proceedings: functions of the menisci: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. <year>1974</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0363546512447792">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Second-look arthroscopic findings after repairs of posterior root tears of the medial meniscus</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0363546512447792">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tibial meniscal dynamics using three-dimensional reconstruction of magnetic resonance images</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0363546512447792">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Utzschneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goettinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of a new method for the radiologic measurement of the tibial slope</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1643</fpage>-<lpage>1648</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0363546512447792">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vedi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tennant</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spouse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gedroyc</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meniscal movement: an in-vivo study using dynamic MRI</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>