<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VES</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spves</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vasc Endovascular Surg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Vascular and Endovascular Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1538-5744</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-9116</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1538574413493680</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1538574413493680</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Atypical Presentation of Priapism in a Patient With Acute Iliocaval Deep Venous Thrombosis Secondary to May-Thurner Syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Alhalbouni</surname>
<given-names>Saadi</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574413493680">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1538574413493680"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deem</surname>
<given-names>Samuel</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>DO</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1538574413493680">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abu-Halimah</surname>
<given-names>Shadi</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1538574413493680">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sadek</surname>
<given-names>Betro T.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1538574413493680">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mousa</surname>
<given-names>Albeir</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574413493680">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1538574413493680">
<label>1</label>Department of Vascular Surgery, Charleston Area Medical Center, West Virginia University, Charleston, WV, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1538574413493680">
<label>2</label>Department of Urology, Charleston Area Medical Center, West Virginia University, Charleston, WV, USA
</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1538574413493680">
<label>3</label>Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1538574413493680">Saadi Alhalbouni, Maimonides Medical Center, 4802 Tenth Avenue, Brooklyn, NY 11219, USA. Email: <email>saadieras@yahoo.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>488</fpage>
<lpage>492</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We report on a 42-year-old male who presented with priapism, severe scrotal swelling, and left lower extremity pain and swelling. Initial management of priapism failed, and he was noted to have both cavernosal and glandular venous obstruction. Computed tomography (CT) was performed and identified extensive acute thrombosis involving the distal inferior vena cava and the left iliac veins. Pharmacomechanical thrombolysis (PMT) was started over the course of two days. At completion of thrombolysis, the culprit lesion in the left common iliac vein was treated with angioplasty and stenting. His postoperative course was uneventful, and his priapism as well as the scrotal and leg swelling improved. He was discharged home on full anticoagulation. To our knowledge, this is the first available description of this rare presentation along with a literature review of the underlying vascular etiology for priapism.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>priapism</kwd>
<kwd>DVT</kwd>
<kwd>IVC</kwd>
<kwd>iliac</kwd>
<kwd>thrombosis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1538574413493680">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Priapism is defined as prolonged erection in the absence of physical or psychological stimulation lasting longer than 4 hours, and it constitutes a surgical emergency. There are 2 types of priapism, low flow (80%-90%) and high flow (10%-20%). Low-flow (ischemic) priapism typically presents with persistent engorgement of the corpora cavernosa with a flaccid glans penis. It can lead to subsequent penile necrosis if appropriate treatment is delayed.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1538574413493680">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574413493680"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574413493680"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1538574413493680">4</xref>
</sup> High-flow (nonischemic) priapism presents with persistent engorgement of both the corpora cavernosa and the glans penis.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574413493680">5</xref>
</sup> Although nearly two-third of the cases are secondary to identifiable causes, one-third of the cases occur without an identifiable cause (idiopathic).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574413493680">6</xref>
</sup> The pathophysiology of the disease can be neurogenic, arterial, or venous related. Common underlying causes may include leukemia, sickle cell anemia, erectile enhancing medications and devices, other medications, and drugs of abuse.</p>
<p>Ischemic priapism is considered a compartment syndrome of the soft tissue of the penis and can result in fibrotic changes and possible tissue loss.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574413493680">7</xref>
</sup> Proximal venous obstruction is a rare cause of ischemic priapism and can be difficult to manage. Here, we report a case of ischemic priapism and discuss the diagnosis and contemporary management of this disease.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1538574413493680">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 42-year-old male presented to our tertiary care facility with priapism for longer than 6 hours. He subsequently developed progressive severe left lower extremity and scrotal swelling. His initial management focused on workup and management of his priapism. The priapism was unique in that the entire penis was erect including the glans penis. With no history of pelvic trauma, nonischemic priapism was considered to be unlikely. Corporal blood gas analysis confirmed nonischemic priapism, and corporal irrigation with normal saline initially followed by phenylephrine failed to resolve the erection. A distal corporo-glandular shunt was performed immediately, with initial resolution but rapid return of the erection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1538574413493680">Figure 1</xref>). Common causes of priapism were investigated and ruled out, and no illicit drug use or erectile medication use was identified. Computed tomographic venogram was then performed and was remarkable for extensive acute thrombosis of the distal inferior vena cava (IVC) and the left iliac vein. An emergent vascular surgery consultation was obtained for acute thrombosis of the dorsal penile vein secondary to proximal venous occlusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1538574413493680">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1538574413493680">3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figures 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Venous-type priapism at presentation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Therapeutic heparin was started intravenously, and the patient was taken to the angiography suite. With the patient supine, the right common femoral vein was cannulated under ultrasound guidance. An IVC venogram was performed, and a retrievable IVC filter (Meridian, Bard Peripheral Vascular Inc, Tempe, Arizona) was placed. The patient was then turned to the prone position and, under ultrasound guidance, the left popliteal vein was accessed via a micropuncture technique, a 5F sheath was placed, and using a soft angled Glidewire and Glidecatheter (Terumo Interventional Systems, Somerset, New Jersey) we navigated through the occluded venous segments. We exchanged the Glidewire to the stiffer Supracore wire (Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, Illinois), and the 5F sheath was exchanged to a 7F sheath. A venogram showed complete occlusion of the left common iliac, external iliac, common femoral, and femoral veins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1538574413493680">Figure 4</xref>). Then, 2 rounds of AngioJet DVX (Medrad Interventional, Indianola, Pennsylvania) pharmacomechanical thrombolysis were performed. A compliant 12-mm balloon was used to dilate the iliac and common femoral veins, and 2 more rounds of pharmacomechanical thrombolysis were performed. A 50-cm thrombolysis catheter (Unifuse, AngioDynamics, Latham, New York) was inserted in the treatment zone, and thrombolysis was started at a rate of 1.2 mg/h of tissue plasminogen activator. Heparin was infused via the side port of the 7F sheath at a rate of 500 units/h. Laboratory parameters (Hematocrit, prothrombin time (PT), partial thromboplastin time (PTT), international normalized ratio, fibrinogen, and fibrin split products) were followed every 6 hours. The PT ≥18, PTT ≥120, platelets ≤100 000, or fibrinogen &lt; 200 mg/mL were the parameters indicating the need to stop thrombolysis. A tight ACE bandage (ACE<sup>TM</sup>, 3M<sup>TM</sup>, United States) dressing was applied from the foot up to the groin, and the patient was monitored in the surgical intensive care unit with bilateral 45° leg elevation with sequential compression devices on both calves. An angiogram of the iliac veins was performed 24 hours later (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1538574413493680">Figure 5</xref>), and a persistent significant thrombus burden was found in the iliac and femoral veins. Therefore, the catheter was left in place and thrombolysis resumed. A repeat venogram at 36 hours revealed 80% stenosis of the left common iliac vein, confirming the diagnosis of May-Thurner syndrome (MTS), and intravascular ultrasound was used to precisely measure the common iliac vein diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1538574413493680">Figure 6</xref>). A 16-mm self-expanding Wallstent (Boston Scientific, Natick, Massachusetts) was used, and the stent was postdilated with a 14-mm balloon. A final completion venogram was performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1538574413493680">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Computed tomography showing the priapism with thrombosis of the dorsal penile vein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Extensive left iliac deep venous thrombosis with extension to the inferior vena cava.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Venogram showing extensive left iliac deep venous thrombosis.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Interval improvement but still with severe culprit lesion as a result of May-Thurner syndrome at 24 hours.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Intravascular ultrasound showing severe stenosis in the left common iliac vein from May-Thurner syndrome.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-1538574413493680" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Completed venogram after angioplasty and stenting of left iliac veins.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413493680-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The popliteal sheath was removed, and a compression dressing was again applied over the entire left lower extremity. Full anticoagulation with heparin was resumed 4 hours after the procedure, and then the patient was eventually transitioned to Warfarin. The patient was discharged home on postoperative day 3 with thigh-high compression stockings (30-40 mm Hg), with interval improvement of the scrotal swelling and complete resolution of priapism. Full anticoagulation was continued for 6 months, and aspirin was continued indefinitely.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1538574413493680">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The name “priapism” is originally related to the Greek word “Priapos” which means god of fertility.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574413493680">5</xref>
</sup> Therefore, this is a misnomer as significant number of patients will have impotence or lower potency after the initial presentation.</p>
<p>Although it has been described in all ages, priapism mainly has a bimodal distribution, the first decade of life or between the third and fifth decades. Also, priapism has been reported in the first day of life.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1538574413493680">8</xref>
</sup> The incidence of priapism is estimated to be 1 case per 67 000 persons/year, with a significant increase to almost 3 cases per 100 000 persons/year after the third decade of life.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1538574413493680">9</xref>
</sup> Prolonged priapism can affect potency and even cause impotence.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1538574413493680">10</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The most common and most serious type is the ischemic low-flow venous type that requires prompt corporal aspiration with injection of sympathomimetic agents. Distal and then proximal cavernosal shunt procedures to divert blood flow into the corpus spongiosum can be considered if the aspiration therapy fails.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1538574413493680">11</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The timing of intervention is imperative in ischemic refractory priapism. One review evaluating the timing of intervention included 12 patients unresponsive to conservative measures, and 11 had undergone unsuccessful shunt surgery. The median duration of erection was 120 hours (range 60-700 hours). The authors concluded that early penile prosthesis placement for acute ischemic priapism is an effective and simple measure.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1538574413493680">12</xref>
</sup> Another review indicated that failure to respond to the conventional doses of an α-agonist will unlikely benefit from high-dose phenylephrine administration.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1538574413493680">13</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Treatments of high-flow priapism include selective ligation,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1538574413493680">14</xref>
</sup> or embolization of the cavernous artery with gelatin sponge<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1538574413493680">15</xref>
</sup> or with microemboli to achieve complete detumescence of the penis.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1538574413493680">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1538574413493680">17</xref>
</sup> Bastuba et al reported that embolization therapy is not only an effective therapy but is also associated with high preservation of premorbid erectile function.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1538574413493680">18</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Thrombosis of the corpus cavernosum can result in a low-flow, ischemic, and partial type of priapism.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1538574413493680">19</xref>
</sup> Intuitively, thrombosis of dorsal penile veins can lead to venous outflow obstruction. This report is the first description of venous-related priapism secondary to iliac vein thrombosis associated with MTS. Other reports have shown underlying thrombosis as an inciting element in the pathogenesis of priapism. A recent report on partial priapism secondary to proximal segmental corpora cavernosa thrombosis was treated with full anticoagulation with local injection of ethylephrine chloridrate. Although thrombosis resolved in 2 months, there was incomplete restoration of erectile function.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1538574413493680">20</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Small vessel vasculitis such as in Henoch-Schonlein purpura has been reported as a contributing factor for dorsal penile vein thrombosis with subsequent priapism.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1538574413493680">21</xref>
</sup> Another similar report described the association with deep venous thrombosis and priapism in patients with Behcet disease.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1538574413493680">22</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In conclusion, a better understanding of the underlying cause of priapism and prompt appropriate therapy in a timely fashion are crucial to achieving adequate outcomes. Evaluating patients with low-flow, ischemic-type priapism objectively with a venous imaging modality to define and rule out any underlying pathology of the venous system is warranted and may improve the outcome of this type of priapism.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1538574413493680">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1538574413493680">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1538574413493680">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dubin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Penile emergencies</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med Clin North Am</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1538574413493680">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Garrett</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rhamy</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Priapism: management with corpus-saphenous shunt</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>1966</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1538574413493680">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harmon</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nehra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Priapism: diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1538574413493680">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cherian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thwaini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kapasi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shergill</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Samman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medical and surgical management of priapism</article-title>. <source>Postgrad Med J</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>964</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1538574413493680">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pohl</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pott</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kleinhans</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Priapism: a three-phase concept of management according to aetiology and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Br J Urol</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1538574413493680">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaisary</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Aetiological factors and management of priapism in Bristol 1978-1983</article-title>. <source>Ann R Coll Surg Engl</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1538574413493680">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tay</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spernat</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rzetelski-West</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Appu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Love</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute management of priapism in men</article-title>. <source>BJU Int</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1538574413493680">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aktoz</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tepeler</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gündoğdu</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ozkuvanci</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Müslümanoğlu</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Priapism in the newborn: management and review of literature</article-title>. <source>Andrologia</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1538574413493680">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eland</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van der Lei</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stricker</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sturkenboom</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of priapism in the general population</article-title>. <source>Urology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>970</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1538574413493680">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adetayo</surname>
<given-names>FO</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome of management of acute prolonged priapism in patients with homozygous sickle cell disease</article-title>. <source>West Afr J Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1538574413493680">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harraz</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shindel</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lue</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation and management of priapism: 2009 update</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Urol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1538574413493680">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Salem</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>El Aasser</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Management of ischemic priapism by penile prosthesis insertion: prevention of distal erosion</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2300</fpage>–<lpage>2303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1538574413493680">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muneer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Minhas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ralph</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Investigating the effects of high-dose phenylephrine in the management of prolonged ischaemic priapism</article-title>. <source>J Sex Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2152</fpage>–<lpage>2159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1538574413493680">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ricciardi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bhatt</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cynamon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bakal</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Melman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Delayed high flow priapism: pathophysiology and management</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1538574413493680">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kojima</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanigawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kariya</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-flow priapism undergoing arterial embolization: review of literature following American Urological Association guideline on the management of priapism</article-title>. <source>Minim Invasive Ther Allied Technol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1538574413493680">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Benko</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stimac</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katusic</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Posttraumatic high-flow priapism: case report, current management options and literature review</article-title>. <source>Acta Clin Croat</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1538574413493680">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kerlan</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LaBerge</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ring</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Superselective microcoil embolization in the management of high-flow priapism</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Interv Radiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1 pt 1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1538574413493680">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bastuba</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saenz de Tejada</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dinlenc</surname>
<given-names>CZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sarazen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krane</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldstein</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arterial priapism: diagnosis, treatment and long-term followup</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>151</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1231</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1538574413493680">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ptak</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larsen</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beckmann</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boyle</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Idiopathic segmental thrombosis of the corpus cavernosum as a cause of partial priapism</article-title>. <source>Abdom Imaging</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1538574413493680">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pepe</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Panella</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Candiano</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, et al. <article-title>Partial priapism secondary to idiophatic segmental thrombosis of corpora cavernosa.</article-title> <source>Arch Ital Urol Androl</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1538574413493680">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sari</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Akar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Secil</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Thrombosis and priapism in a patient with Henoch-Schonlein purpura</article-title>. <source>Rheumatol Int</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>474</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1538574413493680">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ateş</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aydintuğ</surname>
<given-names>OT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Düzgün</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yaman</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sancak</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Omür</surname>
<given-names>ND</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Behcet's disease presenting as deep venous thrombosis and priapism</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>