<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spoto</journal-id>
<journal-title>Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0194-5998</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-6817</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599813481943</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0194599813481943</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>General Otolaryngology</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comparison of Plaintiff and Defendant Expert Witness Qualification in Malpractice Litigation in Otolaryngology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>Jean Anderson</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599813481943">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599813481943">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0194599813481943">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>Peter F.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599813481943">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Dharti</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599813481943">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Setzen</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0194599813481943">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0194599813481943">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>Soly</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599813481943">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0194599813481943">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0194599813481943">
<label>1</label>Department of Otolaryngology–Head &amp; Neck Surgery, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, New Jersey Medical School, Newark, New Jersey, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0194599813481943">
<label>2</label>Department of Neurological Surgery, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, New Jersey Medical School, Newark, New Jersey, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0194599813481943">
<label>3</label>Center for Skull Base and Pituitary Surgery, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, New Jersey Medical School, Newark, New Jersey, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0194599813481943">
<label>4</label>Rhinology Section, North Shore University Hospital, Manhasset, New York, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0194599813481943">
<label>5</label>Department of Otolaryngology, New York University School of Medicine, New York, New York, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0194599813481943">Jean Anderson Eloy, MD, Associate Professor and Vice Chairman, Director of Rhinology and Sinus Surgery, Department of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, UMDNJ–New Jersey Medical School, 90 Bergen St, Suite 8100, Newark, NJ 07103, USA. Email: <email>jean.anderson.eloy@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>148</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>764</fpage>
<lpage>769</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>7</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>19</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>6</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery Foundation 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Official journal of the American Academy of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0194599813481943">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>Malpractice litigation contributes to rising health care costs in the United States. The role of expert witness testimony has been controversial in the past, with medical professional societies issuing statements regarding ethical obligations of physicians. Our objectives were to examine the relative qualifications of expert witnesses testifying on behalf of plaintiffs vs defendants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0194599813481943">
<title>Study Design and Setting</title>
<p>Analysis of expert witness and physician demographic data available on several databases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0194599813481943">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>The Westlaw legal database (Thomson Reuters, New York, New York) was searched for otolaryngologist expert witness testimony. Length of experience, practice setting, and subspecialty training information were obtained from hospital, practice, departmental, and state licensing board sites. Scholarly impact was assessed using calculation of the <italic>h</italic>-index from the Scopus database.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0194599813481943">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Plaintiff expert witnesses had significantly less experience than those testifying for defendants (31.8 vs 35.4 years, <italic>P</italic> = .047) and lower scholarly impact (<italic>h</italic> = 6.3 vs 10, <italic>P</italic> = .045). A significantly higher proportion of defendant witnesses were in academic practice (49.3% vs 31.7%, <italic>P</italic> = .042). No differences were detected in postresidency fellowship training patterns.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0194599813481943">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Upon comparison of otolaryngologist expert witnesses, practitioners testifying on behalf of plaintiffs had statistically fewer years of experience, had a lower scholarly impact, and were less likely to work in an academic setting. Otolaryngologists who repeatedly served as expert witnesses were more likely to be testifying on behalf of plaintiffs than defendants. Professional societies need to frequently update guidelines on expert witness testimony and address the ethical obligations of practitioners.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>medical expert witness testimony</kwd>
<kwd>expert witness ethical obligations</kwd>
<kwd>medical malpractice</kwd>
<kwd>litigation</kwd>
<kwd>medicolegal</kwd>
<kwd>witness expertise</kwd>
<kwd><italic>h</italic>-index</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Medical malpractice litigation has increased since the early 1980s and has affected health care delivery in the United States through direct costs of legal proceedings and rising malpractice premiums,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0194599813481943">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0194599813481943">4</xref></sup> as well as indirectly by promoting the practice of defensive medicine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0194599813481943">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0194599813481943">6</xref></sup> Analyses of malpractice related to otolaryngology have found that in addition to procedure-specific considerations, factors such as perceived deficits in informed consent and undergoing allegedly unnecessary procedures may be present in a significant proportion of litigation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0194599813481943">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0194599813481943">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>Medical expertise is often difficult, if not impossible, to measure in an objective manner. In this regard, the nature of physician expert witness testimony in malpractice litigation has been contentious for many years. In one article from 1898, an author describes some of these issues, quoting a legal official discussing such physician expert witnesses: “they come with such a bias on their minds to support the cause in which they are embarked, that hardly any weight should be given to their evidence.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599813481943">15</xref></sup> In addition, the same article quotes another judge from the New York Court of Appeals sharing a similar opinion and stating, “There is no hypothesis so monstrous that an expert cannot be found to swear to it on the stand, and to defend it with vehemence when off the stand.” Over a century later, similar viewpoints may persist among many practitioners.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599813481943">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599813481943">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although the role of physicians serving as experts as well as what defines an expert are issues that may remain controversial, the legal community has established guidelines for establishing expertise. In <italic>Daubert v Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals</italic>, the US Supreme Court created a set of standards, now adopted by a growing number of states, that allow a judge to act as a “gatekeeper” for determining whether an expert is qualified to provide scientific and medical testimony.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599813481943">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599813481943">22</xref></sup> The main factors in this <italic>Daubert</italic> standard regard whether the expert witness in question has the technical or specialized knowledge to interpret the evidence and whether the expert has sufficient experience applying any underlying medical principles to the case at hand.</p>
<p>In all of these analyses, little attention has been paid to the qualifications of the expert witnesses involved in litigation. Expert witness testimony may certainly affect strategy involved in legal proceedings. Our objectives were to examine the relative qualifications of expert witnesses and compare those testifying on behalf of plaintiffs vs defendants. Although it may be impossible to assess objectively the relative skill of these witnesses, information regarding physician experience, scholarly impact, fellowship training status, and whether they are involved in medical education is available through several databases and is thus of value in assessing potential quality differences.</p>
<sec id="section6-0194599813481943" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>The Westlaw legal database (Thomson Reuters, New York, New York) was searched for malpractice litigation since 2008 involving otolaryngologists serving as expert witnesses using the search terms <italic>medical malpractice</italic> AND <italic>otolaryngology</italic> OR <italic>otolaryngologist</italic>. Since trends in malpractice litigation are dynamic as a result of technological innovations and changes in the law, this analysis focused on most recent malpractice cases. The Westlaw database, widely used by legal professionals, contains publicly available federal and state court records obtained by commercial vendors and has been previously used in analyses of various malpractice topics, including hearing loss,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599813481943">23</xref></sup> facial plastic surgery,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599813481943">13</xref></sup> corticosteroid use,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599813481943">24</xref></sup> tracheal stenosis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0194599813481943">11</xref></sup> recent otolaryngology litigation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0194599813481943">14</xref></sup> iatrogenic orbital injury,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0194599813481943">12</xref></sup> facial nerve paralysis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0194599813481943">7</xref></sup> and cranial nerve injuries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0194599813481943">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>The names and location of expert witnesses identified as otolaryngologists were recorded. An Internet search was conducted using each physician’s name along with the term <italic>otolaryngology</italic>. Multiple website sources were used to determine the year each otolaryngologist graduated from medical school. These sources included the following: (1) private practice sites, (2) medical facility and hospital sites, and (3) academic department websites. Online sites of state medical licensing boards were also used to gather and confirm these data for all practitioners included in this analysis. Graduation date from medical school rather than residency was used in this analysis, as the former is more widely available on individual state licensing board websites.</p>
<p>The same sources and methodology as above were used to determine fellowship training status as well as whether each individual is a full-time faculty member in an academic department. In addition, the scholarly influence of each otolaryngologist was assessed using the <italic>h</italic>-index. The <italic>h</italic>-index is an objective measure of the relevance and impact an author’s research contributions have had on scholarly discourse within his or her field.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0194599813481943">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0194599813481943">30</xref></sup> The Scopus database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scopus.com">www.scopus.com</ext-link>) is one of several resources that contains an <italic>h</italic>-index calculator and was used to calculate this score for all expert witnesses included in this analysis. When common surnames were searched in this database, such as <italic>White</italic> or <italic>Clark</italic>, a multitude of authors with these names may appear in the initial query. Location of practice, departmental affiliations, and the types of journals (ie, otolaryngology journals) were used to ensure that the Scopus <italic>h</italic>-index scores retrieved were calculated for the appropriate individual. All data were collected in December 2012. This study qualifies as exempt status per the “nonhuman subject research” protocol set by the Institutional Review Board of the University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, New Jersey Medical School, Newark, New Jersey.</p>
<sec id="section7-0194599813481943">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>A Student <italic>t</italic> test was used for comparison of normally (symmetric) distributed continuous data, and Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> tests were used for comparison of asymmetric data,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0194599813481943">31</xref></sup> with threshold for significance set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> analysis was used for comparison of categorical data. Statistical analysis was conducted using SPSS version 20 (SPSS, Inc, an IBM Company, Chicago, Illinois).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0194599813481943" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Initial results from the Westlaw database using the previously described search terminology produced 143 malpractice jury verdict reports since January 2008. From these trials, there were 82 otolaryngologist plaintiff expert witnesses and 79 defense expert witnesses. Several otolaryngologists served as expert witnesses in multiple trials; overall, there were 60 unique plaintiff expert witnesses and 69 unique defendant expert witnesses. Plaintiff expert witnesses had a fewer number of years of experience (mean ± SD, 31.8 ± 10.1; range, 8-48 years) than defendant expert witnesses (35.4 ± 9.82; range, 13-55 years; <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>P</italic> = .047) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). Amount of experience did not affect trial outcomes; cases in which a defendant otolaryngologist expert had more experience than his or her plaintiff counterpart were resolved with a defendant verdict 73.7% of the time, whereas cases in which a plaintiff otolaryngologist expert had more experience was resolved in the defendant’s favor 77.2% of the time (Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> test, <italic>P</italic> = .79).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0194599813481943" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of Plaintiff and Defendant Expert Witness Otolaryngologists.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0194599813481943" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599813481943-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Plaintiff</th>
<th align="center">Defendant</th>
<th align="center">Difference (95% Confidence Interval)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Experience, y</td>
<td>31.8</td>
<td>35.4</td>
<td>3.6 (1.9 to 5.4)</td>
<td>.047<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0194599813481943">a</xref></sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>h</italic>-index</td>
<td>6.3</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>3.7 (0.1 to 7.1)</td>
<td>.045<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0194599813481943">a</xref></sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Academic practice, %</td>
<td>31.7</td>
<td>49.3</td>
<td>17.6 (0.6 to 33.1)</td>
<td>.042<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0194599813481943">a</xref></sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fellowship trained, %</td>
<td>33.3</td>
<td>37.7</td>
<td>4.4 (–12.0 to 20.2)</td>
<td>.611</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0194599813481943">
<label>a</label>
<p>Statistically significant.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Individual scholarly impact, as measured by the <italic>h</italic>-index, was found to be lower among plaintiff experts (mean ± SD, 6.3 ± 9.4; median, 1; interquartile range [IQR] <italic>h</italic>, 0-9) than their defendant counterparts (mean ± SD, 10.0 ± 13.4; median, 6; IQR <italic>h</italic>, 0-15; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test, <italic>P</italic> = .045) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). Cases in which defendant otolaryngologist experts had a higher <italic>h</italic>-index than their plaintiff expert counterparts were resolved in the defendant’s favor 81.5% of the time, whereas this figure fell to 60.0% in cases in which plaintiff expert otolaryngologists had a higher scholarly impact. This difference, however, did not reach statistical significance (Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> test, <italic>P</italic> = .18).</p>
<p>Of the otolaryngologists serving as defendant expert witnesses, 49.3% are full-time faculty in an academic otolaryngology department, a statistically significantly higher proportion than the 31.7% of plaintiff expert witnesses serving in such a capacity (Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> test, <italic>P</italic> = .042) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). Upon examination for fellowship training patterns, there was a difference, as 33.3% of plaintiff expert witnesses had confirmed postresidency fellowship training vs 37.7% of defendant expert witnesses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). This difference, however, did not approach statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> = .61). The fellowship training status for a significant proportion of both plaintiff and defendant expert witnesses could not be determined (15.0% and 13.0%, respectively). The number of otolaryngologists testifying in multiple cases on behalf of the same side is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref>. In addition, 1 otolaryngologist testified on behalf of a defendant and plaintiff (1 time, respectively).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0194599813481943" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Expert Witnesses Testifying Multiple Times for the Same Side.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0194599813481943" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599813481943-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">No. of Times Testifying</th>
<th align="center">No. of Plaintiff Experts</th>
<th align="center">No. of Defendant Experts</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Two cases</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Three cases</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Four cases</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Eight cases</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0194599813481943" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Organizations including the American College of Surgeons (ACS) and the American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery periodically release guidelines on physicians acting as expert witnesses, emphasizing obligations and ethics involved in the process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0194599813481943">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0194599813481943">33</xref></sup> Explicitly mentioned is that physicians should uphold standards of impartiality and honesty, regardless of which side they are testifying on behalf of, and that compensation dependent on case outcome is unethical. In addition, the ACS states that physicians testifying should be ready to disclose compensation provided in return for their services, as well as how frequently they testify in malpractice litigation. Although these guidelines and the repercussions for deviating from them, both in reputation and from professional societies, are well recognized, the potential for unethical behavior certainly remains.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599813481943">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599813481943">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0194599813481943">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0194599813481943">35</xref></sup> In addition, there is no mention of guidelines for practitioners who choose to testify frequently. Further clarification of this issue may be needed, as it is currently unclear whether these physicians are violating any ethical obligations.</p>
<p>Although not in itself evidence of wrongdoing, the fact that multiple practitioners testified for the same side multiple times may potentially present a scenario of questionable ethics in some instances. For example, 1 Massachusetts otolaryngologist has testified as an expert on behalf of plaintiffs in 8 trials since 2008, without testimony for defendants during that time period (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref>). There were several otolaryngologists testifying for defendants multiple times during this time period, although only 1 testified more than twice. In many situations, expert witnesses refuse to testify against a colleague unless there is gross evidence of negligence, and it may be for this reason that many will testify more as a defense witness rather than as a plaintiff witness and many times will refuse any case as a plaintiff expert.</p>
<p>Further obfuscating the issue of expert witness service is the potential for opposing testimonies. When a jury of laypersons is exposed to completely different viewpoints for the same medical issue, with both experts being experienced and citing peer-reviewed medical evidence, the credibility of such testimony may diminish. Indeed, 1 analysis found that the presence of contrasting testimonies increased doubt of all expert testimony among jurors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0194599813481943">36</xref></sup></p>
<p>Defendant expert witnesses were found to have a statistically higher level of experience than their plaintiff counterparts (35.4 vs 31.8 years). The aforementioned <italic>Daubert</italic> ruling does explicitly mention sufficient experience as a qualification for expert testimony. Although this statistically significant discrepancy may certainly be important, another noteworthy finding was the paucity of early to mid-career experts in this sample. One potential reason for this is that although practitioners with over 30 years of experience may not be as operatively active as their younger colleagues,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0194599813481943">37</xref></sup> these witnesses may appear more credible as experts to juries, who comprise nonmedical laypersons. In addition, there is the possibility that this more experienced cohort may have more time to contribute toward legal proceedings as a consequence of operating less frequently. Last, another potential reason is that the judge presiding over a particular case may simply disqualify some of the less experienced otolaryngologists, as the <italic>Daubert</italic> standard specifically applies to the judge acting as a gatekeeper. Examining jury verdicts and reports, this study was not designed to address <italic>Daubert</italic> challenges, in which opposing counsel formally challenges the qualifications of a witness.</p>
<p>Although difficult to define objectively, scholarly impact is another potential way the expertise of an individual can be measured. The <italic>h</italic>-index is an objective bibliometric that takes into account the impact an author has had on a field by measuring how frequently an individual’s body of work is cited on a consistent basis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0194599813481943">25</xref></sup> For example, an individual has an <italic>h</italic> of 4 if he or she has had 4 publications cited at least 4 times each in the literature, regardless of his or her total number of publications. It becomes increasingly harder to achieve higher <italic>h</italic> levels, and this measure has been shown to correlate with scholarly impact among otolaryngologists, increasing with successive rank among academicians and other measures such as National Institutes of Health funding levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0194599813481943">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0194599813481943"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0194599813481943">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0194599813481943">38</xref></sup></p>
<p>In addition to reaching statistical significance, the difference in scholarly impact found in this analysis is meaningful. Considering a previous analysis examining scholarly impact among academic otolaryngologists, the calculated <italic>h</italic>-index for plaintiff experts (6.3) placed these witnesses at a level between an assistant professor and associate professor in an academic otolaryngology department, whereas the <italic>h</italic>-index for defendants (10.0) is right in between that of an associate professor and professor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0194599813481943">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>The practice setting of physicians may affect care and may provide insight into the level of expertise. Physicians working in academic centers often see more complicated cases referred from private practice settings and may be more up to date with technological advances within their field.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0194599813481943">39</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0194599813481943"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0194599813481943">41</xref></sup> A significantly higher proportion of defense expert witnesses were full-time faculty involved in an academic otolaryngology department than their plaintiff counterparts. This is another factor suggesting defense expert witnesses have greater expertise than otolaryngologists testifying on behalf of plaintiffs.</p>
<p>The difference in percentage of fellowship-trained otolaryngologists was not statistically significant in this analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599813481943"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). It should be emphasized that the presence of postresidency fellowship training could not be determined for a significant proportion (13.0%-15.0%) of otolaryngologists. Unlike year of graduation from medical school, some states do not provide comprehensive education information, such as whether a physician has undergone fellowship training. In addition, it is unclear how important fellowship training may be in expertise or whether it is more important than number of years of experience. Fellowship training in otolaryngology is a relatively recent trend for some of the otolaryngologic subspecialties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0194599813481943">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0194599813481943">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0194599813481943">43</xref></sup> Practitioners at or above the 20 to 30 years of experience range in this analysis may not have had the opportunity or needed to pursue fellowship training to gain special expertise within a subspecialty.</p>
<p>There may be several potential explanations contributing to the finding that defense witnesses tended to have more experience and a higher scholarly impact. One possibility is that physicians with greater expertise, whether through more experience, greater scholarly impact, or serving in an academic position, may fail to make themselves available for testimony on behalf of plaintiffs because of potential professional repercussions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599813481943">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0194599813481943">28</xref></sup> The relevance of the discrepancy in experience may be unclear, as some may question whether a difference in experience of 4 years equates to a real difference in expertise between plaintiff and defendant expert witnesses, especially among practitioners with over 30 years of experience. Nonetheless, this finding did reach statistical significance and cannot be ignored. Considered in combination with a statistical difference in scholarly impact and practice setting, a strong argument can be made that the witnesses testifying on behalf of defendants may have greater expertise than those testifying on behalf of plaintiffs.</p>
<p>There are several limitations inherent to such an analysis. One important issue deals with the question of how one goes about measuring expertise, as there may be many different definitions. Information such as how many procedures, relevant to a given case, a practitioner may have performed in his or her career may be one way of assessing expertise but is certainly not publicly available. In addition, there is not necessarily any agreed upon way of measuring the “skill” of testifying expert witnesses for the purpose of this analysis. Rather, we attempted to deal with this issue using several different publicly available and objective characteristics in an attempt to gauge expertise.</p>
<p>Another potential weakness is related to the use of Westlaw for legal information. Although this is a comprehensive database widely used by legal professionals, some analyses have pointed out that some cases included may be only those that are voluntarily reported by attorneys.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599813481943">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599813481943">24</xref></sup> It should be noted, however, that this analysis was not intended to assess overall prevalence of otolaryngology expert testimony, although upon contacting Westlaw, research support indicated that data collection patterns vary by jurisdiction, and most jurisdictions may label involuntarily reported cases as “anonymous” or “confidential.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599813481943">13</xref></sup> Many cases are settled before trial or are dismissed in summary judgment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0194599813481943">44</xref></sup> and thus may not be included in the publicly available federal and state court records the Westlaw database encompasses. Consequently, the cases included may have expert selection biases that are not obvious. One possibility is that physicians testifying exclusively for defendants in this analysis may testify for plaintiffs in cases not included in Westlaw. The testimony of these practitioners, who may have higher qualifications, may result in such cases being settled before progressing to the point at which they would appear in these publicly available court records.</p>
<p>With these limitations in mind, Westlaw has been used in previous analyses of malpractice litigation related to facial plastic surgery, facial nerve paralysis, hearing loss, and various other topics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0194599813481943">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0194599813481943">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599813481943">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599813481943">23</xref></sup> Another potential limitation is that we used Scopus to assess scholarly impact, as measured by the <italic>h</italic>-index. The <italic>h</italic>-index can be calculated using multiple available sources, such as Publish or Perish, Web of Science, and Google Scholar. Although results can vary among these sources, one analysis of the <italic>h</italic>-index in neurosurgery found a high degree of correlation between results from Google Scholar and Scopus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0194599813481943">45</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although a potential limitation could have been the ability of this study to detect differences between plaintiff and defendant expert witnesses, statistical analysis did reveal significant differences in experience, scholarly impact, and practice setting. Furthermore, as the <italic>P</italic> values were close to .05, the lower limit of the confidence intervals for the statistically significant findings approached but did not reach zero, suggesting that conclusions from this analysis are reliable.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0194599813481943" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Malpractice litigation contributes both direct and indirect costs to health care delivery in the United States. The role of expert witness testimony has been controversial in the past, with medical professional societies addressing statements regarding ethical obligations of physicians. Upon comparison of otolaryngologist expert witnesses, practitioners testifying on behalf of plaintiffs had statistically fewer years of experience, had a lower scholarly impact, and were less likely to work in an academic setting. One potential explanation for these findings may be that the stigma and potential repercussions associated with testifying on behalf of plaintiffs may discourage some practitioners who may be more qualified to serve as an expert witness. Otolaryngologists who repeatedly served as expert witnesses were more likely to be testifying on behalf of plaintiffs than defendants. Professional societies may need to update their guidelines on expert witness testimony and address the ethical obligations of practitioners who testify.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0194599813481943">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p><bold>Jean Anderson Eloy</bold>, conception, design, analysis, interpretation, revision, final approval; <bold>Peter F. Svider</bold>, conception, design, data acquisition, analysis, drafting, final approval; <bold>Dharti Patel</bold>, data acquisition, revision, final approval; <bold>Michael Setzen</bold>, analysis, revision, final approval; <bold>Soly Baredes</bold>, analysis, revision, final approval.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0194599813481943">
<title>Disclosures</title>
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> Michael Setzen is a speaker for TEVA on its Speakers Bureau for QNasl (not related to current subject).</p>
<p><bold>Sponsorships:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Funding source:</bold> None.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0194599813481943">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynn-Macrae</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynn-Macrae</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Emani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medicolegal analysis of injury during endoscopic sinus surgery</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>1492</fpage>-<lpage>1495</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0194599813481943">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frogner</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health spending in the United States and the rest of the industrialized world</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>903</fpage>-<lpage>914</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0194599813481943">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>2008 Exclusive Survey</collab>. <article-title>Malpractice premiums: dropping, but still high</article-title>. <source>Med Econ</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0194599813481943">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The malpractice liability crisis</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Radiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0194599813481943">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hermer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Defensive medicine, cost containment, and reform</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>-<lpage>473</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0194599813481943">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<article-title>Medical malpractice litigation raises health-care cost, reduces access, and lowers quality of care</article-title>. <source>J Med Pract Manage</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0194599813481943">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lydiatt</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medical malpractice and facial nerve paralysis</article-title>. <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0194599813481943">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lydiatt</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medical malpractice and the thyroid gland</article-title>. <source>Head Neck</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>-<lpage>431</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0194599813481943">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abadin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angelos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Malpractice litigation after thyroid surgery: the role of recurrent laryngeal nerve injuries, 1989-2009</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>718</fpage>-<lpage>722</lpage>; discussion <fpage>722</fpage>-<lpage>723</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0194599813481943">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sunaryo</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovalerchik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Characterizing liability for cranial nerve injuries: a detailed analysis of 209 malpractice trials</article-title> [published online January 29, 2013]. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.23995</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0194599813481943">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pashkova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Determination of legal responsibility in iatrogenic tracheal and laryngeal stenosis</article-title> [published online February 12, 2013]. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.23997</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0194599813481943">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovalerchik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Legal liability in iatrogenic orbital injury</article-title> [published online February 12, 2013]. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.24000</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0194599813481943">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zumba</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Setzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>From the operating room to the courtroom: a comprehensive characterization of litigation related to facial plastic surgery procedures</article-title> [published online January 8, 2013]. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.23905</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0194599813481943">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovalerchik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Determining legal responsibility in otolaryngology: a review of 44 trials since 2008</article-title> [published online January 15, 2013]. <source>Am J Otolaryngol</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2012.12.005</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0194599813481943">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The medical expert as a witness</article-title>. <source>Green Bag</source>. <year>1898</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>464</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0194599813481943">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ethics of serving as a plaintiff’s expert medical witness</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0194599813481943">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medical expert witness litmus</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>528</fpage>-<lpage>529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0194599813481943">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>DN</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Gauvin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Re: Ethics of serving as a plaintiff’s expert medical witness</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>137</volume>:<fpage>667</fpage>; author reply 667-669.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0194599813481943">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gorney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Expert witnesses: caught in a moral and ethical dilemma</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Coll Surg</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0194599813481943">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<italic>Daubert v Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals</italic>, 509 US 579 (<year>1993</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0194599813481943">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snider</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Standardizing the psychological autopsy: addressing the <italic>Daubert</italic> standard</article-title>. <source>Suicide Life Threat Behav</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>511</fpage>-<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0194599813481943">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vallabhajosula</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Gorp</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Post-<italic>Daubert</italic> admissibility of scientific evidence on malingering of cognitive deficits</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Psychiatry Law</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0194599813481943">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hearing loss resulting in malpractice litigation: what physicians need to know</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>112</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0194599813481943">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poetker</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medical malpractice and corticosteroid use</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>144</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0194599813481943">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An index to quantify an individual’s scientific research output</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>16569</fpage>-<lpage>16572</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0194599813481943">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choudhry</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choudhry</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The use of the <italic>h</italic>-index in academic otolaryngology</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0194599813481943">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanghvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Setzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is NIH funding predictive of greater research productivity and impact among academic otolaryngologists?</article-title> <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0194599813481943">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Setzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of fellowship training on research productivity in academic otolaryngology</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>2690</fpage>-<lpage>2694</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0194599813481943">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gender disparities in scholarly productivity within academic otolaryngology departments</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0194599813481943">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cherla</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gender disparities in research productivity among 9,952 academic physicians</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. In press.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0194599813481943">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The seven habits of highly effective data users</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>-<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0194599813481943">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>American College of Surgeons</collab>. <article-title>Statement on the physician acting as an expert witness</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wwwfacsorg/fellows_info/statements/st-8html">http://wwwfacsorg/fellows_info/statements/st-8html</ext-link>. <access-date>Accessed December 28, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0194599813481943">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery</collab>. <article-title>Statement on qualifications and guidelines for the physician expert witness</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wwwentnetorg/aboutus/Ethicscfm">http://wwwentnetorg/aboutus/Ethicscfm</ext-link>. <access-date>Accessed December 26, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0194599813481943">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robicsek</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Are thoracic surgeons ethically obligated to serve as expert witnesses for the plaintiff? Con</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>1137</fpage>-<lpage>1141</lpage>; discussion <fpage>1137</fpage>-<lpage>1141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0194599813481943">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reece</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janis</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Expert witness reform</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>2095</fpage>-<lpage>2100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0194599813481943">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovera</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effectiveness of opposing expert witnesses for educating jurors about unreliable expert evidence</article-title>. <source>Law Hum Behav</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0194599813481943">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Otolaryngologists older than 60 years: results of and reflections on survey responses from 865 colleagues regarding retirement</article-title>. <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0194599813481943">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svider</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pashkova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choudhry</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of scholarly impact among surgical specialties: an examination of 2,429 academic surgeons</article-title> [published online February 16, 2013]. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.23951</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0194599813481943">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Career moves: think twice about academia</article-title>. <source>Med Econ</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0194599813481943">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guglielmo</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Private practice or academia?</article-title> <source>Med Econ</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>, <fpage>56</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0194599813481943">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Balch</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shanafelt</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Satele</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freischlag</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distress and career satisfaction among 14 surgical specialties, comparing academic and private practice settings</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>254</volume>:<fpage>558</fpage>-<lpage>568</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0194599813481943">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ossoff</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>MM</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fellowship and career path preferences in residents of otolaryngology–head and neck surgery</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>882</fpage>-<lpage>887</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0194599813481943">
<label>43.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kingdom</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Citardi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fellowship training in rhinology: American Rhinologic Society survey of U.S. graduates</article-title>. <source>Int Forum Allergy Rhinol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>206</fpage>-<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0194599813481943">
<label>44.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lakdawalla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seabury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of medical malpractice litigation against US physicians</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>892</fpage>-<lpage>894</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0194599813481943">
<label>45.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Couldwell</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Use of the h index in neurosurgery. Clinical article</article-title>. <source>J Neurosurg</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>