<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Reprod Sci</journal-id>
<journal-title>Reproductive Sciences</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1933-7191</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1933-7205</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1933719112450329</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1933719112450329</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Serum Anti-Mullerian Hormone Levels Affect the Rate of Ongoing Pregnancy After In Vitro Fertilization</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Honnma</surname>
<given-names>Hiroyuki</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112450329">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1933719112450329"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baba</surname>
<given-names>Tsuyoshi</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1933719112450329">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sasaki</surname>
<given-names>Masahiro</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112450329">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hashiba</surname>
<given-names>Yoshiki</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112450329">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oguri</surname>
<given-names>Hisanori</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112450329">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fukunaga</surname>
<given-names>Takanori</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112450329">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>Toshiaki</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1933719112450329">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asada</surname>
<given-names>Yoshimasa</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112450329">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1933719112450329">
<label>1</label>Asada Ladies’ Clinic, Kasugai, Aichi, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1933719112450329">
<label>2</label>Department of OB&amp;GY, Sapporo Medical University School of Medicine, Sapporo, Japan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1933719112450329">Hiroyuki Honnma, Asada Ladies’ Clinic, Renak 5F, Matsushincho 1-4, Kasugai, Aichi 486-0931, Japan Email: <email>hihonma@sapmed.ac.jp</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>59</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Gynecologic Investigation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We used logistic regression analysis to investigate the relationship between serum anti-Mullerian hormone (AMH) levels and the rate of ongoing pregnancy. Retrospective data were collected from 1043 women who had undergone their first cycle of in vitro fertilization (IVF), including 540 cycles of fresh embryo transfer and 503 cycles of frozen-thawed embryo transfer. The patients were divided into 4 groups based on the cutoff values from a receiver–operating characteristic curve: 0.0 to 12.4, 12.5 to 25.5, 25.6 to 44.1, and &gt;44.2 pmol/L. After adjustment for multiple confounders, the serum AMH group was found to be significantly related to the rate of ongoing pregnancy in total cycles (0.0-12.4 vs 12.5-25.5 pmol/L; <italic>P</italic> = .0088, odds ratio, 1.909: vs 25.6-44.1 pmol/L; <italic>P</italic> = .0281, odds ratio, 2.109: vs &gt;44.2 pmol/L; <italic>P</italic> = .0008, odds ratio, 2.840). In conclusion, there appears to be a significant relationship between serum AMH levels and the ongoing pregnancy rate in first IVF treatment cycles after adjustment for multiple confounders.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>AMH (anti-Mullerian hormone)</kwd>
<kwd>IVF</kwd>
<kwd>pregnancy rate</kwd>
<kwd>logistic regression analysis</kwd>
<kwd>fresh embryo transfer</kwd>
<kwd>frozen-thawed embryo transfer</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1933719112450329">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>There have been several reports indicating that follicular fluid anti-Mullerian hormone (AMH) is predictive of cycle outcome (pregnancy rate) in in vitro fertilization (IVF) treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112450329">1</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112450329">2</xref></sup> In addition, it has also been reported that serum AMH levels may be similarly predictive of outcome in IVF treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1933719112450329">3</xref></sup>–<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1933719112450329">6</xref></sup> and that the higher number of available embryos in the high AMH population might result in higher cumulative pregnancy numbers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112450329">7</xref></sup> On the other hand, a number of studies have reported a negative correlation between pregnancy and serum AMH.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112450329">7</xref></sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1933719112450329"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1933719112450329"/>–<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1933719112450329">10</xref></sup> Although pregnancy outcome is multifactorial, this discrepancy likely reflects the fact that the underlying mechanisms relating serum AMH and pregnancy are still not fully understood, and there have been no studies investigating this relationship free of the confounding influence of the number of retrieved oocytes.</p>
<p>With the recent advent of embryo cryopreservation technology, which has led to a surplus of good quality embryos in a considerable proportion of IVF cycles and has diminished the incidence of ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS), frozen-thawed embryo transfer (F-TET) cycles have become an integral part of IVF treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1933719112450329">5</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1933719112450329">11</xref></sup> Moreover, although endometrial receptivity reportedly differs significantly between fresh embryo transfer (FET) and F-TET cycles,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1933719112450329">12</xref></sup> there have been few reports on the relationship between serum AMH and cumulative pregnancy rates that take F-TET cycles into consideration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1933719112450329">5</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1933719112450329">13</xref></sup> There have also been no reports separately examining the relationships between serum AMH and FET and F-TET cycles. In the present study, therefore, we investigated the relationship between serum AMH and the rate of ongoing pregnancy in first embryo transfer cycles, distinguishing FET from F-TET.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1933719112450329" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1933719112450329">
<title>Patients and Treatment</title>
<p>Patients undergoing their first assisted reproduction cycles of (n = 1060) between October 2008 and December 2010 were retrospectively evaluated. Inclusion criteria for this study were as follows: (1) the patient was in her first cycle of IVF treatment; (2) her age was &lt;45 years; (3) there was no evidence of an endocrinological disorder (normal prolactin and thyroid-stimulating hormone); (4) basal serum follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) levels were &lt;13.0 mIU/mL; and (5) body mass index (BMI) was &lt;30.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>In addition to the patient’s age, the IVF protocol selection was based on her basal serum FSH level, as follows (FSH level, protocol): serum FSH &lt;8.0 mIU/mL, gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) agonist long protocol (long protocol); serum FSH = 8.0-13.0 mIU/mL, GnRH agonist flare up protocol (short protocol); serum FSH &lt;8.0 mIU/mL with suspected of polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) and OHSS, GnRH antagonist flexible protocol (antagonist protocol).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1933719112450329">14</xref></sup> Patients with an irregular menstrual cycle and suspected of premature ovarian failure were not selected. There were 16 cancelations of embryo transfer cycles because there was no fertilized oocyte in 16 cycles of FET, and 1 cycle cancelation because of oocyte degeneration after warming in an F-TET cycle. These cycles were excluded from this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1933719112450329">
<title>The COH Protocol</title>
<p>The daily gonadotropin administered was either Menopur (Ferring Pharmaceuticals, Tokyo, Japan) or GONAL-f (Merck Serono, Tokyo, Japan). The starting dose of gonadotropin was based on the serum AMH level. Patients with serum AMH = 0.0 to 10.0 pmol/L were initially administered 300 to 450 IU of gonadotropin, while patients with serum AMH = 10.1 to 20.0 pmol/L received 225 to 300 IU of gonadotropin, and those with serum AMH &gt;20.0 pmol/L received 150 to 225 IU of gonadotropin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1933719112450329">15</xref></sup> Gonadotropin was administered for 4 to 5 days beginning on day 3 of the stimulation cycle, after which the dose was adjusted based on the ovarian response, which was monitored using transvaginal ultrasound and serum estradiol (E2) levels. Control of pituitary desensitization (GnRH agonist long and short protocol) and premature luteinizing hormone (LH) surge (GnRH antagonist flexible protocol, antagonist protocol) was assessed based on serum LH measurements. When 3 or more follicles reached a maximum diameter of 18 mm, urinary human chorionic gonadotropin ([hCG] 5000 or 10000 IU) was administered. Transvaginal oocyte retrieval was performed 34 to 35 hours after hCG injection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1933719112450329">15</xref></sup> Oocytes were fertilized conventionally or via intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI). Whether split (ICSI + conventional) or ICSI was indicated depending on the numbers of oocytes and oligozoospermia (total number of zoosperm&lt;10 × 10<sup>6</sup> determined using the swim-up method).</p>
<p>The cryopreservation criteria were (1) serum E2 &gt; 6000 pg/mL, (2) serum progesterone (P4) &gt;2.0 ng/mL at the day of hCG administration, and (3) symptoms of OHSS after oocyte retrieval. In the F-TET cycles, cryopreservation was performed at the pronuclear stage (D1) for all embryos. In the FET cycles, cryopreservation was performed at the blastocyst stage (D5-6) for surplus embryos. Embryo culture from the cleavage stage to the blastocyst stage was dependent on 3 or more high-quality embryos at D3 (6-8 cells at grade 1 or 2 according to Veeck classification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1933719112450329">16</xref></sup>).</p>
<p>The long protocol began with daily nasal buserelin 600 μg/d (Buserecure, Fuji Pharmaceutical, Tokyo, Japan) from day 21of the prestimulation cycle. The short protocol began with daily nasal buserelin 600 μg/d from day 3of the stimulation cycle. The GnRH agonist was continued until the day of hCG administration in both protocols. In the antagonist protocol, a GnRH antagonist, either Ganirelix (Ganirest, MSD, Tokyo, Japan) or Cetrorelix (Cetrotide, Nippon Kayaku, Tokyo, Japan), was administered when the leading follicle reached a maximum diameter of 14 to 16 mm or a premature LH surge was suspected based on serum LH monitoring.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1933719112450329">15</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1933719112450329">
<title>The FET Cycles</title>
<p>In the FET cycles, luteal phase support entailed intramuscular administration of depot progesterone (Proge Depot 125 mg; Mochida Co, Tokyo, Japan) in combination with oral micronized progesterone chlormadinone acetate (Lutoral) for the first 14 days after embryo transfer. The day of oocyte retrieval was counted as D0 and fertilized embryo transfer was performed from the cleavage stage (D2-D4) to the blastocyst stage (D5), depending on the number and morphologic quality of the embryos described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1933719112450329">
<title>Frozen-Thawed Embryo Transfer Cycles</title>
<p>All the F-TET cycles were carried out during artificial hormone replacement cycles. Transdermal E2 (Estrana, Hisamitsu Pharmaceutical, Tokyo, Japan) was used in combination with oral micronized progesterone chlormadinone acetate (Lutoral). Preparation of the endometrium was started on day 2 or 3 of the artificial hormone replacement cycle and entailed a step-up regime (1.44-5.76 mg).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1933719112450329">17</xref></sup> Endometrial thickness was evaluated on cycle days 9 to 11. A thickness of at least 7 to 8 mm with a serum E2 level of 150 pg/mL was required at that time. Oral progesterone was then started on cycle day 15. The day oral progesterone was started was counted as D0, and the fertilized embryo transfer was performed at the cleavage stage (D2-D4) or the blastocyst stage (D5), depending on the number of cryopreserved embryos and their morphologic quality after confirmation of their viability.</p>
<p>Single embryo transfer was mainly performed in the first treatment cycle, and the rate of single embryo transfer was &gt;90% across all cycles. In our criteria, double embryo transfer was performed when the patient’s age was high (&gt;39 years) and embryo quality was low; double blastocyst transfer was not performed in this study.</p>
<p>In both FET and F-TET cycles, urinary hCG was checked 14 days after embryo transfer and patients with hCG &gt;50 IU/L were considered pregnant. Transvaginal ultrasound was performed to confirm intrauterine pregnancy 1 week later, and fetal viability was assessed 3 weeks later. Ongoing pregnancy was determined after 12 weeks of pregnancy. Ongoing pregnancy also included confirmed live birth cases and excluded confirmed miscarriage cases occurring after 12 weeks of pregnancy.</p>
<p>This study was approved by the institutional review board and conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and written informed consent was obtained from all patients for AMH measurement and a description of their treatment outcome.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1933719112450329">
<title>Hormone Assays</title>
<p>Each patient’s age and BMI were determined on days 2 to 5 of the prestimulation cycle. At the same time, peripheral blood was collected, and serum AMH, basal FSH, and basal LH were determined as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1933719112450329">14</xref></sup> Briefly, the AMH concentration was measured in duplicate using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (EIA AMH/MIS A16507; Immunotech, Beckman-Coulter, Marseille, France). The conversion factor for the AMH concentration was 1.0 ng/mL = 7.143 pmol/L. Serum FSH, LH, E2, and P4 were measured using an automated electrochemiluminescence immunoassay via a Cobas e 411 Analyzer (Roche Diagnostics K.K., Tokyo, Japan).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1933719112450329">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>The distribution of variable data was assessed and normal or abnormal distributions were treated appropriately. Group characteristics were compared using the Mann-Whitney test. Values are presented as means (standard deviation). The χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112450329">2</xref></sup> test was used to evaluate the significance of the proportion (%) of pregnancy outcomes. Multivariate logistic regression analysis was used to test ongoing pregnancies and the day of embryo transfer with the measured parameter. Interaction tests in unadjusted logistic regression models were used to assess clinical factors that may affect the outcomes in the 2 groups. A receiver–operating characteristic (ROC) curve was computed to assess the predictive accuracy of serum AMH for ongoing pregnancy. The cutoff value was decided using Youden Index.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1933719112450329">18</xref></sup> These data analyses were performed using the statistical package StatView Ver. 5.0 (SAS Institute Inc, North Carolina) and Excel Statistics (SSRI, Tokyo, Japan). Values of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 were considered significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1933719112450329">
<title>Results</title>
<p>From October 2008 through December 2010, 1060 first IVF treatment cycles, excluding the mild stimulation protocol, were performed in our clinic. Among these cycles, there were 17 cycle cancelations. Therefore, a total of 1043 cycles, including 537 antagonist protocols, 453 short protocols, and 70 long protocols were investigated retrospectively. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1933719112450329">Table 1</xref> shows the patient characteristics for the total cycles as well as for the FET and F-TET cycles separately. Statistically significant differences between the FET and F-TET cycles were seen for serum AMH, basal FSH, serum E2 and P4 on the day of hCG administration, total number of oocytes, and the split/ICSI ratio. Indications for IVF were similarly distributed, except for tubal factor and anovulation (PCOS).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1933719112450329" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline Patient Characteristics With Comparison of the FET and F-TET Cycles<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1933719112450329" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112450329-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variables</th>
<th>Total Cycles</th>
<th>FET Cycles</th>
<th>F-TET Cycles</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Total cycles</td>
<td>1043</td>
<td>540</td>
<td>503</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td>34.7 (4.0)</td>
<td>35.5 (3.9)</td>
<td>33.8 (3.8)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Previous live birth</td>
<td>119 (11.4%)</td>
<td>68 (12.6%)</td>
<td>51 (10.1%)</td>
<td>.2145</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td>
<td>21.0 (2.1)</td>
<td>21.1 (3.0)</td>
<td>20.9 (2.9)</td>
<td>.116</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FSH, mIU/mL</td>
<td>7.6 (2.8)</td>
<td>8.1 (3.0)</td>
<td>7.1 (2.4)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LH, mIU/mL</td>
<td>5.7 (2.8)</td>
<td>5.4 (2.7)</td>
<td>5.9 (2.9)</td>
<td>.0018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serum AMH, pmol/L</td>
<td>30.3 (25.0)</td>
<td>20.2 (14.9)</td>
<td>41.1 (28.8)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Protocol</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Antagonist</td>
<td>535 (51.3%)</td>
<td>194 (36.0%)</td>
<td>341 (67.8%)</td>
<td rowspan="3">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Short</td>
<td>439 (42.1%)</td>
<td>305 (56.5%)</td>
<td>134 (26.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Long</td>
<td>70 (6.6%)</td>
<td>41 (7.6%)</td>
<td>29 (5.6%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Duration of stimulation, days</td>
<td>11.8 (1.7)</td>
<td>11.9 (1.9)</td>
<td>11.7 (1.5)</td>
<td>.0018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total dose of gonadotropin, IU</td>
<td>3577 (1144)</td>
<td>3918 (1175)</td>
<td>3213 (989)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peak E2, pg/mL</td>
<td>5969 (2988)</td>
<td>4391 (1879)</td>
<td>7660 (3033)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>P4, ng/mL</td>
<td>1.54 (1.51)</td>
<td>1.03 (0.41)</td>
<td>2.08 (2.00)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of total oocytes</td>
<td>16.4 (10.2)</td>
<td>11.1 (5.3)</td>
<td>22.2 (11.0)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of M2 oocytes</td>
<td>13.1 (8.6)</td>
<td>8.8 (4.8)</td>
<td>17.8 (9.3)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indication for IVF-ET</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male factor</td>
<td>388 (37.2%)</td>
<td>226 (41.9%)</td>
<td>182 (36.2%)</td>
<td>.0575</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tubal factor</td>
<td>131 (12.5%)</td>
<td>85 (15.7%)</td>
<td>46 (9.2%)</td>
<td>.0079</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Endometriosis</td>
<td>104 (10.0%)</td>
<td>46 (8.5%)</td>
<td>58 (11.5%)</td>
<td>.1047</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anovulation (PCOS)</td>
<td>203 (19.5%)</td>
<td>89 (16.5%)</td>
<td>114 (22.7%)</td>
<td>.0123</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unexplained</td>
<td>197 (18.8.%)</td>
<td>94 (17.4%)</td>
<td>103 (20.5%)</td>
<td>.2061</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Split</td>
<td>546 (52.3%)</td>
<td>245 (45.3%)</td>
<td>301 (59.7%)</td>
<td rowspan="2">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICSI</td>
<td>497 (47.7%)</td>
<td>295 (54.7%)</td>
<td>202 (40.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of embryo transfer</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1</td>
<td>979 (93.9%)</td>
<td>504 (93.3%)</td>
<td>475 (94.2%)</td>
<td rowspan="2">.4595</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2</td>
<td>64 (6.1%)</td>
<td>36 (6.7%)</td>
<td>28 (5.8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day of embryo transfer</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D5</td>
<td>737 (70.7%)</td>
<td>318 (58.9%)</td>
<td>419 (83.3%)</td>
<td rowspan="2">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D2-4</td>
<td>306 (29.3%)</td>
<td>222 (41.1%)</td>
<td>84 (16.7%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1933719112450329">
<p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; peak E2, serum estradiol at the day of HCG administration; serum P4, serum progesterone at the day of HCG administration; ICSI, intracytoplasmic sperm injection; split, conventional + ICSI; FET, fresh embryo transfer; F-TET, frozen-thawed embryo transfer; FSH, follicle-stimulating hormone; LH, luteinizing hormone; AMH, anti-Mullerian hormone; IVF, in vitro fertilization; PCOS, polycystic ovary syndrome; ICSI, intracytoplasmic sperm injection; SD, standard deviation; HCG, human chorionic gonadotropin.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1933719112450329">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Data are shown as means (SD) for each group, and the significance of differences between group characteristics were assessed using the Mann-Whitney test. The χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112450329">2</xref></sup> test was used to evaluate the significance of the proportions, number (%). Values of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 were considered significant.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section10-1933719112450329">
<title>Patient Characteristics Related to Ongoing Pregnancy for Total, FET, and F-TET Cycles</title>
<p>There were 416 patients (39.9%) with a positive pregnancy test and 317 (30.4%) who achieved an ongoing pregnancy among the total cycles. Comparison of the clinical and demographic characteristics of the patients with and without ongoing pregnancy among the total, FET, and F-TET cycles are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1933719112450329">Table 2</xref>. Notable features of the data are that serum AMH and age significantly differed between ongoing pregnancy and nonpregnancy in the total, FET, and F-TET cycles, whereas differences in basal FSH were only significant for the total cycles. The long protocol yielded higher ongoing pregnancy rates in the total, FET, and F-TET cycles than the antagonist or short protocol; these differences were statistically significant (χ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112450329">2</xref></sup>-test) in the total and FET cycles but not in the F-TET cycles. In addition, the pregnancy rate of the F-TET cycles was significantly higher than that of the FET cycles (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001), and D5 embryo transfer cycles produced a significantly higher pregnancy rate than D2-4 embryo transfer in the total, FET and F-TET cycles (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001, respectively).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1933719112450329" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Cycle Information and Ongoing Pregnancy in the Total, FET, and F-TET Cycles</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1933719112450329" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112450329-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="4">Total Cycles</th>
<th colspan="4">FET Cycles</th>
<th colspan="4">F-TET Cycles</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Variables</th>
<th>(+)</th>
<th>(−)</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sup>a</sup>
</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sup>b</sup>
</th>
<th>(+)</th>
<th>(−)</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sup>a</sup>
</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sup>b</sup>
</th>
<th>(+)</th>
<th>(−)</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sup>a</sup>
</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sup>b</sup>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Total cycles</td>
<td>317 (30.4%)</td>
<td>726</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>119 (22.0%)</td>
<td>421</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>198 (39.4%)</td>
<td>305</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AMH, pmol/L</td>
<td>38.6 (26.9)</td>
<td>26.8 (23.3)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>24.9 (18.7)</td>
<td>18.6 (13.1)</td>
<td>.0007</td>
<td>.0002</td>
<td>46.0 (27.1)</td>
<td>37.6 (29.6)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>.0020</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FSH, mIU/mL</td>
<td>7.1 (5.3)</td>
<td>7.8 (2.9)</td>
<td>.0012</td>
<td>.0002</td>
<td>7.8 (2.4)</td>
<td>8.2 (3.1)</td>
<td>.4024</td>
<td>.1966</td>
<td>7.3 (2.7)</td>
<td>6.8 (2.0)</td>
<td>.0531</td>
<td>.0115</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>P4, ng/mL</td>
<td>1.54 (1.02)</td>
<td>1.54 (1.59)</td>
<td>.8627</td>
<td>.9689</td>
<td>0.91 (0.38)</td>
<td>1.07 (0.41)</td>
<td>.0001</td>
<td>.0002</td>
<td>1.89 (1.46)</td>
<td>2.23 (2.32)</td>
<td>.0527</td>
<td>.1442</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age, years</td>
<td>33.1 (3.6)</td>
<td>35.3 (3.9)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>34.3 (3.6)</td>
<td>35.9 (3.9)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>32.5 (3.3)</td>
<td>34.7 (3.9)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peak E2, pg/mL</td>
<td>6649 (3102)</td>
<td>5685 (2893)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>4413 (1824)</td>
<td>4385 (1899)</td>
<td>.6931</td>
<td>.6605</td>
<td>8066 (2911)</td>
<td>7368 (3088)</td>
<td>.0154</td>
<td>.0222</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total dose of gonadotropin, IU</td>
<td>3230 (967)</td>
<td>3725 (1182)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>3683 (1013)</td>
<td>3995 (1215)</td>
<td>.0185</td>
<td>.014</td>
<td>2961 (805)</td>
<td>3404 (1072)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of total oocytes</td>
<td>19.5 (10.4)</td>
<td>15.1 (9.8)</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td>11.4 (4.6)</td>
<td>10.9 (5.6)</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.2275</td>
<td>24.1 (9.9)</td>
<td>20.7 (11.6)</td>
<td>.0001</td>
<td>.0025</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Protocol</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Antagonist</td>
<td>179 (33.5%)</td>
<td>356</td>
<td>.0007</td>
<td>.1275<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>48 (24.7%)</td>
<td>146</td>
<td>.0159</td>
<td>.6044<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>131 (38.4%)</td>
<td>210</td>
<td>.3675</td>
<td>.0241<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Short</td>
<td>108 (24.6%)</td>
<td>331</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>&lt;.0001<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>56 (18.4%)</td>
<td>249</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.002<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>52 (38.8%)</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.0019<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Long</td>
<td>30 (42.9%)</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>15 (36.6%)</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>15 (51.7%)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Day of embryo transfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D5</td>
<td>268 (36.4%)</td>
<td>469</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>82 (25.8%)</td>
<td>236</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>186 (44.4%)</td>
<td>233</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D2-4</td>
<td>49 (16.0%)</td>
<td>257</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>37 (16.7%)</td>
<td>185</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>12 (14.3%)</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1933719112450329">
<p>Abbreviations: +, positive for ongoing pregnancy; −, negative for ongoing pregnancy; peak E2, serum estradiol at the day of HCG administration; serum P4, serum progesterone at the day of HCG administration; SD, standard deviation; FET, fresh embryo transfer; F-TET, frozen-thawed embryo transfer; AMH, anti-Mullerian hormone; FSH, follicle-stimulating hormone; HCG, human chorionic gonadotropin.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1933719112450329">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Data are shown as means (SD) for each group, and the significance of differences between group characteristics were assessed using the Mann-Whitney test (<italic>P</italic>
<sup>a</sup>) and unadjusted logistic regression analysis (<italic>P</italic>
<sup>b</sup>). The χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112450329">2</xref></sup> test was used to evaluate the significance of the proportions (number (%)) (<italic>P</italic>
<sup>a</sup>). Values of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 were considered significant.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1933719112450329">
<p>
<sup>b</sup> Versus long protocol.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1933719112450329">
<title>Cutoff Values for Predicting Ongoing Pregnancy</title>
<p>The ROC analysis was used to evaluate the relationship between serum AMH and the likelihood of producing an ongoing pregnancy across the total cycles. The cutoff value for ongoing pregnancy versus nonpregnancy for the FET cycles was 12.4 pmol/L (ROC AUC = 0.603; sensitivity, 0.400; specificity, 0.795; odds ratio, 2.43; 95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.50-3.95); for the F-TET cycles, the cutoff was 25.5 pmol/L (ROC AUC = 0.617; sensitivity, 0.447; specificity, 0.763; odds ratio, 2.60 [95% CI: 1.59-3.49]); and for the total cycles, the cutoff was 19.3 pmol/L (ROC AUC = 0.655; sensitivity, 0.484; specificity, 0.759; odds ratio, 2.90 [95% CI: 2.16-3.90]). Next, the patients were divided into the following 4 groups based on the above cutoff values: 0.0 to 12.4, 12.5 to 25.5, 25.6 to 44.1, and &gt;44.2 pmol/L (cycles &gt;25.6 pmol/L were divided into 2 groups based on their cycle number).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1933719112450329">
<title>Logistic Regression Analysis of Ongoing Pregnancy</title>
<p>In our logistic regression analysis of ongoing pregnancy, the adjusted variables were determined using unadjusted logistic regression as follows. For total cycles, the variables were serum AMH group, basal FSH, age, peak E2, total dose of gonadotropin, total number of oocytes, selection of the protocol, and F-TET or FET. For FET cycles, the variables were serum AMH group, age, serum P4, total dose of gonadotropin, and selection of the protocol. And for F-TET cycles, the variables were serum AMH group, basal FSH, age, peak E2, total dose of gonadotropin, total number of oocytes, and selection of the protocol. In the total, FET, and F-TET cycles, serum AMH group was significantly related to the ongoing pregnancy rate adjusted for multiple confounders, including age and total number of oocytes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1933719112450329">Table 3</xref>). In the total cycles, the &gt;12.4 pmol/L groups showed ongoing pregnancy rates that were 2 to 3 times higher than the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group (odds ratio: 1.909-2840). We also found that the statistical significance of the relationship between serum AMH level and ongoing pregnancy was strong when serum AMH was considered in the aforementioned groups but was weaker when serum AMH was considered as a continuous variable (<italic>P</italic> = .0453; odds ratio: 1.039 per 7.14 pmol/L increase; 95% CI: 1.001-1.088). Surprisingly, in the FET cycles, the &gt;12.4 pmol/L groups showed an ongoing pregnancy rate that was 3.8 to 7.4 times higher than the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group (odds ratio: 3.863-7.454); however, the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group did not significantly differ from the 25.6 to 44.1 pmol/L group. Age was also significantly related to ongoing pregnancy, with the rate being nearly the same in the total, FET, and F-TET cycles. By contrast, basal FSH was not related to the ongoing pregnancy rate adjusted for confounders in the total, FET, or F-TET cycles.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1933719112450329" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression Analysis of Ongoing Pregnancy in Total, FET, and F-TET Cycles<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1933719112450329" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112450329-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Ongoing Pregnancy</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Variables</th>
<th>Odds Ratio</th>
<th>95% CI</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Total cycles</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Serum AMH group (vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  12.5-25.5 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>1.909</td>
<td>1.188-3.295</td>
<td>.0088</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  25.6-41.1 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>2.179</td>
<td>1.098-3.846</td>
<td>.0281</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  41.2&gt; vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>2.84</td>
<td>1.468-5.512</td>
<td>.0008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age (1 year increase)</td>
<td>0.899</td>
<td>0.863-0.936</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> F-TET vs FET</td>
<td>1.47</td>
<td>1.031-2.026</td>
<td>.0325</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Protocol (vs long)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Antagonist vs long</td>
<td>0.536</td>
<td>0.315-0.913</td>
<td>.0218</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Short vs long</td>
<td>0.519</td>
<td>0.288-0.932</td>
<td>.0282</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">FET cycles</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Serum AMH group (vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  12.5-25.5 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>2.064</td>
<td>1.144-3.724</td>
<td>.016</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  25.6-41.1 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>1.249</td>
<td>0.559-2.792</td>
<td>.5875</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  41.2&gt; vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>2.324</td>
<td>1.021-5.289</td>
<td>.0444</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age (1 year increase)</td>
<td>0.912</td>
<td>0.869-0.977</td>
<td>.0058</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Serum P4 (1.00 ng/mL increase)</td>
<td>0.354</td>
<td>0.196-0.639</td>
<td>.0006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Protocol (vs long)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Short vs long</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>0.301-03864</td>
<td>.0123</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">F-TET cycles</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Serum AMH group (vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  12.5-25.5 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>3.863</td>
<td>1.203-12.406</td>
<td>.023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  25.6-41.1 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>6.152</td>
<td>1.721-21.987</td>
<td>.0052</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  41.2&gt; vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>7.454</td>
<td>2.109-26.348</td>
<td>.0018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age (1 year increase)</td>
<td>0.882</td>
<td>0.832-1.032</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1933719112450329">
<p>Abbreviations: serum P4, serum progesterone at the day of HCG administration; CI, confidence interval; FET, fresh embryo transfer; F-TET, frozen-thawed embryo transfer; AMH, anti-Mullerian hormone; HCG, human chorionic gonadotropin.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1933719112450329">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Adjusted variables selected by unadjusted logistic regression analysis: for total cycles, serum AMH group, basal FSH, age, number of total oocytes, peak E2, total dose of gonadotropin, selection of protocol and F-TET/FET; for FET cycles, serum AMH group, age, serum progesterone, total dose of gonadotropin and selection of protocol; for F-TET cycles, serum AMH group, basal FSH, age and number of total oocytes, peak E2, total dose of gonadotropin and selection of protocol. For the serum AMH groups, the reference group is the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group; for F-TET vs FET, the reference group is FET cycles; for the selection of protocol, the reference group is long protocol. Variables considered significant was described in the table. Values of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 were considered significant.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1933719112450329">
<title>Adjusted and Nonadjusted Ongoing Pregnancy Rate in Total Cycles</title>
<p>The nonadjusted serum AMH levels and ongoing pregnancy rates across the total cycles were as follows (nonadjusted serum AMH, (n [%])): 0.0 to 12.4 pmol/L, (28 of 234 [12.0%]); 12.5-25.5 pmol/L, (51 of 200 [25.5%]); 25.6 to 44.1 pmol/L, (98 of 304 [32.2%]); and &gt;44.2 pmol/L, (136 of 305 [44.6%]). The adjusted values were (adjusted serum AMH, (odds ratio [%])): 0.0 to 12.4 pmol/L, (referent [12.0%]); 12.5 to 25.5 pmol/L, (1.909 [22.9%]); 25.6 to 44.1 pmol/L, (2.179 [26.1%]); and &gt;44.2 pmol/L, (2.840 [34.1%]). The nonadjusted and adjusted ongoing pregnancy rates are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1933719112450329">Figure 1</xref>. The linear approximation shows that the nonadjusted ongoing pregnancy rate increased linearly with the increases in serum AMH; the adjusted ongoing pregnancy rate increased similarly but more gradually. Notably, the adjusted ongoing pregnancy rate in the 12.5 to 25.5 pmol/L group was twice that in the 0.0 to 12.4 pmol/L group and then successively increased in the &gt;25.6 pmol/L groups.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1933719112450329" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Adjusted and nonadjusted ongoing pregnancy rates in 4 serum AMH groups. Patients were divided into the 4 indicated groups based on cutoff values for the rates of ongoing pregnancy. The adjusted ongoing pregnancy rate was referenced to the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group and was adjusted for serum AMH group, basal FSH, age, peak serum E2, total dose of gonadotropin, total number of oocytes, and selection of the protocol and F-TET/FET cycles. Linear approximations are also shown for the adjusted and nonadjusted pregnancy rates. FET indicates fresh embryo transfer; F-TET, frozen-thawed embryo transfer; FSH, follicle-stimulating hormone; AMH, anti-Mullerian hormone</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112450329-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1933719112450329">
<title>Logistic Regression Analysis of Variables and the Day of Embryo Transfer</title>
<p>Finally, we carried out a logistic regression analysis of the day of embryo transfer, adjusting for serum AMH group, basal FSH, age, peak E2, total dose of gonadotropin, total number of oocytes, and selection of the protocol and FET/F-TET. Adjusted variables were determined using unadjusted logistic regression. Serum AMH group, age, peak E2, and total number of oocytes showed significant effects; basal FSH did not show a significant relation to the day of embryo transfer. In the total cycles, the D5 embryo transfer rate in the 12.5 to 25.5 pmol/L group was 1.5 times higher than in the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group and then successively increased in the &gt;25.6 pmol/L groups, like the ongoing pregnancy rate (odds ratio: 1.538-2.357; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1933719112450329">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1933719112450329" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression Analysis of the Day of Embryo Transfer Associated With D5 Embryo Transfer Rate<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1933719112450329" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112450329-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variables</th>
<th>Odds Ratio</th>
<th>95% CI</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Serum AMH group (vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 12.5-25.5 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>1.538</td>
<td>1.041-2.272</td>
<td>.0305</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 25.6-41.1 vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>1.657</td>
<td>1.001-2.840</td>
<td>.0461</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 41.2&gt; vs &lt;12.4 pmol/L</td>
<td>2.357</td>
<td>1.326-4.024</td>
<td>.0005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (1year increase)</td>
<td>0.918</td>
<td>0.881-0.957</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peak E2 (1000 pg/mL increase)</td>
<td>1.102</td>
<td>1.023-1.182</td>
<td>.0116</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of total oocytes (1 follicle increase)</td>
<td>1.071</td>
<td>1.038-1.104</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn8-1933719112450329">
<p>Abbreviations: peak E2, serum estradiol at the day of HCG administration; CI, confidence interval; AMH, anti-Mullerian hormone; FET, fresh embryo transfer; F-TET, frozen-thawed embryo transfer; HCG, human chorionic gonadotropin.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-1933719112450329">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Reference group is D5 embryo transfer. Adjusted variables selected by unadjusted logistic regression analysis: serum AMH group, basal FSH, age, peak E2, total dose of gonadotropin, number of total oocytes, selection of protocol and F-TET/FET. For the serum AMH groups, the reference group is the &lt;12.4 pmol/L group; for F-TET versus FET, the reference group is FET cycles; for the selection of protocol, the reference group is long protocol. Variables considered significant were described in the table. Values of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 were considered significant.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1933719112450329">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This retrospective study involved a large population of patients undergoing their first IVF treatment cycle. The logistic regression analysis showed that serum AMH levels are significantly related to the rate of ongoing pregnancy across total, FET, and F-TET cycles, despite adjustment for multiple confounders, including age and total number of oocytes. Serum FSH did not relate to the ongoing pregnancy rate, irrespective of treatment cycle. On the other hand, the adjusted ongoing pregnancy rate increased with increases in the serum AMH level, and the predictive accuracy of serum AMH for pregnancy versus nonpregnancy using the cutoff value determined through ROC analysis was significant, but it showed that serum AMH might be an average predictor from ROC-AUCs. However, the predictive accuracy of serum AMH was not as good when it was considered as a continuous variable. Based on these and earlier findings,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1933719112450329">4</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1933719112450329">6</xref></sup> we hypothesize that a threshold level of serum AMH is important for pregnancy. Our logistic regression analysis also suggested that serum AMH is related to D3 embryo quality. We suggest that this result explains in part the relationship between serum AMH and ongoing pregnancy.</p>
<p>In our logistic regression analysis of the relationship between serum AMH groups and the rate of ongoing pregnancy, we adjusted for multiple confounders, including age and total number of oocytes. This analysis revealed that serum AMH was significantly related to the rate of ongoing pregnancy in the total, FET, and F-TET cycles. Basal FSH was not significantly related to the ongoing pregnancy rate, which is consistent with an earlier report that basal FSH is a poor predictor of ongoing pregnancy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112450329">19</xref></sup> Interestingly, the total number of oocytes, peak E2, and total dose of gonadotropin were not significantly related to the ongoing pregnancy rate for total, FET, or F-TET cycles adjusted for serum AMH. We suspect this reflects the close relationship between serum AMH and the ovarian response.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1933719112450329">13</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1933719112450329">20</xref></sup> Prediction of pregnancy based on serum AMH cutoff values determined by ROC analysis was significant (χ<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112450329">2</xref></sup> test) for the total, FET, and F-TET cycles. Pregnancy prediction was less accurate when based on ROC-AUCs (total cycles, 0.655; FET cycles, 0.603; F-TET cycles, 0.617), although our values are similar to those reported previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1933719112450329">5</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1933719112450329">21</xref></sup> This may be because serum AMH measurements reflect the total pool of AMH-producing follicles; consequently, the measured levels may not be sufficiently precise to discriminate pregnancy from any one AMH-producing follicle.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112450329">1</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>We also found that the adjusted ongoing pregnancy rate nearly doubled as serum AMH increased from &lt;12.4 to 12.5-25.5 pmol/L, and then increased at a more gradual constant rate as serum AMH increased further. The statistical significance of the effect of serum AMH on the ongoing pregnancy rate was stronger when 4 discrete groups were considered than when the effect was considered as a continuous variable. Nelson et al reported that the live birth rate gradually increased with increasing serum AMH levels under 7.8 pmol/L, but there was no discrimination at higher levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1933719112450329">4</xref></sup> However, their study was not adjusted for confounders, and serum AMH was comparatively low in their study population (median, 9.3 pmol/L) as compared to ours (median, 22.7 pmol/L), which may have influenced the results. Among other studies on the dependence of pregnancy rate on serum AMH,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1933719112450329">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1933719112450329">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1933719112450329">13</xref></sup> Blazar et al reported that pregnancy rate increased with increases in serum AMH adjusted for age and basal FSH. Nonetheless, women with very low serum AMH levels do become pregnant at a reasonable rate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1933719112450329">23</xref></sup> Based on our results and those of others, we suggest that the effect of serum AMH on the rate of ongoing pregnancy is stronger in populations where serum AMH is relatively low than in populations where it is higher. This is consistent with our aforementioned hypothesis that a threshold level of serum AMH is important for achieving a particular rate of ongoing pregnancy and is similar to the relationship between age and pregnancy rate. We also suggest that the serum AMH level is closely related to the ovarian reserve and might be of secondary importance for ongoing pregnancy, with the most important factor for pregnancy being age.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1933719112450329">24</xref></sup> This is consistent with our finding that age was significantly related to ongoing pregnancy in the total, FET, and F-TET cycles (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). It would be desirable to accurately determine a cutoff value for serum AMH below which the pregnancy rate from IVF treatment would be significantly diminished. This cutoff value could be useful for subfertile patients who could receive assisted reproduction on that basis.</p>
<p>Our logistic regression analysis of the effect of day of embryo transfer showed that across total cycles, serum AMH was significantly related to D5 embryo transfer when adjusted for age and other confounders. Our criterion for embryo development to the blastocyst stage was the presence of 3 or more high-quality embryos at D3. Our finding suggests that serum AMH might be related to embryo quality at D3 when adjusted for confounders. In that context, high serum AMH could be predictive of the presence of high-quality embryos on D3 and could potentially improve the rates of embryo development to the blastocyst stage, (single) blastocyst transfer, and pregnancy. To test that idea, it will be necessary to evaluate the relationships between embryo quality at D3/D5, embryo developmental speed, and serum AMH level. In the present study, these relationships were evaluated only indirectly, and embryo quality was not investigated.</p>
<p>Ovarian reserve currently refers to both the number and quality of oocytes within the ovary. Ovarian aging is said to reduce the follicular pool and thus oocyte quality through granulosa cell apoptosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112450329">19</xref></sup> We suggest that reductions in serum AMH due to ovarian aging reflects not only a reduction in the size of the primordial follicle pool but also an increasing rate of per-follicle granulosa cell apoptosis, which would be expected to reduce the per-follicle production of AMH and diminish oocyte quality.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1933719112450329">4</xref></sup><sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1933719112450329">24</xref></sup> There have been several reports that diminished ovarian reserve might lead to trisomic pregnancy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1933719112450329">25</xref></sup>–<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1933719112450329">27</xref></sup> Notably, van der Stroom et al reported that mothers with a Down syndrome pregnancy had serum AMH values that were significantly lower than in their age-matched controls.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1933719112450329">26</xref></sup> They also suggested the possibility that a diminished follicular pool could lead to a reduction in oocytes quality due to meiotic errors. Moreover, Li et al reported that in intrauterine insemination cycles, serum AMH remained the only significant predictor of cumulative live birth after controlling for confounders such as age and FSH.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1933719112450329">22</xref></sup> Based on our findings and those of earlier studies, we suspect that serum AMH levels could be used as an indicator of high or low responsiveness to IVF treatment and as an indicator, along with age, for counseling patients with respect to their expectations for pregnancy and birth during assisted reproduction. This would likely be of particular benefit, psychologically and physically, to patients receiving their first IVF treatment.</p>
<p>Although this study included a relatively large population, limitations of the study are that it was conducted retrospectively and live birth rates were not examined. Moreover, patients receiving F-TET cycles were high responders as compared to those receiving FET cycles, and this difference in the patients’ characteristics might have affected the results of this study. In addition, urinary hCG, which could affect protocol selection and gonadotropin dosage, was administered for oocyte maturation in all cycles. Therefore, a future prospective study of the relationship between serum AMH levels and live birth rates is needed to confirm our results.</p>
<p>In sum, our study clearly shows that there was a significant relationship between serum AMH levels and the rate of ongoing pregnancy among 1043 women receiving their first IVF treatment (FET or F-TET cycles). To the best of our knowledge, this is the largest retrospective analysis of the relationship between serum AMH and the rate of ongoing pregnancy after first treatment cycles. Although our ROC-AUCs and previous studies indicate that the predictive accuracy of serum AMH levels for pregnancy is not strong, it appears that serum AMH may be related to the pregnancy rate and D3 embryo quality when adjusted for age, total number of oocytes, and other confounders. We hypothesize a threshold level of serum AMH may be an important factor affecting the pregnancy rate after IVF treatment. We will test that hypothesis and confirm the relationship between serum AMH, embryo quality, and embryo development in the future.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgment</title>
<p>We thank the nursing and embryology staffs of the Asada Ladies Clinic for their expert technical help.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1933719112450329"><label>Authors’ Contributions</label>
<p>HH conceived the study and the design. TB carried out the bibliographic research and MS drafted the manuscript. YH and HO helped draft the manuscript. TF carried out statistical analyses. TE analyzed the results. YA participated in the study as project supervisor coordinator overseeing the critical revision of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-1933719112450329"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1933719112450329"><label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1933719112450329">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fanchin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mendez Lozano</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frydman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone concentrations in the follicular fluid of the preovulatory follicle are predictive of the implantation potential of the ensuing embryo obtained by in vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1796</fpage>–<lpage>1802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1933719112450329">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fujito</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kazuka</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sugiyama</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isaka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone substance from follicular fluid is positively associated with success in oocyte fertilization during in vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1933719112450329">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Silberstein</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacLaughlin</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shai</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Mullerian inhibiting substance levels at the time of HCG administration in IVF cycles predict both ovarian reserve and embryo morphology</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1933719112450329">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yates</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyall</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone-based approach to controlled ovarian stimulation for assisted conception</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1933719112450329">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>HW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morrell</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pickering</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thong</surname>
<given-names>KJ.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Anti-mullerian hormone and cumulative pregnancy outcome in in-vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source>J Assist Reprod Genet</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1933719112450329">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blazar</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lambert-Messerlian</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hackett</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krotz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robins</surname>
<given-names>JC.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Use of in-cycle antimullerian hormone levels to predict cycle outcome</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>205</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<comment>223</comment>.<fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>e5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1933719112450329">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>La Marca</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sighinolfi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone (AMH) as a predictive marker in assisted reproductive technology (ART)</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod Update</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1933719112450329">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lie Fong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baart</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martini</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone: a marker for oocyte quantity, oocyte quality and embryo quality?</article-title> <source>Reprod Biomed Online</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>664</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1933719112450329">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guerif</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemseffer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Couet</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gervereau</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ract</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Royere</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Serum antimullerian hormone is not predictive of oocyte quality in vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source>Ann Endocrinol (Paris)</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1933719112450329">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Riggs</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kimble</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oehninger</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone serum levels predict response to controlled ovarian hyperstimulation but not embryo quality or pregnancy outcome in oocyte donation</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1933719112450329">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Honnma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Continuation of GnRH agonist administration for 1 week, after hCG injection, prevents ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome following elective cryopreservation of all pronucleate embryos</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2548</fpage>–<lpage>2551</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1933719112450329">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daneshmand</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garner</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aguirre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hudson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of impaired endometrial receptivity after ovarian stimulation for in vitro fertilization: a prospective randomized trial comparing fresh and frozen-thawed embryo transfers in high responders</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1933719112450329">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lekamge</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barry</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kolo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gilchrist</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tremellen</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anti-Mullerian hormone as a predictor of IVF outcome</article-title>. <source>Reprod Biomed Online</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1933719112450329">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Honnma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baba</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sasaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Different ovarian response by age in an anti-Müllerian hormone-matched group undergoing in vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source>J Assist Reprod Genet</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1933719112450329">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Honnma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hashiba</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Asada</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Failure of triggering oocyte maturation with a GnRH agonist in polycystic ovary syndrome: two case reports</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1933719112450329">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Veeck</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Oocyte assessment and biological performance</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>541</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1933719112450329">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kadowaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tanaka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hashimoto</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kokeguchi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shiotani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of pregnancy rate by blastocyst morphological score and age, based on 1,488 single frozen-thawed blastocyst transfer cycles</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>948</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1933719112450329">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Akobeng</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Understanding diagnostic tests 3: receiver operating characteristic curves</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1933719112450329">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bancsi</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huijs</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>den Ouden</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Basal follicle-stimulating hormone levels are of limited value in predicting ongoing pregnancy rates after in vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1933719112450329">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gnoth</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schuring</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friol</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tigges</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mallmann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Godehardt</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relevance of anti-Mullerian hormone measurement in a routine IVF program</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1359</fpage>–<lpage>1365</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1933719112450329">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>HW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lau</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating the performance of serum antimullerian hormone concentration in predicting the live birth rate of controlled ovarian stimulation and intrauterine insemination</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2177</fpage>–<lpage>2181</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1933719112450329">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weghofer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dietrich</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barad</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gleicher</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Live birth chances in women with extremely low-serum anti-Mullerian hormone levels</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1905</fpage>–<lpage>1909</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1933719112450329">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Douglas</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nakhuda</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>The association between anti-Mullerian hormone and IVF pregnancy outcomes is influenced by age</article-title>. <source>Reprod Biomed Online</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>761</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1933719112450329">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ebner</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sommergruber</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shebl</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schreier-Lechner</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tews</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Basal level of anti-Mullerian hormone is associated with oocyte quality in stimulated cycles</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2022</fpage>–<lpage>2026</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1933719112450329">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Haadsma</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mooij</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Groen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>A reduced size of the ovarian follicle pool is associated with an increased risk of a trisomic pregnancy in IVF-treated women</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1933719112450329">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van der Stroom</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Konig</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Dulmen-den Broeder</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Early menopause in mothers of children with Down syndrome?</article-title> <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>985</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1933719112450329">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kline</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kinney</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Warburton</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Trisomic pregnancy and elevated FSH: implications for the oocyte pool hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1537</fpage>–<lpage>1550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>