<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">QRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spqrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Qualitative Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1468-7941</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3109</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468794112443475</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1468794112443475</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On the road in Highlands Papua New Guinea: intimacy and ethnographic method</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>Neil</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1468794112443475">The University of Sydney, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1468794112443475">Neil Maclean, Department of Anthropology, School of Social and Political Sciences, University of Sydney, Mills Building A26, Sydney, NSW 2006, Australia. Email: <email>neil.maclean@sydney.edu.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Revelatory moments in ethnographic research</issue-title>
<fpage>575</fpage>
<lpage>587</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Drawing on Schutz’s treatment of the We-relationship and of meaning contexts, and on Michael Jackson’s exploration of the ambiguities of the intersubjective, this article examines the methodological implications of the empathic orientation developed in the context of intimacy for a discipline based on participant observation. I argue that moments of ‘breakdown’, a classic way in which ethnographic questions are revealed, are predicated on the intentional dynamics of intersubjective relationships. I draw on a particular experience of ‘breakdown’ on an overnight truck trip in Highlands Papua New Guinea juxtaposed with expectations of intimacy developed over long-term fieldwork spanning 12 years.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ethnographic method</kwd>
<kwd>intersubjectivity</kwd>
<kwd>intimacy</kwd>
<kwd>Maring</kwd>
<kwd>Papua New Guinea</kwd>
<kwd>phenomenology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In October 1991, I travelled by truck from my fieldwork home in Kwima in the Jimi Valley of the Western Highlands Province of Papua New Guinea to Banz, in the Wahgi Valley, the economic ‘core’ of the Western Highlands. The truck owners were selling coffee and buying trade store stock and car parts, and I had banking to do. The Sepik–Wahgi Divide separating the Jimi and Wahgi Valleys is chronically vulnerable to bandit attacks and, as it was raining and too close to nightfall, we decided to stay the night at a hamlet that incorporated a trade store (Lopme) that was part of the truck owner’s business network. The fence surrounding the compound was two-metre high made of closely bound pit–pit. The fence was completed with a gate that was securely locked at night. Locks on trade stores were commonplace, but security fences around entire hamlets were not. The characteristic hamlet fence was maybe one-metre high, made of split logs and primarily designed to keep pigs out or in. The explicit way in which the fence set itself up against the encompassing social world was shocking. The way the intimate sociality of that evening unfolded both amplified the defensive sensibility that the fence heralded and gave form to the shock. It is the implications and dynamics of intimacy from the standpoint of the ethnographer that forms the focus of this essay.</p>
<p>Intimacy is both a general possibility of human face-to-face relationships, the more so as they are sustained over time, and of specific cultural and political significance in kinship-based social systems. At the same time, it is of primary methodological significance for the ethnographers of such societies because these are the relationships that one is thrown into as the ground from which the rest of the social field is explored. As such, they are often the context of the first experience of the shock of difference. In this article, I will be treating empathy, reflexivity and irreducible difference, all dialectically related aspects of intimate relationships, as of peculiar significance to a discipline whose primary method is one of participant observation. From this perspective, subjectivity is one perspective within an intersubjective field (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468794112443475">Jackson, 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468794112443475">1998</xref>), and I write this article always with one eye on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468794112443475">Schutz’s (1972 [1967])</xref> analysis of the varying dynamics of the We-relationship as distinct modalities of the coordination of consociate streams of consciousness (pp. 164–172). At the same time, I will be treating the long-term nature of anthropological fieldwork as the critical context in which such relationships yield their significance – in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468794112443475">Schutz’s (1972 [1967])</xref> happy phrase, the peculiar way in which ethnographers and the people they work with are ‘growing older together’ (p. 163). I juxtapose a critical exegesis of an iconic example of a revelatory moment of intimacy, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1468794112443475">Gell’s (1979)</xref> ‘Reflections on a Cut Finger’, with an examination of my own experience of a men’s house as a socially instituted site of intimacy among Maring speakers of the Western Highlands Province of Papua New Guinea. In Gell’s case, his violation of a taboo produces a shock that is revelatory and radically redirects his line of enquiry. In my case, a specific experience of intimacy, marked by anxiety and entrepreneurial ambition, is revelatory in its contrast with the taken-for-granted intimacy of my fieldwork home. In both cases, the empathic orientation developed in the context of intimacy is the ground on which the revelation is predicated.</p>
<sec id="section1-1468794112443475">
<title>Joint attention and empathy</title>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>My experience is that direct questioning of the native about a custom or belief never discloses their attitude of mind as thoroughly as the discussion of facts connected with the direct observation of a custom, or with a concrete occurrence, in which both parties are materially concerned. (Malinowski quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1468794112443475">Stocking, 1983</xref>: 97–98)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In my reading, this is the key quote around which Stocking builds his influential genealogy of the ethnographic method. It is this consociate triangle of event/custom, ethnographer and native that underpins the status of Malinowski’s work as the charter of participant observation. Nevertheless, anthropologists have struggled ever since, both over the facticity of the event/custom pole and over the nature of the implied relationship between ethnographer and native – a matter on which the subjectively non-committal phrase ‘in which both parties are materially concerned’ suggests some ambivalence. The posthumous publication of Malinowski’s <italic>A Diary in the Strict Sense of the Word</italic> threw this ambivalence into stark relief. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468794112443475">Geertz’s (1967)</xref> view of ‘this gross, tiresome, posthumous work’ was that it ‘destroyed one final idol, and one he himself [Malinowski] did much to create: that of the fieldworker with extraordinary empathy for the natives’. Geertz did not think that this was entirely a bad thing:
<disp-quote>
<p>The value of Malinowski’s embarrassing example is that, if one takes it seriously, it makes it difficult to defend the sentimental view of rapport as depending on the enfolding of anthropologist and informant into a single moral, emotional, and intellectual universe. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468794112443475">Geertz, 1967</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1468794112443475">1</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1468794112443475">Hortense Powdermaker (1967)</xref>, in her response to Geertz’s review, certainly agreed that the diary was tedious but took issue with Geertz’s evident dislike of Malinowski (she entitled her response ‘An Agreeable Man’) and rejected the view that ‘empathy’ was part of the mythic charter of participant observation. Nevertheless, whatever their differences, both Geertz and Powdermaker agree in their reservations about ‘empathy’ and on the necessary recognition of the fundamental disjunction between ethnographer and native/informant in any critical appreciation of the method.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1468794112443475">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>One theme of the ‘phenomenological turn’ in anthropology that forms the backdrop to this article has been a critical recuperation of the term empathy that avoids the kind of sentimental reduction of a methodological claim to a moral one that concerned Geertz. In Jackson’s work, this flowed from his more central concern with the dynamics, ambiguities and contradictions of the intersubjective. More recently, there has been an efflorescence of work with a specific focus on empathy as an aspect of mutuality, in which its methodological significance and status as an object of ethnographic study are intertwined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1468794112443475">Grønseth and Davis, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop, 2011</xref>; Throop and Hollan, 2008). This work has built on a sustained, varied and contested range of phenomenological critiques of empathy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468794112443475">Zahavi (2010)</xref> has reviewed this critical history with an eye to its sociological as well as its philosophical value, and I draw on his specific recognition of the value of Schutz:
<disp-quote>
<p>Schutz rejects what he considers to be the two extreme positions of Scheler and Carnap. Whereas the former, on Schutz’ reading, argues that I have as direct an access to the lived experiences of others as I have to my own, the latter argues that we never have any experience of other minds at all, but only of physical objects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468794112443475">Schutz, 1967</xref>, pp. 20–21). By contrast, Schutz defends the view that we do have experiential access to others, while denying that the experiences of others are intuitively given to us in their full self-presence. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468794112443475">Zahavi, 2010</xref>: 296)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>It is important to remember that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468794112443475">Schutz’s 1972 [1967]</xref>) point of departure was a disciplined critique of Weber’s taken-for-granted assumption of ‘the meaningful phenomena of the world as a matter of intersubjective agreement’ (p. 9). He insisted that ‘far from being homogeneous, the social world is given to us in a complex system of perspectives’ (p. 8). He was keen to make sure that a naïve concept of <italic>verstehen</italic> did not collapse this ‘system of perspectives’, and this concern was reflected in his view of empathy. So while it is of fundamental importance to argue that
<disp-quote>
<p>certain aspects of the other’s consciousness, such as his joy, sorrow, pain, shame, pleading, love, rage and threats, are given to us directly and non-inferentially … [Schutz] denies that … we also have a direct access to the <italic>why</italic> of such feelings. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468794112443475">Zahavi, 2010</xref>: 297).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Furthermore, Zahavi emphasises that empathy is limited in its sociological scope, specifically once we move our interest beyond the face-to-face relationship.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1468794112443475">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>It is one of the attractions of Schutz that he recognises both that empathy may form a moment of an unfolding interaction and that it may be embedded in differing and changing ways in specific forms of relationship. What is very clear from the recent resurgence of debate on empathy is that people come to this apparently unifying aspect of experience with both very different problems and, indeed, very different concrete forms of experience driving them. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1468794112443475">Gieser (2008)</xref>, for instance, draws on a similar phenomenological and psychological literature to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1468794112443475">Zahavi (2008)</xref>, in making a sustained argument for the importance of empathy as a drive towards the unity of I and thou in the learning relationship between apprentice and practitioner: ‘the intention-in-action of the observed “infects” the intention-in-action of the observer and becomes one with his or hers’ (p. 311). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1468794112443475">Ridler (1996)</xref>, due to his concern with friendship, has a very different take again. He does not construe empathy as an aspect of every face-to-face relationship, but rather as a moment of revelation that is the culmination of a sustained relationship of ‘growing old together’. As such, he also sees empathy as part of the way in which anthropology addresses its ‘why’ in the context of the long-term dynamic of fieldwork. ‘Without revelation’, he writes, ‘ambiguous and nuanced as it may be, resonance and an empathic understanding are impossible. Such understanding is the ground of social knowledge, and the principal means we have available to understand the “natural standpoint” of others’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1468794112443475">Ridler, 1996</xref>: 255). In this article, I am not concerned with the development of a particular empathic relationship but with empathy as a recurrent moment of the particular context of domestic interaction through which I was drawn into the social life of Kwima.</p>
<p>As Stocking’s exploration of Malinowski’s method makes clear, the ethnographer – informant – event triangle combines the processes of learning <italic>within</italic> an encompassing context and empirical investigation <italic>of</italic> that context. As a model of learning, it is not unique; indeed that is part of the point of the method. Rather, it bears a close family resemblance to a dominant strand in the analysis of the intersubjective dynamics of infant socialisation and the key role of joint attention in that process. The phenomenological turn in anthropology has developed its more rigorous description of the intersubjective in dialogue with this literature.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1468794112443475">4</xref></sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1468794112443475">Stern (1985)</xref>, in his influential exploration of <italic>The Interpersonal World of the Infant</italic>, draws on Trevarthan and Hubley’s succinct definition of the operationalisation of intersubjectivity in learning as ‘a deliberately sought sharing of experiences about events and things’ (Trevarthan and Hubley in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1468794112443475">Stern, 1985</xref>: 128). In the process, three key pre-linguistic grounds on which ethnography, socialisation and language learning itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1468794112443475">Baldwin, 1995</xref>) are all built are established: ‘sharing joint attention, sharing intentions, and sharing affective states’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1468794112443475">Stern, 1985</xref>: 128). The recognition of the ‘deliberate’ aspect of this process is vital. A common relation to an object/event is not enough. The learning process requires the desire for the intersubjective relationship, as the basis of an interest in the object, and the skills to establish and maintain it (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1468794112443475">Baldwin, 1995</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1468794112443475">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>The perspective of learning also reveals the dialectical nature of the triangle: we learn about the meaning, practical and technical possibilities of an object/event in relation to the shared intentional focus with another, and so, in the same moment, we also come to learn about the people we are doing fieldwork with as intentional agents:
<disp-quote>
<p>[W]hat underlies infants’ early skills of joint attention is their emerging understanding of other persons as intentional agents; that is, their understanding of human activity in terms of the outcomes it is designed to achieve. When infants begin to view others as intentional they begin to comprehend that: Other persons may attend selectively (intentionally) to some things in the environment and ignore others; Other persons may intend for them to selectively attend to some things in the environment and ignore others; With certain behaviours they may induce other persons to intentionally attend to new things in the environment. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1468794112443475">Tomasello, 1995</xref>: 103–104)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In Malinowski’s terms, it is a discussion of the ‘facts of the matter’ that discloses the ‘attitude of mind’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1468794112443475">6</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1468794112443475">
<title>The dialectics of empathy and breakdown</title>
<p>While the development of a mutual empathetic orientation has formed one strand in the narrative of participant observation, the shock of difference has formed another. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1468794112443475">Agar (1982)</xref> has identified the well-documented importance of such moments in fieldwork by the term ‘breakdown’: the violation of the taken-for-granted expectations of the ethnographer (pp. 783–784). That these are in fact two sides of the same dynamic is one aspect of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468794112443475">Jackson’s (1998)</xref> extended discussion of the ambiguities of the intersubjective (pp. 8–12).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1468794112443475">7</xref></sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1468794112443475">Gell’s (1979)</xref> ‘Reflections on a Cut Finger’ represents an iconic example of such a moment of ‘breakdown’. I subject the ‘moment’ to an extended exegesis to provide a concrete sense of the integral relationship between joint attention on the one hand and the dialectical relationship between empathy and difference on the other.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1468794112443475">8</xref></sup> The comparability of the social context within which Gell was working and my own fieldwork ‘home’ also allows this exegesis to serve as a reference point for my later analysis of Maring insider sociality.</p>
<p>The moment that ‘sharpened’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1468794112443475">Gell’s (1979)</xref> observation (p. 135), and led to his reconsideration of Umeda taboo, is condensed enough to be quoted in full:
<disp-quote>
<p>I happened once, during my fieldwork, to be peeling a stick of sugar-cane together with some companions from Umeda village. Clumsily, I allowed my knife to slip and it embedded itself in my finger. Unhurriedly, but still unthinkingly, I deposited the offending kitchen knife and the still unpeeled stick of sugar-cane and raised my bleeding finger to my lips. The external world ceased momentarily to exist for me, conscious only of the familiar saltwater taste on my tongue and a just perceptible pulsation where the sting would be. My world contracted to a simple circuit, a chain of actions and sensations completed by finger, lips, and tongue tentatively exploring the extent of the wound, which was only slight, in fact. Slight enough to be in itself entirely unremarkable, and the momentary lapse into unreflectiveness prompted by it equally so, were it not that, reflected in the distorting mirror of an alien, or at least partially alien, set of cultural categories, my lapse of consciousness was a lapse indeed, as the shocked countenances and expressions of disgust evinced by my Umeda companions told me soon enough, just as soon as I recovered my wits and looked about me. (pp. 134–135)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>I take Gell’s peeling of the sugarcane as a matter of shared intention. Here, I am projecting my own experience as a fieldworker in fringe Highlands Papua New Guinea. It is generally the case that any of one’s kindred engaged in any kind of technical task is a matter of interest and a likely target of advice. On top of that, in a cultural context which revolves, from infanthood on, around the everyday manipulation of knives and axes, a European wielding any kind of knife or axe is an object of interested commentary, and likely to be considered a danger to themselves (often rightly so) in need of supervision. The slip of the knife and the cut would have only intensified the focus on Gell even as his own intersubjective attention was suspended by the mild shock and habitual response. Gell recovers ‘his wits’ and checks the gaze and response of his companions to find himself an object of shock and disgust.</p>
<p>It is important to emphasise that, despite the alien assumptions of the mirror, Gell seems to have been in no doubt that (a) the sucking of the cut finger was the focus of attention and (b) the affective reactions were ones of shock and disgust. In other words, shared intention, attention and affect were part of the dynamics of this face-to-face relationship (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468794112443475">Schutz, 1972 [1967]</xref>: 164–72). Furthermore, the nature of that affect was given to Gell ‘directly and non-inferentially’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468794112443475">Zahavi, 2010</xref>: 297). The ‘revelation’ that leads Gell on to an entirely new line of inquiry arises from both being in a We-relationship, in the sense of mutual orientation towards each other, and in the (unintentional) violation of that mutuality in the auto-cannibalistic (from the Umeda perspective) act of sucking the blood from his finger.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1468794112443475">9</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1468794112443475">
<title>Maring intimacy as meaning context</title>
<p>Over time, the intimacy of the hamlet that became my fieldwork home formed an integral part of my fieldwork self, a transformation that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1468794112443475">Ladermann (1994)</xref> refers to as one of the ‘acculturation’ of the ethnographer. For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468794112443475">Schutz (1972 [1967])</xref>, such intimacy is a meaning context, and he captures the sedimentation of experience that this entails in the following terms:
<disp-quote>
<p>We say that our lived experiences E<sub>1</sub>, E<sub>2</sub>,…, E<sub>n</sub> stand in a meaning context if and only if, once they have been lived through in separate steps, they are then constituted into a synthesis of a higher order, becoming thereby unified objects of monothetic attention. (p. 75)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Among the Maring, sharing food cooked over a common fire is a fundamental statement of being an integral part of a kindred. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1468794112443475">Rappaport (1984 [1968])</xref> documents taboos against ‘eating food cooked over the same fire or grown in the same garden as that of one’s enemy’ (p. 111). The logic of these taboos had the potential to prevent wives from eating with husbands or sisters with their brothers. The same issues provoked regular anxiety about sorcery, and recurrent accusations, throughout the period of my fieldwork. In the first week that I and my then partner were thrown into the Dwend hamlet in 1979, it was made very clear to me that being part of the hamlet bestowed the right, in fact the obligation, to ask for food – the first Maring phrase I was explicitly taught was ‘I am hungry’. As with food, so it was with the inside space of one’s house of an evening: one did not invite people into one’s house, they defined themselves as part of the kindred by socialising there.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1468794112443475">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>During my first period of fieldwork in 1979, my house was a family house open to all. My tape recorder was used to record songs, I became part of regular card games (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1468794112443475">Maclean, 1984</xref>) and my incompetence in the management of a fire and cooking was regularly exposed (often by children). During fieldwork, in 1987, I stayed in Councillor Ingwai’s family house. In 1991, the house I had built for me in Dwend came to function as a men’s house. Maring hamlets characteristically had one men’s house and a separate women’s house for each married or widowed woman resident. Each clan also had a single ritual men’s house at which any of the men of the clan might sleep and socialise. Men’s houses thus stood for the unified inside interests of the clan and sub-clan.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1468794112443475">11</xref></sup> In 1991, there was no other men’s house within the sprawling hamlet in which the main adult men Ingwai, his brother’s son Ronold and his son Jim were all involved in polygynous marriages. Ingwai had, instead, built a family house in the modern style with separate sleeping compartments, but fires were explicitly banned inside because of the soot they left on the roof. Moreover, as a family house, it provided no genuine escape for the men of the hamlet. My house, on the other hand, had a fire, and as I was on my own at the time, it was open to definition as a men’s house. Rapidly, the men enforced the exclusion of women, although they frequently sat on the steps outside and chatted.</p>
<p>I have emphasised the importance of my fire because it is a key practical and symbolic focus of the synchronisation of selves in the domestic context. Discussion and advice on reviving the fire from coals, adding more wood and getting the quality and focus of the fire right for different cooking tasks punctuated the evenings. The fire and cooking structured not only the disposition of people inside the house but also any movement within the house, as care had to be taken to avoid polluting food by stepping over, or near, it. If kerosene was running low, fire might be the main source of light, the basis of being visually present to each other. At the same time, it was important to be present to each other through talk. To be silent was tantamount to acknowledging a lack of a right to talk, to shame and thus to a lack of full personhood. In other words, we can describe men’s house sociality in terms of the everyday practical activity in which face-to-face relationships are intentionally coordinated and people grow older together (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468794112443475">Jackson, 1996</xref>: 18–21).</p>
<p>However, it would be too simple to leave the matter with a description in which the organisation of the fire, spatial disposition, eating and talk are all synchronised in an internal focus on a masculine We-relationship. The nature of talk, in particular, complicates the matter. While my house at Dwend was appropriated to serve as a men’s house, it nevertheless remained a part of the broader domestic complexity of the hamlet, driven largely by the politics of polygyny. The exclusion of women from my house was, at one level, a form of artifice in that conversations, not infrequently on-going domestic quarrels, took place between houses, and women continually tested the spatial boundaries, openly dubious of their status. In other words, rather than being synchronised, the intersubjective foci of fire/food and talk frequently cut across each other.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1468794112443475">12</xref></sup> In linguistic terms, these shifts in focus were registered by the oscillation between Tok Pisin and Maring. Tok Pisin marked a contemporary masculinity and also allowed me to be a fluent part of the conversation. Talk in Maring included women and older men, but left me passively following the gist.</p>
<p>In summary, this kind of intimate sociality is constituted by a focus (fire and food), a boundary (walls and door marking a gender distinction) and by a mutual and intentional orientation towards others (talk and fire and food). However, despite the centripetal dynamics, the relationship to the outside remains permeable. The boundary marks a complementary difference not a disjunction, a point of concentration within an encompassing kinship field. It is this very permeability that enables the cultural elaboration of this kind of insider sociality as a metaphor for in-group solidarity at a very broad range of social scale and political and economic significance (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1468794112443475">Maclean, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1468794112443475">2010</xref>). In this sense, the face-to-face dynamics of intimacy is always politically charged.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1468794112443475">
<title>Intimacy on the road</title>
<p>I turn now to the specific experience of intimacy on the road. For me, while the evening I spent at Lopme in 1991 was marked as one of male insider sociality, it had a very different quality from my everyday experience in Kwima. The dim light of the fire seemed to emphasise the exclusion of the outside rather than being a warmth that had drawn people together. Rather than serving as the taken-for-granted ground from which mundane matters of common interest might be explored, an anxious affirmation of our insider relationship to each other permeated talk here. Bombastic claims to importance, while recognisable from other contexts, dominated in a way that was unusual.</p>
<p>In contrast to the domestic complexity of my Kwima hamlet, the Lopme context remained remarkably simple in its sustained closure. There were two symptoms of this. One was the extent to which it was policed. The two-metre high pit–pit wall surrounding the compound was completely unlike ordinary hamlets. This was a business, always potentially at war with its outside and thus overtly defensive. From the moment we arrived, there was regular commentary on the social identity of the business ownership of the place as opposed to the local clan-based identity that encompassed it. As night fell, the local women socialising around the store were hustled out, as not belonging, and the gates were closed and locked. There was sustained commentary during the evening on who had a right to stay in the compound and moralising about the inappropriate nature of a particular claim that had been tried on recently. As with ordinary hamlets, it remained the case that being part of the inside was a matter of assertion rather than invitation, but it was also the case that those claims were far more fraught than the everyday quality of the kindred.</p>
<p>The second was that Tok Pisin remained the dominant medium of conversation throughout the evening. Precisely because this was a business hamlet and not a domestic one, and this was a group of men passing though on business, there was no modification of the sociality of the evening by a connection to a domestic outside. Just as the business was cut-off from its surrounding social environment by the wall, the men’s house in which I spent the night had no connection to a domestic outside. Tok Pisin, then, was the language of the contemporary masculinity of business that was the intentional focus of the evening. As such, it was also appropriate to the hybrid social make up of the group I was travelling with. This was no kindred. Of the six sharing the men’s house, two were from groups formerly enemies of the Kwima people, and one was from a very different part of the valley for whom Maring was not the native language. It was the business that made them insiders.</p>
<p>The absolute synchronisation of fire, food and talk that characterised the face-to-face relationships of the evening was in turn a function of the hostile and unstable orientation of the business to its social exterior (and vice versa). The fence stands both for that hostility and the attempts to police it. The intimacy inside the fence is no point of concentration within a kinship field but rather an enclave that has to be defended. In doing so, however, the business builds on the capacity of its members for this kind of insider sociality and the moral claims that accompany it. In methodological terms, I am treating the shock of the fence as a moment of ‘breakdown’. However, if this essay is to yield its comparative and methodological value, it is important to be precise about whom it is a breakdown for and what kind of expectations have been violated.</p>
<p>An emerging consensus of the dialogue about intersubjectivity, empathy and mutuality that informs this essay is that fieldwork depends as much on the intentional relationships ‘informants’ develop with ethnographers and their projects, as it does on the sensibility of the ethnographer.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1468794112443475">13</xref></sup> In my account earlier, it was the intentional relationship of the Umeda to Gell that drives the ‘revelation’ and sucking the cut finger is a breakdown for them.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1468794112443475">14</xref></sup> The night spent at Lopme was a breakdown for me. I found the evening alienating and claustrophobic, an index of the disjunction with my previous experience and the lurking sense of threat. For the older men, by contrast, the investment in the business as a way of making their names was palpable. For the younger men, the excitement of the accompanying adrenalin rush of the truck trip infused their attitude. However, it is important to emphasise that this difference in affective orientation developed within the mutuality of the context. The sustained closure of an empathic orientation towards my consociates meant both that their emotional timbre was ‘given’ to me directly and, in turn, set the terms of my reflexive attitude – the ‘why?’. Equally, as the evening unfolded, it became clear that the conjunction of my White difference and implication in this masculine intimacy had brought into focus a ‘why’ for my consociates – the evening culminated with a sustained discussion about whether I thought it was possible that money was being manufactured in the Jimi Valley, a revelatory proposition in its own right.</p>
<p>However, the contribution made by this essay to the broader methodological debate that I most want to emphasise is that the circumstance of my expectations and their violation were not one of cultural difference, <italic>simpliciter</italic>. In this, it contrasts with the iconic example of Gell (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1468794112443475">Briggs, 1970</xref>). Rather, they were expectations that had been developed through the very particular way that I had ‘grown old’ within that social field. As I understand it, this is the direction that two recent collections on empathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1468794112443475">Grønseth and Davis, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop, 2011</xref>) are pointing to, albeit in different ways. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1468794112443475">Josephides (2010)</xref> concludes one collection emphasising the transformative force of the fieldwork experience and the way ‘ethnographers stretch themselves to meet others in a new place’ (p. 175). Josephides notes that ‘[w]hat this new place is and how it can be legitimized must be the subject of further enquiry’ (p. 175) and one way of reading this essay would be as a strand of such a project. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop (2011)</xref> remind us of the relatively unexamined status of the hermeneutic dynamic of this stretching: ‘that empathy is a process that requires ongoing dialogue for its accuracy’ (p. 3). My experience of shock was one of an extrusion into my social field, explicable in generative terms, but unexpected in its form from the standpoint of the ethnographer. In the middle of what I thought had become familiar, I was suddenly stretched. In terms of Schutz’s definition of a meaning context, we might call this specific experience of intimacy, Intimacy E<sub>n+1</sub>. It evoked that established synthetic sense of intimacy and that in turn allowed me to be drawn into the dynamics of the evening. However, at the same time, its distinctive qualities resisted assimilation to that context. As such, the specifics of this experience that refused assimilation to established expectations raised a ‘why?’ for me about the relationship between business, the control of space and the emergence of a new kind of politicised ‘inside’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1468794112443475">15</xref></sup> In methodological terms, it is the participant accumulation and sedimentation of experience that lays the ground for interpretation; it is events in their specificity that are revelatory.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This article covers material collected during three different periods of fieldwork with Maring speakers in Kwima, Western Highlands Province, Papua New Guinea. The first period of fieldwork of 15 months was the basis of my PhD Dissertation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1468794112443475">Maclean, 1985</xref>). This was followed by two further periods of one month in 1987 and three months in 1991–1992. I would like to thank the residents of Dwend who allowed me to share in the life of the hamlet. I would also particularly like to thank Ronold Ti who so patiently assisted with my work and Tom Ernst who first introduced me to Schutz’s work, although it has been a long time bearing fruit. Finally, I thank the two anonymous referees from whose advice the argument of the article has certainly benefited.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The fieldwork in 1987 and in 1991–1992 was funded by small grants from the University of Sydney.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1468794112443475">
<label>1.</label>
<p>A more sustained version of this argument can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1468794112443475">Geertz (1974)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1468794112443475">
<label>2.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop (2011</xref>: 5–9) for a discussion of the legacy of Geertz’s intervention.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1468794112443475">
<label>3.</label>
<p>In following Zahavi, I am in agreement with Hollan and Throop’s emphasis on connecting the empathic recognition of the fact of an emotion to how and why questions, but I am at odds with their more expansive view of empathy as helping answer those questions. In developing this view, they draw on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1468794112443475">Stueber’s (2006)</xref> distinction between basic and re-enactive empathy (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1468794112443475">Zahavi’s (2008)</xref> critical dialogue with Stueber, among others, on these issues). As I understand it, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468794112443475">Zahavi’s (2010)</xref> perspective (pp. 289–296) is also at odds with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop’s (2011)</xref> emphasis on gaining a ‘first-person perspective on another’s thoughts and feelings’ as the ‘core of the empathy concept’ (p. 3) . The view I take in this article is more consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1468794112443475">Grønseth and Davis (2010)</xref> who define empathy as ‘a mode of embodied and intersubjectively negotiated understanding that derives from being together and coordinating common tasks’ (p. 13).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1468794112443475">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Jackson draws on Stern’s work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468794112443475">Jackson, 1996</xref>: 27) and on the intersection of cognitive psychology and psycholinguistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468794112443475">Jackson, 1998</xref>: 11) in his description of the ground of the intersubjective. Hollan and Throop, and authors in that collection such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1468794112443475">Lohmann (2011)</xref>, seek to develop this conjunction even as they recognise that contemporary debates surrounding ‘theory of mind’ and ‘simulation theory’ make this a highly contested terrain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop, 2011</xref>: 3–4). It has been my own recent work on autism and the associated intertwined debates surrounding theory of mind, imagination and empathy that has inclined me to resist any straightforward assimilation of a phenomenological perspective to the contemporary terrain of a cognitive psychology. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1468794112443475">Zahavi (2005)</xref> spells out clearly what is at stake in these debates with particular reference to the implications of ‘theory of mind’ for our understanding of autism. While Rumsey in his afterword to the Hollan and Throop volume both recognises the issues that give rise to my anxiety, and clearly finds that anxiety misplaced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1468794112443475">Rumsey, 2011</xref>: 215), I appreciate his return to the literature on joint attention and affective attunement as a key basis on which such analysis can proceed (pp. 219–221).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1468794112443475">
<label>5.</label>
<p>This is why pointing and monitoring of the gaze of others (usually in the mother–child relationship) are important empirical foci of the study of this process. This is also what makes so implausible <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468794112443475">Geertz’s (1967)</xref> claim that the ‘insight into Trobriand life Malinowski apparently was unable to gain by human contact he gained by industry’. There is an unwillingness to recognise that Malinowski’s kind of industry does not just produce a ‘staggering quantity of data’ – one also begins to learn and discriminate.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1468794112443475">
<label>6.</label>
<p>It is an intriguing aspect of Jackson’s work that he has developed this argument over time drawing on the work of two philosophers apparently at loggerheads: Adorno and Husserl. For example, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468794112443475">Jackson (1996</xref>: 22, 29).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1468794112443475">
<label>7.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1468794112443475">High (2011)</xref> has explored the informant ethnographer relationship from the closely related Freudian perspective of ambivalence. I particularly appreciate her recognition of the dialectics of anthropological melancholia on the one hand and Thai concerns with nurturing and abandonment on the other.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1468794112443475">
<label>8.</label>
<p>In doing so, I will be making explicit what Gell preferred to leave implicit. He does make it clear that his interpretation owed a lot to a reading of the phenomenological writings of Merleau-Ponty, Schutz and Berger.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1468794112443475">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1468794112443475">Agar (1982</xref>: 783–784), it is the Umeda who register the ‘breakdown’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1468794112443475">
<label>10.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468794112443475">Hollan and Throop (2011)</xref> recognise the point, implicit in this description, that ‘empathy tends to flow along, and support, boundaries of kinship and other intimate social relations’ and go on to make the important point that ‘this pattern clashes with the common understanding that empathy is a neutral form of knowing or understanding of others’ (p. 13). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1468794112443475">Mageo’s (2011)</xref> article in the same volume on ‘Empathy and “As-If” attachment in Samoa’ is a particularly telling development of this argument. I simply want to emphasise that this makes a critical appreciation of general claims about the methodological implications of empathy, and the connections it opens into a social field, imperative.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1468794112443475">
<label>11.</label>
<p>A sub-clan would typically consist of some 30–50 people, maybe 10 of whom would be adult men and within which matters such as bride-wealth and compensation claims are discussed.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1468794112443475">
<label>12.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1468794112443475">Helliwell (1996</xref>: 138) has remarked on a similar dynamic in the way the formal partitioning of the Dayak longhouse is cut across by the ‘community of voices’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1468794112443475">
<label>13.</label>
<p>This is the point of the well-known vignette that opens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1468794112443475">Geertz’s (1973)</xref> essay on the Balinese cockfight. It is the turning of the taken-for-granted agency of the relationship around (a ‘breakdown’ from the point of view of the reader) that makes it work.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1468794112443475">
<label>14.</label>
<p>Similarly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1468794112443475">Briggs (1970)</xref> builds her classic, empirically nuanced account around a breakdown for the Utku. Unlike Gell, however, Briggs’ account remains remarkably contemporary in its sustained attention to what the Utku do with the ‘why’ that arises for them from that breakdown (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1468794112443475">Josephides, 2010</xref>: 175).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1468794112443475">
<label>15.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1468794112443475">Maclean (1994)</xref> for one response to the question. There is direct companion piece to this essay that sets the event within a broader historical and spatial context and picks up on the discussion of locally manufactured money in particular. The need to take the ‘why?’ of encounters into broader sociological forms of explanation is one of the reasons that Zahavi questions the status of ‘re-enactive’ empathy:<disp-quote>
<p>… although it is important to recognize the importance of empathy, it is also important to recognize its limitations. There is a limit to how far empathy (plus sensitivity to the immediate context) can get us. Our everyday understanding of others draws on other resources as well. If we wish to unearth why somebody is feeling the way he does or why he is acting the way he does, we might need to consider the larger social, cultural, and historical context, and this understanding cannot be provided by empathy (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1468794112443475">Stueber, 2006</xref>). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1468794112443475">Zahavi, 2008</xref>: 522)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Biographical note</title>
<p><bold>Neil Maclean</bold> is senior lecturer in Anthropology at the University of Sydney with research interests in the post-colonial state and economic anthropology based on long-term fieldwork with Maring speakers of the Western Highlands Province of Papua New Guinea. More recently he has developed a research interest in autism and imagination.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agar</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Toward an ethnographic language</article-title>. <source>American Anthropologist</source> <volume>84</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Understanding the link between joint attention and language</article-title>. In: C and <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Joint Attention: Its Origins and Role in Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>, <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <source>Never in Anger: Portrait of an Eskimo Family</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA; London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geertz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Under the mosquito net</article-title>. <source>The New York Review of Books</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <day>14</day> <month>September</month>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geertz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Deep play: notes on a Balinese cockfight</article-title>. <source>Daedalus</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geertz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>‘From the Native’s Point of View’: on the nature of anthropological understanding</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Reflections on a cut finger: taboo in the Umeda conception of the self</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Fantasy and Symbol: Studies in Anthropological Interpretation</source>. <publisher-loc>London; New York; San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gieser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Embodiment, emotion and empathy: a phenomenological approach to apprenticeship learning</article-title>. <source>Anthropological Theory</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Grønseth</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2010</year>) <source>Mutuality and Empathy: Self and Other in the Ethnographic Encounter (Anthropology Matters)</source>, <volume>vol. 5</volume>. <publisher-loc>Wantage</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sean Kingston Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Space and sociality in a Dayak longhouse</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Things as They Are: New Directions in Phenomenological Anthropology</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>High</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Melancholia and anthropology</article-title>. <source>American Ethnologist</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hollan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Throop</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The anthropology of empathy: introduction</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hollan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Throop</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Anthropology of Empathy: Experiencing the Lives of Others in Pacific Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Introduction: phenomenology, radical empiricism, and anthropological critique</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Things as They Are: New Directions in Phenomenological Anthropology</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Minima Ethnographica: Intersubjectivity and the Anthropological Project</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Josephides</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Speaking-with and feeling-with: the phenomenology of knowing the other</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Grønseth</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Mututality and Empathy: Self and Other in the Ethnographic Encounter (Anthropology Matters)</source>, <volume>vol. 5</volume>. <publisher-loc>Wantage</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sean Kingston Publishing</publisher-name>, <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laderman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The embodiment of symbols and the acculturation of the anthropologist</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Csordas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Embodiment and Experience: The Existential Ground of Culture and the Self</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Empathic perception and imagination among the Asabano: lessons for anthropology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hollan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Throop</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Anthropology of Empathy: Experiencing the Lives of Others in Pacific Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Is gambling ‘Bisnis’?: the economic and political functions of gambling in the Jimi Valley</article-title>. <source>Social Analysis</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>To develop our place: a political economy of the Maring</source>. Unpublished PhD Thesis, <publisher-name>Department of Anthropology, The University of Adelaide</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Adelaide, SA, Australia</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Maring clan clusters: strategy, disposition and interest</article-title>. <source>Oceania</source> <volume>69</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Freedom or autonomy: a modern Melanesian dilemma</article-title>. <source>Man (New Series)</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Globalisation and bridewealth rhetoric</article-title>. <source>Dialectical Anthropology</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mageo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Empathy and ‘As-If’ attachment in Samoa</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hollan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Throop</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Anthropology of Empathy: Experiencing the Lives of Others in Pacific Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>, <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Powdermaker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>An agreeable man</article-title>. <source>The New York Review of Books</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <day>9</day> <month>November</month>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rappaport</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984 [1968]</year>) <source>Pigs for the Ancestors: Ritual in the Ecology of a New Guinea People</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT; London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ridler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>If not the words: shared practical activity and friendship in fieldwork</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Things as They Are: New Directions in Phenomenological Anthropology</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rumsey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Empathy and anthropology: an afterword</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hollan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Throop</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Anthropology of Empathy: Experiencing the Lives of Others in Pacific Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>, <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schutz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972 [1967]</year>) <source>The Phenomenology of the Social World</source> (trans. <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lehnert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann Educational Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>The Interpersonal World of the Infant: A View from Psychoanalysis and Developmental Psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stocking</surname><given-names>GW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The ethnographer’s magic: fieldwork in British anthropology from Tylor to Malinowski</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stocking</surname><given-names>GW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Observers Observed: Essays on Ethnographic Fieldwork</source>, <volume>vol. 1</volume>. <publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stueber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Rediscovering Empathy: Agency, Folk Psychology, and the Human Sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomasello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Joint attention as social cognition</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Joint Attention: Its Origins and Role in Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>, <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zahavi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Subjectivity and Selfhood: Investigating the First Person Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA; London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zahavi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Simulation, projection and empathy</article-title>. <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1468794112443475">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zahavi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Empathy, embodiment and interpersonal understanding: from Lipps to Schutz</article-title>. <source>Inquiry</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>