<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SAC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsac</journal-id>
<journal-title>Space and Culture</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1206-3312</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8308</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1206331212466080</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1206331212466080</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Sylheti <italic>Bari</italic> and the <italic>Londoni</italic> Flat</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Zeitlyn</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1206331212466080">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1206331212466080"><label>1</label>University of Sussex, Brighton, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1206331212466080">Benjamin Zeitlyn, Centre for International Education, Department of Education, Essex House, University of Sussex, Brighton, BN19QQ, UK Email: <email>b.o.zeitlyn@sussex.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>317</fpage>
<lpage>329</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article examines the ways in which migration from rural homesteads in Sylhet, Bangladesh, to urban flats in London has affected the practices of British Bangladeshi families around gender and childhood. Drawing on the work of Pierre Bourdieu on the “Kabyle house,” I describe relations between the spatial arrangement of homes and practices. Analyzing the “Sylheti <italic>bari</italic>” (rural homestead) and contrasting it with the “<italic>Londoni</italic> (British Bangladeshi) flat,” I describe the significance of the way in which ideas of “inside” and “outside” have translated from one setting to another. I will show how the translation of these ideas to the urban landscape in London affects British Bangladeshi practices surrounding headscarf wearing, children’s play, and socializing, as well as attitudes toward school and language.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>British Bangladeshis</kwd>
<kwd>London</kwd>
<kwd>Bourdieu</kwd>
<kwd>home</kwd>
<kwd>belonging</kwd>
<kwd>socialization</kwd>
<kwd>children</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Significant numbers of Bangladeshis came to Britain in the 1950s and 1960s. They were single men and were helped by friends or kin among the earliest arrivals. The 1962 Commonwealth Immigrants Act reinforced this pattern; those already in the United Kingdom helped their family members and neighbors from villages in Sylhet to get employment vouchers to come to the United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1206331212466080">Choudhury, 1993</xref>, p. 135). This social network effect led to the high number of migrants to Britain from very concentrated areas of Sylhet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1206331212466080">Dench, Gavron, &amp; Young, 2005</xref>, p. 40). The new migrants at first saw themselves as temporary work migrants rather than settlers; the “myth of return” was ever present in their minds. They came in search of high wages rather than as a response to poverty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1206331212466080">Gardner &amp; Shukur, 1994</xref>, p. 147).</p>
<p>There were 283,063 British citizens of Bangladeshi origin recorded in the 2001 census (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1206331212466080">Office for National Statistics, 2005</xref>). A total of 153,893 (55%) of all British Bangladeshis live in London. A quarter of British Bangladeshis, about 65,000 people, live in Tower Hamlets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1206331212466080">Piggot, 2004</xref>, p. 5). Bangladeshis in East London were mainly employed in the local garment industry, but as this has declined because of foreign competition, more have moved into the restaurant trade or shop keeping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1206331212466080">Eade, 1989</xref>, p. 29).</p>
<p>When seen from a British perspective, British Bangladeshis are a relatively deprived group. Seventy percent of Bangladeshi pupils in U.K. schools live in the 20% most deprived postcode areas. A large proportion (45%) live in the 10% most deprived postcode areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1206331212466080">Department for Education and Skills, 2006</xref>, p. 19). In all, 68% of Bangladeshis live in low-income, often overcrowded, households that rely more on benefits than any other community. Of any ethnic group, British Bangladeshi pupils have the highest percentage eligibility for free school meals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1206331212466080">Office for Standards in Education, 2004</xref>, p. 5).</p>
<p>From a Bangladeshi perspective, the council housing, benefits, and free school meals that are markers of poverty in the United Kingdom are almost unimaginable luxuries. The British Bangladeshi social field is defined by the unequal power relations between London and Sylhet and the exchanges of different types of capital that take place as a result. This article analyzes some of the effects of migration and the transition from life in rural Sylhet to urban London—specifically the influence of space on the socialization of children and other practices among British Bangladeshi families.</p>
<p>The transition from the <italic>bari</italic> (rural homestead) in Sylhet to urban flats in London has meant that the barriers between inside and outside the home are thinner and more stark. The layout of flats in London compared with rural homesteads in Sylhet and the practical realities of life as a nuclear family in London mean that restrictions on women and children’s uses of space change. Practices such as headscarf wearing for women and girls have become more prevalent among Bangladeshis with urbanization and education. Children’s play is restricted in the urban spaces of London, considered unsafe and not sufficiently “inside” like the spaces around the homesteads in rural Sylhet.</p>
<sec id="section1-1206331212466080">
<title>Inside and Outside</title>
<speech>
<speaker>Benji:</speaker>
<p>Do you like living in London?</p>
<p>Tasneem<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1206331212466080">1</xref></sup>: Not that much.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Why not?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>T:</speaker>
<p>Because there’s too much um thingy, cars and when you’re about to come and you don’t see the car um, say like you thought the car’s going to turn that way, it actually comes your direction and you can hit yourself, like Zain did.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>OK . . . cars are dangerous.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>T:</speaker>
<p>And then and there’s what’s it? Killers and all that.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Killers?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>T:</speaker>
<p>Yeah and bad boys, around Islington and Arden.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>There’s bad boys on your estate?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>T:</speaker>
<p>Yeah.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>OK, and what do they do?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>T:</speaker>
<p>They like put on loud music, and then when we’re trying to sleep they go on and on. We call, call the police and say that everyone’s putting on loud music in the night. (Tasneem, personal communication, March 12, 2008)</p>
</speech>
<p>Tasneem, like Ishrat, who I have quoted below, had the perception that the streets and public spaces of Islington and London are not safe. These girls have been taught by parents, relatives, and teachers that the world outside their homes and school is full of people who mean them harm and dangers to their lives and morality. School and home were seen as safe spaces, where children spent most of their time and through repetitious practices of socialization learned how to behave. The streets and spaces of their neighborhoods were constructed as being inappropriate places for children.</p>
<p>A “wall” separating the “inside” and “outside” the home and the world is, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet (1996)</xref>, a core value of Bengali culture and society. This principle, which affects rural women’s lives in particular, has been translated into urban life in Bangladesh and Britain. In the city, it is not only women and female children who are at risk; young boys are also seen as needing protection from moral corruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet, 1996</xref>, p. 156; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1206331212466080">Gardner, 1995</xref>, p. 208). The middle-class children in Dhaka, from Blanchet’s account, are moved between home and school in rickshaws or private cars; they rarely set foot outside the gate of their house or block of flats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet, 1996</xref>, p. 157).</p>
<p>Like the children in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet’s (1996)</xref> study and those in New York City in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1206331212466080">Katz’s (2004)</xref> study, many British Bangladeshi children in Islington are rarely allowed out onto the street unsupervised. Home and school are seen as safe islands in the midst of the unsafe urban landscape. These are contrasted by children and parents with the street/outside, which is seen as dangerous. For the children in my study, the fun and safety of school compared favorably to the routines of life at home and the dangers of the streets. The excerpt below from an interview with Ishrat, an 11-year-old girl, shows how the perception of danger and moral corruption of the streets and public areas of their estate limits the possibilities of play and confines many children to activities in the home.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Benji:</speaker>
<p>So, when and where do you play with your friends?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Ishrat:</speaker>
<p>I don’t really . . . play in London because I’m not allowed to go out because of my area, you know, drugs and all everything.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>So you’re not . . .</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>My mum’s scared.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>You never have your friends round or go round to their house?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>No, because my mum’s a bit, protective.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Yeah?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Like she says not to go there and that something will happen.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Ok, ok, so you only play with your friends at school?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Yeah.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>And so when you’re at home, what do you do in your free time? You were saying, reading . . .</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Reading, watching television, do homework when I feel like it. Do mosque homework when I feel like it.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Mosque homework?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Yeah, if I want I play Playstation, sometimes, ’cause it’s fun, sleep.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Ok, and what do you watch on TV?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Um, Indian dramas, uh, films. (Ishrat, personal communication, February 12, 2008)</p>
</speech>
<p>Ishrat and many of her peers had very limited contact with other children outside school. Friendships with children at school were not considered particularly important or encouraged by their parents. Most peer contact outside school was with siblings, cousins, and children of families known to the parents (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet, 1996</xref>, p. 159). Parents were also worried that children might make the “wrong sort” of friends and learn bad habits or become “corrupted” in some way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet, 1996</xref>, p. 153; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1206331212466080">Crozier &amp; Davies, 2006</xref>, p. 687).</p>
<p>British Bangladeshis have their own understanding of the <italic>samaj</italic> “a moral society which upholds <italic>dhormo</italic>” and the <italic>dhormo</italic> “the life-path attributed to an individual’s gender, rank, family (lineage) occupation and status in a god-ordained world” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet, 1996</xref>, p. 224). These understandings, derived from Sylheti practices and Islam, influence their sense that many of the people and practices of the street and public spaces in London are corrupt and that their children should be shielded from them in ways that overlap but are different from other inhabitants of the city.</p>
<p>Things were not always like this, however, and nor are they the same when the children visit Bangladesh. Ishrat described visits to Bangladesh in rather different terms than she described her life in London. She associated her visit to Bangladesh with playing outside and with friends.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Like in London, stay in your house do work, go out, go to school, come back, sleep, finished.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>But in Bangladesh you feel different?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>I:</speaker>
<p>Yeah we’re outside, playing outside, 24 × 7, going to the swimming pool, playing around with my friends. (Ishrat, personal communication, February 12, 2008)</p>
</speech>
<p>As an adult with her own children, Seema reminisced about her own childhood in London in the 1980s and how protected her children are now:
<disp-quote>
<p>I realised because my daughter’s going to go to secondary school next year is that they’ve had such a sheltered life, really you know, I don’t let them out and play by themselves as often as I used to go out. I remember . . . even at the age of like 6 or 7 me and my sister were down, we had a playground at the bottom of our block of flats and you know we’d just be out playing all the time. Or um, we used to live near Chalk Farm, my mum and dad would send us out to do the shopping in Camden town which isn’t really for a ten year old and a seven year old to go up to Camden by themselves, we used to do that . . . I remember, because you know my mum was always busy with the younger ones, my dad was working so me and her we actually had quite a lot of responsibility. (Seema, personal communication, November 21, 2007)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Seema’s parents had let her and her sister out to play by themselves and had sent them to run errands, whereas Seema never let her children out of their flat unattended. Her children enjoyed visiting her family back in Sylhet partly because, like Ishrat, they enjoyed the opportunities to play outdoors. However, she put this down to a difference between living in the city and the countryside and also mentioned differences between parts of London. Her sister, who lives in a more suburban area of London, affords her children more freedom to play on the street. These experiences of inner London life are not limited to Bangladeshis, as Seema mentioned in her interview, other families in London are similarly protective of young children.</p>
<p>When she visits her husband’s family in Bangladesh, in a built-up part of Dhaka, the children are restricted in the way that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1206331212466080">Blanchet (1996)</xref> describes and play outside only on the roof of the house. Another British Bangladeshi woman, Shaju who, unlike Seema, grew up in Bangladesh, explained how the playful early part of childhood came to an end when they moved to the city of Sylhet for her and her brothers to go to school.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>When I was eight I went to live in the city— Sylhet. I liked living in the city because there was a good education available there. I missed out on my childhood in the city because I couldn’t go out by myself and there was no space to play in. Compared to the village it wasn’t so much fun and I didn’t have so much freedom. (Shaju, personal communication, April 13, 2008)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In the translation of attitudes of families from rural Sylhet to the realities of life in urban Sylhet, Dhaka, or London and the transition from one generation to the next, some of these freedoms have been lost. Across space and time, the interaction between rural Bangladeshi practices and London’s urban landscape have created new practices and relationships with space that have placed the “wall” between “inside” and “outside” much closer to “home.” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1206331212466080">Rozario’s (2006)</xref> article deals with this issue regarding the interactions between modernity, urbanity, and practices of <italic>parda</italic> (<italic>purdah—</italic>literally meaning curtain; meaning that women retreat behind curtains, screens, or into spaces where they cannot be seen, into the private, feminine parts of the house) and wearing burqa (loose fitting clothes covering the head and body) among Bangladeshi women.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The ideology of <italic>parda</italic> implies that women should remain within the private sphere as far as possible. Any deviation, such as taking a job that involves interaction with unrelated men, compromises their honour and the status of the family as a whole. Thus while Bangladeshi women at all levels are at present experiencing substantial changes in their lives as a result of the forces of modernisation and globalisation, there is a disjunction between these broader (structural) changes and persisting Bangladeshi gender values. (p. 370)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1206331212466080">Rozario’s (2006)</xref> analysis of young women in urban settings in Bangladesh who are increasingly choosing to wear the burqa has some parallels among British Bangladeshis in London. The interactions of Bangladeshi values concerning gender and childhood, the idea of inside and outside—private and public spheres, and the realities of living in an urban setting are behind both the practices that Rozario describes and some of those in London. Rozario highlights issues of physical movement and responses to modernity.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1206331212466080">Dwyer’s (1999)</xref> analysis of headscarf wearing among young Muslim women in Hertfordshire demonstrates the variety of reactions that headscarves elicit and the number of ways in which wearing a headscarf can be employed by women to negotiate spaces, explore identities and sexualities, and perform different socially and spatially influenced roles. Dwyer highlights the spatial element of headscarf wearing, for example, on the way to school to be removed in school either in the toilets or during classes. These costume changes are both strategic negotiation of public spaces and young women’s experimentation with their sexual identities. Dwyer reminds us that the careful management of appearances to negotiate one’s identity, sexuality, and relations with peers, colleagues, and strangers is an experience shared by all women, not just young Muslims in headscarves.</p>
<p>In some ways then, regarding children’s access to public space and women’s choice of clothing, British Bangladeshi practices correspond with common practices and ideas in London, they are not just linked to the experience of being British Bangladeshi. In the next section, however, I will specifically analyze the effects of the spatial arrangements of houses on the lives of British Bangladeshi families.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1206331212466080">
<title>The Sylheti <italic>Bari</italic></title>
<p>Bourdieu’s account of the Kabyle house in his <italic>Outline of a Theory of Practice</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1206331212466080">1977</xref>) presents some binaries in the organization of space:
<disp-quote>
<p>Thus, the house is organised according to a set of homologous oppositions—fire:water :: cooked:raw :: high:low :: light:shade :: day:night :: male: female :: <italic>nif:hurma</italic> :: fertilising:able to be fertilised. But in fact the same oppositions are established between the house as a whole and the rest of the universe, that is, the male world, the place of assembly, the fields and the market. (pp. 90–91)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Leaving aside a comparison between Kabyle and Sylheti households, I wish to engage with Bourdieu’s notion of habitus and analysis of the household to speak about the effects of living in very different housing in London on behavior and the socialization of children.</p>
<p>Space, says Bourdieu is influential, contributing to the “system of durable, transposable dispositions”—the habitus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1206331212466080">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>, p. 72). Space is made by these actions as much as it makes them; it is part of the process of socialization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1206331212466080">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>, p. 90). The material conditions and histories in a social field and among different classes and groups of people produce different habitus. Habitus is so ingrained and instilled in people that they regulate behavior unconsciously without people appearing or feeling like they are obeying rules.</p>
<p>Habitus is a product of collective and individual histories and contexts and perpetuates itself by producing practices and events based on its principles and dispositions. Habitus is both structured and structuring, determined and determining, producer and product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1206331212466080">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>, p. 82). Habitus makes possible but also sets limits to thoughts and behavior. It is a template setting out acceptable behavior for specific positions within a social field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1206331212466080">Friedmann, 2002</xref>, p. 316).</p>
<p>So the space of the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic> not only reflects the system of beliefs and ideas of Sylhetis but also helps form them. It is constituted by and constitutes the habitus. Within the <italic>bari</italic>, following the practices of <italic>parda</italic>, there is a division between public and private, male and female. When the women of the <italic>bari</italic> I spent time in with a visiting <italic>Londoni</italic> family fled from my gaze as I blundered into their private space, it was because the male, public, and outside, in the form of an inquisitive foreigner, was entering the feminine, private, inside space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1206331212466080">Gardner, 1995</xref>, p. 206, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1206331212466080">Rozario, 2006</xref>, p. 370).</p>
<p>The “back” of the house, where the women, especially young unmarried women, spent most of their time was where the kitchen was and where laundry was hung out: it was dark, hot, airless, and humid. There was also a bathroom that the family used, but I was not encouraged to use it. The “front” of the house was cool and airy, and many different people wandered through the rooms that doubled as bedrooms and reception rooms. Across the courtyard was the <italic>fukur ghor</italic> (pond room), which opened out onto the pond and the outside world beyond. It caught the occasional breezes and was cooler than the other parts of the house, an ideal place for the men to sit on hot afternoons and chew <italic>paan</italic> (betel nut) as they chatted. Young male guests slept, three to a bed, in the <italic>fukur ghor</italic>.</p>
<p>The house did not totally surround the courtyard, other houses of the <italic>bari</italic>, which is really a collection of houses, lived in by an extended family, lined the long courtyard. The other families of the <italic>bari</italic> were all related to the <italic>Londoni</italic> family, and their members came and went through the courtyard and outer rooms of the house as insiders within the private domain.</p>
<p>Most of the time, the private inside parts of rural households, such as this one, do not have unannounced visitors. The members of the <italic>bari</italic> have quite a lot of space to use, even if, like the women and children of the <italic>bari</italic>, they are not encouraged to leave. There is considerable space outside the actual house within which women go without being veiled and children could play in. The <italic>bari</italic>’s tight knit network of family and neighbors are a large in-group considered part of the inside, the private sphere. The pond and its surrounding fields make a sufficient barrier between the inside and the outside. There is usually space for women and children to fulfill most of their daily needs without going beyond these boundaries and into the “outside” “public sphere.” The track outside the <italic>bari</italic> was the site of many games and energetic playing with other children from the <italic>bari</italic>. The pump in between one part of the <italic>bari</italic> and another was the location for fun for the British Bangladeshi children and chores for some of the children of other less well off families in the <italic>bari</italic>.</p>
<p>When women did venture out, on visits to the doctor, for going to school, or occasionally for shopping, they were usually accompanied by male kin and wore burqa. The men did most of the shopping, however, and tradesmen would come to the house to sell products or provide services. Living in large extended families meant that the women of the household provided a lot of the support and services in terms of cooking, health care, and cosmetic treatments for each other without ever needing to leave the <italic>bari</italic>.</p>
<p>In both the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic> and the <italic>Londoni</italic> flat, the male roles were more mobile and the female body more spatially restricted. The socialization of boys and girls created gendered embodied habitus in which for boys mobility and autonomy are valued and for girls sedentary and risk-averse activities are favored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1206331212466080">Sheller, 2008</xref>). The difference was in the available space. The restricted space and practices this necessitated in London’s council flats create the conditions for changes to habitus.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1206331212466080">
<title>The <italic>Londoni</italic> Flat</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1206331212466080">Friedmann (2002)</xref> describes the transition an imaginary Kabyle family make from their rural, traditional Kabyle house in Algeria (described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1206331212466080">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>) to a “tenement” flat in a working-class neighborhood of Frankfurt, Germany, in the 1960s. The housing and spatial arrangement of the city bore no resemblance to their old housing. “The cosmic order that had always given meaning to their lives has been shattered for good” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1206331212466080">Friedmann, 2002</xref>, p. 323). The Kabyle habitus was dealt a severe blow by this migration, as it could not be sustained in the physical space that did not lend itself to the rhythms of their old lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1206331212466080">Friedmann, 2002</xref>, p. 329).</p>
<p>Friedmann describes the gathering of Kabyle and other North African and Turkish families in particular areas of Frankfurt, creating what he calls an “affinity environment.” The disorientated foreigners helped each other with the struggle to make sense of their new lives. Visits to the mosque and a local festival welcoming migrants to the city involved awkward, especially for the women, encounters with strangers. In time and in turn, the Kabyle turned their neighborhood into an “ethnic enclave,” which the local German working class resented, their use and understandings of the space disrupted by the unfamiliar activities of the Kabyle <italic>gastarbeiter</italic> (guest workers; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1206331212466080">Friedmann, 2002</xref>, p. 326).</p>
<p>In London, space is arranged in completely different ways from the <italic>bari</italic> in rural Sylhet, both within the flat and outside in the immediate surroundings. Lives have different patterns that have created the spatial organization and are, in turn created by them. Within the cramped living quarters of British Bangladeshi families in Islington, it is not very practical to practice purdah. The small kitchen is not built for several women to gather, cooking and eating in the private sphere; it is attached directly onto the main reception room of the house, which is designed for receiving guests.</p>
<p>There is no courtyard, no separate spheres for activities, for public and private social milieu to run simultaneously. Any courtyards or public spaces there are between blocks are not semiprivate like the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic>, they are open and observed by all. Indeed on the De Vere Estate in Islington, the small pathways and passages so beloved of the original celebrated architects had been opened up into public roads in a total redevelopment of the estate as they had become crime hotspots. There is precious little private outside space, although many of the flats have a small balcony. On the third, sixth, or ninth floor of a concrete block of flats, the idea of outside is immediate and close.</p>
<p>From the window of one flat was a spectacular view of the East End of London, an urban panorama of tower blocks and construction sites; there was no space there that could be considered in any way “inside” or “private”—no track, field, pond, or scrap of land that was a buffer between the intimacies of the household and the outside world. On the other side of the flat was the door to a dark concrete corridor lit only with strip lights. Off that corridor were the doors to other flats, so the space was shared, public, and not very inviting. The lift and stairs sometimes smelt of smoke or urine and occasionally had a cigarette butt or broken bottle in them. The cold stale air and sharp <italic>haram</italic> (forbidden) smells are the antithesis of the soft, warm, oily <italic>halal</italic> (permissible) fragrances of “inside.” While outside it is often bitterly cold, inside the thermostats are turned up to a Sylheti 25 °C.</p>
<p>The emphasis in reception space was on comfortable seating—sofas and chairs—and on watching television. The size and sophistication of televisions in the <italic>Londoni</italic> flats I visited surprised me. In line with Islamic ideas, there was little decoration on the walls and few, if any, images of people or animals. Most houses had some sort of Qur’anic inscription on a poster hung on the wall. A large television usually dominated the communal space. The cramped private sphere made the lives of women and children at home more restrictive in the <italic>Londoni</italic> flat than in the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic>. The television and the telephone were windows to the outside, a stimulating, ever-changing antidote to the monotony of the small private, undecorated space.</p>
<p>Bangladeshi eating patterns mean that the whole family rarely eats all together sitting at a large table in the European ideal, so there were no large dining tables. One family I visited regularly had a curtain between the kitchen and the living room, which separated this space within the household. In the small kitchen, there was a table where the husband would eat alone or with his oldest son, the children would be fed when they returned from school, or I would eat alone, or with the father or the oldest son, on visits to the house. In another flat, the door to the kitchen remained closed throughout my first visit. Later it opened, and as I became closer to the family, the headscarves, modified purdah, and privacy were abandoned.</p>
<p>In the flats in Islington, the bedrooms were in the deepest recesses away from the entrance, not at the front as they are in the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic>. Outside the door is the cold, hard, public world of the corridor and street. There, one may be observed by any stranger or run into any kind of person. Before leaving that door, headscarves were positioned and the private world left behind. Rather than an expanse of field, a pond, and a track between the private and the public spheres, there was a narrow wooden door.</p>
<p>The flat is small, designed for a nuclear family, so however close by friends or kin may be, a visit to them requires passing through outside, public space. The dangers of the street and potential for observation by strangers are present as soon as one steps over the threshold. Any shopping or visits to local services also require entering into public space. This arrangement is structured and structuring. Systems have been designed to fit with patterns of behavior and in turn reinforce them; the centralized services of the state health care and education system, for example, like in Frankfurt, require interaction in the public sphere.</p>
<p>The practices of confinement to private, inside space for women and children present in the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic> are highly restrictive when applied to the <italic>Londoni</italic> flat. Children in my study found school stimulating and liberating, they participated eagerly in whatever activities they could. This is partly because of the restrictive nature of the ideas of inside and outside in Bangladeshi notions of childhood applied to inner-city London architecture. I also found that the space of the “Bangla-speaking sphere” and British Bangladeshi habitus was shrinking. Alongside the strong vitality of other languages and social fields, this is because the dividing line between the inside and outside is so thin and the space inside so small. This phenomenon has also influenced Islamic practices such as headscarf wearing, which is more prevalent in London than it is in rural Sylhet. I argue, influenced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1206331212466080">Rozario (2006)</xref>, that this is partly because of the coming together of the realities of modern urban life and Islamist influences on British Bangladeshis.</p>
<p>The <italic>Londoni</italic> flat and London’s public architecture, structured by Londoners’ practices are (re)structuring the lives, practices, and habitus of British Bangladeshi children. Places are cultural constructions, they do not exist in and of themselves. They exist as a result of social life, as a result of the meanings that people ascribe to them. Conceptions of place are constantly negotiated and reformulated based on changing material conditions of contexts and positionality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1206331212466080">Olwig &amp; Gullov, 2003</xref>, p. 7). Transitions such as the one from the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic> to the <italic>Londoni</italic> flat create social change. Children negotiate these changes, and practices relating to children are also influenced, as I have shown, by space. Spaces and the meanings ascribed to them proved to be an influential factor in British Bangladeshi children’s lives. Next, I want to discuss ideas about that very special place—built out of a dense mass of meaning and social construction—“home.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1206331212466080">
<title>Home and Belonging</title>
<p>The idea of home, it has been argued, has been altered by huge changes in patterns of communication and physical mobility in a deterritorialized, transnational, or globalized world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1206331212466080">Morley, 2001</xref>, p. 428). Home can be seen both as a physical place, the house, and as a more symbolic concept, what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1206331212466080">Morley (2001)</xref> refers to as “<italic>heimat</italic>,” the “spaces of belonging,” which can be at different scales—local, national, or transnational (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1206331212466080">Morley, 2001</xref>, p. 425). For people who move during their lifetimes, as nearly everyone does now; home can have a variety of meanings: where one usually lives, or where one’s family lives, one’s native country; but that concept can have different interpretations: where one was born, where one now lives, or where one grew up could all be in different physical places (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1206331212466080">Ahmed, 1999</xref>, p. 338).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1206331212466080">Morley (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1206331212466080">2001</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1206331212466080">Ahmed (1999)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1206331212466080">Brah (1996)</xref> all point to a distinction between the idea and practice of home. Brah writes specifically about diaspora groups. The idea of home is as a “mythic place of desire in the diasporic imagination” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1206331212466080">Brah, 1996</xref>, p. 192), the place of origin, a place so romanticized and mythologized that it is impossible to return to because it does not exist. Home is also the “lived experience of a locality” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1206331212466080">Brah, 1996</xref>, p. 192), the sensory, physical experiences of living in a particular place. This experience is, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1206331212466080">Brah (1996)</xref> reminds us, “mediated by the historically specific everyday of social relations” (p. 192). This sounds like Bourdieu’s link between habitus and home described above.</p>
<p>Brah is influenced by Gilroy’s contention that the idea of home is simultaneously about roots and routes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1206331212466080">Gilroy, 1993</xref>, p. 190). Gilroy’s play on words describes both the mythic place of origin, the roots and the lived experiences, the daily physical realities and practices, the routes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1206331212466080">Brah, 1996</xref>, p. 192). The mythic place of desire that Brah discusses, applies not only to diaspora groups or migrants but to all of us, who, to varying degrees, have an imagination about our own and other nations that develops during childhood (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1206331212466080">Piaget &amp; Weil, 1951</xref>). Who inhabits or shares our imagination of the home or homeland is an important part of this concept. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1206331212466080">Brah (1996)</xref> argues,
<disp-quote>
<p>The question of home . . . is intrinsically linked with the way in which processes of inclusion and exclusion operate and are subjectively experienced under given circumstances. It is centrally about our political and personal struggles over the social regulation of “belonging.” (p. 192)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>“Primordialist” approaches to belonging see the nation as linked to race, kinship, blood ties, and land binding people together, conflating a territory with a group of people. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1206331212466080">Anderson (1983)</xref> shows how belonging and connections are socially constructed through the consumption of similar print media, books, and newspapers, as well as television and Internet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1206331212466080">Kalra, Kaur, &amp; Hutnyk, 2005</xref>, p. 31). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1206331212466080">Morley (2000)</xref> shows how the concept of the nation and of home are constructed and maintained by “coordinated choreographies.” These must be performed at specific times in specific places, which not only create the sense of community, knowing that every family is doing the same (eating a thanksgiving meal in one example), but also contribute to the meaning of the home as the place where this ritual takes place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1206331212466080">Morley, 2000</xref>, pp. 16, 19).</p>
<p>The “apprenticeship” that children go through teaches them how to behave in a way appropriate to their “culture” class and is heavily gendered (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1206331212466080">Silva, 2005</xref>, p. 94). The division of space into male-public and female-private and the construction of home as the space for interactions between mother and child have been instrumental in the strong relationship between ideas of the “home” and of the “child.” However, the home is not always an ideal space for children; it is the most common site of abuse by adults, for example. The strict regulation of space, surveillance, and control by adults at home is also problematic for many children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1206331212466080">James, Jenks, &amp; Prout, 1998</xref>, p. 53).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1206331212466080">Morley (2000)</xref> cites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1206331212466080">Wood and Beck’s (1994)</xref> analysis, which sees children as outsiders in the home, barbarians who dirty and disrupt it. Parents must teach children a huge number of rules to bring them in (and up). These rules are latent but are “disrobed” as they are explained to children. This both maintains the values of the adults by protecting the room and its contents from the children and reproduces them by instilling them in the children. The home thus becomes a “field of rules” for the child and is where they learn to behave “properly”; learning the “habitus” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1206331212466080">Morley, 2000</xref>, p. 20).</p>
<p>It seems that for the moment, the “routes,” the repetitive practices, and lived experiences of the habitus and home are more important for these British Bangladeshi children than the “mythical place of desire” or their “roots.” Perhaps later in life, with more searching and intellectualization in addition to a sense of rejection of and from aspects of British society, these children will examine their “roots,” their mythic places of origin in more depth. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1206331212466080">Hebdige (1987)</xref> notes, a person’s “roots” can be made and remade and mixed and remixed within their lifetime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1206331212466080">Hebdige, 1987</xref>, p. 157). The significance and meanings of home to these children may change dramatically over the next few years of their lives.</p>
<p>When I asked children about the meanings of <italic>desh</italic> and <italic>bidesh</italic> (<italic>desh</italic> and <italic>bidesh</italic> are loosely translated as home and away; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1206331212466080">Gardner, 1993</xref>), the results were often tortuous and complex. Discussions of the meanings of <italic>desh</italic> and <italic>bidesh</italic> led to some interesting revelations in a discussion with Shirin and Rafique about their visit to Bangladesh:</p>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Do you know what <italic>desh</italic> means?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Shirin:</speaker>
<p>Yeah.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>Where’s your <italic>desh</italic>?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Shirin:</speaker>
<p>Er, London.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>What about <italic>bidesh</italic>?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Shirin:</speaker>
<p><italic>Bidesh—</italic>Bangladesh.</p>
<p>Laughter from Sumaya [mother]</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Rafique:</speaker>
<p>I don’t know.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Shirin:</speaker>
<p>Oh no no, <italic>bidesh</italic> is this one and then <italic>desh</italic> is the other, Bangladesh.</p>
<p> . . .</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>B:</speaker>
<p>What do you think, what is the <italic>desh</italic>, what does <italic>desh</italic> mean?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Abdul [father]:</speaker>
<p>For them, which is they’re describing which is correct. For me as I grew up in Bangladesh so for me, my country is . . . already Rafique said it, because he’s saying that, that, he feels in Bangladesh wasn’t his home, he felt it he was in holiday so he can’t call that as a home.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Rafique:</speaker>
<p>I know why, I was born in London and I wasn’t born in Bangladesh, I was already settled in London, which I felt comfortable with, but in Bangladesh, I was not born there, I was not settled, it was a holiday. (Discussion about visits with Shirin, Rafique, and Nasrin, November 28, 2008)</p>
</speech>
<p>In this excerpt from the discussion, Abdul summarizes his children’s feelings of belonging in London, which they and especially Rafique expressed on more than one occasion. His understanding of <italic>desh</italic> and <italic>bidesh</italic> is based on the literal meaning of the words, so he says that the children are correct in saying that London is their <italic>desh</italic>. His understanding of <italic>desh</italic> and “home” is based on the “primordialist” notion discussed earlier. He says that Bangladesh will always be his <italic>desh</italic> as he was born there and lived there until he was 11. An individual’s relations with Britain and Bangladesh, factors such as the length of time spent in each place, and the sense of belonging one has to each place are influential in determining one’s understanding of the terms <italic>desh</italic> and <italic>bidesh</italic>. Semantic understandings of the terms also vary, and these variables create different interpretations of their meanings. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1206331212466080">Gardner and Mand (2008)</xref>, for example, encountered quite different interpretations of <italic>desh</italic> and <italic>bidesh</italic> in their research (p. 12).</p>
<p>Feeling “comfortable” and “settled” are things that Rafique appeals to in his idea of what home means. Many of the children felt disorientated and uncomfortable on visits to Bangladesh. The familiar, learned routines and dispositions of the habitus, intimately bound up with the inhabited space of London are what create a sense of “home” for them. The embodied, unconscious nature of this habitus also contributed to the contradictory and confusing nature of children’s replies to questions about this. Trying to express in words something that just feels right is hard. The ambivalence and disorientation observed among children on visits to Bangladesh and their sense of relief on return to London revealed the effects of their socialization in London on their sense of home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1206331212466080">Zeitlyn, 2012</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1206331212466080">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>We can see how ideas about childhood and gender are manifested in the way in which space in the rural Sylheti <italic>bari</italic> and the <italic>Londoni</italic> flat is used and access to space is restricted. Through socialization in the home, in these spaces, children learn their habitus. British Bangladeshi children learn elements of a Bangladeshi habitus on their visits to the Sylheti <italic>bari</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1206331212466080">Zeitlyn, 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>However, British Bangladeshi children learn different habitus in their flats, schools, and neighborhoods in London. The arrangement of space leads to different practices and awkward translations of practices from rural Sylhet. The translation of practices from Sylhet has led to new practices emerging in London and the spatial restriction of the lives of women and children. They are confined to the inside, private space, of their flats in London. The importance of spatial arrangements should not be overplayed; it must be set alongside diverse local and transnational influences on children and families. Spatial arrangements both create and reflect these social influences.</p>
<p>The extent to which habitus is tied to a place, where the objective conditions and experiences produce it, is not clear from Bourdieu’s work. Bourdieu used his concepts to discuss classes of people, but most subsequent work using his concepts has centered on particular places (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1206331212466080">Kelly &amp; Lusius, 2006</xref>, p. 835). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1206331212466080">Kelly and Lusius (2006)</xref> argue, in their article about Filipino immigrants in Canada, that habitus need not be confined to one place and that immigrants may continue to react to new conditions using the rules of their place of origin. They venture a step further and maintain that habitus itself may become transnational, encompassing the two (or more) locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1206331212466080">Kelly &amp; Lusius, 2006</xref>, p. 836). They argue that the “lived spaces that contain the habitus are thus more social than physical” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1206331212466080">Kelly &amp; Lusius, 2006</xref>, p. 845).</p>
<p>Here I am arguing that although habitus can and does become transnational, and relate to social spaces (or social fields), the connection between physical places and spaces and the bodies of the people who inhabit them are vital for the effects that they have on the way habitus develops as an embodied, automatic set of dispositions. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1206331212466080">Mitchell (2000)</xref> observes, even if we conceptualize space as social and transnational, “neither territory nor space simply dematerialise, and so neither do identities come untethered from the spaces that give them shape” (p. 263).</p>
<p>Despite the confinement children feel in their small flats and the frustrations this leads to, British Bangladeshi children, socialized in this space, feel comfortable in it. The routine, repeated, everyday practices of socialization into their habitus have been influenced by the spaces they inhabit and also influence the nature of the space. The different uses of space, practices, and systems of logic in Bangladesh lead them to feel disorientated when they are on visits to Bangladesh and to consider the familiar spaces of London their “home.”</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This article is based on my doctoral research, which was funded by the Arts and Humanities Research Council’s Diasporas Migration and Identities Programme <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diasporas.ac.uk/">http://www.diasporas.ac.uk/</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1206331212466080">
<label>1.</label>
<p>All names of people and places are pseudonyms.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Benjamin Zeitlyn</bold> is a lecturer in international education and development in the Centre for International Education at the University of Sussex. His recent research has been on access to education and dropping out of school in Ethiopia. At the Sussex Centre for Migration Research, he worked on transnational childhoods and identities, principally with British Bangladeshi children. His work developed ideas of transnational social spaces and the experiences of children growing up in multicultural and transnational societies. He has an interest in migration and development and, particularly, in the experiences of children.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Home and away, narratives of migration and estrangement</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Cultural Studies</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Imagined communities</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blanchet</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Lost innocence, stolen childhoods</source>. <publisher-loc>Dhaka, Bangladesh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bourdieu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <source>Outline of a theory of practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Cartographies of diaspora: Contesting identities</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The routes and tales of the Bangladeshi settlers</source>. <publisher-loc>Birmingham, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sylhet Social History Group</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Family matters: A discussion of the Bangladeshi and Pakistani extended family and community in supporting the children’s education</article-title>. <source>Sociological Review</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>678</fpage>-<lpage>695</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dench</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gavron</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The new East End</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Profile Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Department for Education and Skills</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Ethnicity and education: The evidence on minority ethnic pupils aged 5-16</source> (Research Topic Paper, 2006 ed.). <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Veiled meanings: Young British Muslim women and the negotiation of differences</article-title>. <source>Gender, Place &amp; Culture</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eade</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>The politics of community: Bangladeshis in East London</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Place-making as project? Habitus and migration in transnational cities</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rooksby</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Habitus: A sense of place</source> (pp. <fpage>315</fpage>-<lpage>333</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Farnham, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Desh Bidesh: Sylheti images of home and away</article-title>. <source>Man</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Global migrants, local lives: Travel and transformation in rural Bangladesh</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mand</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Transglobal childhoods: Diasporic children in East London, diasporas migration and identities</source> (Working paper No. 009, Arts and Humanities Research Council). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diasporas.ac.uk/assets/Gardner%20working%20paper.pdf">http://www.diasporas.ac.uk/assets/Gardner%20working%20paper.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shukur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>“I’m Bengali, I’m Asian, and I’m living here”: The changing identity of British Bengalis</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Desh Pardesh: The South Asian presence in Britain</source> (pp. <fpage>142</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>C. Hurst</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The black Atlantic: Modernity and double consciousness</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hebdige</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>Cut ‘N’ mix: Culture, identity and Caribbean music</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prout</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Theorising childhood</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hutnyk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Diaspora and hybridity</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Growing up global: Economic restructuring and children’s everyday lives</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lusius</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Migration and the transnational habitus: Evidence from the Philippines and Canada</article-title>. <source>Environment and Planning A</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>831</fpage>-<lpage>847</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Cultural geography: A critical introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Home territories: Media, mobility and identity</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Belongings, place, space and identity in a mediated world</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Cultural Studies</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Office for National Statistics</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>Focus on People and Migration.</source> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/rel/fertility-analysis/focus-on-people-and-migration/december-2005/index.html">http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/rel/fertility-analysis/focus-on-people-and-migration/december-2005/index.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Office for Standards in Education</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <source>Achievement of Bangladeshi heritage pupils</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olwig</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gullov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Towards an anthropology of children and place</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Olwig</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gullov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Children’s places, cross cultural perspectives</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piaget</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1951</year>). <article-title>The development in children of the idea of the homeland and of relations with other countries</article-title>. <source>International Social Science Bulletin</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>561</fpage>-<lpage>578</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piggott</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>2001 census profiles: Bangladeshis in London DMAG Briefing 2006/16</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greater London Authority, Data Management and Analysis Group</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rozario</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The new burqa in Bangladesh: Empowerment or violation of women’s rights?</article-title> <source>Women’s Studies International Forum</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>368</fpage>-<lpage>380</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Gendered mobilities: Epilogue</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Uteng</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Gendered mobilities</source> (pp. <fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>265</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Aldershot, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Gender, home and family in cultural capital theory</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Home rules: Culture, environment and the American family</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1206331212466080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zeitlyn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Maintaining transnational social fields: The role of visits to Bangladesh for British Bangladeshi children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>953</fpage>-<lpage>968</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>