<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LRT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splrt</journal-id>
<journal-title>Lighting Research &amp; Technology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1477-1535</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0938</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1477153511427427</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1477153511427427</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Energy efficiency of alternative lighting control systems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Chiogna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1477153511427427">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1477153511427427"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mahdavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1477153511427427">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Albatici</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1477153511427427">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Frattari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><degrees>PE</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1477153511427427">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1477153511427427"><label>a</label>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of Trento, Trento, Italy</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1477153511427427"><label>b</label>Department of Building Physics and Building Ecology, Vienna University of Technology, Vienna, Austria</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1477153511427427">Michela Chiogna, University of Trento, Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Via Mesiano 77, 38123 Trento, Italy. E-mail: <email>michela.chiogna@ing.unitn.it</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>397</fpage>
<lpage>415</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Chartered Institution of Building Services Engineers 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Due to new European standards and requirements for energy performance in non-residential buildings, it is important to explore and quantify the benefits of intelligent (automated) energy-efficient operating systems relative to conventional (manual) systems. This paper explores the energy performance of an automated lighting control system under realistic conditions in two groups of lecture rooms that have the same shape, dimensions and exposure. The results demonstrate that the use of automated systems for electric lighting control can improve the energy performance of the system between 40% and 65% depending on the complexity of the system and the parameters under control.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1477153511427427" sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title>
<p>An early definition of sustainable development was formulated in 1987 by the World Commission on Environment and Development (WCED).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1477153511427427">1</xref></sup> The importance of environmental issues became a key aspect of political and scientific debates around the world from that moment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1477153511427427">2</xref></sup> In this context, the built environment plays an important role: The residential and commercial sectors account for more than 40% of end energy consumption in the European Community and are thus responsible for an important part of carbon dioxide emissions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1477153511427427">3</xref></sup> According to the IEA (International Energy Agency), electricity use for lighting ranges from 5% (Belgium and Luxembourg) to 15% (Denmark, Japan, and the Netherlands) of the total electrical energy use in industrialised countries. Approximately 50% of lighting energy (531 TWh) in IEA member countries evaluated is used within the service sector (from 39% in Germany and Japan to 61% in the Netherlands).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1477153511427427">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Considerable savings could be achieved by application of intelligent control technologies in existing buildings, with acceptable economic implications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1477153511427427">5</xref></sup> New European Regulations refer specifically to the use of occupancy and light sensors to control artificial light and to improve the systems’ efficiency.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1477153511427427">6</xref></sup> Software design tools are intended to help designers with the qualitative and quantitative elements of daylighting design through features that commonly include: Visualisation of the luminous environment of a given daylighting design, prediction of daylight factors in a space lit by diffuse daylight, control of the penetration of the sun’s rays and visualisation of the dynamic behaviour of sunlight.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1477153511427427">7</xref></sup> In addition, software applications have been developed to predict the energy saving obtainable using automated lighting systems: Specifically the dimming of the artificial light as a function of the natural light levels measured at discrete points.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1477153511427427">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1477153511427427">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>These simulation tools require lengthy input processes and are too time consuming to be used by architects and designers. As a result, simplified methods have been developed to estimate the saving in electrical energy use for artificial lighting due to the proper use of daylight. However, the parameters typically considered (window area, window type, perimeter area) do not include automated control systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1477153511427427">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>Moreover, energy simulation tools for existing buildings do not necessarily adequately model the actual performance of daylighting systems. The use of reference information instead of measured solar radiation data can cause errors of between 10% and 25%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1477153511427427">15</xref></sup> Energy saving potential can be increased up to 27% by proper adjustment of the lighting control system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1477153511427427">16</xref></sup> Standard sky conditions considered in many simulation programs are often far from the real data (overestimated up to 30% and underestimated up to 60%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1477153511427427">17</xref></sup>). The main causes of prediction errors are temporal problems, outdoor illuminance and sky luminance distribution simulation, fenestration features, operation, indoor illuminance level expected, human factors and lighting control results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1477153511427427">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>These last two factors show a high variability and significantly influence the final energy saving amount expected from the operation of automated control systems. For this reason, the international scientific community carried out several studies in order to monitor and analyse users’ interactions with building control systems and devices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1477153511427427">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1477153511427427">20</xref></sup> The computational modelling of occupants’ control-oriented actions in building performance simulation applications can be significantly improved when based on such empirical information as user behaviour<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1477153511427427">21</xref></sup> and real use conditions. In this way it is possible to collect data about both building users’ interactions with building control systems and device efficiency in order to develop a stochastic model for predicting lighting energy consumption.</p>
<p>For this reason, it is important to explore and quantify the benefits of energy efficient automated control systems compared with a conventional (manual) operation system via realistic case studies. The energy saving potential of automated lighting scenarios should be monitored in real use conditions and not just in controlled laboratory environments in order to reliably document the energy efficiency of automated control systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1477153511427427">22</xref></sup> A number of studies have been conducted in this field<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1477153511427427">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1477153511427427">24</xref></sup> where the monitored scenarios are compared with assumed conditions and not actually monitored ones.</p>
<sec id="sec2-1477153511427427"><title>1.1 Aim of the paper</title>
<p>This paper deals with an elaboration of an innovative design tool for lighting systems. Specifically, a methodological approach for the energy efficiency evaluation under different scenarios is presented. A comparison has been made between automated lighting operation on the one side and conventional operation scenarios on the other side of a building.</p>
<p>The goals of the data analysis presented in this paper are:
<list id="list1-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>To calculate the percentage energy saving potential for various applications of building automation systems used for lighting control.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>To monitor users’ behaviour in lecture halls with the traditional lighting system and to quantify the amount of energy use constituting an improper use of electric light.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>To analyse the performance of the automated systems, in order to improve their efficiency in different scenarios.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The final objective in this research is to compare the performance of lighting systems operated manually and lighting systems operated automatically in terms of energy efficiency and the visual comfort maintained.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1477153511427427" sec-type="methods"><title>2. Method</title>
<p>The analysis of environmental conditions is conducted in two groups of spaces, namely lecture rooms at the Faculty of Engineering of the University of Trento – Italy, with the same shape, dimensions, and orientation.</p>
<p>The geometrical parameters checked in order to guarantee the comparability of the spaces are:
<list id="list2-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Geometric base case (orientation, dimension – area and perimeter, etc.).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Materials for walls, ceiling(s) and floor(s).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Openings (windows, roof lights) and their positions.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Outside obstructions for the windows.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Luminaires.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>In this research the manual lighting system is assumed to be operated by switching the lights on/off. The automatic operating scenarios are defined as follows:</p>
<p><italic>Scenario 1 (SL<sub>1</sub>):</italic>
<list id="list3-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Occupancy detection and minimum illuminance control, as primary condition to switch on the lighting system (if <italic>E</italic><sub>m</sub> &gt; <italic>E</italic><sub>threshold</sub> then switch off, where <italic>E</italic><sub>m</sub> = mean illuminance coming from daylight).</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p><italic>Scenario 2 (SL<sub>2</sub>):</italic>
<list id="list4-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>As SL<sub>1</sub>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dimming regulation of the artificial light as a function of the natural light level detected at discrete points, as the second automation level.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p><italic>Scenario 3 (SL<sub>3</sub>):</italic>
<list id="list5-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Occupancy detection by zones (the space has been divided into discrete parts, each one detected by a presence sensor) and minimum illuminance control as primary condition to switch on the lighting system (if <italic>E</italic><sub>m</sub> &gt; <italic>E</italic><sub>threshold</sub> then switch off).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dimming regulation of the artificial light in more dimming loops in order to approximate an ideal continuous dimming in the space, as the second automation level.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Use of different and more efficient light sources.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<sec id="sec4-1477153511427427"><title>2.1 Energy saving percentage</title>
<p>The energy consumption of both automated systems and traditional ones has been recorded in order to use these data to calculate the mean energy use of the traditional class rooms (ML) with the scenarios (SL<sub>1,</sub> SL<sub>2,</sub> SL<sub>3</sub> levels).</p>
<p>The energy consumption of the <italic>i</italic>-th room has been recorded in Wh/m<sup>2</sup>. This data has been divided by a defined operating time interval, so that it has been calculated in terms of W/m<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1477153511427427">Equation (1)</xref>). In order to have a continuous profile of energy demand, a system with a significant detection interval has to be used. For this purpose an impulse counter has been interfaced to a static active energy meter.</p>
<p>A detection time interval has to be fixed. The discrete number of Wh accumulated in this time interval has been recorded and displayed by the supervision system as:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1477153511427427"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ec</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ec</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>fa</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list6-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>ec<sub>i,j</sub></italic> = energy consumption of the <italic>i</italic>-th room during the <italic>j</italic>-th time interval, for the observed operating period (W/m<sup>2</sup>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>j</italic> = <italic>j</italic>-th time interval.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>fa<sub>i</sub></italic> = <italic>i</italic>-th room floor area (m<sup>2</sup>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of intervals (day).</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The energy consumption for the ML during the <italic>j</italic>-th interval, expressed in W/m<sup>2</sup>, has been calculated as:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1477153511427427"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ec</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ML</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ec</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list7-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>ec<sub>i,j</sub></italic> = energy consumption of the <italic>i</italic>-th room operated by manual system during the <italic>j</italic>-th time interval (W/m<sup>2</sup>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>j</italic> = <italic>j</italic>-th time interval.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of rooms operated by the manual system considered.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1477153511427427"><title>2.2 Observed occupancy time</title>
<p>Presence is recorded by a numerical variable defined as an integer that assumes the value 1 if occupancy is detected or the value 0 if it is not (absence). Each datum recorded is correlated with the detection time. The time included between two values equal to 1 of the presence variable is the presence interval (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1477153511427427">Equation (3)</xref>), the time included between two values equal to 0 of the presence variable is the absence interval (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-1477153511427427">Equation (4)</xref>).
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1477153511427427"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
if the presence variable value is 1 where:
<list id="list8-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>i</italic> = room detected index</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>j</italic> = time interval index</p></list-item>
</list>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-1477153511427427"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math4-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
if the presence variable value is 0 and <inline-formula id="ilm1-1477153511427427"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> &gt; <inline-formula id="ilm2-1477153511427427"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>min</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> while <inline-formula id="ilm3-1477153511427427"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <italic>i</italic> is the room detected index and <italic>j</italic> is the time interval index.</p>
<p>The space is monitored by the occupancy sensors after a defined time interval, determined by the accuracy of the measurement and the precision of the device.</p>
<p>These data have to be collected and registered in a databank by the supervision software, calculating a minimum significant absence period <italic>Δt<sub>a</sub></italic><sub>,min,</sub> defined depending on the space size and the activity typology. This time interval could be smaller than the one implemented in the presence sensor detection program.</p>
<p>The normalisation factor for presence <italic>PF<sub>i</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-1477153511427427">Equation (5)</xref>) has to be calculated for each automated room as the ratio between the arithmetic mean of observed presence (in seconds) in each automated room <italic>P<sub>A</sub></italic>,<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-1477153511427427">Equation (6)</xref>) and the arithmetic mean of observed presence in the traditional rooms considered <italic>P<sub>T</sub></italic> (in seconds) (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-1477153511427427">Equations (7)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-1477153511427427">8</xref>)).
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-1477153511427427"><label>(5)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math5-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-1477153511427427"><label>(6)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math6-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PF</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list9-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>p<sub>i,j</sub></italic> = presence seconds in the <italic>i</italic>-th automated room during the <italic>j</italic>-th presence time interval</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of time intervals into which a day has been divided</p></list-item>
</list>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-1477153511427427"><label>(7)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math7-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list10-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>p<sub>i,j</sub></italic> = presence seconds in the <italic>i</italic>-th traditional room during the <italic>j</italic>-th presence time interval</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of time intervals into which a day has been divided</p></list-item>
</list>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-1477153511427427"><label>(8)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math8-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list11-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of rooms operated manually under monitoring.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1477153511427427"><title>2.3 Outside illuminance</title>
<p>Each room monitored has a different occupancy time related to the time table of the workday. In order to compare the same outside conditions it is necessary to check and compare the outside illumination conditions during the occupancy period.</p>
<p>For this reason a normalisation factor <italic>IF<sub>i</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-1477153511427427">Equation (9)</xref>) has been introduced. It is calculated as the ratio between the arithmetic mean of the outside illuminance during the work period in each automated room <italic>I<sub>Ai</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-1477153511427427">Equation (10)</xref>) and the arithmetic mean calculated for the manually operated rooms <italic>I<sub>T</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11-1477153511427427">Equation (11)</xref>).
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-1477153511427427"><label>(9)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math9-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>IF</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula9-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-1477153511427427"><label>(10)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math10-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula10-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list12-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>i<sub>i,j</sub></italic> = outside illuminance for the <italic>i</italic>-th automated room during the <italic>j</italic>-th time interval.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = numbers of time intervals into which a day has been divided.</p></list-item>
</list>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-1477153511427427"><label>(11)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math11-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula11-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list13-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of rooms operated manually under monitoring.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-1477153511427427"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math14-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula14-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
<p>The outside illumination in lux is monitored and recorded by a numerical variable defined as an integer. Each datum recorded is correlated with the detection time. The detection interval is implemented in the weather device program depending on the technical characteristic of the instrument and on the climatic conditions of the monitored site.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1477153511427427"><title>2.4 Indoor illuminance values</title>
<p>The intelligent light system is regulated and dimmed by means of light detectors and dimming actuators in order to guarantee a minimum illuminance level (in compliance with the existing European standard<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1477153511427427">25</xref></sup>). Nevertheless, in traditional rooms build before 2004, the minimum illuminance could be lower, in compliance with the previous standard.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1477153511427427">26</xref></sup> Note that in this paper the illuminance is the sum of daylight and electric light unless specified otherwise.</p>
<p>In order to evaluate different levels of lighting system performance, as a function of the illuminance maintained on the task area, the indoor illuminance factor <italic>i<sub>i</sub></italic> has been introduced (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula12-1477153511427427">Equation (12)</xref>). This factor is calculated as the weighted mean between the illuminance detected <italic>E<sub>i,j</sub></italic> and the minimum illuminance <italic>E</italic><sub>min</sub>:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-1477153511427427"><label>(12)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math12-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>min</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>min</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula12-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
where:
<list id="list14-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>E<sub>i,j</sub></italic> = inside illuminance in the <italic>i</italic>-th traditional room during the <italic>j</italic>-th time interval.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>N</italic> = number of time intervals into which a day has been divided.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1477153511427427"><title>2.5 Calculation of the energy saving for each scenario</title>
<p>Using the normalisation factors explained above, the energy use and the consequent performance of each scenario is defined in conformity with the boundary conditions of the other rooms monitored (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-1477153511427427">Equation (13)</xref>). So, in a second step, it will be possible to establish the energy saving percentage for different scenarios in comparison with the ML.
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-1477153511427427"><label>(13)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math13-1477153511427427"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>SL</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ec</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PF</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>IF</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula13-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
With the <italic>paired comparison</italic> between the operation systems of each scenario, it is possible to define the energy saving percentage for each automation system solution.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1477153511427427"><title>2.6 Typical day data analysis</title>
<p>In order to understand and model users’ behaviour in traditional classrooms (ML) and to quantify the energy saving potentials of automation systems for lighting control, a typical day data analysis has been carried out. In this way, it is possible to perform an hourly data analysis, instead of a daily overview of the system functions and user interactions. To conduct this statistical analysis, it is necessary to consider the conditions operating in the monitored environment during a defined time interval over the course of the day.</p>
<p>The data monitored by the input devices of the automation system are sent to the bus not regularly, but in an event-based manner (recorded by the supervision system). For this reason, the data for each day analysed has been averaged considering a discrete temporal interval, using a LabView calculation programmed for the research data analysis. In this way the collected results are synchronised and it is possible to relate different factors occurring at the same time in a specific room.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1477153511427427"><title>3. Case study</title>
<p>The research has been carried out at the Faculty of Engineering of the University of Trento – Italy. The cross-shaped layout of the building is characterised by two parallel wings, both facing south (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1477153511427427">Figure 1</xref>). The lecture rooms are symmetrical and have the same shape. This configuration allows the comparison between three classrooms in the east wing (2A, 2B, and 2C), operated in a conventional manner (luminaires operated manually by the users), and three classrooms in the west wing (2M, 2N, and 2P), operated automatically and programmed specifically for different scenarios.
<fig id="fig1-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Building and luminaire layout (above: in east wing traditional classrooms, in west wing automated classrooms; next page: control circuits distribution and sensor positions).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig1a.tif"/><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig1b.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p>In the traditional classrooms considered, both teachers and students have the right to control electric lighting (switch on and off) as well as opening windows and shutters, depending on their common needs. (Note that the blinds are also manually operated in the classrooms with automated lighting controls.)</p>
<p>The main geometric parameters describing the classrooms analysed are the following:
<list id="list15-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>2P, 2N, 2B, 2C: 32 seats, length 7 m, width 6.3 m, height 3 m, three windows each 1.4 m width and 2.8 m height.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>2M, 2A: 77 seats, length 12.8 m, width 6.3 m, height 3 m, six windows each 1.4 m width and 2.8 m height.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>We measured the inside illuminance on the desk using a grid of discrete point (1.5 m x 1.5 m) with no electric lights on and with window blinds retracted during 4 days in the winter season and 4 days in the summer season, considering different sky conditions. We have verified that the difference in the data was small (around 10% close to the windows, less than 5% internally). The measurements were also compared with a simulation model of the rooms performed with Adeline and the results fit the simulation outputs. The installed electric power density and electric light illuminance was also the same in both groups of rooms.</p>
<sec id="sec11-1477153511427427"><title>3.1 Lighting system design</title>
<p>The technology used to control the lecture halls is a comprehensive, integrated system for home and building automation: the Konnex solution. The KNX standard complies with the regulations EN 50090 (standard containing technical rules from Home and Building Electronic Systems) and allows a remarkable flexibility for the electric system.</p>
<p>The lighting used in lecture room 2M is a fluorescent ceiling luminaire 4x14W T5. In the other rooms the lighting type used is a fluorescent ceiling luminaire 4x18W T8. In the constant light regulation mode, the lights are operated in parallel rows.</p>
<p>In each traditional classroom a presence/light sensor has been installed, but only for monitoring.</p>
<p>The scenarios implemented and monitored in the research case study are defined as follows:
<list id="list16-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Scenario 1: use of occupancy sensors (the light will be turned off automatically after 15 min of absence) and minimum illuminance control (if <italic>E</italic><sub>m</sub> &gt; 500 lx then switch off). This scenario has been used between September and December in the classroom 2P.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Scenario 2: as scenario 1 plus dimming regulation of the electric light in two rows of dimming loops (<italic>E</italic><sub>threshold</sub> = 500 lx, in compliance with existing standard<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1477153511427427">25</xref></sup>). This scenario has been applied in the new classroom 2 N for the whole year.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Scenario 3: as scenario 2, but with dimming of the electric light in three rows of dimming loops, switching on divided by zones (the lecture room has been divided into two parts, each one detected by a presence sensor).This scenario has been applied in the new classroom 2M during the whole year.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Scenario 1 bis: as scenario 2, but with dimming of the electric light in three rows of dimming loops. This scenario has been applied in the new classroom 2P between March and June.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>It is necessary to specify that in traditional lecture rooms the minimum illuminance should be only 300 lx, in compliance with the old national regulation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1477153511427427">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the second semester (Spring semester from March to June) the illuminance required has been changed to 300 lx instead of the 500 lx of the first semester. In this way it is possible to verify the effective energy saving percentage for the same performance of the light system.</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1477153511427427">Table 1</xref> the main characteristics of the electric lighting system for each room are shown. In order to separate the energy saving amount of each specific automation level the following paired comparisons have been made:
<list id="list17-1477153511427427" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>2P vs. ML = &gt; presence sensor (scenario 1)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>ML vs. 2P’ = &gt; dimming 1 + 1 + 1 (scenario 2)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>2N vs. 2P = &gt; dimming 1 + 2 (scenario 3)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>2P vs. 2M = &gt; room division (scenario 4)</p></list-item>
</list>
<table-wrap id="table1-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Lighting automation system definition for each classroom</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>LECTURE ROOM (application period)</th>
<th>presence sensor</th>
<th>Dimming channels = 1 + 1 + 1</th>
<th>Dimming channels = 2 + 1</th>
<th>New luminaires and 2 presence sensors</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>2A/2B/2C (winter and summer)</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>NO</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2P (winter)</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>NO</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2P’ (summer)</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>NO</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2N (winter and summer)</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>NO</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2M (winter and summer)</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>YES</td>
<td>NO</td>
<td>YES</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>In order to detect and record outside meteorological conditions a weather station has been installed. This device is used primarily for detection of brightness, but can also measure rain, temperature, day/night and wind speeds. It is necessary to select a place for the installation on the building where the wind, rain and sun can be measured uninhibited by obstructions. In particular, the light dome of the cover must not be in a shadow of the building or other external obstructions. In order to observe these installation requirements, the weather station has been installed closed to the roof, on the upper part of the south façade of the university building.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1477153511427427"><title>4. Data analysis evaluation</title>
<p>The data recorded and analysed are:
<list id="list18-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Presence and absence periods (by infrared occupancy sensors in all six classrooms).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Indoor illuminances (by indoor illuminance sensors).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>External illuminances (by weather station).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dimming percentage (by dimming actuators for scenarios involving dimming operations).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Energy use for lighting system (monitored separately for each lecture room by means of 6 dedicated meters).</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Monitoring results are stored in a database and structured by the supervision software Gefasoft 7.1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1477153511427427">27</xref></sup> For each day, a file is generated with temporally ordered data. Each single message is labelled with its own number by means of a FORTRAN program.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1477153511427427">28</xref></sup> The different data points have been synchronised using the LabView program.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1477153511427427">29</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="sec13-1477153511427427"><title>4.1 Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1477153511427427">Figure 2</xref> shows the occupancy results (presence level in percentage) as a function of the time for the three automated control scenarios. Moreover, it compares the mean presence value in the traditional classrooms both in winter and in summer semester (69 and 75 days recorded and analysed, respectively). A classroom is considered occupied when the occupancy sensor is activated in the space monitored, independent of the number of occupants.
<fig id="fig2-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Mean presence value for the traditional (ML) and for the three scenarios applied in the automated classrooms for the winter (upper) and summer (lower) periods. The presence levels in percentages are shown as a function of the time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1477153511427427">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the course of the indoor total illuminances (electric plus daylight) for different reference days in winter during the times when the traditional classroom were occupied.
<fig id="fig3-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Indoor total illuminances (electric plus daylight) during the occupancy period in the traditional classrooms (2A, 2B, 2C) for the winter months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1477153511427427">Figure 4</xref> shows, for the month of October, the course of the indoor illuminances for occupancy hours of the three traditional classrooms (2A, 2B, and 2C) and the associated mean value (ML).
<fig id="fig4-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Indoor total illuminances (electric plus daylight) during the occupancy period in the traditional classrooms (2A, 2B, 2C) in October and the associated mean value (ML).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1477153511427427">Figure 5</xref> shows the mean lighting energy use (Wh/m<sup>2</sup>) in the traditional classrooms as a function of the time of the day for three different months, for both the winter semester and the summer semester, as well as the seasonal mean values.
<fig id="fig5-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Mean lighting energy use in the traditional classrooms for three different months, both for winter semester (upper) and summer semester (lower).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1477153511427427">Figure 6</xref> shows the ML energy use in comparison with the lighting energy use of scenario 3 as a function of the time of the day for three different months together with the mean value, without normalisation factors.
<fig id="fig6-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Lighting energy use for scenario 2 for three different months in summer comparing mean values for automated classrooms and ML for traditional classrooms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1477153511427427">Figure 7</xref> shows, together for scenario 2 and ML, the occupancy-normalised lighting energy use.
<fig id="fig7-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Occupancy-normalised energy use for ML and scenario 2 as a function of the time of the day.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1477153511427427">Figure 8</xref> shows the energy use for scenario 2 normalised for (i) occupancy level and (ii) for occupancy and indoor illuminace.
<fig id="fig8-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Energy use for scenario 2 normalised for occupancy level and both indoor illuminance and occupancy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1477153511427427" sec-type="discussion"><title>5. Discussion</title>
<p>There is a difference between the occupancy levels monitored in the traditional classrooms in different winter and summer months. In addition, the occupancy level differs significantly between traditional rooms and those with the automated control scenarios (see for instance scenario 1 in the winter semester – <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1477153511427427">Figure 2</xref>). Thus, it was necessary to normalise the energy use values based on the occupancy data so as to properly compare the various scenarios. A normalisation was also performed regarding the outdoor illuminances that significantly change with the period considered, even though in this case the variations of illuminances for different scenarios were no more than 3% to 5% throughout the observation period. The occupancy period differs for each classroom, depending on the lecture schedule. As a consequence, the outdoor illuminance is different during the lecture period.</p>
<p>The indoor illuminance levels in the three traditional classrooms differ from each other and are different in different months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1477153511427427">Figure 3</xref>). Specifically, at certain periods, early in the morning or late in the evening, the illuminances are rather low. This is due to the fact that users either did not switch on the lights or did not open the shading devices. This fact was considered in the comparison of energy use values taking into account the actually prevailing illuminances. The classrooms have been modelled with the simulation software Adeline3.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1477153511427427">8</xref></sup> We compared calibrated simulated indoor illuminances (without the electric lighting contribution) with those measured by sensors for cases with the shades open. Simulated values were significantly higher than measured ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1477153511427427">Figure 4</xref>). This can be explained by considering the shades’ positions. In fact, the shading system is not always properly used to maximise daylight utilisation.</p>
<p>The energy consumption in traditional classrooms does not always directly correlate with outdoor illuminances. Indeed, the energy consumption during morning and early afternoon in October is higher than in the same period in November even if outside illuminance conditions are more favourable. Nonetheless, the mean energy use over the whole observation period is clearly related to outside illuminance, especially comparing winter and summer mean energy demand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1477153511427427">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
<p>The monitored energy use patterns in the classrooms with automated lighting control scenarios show a better daylight utilisation. In the winter semester the energy use for scenario 1 is higher than scenario 3, especially during evening classes, since maintaining the minimum illuminance (in scenario 1) requires all luminaires to be switched on. Again we can observe better performance in the summer months for scenario 3 when compared with traditional lecture rooms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1477153511427427">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the monitored energy use for the traditional classrooms and the ones with automated lighting control scenarios could not be directly compared, given the differences in occupancy and maintained illuminances. To observe the effect of occupancy, we can consider that the energy consumption of scenario 2 after 18:30 is higher than for ML but, considering the occupancy period as a normalisation factor, the energy demand in ML is higher in the last lesson hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1477153511427427">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
<p>To illustrate the effect of the maintained illuminances, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1477153511427427">Figure 8</xref> shows the monitored energy use for scenario 2 together with normalised curves for maintained illuminances of 300 lx and 500 lx. The effect of normalisation is understandably more significant in the evening and early morning hours, especially in the winter semester when compared to the summer one.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1477153511427427">Table 2</xref> shows the energy saving in different winter semester months for the three scenarios calculated as absolute values and, additionally, normalised for the following factors: presence, outdoor illuminance, and inside illuminace. Moreover, the percentage of energy saving has been converted in to values correlated to environmental and economic factors: CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> and €/m<sup>2</sup> (the conversion factor to express kWh in grams of CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent is 580 – experimentation year 2007;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1477153511427427">30</xref></sup> the cost of 1 kWh of electricity is 0.14588€ at 12/2007 in Italy).
<table-wrap id="table2-1477153511427427" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Energy saving in different winter and summer months for the three scenarios: Absolute values and normalised for presence, outdoor illuminance and inside illuminance factor.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1477153511427427" xlink:href="10.1177_1477153511427427-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="2"/><th colspan="3">SEPTEMBER<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">OCTOBER<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">NOVEMBER<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">DECEMBER<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th/>
<th/>
<th>SCENARIO1</th>
<th>SCENARIO2</th>
<th>SCENARIO3</th>
<th>SCENARIO1</th>
<th>SCENARIO2</th>
<th>SCENARIO3</th>
<th>SCENARIO1</th>
<th>SCENARIO2</th>
<th>SCENARIO3</th>
<th>SCENARIO1</th>
<th>SCENARIO2</th>
<th>SCENARIO3</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">ABSOLUTE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>1.15</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>1.35</td>
<td>2.26</td>
<td>2.05</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>2.17</td>
<td>2.16</td>
<td>1.21</td>
<td>1.98</td>
<td>1.65</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>37</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>44</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>0.30</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.32</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.29</td>
<td>0.24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>293</td>
<td>668</td>
<td>433</td>
<td>783</td>
<td>1313</td>
<td>1190</td>
<td>706</td>
<td>1258</td>
<td>1251</td>
<td>702</td>
<td>1146</td>
<td>954</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">NORMALIZED BY PRESENCE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>1.12</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>1.32</td>
<td>2.34</td>
<td>2.12</td>
<td>1.21</td>
<td>2.30</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>1.84</td>
<td>1.56</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>39</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>42</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>0.23</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>309</td>
<td>646</td>
<td>456</td>
<td>763</td>
<td>1355</td>
<td>1229</td>
<td>702</td>
<td>1332</td>
<td>1242</td>
<td>740</td>
<td>1067</td>
<td>906</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">NORMALIZED BY OUT. ILLUMINANCE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>2.62</td>
<td>2.34</td>
<td>1.37</td>
<td>2.56</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>1.35</td>
<td>1.79</td>
<td>1.44</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>38</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>39</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.21</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>300</td>
<td>589</td>
<td>465</td>
<td>685</td>
<td>1520</td>
<td>1359</td>
<td>796</td>
<td>1484</td>
<td>1302</td>
<td>784</td>
<td>1036</td>
<td>834</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">NORMALIZED BY INS. ILLUMINANCE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>1.48</td>
<td>3.28</td>
<td>2.93</td>
<td>1.76</td>
<td>3.28</td>
<td>2.89</td>
<td>1.80</td>
<td>2.38</td>
<td>1.92</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>42</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>52</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>0.28</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold><hr/></td>
<td>333</td>
<td>652</td>
<td>515</td>
<td>856</td>
<td>1900</td>
<td>1699</td>
<td>1021</td>
<td>1905</td>
<td>1671</td>
<td>1045</td>
<td>1380</td>
<td>1111</td></tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3"><bold>MARCH</bold><hr/></td>
<td colspan="3"><bold>APRIL</bold><hr/></td>
<td colspan="3"><bold>MAY</bold><hr/></td>
<td colspan="3"><bold>JUNE</bold><hr/></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><hr/></td>
<td/>
<td>SCENARIO1</td>
<td>SCENARIO2</td>
<td>SCENARIO3</td>
<td>SCENARIO1</td>
<td>SCENARIO2</td>
<td>SCENARIO3</td>
<td>SCENARIO1</td>
<td>SCENARIO2</td>
<td>SCENARIO3</td>
<td>SCENARIO1</td>
<td>SCENARIO2</td>
<td>SCENARIO3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">ABSOLUTE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>1.09</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.99</td>
<td>0.93</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>0.59</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>0.66</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>61</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>65</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>0.10</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>725</td>
<td>539</td>
<td>631</td>
<td>507</td>
<td>367</td>
<td>573</td>
<td>539</td>
<td>238</td>
<td>298</td>
<td>342</td>
<td>709</td>
<td>381</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">NORMALIZED BY PRESENCE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>1.15</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.53</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>0.64</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>45</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>63</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.09</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>534</td>
<td>516</td>
<td>667</td>
<td>457</td>
<td>365</td>
<td>514</td>
<td>442</td>
<td>234</td>
<td>310</td>
<td>334</td>
<td>685</td>
<td>369</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">NORMALIZED BY OUT. ILLUMINANCE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>0.64</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>48</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>63</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.09</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>568</td>
<td>536</td>
<td>686</td>
<td>457</td>
<td>365</td>
<td>514</td>
<td>483</td>
<td>271</td>
<td>337</td>
<td>345</td>
<td>685</td>
<td>370</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">NORMALIZED BY INS. ILLUMINANCE</td>
<td><bold>kWh/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>1.34</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.55</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>0.67</td>
<td>1.34</td>
<td>0.72</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>%</bold></td>
<td>54</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>71</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>€<bold>/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>0.11</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>CO<sub>2</sub> g/m<sup>2</sup> month</bold></td>
<td>646</td>
<td>609</td>
<td>779</td>
<td>507</td>
<td>405</td>
<td>570</td>
<td>571</td>
<td>321</td>
<td>398</td>
<td>390</td>
<td>775</td>
<td>419</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The effect of the normalisation factors is significant in the energy saving calculation. For instance, in October the application of the normalisation factors calculated for scenario 3 increases the energy saving from 53.45% to 76.32%. The more significant standardisation factor is indoor illuminance factor: Normalising by inside illuminance, the saving amount can increase by 15.07%.</p>
<p>The use of automation techniques achieves a significant energy saving. The overall energy use comparison between traditional and automated classrooms shows that, depending on the observation month,
<list id="list19-1477153511427427" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Scenario 1 requires 39% to 49% less energy for electric lighting.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Scenario 2 consumes 40% to 85% less electrical energy monthly for lighting.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Scenario 3 needs 50% to 85% less electrical energy for lighting.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Comparing winter and summer trends, the mean energy saving for scenario 3 is above the 65% for the whole year. Checking the difference between scenario 2 and 3 in the summer semester, there is not any significant improvement in system efficiency. This means that dividing the lecture room into two separate spatial zones (front and back) with dedicated occupancy sensors does not increase efficiency.</p>
<p>The mean difference between the winter and summer semester performances is mainly significant for the scenario 2: Indeed the energy saving percentage for this scenario decreases from the 75% in the winter semester to the 55% in the summer semester.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-1477153511427427" sec-type="conclusions"><title>6. Conclusions</title>
<p>The results of the research demonstrate that the use of automated systems for controlling electric lighting can yield considerable energy savings, roughly between 40% and 65% depending on the complexity of the system and the parameters under control.</p>
<p>Moreover, it was possible to define new automated lighting scenarios and to investigate their potential (evaluated using standardisation techniques) for the specific case study analysed.</p>
<p>Considering the whole observation period, the energy saving percentage of the automated control as compared with the traditional classroom, was:
<list id="list20-1477153511427427" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>40%, with all three rows of luminaires switched on when occupancy is detected and the room illuminance (measured in the middle of the room) is below a predefined minimum level (scenario 1 – winter semester).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>65%, with three rows of luminaires switched on when occupancy is detected and dimmed (in two separately controlled circuits) so as to provide predefined minimum illuminances, measured at two points in the room, each corresponding to a circuit (scenario 2). This lighting system has a better performance in winter than in the summer.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>65%, with three rows of luminaires switched on when occupancy is detected and dimmed (in three separately controlled circuits) so as to provide predefined minimum illuminances (measured at three points in the room, each corresponding to a circuit – scenario 3).</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>There are no significant differences in the results if the lecture room is controlled in terms of two separate spatial zones (front and back) with dedicated occupancy sensors.</p>
<p>It is important to notice that disability and discomfort glare influence this trend, because an improper use of the shading system often causes the unnecessary use of the electric lighting. Moreover, visual comfort is not always guaranteed. In fact, the minimum illuminance maintained in the traditional classrooms is low, especially in the winter semester in the early morning and late in the afternoon. Thus, the automated control system used for this research could be further improved by incorporating shading control.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec16-1477153511427427"><title>Funding</title>
<p>The research presented in this paper was supported by a PhD scholarship awarded by the Doctoral School of Environmental Engineering of the University of Trento, Italy.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1477153511427427"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs (DESA), Report of the World Commission on Environment and Development, 96th plenary meeting, 11 December 1987. Retrieved 1 March 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/42/ares42-187.html">http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/42/ares42-187.html</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1477153511427427"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Operational principles for sustainable development</article-title>. <source>Ecological Economics</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1477153511427427"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>UNEP. Buildings and Climate Change, Status, Challenge and Opportunities. United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unglobalcompact.org/docs/issues_doc/Environment/climate/Buildings_and_climate_change.pdf">http://www.unglobalcompact.org/docs/issues_doc/Environment/climate/Buildings_and_climate_change.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1477153511427427"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Mills E. The $230-billion Global Lighting Energy Bill, 2002. Retrieved 1 March 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evanmills.lbl.gov/pubs/pdf/global_lighting_energy.pdf">http://evanmills.lbl.gov/pubs/pdf/global_lighting_energy.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1477153511427427"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Zalesak M. <italic>Possible impacts of intelligent technologies application in residential buildings on energy efficiency</italic>: <italic>Proceedings of KNX Scientific Conference</italic>, Technical University of Vienna. Vienna: KNX Association cvba, 2006</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1477153511427427"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Energy performance of buildings — Energy requirements for lighting, UNI EN Norm 15193, 2008</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1477153511427427"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>International Energy Agency, Daylight in Building, Solar Heating and Cooling Programme Task 21, section 6, 2000. Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iea-shc.org/task21/source_book.html">http://www.iea-shc.org/task21/source_book.html</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1477153511427427"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erhorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Szerman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Documentation of the Software Package ADELINE (9 volumes)</source> , <publisher-loc>Stuttgart</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fraunhofer-Institut für Bauphysik</publisher-name>, <year>1994</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1477153511427427"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Lawrence Berkeley Lab, Superlite 2.0, Building Energy. Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://btech.lbl.gov/tools/superlite">http://btech.lbl.gov/tools/superlite</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1477153511427427"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Walkenhorst</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic RADIANCE-based daylight simulations for a full scale test office with outer Venetian blinds</article-title>. <source>Energy and Buildings</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>33</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1477153511427427"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DDC. Validation of AGi32 against CIE 171:2006; Vancouver, Canada (Dau Design and Consulting,). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dau.ca/ddci/files/Download/ReportonAGI32validationofCIE171_Compiled_070620.pdf">http://www.dau.ca/ddci/files/Download/ReportonAGI32validationofCIE171_Compiled_070620.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1477153511427427"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Buhl WF, Birdsall B, Erdem AE, Ellington KL Winkelmann FC, Hirsch &amp; Associates, DOE-2 Supplement, version 2.1E, LBL-34947 (LBL). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gundog.lbl.gov/dirpubs/d2pub90-94.html">http://gundog.lbl.gov/dirpubs/d2pub90-94.html</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1477153511427427"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Marsh AJ. <italic>Survey of simulation modeling into initial stages of design</italic>: <italic>Proceedings of ANZAScA Conference</italic>, University of Hong Kong. Hong Kong: University of Hong Kong, 1996</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1477153511427427"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krarti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillman</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A simplified method to estimate energy savings of artificial lighting use from daylighting</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>747</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1477153511427427"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihm</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krarti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of an optimal daylighting controller</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1011</fpage>–<lpage>1022</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1477153511427427"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atif</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galasiu</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energy performance of daylight-linked automatic lighting control systems in large atrium spaces: Report on two field-monitored case studies</article-title>. <source>Energy and Buildings</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1477153511427427"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Herkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The simulation of annual daylight illuminance distributionse: A state-of-the-art comparison of six RADIANCE-based methods</article-title>. <source>Energy and Buildings</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1477153511427427"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The use of artificial lighting in relation to daylight levels and occupancy</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <year>1979</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1477153511427427"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lightswitch 2002: A model for manual control of electric lighting and blinds</article-title>. <source>Solar Energy</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1477153511427427"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occupants' operation of lighting and shading systems in office buildings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Building Performance Simulation</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1477153511427427"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pröglhöf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Two case studies on user interactions with buildings’ environmental systems</article-title>. <source>Bauphysik</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1477153511427427"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Shading and lighting in office buildings in Austria: a study of user control behaviour</article-title>. <source>Building Simulation</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1477153511427427"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galasiu</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Newsham</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Suvagau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energy saving lighting control systems for open-plan offices: A field study</article-title>. <source>Leukos</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1477153511427427"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>NRCC. Birt B, Newsham GR. Energy savings from photosensors and occupant sensors/wall switches on a college campus. National Research Council Canada (NRCC). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nrc-cnrc.gc.ca/obj/irc/doc/pubs/nrcc51319.pdf">http://www.nrc-cnrc.gc.ca/obj/irc/doc/pubs/nrcc51319.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1477153511427427"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment><italic>Light and lighting - Lighting of work places - Part 1: Indoor work places</italic> UNI EN Norm12464-2, 2004</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1477153511427427"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment><italic>Principi di ergonomia della visione. Sistemi di lavoro e illuminazione</italic> UNI EN Norm 10530, 1997 (in Italian)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1477153511427427"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Gefasoft Engineerig, Erfassung und Auswertung von Prozessdaten. (in German). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gefasoft-eng.de/fileadmin/styles/02_layouts_2col/pdf/Gefasoft%20ProzessDatenAuswertung%20ProDA.pdf">http://www.gefasoft-eng.de/fileadmin/styles/02_layouts_2col/pdf/Gefasoft%20ProzessDatenAuswertung%20ProDA.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1477153511427427"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Page CG, Professional Programmer's Guide to Fortran77.University of Leicester, UK. Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.star.le.ac.uk/~cgp/prof77.html">http://www.star.le.ac.uk/~cgp/prof77.html</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1477153511427427"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>NI. LabView User Manual, Part Number 320999E-01. National Instruments Corporates (NI). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ni.com/pdf/manuals/320999e.pdf">http://www.ni.com/pdf/manuals/320999e.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1477153511427427"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>ISPRA. Produzione termoelettrica e produzione di CO2 – Fonti rinnovabili e progetti sottoposti ad ETS, 135/2011; 32 (in italian). Istituto superiore per la Protezione e la ricerca Ambiente (ISPRA). Retrieved 10 September 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isprambiente.gov.it/site/_contentfiles/00009400/9486_Rapporto_135_2011.pdf">http://www.isprambiente.gov.it/site/_contentfiles/00009400/9486_Rapporto_135_2011.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>