<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spoto</journal-id>
<journal-title>Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0194-5998</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-6817</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599812451408</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0194599812451408</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Sinonasal Disorders</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sino-Nasal Characteristics in Asthmatic Patients</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Thorstensen</surname><given-names>Wenche Moe</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812451408">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451408">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bugten</surname><given-names>Vegard</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812451408">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451408">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sue-Chu</surname><given-names>Malcolm</given-names></name>
<degrees>MBChB, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0194599812451408">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0194599812451408">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fossland</surname><given-names>Nils Petter Wold</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812451408">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Romundstad</surname><given-names>Pål Richard</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0194599812451408">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Steinsvåg</surname><given-names>Sverre Karmhus</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-0194599812451408">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-0194599812451408">7</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0194599812451408"><label>1</label>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, St Olavs Hospital, University Hospital of Trondheim, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0194599812451408"><label>2</label>Institute of Neuroscience, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0194599812451408"><label>3</label>Department of Thoracic Medicine, St Olavs Hospital, University Hospital of Trondheim, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0194599812451408"><label>4</label>Institute of Circulation and Imaging, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0194599812451408"><label>5</label>Institute of Public Health and General Practice, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff6-0194599812451408"><label>6</label>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Sorlandet Hospital, Kristiansand, Norway</aff>
<aff id="aff7-0194599812451408"><label>7</label>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Kristiansand, and Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway, University of Bergen, Norway</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0194599812451408">Wenche Moe Thorstensen, MD, Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, St Olavs Hospital, University Hospital of Trondheim, and Institute of Neuroscience, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, 7006 Trondheim, Norway Email: <email>wenche.m.thorstensen@ntnu.no</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>147</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>950</fpage>
<lpage>957</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>26</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>18</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>22</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery Foundation 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Official journal of the American Academy of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0194599812451408">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>The Unified Airways Hypothesis suggests an involvement of the upper airways in asthma. We aimed to evaluate the association between subjective sino-nasal complaints, nasal air flow, and sino-nasal quality of life (QOL) in patients with asthma compared with nonasthmatic subjects.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0194599812451408">
<title>Study Design</title>
<p>Case-control study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0194599812451408">
<title>Setting</title>
<p>A tertiary referral center.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0194599812451408">
<title>Subjects and Methods</title>
<p>Symptoms, quality of life, and nasal airflow were assessed in 91 asthmatics and 95 nonasthmatic controls with Visual Analog Scale (VAS, 0-100), Sino-Nasal Outcome Test (SNOT-20), and Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow (PNIF), respectively. Asthma and allergy status were assessed by Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ) and skin prick test or specific IgE.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0194599812451408">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Asthmatic patients (men/women, 37/54; mean age, 43.7 years; range, 19-64 years) reported significantly more nasal obstruction (mean VAS, 37 mm; SD = 26, 95% CI, 32-43 vs 9 mm, SD = 11, 95% CI, 7-11, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and lower sino-nasal quality of life (mean SNOT-20, 1.3; SD = 0.8, 95% CI, 1.1-1.5 vs 0.4, SD = 0.5, 95% CI, 0.3-0.5, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) than controls (men/women, 42/53; mean age, 43.8 years; range, 20-65 years). PNIF was significantly lower in asthmatic patients than controls (mean PNIF, 84 l/min; SD = 24, 95% CI, 79-89 vs 100 l/min SD = 24, 95% CI, 95-105, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0194599812451408">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Both allergic and nonallergic asthma were associated with increased sino-nasal symptoms, reduced sino-nasal QOL, and reduced inspiratory nasal air flow compared to controls. This provides further evidence of the clinical importance of the upper airway in the diagnostic and therapeutic management of asthma patients beyond the scope of allergy.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>allergy</kwd>
<kwd>asthma</kwd>
<kwd>rhinitis</kwd>
<kwd>sinusitis</kwd>
<kwd>quality of life</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The concept of the Unified Airway Hypothesis considers the entire respiratory system from the nose and paranasal sinuses, larynx, trachea, and large and small airways as one integrated unit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0194599812451408">1</xref></sup> It has become increasingly clear that inflammation in the upper respiratory tract affects the lower respiratory tract and vice versa. Over 75% of adult patients with allergic and nonallergic asthma have symptoms of rhinitis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599812451408">2</xref></sup> The coexistence of asthma with allergic rhinitis is associated with more severe asthma symptoms, reduced asthma-related quality of life, and greater problems controlling the lower airway symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0194599812451408">3</xref></sup> Conversely, 20% to 50% of patients with rhinitis have asthma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0194599812451408">4</xref></sup> An increase in nonspecific bronchial responsiveness is seen in patients with allergic rhinitis without manifest asthma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0194599812451408">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>There are several potential pathophysiological links between the upper and lower airways. Inhalation of allergens leads to local IgE-mediated inflammatory reactions both in the nose and bronchi in sensitized individuals. In rhinitis, sympathetic and parasympathetic signals are generated in the nose that may have pathophysiological influence on the bronchial tree.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0194599812451408">6</xref></sup> Nasal patency is a key feature in rhinitis, and oral breathing is a consequence. The consequent lack of cleaning, warming, and humidification of the air during inspiration may harm the lungs. The nose represents an important source of resistance for the lower airways during expiration. Mouth breathing, secondary to nasal obstruction may even in this perspective have a negative impact on the lungs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0194599812451408">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although the concept of the unified airway is based on evidence from epidemiological, pathophysiological, and treatment outcome studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0194599812451408">8</xref></sup> there are limited studies that have investigated the upper airway characteristics in asthmatic patients using subjective and objective tools. In the study by Hens et al, increased nasal symptoms, reduced sino-nasal quality of life (QOL), and nasal inflammation were seen in asthmatic patients with and without allergy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0194599812451408">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>Optimal diagnosis and treatment of nose problems in asthma patients are likely to improve QOL and reduce morbidity and asthma medication. Thus, it is important to learn about nose- and sinus-related symptoms and quality of life in these patients. In this study we investigated sino-nasal symptoms, nose- and sinus-related quality of life, and nasal airflow in allergic and nonallergic asthma patients.</p>
<sec id="section7-0194599812451408" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section8-0194599812451408">
<title>Subjects</title>
<p>The study population consisted of 91 patients with asthma and 95 nonasthmatic controls.</p>
<p>The asthma diagnosis was based on the presence of typical asthma symptoms and variable airflow obstruction and in accordance with the British Thoracic Society criteria.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0194599812451408">10</xref></sup> Variable airflow obstruction was defined as an increase of ≥ 12% and ≥ 200 mL in the forced expiratory volume in the first second (FEV1) from baseline after administration of salbutamol or a positive bronchial provocation test, defined as the provocative dose of methacholine of ≤ 1600 µg that causes a fall in FEV1 of at least 20% from baseline.</p>
<p>Exclusion criteria were pregnancy, a history of cancer, presence of acute and chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS), and nasal polyposis on otorhinolaryngological examination, previous nasal surgery, and systemic disease with potential affection of the nose, such as Wegener’s granulomatosis, cystic fibrosis, primary ciliary dyskinesia, Kartagener’s syndrome, and sarcoidosis.</p>
<p>Written informed consent was obtained from all subjects. The study was approved by the National Ethical Committee of Norway and investigations were performed in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki/Hong Kong. All subjective and objective recordings were performed between June 2009 and December 2010 in a controlled environment using trained personnel and modern equipment. Allergic control subjects were not included in the pollen season (May-August) and asthmatic subjects were investigated between September 2009 and February 2010.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0194599812451408">
<title>Subjective Measures</title>
<sec id="section10-0194599812451408">
<title>Questionnaire</title>
<p>Data on sex, weight, height, smoking habits, allergies, and medication were collected in a self-administered questionnaire.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0194599812451408">
<title>Symptoms</title>
<p>The degree of nasal obstruction (NO), oral breathing, snoring, sleep apnea, nasal discharge/secretions, headache, mid facial pain, rhino-sinusitis, coughing, sneezing, reduced general health, and reduced sense of smell was assessed on a 100 mm Visual Analog Scale (VAS). The endpoints were 0 mm (never) and 100 mm (always).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0194599812451408">
<title>Quality of life</title>
<p>This was assessed with the Sino-Nasal Outcome Test-20 (SNOT-20) questionnaire, which is a validated disease-specific QOL questionnaire for rhino-sinusitis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0194599812451408">11</xref></sup> Subjects were asked to grade 20 items on a scale of 0 (no problem) to 5 (problem as severe as can be). The SNOT-20 score for each subject was defined as the mean value of the response to the 20 items. Furthermore, the SNOT-20 questionnaire was divided into subsets based on the study of Browne et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0194599812451408">12</xref></sup> The first subset was composed of the questions about the symptoms related to nose, ear, and face; the second subset included the questions on psychological issues; and the third subset addressed sleep function. Questions about cough and waking up tired are separate entities and do not belong to any subset.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0194599812451408">
<title>Asthma control</title>
<p>Asthma control in asthmatic subjects was assessed with the Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ), which is a validated disease-specific test used for evaluation of asthma symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599812451408">13</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0194599812451408">
<title>Clinical Investigation</title>
<p>A complete otorhinolaryngological examination with emphasis on the anatomic and functional aspects of the nose was performed.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0194599812451408">
<title>Objective Measures</title>
<sec id="section16-0194599812451408">
<title>Allergy</title>
<p>Skin prick tests (Soluprick SQ, ALK-Abello, Horsholm, Denmark) or specific IgE (AlaTOP, Diagnostics Products Corp., Los Angeles, California) for pollen (birch, grass, and mugwort), cladosporium, house dust mite (<italic>Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus</italic>), and animal epithelia (horse, dog, and cat) were performed. Use of antihistamines was discontinued 4 days prior to skin prick tests. Subjects with positive tests and typical symptoms of hypersensitivity on exposure to the allergen(s) were classified as allergic.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0194599812451408">
<title>Nasal airflow</title>
<p>This was assessed noninvasively by measuring the Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow (PNIF, L/min) during forced inspiration with a portable PNIF meter (In-check DIAL, Clement Clarke International, Harlow, UK) prior to measurement of lung function. The maximum PNIF that can be measured with this meter was 120 L/min. PNIF in excess of this value was recorded as 120 L/min. The mean value of 3 satisfactory maximal nasal inspirations was calculated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0194599812451408">
<title>Lung function</title>
<p>Lung function was assessed by flow-volume spirometry (Spirostar USB spirometer, Medikro Oy, Kuopio, Finland) before and 10 minutes after administration of 0.4 mg salbutamol in a spacer (Ventoline, Volumatic, GlaxoSmithKline, Middlesex, UK). The best FEV1 in liters and percentage of predicted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0194599812451408">14</xref></sup> of 3 acceptable attempts before and after salbutamol was recorded, in accordance with international guidelines.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599812451408">15</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0194599812451408">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>The number of participants included in the study was based on power calculations. To obtain 80% power, we needed 100 participants in each group at a significance level of 0.05 (alpha) and given a difference in SNOT-20 of 0.4 between the groups. If the difference is 0.5 the estimated power was 94%.</p>
<p>Data are presented as mean, standard deviation (SD), and 95% confidence interval (95% CI). To evaluate differences in mean values we used independent samples <italic>t</italic> test. To assess the correlation between ACQ score and SNOT-20 and between ACQ score and NO-VAS, we used linear regression.</p>
<p>All statistical analysis was performed using PASW Statistics, version 18 for Windows (SPSS Inc., Chicago, Illinois).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0194599812451408" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Demographic data, allergy, smoking status, and use of intranasal steroids, antihistamines, and asthmatic medication are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599812451408"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>. Allergy was present in 62% of asthmatic patients and 22% of controls.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0194599812451408" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Demographic Data and Medical History on Asthmatic Patients and Controls</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0194599812451408" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451408-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristics</th>
<th align="center">Asthmatic Patients (n = 91)</th>
<th align="center">Controls (n = 95)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mean age, y (range)</td>
<td>43.7 (19-64)</td>
<td>43.8 (20-65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup> (SD)</td>
<td>26.7 (4.9)</td>
<td>25.3 (3.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male, n (%)</td>
<td>37 (41)</td>
<td>42 (44)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Allergy</td>
<td>56/91 (62)</td>
<td>21/95 (22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Pollen, n (%)</td>
<td>47/56 (83)</td>
<td>21/21 (100)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Animal dander, n (%)</td>
<td>41/56 (73)</td>
<td>9/21 (42)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> House dust mite, n (%)</td>
<td>19/56 (34)</td>
<td>2/21 (10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Smoking, n (%)</td>
<td>8 (9)</td>
<td>12 (13)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Samter’s triad, n (%)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medication</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intranasal steroids, n (%)</td>
<td>31 (34)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Antihistamines, n (%)</td>
<td>30 (33)</td>
<td>5 (5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ICS, n (%)</td>
<td>11 (12)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> LABA, n (%)</td>
<td>4 (4)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Combined ICS and LABA, n (%)</td>
<td>75 (82)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anticholinergic medication, n (%)</td>
<td>6 (7)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Leukotriene receptor antagonists, n (%)</td>
<td>18 (20)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Oral steroids, n (%)</td>
<td>6 (7)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0194599812451408">
<p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; ICS, inhaled corticosteroids; LABA, long-acting β2 agonist.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section21-0194599812451408">
<title>Subjective Measures</title>
<sec id="section22-0194599812451408">
<title>Symptoms</title>
<p>The VAS for each symptom was significantly greater in asthmatic patients than in controls (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0194599812451408"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref>). The asthma patients had a mean VAS of the 12 sino-nasal symptoms of 30 (SD = 14, 95% CI, 27-33) and the control group 11 (SD = 9, 95% CI, 9-12), <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001. As to nasal obstruction, the asthmatic patients had a mean NO-VAS of 37 (SD = 26, 95% CI, 32-42) and the controls 9 (SD = 11, 95% CI, 7-11), <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0194599812451408"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0194599812451408" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Visual Analog Scale (VAS) Scores for Sino-Nasal Symptoms in Asthmatic Patients and Controls: Values Presented as Mean (SD)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0194599812451408" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451408-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Symptom</th>
<th align="center">Asthmatic Patients (N = 91)</th>
<th align="center">Controls (N = 95)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Nasal obstruction</td>
<td>37 (26)</td>
<td>9 (11)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oral breathing</td>
<td>47 (29)</td>
<td>13 (22)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Snoring</td>
<td>40 (33)</td>
<td>26 (29)</td>
<td>.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleep apnea</td>
<td>15 (27)</td>
<td>7 (17)</td>
<td>.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nasal discharge/secretions</td>
<td>28 (23)</td>
<td>11 (18)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Headache</td>
<td>32 (28)</td>
<td>16 (21)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mid-facial pain</td>
<td>15 (21)</td>
<td>9 (17)</td>
<td>.033</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rhino-sinusitis</td>
<td>12 (21)</td>
<td>4 (8)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coughing</td>
<td>41 (31)</td>
<td>7 (9)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sneezing</td>
<td>39 (26)</td>
<td>15 (17)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reduced general health</td>
<td>27 (29)</td>
<td>5 (8)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reduced sense of smell</td>
<td>24 (27)</td>
<td>5 (10)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-0194599812451408" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Symptoms described by the mean Visual Analog Scale (A) and Nasal Obstruction Visual Analog Scale (B) in the asthmatic patients (gray) and controls (white). Values presented as mean, 95% CI.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451408-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0194599812451408">
<title>Quality of life</title>
<p>The asthmatic patients had a significant impairment of their nose and sinus–related quality of life (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0194599812451408"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). The mean SNOT-20 score in asthmatic patients was 1.3 (SD = 0.8, 95% CI, 1.1-1.5) and in the control group 0.4 (SD = 0.5, 95% CI, 0.3-0.5), <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001. Comparison of SNOT-20 scores for each question in the asthma group and control group showed highly significant differences for all questions, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001, except ear pain (<italic>P</italic> = 0.1). The scores for rhinologic, ear/facial, sleep function, and psychological function subsets showed statistical significance between asthmatic patients and controls in all subset scores (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0194599812451408" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Comparison of Sino-Nasal Outcome Test (SNOT-20) Scores for Each Question and Subset in Asthmatic Patients and Controls: Values Presented as Mean (SD)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0194599812451408" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451408-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Question</th>
<th align="center">Asthmatic Patients (n = 91)</th>
<th align="center">Controls (n = 95)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Need to blow nose<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0194599812451408">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.9 (1.3)</td>
<td>0.6 (0.8)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sneezing<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0194599812451408">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.6 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.5 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Runny nose<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0194599812451408">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.4 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cough</td>
<td>1.9 (1.4)</td>
<td>0.3 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Postnasal discharge<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0194599812451408">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.9 (1.3)</td>
<td>0.2 (0.6)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Thick nasal discharge<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0194599812451408">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.0 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.2 (0.5)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ear fullness<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451408">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.3 (1.3)</td>
<td>0.6 (1.1)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dizziness<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451408">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.1 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.8)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ear pain<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451408">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.6 (1.0)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.9)</td>
<td>.100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Facial pain/pressure<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451408">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.8 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.2 (0.5)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulty falling to sleep<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0194599812451408">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.2 (1.4)</td>
<td>0.3 (0.9)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wake up at night<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0194599812451408">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.7 (1.4)</td>
<td>0.7 (1.2)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lack of good night’s sleep<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0194599812451408">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.8 (1.5)</td>
<td>0.6 (1.2)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wake up tired</td>
<td>2.2 (1.4)</td>
<td>1.0 (1.8)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fatigue<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.3 (1.4)</td>
<td>0.3 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reduced productivity<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.5 (1.5)</td>
<td>0.2 (0.6)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reduced concentration<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.5 (1.4)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frustrated/restless/irritable<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.4 (1.5)</td>
<td>0.3 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sad<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.8 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.2 (0.5)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Embarrassed<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.5 (1.0)</td>
<td>0.1 (0.3)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Subset</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rhinologic<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0194599812451408">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.4 (0.8)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.4)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ear/facial<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451408">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.9 (0.9)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.7)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sleep function<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0194599812451408">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.6 (1.2)</td>
<td>0.5 (0.9)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Psychological function<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451408">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.2 (1.1)</td>
<td>0.3 (0.5)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean SNOT-20</td>
<td>1.3 (0.8)</td>
<td>0.4 (0.5)</td>
<td>&lt; .001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0194599812451408">
<label>a</label>
<p>Questions belonging to rhinologic subset.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0194599812451408">
<label>b</label>
<p>Questions belonging to ear/facial subset.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0194599812451408">
<label>c</label>
<p>Questions belonging to sleep function subset.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0194599812451408">
<label>d</label>
<p>Questions belonging to psychological function subset.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0194599812451408">
<title>Asthma control</title>
<p>The asthma patients had an ACQ score of 1.6 (SD = 1, 95% CI, 1.4-1.8).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0194599812451408">
<title>Clinical Investigation</title>
<p>The investigation confirmed that the asthmatic patients and the controls included in the study did not have symptoms or signs of CRS or nasal polyposis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0194599812451408">
<title>Objective Measures</title>
<sec id="section27-0194599812451408">
<title>Allergy</title>
<p>Mean VAS score, NO-VAS, SNOT-20, and PNIF were significantly greater in allergic asthmatic patients than in allergic controls and in nonallergic asthmatic patients than in nonallergic controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0194599812451408"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0194599812451408" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Mean VAS (A), NO-VAS (B), SNOT-20 (C), and PNIF (D) in allergic asthmatic patients, nonallergic asthmatic patients, allergic controls, and nonallergic controls. Values presented as mean, 95% CI. Abbreviations: VAS, Visual Analog Scale; NO-VAS, Nasal Obstruction Visual Analog Scale; SNOT-20, Sino-Nasal Outcome Test; PNIF, Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451408-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0194599812451408">
<title>Nasal airflow</title>
<p>The baseline mean PNIF in asthmatic patients was 84 (SD = 24, 95% CI, 79-89) and among the controls 100 (SD = 24, 95% CI, 95-105), <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0194599812451408">
<title>Lung function</title>
<p>The asthma patients had a mean pre FEV1 value of 80% predicted (SD = 18, 95% CI, 76-84) and the control group 96% predicted (SD = 13, 95% CI, 94-99), <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0194599812451408">
<title>Association of SNOT-20 and NO-VAS with ACQ</title>
<p>Linear regression analysis showed that the ACQ score increased by 0.76, per unit increase in SNOT-20 (95% CI, 0.52-0.97) and by 0.12 (95% CI, 0.5-2.0) per 10 unit increase in NO-VAS.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-0194599812451408" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study we have demonstrated that asthma patients have more sino-nasal symptoms and lower sino-nasal QOL and PNIF compared to the controls. These findings also apply to asthmatic patients and controls, irrespective of their allergy status. In addition, quality of life and nasal obstruction are correlated with the degree of asthma control, and FEV1 percentage predicted is significantly lower than in controls. The findings of increased sino-nasal symptoms and lower QOL in our study are in agreement with the study by Hens and coworkers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0194599812451408">9</xref></sup> However, we have also shown that asthmatic patients have a reduced sense of smell and general health.</p>
<p>The higher level of NO-VAS in the asthmatic patients compared with the controls may be caused by nasal obstruction among the former. The recently demonstrated correlation between subjective and objective nasal obstruction makes such an assumption fair.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599812451408">16</xref></sup> The reduced PNIF in the asthma group compared with the controls supports this, as it also has been shown that there is a correlation between the subjective sense of nasal patency and objective nasal airflow.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599812451408">17</xref></sup> Nasal obstruction may principally be due to either structural and/or mucosal abnormalities. We have deliberately chosen not to classify the extent of septal deviations, turbinate hypertrophy, or other structural deformities as there is a lack of standardized classification systems and as the very subjective, investigator-dependent, and descriptive nature of such data severely limits their scientific transfer value.</p>
<p>As it is less likely that there should be a systematic increased incidence of structural abnormalities in the asthmatic patients’ noses, the nature of such an obstruction probably is mucosal. This is in line with the theory that the link between asthma and rhinitis involves a generalized mucosal inflammation affecting both the upper and lower airways, including a mucosal edema in the nose.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599812451408">18</xref></sup> However, perception of nasal obstruction may have different etiologies as it depends not only on flow alone, but on nasal cavity dimensions, thermal receptors, pressure receptors, pain receptors, secretions, change in mood, sinus congestion, and Eustachian tube function as well.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599812451408">19</xref></sup> The sensation of nasal airflow is primarily based on a cool sensation in the nose rather than to sensations from the lungs and respiratory muscles.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599812451408">20</xref></sup> The increased experience of nasal obstruction in asthmatic patients might be a result of less stimulation of these receptors. This assumption is supported by the reduced PNIF in the asthmatic patients.</p>
<p>PNIF is based on forced inspiration and reduced forced inspiration may give reduced stimulation of the sensors for nasal airflow. Low PNIF values may be an expression of low ventilatory activity rather than an expression of nasal obstruction. Accordingly, the subjective nasal obstruction reported by the asthmatic patients may not be a reflection of nasal pathology per se, but of a reduced pulmonary ventilatory capacity as shown by reduced FEV1 percentage values.</p>
<p>The coexistence of rhinitis and asthma in allergic individuals is well recognized by clinicians. However, we found significant greater VAS for sino-nasal symptoms, NO-VAS, SNOT-20, and PNIF in nonallergic asthmatic patients who were assessed outside of the pollen season, compared with nonallergic controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0194599812451408"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>). Similar findings have been reported by Hens et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0194599812451408">9</xref></sup> and highlight the importance of a thorough otorhinolaryngological examination, with particular focus on the anatomic and functional aspects of the nose, and evaluation in all asthma patients, irrespective of the presence or absence of airway allergy.</p>
<p>It is well acknowledged that the coexistence of rhinitis and asthma appears to impair asthma control.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599812451408">2</xref></sup> The ACQ score in the present study corresponds well to the ACQ scores of other comparable studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599812451408">21</xref></sup> The positive correlation between ACQ score and SNOT-20 and NO-VAS scores provides further evidence in support of the relationship between poor asthma control and sino-nasal symptoms and quality of life in asthmatic patients.</p>
<p>The asthma patients have a reduced sino-nasal QOL as reported by SNOT-20. As expected, the asthma patients had lower SNOT-20 score compared with patients with CRS who have a SNOT score of 1.9.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0194599812451408">11</xref></sup> Despite this, subgroup analysis shows a threefold increase in SNOT-20 score in the allergic asthmatic patients and nonallergic asthmatic patients, compared with their respective controls. This is in line with our clinical experience, where patients with asthma have less sino-nasal problems compared with patients with CRS but still have serious upper airway malfunctions that affect their sino-nasal QOL. Thus SNOT-20 may also be a useful tool for the assessment of QOL, health status, and treatment response in asthmatic patients.</p>
<p>Analysis of the SNOT-20 questionnaire by subsets may suggest that differences in SNOT-20 scores between asthmatic patients and controls can be due to sleep disturbances. The ACQ score in the asthmatic patients is suggestive of relatively poor asthma control that can be associated with sleep disturbance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599812451408">22</xref></sup> However, the difference between the asthma and control groups remained highly significant with <italic>P</italic> values &lt; .001, when sleep questions were excluded from the SNOT-20 questionnaire. Moreover, asthmatic patients scored significantly higher on all questions in the SNOT-20, with the exception of the question concerning the presence of ear pain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0194599812451408"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>).</p>
<p>The use of VAS, SNOT-20, and PNIF as tools to assess sino-nasal characteristics has some limitations. VAS may be limited, primarily because of its simplicity, while SNOT-20 lacks questions about nasal obstruction and loss of smell and taste. PNIF gives a global characterization of the nasal air flow, but does not give any information about the separate nasal passages or nasal airflow under resting conditions. In addition, it is influenced by a number of covariates, especially peak expiratory flow (PEF), age, sex, and height.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451408">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599812451408">24</xref></sup> However, VAS is a validated and established instrument for assessing a wide range of symptoms, including nasal congestion, nasal discharge, headache, snoring, rhinosinusitis, decreased olfaction, and facial pain,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0194599812451408">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0194599812451408">26</xref></sup> and SNOT-20 has been used in a number of medical and surgical studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0194599812451408">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0194599812451408">28</xref></sup> The results of the present study suggest that the multidimensionality of sino-nasal symptoms may be better characterized when these instruments are used in conjunction.</p>
<sec id="section32-0194599812451408">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>We have shown that both allergic and nonallergic asthma were associated with increased sino-nasal symptoms, reduced sino-nasal QOL, and reduced inspiratory nasal air flow. This supports previous observations emphasizing that nasal pathology should be considered in the diagnostic and therapeutic approach of asthma patients beyond the scope of allergy.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-0194599812451408">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p><bold>Wenche Moe Thorstensen</bold>, substantial contribution to design, acquisition of data, analyzing, and interpretation of data; drafting the article and final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Vegard Bugten</bold>, substantial contribution to design, acquisition of data, analyzing, and interpretation of data; revising the article and final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Malcolm Sue-Chu</bold>, substantial contribution to design, analyzing, and interpretation of data; revising the article and final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Nils Petter Wold Fossland</bold>, substantial contribution to design, analyzing, and interpretation of data; revising the article and final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Pål Richard Romundstad</bold>, substantial contribution to design, analyzing, and interpretation of data; revising the article and final approval of the version to be published; <bold>Sverre Karmhus Steinsvåg</bold>, substantial contribution to design, acquisition of data, analyzing, and interpretation of data; revising the article and final approval of the version to be published.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section34-0194599812451408">
<title>Disclosures</title>
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Sponsorships:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Funding source:</bold> Unifor Legacy, Postboks 1131, Blindern, 0317 Oslo. The funding source had no role in design or conduct, collection, analysis, and interpretation of the data. The funding source had no role in interpretation of the data, writing, or approval of the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank the research nurses Else Bartnes and Petra Aspås.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p>
<p>This article was presented at the 2011 AAO-HNSF Annual Meeting &amp; OTO EXPO; September 11-14, 2011; San Francisco, California.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0194599812451408">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krouse</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veling</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Executive summary: asthma and the unified airway</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>699</fpage>-<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0194599812451408">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khaltaev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Allergic Rhinitis and its Impact on Asthma (ARIA) 2008 update (in collaboration with the World Health Organization, GA(2)LEN and AllerGen)</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<supplement>suppl 86</supplement>):<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0194599812451408">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steinsvag</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nose and lungs—two of a kind</article-title>. <source>Tidsskr Nor Laegeforen</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>1982</fpage>-<lpage>1984</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0194599812451408">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vignola</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demoly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Links between rhinitis and asthma</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>691</fpage>-<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0194599812451408">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Corren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between allergic rhinitis and bronchial asthma</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Pulm Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0194599812451408">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sarin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Undem</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanico</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Togias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The role of the nervous system in rhinitis</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>999</fpage>-<lpage>1016</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0194599812451408">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Allergic rhinitis and asthma in the athlete</article-title>. <source>Allergy Asthma Proc</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0194599812451408">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krouse</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The unified airway—conceptual framework</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Clin North Am</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>, <fpage>v</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0194599812451408">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vanaudenaerde</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bullens</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sinonasal pathology in nonallergic asthma and COPD: “united airway disease” beyond the scope of allergy</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0194599812451408">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>British Guideline on the Management of Asthma</collab>. <source>Thorax</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<supplement>suppl 4</supplement>):<fpage>iv1</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0194599812451408">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piccirillo</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>MG</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric and clinimetric validity of the 20-Item Sino-Nasal Outcome Test (SNOT-20)</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0194599812451408">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Sino-Nasal Outcome Test (SNOT): can we make it more clinically meaningful?</article-title> <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>736</fpage>-<lpage>741</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0194599812451408">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Byrne</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferrie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of a questionnaire to measure asthma control</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>902</fpage>-<lpage>907</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0194599812451408">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crapo</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reference spirometric values using techniques and equipment that meet ATS recommendations</article-title>. <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>-<lpage>664</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0194599812451408">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hankinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brusasco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Standardisation of spirometry</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0194599812451408">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kjaergaard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cvancarova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinsvag</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does nasal obstruction mean that the nose is obstructed?</article-title> <source>Laryngoscope</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>1476</fpage>-<lpage>1481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0194599812451408">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kjaergaard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cvancarova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinsvag</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relation of nasal air flow to nasal cavity dimensions</article-title>. <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>-<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0194599812451408">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacot</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vignola</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bachert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Cauwenberge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Allergic rhinitis: a disease remodeling the upper airways?</article-title> <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0194599812451408">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nasal congestion: mechanisms, measurement and medications. Core information for the clinician</article-title>. <source>Clin Otolaryngol Allied Sci</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>-<lpage>666</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0194599812451408">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nasal airflow in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Acta Otolaryngol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>580</fpage>-<lpage>595</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0194599812451408">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wyrwich</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Navaratnam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>DF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Validation and agreement across four versions of the asthma control questionnaire in patients with persistent asthma</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>698</fpage>-<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0194599812451408">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teodorescu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polomis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea risk with asthma control in adults</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>138</volume>:<fpage>543</fpage>-<lpage>550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0194599812451408">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ottaviano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scadding</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Peak nasal inspiratory flow; normal range in adult population</article-title>. <source>Rhinology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0194599812451408">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ottaviano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staffieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scadding</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does peak nasal inspiratory flow relate to peak expiratory flow?</article-title> <source>Rhinology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>200</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0194599812451408">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Spronsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ingels</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graamans</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fokkens</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evidence-based recommendations regarding the differential diagnosis and assessment of nasal congestion: using the new GRADE system</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>-<lpage>833</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0194599812451408">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Symptom-based presentation of chronic rhinosinusitis and symptom-specific outcomes after endoscopic sinus surgery</article-title>. <source>Am J Rhinol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0194599812451408">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMains</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kountakis</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Revision functional endoscopic sinus surgery: objective and subjective surgical outcomes</article-title>. <source>Am J Rhinol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>344</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0194599812451408">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guilemany</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angrill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alobid</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>United airways: the impact of chronic rhinosinusitis and nasal polyps in bronchiectasic patient’s quality of life</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1524</fpage>-<lpage>1529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>