<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spajh</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Hosp Palliat Care</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine®</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-9091</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2715</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049909111414863</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049909111414863</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Improving Cultural Competency Among Hospice and Palliative Care Volunteers</article-title>
<subtitle>Recommendations for Social Policy</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Jovanovic</surname>
<given-names>Maja</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MA</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111414863">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1049909111414863"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1049909111414863"><label>1</label>Department of Sociology, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049909111414863">Maja Jovanovic, Department of Sociology, McMaster University, 1280 Main Street West, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada L8S 4M4 Email: <email>jovanm3@mcmaster.ca</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>268</fpage>
<lpage>278</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This case study of 14 hospice and palliative care volunteers looked for recommendations and suggestions on how to increase cultural competency among hospice volunteers. In-depth interviews were conducted with a hospice in Toronto, Canada, and findings reveal that volunteers have very specific and diverse recommendations on how they prefer to be briefed and educated on cultural competency issues surrounding their patients. Findings also reveal hospice volunteers want more cultural competency training and acknowledge the importance of being culturally competent. This article concludes with a précis on recommendations for increasing cultural competency in hospice and palliative care for both volunteers and agencies and discusses the top 4 future trends in cultural competency for hospice care.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>cultural competency</kwd>
<kwd>hospice</kwd>
<kwd>palliative care</kwd>
<kwd>volunteers</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It is been widely reported that ethnic minorities underutilize not only health care services in general<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909111414863">1</xref>
</sup> but hospice and palliative care services specifically.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111414863">2</xref>
</sup> This is due to a number of reasons including a lack of awareness of hospices services, language barriers, ethnocentrism, prejudice, racism and discrimination, lack of insurance coverage, mistrusting or suspicious of health care providers, and lack of cultural and linguistic competency among health care providers. In fact, the National Hospice and Palliative Care Organization (NHPCO) stated in their 2010 report that 80.5% of hospice patients were white/Caucasian, 8.5% were multiracial or other race, 8.7% were black/African American, 5.3% were Latino/Hispanic, 1.9% were Asian, Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, and 0.2% were American Indians or Alaskan Natives.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049909111414863">3</xref>
</sup> While hospices and long-term care facilities are known to manage pain relief, alleviate caregiver burdens, and improve the quality of life during the last stages of life, ethnic minorities continue to be underserviced by hospices. This underutilization of hospice services by ethnic minorities can lead to undertreatment, inadequate treatment or even worse outcomes.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049909111414863">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>One of the ways to alleviate this outcome is by increasing the cultural competency within hospice and palliative care. Cultural competency can aid the navigation involved in the complexities of the death and dying stages for ethnic minorities. These include but are not limited to the questions of patient autonomy, decision-making preferences, communication abilities, the role of family and caregivers, attitudes toward pain relief and self-care, nutritional habits or customs, advanced directives (ie, do not resuscitate), alternative treatments or medicines, expectations of care, postmortem decisions such as burials and organ donations, and expressions of grief and bereavement. The present study provides recommendations for hospice and palliative care agencies on how to increase cultural competency among volunteer workers.</p>
<sec id="section1-1049909111414863" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section2-1049909111414863">
<title>Materials and Procedures</title>
<p>This case study included 14 hospice volunteers from 1 hospice in the Greater Toronto Area (GTA) in Ontario, Canada. The data were collected over the course of 8 months from January to July 2008. Ethics clearance was first obtained from the Hospice Board of Directors, then formally through the Research Ethics Board at the University of Waterloo. All participants read and signed the letter of information and consent forms and were advised they could refuse to answer any questions they felt uncomfortable with and could stop the interview at anytime. Caution was taken to exclude all identifiers and volunteers were coded by VT1, VT2, and so on. Of the 14 interviews 11 were conducted face-to-face, while 2 interviews were handled over the phone, and 1 interview was conducted via e-mail. Interview questions fell into 3 categories: (1) sociodemographic questions, such as ethnicity, languages spoken, education, marital status, income level, and employment; (2) volunteer history, such as the reason for volunteering in a hospice and how long they had been volunteering; and (3) cultural competency questions which focused on their training in cultural competency, their knowledge of what cultural competency was, their experiences working with multilingual and multiethnic patients, and their recommendations on how to improve cultural competency training for hospice and palliative care volunteers. These questions explored their thoughts on the cultural competency training received from the hospice, their experiences dealing with clients of different ethnicities, religions, language abilities and culture, how informed volunteers felt about other cultures, whether or not they would like to be better informed, and how they wanted further cultural competency information disseminated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049909111414863">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Of the 14 participants 2 were complementary care volunteers who specialize in specific stress-relieving services such as Reiki, reflexology, massage, or music therapy. While complementary care volunteers generally visit their patients once a week for 1 to 2 hours, regular hospice volunteers are with their patients weekly for a 4-hour visit and provide emotional, spiritual, and physical support. The age range for participants was 31 to 75 years, with a mean age of 52.1 years; 11 (79%) of the hospice volunteers were women, 12 (86%) were born in Canada, 13 volunteers (93%) were white/Caucasian with European decent, 11 (79%) were university graduates, 9 (64%) had annual incomes of over $41 000, and 11 (79%) were hospice volunteers for the first time. Six volunteers (43%) spoke a language other than English, while only 2 volunteers (14%) spoke a language other than English and French.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1049909111414863">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The majority of volunteers (9 of the 14) in this study could not remember if they were trained on cultural competency, nor what the training entailed. Not being able to remember if they were trained on cultural competency suggests the training was not adequate and needs to be reiterated on a continuous basis. “It’s not very nice to say that I can’t remember what the training on cultural competency was. Maybe it’ll come to me during the interview” (VT3, p1). Although, it was surprising the volunteers could not remember being trained on cultural competency, the initial hospice training for many of them occurred years prior and their official introduction to cultural competency was less than 2 hours in a 30-hour training session. What was surprising to learn was that there were no refresher courses or extra training material provided to volunteers on cultural competency.</p>
<sec id="section5-1049909111414863">
<title>Volunteers Want More Cultural Competency Training</title>
<p>Learning the proper techniques for becoming culturally competent as a hospice volunteer requires the commitment of both the hospice organization and the volunteers to engage in the dialogue, attend educational sessions, and inform themselves. At the time of this study, cultural competency training is not a requirement of the Hospice Organization of Ontario (HOA). The interview schedule probed cultural competency issues, and 13 of the14 volunteers expressed a genuine desire for more training on cultural issues related to their patients. Some volunteers considered themselves culturally competent already because of their vast travel experiences and or higher education that exposed them to the diversity of cultures. For instance “For someone with my background [the training] was adequate. I come from studies in sociology and psychology at university, and also my life experiences, so I’m used to dealing with multi-faith and multi-ethnic people or issues” (VT13, p2). “Yes, absolutely, I always want to learn more. You can never learn everything about everyone, so more education is good.”<disp-quote>
<p>No, culture isn’t an issue for me. Toronto is the most multi-cultural city in the world and I’m glad to be living in the city. We’re all essentially the same, so different cultures don’t mean anything to me. I feel like a citizen of the world. Living in Toronto is a pleasure. I’ve done a ton of travelling and it’s fantastic to see that we have the largest percentage of Chinese people living in Canada, other than in Mainland China, or Hong Kong. I really don’t even know what a “Canadian” is. (VT5, p1)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The theme of experience, whether through traveling, education or internal reflection and spirituality arose, with many volunteers expressing the belief that their travel experiences led them to be more culturally aware of the growing diversity of cultures and also increased their awareness of different cultures and ethnicities. They expressed their opinions thoughtfully in the following quotes:<disp-quote>
<p>I can’t really remember it [the training]. You know, I have my own ideas of what cultural competency means from my own experiences. I’ve travelled extensively. I’ve worked with the African-Canadian Legal Clinic. I’ve had various experiences from training. But ultimately, it’s about people and human beings, and we’re all basically the same, and we all want the same basic things from life. But I guess for me it was adequate. You can teach principles, but ultimately, you learn from experience. A lot of stuff comes out of ignorance, people cling to their cultural identities as a way of separating themselves from others. You must be sensitive and open to whatever is there from people. You can do what is required compassionately though. (VT12, p2)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Another volunteer with vast traveling experiences discussed the role and importance of seeing and experiencing different cultures around the world and the impact that had on being a hospice volunteer specifically but also in being sensitive and culturally competent in general.<disp-quote>
<p>I’m very informed because I’ve traveled extensively and lived in various places around the world. I also work with many different cultures in my day-to-day job. I’ve lived in Kaput, lived in communal farms, lived in South East Asia, in the West Coast, the East Coast, in the Yukon. I’ve lived in Mexico and traveled to South America. I’ve lived in Europe and I’ve been in youth travel exchange programs all throughout school. I’ve lived in Japan as a kid and as a group leader I’ve lived in India … I’ve seen so many different cultures and I’ve become more sensitive to people as a result of that. (VT11, p2-3)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>One volunteer in particular was adamant about providing details of her traveling experiences because she felt her travels shaped her values and understandings of other cultures and ethnicities which allowed her to become a more compassionate hospice volunteer.<disp-quote>
<p>I have traveled extensively and found that people who travel a lot, tend to care a lot and are interested in other cultures. I’ve spent 10 years living outside of Canada. I’ve traveled in Asia and lived in Australia and Papua New Guinea for 4 years. I’ve also lived one month of the year in Mexico and I’ve also lived in France for 3 months. Traveling has taught me to be more aware of death practices, different ways of being, others’ spirituality, &amp; others’ religious practices. (VT7, p4-5)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>When asked whether they would like further training on cultural competency, 13 volunteers expressed an interest in it. “Oh yes, of course. Learning about different cultures is very important, especially for the work what we do. I’m lucky, because I knew about many different cultures, I was married to an Asian man for 10 years, so I got to know about the Asian culture and beliefs quite well” (VT3, p2). Others knew they wanted more training but could not articulate what they needed from the hospice. “I don’t know what else the hospice could do, but yes, I would like more [training on cultural competency]” (VT8, p2). Others stated that “more would always be useful” (VT10, p2),“Yes, more is always better, I’m a lifelong learner” (VT11, p2).<disp-quote>
<p>That’s a really good question. With the training, it’s almost a—it’s so intensive, it’s almost a whirlwind of information, so probably in some respects yes, if you could focus on each section, but once you get out into the real world, if you do not have a lot of experience with people and also experience with people who are dying and their families, because that’s a whole different dynamic—it can be a little frightening and well, scary, it can be scary. (VT4, p2)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>When asked whether they would like to be better informed about the different cultures and ethnicities of their clients, 13 of volunteers responded positively that they would like more information. The only volunteer who did not particularly support further training stated “At the moment, I don’t see a need for it.… I don’t see them [the patients] as different as everyone else sees them” (VT5, p3). This particular volunteer felt that people share more similarities than differences therefore, more training on cultural competency was not necessary.</p>
<p>These findings reveal that volunteers are eager for more information, readily acknowledge the growing diversity of the population they serve and are earnest in their desires for greater education on cultural competency.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1049909111414863">
<title>Volunteers Acknowledge Importance of Being Culturally Competent</title>
<p>Almost all of the volunteers (13) strongly believed in the importance of cultural competency training for hospice palliative care work. For instance, “Absolutely, especially at a time as important as the end-of-life. It’s very important to recognize the variety of belief systems that exist and do everything you can to support that, to support people’s beliefs, especially at this time in their lives” (VT13, p2). Some of the volunteers were quite eloquent and their responses were rich with detail.<disp-quote>
<p>Absolutely, because, I mean, it’s just, it doesn’t necessarily have to be in Toronto. I mean it’s everywhere you go, in any country you go to, you can find so many different people from different cultures and languages and especially when you’re working with people who are dying. I mean what might not be so relative when you’re going to the grocery store to buy milk and eggs—I mean, it could be a whole different ball game if you’re interacting with these people in their home, when a family member is dying, because it just brings up cultural issues, that if you’re not from that culture, you may never have even considered, or know nothing about. (VT1, p1)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The volunteers seemed to acknowledge the great diversity of Toronto and their patients and realized the importance of being sensitive to and understanding of these different cultures in general, but especially during the dying process where people are more vulnerable. “Yes, for some people especially. Every one of us has our own prejudices, no matter where we come from” (VT12, p2). “Absolutely, especially living in such a multi-cultural society and city, we have to be sensitive, especially in that critical time in someone’s life where they are dying, it’s necessary to be sensitive” (VT11, p2). For instance, “It’s so that you don’t offend people accidentally, so that you don’t hurt people’s feelings, or say tactless things.”<disp-quote>
<p>Yes, in a household where someone is dying, absolutely. When dealing with clients and their families, you have to be sensitive. For example, I had a Japanese client that had immigrated to Canada as adults, and although they were Canadianized—they were still very much Japanese, and had Japanese cultural traits. So, being aware of the Asian culture, since I am Korean myself, I was aware of the cultural expectations and norms of household culture, such as talking off your shoes outside. I mean its surface stressors really, but at least I knew something about the culture. (VT10, p2)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Others were more pragmatic in their assessment of different cultures and simply tried to avoid any controversial topics that would inadvertently offend their patients.<disp-quote>
<p>You need to have some sensitivity and know that there are certain areas that you just don’t go into. It’s inappropriate to get into a heavy discussion on religion with your clients. (VT7, p2).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Another volunteer expressed the same sentiments by stating that:<disp-quote>
<p>You’re there to relax them, to hang out with them. I refuse to engage in anything remotely controversial or in differences of opinion. I’m only there to help them, and I don’t take their “stuff” home with me. When I’m there, I’m there. When I’m gone, then I don’t think about it. I try to use the most non-invasive option in every sense of the word. (VT5, p3)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>It is clear from these quotes that the majority of hospice volunteers not only want more training on cultural competency, but they firmly believe in the importance of being trained in this issue. Volunteers also had definite ideas for how they wanted to be kept informed on culturally competent issues.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049909111414863">
<title>Volunteer’s Recommendations to Increase Cultural Competency Training</title>
<p>When asked whether the volunteers had any suggestions to increase cultural competency for the hospice, all 14 of the volunteers had very specific ideas. For example,<disp-quote>
<p>I think some of the most helpful bits in the training was when other volunteers came in and spoke about their experience, or when a family member came in and talked about what an impact it made on their family, their situations, or even some of the written case studies that we looked at. The first-hand experience bits were the most helpful to me and I think could be really helpful for people coming up against cultural scenarios that they haven’t encountered before (VT1, p4)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Of the 14 participants, 11 shared an enthusiasm for pamphlets, brochure handouts, or even educational manuals that could list the most useful information on a particular culture, such as important customs, dates of celebration, dates of remembrance, rituals surrounding death and dying, and bereavement issues. Although these pamphlets were not specifically given out to volunteers during their employment with the hospice, volunteers expressed an interest in receiving them. “I also think some type of booklet or handout would be useful for the hospice to give out to volunteers on the major cultures surrounding death and dying” (VT8, p3). For instance,<disp-quote>
<p>I think anything helps, any training helps out. I think pamphlets on different cultures that you might come across would be helpful. I remember when I was teaching ESL, they had all these great pamphlets on different cultures, and one thing I remember was that you were never supposed to touch a Cambodian kid on the top of the head, because it had something to do with the spirits. I remember being startled when I read that, because I absolutely wouldn’t have known about that before. So there are things that you just wouldn’t know, and if we can be prepared and told any of that stuff beforehand—you know we’re going there to help these people, we don’t want to offend them or hurt their feelings, or accidentally make it more difficult for them. (VT3, p4)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Another volunteer thought having a calendar showcasing important dates for a specific culture would be helpful.<disp-quote>
<p>Some type of a calendar that showed the most important dates of both celebration and revolution, both sides of the spectrum. Obviously, they don’t have a sheet on every type of ethnic group there is, but you know, the main ones. Chinese, for instance, what are the languages they speak? How about the Eastern European’s—even keeping it that broad. I hate watching the news, but I guess in some respects, depending on who your client is, and what is going on in the world, it may—it can affect your service, depending on how the world news affects them. You know, they may have relatives and family in other places. (VT4, p6)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Many volunteers agreed that listening to community minority leaders would be quite helpful. Two volunteers thought that the only way to learn is to experience situations firsthand and although cultural competency training may be helpful, they believed experience is the key. “I don’t know. I can only tell people my own experience and my successful experiences, and what I’ve done, but whether that will work for them is unknown” (VT5, p2). “Any kind of experiential learning is helpful, not just telling us about it, not just hearing about it, but experiencing it” (VT11, p2).</p>
<p>Another volunteer wanted to “Bring in community members from different cultural backgrounds to speak to anyone at the Hospice who was interested in learning about different cultures, religions and ethnicities” (VT9, p2).<disp-quote>
<p>I think guest speakers wouldn’t be a bad idea, especially from different faiths, to come in and talk to the volunteers to discuss particular challenges, especially when someone is dying. Like those that have AIDS or because whose illnesses may be “tied” to their ethnicity or sexual orientation—that’s difficult, so to have someone come in and talk to the volunteers to give sensitivity training on it would be good—to put a human face on things (VT13, p2).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Another wished to hear directly from other volunteers and listen to their experiences.<disp-quote>
<p>Bringing in family members to talk to volunteers about cultural differences would be helpful. Also, listening to volunteers who have worked in diverse cultural settings and have overcome obstacles, hearing about their solutions and experiences would be helpful (VT11, p2).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Another volunteer mentioned information overload, where volunteers could have too much textbook knowledge about cultures that may not even be applicable to the patient, depending on their level of acculturation into Canadian society, and how much of their own cultural customs they still practice.<disp-quote>
<p>I don’t think so, because it’s just general information. I don’t want to go into a situation with a client with too many general assumptions about their culture and who they are. I’m not going to go into someone’s house and bow when I meet them just because they’re Japanese, even though that’s what the brochure says. But mean while, they haven’t been practicing that tradition in years, and now it’s an awkward situation. I don’t know if there’s something that the Hospice can really do to better inform us about culture. There’s too many diverse cultures out there. I don’t know if they have the time or budget to do that. (VT6, p2)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>What was most surprising was how detailed the responses were in terms of what volunteers wanted and expected the Hospice to provide to increase cultural competency. Their ideas for training were well thought out, specific, and comprehensive. Some preferred to have Web-based training available, while others vehemently disagreed and preferred face-to-face interactions, where they could ask questions and listen to speakers themselves. “I don’t want any web-based training. I want to ask questions and hear the responses in person. I want dialogue with others, I want a face-to-face interaction—nothing to read about, I want to hear it and understand it” (VT11, p2). Most volunteers thought brochures were a great idea, while one thought any printed material was a waste of money. Either way, volunteers were very particular in their preferences for training, and their opinions were thorough and almost itemized in a sense. “I think that web-based training would be helpful, as would written materials. I probably wouldn’t come to an actual meeting for more specialized training, but I would read the material on-line” (VT12, p2).<disp-quote>
<p>Perhaps on a bi-monthly, or monthly basis, there could be some on-line training for people who can’t make the get-together, or prefer web-based training. I think that the first training on cultural competency should be a face-to-face interaction so people can ask questions and get issues clarified, and then after that there should be training available on-line (VT11, p3).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>One volunteer suggested raising the consciousness of people as a way of increasing cultural competency.<disp-quote>
<p>The most useful techniques would be raising the consciousness of people. Bringing up issues that could possibly come up and how to handle them. The general principle of cultural sensitivity is important to know, and specifically, to know what cues and signals you should be sensitive to. I think the hospice e-newsletter is a good forum. Maybe having a regular feature like “Keep in Mind,” which would point out the important points of cultural competency and would help keep the message up front so people would remember. I think print brochures are a waste of money. I also think that the regular or irregular hospice get-together for the volunteers is a good forum for raising issues. People could bring their experiences to share with other volunteers, of situations that occurred and how to handle them (VT10, p2).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The majority of volunteers had detailed ideas of how they wanted to be supported through further training in cultural competency and their responses show how seriously they take their volunteering and how much thought and effort goes into working with people who are dying. Volunteers in this study showcased a great deal of sensitivity and empathy toward their patients and genuinely wished to improve their level of cultural competency. One volunteer had a great idea of increasing cultural competency that was not previously stated, “… perhaps a course on non-verbal communication skills” (VT 6, p2). Others wanted more detailed training.<disp-quote>
<p>I find the little Hospice meetings where you get to ask questions quite helpful. Perhaps they could bring in some religious heads of different religions to come in and discuss the religious practices, &amp; cultural differences. Maybe other volunteers could discuss these things also, to discuss basic principles like numerology, what numbers are lucky or unlucky with certain cultures. Also colors, for instance, the color white in Chinese is the color of death, so being aware or conscious of your dress is important when visiting with clients. Maybe people could be brought in to just discuss some cultural differences or different food choices. It goes without saying that you can’t generalize cultures, everyone is unique and different. I think the most important thing is to be present and really listen, those are the most important skills. You have to take their concerns seriously, and don’t be dismissive of what they want to say. I think the Hospice can certainly pay for more training or courses to take. I think putting resources on the Web is a great idea, that way people can look up the most important cultural differences before they visit with their client. I also think a handbook or a one-page summary on cultures and things that are related to death and dying, or cultural practices would be quite helpful. For instance, issues on religious beliefs, death practices and bereavement. I also wouldn’t mind receiving little reminders about different cultures through the web from the Hospice, because sometimes we don’t even use the resources we know about, so reminders are good. Certain books that deal with different cultures, or articles should be assigned reading for volunteers, and make them available either through the web, or on loan through the hospice library. (VT7, p3)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>One volunteer thought that cultural information should be given about the patient being currently matched up with the volunteer and that particular information should be disseminated before the first visit with the patient. For instance,<disp-quote>
<p>I think the Hospice needs to give more information about the clients’ culture, ethnicity, religion and customs, when they’re giving us the initial information about the client. I think that any cultural, religious or ethnic information related to death and dying would be very helpful to know BEFORE (emphasis by volunteer), visiting with the client. For instance, I have a new client, and I’m going to be reading a lot with this client, and it would be really helpful to know before hand if this client was very religious, or if there were any specific cultural or ethnic things I should be aware about before I start reading to them. For instance, is there anything inappropriate that I shouldn’t be reading to them? I think that would be very useful information to know what inappropriate customs to avoid regarding death and dying with your clients. I feel that the Hospice just doesn’t give enough information about the client other than the basic medical issues, before going into your first visit with a client. I mean, you know their level of mobility, their age, their gender, their name, but that’s about it. Everything else, you’re left to find out for yourself on your first visit. I would like to know their religion and cultural or ethnic customs to be aware or to avoid (VT8, p2).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Volunteers in this study were keenly aware of the complexities involved not only in death and dying but also in dealing with such a diverse population as found in the Greater Toronto Area, and their responses expressed a deeper understanding of the intricate layers of disease, illness, family dynamics, culture, diversity, death, dying and vulnerability. Volunteers can become engrossed in the emotional ramifications of dying and to expect them to be unscathed by their care-giving duties is unrealistic. The human experience of witnessing someone in the dying process and eventual death is staggering in its intensity and unimaginable for most people. Therefore, it becomes a necessity to adequately prepare hospice and palliative care volunteers with a comprehensive training to equitably be able to handle patients from a diverse cultural and linguistic background. Training must be an ongoing and continuously reflexive journey with no predetermined end point. The goal is to <italic>become </italic>culturally competent rather than <italic>be </italic>culturally competent. Hospice volunteers need to be regularly briefed on all issues related to death and dying from a multicultural perspective.</p>
<p>It is possible to adequately train both hospice volunteers and staff, along with health care providers, such as hospitals and clinics, to become culturally competent. To do so requires a commitment from individuals and agencies to assess their internal values, to be open to learning, and be willing to make the time to create positive changes. To foster an environment conducive to learning, and to prepare people to become culturally competent, individuals and agencies must begin to bear the responsibilities for this change to occur. Policies need to be implemented, institutionalized, and regularly monitored, and people need to have the resources and tools necessary to enable them to achieve a greater degree of cultural competency. To achieve this level of awareness and knowledge, certain recommendations are given below. I have divided them into 2 groups: individual-level recommendations and agency recommendations.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1049909111414863">
<title>Volunteer Recommendations</title>
<p>Individual volunteers working for health care providers such as hospitals or hospices need to access their own values, belief systems, attitudes, judgments and worldviews in order to effectively and equitably service a diverse population.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049909111414863">5</xref> </sup>Volunteers need to accept personal responsibility for learning about different cultures and ethnicities since they have volunteered to work with a diverse public or catchment area. Through the assistance of the hospice agency, volunteers should be able to access online resources, attend lectures on cultural and diversity issues, borrow literature from the hospice, listen to cultural competency experts, and be given every available means to strengthen their knowledge and confidence about cultural competency.</p>
<p>Volunteers in this study and in previous research<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049909111414863">6</xref>
</sup> have expressed their preferences for increased training and refresher courses or training modules to be given on a regular basis on a variety of topics pertaining to hospice care. Volunteers would also benefit from building stronger relationships with their colleagues by having online chat rooms or discussion boards to discuss difficult situations or patients, to ask questions and give or receive advice in a friendly nonjudgmental environment. Having online resources that are available to download, such as literature and research on death and dying in general, and cultural competency specifically—would be a simple and convenient way to enhance hospice volunteer confidence and effectiveness. Having an interactive forum where volunteers can log on to the hospice Web site to watch “Hospice episodes” of lectures, listen to other volunteers speaking, specialists discussing pertinent hospice issues, or hospice staff discussing policy and procedures would also be helpful and cost-effective. Having an interactive Web site that allows volunteers to e-mail, chat, phone or “Skype” (free software that allows users to make phone calls over the Internet) to discuss issues creates the beginning of effective communication, allowing volunteers to access the training at a time and place convenient for them. Staying current with ever-changing technology can allow hospices to stay ahead of the learning curve by providing information instantly accessible to iPhones, iPads, and Blackberries. Hospice and palliative care agencies can even create an “Apps” specific for hospice and palliative care that volunteers and staff can download, open, and use at their convenience.</p>
<p>Volunteers in this study mentioned the value of listening to firsthand accounts from other volunteers about difficult situations or patients, in order to personally hear how someone handled a situation and are then able to ask questions and engage in a dialogue. Volunteers would also appreciate hearing from visible minority volunteers, staff, and community leaders about topics specific to death and dying or end-of-life care related to different cultures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1049909111414863">
<title>Agency Recommendations</title>
<p>For health care providers to adequately represent the diverse community they serve by increasing cultural competency, recommendations are made based on 4 aspects of hospice care: (1) volunteer support; (2) internal changes; (3) training; and (4) community outreach.</p>
<sec id="section10-1049909111414863">
<title>Volunteer Support</title>
<p>The research is consistent in describing the importance of valuing, satisfying, and meeting the expectations of hospice and palliative care volunteers. If volunteers are satisfied with their work and feel valued and appreciated, they are less likely to leave. Decreasing volunteer turnover saves money, time, and resources for hospices. Volunteers need to feel as if they are making a difference and that they are appreciated, valuable, and unique individuals. Ensuring that volunteers are consistently reminded of their value and contribution to patients, the community, and the hospice will secure their longevity as happy hospice volunteers and save health care providers money and time in both recruitment and training.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049909111414863">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049909111414863">8</xref>
</sup> Alienating the valuable volunteer base of a hospice can have disastrous consequences for lowering morale and decreasing loyalty, which can very easily lead to apathy and a high desertion rate. Hospices must make it a priority to keep their volunteers engaged, involved, and must strive to answer all questions and concerns within a timely manner. Hospices must make sure their volunteers feel appreciated and supported or they will risk losing them.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909111414863">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909111414863"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049909111414863"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909111414863">12</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Offering support for cultural competency can increase morale and decrease turnover and desertion. Therefore it makes sense for hospices to invest in this as it benefits patients and the volunteers hospices want to keep. Encouraging engagement from volunteers can be facilitated by creating greater opportunities for volunteers to be in touch with their colleagues and feel connected in order to benefit by creating stronger bonds or alliances with their fellow volunteers. Whether this is through volunteer-specific forums, such as discussion boards, chat rooms, or mentoring programs, volunteers need that human touch to keep them engaged and to maintain service and loyalty. These forums can be an opportunity for volunteers to share stories, relay information, and convey messages about working with clients of a different ethnic, cultural, religious, or linguistic background. This type of conversation is really about “sharing our humanity”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049909111414863">13</xref>
</sup> with one another, allowing others to bear witness to our vulnerabilities, our mistakes, our assumptions, and our imperfections. Knowing that mistakes happen when we are with our patients, eases the anxiety other volunteers may have about making mistakes themselves. Hearing how other volunteers maneuvered through difficult or unchartered territory with diverse patients though online forums are an effective way to reach a large number of volunteers while minimizing costs.</p>
<p>Another way to keep hospice volunteers engaged is to consistently ask for their feedback through anonymous surveys such as Survey Monkey.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049909111414863">14</xref>
</sup> This type of feedback allows volunteers to quickly, easily, and conveniently relay their opinions on a variety of hospice and palliative care issues all done in an anonymous and confidential manner. Eliciting periodic feedback from volunteers is an essential way to monitor the progress and implementation of new hospice policies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1049909111414863">
<title>Internal Changes</title>
<p>Hospices need to make a commitment from the front lines by ensuring that their staff and volunteers are culturally, ethnically, and linguistically diverse themselves and can accurately reflect the community they serve. Of the fourteen volunteers in this study, 13 were white/Caucasian, as was the majority of the hospice staff. This is problematic when servicing a multicultural and multilingual community. This also presents a formidable challenge for hospices to become more diverse themselves. Communication and services must be provided in a variety of different languages.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049909111414863">15</xref>
</sup> Looking within, hospices must evaluate and assess their belief systems in general but specifically the beliefs of their staff and volunteers.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049909111414863">16</xref>
</sup> Hospice administrators must assess the level of awareness, sensitivity to, and competency of different cultures from their own staff. Hospice and palliative care agencies need to also provide regular progress reports and develop training initiatives to ensure recommendations are being followed.</p>
<p>Increased funding needs to be made available to create a new board or committee on cultural competency.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049909111414863">17</xref>
</sup> This committee should be responsible for handling all cultural competency issues, such as training of staff and volunteers, analyzing training techniques and modules, developing a mission statement, establishing goals, and assessing implementation of these goals. The new mission statement on cultural competency should reflect the core values of the hospice, and all training material and brochures should feature this statement. A mission statement to make commitment to equity and respect for diversity also needs to be developed.</p>
<p>Staffing shortages, budget freezes, fiscal restructuring, and time constraints can make cultural competency programs seem like an overwhelming burden. A lack of consensus over core diversity values or teaching techniques or even lack of institutional or organizational support for cultural competency can create barriers to implementation. We need to create a sense of urgency and move past these initial pragmatic resistances or concerns for implementing yet another training strategy and view cultural competency training as a core feature of an equitable and accessible end-of-life health care system. With the incorporation of increased funding, the necessary research, training, and education can mature to ensure all hospice providers can deliver on their commitment to a more culturally inclusive environment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1049909111414863">
<title>Training</title>
<p>To improve the cultural competency of their staff and volunteers, hospices must engage people with innovative training techniques and incorporate creative training modules on a consistent basis. Beginning from the initial volunteer training program, cultural competency must be introduced in an in-depth manner. Volunteers should have the opportunity to learn about cultural competence and the importance of respecting and valuing diversity through modern training exercises, including visuals, media, lectures, written material, webcasts, online training, discussion boards, regular meetings, role-playing, short skits, and listening to firsthand experience from fellow volunteers, minority leaders, and cultural competency specialists. Volunteers must be given the necessary tools to continually learn, assess, and reassess their skills and knowledge about the importance of servicing diverse clients in a culturally competent manner.</p>
<p>As was evidenced in this case study, hospice volunteers could not remember being trained on cultural competency, even though they all received a 2-hour workshop on diversity. This suggests the type of workshop given was ineffective in either its delivery or breadth. Training must accommodate various types of learning (activists, reflective, theorizing, and experimental) and be delivered through a multiplicity of techniques, including individual case discussions, group work, self-reflection, role-playing, “show-tell-and-do,” the use of vignettes, patient narratives, video re-enactments of stimulated health care encounters, video interviews of patients, and didactically through lectures and podcasts.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049909111414863">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049909111414863">19</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Role-playing strategies are effective approaches for learning and assimilating new information should be incorporated as part of diversity training.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049909111414863">20</xref>
</sup> Since listening to a lecture-style module on cultural competency is notoriously weak for memory retention, interactive participation exercises will elicit higher retention values and should be emphasized more often. Studies have shown an increase in cultural competency levels after an initial training module occurred, however limited these gains may be, they exist nonetheless, showing that training and education in cultural competency can make hospice and palliative care volunteers more knowledgeable and confident in their abilities to handle diverse multilingual and multicultural patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049909111414863">21</xref>
</sup> Cultural competency training can improve communication between health care providers and patients, ultimately leading to more effective patient-centered care.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1049909111414863">
<title>Community Outreach</title>
<p>Advertisements about hospice services such as brochures should be accessible in major community centers in different languages to continuously attract new clients while affirming continuity and trust in the community. Brochures and pamphlets should be made available in organizations that service diverse ethnic groups including newcomers to Canada such as Churches, community centers, walk-in-clinics, libraries, hospitals, local YMCAs, and health clubs. It is imperative for hospice organizations to increase the recognition and importance of their services in the community by creating stronger relationships with minority community leaders and centers.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049909111414863">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049909111414863">23</xref>
</sup> Alliances should be formed so that community members feel safe, comforted, and respected by the competent community health care services provided by the hospices. Most importantly, liaisons between the ethnic minority communities and hospices needs to be strengthened so that the minority population is informed of the existence of hospice and palliative care services available to them, and cognizant of the important roles they can play during the last stages of life. Attracting minority volunteers to work with hospice organizations can be an effective “word-of-mouth” strategy to encourage other minorities to utilize palliative care services. Research is needed to examine not only why ethnic or visible minorities are not fully represented as hospice volunteers themselves but also strategies to encourage their participation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1049909111414863">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The current research on cultural competency tends to focus on 4 main areas: definitions of cultural competency and its importance for health care systems<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049909111414863">24</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049909111414863"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049909111414863"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049909111414863">27</xref>
</sup>; theoretical frameworks<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049909111414863">28</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049909111414863"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049909111414863"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1049909111414863">31</xref>
</sup>; culturally competent barriers and or techniques: usually 9 are cited—interpreter services; recruitment and retention; training; coordinating with traditional healers; use of community health workers; culturally competent health promotion; including family and or community members; immersion into another culture; and administrative and organization accommodations<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049909111414863">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049909111414863">33</xref>
</sup>; and racial and ethnic health disparities.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1049909111414863">34</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049909111414863"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049909111414863"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049909111414863"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1049909111414863">38</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>What is missing from this field of data is the aftermath of implementing culturally competent health care measures. When culturally competent techniques are enforced, does that necessarily lead to better health outcomes for hospice and palliative care patients? If so, it is unclear how culturally competent policies and progress are measured within agencies or institutions. The future trends for cultural competency in hospice palliative care include the following 4 key issues.</p>
<sec id="section15-1049909111414863">
<title>Definitions</title>
<p>Each health care agency and or discipline defines cultural competency somewhat differently. This leads to various vague and open-ended definitions that create more confusion then clarity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049909111414863">39</xref>
</sup> There needs to be a unifying definition when dealing with health care. Instead, we have various perspectives from medicine,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049909111414863">40</xref>
</sup> mental health,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049909111414863">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1049909111414863">42</xref>
</sup> nursing,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049909111414863">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049909111414863">44</xref>
</sup> child welfare,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1049909111414863">45</xref>
</sup> occupational<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1049909111414863">46</xref>
</sup> and physical therapy,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1049909111414863">47</xref>
</sup> and addiction.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1049909111414863">48</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1049909111414863"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1049909111414863">50</xref>
</sup> If it is impossible to use a consistent and agreed upon definition, then a separate definition of cultural competency for hospice palliative care must be conceived and agreed upon. Previous definitions of cultural competency are simply not detailed enough for hospice and palliative care educators, who need an absolute development of the cultural diversity among and between cultures during the death, dying, and bereavement stages exclusively. In fact, all the models previously mentioned focus on cultural competency as it relates to the living but do not specifically address the patients’ dying moments, either as process or as event. This is where the gap in the literature exists and why it is imperative that a cultural competency model specifically for hospice and palliative care be developed. Definitions must be distinguished for both health care organizations in general (ie, hospices and palliative care centers) and individuals (volunteers and staff members).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1049909111414863">
<title>Measurement and Assessment Issues</title>
<p>Organizations need a mission statement on cultural competency and equity, alongside specific training on diversity issues. To ensure proper implementation reflective monitoring mechanisms are needed to measure this cultural competency progress. Currently, the measurement of cultural competency is a conundrum. Validity and reliability of these measurements is often divergent and nebulous in nature. Biases can exist and enforcement of cultural competency policies and progress is often difficult to measure. If an agency has culturally competent policies, it does not necessarily mean they are being implemented nor that cultural competency has become a reality within a particular agency. Also, if an agency does not have culturally competent mission statements, it does not mean they are not being practiced. It is imperative to know which of the culturally competent techniques (interpreter services, training of staff, immersion of cultures, inclusion of family and/or community, organizational accommodations)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1049909111414863">51</xref>
</sup> actually improve conditions for both patients and hospice palliative care volunteers and staff. Questions surrounding reliability and measurement difficulties abound, and once policies are put in place, continued or vigilant enforcement of policies is difficult to maintain. Currently, there is no governing body involved in monitoring cultural competency within hospice palliative care agencies, and the consequences for not adhering to culturally competent guidelines are felt most poignantly with the patients and their families/caregivers, and secondarily with hospice volunteers themselves.</p>
<p>Assessment tools for cultural competency in hospice and palliative care agencies requires a unifying measure and all tools, checklists, and appraisals should be standardized. Cultural competency is a complex subject requiring multilevel constructs, but each agency may have different checklists, which makes for confusion when attempting to assess skill levels or competencies in cultural awareness for health care providers. It is also problematic when trying to conduct comparative research across different health care agencies. Assessments should include the following 3 questions. “First, do providers learn what is taught? Second, do we use what is taught? Third, does what is taught have an impact on care?”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1049909111414863">52</xref>
</sup> Assessments of cultural competency training should always reflect the core values and mission statements of the hospice and palliative care organizations while also mirroring the original learning objectives.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1049909111414863">
<title>Financing and Training</title>
<p>Training health care providers in cultural competency is a multilevel responsibility beginning with our diverse patients themselves, who need to inform hospice staff and volunteers of their cultural preferences. Next, hospice agencies bear a large responsibility to ensure both their staff and volunteers are culturally representative of their catchment area and are adequately trained on a regular basis in all issues relating to cultural competency and diversity. By enforcing the significance of the cultural <italic>journey</italic> rather than the <italic>destination</italic> for competency, hospice agencies can begin to internalize the belief that health care needs to be accessible and equitable for all our community members. Lastly, the responsibility for assisting in the implementation of culturally competent health care practices needs to be committed to by local and national governments.</p>
<p>Future training materials including the printing, production, and development of DVDs, CDs, brochures; training and workshops; booklets, books, and magazines or journals; and use of experts need to be factored into yearly budget discussions. Cultural competency training is a fiscal responsibility for both the individual agencies and institutions relating to end-of-life care and provincial/state and national/federal agencies themselves.</p>
<p>Consideration should be given to who provides the cultural competency training with emphasis placed on collaboration with cultural competency specialists. Training needs to be updated every 1 to 2 years and training materials should be readily accessible both in print and online for all hospice volunteers and staff. People who need answers on cultural competency should know where to go within their own agency to find it. Educational material such as books, articles, DVDs, and CDs should be on reserve, so that anyone can read them, borrow them, and or photocopy them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1049909111414863">
<title>Patient Perspectives</title>
<p>This is the most important category and yet we know very little of what patients expect in terms of cultural competency. To date, there is no research that illustrates whether hospice palliative care agencies are meeting the needs of their diverse and multicultural patients, from a patient-centered perspective. Nor, is there any indication that patients and hospice providers define cultural competency in similar ways. Cultural clashes between hospice patients and providers may be perceived differently and efforts must be taken to include the patient’s perspective.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1049909111414863">53</xref>
</sup> Definitions and assessments of what our diverse patients seek from palliative care providers is not explicitly clear in the research, nor do we know if patients and their families or caregivers have any suggestions for improving the hospice system to make it more culturally competent. To date, there have been no studies researching the viewpoint of hospice patients regarding cultural competency. This is an opportunity for improvement and can occur through brief questionnaires, interviews, or surveys given to patients and/or their families and caregivers both before and after the patient dies. Ethical dilemmas on researching dying patients certainly exists, but the difficulties in ascertaining ethics approval should not prevent these types of essential questions from being asked of the dying, if only to improve the limited time left for others. The responsibility for cultural competence does not solely lie with agencies themselves but is also shouldered by volunteers and patients. Patients and their families and caregivers are intimately involved in a reciprocal relationship with palliative care providers and need to provide their own input, feedback, suggestions, and knowledge for a collaborative and cohesive patient-centered health care experience.</p>
<p>As can be shown from the above list, cultural competency within health care has many shortcomings and future trends must focus on filling in these gaps so that definitions are standardized, assessments tools and checklists are uniform, policies are easily implemented, and progress is monitored in a timely and efficient manner.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1049909111414863">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This study’s major concern deals with the scope of cultural competency in hospice palliative care and the research findings will be beneficial in practice for patients, their families, volunteers, and health care providers such as nurses, doctors, social workers, and personal support workers by providing the knowledge and tools necessary to enhance their level of cultural competency. By initiating the discussion on the importance of cultural competency of volunteers and staff in hospice and palliative care, this research goes beyond simply stating the challenges to providing culturally competent care in palliative care settings, and instead gives the hospice-volunteer perspective on how to increase cultural competency through specific recommendations and strategies. Relevant agencies can begin to take measures for the improvement of care giver training, and the patient–caregiver relationship by implementing some of the recommendations given.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>Helpful feedback and advice on this paper were provided by Dr. Sandra Colavecchia. The author would also like to acknowledge the tremendous support and guidance provided by Dr. Weizhen Dong during this study.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1049909111414863">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1049909111414863">
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049909111414863">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</collab>. <source>Tracking healthy people 2010</source>. <edition>(2nd ed.)</edition>. <publisher-loc>Pittsburgh, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S</publisher-name>. <publisher-name>Government Printing Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049909111414863">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elwert</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spence</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Christakis</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Racial disparity in hospice use in the united States in 2002</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049909111414863">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">National Hospice and Palliative Care Organization (NHPCO)</collab>. <article-title>NHPCO facts and figures on hospice care 2010 edition</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhpco.org">http://www.nhpco.org</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed May 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049909111414863">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kemp</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural issues in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Semin Oncol Nurs</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049909111414863">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bernard</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moriah</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competency: an individual or institutional responsibility?</article-title> <source>Canad Social Work Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049909111414863">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pearson-Scott</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caldwell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Needs and program strengths: perceptions of hospice volunteers</article-title>. <source>Hospice J</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049909111414863">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ohlen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Being a hospice volunteer</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049909111414863">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chevrier</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steuer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacKenzie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting satisfaction among community-based hospice volunteer visitors</article-title>. <source>Am J Hospice Palliat Care</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049909111414863">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Webster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>“But isn’t it depressing?”-the vitality of palliative care</article-title>. <source>J Palliat Care</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049909111414863">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dien</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qamar-Abbas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The stresses of volunteering in a hospice: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049909111414863">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Korda</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The benefits of beneficence: rewards of hospice volunteering</article-title> <source>Am J Hospice Palliat Care</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049909111414863">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glass</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hasting</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Stress and the Burnout: concerns for the Hospice Volunteer</article-title>. <source>Educ Gerontol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049909111414863">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rokach</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Caring for those who care for the dying: coping with the demands on palliative care workers</article-title>. <source>Palliat Support Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049909111414863">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Survey Monkey</collab>. <comment>URL</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.surveymonkey.com/">http://www.surveymonkey.com/</ext-link> <comment>Accessed May 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049909111414863">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maher</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cross cultural research in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Social Work Health Mental Health</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>35</volume>
<issue>(1/2)</issue>:<fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049909111414863">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Colon</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of hospice use and demographics among European Americans, African Americans, and Latinos</article-title>. <source>Am J Hospice Palliat Care</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049909111414863">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maher</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cross cultural research in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Social Work Health Mental Health</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>35</volume>
<issue>(1/2)</issue>:<fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049909111414863">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doyle</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>The Training and Education of Volunteers in Volunteers in Hospice and Palliative Care: A Handbook for Volunteer Service Managers</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NY. Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049909111414863">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Institute of Medicine</collab>. <source>“Interventions: Cross-Cultural Education in the Health Professions” Unequal Treatment: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Disparities in Health Care</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049909111414863">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Engebretson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carlson</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competence in the era of evidence-based practice</article-title>. <source>J Professional Nurs</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049909111414863">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schim</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Doorenbos</surname>
<given-names>AZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Borse</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing cultural competence among hospice staff</article-title>. <source>Am J Hospice Palliat Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049909111414863">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Colon</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lyke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of hospice use and demographics among European Americans, African Americans, and Latinos</article-title>. <source>Am J Hospice Palliat Care</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049909111414863">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maher</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cross cultural research in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Social Work Health and Mental Health</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>35</volume>
<issue>(1/2)</issue>:<fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>543</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049909111414863">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bazron</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dennis</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isaacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Towards a Culturally Competent System of Care, Volume I</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CASSP</publisher-name> <publisher-name>Technical Assistance Center, Georgetown University Child Development Center</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049909111414863">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Isaacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Towards a Culturally Competent System of Care. Volume III</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CASSP Technical Assistance Centre, Georgetown University Child Development Centre</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1049909111414863">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">National Center for Cultural Competence (NCCC)- Georgetown University Center for Child and Human Development</collab>. <comment>URL</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.gucchd.georgetown.edu">www.gucchd.georgetown.edu</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed May 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1049909111414863">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Office of Minority Health (OMH)</collab>. <article-title>National Standards for Culturally and Linguistically Appropriate Services in Health Care: Executive Summary</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>. <comment>URL</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.gucchd.georgetown.edu">www.gucchd.georgetown.edu</ext-link>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/">http://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed May 2011</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1049909111414863">
<label>28</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Camphina-Bacote</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The process of cultural competence in the delivery of healthcare services: a model of care</article-title>. <source>J Transc Nursing</source>.<year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1049909111414863">
<label>29</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giger</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davidhizar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The giger and davidhizar transcultural assessment model</article-title>. <source>J Transc Nursing</source>.<year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1049909111414863">
<label>30</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leininger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Transcultural Nursing: Theories, Research and Practice</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>1978</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1049909111414863">
<label>31</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Purnell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Purnell model for cultural competence</article-title>. <source>J Transc Nursing</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1049909111414863">
<label>32</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scrimshaw</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fullilove</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fielding</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Normand</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>; <collab collab-type="author">Task Force on Community Preventive Services</collab>. <article-title>Culturally competent healthcare systems: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Am J Prevent Med</source>.<year>2003</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3S</issue>):<fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1049909111414863">
<label>33</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fong</surname>
<given-names>LGW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gibbs</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Facilitating services to multicultural communities in a dominant culture setting: an organizational perspective</article-title>. <source>Admin Social Work</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1049909111414863">
<label>34</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chin</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walters</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interventions to reduce racial and ethnic disparities in health care</article-title>. <source>Med Care Res Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>7S</fpage>–<lpage>28S</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1049909111414863">
<label>35</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mayberry</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mili</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vaid</surname>
<given-names>IGM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <source>Racial and Ethnic Differences in Access to Medical Care: A Synthesis of the Literature</source>. <publisher-loc>Menlo Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation</publisher-name>; <year>1999</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1049909111414863">
<label>36</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tseng</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Streltzer</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Healthcare for people of different ethnicities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Tseng</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Streltzer</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, Eds. <source>Cultural Competence in Health Care</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1049909111414863">
<label>37</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weinick</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zuvekas</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic differences in access to and use of health care services, 1977-1996</article-title>. <source>Med Care Res Rev</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1049909111414863">
<label>38</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kigawa-Singer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increasing access to care for cultural and linguistic minorities: ethnicity-specific health care organizations and infrastructure</article-title>. <source>J Health Care Poor Underserved</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1049909111414863">
<label>39</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Engebretson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carlson</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competence in the era of evidence-based practice</article-title>. <source>J Profession Nursing</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1049909111414863">
<label>40</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geiger</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Racial stereotyping and medicine: the need for cultural competence</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>164</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1699</fpage>–<lpage>1700</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1049909111414863">
<label>41</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bhui</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Warfa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Edonya</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bhugra</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competence in mental health care: a review of model evaluations</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<fpage>7</fpage>:<volume>15</volume>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1049909111414863">
<label>42</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hernandez</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nesman</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mowery</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Acevedo-Polakovich</surname>
<given-names>ID</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Callejas</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competence: a literature review and conceptual model for mental health services</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1557</fpage>–<lpage>1580</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1049909111414863">
<label>43</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leininger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McFarland</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Culture care diversity and universality theory and evolution of the ethnonursing method</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Leininger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McFarland</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, Eds. <source>Culture Care Diversity and Universality: A Worldwide Nursing Theory</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Sudbury, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Barlett</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1049909111414863">
<label>44</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Purnell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paulanka</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Transcultural Health Care: A Culturally Competent Approach</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FA Davis Company</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1049909111414863">
<label>45</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bazron</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dennis</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isaacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Towards a Culturally Competent System of Care, Volume I</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CASSP</publisher-name> <publisher-name>Technical Assistance Center, Georgetown University Child Development Center</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1049909111414863">
<label>46</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Odawara</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competency in occupational therapy: beyond a cross-cultural view of practice</article-title>. <source>Am J Occup Ther</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1049909111414863">
<label>47</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Lattanzi</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Purnell</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds <source>Developing Cultural Competency in Physical Therapy Practice</source>. <publisher-name>Philadelphia</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>PA, FA Davis</publisher-loc>; <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1049909111414863">
<label>48</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Amodeo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Viewing alcohol and other drug use cross culturally: a cultural framework for clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Families Soc J Contemp Human Serv</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1049909111414863">
<label>49</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing ethnic sensitivity: implications for alcoholism counsellors</article-title>. <source>Counselor</source>. <year>1994;(November/December): 8-12</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1049909111414863">
<label>50</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Addressing the needs of cultural minorities in drug treatment</article-title>. <source>J Substance Abuse Treatment</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1049909111414863">
<label>51</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brach</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fraserirector</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Can cultural competency reduce racial and ethnic health disparities?</article-title> <source>A review and conceptual model. Med Care Res Rev</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1049909111414863">
<label>52</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Institute of Medicine</collab>. <source>Unequal Treatment: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Disparities in Health Care. “Interventions: Cross-Cultural Education in the Health Professions”. 199-214</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1049909111414863">
<label>53</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geron</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cultural competency: how is it measured? does it make a difference?</article-title> <source>Generation J Am Soc Aging</source>. <year>2002/03</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>