<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spbas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Business &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0007-6503</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4205</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0007650308324047</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0007650308324047</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An Exploratory Analysis of Corporate Social Responsibility and Disclosure</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Dawkins</surname><given-names>Cedric E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0007650308324047">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fraas</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0007650308324047">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0007650308324047"><label>1</label>California State Polytechnic University, Pomona</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0007650308324047"><label>2</label>Ashland University</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0007650308324047">Cedric E. Dawkins, California State Polytechnic University– Pomona, Pomona, CA 92768, USA. Email: <email>cedawkins@csupomona.edu</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>52</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>245</fpage>
<lpage>281</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2008 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Previous studies indicate two possibly asymmetric findings about the relationship between corporate social performance (CSP) and annual report disclosure practices: (a) disclosure practices of companies with favorable CSP emanate from a sense of ethical duty, and (b) there are strategic reasons to link CSP with disclosure practices. To test the relationship between CSP and annual report disclosure, this study divided S&amp;P 500 companies into two groups, defined for low CSP (resulting <italic>n</italic> = 148) and high CSP (resulting <italic>n</italic> = 69). For the low CSP group of companies, disclosure was positively related to CSP strengths. For the high CSP group of companies, disclosure was positively related to CSP weaknesses. The authors conclude that low CSP disclosure practices are related to CSP strengths to build or repair reputation, whereas high CSP disclosure practices are associated with CSP weaknesses to protect favorable CSP brand.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>corporate social responsibility</kwd>
<kwd>corporate social performance</kwd>
<kwd>disclosure</kwd>
<kwd>image management</kwd>
<kwd>reputation</kwd>
<kwd>corporate citizenship</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Corporate disclosure is receiving considerable attention from stakeholders as part of the business dialogue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0007650308324047">Dye, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0007650308324047">Pearce &amp; Doh, 2005</xref>). Increased expectations for disclosure have resulted from a number of factors such as: public outcry over high profile corporate scandals; the growing prevalence of reporting mechanisms such as the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0007650308324047">Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development initiatives (1998)</xref>, the Global Reporting Initiative, and triple bottom-line reporting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0007650308324047">Elkington, 1999</xref>); and increased regulatory oversight, such as the Sarbanes–Oxley Act. The hope is that higher levels of disclosure will generate increased diligence and better corporate behavior.</p>
<p>Disclosure is the timely provision of relevant information that results in a transparent and accurate picture of corporate operations, financial performance, and governance. Although researchers differ on the matter, there is considerable evidence of a positive relationship between corporate disclosure and beneficial financial outcomes such as lower cost of debt capital (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0007650308324047">Botosan, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0007650308324047">Diamond &amp; Verrecchia, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-0007650308324047">Sengupta, 1998</xref>), improved liquidity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0007650308324047">Diamond &amp; Verrecchia, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0007650308324047">Krishnamurti, Ševic, &amp; Ševic, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr107-0007650308324047">Welker, 1995</xref>), better price-to-book ratios (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0007650308324047">Patel, Balic, &amp; Bwakira, 2002</xref>), and favorable perceptions of corporate governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0007650308324047">Black, Jang, Kim, &amp; Mark, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0007650308324047">Brounen, Cools, &amp; Schweitzer, 2001</xref>). In addition to its relationship to financial outcomes, disclosure is a means by which stakeholders can evaluate corporate social performance (CSP). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-0007650308324047">Waddock (2004)</xref> opines that globally accepted social, environmental, and financial reporting standards are essential to improving the level of corporate citizenship.</p>
<p>Recently, some researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0007650308324047">Cahan &amp; Malone, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0007650308324047">Gelb &amp; Strawser, 2001</xref>) have attributed a positive relationship between disclosure and CSP to ethical company culture. That is, companies provide information as part of their responsibility to stakeholders, and disclosure is an outgrowth of CSP orientation. The relationship may not, however, be straightforward. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0007650308324047">Near, Baucus, and Miceli (1993)</xref> investigated the impact of corporate values on company practices with respect to wrongdoing, whistle blowing, and retaliation and found the relationship to be weak. In fact, company structures, reward systems, outside pressures, and industry norms can combine to create a gap between company values and actual behavior. The gap between values and behavior contradicts the (seemingly) common sense notion that corporate activity is influenced by corporate culture. An alternative view regarding disclosure is that it enables managers to strategically employ CSP to build competitive advantage. When disclosure is employed strategically, the relationship between CSP and disclosure is strategically developed to enhance the company’s CSP <italic>brand</italic>.</p>
<p>The purpose of this study is to examine the relationship between CSP and annual report disclosure. We first provide the theoretical underpinnings for corporate disclosure, then operationally define CSP and annual report disclosure, then test the relationship between the two constructs, and end with a discussion of the results.</p>
<sec id="section1-0007650308324047">
<title>Literature Review and Development of the Research Question</title>
<sec id="section2-0007650308324047">
<title>Terminology</title>
<p>Corporate social responsibility (CSR) is the set of corporate responsibilities— economic, legal, ethical, and philanthropic—that a company undertakes to coexist favorably with its stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0007650308324047">Carroll, 1991</xref>). Companies meet these responsibilities through CSP, defined as “policies, programs, and observable outcomes that relate to the company’s societal relationships” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr111-0007650308324047">Wood, 1991</xref>, p. 693). Stakeholder theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0007650308324047">Freeman, 1984</xref>) essentially proposes that a company’s relationships with those affected by its policies and actions are the basis of business value. Therefore, it is particularly useful in determining those stakeholders toward which CSP is directed.</p>
<p>Disclosure comprises mandatory and voluntary items. Mandatory disclosure is information required by law or code of practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0007650308324047">Gray, Javad, Power, &amp; Sinclair, 2001</xref>) such as 10K and proxy statements. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr109-0007650308324047">Williams (1999)</xref> noted that the Securities Exchange Commission requires disclosure of information that is material—substantially likely to be considered significant by a reasonable investor. Voluntary disclosure includes information that is not required by the government, but is nonetheless useful for stakeholders.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0007650308324047">1</xref></sup> Consequently, the annual report contains both mandatory and voluntary types of disclosure. The extent of voluntary disclosure has expanded as the annual report moved away from being largely a statutory document concerned with financial stewardship towards a public relations document (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0007650308324047">Bartlett &amp; Jones, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>The annual report is the most representative vehicle of disclosure for a number of reasons: (a) as the primary source of information for investors, it is the most important formal communication that a company has with its stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0007650308324047">Epstein &amp; Freedman, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0007650308324047">Hutchins, 1994</xref>); (b) due to its similarity to audited financial statements, it is perceived to be highly credible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0007650308324047">Neu &amp; Wright, 1992</xref>); (c) it represents a company’s best effort to respond to its stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0007650308324047">Preston, Wright, &amp; Young, 1996</xref>); and (d) because it provides voluntary information in addition to mandatory data, it is a useful indicator of corporate priorities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0007650308324047">Gray et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0007650308324047">
<title>CSP and Disclosure</title>
<p>Research on disclosure and CSP has generally addressed CSP reporting, thereby implying that CSP disclosure differs substantially from financial and operational disclosure. We believe the distinction between disclosure documenting <italic>that profits are generated</italic> (financial reporting) and disclosure documenting <italic>how profits are generated</italic> (CSP reporting) is exaggerated and suggest that financial and social responsibility disclosures are both related to CSP. In making the case that the original intent of federal securities laws was to promote integrity and social accountability, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr109-0007650308324047">Williams (1999)</xref> argues that expanded social disclosure meets the Securities Exchange Commission threshold of being <italic>substantially likely</italic> to be significant to a growing sector of the investing public. Indeed, it is very difficult to separate social issues from operational and financial issues. Social investors attend to corporate disclosure beyond what is required by law but, because today’s social issue can become tomorrow’s financial issue, other stakeholders have reason to be attentive as well.</p>
<p>The recent experience of Dow Chemical Company illustrates the connection between social and financial issues. Dow CEO Andrew Liveris was quoted in the January 27, 2007 issue of <italic>BusinessWeek</italic> saying, “There is 100% overlap between our business drivers and social and environmental interests” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0007650308324047">Engardio, Capell, Carey, &amp; Hall, 2007</xref>) and many of Dow’s shareholders agreed. Five months later at the annual shareholders meeting, groups representing more than 6.6 million shares<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0007650308324047">2</xref></sup> introduced three resolutions voicing serious concerns about the company’s ability to manage risk and reputation. Among their complaints, they alleged that Dow failed to disclose possible material liabilities to investors regarding the lingering Agent Orange<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0007650308324047">3</xref></sup> and the Bhopal<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0007650308324047">4</xref></sup> controversies in previous annual reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0007650308324047">CSPWire, 2007</xref>). The complaint highlighted the relationship between social and financial issues and the need for greater disclosure. Research also suggests that good corporate governance is associated with increased transparency and lucid financial disclosure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0007650308324047">Mallin, 2002</xref>), whereas poor corporate governance and financial statements are closely aligned with poor CSP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0007650308324047">Bhimani &amp; Soonawalla, 2005</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0007650308324047">
<title>Theoretical Framework</title>
<p>Although the levels of disclosure vary, most companies provide some level of disclosure in the annual report that exceeds regulatory requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0007650308324047">Patel &amp; Dallas, 2002</xref>). This voluntary disclosure stems from the need to maintain legitimacy, the agent–principal relationship, and cultural and strategic considerations. Legitimacy and agency theories provide reasons why calls for increased disclosure have become more prevalent. The different approaches to disclosure in relation to CSP are derived from organization culture theory and the resource-based view of corporate strategy.</p>
<sec id="section5-0007650308324047">
<title>Institutional theory</title>
<p>Institutional theorists have emphasized the value of conformity with the institutional environment and adherence to external rules and norms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0007650308324047">DiMaggio &amp; Powell, 1983</xref>). Regulatory bodies, nongovernmental organizations, interest groups, and the public are all institutions that voice expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-0007650308324047">Scott, 1987</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0007650308324047">Donaldson (1982)</xref>, society contracts with companies to comply with institutional norms and requirements as a requisite for approval to operate in the public sphere. The advantages of that compliance include prestige, legitimacy, and social support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0007650308324047">DiMaggio &amp; Powell, 1983</xref>).</p>
<p>To enjoy the benefits of legitimacy, however, companies must also disclose enough about their policies and activities for institutions to determine if they are adhering to the social contract. Increased disclosure reflects a company’s awareness of its responsibility to society and shows the extent to which the company has embraced the prevailing societal values. It is also a means of integrating companies into the institutional fabric of their stakeholder communities and strengthening the social bonds between the companies and their stakeholders. As a result, companies that provide disclosure are viewed to be more legitimate than their counterparts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-0007650308324047">Woodward, Edwards, &amp; Birkin, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>The proliferation of reporting mechanisms (e.g., ISO, Global Reporting Initiative, and Social Accountability 8000) is a reflection of heightened expectations that stakeholders and societal institutions have for disclosure and increases uncertainty in the business environment. Concern about maintaining legitimacy in an ambiguous stakeholder environment results in isomorphism, “the constraining process that forces one unit in a population to resemble other units that face the same set of environmental conditions” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0007650308324047">DiMaggio &amp; Powell, 1983</xref>, p. 149). Thus, corporate disclosure is likely to be characterized by conformity to normative standards established by external institutions or imitation of the practices adopted by competitors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0007650308324047">
<title>Agency theory</title>
<p>Having established that the social contract requires company disclosure, agency theory describes the nature of that accountability. The social contract can be viewed in agent–principal terms whereby the agent acts on behalf of the principal. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0007650308324047">Gray, Owen, and Maunders (1987)</xref> note that under an agency contract—written or implicit—the principal charges the agent with responsibility to take action and to account for the actions taken. The separation of agents from principals can create conflicts of interest because information asymmetries favor the agents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0007650308324047">Eisenhardt, 1989</xref>). Consequently, principals attempt to control unfavorable information asymmetries by closely monitoring the activity of agents through various disclosure mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0007650308324047">Cooke, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0007650308324047">Hossain, Tan, &amp; Adams, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>Disclosure practices are an indication of how companies address agency problems. According to signaling theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-0007650308324047">Spence, 1973</xref>), signals are a reaction to information asymmetries between companies and stakeholders, and companies reduce the asymmetry by providing information. Companies that are characterized by increased disclosure signal to their stakeholders that they are trustworthy and are less likely to be encumbered by regulatory oversight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0007650308324047">Lynxwiler, Shover, &amp; Clelland, 1983</xref>). There is also an emerging stream of literature on how disclosure augments the alignment of agent– principal interests with respect to governance and corporate oversight (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0007650308324047">Frankforter, Davis, Vollrath, &amp; Hill, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-0007650308324047">Rutherford &amp; Buchholtz, 2007</xref>). By using disclosure to serve these purposes, managers of better performing companies can distinguish themselves from their peers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0007650308324047">
<title>Organization culture</title>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-0007650308324047">Schein (1985)</xref>, the deeply held cultural values and beliefs of an organization form the basis for its policies. Two studies have found positive relationships between CSP and disclosure practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0007650308324047">Cahan &amp; Malone, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0007650308324047">Gelb &amp; Strawser, 2001</xref>). The researchers concluded that companies provide increased disclosure because doing so is a reflection of their commitment to CSP. Providing extensive disclosure is also consistent with the view that the underlying ethical values of the company shape a broad range of ostensibly disparate corporate policies. One of the ways that a company derives values and beliefs is through the influence of its executive leaders.</p>
<p>The leadership of a company has great impact on its culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-0007650308324047">Schein, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-0007650308324047">Schneider, 1987</xref>), and the extent to which managers are personally committed to a company’s social priorities is linked to corporate image (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0007650308324047">Elsbach &amp; Sutton, 1992</xref>) and external assessments of CSP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0007650308324047">Bhambri &amp; Sonnenfeld, 1988</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0007650308324047">Miles (1987)</xref> proposed that the social philosophies of executive managers were strongly associated with the companies’ external affairs strategies. More specifically, he argued that companies directed by institutionally oriented leaders—those who pursue adaptive approaches to external influence and believe the company has important effects on society— tend to develop more collaborative approaches to stakeholder issues. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0007650308324047">Meznar and Nigh (1995)</xref> established an empirical relationship between institutionally oriented management and public affairs activities that conformed to external expectations (bridging) rather than resisting external interference (buffering). Thus, it appears that when corporate leaders are motivated by the desire to conform to societal expectations, it is reflected in the disclosure practices of their companies.</p>
<p>The last way that disclosure practices reflect a company’s values is through its operations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0007650308324047">Ball, Robin, and Wu (2003)</xref> established that disclosure practices evolve as complementary dimensions of corporate infrastructure because of the impact of incentives and political pressures. In the same way, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-0007650308324047">Thomas (1989)</xref> found that company culture—exemplified by the accounting method, symbols, and language used in the annual report—was associated with the extent of financial disclosure. These studies support the broad conclusion of researchers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0007650308324047">Brammer &amp; Pavelin, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0007650308324047">Lang &amp; Lundholm, 1993</xref>) that companies develop a general posture towards disclosure such that increased disclosure in one area of operation leads to increased disclosure in other areas as well.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0007650308324047">
<title>CSP, strategy, and disclosure</title>
<p>The strategic approach to CSP and information disclosure provides an alternative to the view that disclosure is undertaken as a result of ethical culture. There are a number of studies centered on the resource-based view that demonstrate a link between CSP and competitive advantage (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0007650308324047">Barney &amp; Hansen, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0007650308324047">Branco &amp; Rodrigues, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0007650308324047">Mackey, Mackey, &amp; Barney, 2007</xref>). According to the resource-based view, a competitive advantage can be attained if a company uses an asset to create value and that asset is not available to its competitors. CSP is a strategic asset because it augments an organization’s social legitimacy. In turn, social legitimacy strengthens the company’s competitive advantage among key stakeholders such as prospective workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0007650308324047">Greening &amp; Turban, 2000</xref>) and consumers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0007650308324047">Mohr, Webb, &amp; Harris, 2001</xref>). To achieve these benefits, however, CSP must be strategically integrated throughout a company’s operations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr108-0007650308324047">Werther &amp; Chandler, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Favorable CSP contributes to competitive advantage through its impact on three mediating variables: reputation, stakeholder influence capacity, and moral capital. Corporate reputation is a cognitive representation of a company’s actions and results that crystallizes its ability to deliver valued outcomes to its stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0007650308324047">Fombrun &amp; Shanley, 1990</xref>), and reputation mediates the relationship between CSP and profitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0007650308324047">Gardberg &amp; Fombrun, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0007650308324047">2006</xref>). Consequently, a company that exhibits favorable CSP builds goodwill over and above its stock of patents and know-how that attracts customers, investors, and employees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0007650308324047">Fombrun, 1996</xref>). Because CSP can help to differentiate a company by building its brand and reputation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0007650308324047">Fombrun, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0007650308324047">McWilliams &amp; Siegel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-0007650308324047">Waddock &amp; Graves, 1997</xref>), it is important to adopt a pattern of disclosure that enables a company to capitalize on the asset.</p>
<p>The second mediator between CSP and financial performance is stakeholder influence capacity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0007650308324047">Barnett (2007)</xref> describes stakeholder influence capacity—the ability of a company to identify, act on, and profit from opportunities to improve stakeholder relationships through CSP—as an aggregate representation of how stakeholders perceive the character of the company. As companies engage in CSP actions, such as compliance with institutional norms and requirements, a record of social responsibility accrues that increases stakeholder influence capacity. Disclosure is likely to moderate the relationship between CSP and stakeholder influence capacity because, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0007650308324047">Godfrey (2005)</xref>, the impact of CSP is greatest when there is evidence of its impact on social welfare.</p>
<p>If favorable CSP adds to strategic advantage and stakeholder influence capacity, why not simply increase disclosure when the circumstances are favorable to the company? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0007650308324047">Godfrey (2005)</xref> proposes that, because stakeholders have become more wary about the motives of CSP, it is important for companies to avoid the appearance of ingratiation. Therefore, companies should publicly disclose the details of their philanthropic activities, including levels of funding, objectives, and the targets of their activities, but the disclosure must be a part of timely, regular disclosure, and not seen as after the fact. When companies are transparent with respect to their philanthropy they generate moral capital, a perception derived from the broad assessment and evaluation of a company’s philanthropic activities.</p>
<p>Hence, CSP can lead to competitive advantage if a company is able to focus stakeholders’ attention on that resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0007650308324047">Mackey et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-0007650308324047">Teece, Pisano, &amp; Shuen, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-0007650308324047">2000</xref>) and increased disclosure is one way for companies to accomplish that objective. Increased disclosure has the potential to influence social legitimacy and stakeholder perceptions, which in turn affect economic performance, but only to the extent that stakeholders are aware of what the company is doing. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0007650308324047">Godfrey’s (2005)</xref> characterization of effective philanthropy highlights the role of reputation and stakeholder influence capacity in CSP and disclosure—favorable CSP activities must be part of ongoing pattern of disclosure. If a company has <italic>a story to tell</italic> then a record of consistently thorough disclosure can enhance its reputation, ability to influence stakeholders, and moral capital.</p>
<p>There are then four basic reasons for companies to provide increased disclosure. First, disclosure is necessary to maintain legitimacy with institutional stakeholders. Second, through disclosure stakeholders receive an additional measure of accountability in the agent–principal relationship. Third, disclosure is a reflection of corporate values and priorities. Finally, CSP is a resource that can be leveraged into competitive advantage through disclosure.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0007650308324047">
<title>Research Question</title>
<p>To address the relationship of CSP and annual report disclosure, CSP should be characterized with regard to two different, but related, constructs—CSP level and CSP dimension. A company’s global CSP rating (which is a composite index) will be referred to as <italic>CSP level</italic> and a company’s rating with respect to particular components of CSP (e.g., social, financial, or environmental) will be referred to as <italic>CSP dimension</italic>. This distinction between level and dimension is necessary and important for two reasons. First, CSP is not always—or perhaps even generally—evaluated in a compensatory manner. That is, positive and negative dimensions always do not offset one another. For example, Oxfam once dismissed philanthropic giving by pharmaceutical companies as (relatively unimportant) <italic>islands of philanthropy</italic> amid broader corporate policies that consigned millions to suffer unnecessarily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0007650308324047">Oxfam, 2001</xref>). The social component of CSP, typified as accessibility to medications, generated an unfavorable global perception of CSP that was not mitigated by philanthropy or favorable performance in financial or environmental areas of operation.</p>
<p>Second, because CSP is multidimensional, the relative impact of perceptions of particular CSP components on the global perception of CSP and the inconsistencies between the global perception of CSP and the perceptions of particular components of CSP may be less apparent. Although activities directed to separate components of CSP are indeed reflected in the global CSP level, those components contribute to the global CSP level in different ways. Hence, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0007650308324047">Griffin and Mahon (1997)</xref> note that favorable outcomes on one component of CSP can obscure unfavorable outcomes on another. Wal-Mart was praised for its efforts to help survivors in the wake of Hurricane Katrina, but concurrently faced numerous wage and hour lawsuits and the largest gender bias lawsuit in history. Philanthropy and the treatment of workers are two separate components of CSP that must be reconciled to develop a global assessment of CSP at Wal-Mart. Consequently, separating the global CSP level of companies from assessment of specific CSP components can provide a more complete picture of CSP. As detailed later, we sum the positive and negative ratings on the components of CSP typically used in CSP research (social, environmental, financial, worker relations, community relations) to form two CSP dimensions—CSP strength and CSP weakness. However, this summing occurs across only positive or across only negative dimensions. We do not attempt to aggregate positive and negative dimensions together.</p>
<p>Our premise is that, although it is likely all companies will have positive and negative CSP results to disclose (or conceal) on different components of CSP, companies with lower levels of CSP will have fewer positives and more negatives in that regard. Thus, it might be expected that companies with high levels of CSP will draw attention to their diligence through increased disclosure of their business operations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0007650308324047">Neu, Warsame, &amp; Pedwell, 1998</xref>). Although companies with lower levels of CSP will have less favorable information to disclose, institutional pressures bring about increased disclosure as well. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0007650308324047">Deegan and Gordon (1996)</xref> determined that the extent of corporate environmental disclosure was positively associated with environmental lobby groups’ concerns about environmental performance. A similar study found that, following environmental catastrophes, companies operating in the affected industries increased their annual report disclosure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0007650308324047">Deegan, Rankin, &amp; Voght, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Consequently, a company that was roundly criticized for CSP lapses in the past (e.g., Nike) can later become a CSP leader. After company practices are challenged, it can respond with heightened levels of disclosure in order to maintain legitimacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0007650308324047">Brown &amp; Deegan, 1998</xref>). The pharmaceutical industry was castigated for resisting the production of generic HIV/AIDS medications for Sub-Saharan Africa and, after relenting, began to emphasize product donations (e.g., Mectizan for river blindness) and other philanthropic activities (e.g., partnership for prescription assistance) in their corporate disclosures. In the same way, after settling a racial discrimination lawsuit in 2001, Coca-Cola agreed to provide regular, publicly accessible updates regarding its diversity efforts and human resource management policies.</p>
<p>There is also a risk–reward calculation that can be employed with respect to annual report disclosure regardless of CSP level. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-0007650308324047">Skinner (1994)</xref> established that managers’ perceive an asymmetric loss function with respect to their disclosure practices. That is, the negative repercussions for stakeholders receiving unexpected bad news about their companies exceed the possible benefits of stakeholders receiving unexpected good news. When stakeholders raise issues themselves, they become more polarized in their positions and less likely to compromise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0007650308324047">Cole, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0007650308324047">Grunig &amp; Hunt, 1984</xref>). For that reason, it may be prudent for companies to adopt a preemptive disclosure strategy regarding bad news (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0007650308324047">Pownall, Wasley, &amp; Waymire, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0007650308324047">Fombrun and Gardberg (2000)</xref> characterize two basic ways to manage CSP risk and reward, operational platforms and safety nets. When CSP is used to develop a favorable operational platform, its value is in creating potential for future gains, whereas a CSP safety net buffers against downside risk to reputation by mitigating the threats. Whether a company chooses to use CSP as an operational platform or a safety net may be influenced by CSP level. Companies with lower CSP levels have more unflattering news to disclose and can frame their disclosure practices to augment CSP safety nets that diminish losses to reputation. Although companies with favorable CSP have better information to disclosure, they have a different reason for employing the safety net strategy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-0007650308324047">Rhee and Haunschild (2006)</xref> examined the effects of automobile recalls on reputation and found that consumers judged recalls from companies with favorable reputations more harshly than recalls from lesser companies. Consider the controversy that surrounded The Body Shop when the legitimacy of its social activism, which was employed as an operational platform, was called into question.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0007650308324047">5</xref></sup> Favorable CSP level is, therefore, a “two-edged sword” that contributes to heightened expectations for performance by stakeholders.</p>
<p>In view of the literature examined here, we conclude that there is no straightforward case to be made for the relationship between CSP and annual report disclosure. Rather than ethical company culture leading to disclosure, or high-level CSP companies disclosing information and low-level CSP companies concealing information, there may be an asymmetrical association between CSP and disclosure. Because companies must make strategic decisions regarding disclosure policy that entail the CSP whole (CSP level) <italic>and</italic> its parts (CSP dimensions), the nuanced relationship is likely to be reflected in companies’ disclosure practices. That is, companies that are broadly perceived to exhibit favorable CSP must determine how to address dimensions of CSP where theirs records are less favorable. Conversely, companies that are broadly perceived to exhibit poor CSP must determine how to showcase dimensions of CSP where their record is favorable. These strategic considerations make it likely that in addition to direct effects on disclosure, CSP level and CSP dimension interact to influence disclosure, but the nature of the interaction is unclear. Thus, we will address the following research question:</p>
<list id="list1-0007650308324047" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Research Question: What is the nature of the relationship between CSP and annual report disclosure?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0007650308324047" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section11-0007650308324047">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>The sample for this study consists of 217 S&amp;P 500 companies (divided into 148 low CSP and 69 high CSP companies). The CSP strength and weakness dimensions, treated as the two independent variables, were composed of CSP ratings on various components from Kinder, Lydenberg, and Domini (KLD). We term these two dimensions as <italic>CSP strength</italic> and <italic>CSP weakness</italic> (or <italic>concern</italic>). The moderator variable, <italic>CSP level</italic>, had low and high levels derived from two sets of company rankings: the 100 Best Corporate Citizens and the KLD DS 400 index of socially responsive companies. S&amp;P 500 companies with global CSP ratings that place them in the 100 Best Corporate Citizens (<italic>n</italic> = 69) are a proxy for high CSP level and companies with global CSP ratings that precluded them from being including in the DS 400 (<italic>n</italic> = 148)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0007650308324047">6</xref></sup> are a proxy for low CSP level. Disclosure ratings from the S&amp;P disclosure study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0007650308324047">Patel &amp; Dallas, 2002</xref>) were used to calculate the values for annual report disclosure, the dependent variable.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0007650308324047">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section13-0007650308324047">
<title>Corporate social performance</title>
<p>First, we will detail the development of the CSP dimension independent variables and then describe the development of the moderator and dependent variables. KLD specializes in CSP analysis and rankings and maintains the largest multidimensional CSP database available to the public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0007650308324047">KLD Analytics, 2007a</xref>). The advantages of the KLD ratings are that they (a) use an objective set of evaluative criteria (b) are consistently applied across companies by a specialized independent staff (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0007650308324047">Graves &amp; Waddock, 1994</xref>), and (c) have been widely used in CSP research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0007650308324047">Dawkins, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0007650308324047">Johnson &amp; Greening, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-0007650308324047">Waddock, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>KLD employs a wide variety of company, government, nongovernmental organization, and media sources to track each company in its database daily. Companies are rated on nine components of CSP, five of which have been frequently used for research purposes: (a) <italic>community</italic> addresses matters such as giving and support for housing and education; (b) <italic>diversity</italic> addresses hiring, contracting, advancement, and so on with respect to female, disabled, and minority populations; (c) <italic>employee relations</italic> addresses matters such as labor union practices; (d) <italic>environment</italic> addresses impact on pollution levels and climate among other issues; and (e) <italic>product</italic> addresses quality and safety of products and services.</p>
<p>The data presented in KLD ratings consist of <italic>strength</italic> and <italic>concern</italic> (which we have termed <italic>weakness</italic>) item ratings on each of the evaluative components listed above. In each case, if KLD assigned a rating on a particular component (either strength or weakness) it is indicated with a rating of 1. If the company had neither a strength nor weakness on a given component, this eventuality was indicated with a rating of 0. In the event that a component of performance was not covered in a particular year, this eventuality was indicated as NR (not rated) or NA (not available) respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0007650308324047">KLD Analytics, 2007b</xref>).</p>
<p>To avoid strengths and weakness offsetting one another, we summed the KLD rating of strengths and weaknesses across the five components to develop two CSP dimension independent variables, which were labeled CSP strength and CSP weakness. Because the numbers of items used to evaluate the components of CSP differ,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0007650308324047">7</xref></sup> we insured evenly weighted component scores by converting the component rating totals to <italic>z</italic> scores before summing them into two CSP dimension scores. Examples of the questions comprising the five KLD components measured for this study are provided in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-0007650308324047">Appendix A</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0007650308324047">
<title>Group composition</title>
<p>The moderator variable, CSP level, was developed by dividing the sample into two groups: high CSP companies that demonstrate favorable global CSP rankings and low CSP companies with pedestrian global CSP rankings. The technique of dividing into low- and high-performing groups to determine the factors that differentiate the two groups has been used in a number of studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0007650308324047">Felfe &amp; Schyns, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0007650308324047">Garry, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-0007650308324047">Sun, Wang, Zhang, &amp; Li, 2007</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0007650308324047">Pothukuchi (2008)</xref> divided a sample of workers into two groups exhibiting either poor or good time-management skills to determine if time-management skills moderated the impact of personality on creativity. As noted previously, we used companies selected as the 100 Best Corporate Citizens in 2002 as a proxy for high CSP and companies excluded from the DSI 400 in 2002 as a proxy for low CSP.</p>
<p>The 100 Best Corporate Citizens list is a ranking of leading CSP companies that is published by <italic>Corporate Responsibility Officer</italic> magazine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0007650308324047">KLD.com, 2007</xref>). The scoring system ranks companies according to the KLD environmental and social categories described above and annualized 3-year shareholder return.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0007650308324047">8</xref></sup> Being included in the 100 Best Corporate Citizens is a highly prized distinction, and the listing has been widely used in academic research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0007650308324047">Liston-Heyes &amp; Ceton, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0007650308324047">Luo &amp; Bhattacharya, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-0007650308324047">Radin, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-0007650308324047">Schaefer, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>KLD developed the DS 400 as an index of socially and environmentally friendly companies. In this capacity, the DS 400 excludes companies that do not have favorable CSP in relation to their respective industries and the broader market. The S&amp;P 500 companies excluded from the DS 400 serve as a proxy for low CSP level. Although there is overlap between the KLD and the 100 Best Corporate Citizens rating methods, the latter ranks companies and identifies the top 100. Consequently, contrasting the 100 best companies with those that are excluded from KLDs listing of socially and environmentally screened companies provides a clear distinction between high and low CSP levels. This distinction enables an examination of the differences in disclosure that are central to this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0007650308324047">
<title>Annual report disclosure</title>
<p>The transparency and disclosure ratings developed from the <italic>Standard &amp; Poor’s Transparency and Disclosure Study</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0007650308324047">Patel et al., 2002</xref>) constitute the dependent variable for this study, which was labeled <italic>annual report disclosure</italic>. These ratings were part of an extensive study covering approximately 1,500 companies from around the world and have been widely used in the financial and accounting literatures (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0007650308324047">Bae, Lim, &amp; Wei, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0007650308324047">Huang, Cheng, &amp; Collins, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0007650308324047">Khanna, Palepu, &amp; Srinivasan, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0007650308324047">Patel et al., 2002</xref>). The study methodology involved assessment of 98 disclosure attributes that were divided into three categories: ownership structure and investor rights (28 attributes), financial transparency and information disclosure (35 attributes), and management structure and process (35 attributes).</p>
<p>To increase objectivity, the S&amp;P study employed binary ratings focused only on the presence of particular attributes rather than assessing the quality of the information provided. The final ratings were an aggregate disclosure rating for all three categories and, as with the CSP components, we transformed the three areas of questions to <italic>z</italic> scores before summing them to form the annual report disclosure scores. The overall ratings reflect the ratio of the number of attributes present in a given company to the total number of attributes assessed. A more thorough description of what is entailed in the transparency and disclosure categories and a sample of the questions used are provided in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app2-0007650308324047">Appendix B</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0007650308324047">
<title>Control variables</title>
<p>Previous research has indicated that performance, size, and industry can affect disclosure practices and CSP ratings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0007650308324047">Bushman, Piotroski, &amp; Smith, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0007650308324047">Graves &amp; Waddock, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0007650308324047">Patten, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-0007650308324047">Roberts, 1992</xref>); hence, we formed additional independent variables as control variables. Performance was measured by using the return on assets and size was determined on the basis of total assets. The variables used to represent these performance and size measures are labeled <italic>performance</italic> and <italic>size</italic>, respectively.</p>
<p>To adjust for possible industry effects on CSP ratings, we created a series of dummy variables representing eight industries. We placed companies into industry groups by using the 2-digit Standard Industrial Classification codes, but because the S&amp;P 500 is heavily populated with companies in the manufacturing Standard Industrial Classification code, this could lead to classifying the industries in a manner that could confound the results. Therefore, we combined similar types of manufacturing companies into three separate categories. The result was the following eight categories for the <italic>industry</italic> variable: mining and construction (10-19), diversified manufacturing (20-33), machinery and transportation equipment (34, 35, and 37), electronic and electrical equipment (36, 38, and 39), transportation, communications, and utilities (40-49), wholesale and retail trade (50-59), finance, insurance and real estate (60-69), and services (70-89). We labeled the eight dichotomous variables used to represent these eight industrial categories as industry 1 through industry 8. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0007650308324047">Table 1</xref> provides the number of companies from each industry that are included in the analyses. All data were collected from 2002 and the companies averaged 45,684 employees, return on assets of 8.19%, and total assets of $27,703 million.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0007650308324047" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Composition of Sample by Industry (N = 217).</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0007650308324047" xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Industry (SIC Code)</th>
<th align="center">Low CSR Companies</th>
<th align="center">High CSR Companies</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Mining and construction (10-19)</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Diversified manufacturing (20-29)</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Machinery and transportation equipment (30-34)</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Electronic, electrical equipment, and components (35-39)</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Transportation, communications, electric, gas, and sanitary services (40-49)</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Wholesale and retail trade (50-59)</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. Finance, insurance, and real estate (60-67)</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8. Services (70-89)</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0007650308324047">
<title>Interaction variables</title>
<p>The research question posed in this study raises the possibility that CSR level modified the relationships between the two CSR dimensions and annual report disclosure. As detailed later, such a modification requires interaction effects to exist between the CSP level and the CSR strength and weakness dimensions and the dependent variable, annual report disclosure. To statistically test these interaction effects, four interaction variables were generated as follows:</p>
<list id="list2-0007650308324047" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The variable labeled high CSP × strength was the product of the high CSP and CSP strength variables.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The variable labeled high CSP × weakness was the product of the high CSP and CSP weakness variables.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The variable labeled low CSP × strength was the product of the low CSP and CSP strength variables.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The variable labeled low CSP × weakness was the product of the low CSP and CSP weakness variables.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0007650308324047" sec-type="results">
<title>Analysis and Results</title>
<sec id="section19-0007650308324047">
<title>Analytic Technique Used to Test Research Questions</title>
<p>The mean and standard deviation values of the control variables (size, performance, and industry), the independent variables (CSP strength and CSP weakness), and the dependent variable (annual report disclosure) are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0007650308324047">Table 2</xref>. There were a number of significant correlations that will be summarized here. Among the control variables, there were significant correlations between machinery and transportation equipment and finance, insurance, and real estate classifications and each of the other classifications. In addition, the machinery and transportation and finance, insurance, and real estate classifications were correlated with CSP weakness. None of the other control variables were significantly correlated with the independent or dependent variables. CSP strength and weakness were positively correlated, and CSP strength was positively correlated with annual report disclosure.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0007650308324047" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Means, Standard Deviations, and Correlation Matrix.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0007650308324047" xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
<th align="center">6</th>
<th align="center">7</th>
<th align="center">8</th>
<th align="center">9</th>
<th align="center">10</th>
<th align="center">11</th>
<th align="center">12</th>
<th align="center">13</th>
<th align="center">14</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Size</td>
<td>4.56</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Performance</td>
<td>13.16</td>
<td>11.99</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Industry 1</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Industry 2</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Industry 3</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>−.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Industry 4</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>−.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>−.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>−.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. Industry 5</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>−.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8. Industry 6</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9. Industry 7</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>−.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>−.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>−.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>−.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10. Industry 8</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.13</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11. CSP weakness</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>2.80</td>
<td>−.13</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12. CSP strength</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>2.95</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13. Low CSR level</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>−.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14. High CSR level</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>−.17</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−1.00</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15. Annual report disclosure</td>
<td>−0.20</td>
<td>2.44</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.03</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0007650308324047">
<p><italic>Note.</italic> CSP = corporate social performance, <italic>N</italic> = 217; high CSP group, <italic>N</italic> = 138; low CSP group, <italic>N</italic> = 79.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0007650308324047">
<label>*</label>
<p>Significant at the .05 level (two-tailed). **Significant at the .01 level (two-tailed).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section20-0007650308324047">
<title>Multiple linear regression models</title>
<p>The research question is: what is the nature of the relationship between CSP and annual report disclosure? The model diagrammed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0007650308324047">Figure 1</xref> is derived from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0007650308324047">Baron and Kenny (1986)</xref> and illustrates three causal paths to annual report disclosure that arise from the research question: <italic>Path a</italic>, CSP dimension (strength/weakness) as a predictor; <italic>Path b</italic>, CSP level (low/high) as a moderator; and <italic>Path c</italic>, the interaction or product of CSP dimension and CSP level. CSP level moderates the relationship between CSP dimension and annual report disclosure if the interaction between CSP dimension and CSP level (path c) is significant. There may also be significant main effects for CSP dimension and CSP level (Paths a and b).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0007650308324047" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>CSP Dimension, CSP Level, and Annual Report Disclosure.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Three multiple linear regression models were designed and analyzed to address the three paths in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0007650308324047">Figure 1</xref>. In each of these models annual report disclosure was the dependent variable and size, performance and industry classification were control variables. Model 1 was designed and analyzed to determine whether statistically significant relationships existed between the CSP strength and weakness dimensions and annual report disclosure and between CSP level and annual report disclosure, which are represented by Paths <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0007650308324047">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<p>Model 2 was designed and analyzed to determine whether the relationships between the CSP strength and weakness dimensions analyzed in Model 1 were modified by CSP level (low and high CSP companies), which is illustrated by path c in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0007650308324047">Figure 1</xref>. Such modifications required the interaction effects between the CSP strength dimension and CSP level and between CSP weakness dimension and CSP level to be significant. The tests of these interaction effects were conducted by adding the product of the moderator variable (CSP level) and each CSP dimension variable (CSP strength and CSP weakness variable) to the regression model, a procedure used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0007650308324047">Baron and Kenny (1986)</xref>. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0007650308324047">Figure 1</xref>, if the CSP dimension independent variable is denoted as <italic>x</italic>, and the CSP level moderator independent variable is labeled <italic>z</italic>, and the dependent variable annual report disclosure is identified as <italic>y; y</italic> is regressed on <italic>x</italic>, and <italic>xz</italic>. Moderator effects are indicated by the significant effect of <italic>xz</italic> while <italic>x</italic> and <italic>z</italic> are controlled.</p>
<p>Lastly, if the interaction effects in Model 2 are significant, an additional model labeled Model 3 is required to test which of the four distinct relationships is statistically significant. Specifically, significant interactions effects would indicate that the relationship between the CSP strength dimension and annual report disclosure for the low CSP companies differed from the relationship between the CSP strength dimension and annual report disclosure for the high CSP companies. In addition, significant interactions effects would indicate that the relationship between the CSP weakness dimension and annual report disclosure for the low CSP companies differed from the relationship between the CSP weakness dimension and annual report disclosure for the high CSP companies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0007650308324047">
<title>Analysis of Model 1</title>
<p>As previously stated, one purpose of Model 1 was to determine whether statistically significant relationships existed between the CSP strength and weakness dimensions and annual report disclosure. It is important to note that these relationships were assumed not to be modified by the CSP level of the companies. The second purpose of Model 1 was to determine whether a statistically significant relationship existed between CSP level and annual report disclosure.</p>
<p>If the relationships between the CSP strength and weakness dimensions and annual report disclosure were <italic>not</italic> modified by CSP level, separate regression lines for the two CSP levels were not needed. Thus, these relationships can be estimated and assessed with one regression line for the CSP strength dimension and another regression line for the CSP weakness dimension. The slopes of the regression lines for the CSP strength and weakness dimensions were estimated by the coefficients for the CSP strength variable and the CSP weakness variable, respectively. The coefficient for the dichotomous CSP level variable estimated the difference between the annual report disclosure means of the high CSP companies and the low CSP companies, adjusted for the other independent variables included in the model. If CSP level is related to the annual report disclosure, the difference between the two adjusted means must be statistically significant.</p>
<p>We used <italic>t</italic> tests of the CSP strength and CSP weakness dimension coefficients to determine if their respective relationships with annual report disclosure were statistically significant. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0007650308324047">Table 3</xref>, the estimated coefficients for the CSP strength variable (0.11) and CSP weakness variable (0.03) were positive. However, the two-tailed probability levels of the <italic>t</italic> tests of the CSP strength coefficient (<italic>p</italic> = .02) and the CSP weakness coefficient (<italic>p</italic> = .17) indicated that only the positive CSP strength coefficient was significant at the .05 α level. Thus, the relationship between the CSP strength dimension and annual report disclosure, which was not modified by the CSP levels of the companies, was positive and statistically significant, but the unmodified positive relationship between the CSP weakness dimension and annual report disclosure was not statistically significant.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0007650308324047" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Summary of Regression Analyses: Model 1.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0007650308324047">a</xref></sup></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0007650308324047" xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="center">Coefficient</th>
<th align="center">Standard Error</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Control</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Performance</td>
<td>−0.36</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>−1.03</td>
<td>.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Size</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>.98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 1</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.67</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 2</td>
<td>−0.37</td>
<td>1.10</td>
<td>−0.34</td>
<td>.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 3</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 4</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>−0.31</td>
<td>.76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 5</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>−0.41</td>
<td>.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 6</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 7</td>
<td>−0.61</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>−0.87</td>
<td>.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Corporate social responsibility</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP level<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0007650308324047">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP strength</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP weakness</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>.94</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0007650308324047">
<p><italic>Note.</italic> CSP = corporate social performance, Model 1: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .04, <italic>F</italic>(11, 205) = .72, <italic>p</italic> = .72.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0007650308324047">
<label>a.</label>
<p>Dependent variable: Annual report disclosure.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0007650308324047">
<label>b.</label>
<p>To account for CSP level (low/high) only the value of the high CSP variable was included because the dichotomous low and high CSP variables are linearly dependent. Thus, only one of the variables was necessary.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0007650308324047">
<label>*</label>
<p>Coefficient is significant at the .05 level (two-tailed).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The coefficient for the CSP level variable was 0.11, which indicates that the mean value for annual report disclosure is .11 higher for the high CSP level companies than for the low CSP level companies. This coefficient value, however, was not statistically significant at the .05 level (<italic>p</italic> = .79). Thus, the relationship between CSP level and annual report disclosure was not statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0007650308324047">
<title>Analysis of Model 2</title>
<p>The purpose of Model 2 was to determine whether the low and high CSP levels of the companies modified the relationships between CSP dimension and annual report disclosure. The CSP strength variable and the CSP (level × strength) variable were included in Model 2 to provide an estimate of the <italic>difference</italic> between the regression line slopes of the high and low CSP companies that depicted the relationship between CSP strength and annual report disclosure. Similarly, the CSP weakness variable and the CSP (level × weakness) variable were included to provide an estimate of the difference between the slopes of the low and high CSP level regression lines depicting the relationship between CSP weakness and annual report disclosure. This analytic technique is discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0007650308324047">McNeil, Newman, and Kelly (1996)</xref>.</p>
<p>With the inclusion of these two sets of variables, the coefficient for the CSP strength variable estimated the slope of the regression line for the low CSP level group, whereas the coefficient for the CSP level × strength variable estimated the <italic>difference</italic> between the slopes of the regression lines for the low and high CSP companies. In the same way, the coefficient for the high CSP weakness variable estimated the slope of the regression line for the high CSP level group, whereas the coefficient for the high CSP level × weakness variable estimated the difference between the slopes of the regression lines for the high and low CSP level groups. The two-tailed <italic>t</italic> tests of the CSP level × strength variable and CSP level × weakness coefficients were used to determine if CSP level significantly modified the relationship between the CSP strength and weakness dimensions and annual report disclosure.</p>
<p>As displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0007650308324047">Table 4</xref>, the coefficient for the CSP level × strength variable (−0.38) indicated that the slope for the high CSP companies was 0.38 lower than the slope for the low CSP companies. Subsequently, the two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test of this coefficient revealed that it was statistically significant (<italic>t</italic> = −3.00, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). Thus, CSP level did significantly modify the relationship between CSP strength and annual report disclosure. The coefficient for the CSP level × weakness variable (0.31) indicated that the slope for the high CSP companies was 0.31 higher than the slope for the low CSP companies. The two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test of this coefficient revealed that this coefficient was also statistically significant (<italic>t</italic> = 1.99, <italic>p</italic> = .05). Thus, CSP level significantly modified the relationships between both the CSP strength and weakness dimensions and annual report disclosure.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0007650308324047" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Summary of Regression Analyses: Models 2 and 3.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0007650308324047">a</xref></sup></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0007650308324047" xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="center">Coefficient</th>
<th align="center">Standard Error</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Control</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Performance</td>
<td>−0.36</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>−1.03</td>
<td>.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Size</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>−0.07</td>
<td>.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0007650308324047">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>.76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 2</td>
<td>−0.25</td>
<td>1.09</td>
<td>−0.23</td>
<td>.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 3</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 4</td>
<td>−0.29</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>−0.40</td>
<td>.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 5</td>
<td>−0.19</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>−0.24</td>
<td>.81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 6</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>−0.01</td>
<td>.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Industry 7</td>
<td>−0.45</td>
<td>0.69</td>
<td>−0.65</td>
<td>.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Model 2: Corporate social performance (CSP)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP level<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0007650308324047">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>.97</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP strength</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>&lt;.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP weakness</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP level × strength</td>
<td>−0.38</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>−3.00</td>
<td>&lt;.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP level × weakness</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>1.99</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Model 3: CSP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CSP Level<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0007650308324047">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>.97</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Low CSP × strength</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>&lt;.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0007650308324047">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  High CSP × strength</td>
<td>−0.17</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>−1.62</td>
<td>.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Low CSP × weakness</td>
<td>−0.02</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  High CSP × weakness</td>
<td>0.29</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td>2.05</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0007650308324047">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>1.65</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>.93</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0007650308324047">
<p>Models 2 and 3: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .08; <italic>F</italic>(14, 202) = 1.30, <italic>p</italic> = .21.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0007650308324047">
<label>a.</label>
<p>Dependent variable: Annual report disclosure.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-0007650308324047">
<label>b.</label>
<p>The industry classifications consisted of a series of eight dichotomous variables and because these variables were linearly dependent, only seven of the eight variables were entered into each model.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn10-0007650308324047">
<label>c.</label>
<p>To account for CSP level (low/high) in each of the models only the value of the high CSP variable was included because the dichotomous low and high CSP variables are linearly dependent. Thus, only one of the variables was necessary.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn11-0007650308324047">
<label>*</label>
<p>Coefficient is significant at the .05 level (two-tailed). **Coefficient is significant at the .01 level (two-tailed).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0007650308324047">
<title>Analysis of Model 3</title>
<p>Because the analysis of Model 2 indicated that the relationships between the CSP strength and weakness dimensions and annual report disclosure were modified by CSP level, we conducted follow-up tests to determine whether the four distinct relationships were statistically significant. That is, we determined if each of the four regression line slopes differed from 0. For the strength dimension of CSP, the slope for the low CSP companies was estimated by the low CSP × strength coefficient and the slope for the high CSP companies was estimated by the high CSP × strength coefficient. Likewise, for the weakness dimension of CSP, the slope for the low CSP companies was estimated by the low CSP × weakness coefficient and the slope for the high CSP companies was estimated by the high CSP × weakness coefficient. Two-tailed <italic>t</italic> tests were used to determine if these coefficients were statistically significant.</p>
<p>The results of the analysis of Model 3 are also provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0007650308324047">Table 4</xref>. The coefficient for the low CSP × strength variable was 0.21, and the relationship between CSP strength and annual report disclosure for the low CSP companies was positive and statistically significant (<italic>t</italic> = 3.00, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). The coefficient for the high CSP × strength variable was −0.17, indicating that the relationship between the CSP strength and annual report disclosure variables for the high CSP companies was negative, but the relationship was not statistically significant (<italic>t</italic> = −1.62, <italic>p</italic> = .11). Consequently, the positive relationship between CSP strength and annual report disclosure was statistically significant only for the low CSP companies.</p>
<p>The coefficient for the low CSP × weakness variable was −0.02, indicating that the relationship between CSP strength and annual report disclosure for the low CSP companies was negative and not statistically significant (<italic>t</italic> = −0.31, <italic>p</italic> = .75). The coefficient for the high CSP × weakness variable was 0.29, which indicated a positive relationship between CSP weakness and annual report disclosure for the high CSP companies and was statistically significant (<italic>t</italic> = 2.05, <italic>p</italic> = .05). Thus, the positive relationship between the CSP weakness and annual report disclosure was statistically significant only for the high CSP companies.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0007650308324047" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The above analysis yields three findings that, taken together, suggest that companies strategically link their CSP and disclosure practices. An initial analysis of the data revealed that a direct positive relationship existed between CSP strengths and disclosure, but not between CSP weakness and disclosure. This first finding suggests that all companies, without regard to their global CSP rating, have annual report disclosure that complements their CSP strengths. Further analyses, however, revealed that the relationships between CSP strengths and disclosure on the one hand, and between CSP weakness and disclosure on the other were dependent on the CSP level of the companies.</p>
<p>With respect to CSP weaknesses, there was a positive relationship between annual report disclosure for the top CSP companies, but not for the companies with lower global CSP ratings. In addition, the results indicate that a positive relationship existed between CSP strengths and annual report disclosure for companies with lower global CSP, but not for CSP leaders. Thus, the way that a company coordinates its disclosure to complement its CSP strengths or weaknesses differs depending on the company’s global CSP brand.</p>
<p>The positive relationship between CSP strengths and annual report disclosure provides an alternative to the notion that disclosure emanates from commitment to the principles of corporate social responsibility as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0007650308324047">Cahan and Malone (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0007650308324047">Gelb and Strawser (2001)</xref>. These results indicate that annual report disclosure was not associated with all components of CSP as would be expected if an ethical commitment to corporate social responsibility motivated the disclosure. The dissimilar findings may, however, be attributable to methodological differences. In addition to the annual report, the Gelb and Strawser disclosure variable included voluntarily published reports and investor relations materials that were not included in this study. Moreover, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0007650308324047">Gelb and Strawser (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0007650308324047">Cahan and Malone (1995)</xref> studies used a measure of CSR that was composed of Council of Economic Priorities’ ratings on diversity, community, and philanthropy. Thus, there was no consideration of the employee relations and natural environment categories of CSP provided in the KLD ratings.</p>
<p>Notably, the relationship between disclosure and CSP strengths was not significantly different for leading CSP companies than for their competitors. The lack of significance is inconsistent with what could be expected given the resource-based view of CSP, but perhaps having annual report disclosure that is aligned with CSP weakness is beneficial to leading CSP companies as well. Because the leading CSP companies had disclosure patterns related to CSP negatives, it appears that they may be adopting disclosure practices that enable them to use CSP as a safety net to protect that favorable position. When describing how the negative impact of bad news exceeds the positive impact of good news, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-0007650308324047">Skinner (1994)</xref> refers to bad news that is <italic>unforeseen</italic> by stakeholders rather than all bad news. For this reason, leading CSP companies may be more diligent in making sure that their disclosure practices enable them to be the source of unfavorable information. Indeed, having disclosure practices that enables the company to be the source of unfavorable information may be indicative of the type of stakeholder responsiveness that leads to higher levels of CSP.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0007650308324047">Godfrey (2005)</xref> proposed that for positive acts to be viewed as authentic they must be coupled with ongoing thorough disclosure. An inverse corollary is that for negative information to be perceived as evidence of transparency it must also be the product of ongoing thorough disclosure. In that way, the provision of unfavorable information can also add to stakeholders’ perception that the company is open, transparent, and forthcoming. From an issue management perspective, this approach enables companies to maintain a more favorable position with regard to emerging issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0007650308324047">Grunig &amp; Hunt, 1984</xref>). The leading CSP companies have reason to be more risk averse with respect to their disclosure practices than their peer companies with lower CSP. As a result, they may be more focused on protecting their CSP brand through preemptive disclosure than attempting to capitalize on favorable CSP in their annual reports.</p>
<p>Conversely, companies with lower global CSP ratings demonstrated annual report disclosure that was associated with CSP strengths. Those disclosure practices help companies with less favorable CSP to use positive CSP events to build an operational platform for the future. In this way, companies with less favorable CSP can use annual report disclosure to emphasize strengths and restore or enhance reputation and legitimacy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0007650308324047">Barnett (2007)</xref> proposes that companies with a history of unfavorable CSP will have less stakeholder influence capacity and are more likely to have their favorable acts overlooked or met with skepticism. For example, retail analysts are not sure if Wal-Mart’s low-cost prescription medications and plans for a more public role in health care are the result of a <italic>kinder and gentler</italic> Wal-Mart or an attempt to mute union criticism about the health care benefits it provides to its workers or both (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0007650308324047">Kabel, 2008</xref>). Consequently, companies like Wal-Mart must exert more effort to overcome stakeholder skepticism and have their favorable actions recognized and accepted as such (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr106-0007650308324047">Webb &amp; Mohr, 1998</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section25-0007650308324047">
<title>Implications for Practice and Research</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0007650308324047">Hooghiemstra (2000)</xref> describes two approaches to corporate communication: positive acclaiming through entitlements and enhancements and negative accounting through excuses and justifications. Rather than an intuitively appealing account of companies with good CSP <italic>acclaiming</italic> and those with less favorable CSP <italic>accounting</italic>, we have found the more nuanced association described above. The moderating role of CSP level on the association between CSP dimension and annual report disclosure in this study lends credence to the notion that information provided by companies will be filtered and points to the role of what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0007650308324047">Post and Waddock (1995)</xref> call <italic>philanthropic strategy</italic> in shaping annual report disclosure. In view of that likelihood, it is important to consider the circumstances under which disclosure occurs. Researchers and stakeholders must be wary of aggregated ratings unless (a) a company must score favorably on all areas to be a CSP leader, or (b) areas of inadequacy are indicated regardless of aggregate rating. In other words, a multiple hurdles rating approach will provide a more precise portrait of behavior than a compensatory rating approach.</p>
<p>Given the proliferation of social and environmental reporting mechanisms, CSP will continue to be linked to disclosure. Future research should attempt to distinguish between the ongoing provision of information, which might be expected of socially responsive companies and disclosure that is driven by negative circumstances. These findings also suggest that future investigations of disclosure practices and CSP should carefully distinguish the type of CSP disclosure. Specifically, indicate whether the focus is on specific aspects of CSP or the global rating. It appears that separating those two concepts will influence the results.</p>
<p>We have asserted that the distinction between CSP reporting and financial reporting is exaggerated and this distinction may be interesting explore. If there is the “100% overlap between business drivers and social and environmental interests” that Liveris identifies, why do annual reports so frequently refer the reader to separate citizenship reports for social and environmental reports? Lastly, it would be helpful to examine what, if any, impact disclosure has on corporate behavior. The measurement process necessary to develop disclosure statements directs managers’ attention to the foci of disclosure and affords them an opportunity to identify and rectify problems.</p>
<p>For stakeholders it is important to distinguish transparency from disclosure and be mindful of the extent to which companies are transparent about their business practices. Whereas disclosure refers to the timely provision of relevant information by the company, transparency is characterized by the extent to which a company permits stakeholders to gather information for themselves. Unless CSP is linked more strongly to transparency there is the danger that it, like the annual report, will become part of a company’s communication strategy and further removed from objective independent assessment. The controversy over child labor practices in Nike factories abroad was an indication that stakeholders appreciate the difference. After attempting to resist stakeholders’ demands for outside representatives to join their auditors on inspections, Nike relented. In a subsequent statement that indicates the increased importance of transparency, Philip Knight, Nike’s CEO stated, “We believe that these are practices that conscientious, good companies will follow in the 21st century” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0007650308324047">Cushman, 1998</xref>, p. D1).</p>
<p>This research provides insight into how companies’ CSP brand can be augmented by annual report disclosure. The results should be interpreted with caution, keeping in mind some limitations of the research. First, the analyses are based on one year of ratings data and do not account for possible longitudinal effects. Second, the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> statistics for each of the regression models were small, which limits the strength of assertions that can be made on that basis. Finally, the annual reports examined in this study are from a relatively small sample of very large companies, which limits the generalizability of the findings. That aside, there is much work to be done to understand the role of disclosure as it relates to CSP. This research seeks to contribute to that effort.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0007650308324047">
<title>Appendix A.</title>
<table-wrap id="table5-0007650308324047" position="float">
<caption><p>KLD Analytics Sample of CSP Rating Items.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0007650308324047" xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Strength</th>
<th align="center">Concern</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Community</td>
<td>Charitable giving. The company has consistently given over 1.5% of trailing three-year net earnings before taxes (NEBT) to charity, or has otherwise been notably generous in its giving. In 2002, KLD renamed the Generous Giving Strength as Charitable Giving.</td>
<td>Investment controversies. The company is a financial institution whose lending or investment practices have led to controversies, particularly ones related to the Community Reinvestment Act.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diversity</td>
<td>Promotion. The company has made notable progress in the promotion of women and minorities, particularly to line positions with profit-and-loss responsibilities in the corporation.</td>
<td>Non-representation. The company has no women on its board of directors or among its senior line managers.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Employee relations</td>
<td>Cash profit sharing. The company has a cash profit-sharing program through which it has recently made distributions to a majority of its workforce.</td>
<td>Health and safety concern. The company recently has either paid substantial fines or civil penalties for willful violations of employee health and safety standards, or has been otherwise involved in major health and safety controversies.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Environment</td>
<td>Beneficial products and services. The company derives substantial revenues from innovative remediation products, environmental services, or products that promote the efficient use of energy, or it has developed innovative products with environmental benefits. (The term “environmental service” does not include services with questionable environmental effects, such as landfills, incinerators, waste-to-energy plants, and deep injection wells.)</td>
<td>Hazardous waste. The company’s liabilities for hazardous waste sites exceed $50 million, or the company has recently paid substantial fines or civil penalties for waste management violations.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Product</td>
<td>Benefits to economically disadvantaged. The company has as part of its basic mission the provision of products or services for the economically disadvantaged.</td>
<td>Product safety. The company has recently paid substantial fines or civil penalties, or is involved in major recent controversies or regulatory actions, relating to the safety of its products and services.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</app>
<app id="app2-0007650308324047">
<title>Appendix B.</title>
<table-wrap id="table6-0007650308324047" position="float">
<caption><p>S&amp;P Transparency and Disclosure Sample Categories and Questions.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0007650308324047" xlink:href="10.1177_0007650308324047-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Ownership Structure and Investor Rights Subcategory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Transparency of ownership, addressing disclosure of share classes, shareholder types, par values, and voting rights</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Concentration of ownership, dealing with disclosures of large shareholders and percentages of cross-ownership</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Voting and shareholder meeting procedures, shareholder proposals and nominations, and corporate governance charters</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  1. A description of the share classes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2. A review of shareholder by type</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  3. A description of the voting rights</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Financial Transparency and Information Disclosure Subcategory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Business focus, dealing with company strategy, market analysis, efficiency indicators, and forward-looking information</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Accounting policy review, and frequency of financial reporting</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Asset valuation/depreciation and consolidation policies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Information on auditors, minority interests, and ownership of affiliates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  1. The company’s accounting policy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2. Consistency of company accounting with the international accounting standards (IAS or U.S. GAAP)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  3. Efficiency indicators (return of assets, return on equity, etc.)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Board Structure and Process Subcategory</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Board structure and composition, addressing the identity, tenure, and affiliations of board members</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • The role of the board, addressing decision rights and the make-up of board committees</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • The director training and compensation category, focusing on the training, ownership interest, and compensation of the directors</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1. A list of board members</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2. A list of board committees</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  3. A list of audit committee members</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  4. Details of directors’ remuneration and performance-related pay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  5. Related party transactions</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn12-0007650308324047">
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0007650308324047">Patel and Dallas (2002)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</app>
</app-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0007650308324047">
<label>1.</label>
<p>For a thorough treatment of the differences between voluntary and mandatory disclosure see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr110-0007650308324047">Williams (2008)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0007650308324047">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The shareholders included the New York City Pension Funds, New York State Common Retirement Fund (NYSCRF), Trillium Asset Management, Amnesty International USA (AIUSA), Dominican Sisters: Grand Rapids, Sisters of Holy Cross, and Sisters of Mercy Regional Community of Detroit Charitable Trust.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0007650308324047">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Agent Orange is a defoliant used in Vietnam during the Vietnam War to clear vegetation. U.S. Veterans and Vietnamese civilians have sued Dow for illnesses they claim resulted from Agent Orange exposure. Dow and other chemical industry companies settled a class action suit with the U.S. veterans, but the Supreme Court has recently permitted new litigation by veterans not involved in the initial settlement. This opens an entire new avenue for litigation. A group of Vietnamese civilians also filed suit and had their case dismissed. That case is under appeal.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0007650308324047">
<label>4.</label>
<p>The Bhopal chemical disaster occurred when chemicals (methyl isocyanate gas) stored at a Union Carbide plant overheated and escaped into the city of Bhopal, India in 1984. Dow has since purchased Union Carbide. In May 1989, Union Carbide entered into a legal settlement with the government of India that represented all claimants in the case. Dow states that the Union Carbide settlement has fulfilled their financial responsibility for the disaster, but critics claim that severe contamination continues and should be addressed by the company.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0007650308324047">
<label>5.</label>
<p>In March 2006, The Body Shop, founded by Anita Roddick, agreed to a £652.3 million takeover by L’Oréal. Critics claimed that Roddick and The Body Shop were “selling out” because L’Oreal engaged in animal testing, which contradicted The Body Shop’s stated opposition to the practice.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0007650308324047">
<label>6.</label>
<p>The original number of companies excluded from the DSI 400 was 150. Two companies were eliminated because dependent variable data from the S&amp;P disclosure ratings were not available. The S&amp;P transparency and disclosure study included companies that were members of the S&amp;P 500 during 2002 and for which there was complete information and no regulatory inquiries related to their public filings.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0007650308324047">
<label>7.</label>
<p>The KLD dimensions and items: Community strength, 6 items; community concern, 3 items; diversity strength, 8 items; diversity concern, 3 items; employee relations strength, 5 items; employee relations concern, 5 items; environmental strength, 6 items; environmental concern, 7 items; product strength, 4 items; and product concern, 4 items.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0007650308324047">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Ratings of reputation and social performance have been influenced by financial halo effect, whereby a blurring of distinctions among attributes occurs due to the strong overall impression provided by financial performance. Consequently, the impact of financial performance on the overall citizenship rating can be overestimated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0007650308324047">Brown &amp; Perry, 1994</xref>). We were unable to disentangle this halo effect from our results. Our findings should be viewed with this limitation in mind.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Cedric E. Dawkins</bold>, PhD, is an associate professor of management at California State Polytechnic University, Pomona. His research interests include corporate transparency and disclosure, labor relations, normative stakeholder theory, and corporate social responsibility.</p>
<p><bold>John W. Fraas</bold>, PhD, is Emeritus Trustees Distinguished Professor of Business Administration at Ashland University. He has authored more than 30 journal articles, and a number of books, including a textbook titled <italic>Basic Concepts in Educational Research</italic>.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Corporate governance and conditional skewness in the world’s stock markets</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>2999</fpage>-<lpage>3028</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Incentives versus standards: Properties of accounting income in four East Asia countries</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accounting and Economics</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Stakeholder influence capacity and the variability of financial returns to corporate social responsibility</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>794</fpage>-<lpage>816</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barney</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Trustworthiness as a source of competitive advantage</article-title>. <source>Strategic Management Journal</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual, strategic and statistical considerations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>-<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Annual reporting disclosure 1970-90: An exemplification</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Business and Financial History</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhambri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonnenfeld</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Organization structure and corporate social performance: A field study in two contrasting industries</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>642</fpage>-<lpage>662</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhimani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soonawalla</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>From conformance to performance: The corporate responsibilities continuum</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accounting and Public Policy</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Does corporate governance affect company value? Evidence from Korea</source> (Working Paper). <publisher-name>Stanford Law School</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Botosan</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Disclosure level and the cost of equity capital</article-title>. <source>Accounting Review</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brammer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pavelin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Voluntary social disclosures by large UK companies</article-title>. <source>Business Ethics: A European Review</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Corporate social responsibility and resource-based perspectives</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Ethics</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brounen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cools</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Information transparency pays: Evidence from European property shares</article-title>. <source>Real Estate Finance</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deegan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The public disclosure of environmental performance information: A dual test of media agenda setting theory and legitimacy theory</article-title>. <source>Accounting and Business Research</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Removing the financial performance halo from fortune’s “most admired companies</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1347</fpage>-<lpage>1359</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bushman</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piotroski</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>What determines corporate transparency?</article-title> <source>Journal of Accounting Research</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cahan</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>An empirical examination of the relationship between corporate social responsiveness and extent of disclosure</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Professional Ethics Journal</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The pyramid of corporate social responsibility: Toward the moral management of organizational stakeholders</article-title>. <source>Business Horizons</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>The macropolitics of organizational change: A comparative analysis of the spread of small group activities</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>560</fpage>-<lpage>585</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The impact of size, stock market listing type on disclosure in the annual reports of Japanese listed corporation</article-title>. <source>Accounting and Business Research</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>CSPWire</collab>. (<year>2007</year>, <month>May</month> <day>9</day>). <source>Dow Chemical investors worth $305 million challenge company on social and environmental catastrophes</source>. <access-date>Retrieved July 29, 2007</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.CSPwire.com/News/8473.html">http://www.CSPwire.com/News/8473.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>, <month>May</month> <day>13</day>). <article-title>Nike pledges to end child labor and apply U.S. rules abroad</article-title>. <source>New York Times</source>, pp. <fpage>D1</fpage>-<lpage>D5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dawkins</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Corporate welfare, corporate citizenship, and the question of accountability</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Society</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deegan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A study of the environmental disclosure practices of Australian corporations</article-title>. <source>Accounting and Business Research</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deegan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voght</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Companies’ disclosure reactions to major social incidents: Australian evidence</article-title>. <source>Accounting Forum</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verrecchia</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Disclosure, liquidity, and the cost of capital</article-title>. <source>Journal of Finance</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1325</fpage>-<lpage>1355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DiMaggio</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>The iron cage revisited: Institutional isomorphism and collective rationality in organizational fields</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <source>Corporate morality</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>An evaluation of ‘essays on disclosure’ and the disclosure literature in accounting</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accounting and Economics</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenhardt</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Agency theory: An assessment and review</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elkington</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Triple bottom-line reporting: Looking for balance. Australian CPA</article-title>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elsbach</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Acquiring organizational legitimacy through illegitimate actions: A marriage of institutional and impression management theories</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>699</fpage>-<lpage>738</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Engardio</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>, <month>January</month> <day>29</day>). <source>Beyond the green corporation</source>. <access-date>Retrieved September 10, 2007</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/07_05/b4019001.htm">http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/07_05/b4019001.htm</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Social disclosure and the individual investor</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Auditing and Accountability Journal</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>-<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Felfe</surname><given-names>J. N~.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schyns</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Personality and the perception of transformational leadership: The impact of extraversion, neuroticism, personal need for structure, and occupational self-efficacy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Social Psychology</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>708</fpage>-<lpage>739</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fombrun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Reputation: Realizing value from the corporate image</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fombrun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Opportunity platforms and safety nets: Corporate citizenship and reputational risk</article-title>. <source>Business and Society Review</source>, <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frombrun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>What’s in a name? Reputation building and corporate strategy</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frankforter</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vollrath</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Determinants of governance structure among companies: A test of agency theory predictions</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Management</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Strategic management: A stakeholder approach</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pitman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardberg</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fombrun</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The global reputation quotient project: First steps towards a cross-nationally valid measure of corporate reputation</article-title>. <source>Corporate Reputation Review</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardberg</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fombrun</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Corporate citizenship: Creating intangible assets across institutional environments</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garry</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Consumer sophistication and the role of emotion on satisfaction judgments within credence services</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Behaviour</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>-<lpage>397</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gelb</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strawser</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Corporate social responsibility and financial disclosures: An alternative explanation for increased disclosure</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Ethics</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The relationship between corporate philanthropy and shareholder wealth: A risk management perspective</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>777</fpage>-<lpage>798</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waddock</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Institutional owners and corporate social performance</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1034</fpage>-<lpage>1047</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Javad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Social and environmental disclosure and corporate characteristics: A research note and extension</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Finance &amp; Accounting</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maunders</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Corporate social reporting: Emerging trends in accountability and the social contract</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Auditing and Accountability Journal</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greening</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turbin</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Corporate social performance as a competitive advantage in attracting a quality workforce</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Society</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>254</fpage>-<lpage>280</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahon</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The corporate social performance and corporate financial performance debate: Twenty-five years of incomparable results</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Society</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grunig</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Managing public relations</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hooghiemstra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Corporate communication and impression management: New perspectives why companies engage in corporate social reporting</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Ethics</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Voluntary disclosure in an emerging capital market: Some empirical evidence from companies listed on the Kuala Lumpur Stock Exchange</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Accounting</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Shareholder rights, financial disclosure, and the cost of equity capital</article-title>. <source>Review of Quantitative Finance and Accounting</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>204</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutchins</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Annual reports . . . Who reads them?</article-title> <source>Communication World</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greening</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The effects of corporate governance and institutional ownership types on corporate social performance</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>-<lpage>578</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kabel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Wal-Mart expanding in-store health clinics. The Associated Press</source>. <access-date>Retrieved February 21, 2008</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://articles.moneycentral.msn.com/Insurance/InsureYourHealth/WalMartExpandingInStoreHealthClinics.aspx">http://articles.moneycentral.msn.com/Insurance/InsureYourHealth/WalMartExpandingInStoreHealthClinics.aspx</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palepu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Disclosure practices of foreign companies interacting with U.S. markets</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accounting Research</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>475</fpage>-<lpage>508</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://KLD.com">KLD.com</ext-link></collab>. (<year>2007</year>). <source>100 Best Corporate Citizens 2007</source>. <access-date>Retrieved September 6, 2007</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kld.com/research/socrates/businessethics100/2007/">http://www.kld.com/research/socrates/businessethics100/2007/</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>KLD Analytics</collab>. (<year>2007a</year>). <source>KLD Stats: Statistical tool for analysis of trends</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>KLD Research &amp; Analytics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>KLD Analytics</collab>, (<year>2007b</year>). <source>Research methodology</source>. <access-date>Retrieved July 29, 2007</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kld.com/research/methodology.html">http://www.kld.com/research/methodology.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krishnamurti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ševic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ševic</surname><given-names>Ž</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Voluntary disclosure, transparency, and market quality: Evidence from emerging market ADRs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Multinational Financial Management</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>454</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lundholm</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Cross-sectional determinants of analyst ratings of corporate disclosures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accounting Research</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>246</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liston-Heyes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceton</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Corporate social performance and politics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Corporate Citizenship</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Corporate social responsibility, customer satisfaction, and market value</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynxwiler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shover</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clelland</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>The organization and impact of inspector discretion in a regulatory bureaucracy</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>436</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barney</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Corporate social responsibility and company performance: Investor preferences and corporate strategies</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>835</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mallin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Editorial: The relationship between corporate governance, transparency and financial disclosure</article-title>. <source>Corporate Governance</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Testing research hypotheses with the general linear model</source>. <publisher-loc>Carbondale</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Southern Illinois University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Corporate social responsibility: A theory of the company perspective</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meznar</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nigh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Buffer or bridge? Environmental and organizational determinants of public affairs activities in American firms</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>975</fpage>-<lpage>996</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Managing the corporate social environment: A grounded theory</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Do consumers expect companies to be socially responsible? The impact of corporate social responsibility on buying behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Affairs</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Near</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baucus</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miceli</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The relationship between values and practice: Organizational climates for wrongdoing</article-title>. <source>Administration &amp; Society</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warsame</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pedwell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Managing public impressions: Environmental disclosures in annual reports</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Organizations, and Society</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Bank failures, stigma management and the accounting establishment</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Organizations and Society</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>645</fpage>-<lpage>665</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) Business Sector Advisory Group on Corporate Governance</collab>. (<year>1998</year>). <source>Corporate governance: Improving competitiveness and access to capital in global markets</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Oxfam</collab>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Cutting the cost of global health</article-title>. <source>Parliamentary briefing #</source><day>16</day>, <month>February</month>. <access-date>Retrieved August 14, 2008</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oxfam.org.uk/resources/policy/health/index">http://www.oxfam.org.uk/resources/policy/health/index</ext-link> .html</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bwakira</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Measuring disclosure at company level in emerging markets</article-title>. <source>Emerging Markets Review</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>-<lpage>337</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dallas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>, <month>October</month> <day>16</day>). <article-title>Transparency and Disclosure: Overview of methodology and study results—United States</article-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Standard &amp; Poor’s</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The relation between environmental performance and environmental disclosure: A research note</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Organizations and Society</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>763</fpage>-<lpage>764</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The high impact of collaborative social initiatives</article-title>. <source>MIT Sloan Management Review</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waddock</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Strategic philanthropy and partnerships for economic progress</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>America</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Philanthropy and economic development</source> (pp. <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pothukuchi</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Personality-time management skills relationship</article-title>. <source>ICFAI Journal of Organizational Behavior</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pownall</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waymire</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The stock price effects of alternative types of management earnings forecasts</article-title>. <source>Accounting Review</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>896</fpage>-<lpage>912</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Imagining annual reports</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Organizations and Society</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radin</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The effectiveness of global codes of conduct: Role models that make sense</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Society Review</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haunschild</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The liability of good reputation: A study of product recalls in the U.S. automobile industry</article-title>. <source>Company Science</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Determinants of corporate social responsibility disclosure: An application of stakeholder theory</article-title>. <source>Accounting, Organizations and Society</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>-<lpage>612</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buchholtz</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Investigating the relationship between board characteristics and board information</article-title>. <source>Corporate Governance: An International Review</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>576</fpage>-<lpage>584</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>International corporate social responsibility rating systems</article-title>. <source>Journal of Corporate Citizenship</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Organizational culture and leadership</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The role of the founder in creating organizational culture</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hesselbein</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckhard</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The leader of the future</source> (pp. <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The people make the place</article-title>. <source>Personnel Psychology</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The adolescence of institutional theory</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>511</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Corporate disclosure quality and the cost of debt</article-title>. <source>The Accounting Review</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>-<lpage>474</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Why companies voluntarily disclose bad news</article-title>. <source>Journal of Accounting Research</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr98-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Job market signaling</article-title>. <source>Quarterly Journal of Economics</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr99-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.-Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Assessing the cumulative effects of stress: The association between job stress and allostatic load in a large sample of Chinese employees</article-title>. <source>Work &amp; Stress</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr100-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teece</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pisano</surname><given-names>G. P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shuen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Dynamic capabilities and strategic management</article-title>. <source>Strategic Management Journal</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>533</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr101-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teece</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pisano</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shuen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Dynamic capabilities and strategic management</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dosi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The nature and dynamics of organizational capabilities</source> (pp. <fpage>334</fpage>-<lpage>362</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr102-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>The effects of organizational culture on choices of accounting methods</article-title>. <source>Accounting and Business Research</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr103-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waddock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Myths and realities of social investing</article-title>. <source>Organization and Environment</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>380</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr104-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waddock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Parallel universes: Companies, academies, and the progress of corporate citizenship</article-title>. <source>Business &amp; Society Review</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr105-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waddock</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The corporate social performance-financial performance link</article-title>. <source>Strategic Management Journal</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>-<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr106-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>A typology of consumer responses to cause-related marketing: From skeptics to socially concerned</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Policy and Marketing</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>226</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr107-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Welker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Disclosure policy, information asymmetry and liquidity in equity markets</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Accounting Research</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>801</fpage>-<lpage>827</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr108-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Werther</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Strategic corporate social responsibility as global brand insurance</article-title>. <source>Business Horizons</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>324</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr109-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The securities and exchange commission and corporate social transparency</article-title>. <source>Harvard Law Review</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>1197</fpage>-<lpage>1311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr110-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Toward a taxonomy of corporate reporting strategies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Communication</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>232</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr111-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Toward improving corporate social performance</article-title>. <source>Business Horizons</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>66</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr112-0007650308324047">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birkin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Organizational legitimacy and stakeholder information provision</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Management</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>