<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcre</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Rehabil</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Rehabilitation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0269-2155</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0873</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269215511434993</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269215511434993</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Data collection tools</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An investigation of the validity of six measures of physical function in people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>Stephen D</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0269215511434993">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>de Morton</surname><given-names>Natalie A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0269215511434993">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mc Burney</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0269215511434993">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0269215511434993"><label>1</label>Barwon Health, Australia</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0269215511434993"><label>2</label>Musculoskeletal Research Centre and School of Physiotherapy, La Trobe University, Australia</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0269215511434993"><label>3</label>Monash University, Australia</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0269215511434993">Stephen D Gill, Physiotherapy Department, Barwon Health, PO Box 281, Geelong, 3220, Australia Email: <email>steveg@barwonhealth.org.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>945</fpage>
<lpage>951</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>5</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0269215511434993">
<title>Objective:</title>
<p>To assess and compare the validity of six physical function measures in people awaiting hip or knee joint replacement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0269215511434993">
<title>Design:</title>
<p>Eighty-two people awaiting hip or knee replacement were assessed using six physical function measures including the WOMAC Function scale, SF-36 Physical Function scale, SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale, Patient Specific Functional Scale, 30-second chair stand test, and 50-foot timed walk. Validity was assessed using a head-to-head comparison design.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0269215511434993">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Convergent validity was demonstrated with significant correlations between most measures (Spearman’s rho 0.22 to 0.71). The Patient Specific Functional Scale had the lowest correlations with other measures of physical function. Discriminant validity was demonstrated with low correlations between mental health and physical function scores (Spearman’s rho −0.12 to 0.33). Only the WOMAC Function scale, 30-second chair stand test, and 50-foot timed walk demonstrated known groups validity when scores for participants who walked with a gait aid were compared with those who did not. Standardized response means and Guyatt’s responsiveness indexes indicated that the SF-36 was the least responsive measure.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0269215511434993">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>For those awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee, the current investigation found that the WOMAC Function scale, 30-second chair stand test, and 50-foot timed walk demonstrated the most evidence of validity. The Patient Specific Functional Scale might complement other measures by capturing a different aspect of physical function.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Clinimetrics</kwd>
<kwd>joint replacement</kwd>
<kwd>measurement</kwd>
<kwd>physical function</kwd>
<kwd>validity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section5-0269215511434993" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Outcome Measures for Arthritis Clinical Trials (OMERACT) recommended that the core set of outcome measures in osteoarthritis clinical trials should include measurement of physical function.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269215511434993">1</xref></sup> However, no specific measures of physical function have been recommended.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269215511434993">2</xref></sup> To decide which measures to use or recommend, clinimetric properties such as validity should be considered and compared.</p>
<p>The SF-36 and WOMAC are the most widely used generic and condition-specific measures of function for people with lower limb arthritis and have acceptable reliability and validity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269215511434993">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269215511434993"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511434993">5</xref></sup> An alternative measure, the Patient Specific Functional Scale, aims to overcome the perceived limitations of generic and condition-specific questionnaires by asking participants to select and score only activities they consider important.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269215511434993">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269215511434993">7</xref></sup> Studies to date have indicated that the Patient Specific Functional Scale is reliable and valid in populations with vertebral pain and lower limb dysfunction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269215511434993">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269215511434993">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269215511434993">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>Despite their widespread use, self-report measures are limited by errors associated with memory, judgement, cognition and willingness to answer questions accurately.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0269215511434993">10</xref></sup> Performance-based measures overcome these limitations and provide unique information about function and health status.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269215511434993">11</xref></sup> The 50-foot timed walk and 30-second chair stand test are two performance-based measures used to assess physical function in those with lower limb arthritis. Acceptable reliability of these instruments has been documented in patients with advanced stage osteoarthritis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269215511434993">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>No studies have directly compared the clinimetric properties of the WOMAC, SF-36, Patient Specific Functional Scale, 30-second chair stand test and 50-foot timed walk in people with end-stage arthritis of the hip or knee. The aim of this study was to investigate the validity of these commonly used measures, using a head-to-head comparison design. The results of this comparison will assist clinicians and researchers to select the most appropriate measure or measures of physical function when assessing people with advanced hip or knee osteoarthritis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0269215511434993" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Participants were part of a clinical trial comparing the effects of two six-week exercise-based interventions on pain and function in people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269215511434993">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>Blinded assessment occurred on two separate occasions, immediately before and after the six-week intervention. All assessors were trained and assessed for competence by the primary author. Measures were completed in the same order at each assessment.</p>
<p>Regarding the self-report measures, the WOMAC Function scale,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511434993">5</xref></sup> SF-36 Physical Function scale,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269215511434993">13</xref></sup> SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0269215511434993">13</xref></sup> and the Patient Specific Functional Scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269215511434993">6</xref></sup> were used to assess physical function. The SF-36 Mental Health scale was used to measure psychological well-being. For the SF-36 scales and Patient Specific Functional Scale, higher scores indicated better function. For the WOMAC, lower scores indicated better function. Our version of the Patient Specific Functional Scale required subjects to ‘identify three important activities that you are unable to do or have difficulty with as a result of your hip or knee problem’. Scores for the three activities were then averaged to give a single score for the scale.</p>
<p>The 30-second chair stand test assessed the number of times a participant could stand then sit in a chair in 30 seconds.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269215511434993">14</xref></sup> The 50-foot timed walk assessed the time taken to walk 50 feet (15.2 m) in a straight line.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269215511434993">11</xref></sup> Subjects were advised to ‘go as fast as you can safely walk’. Participants were allowed to use a walking aid if this was their usual practice. All instructions, encouragement and measurements for both performance-based measures were carried out in a consistent manner according to standardized instructions documented elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0269215511434993">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Participants’ overall change was assessed with a global assessment of change scale, a seven-point Likert scale similar to that used by Middel et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0269215511434993">15</xref></sup> At the post-intervention assessment participants were asked ‘Overall have you changed as a result of this programme, be that physically, emotionally or functionally?’ Improvement or deterioration could be recorded as ‘a little’, ‘moderately’ or ‘a lot’. ‘No change’ was also an option.</p>
<p>Validity was assessed using four tests: convergent validity, discriminant validity, known groups validity, and responsiveness (longitudinal validity). The outcome measure(s) that performed best across the four tests was considered the most valid.</p>
<p>Convergent and discriminant validity were investigated by calculating Spearman’s rho correlation coefficient between measures of related constructs (i.e. correlation between each measure of physical function) and measures of other constructs (i.e. correlation between physical function measures and mental health), respectively. Evidence of convergent validity was obtained if moderate to high correlation was identified between the measures of physical function. Evidence of discriminant validity was obtained if a low correlation was identified between the physical function measures and the SF-36 Mental Health scale.</p>
<p>Known groups validity was investigated by comparing scores on each physical function measure for participants who walked with a gait aid compared to participants who walked without a gait aid. Evidence of known groups validity was obtained if a statistically significant difference between groups was identified using an independent <italic>t</italic>-test. Effect sizes were calculated according to the method described by Thalheimer and Cook.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0269215511434993">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>Since there is no ‘gold standard’ recommendation regarding the optimal index for calculating responsiveness to change, a distribution based method (the standardized response mean (SRM))<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269215511434993">17</xref></sup> and a criterion-based method (Guyatt’s responsiveness index (GRI))<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269215511434993">8</xref></sup> were selected a priori and calculated as follows:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0269215511434993">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0269215511434993">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>SRM</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>average</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>change</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>entire</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>group</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>standard</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>deviation</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>change</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>scores</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>entire</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>group</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0269215511434993" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511434993-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where average change = (post-intervention mean–baseline assessment mean)</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0269215511434993">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0269215511434993">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>GRI</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>average</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>change</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>change</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>group</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>standard</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>deviation</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>change</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>scores</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>stable</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>group</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0269215511434993" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511434993-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where stable group = participants who indicated ‘a little’ or ‘no change’ on the global assessment of change scale.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269215511434993">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>Change group = participants who indicated ‘moderately’ or ‘a lot’ on the global assessment of change scale.</p>
<p>The Barwon Health Research and Ethics Committee, and the La Trobe University Faculty of Health Sciences Human Ethics Committee approved this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0269215511434993" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Eighty-two participants were included in the study. The average age was 70.3 (SD 9.8), 51 (63%) participants were female, and 35 (43%) were awaiting hip replacement surgery. Additional participant details have been published elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0269215511434993">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>With the exception of the comparison between the Patient Specific Functional Scale and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale, all measures demonstrated evidence of convergent validity with significant correlations with the other measures of physical function (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0269215511434993">Table 1</xref>). The strongest evidence of convergent validity was between the SF-36 Physical Function scale and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale (ρ = 0.71). The 30-second chair stand test had moderately high correlations with both the 50-foot timed walk and WOMAC Function scale (ρ = 0.64 and ρ = 0.62 respectively); the WOMAC Function scale and SF-36 Physical Function scales were also moderately correlated with each other (ρ = 0.55). Typically, the Patient Specific Functional Scale had the lowest correlation with each other measure of physical function (ρ ≤ 0.37).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0269215511434993" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Convergent and discriminant validity (Spearman’s rho, 95% confidence interval)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0269215511434993" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511434993-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">50 FTW</th>
<th align="left">30 CST</th>
<th align="left">PSFS</th>
<th align="left">SF-36 PF</th>
<th align="left">SF-36 PCS</th>
<th align="left">WOMAC Function</th>
<th align="left">SF-36 MH</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>50 FTW</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>−0.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.75 to −0.49)</td>
<td>−0.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.54 to −0.16)</td>
<td>−0.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.56 to −0.19)</td>
<td>−0.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.55 to −0.17)</td>
<td>0.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (0.23 to 0.58)</td>
<td>−0.12 (−0.33 to 0.10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 CST</td>
<td/>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>0.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">*</xref> (0.04 to 0.45)</td>
<td>0.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (0.19 to 0.56)</td>
<td>0.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (0.14 to 0.53)</td>
<td>−0.62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.74 to −0.47)</td>
<td>0.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (0.12 to 0.51)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSFS</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">*</xref> (0.01 to 0.42)</td>
<td>0.11 (−0.11 to 0.32)</td>
<td>−0.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.54 to −0.17)</td>
<td>0.16 (−0.06 to 0.36)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF-36 PF</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>0.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (0.59 to 0.81)</td>
<td>−0.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.69 to −0.38)</td>
<td>0.21 (−0.01 to 0.41)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF 36 PCS</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>−0.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.64 to −0.30)</td>
<td>−0.18 (−0.38 to 0.04)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WOMAC Function</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>−0.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0269215511434993">**</xref> (−0.49 to −0.09)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF-36 MH</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1.00</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0269215511434993">
<p>Data is from the baseline assessment. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <italic>n =</italic> 82 all measures.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0269215511434993">
<p>50 FTW, 50-foot timed walk; 30 CST, 30-second chair stand test; PSFS, Patient Specific Functional Scale; SF-36 PF, SF-36 Physical Function scale; SF-36 PCS, SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Each measure of physical function had a low correlation with the SF-36 Mental Health scale indicating discriminant validity (ρ ≤ 0.33) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0269215511434993">Table 1</xref>). However, low correlations were significant for the 30-second chair stand test and WOMAC Function scale.</p>
<p>Evidence of known groups validity was obtained for the 50-foot timed walk, 30-second chair stand test and WOMAC Function scale through significantly higher scores for participants who ambulated without a gait aid compared to participants who did (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0269215511434993">Table 2</xref>). Significant differences had moderate effect sizes. Results for the SF-36 Physical Function scale, SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale, and Patient Specific Functional Scale did not demonstrate known groups validity, though the Patient Specific Functional scale approached significance (<italic>P</italic> = 0.06).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0269215511434993" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Known groups validity</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0269215511434993" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511434993-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Mean (SD) No gait aid (<italic>n =</italic> 50)</th>
<th align="left">Mean (SD) Gait aid (<italic>n =</italic> 32)</th>
<th align="left">Mean difference (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left">Significance (2-tailed)</th>
<th align="left">Effect size (95% CI)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>50 FTW (s)</td>
<td>13.9 (7.7)</td>
<td>19.0 (5.9)</td>
<td>−5.1 (−8.3 to −1.9)</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>−0.55 (−0.90 to −0.21)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 CST (stands)</td>
<td>7.3 (2.8)</td>
<td>4.5 (3.3)</td>
<td>2.8 (1.4 to 4.1)</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.64 (0.32 to 0.95)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSFS</td>
<td>3.7 (1.3)</td>
<td>3.1 (1.5)</td>
<td>0.6 (−0.02 to 1.2)</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.30 (0.01 to 0.60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF-36 PF</td>
<td>33.6 (16.8)</td>
<td>30.1 (22.5)</td>
<td>3.5 (−5.1 to 12.2)</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.13 (−0.18 to 0.43)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF-36 PCS</td>
<td>28.5 (6.4)</td>
<td>27.7 (7.1)</td>
<td>0.9 (−2.1 to 3.9)</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>0.09 (−0.22 to 0.41)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WOMAC Function</td>
<td>34.7 (11.4)</td>
<td>40.8 (11.0)</td>
<td>−6.1 (−11.1 to −1.0)</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>−0.39 (−0.70 to −0.06)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0269215511434993">
<p>Data are from the baseline assessment.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0269215511434993">
<p>50 FTW, 50-foot timed walk; 30 CST, 30-second chair stand test; PSFS, Patient Specific Functional Scale; SF-36 PF, SF-36 Physical Function scale; SF-36 PCS, SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale; SF-36 MH, SF-36 Mental Health scale.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Standardized response means and Guyatt’s responsiveness indexes of 0.2, 0.5 and 0.8 have been interpreted to represent small, moderate and large responsiveness to change respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0269215511434993">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0269215511434993">18</xref></sup> <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0269215511434993">Table 3</xref> indicates standardized response means: the 30-second chair stand test had large responsiveness, the WOMAC Function, 50-foot timed walk and Patient Specific Functional Scale had moderate responsiveness, and the SF-36 Physical Function and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale had small responsiveness. Guyatt’s responsiveness indexes indicate that all measures except the SF-36 Physical Function and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale had large responsiveness (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0269215511434993">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0269215511434993" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Standardized response mean and Guyatt’s Responsiveness Index</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0269215511434993" xlink:href="10.1177_0269215511434993-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">SRM (95% CI) (<italic>n</italic> = 75)</th>
<th align="left">GRI (95% CI) (<italic>n</italic> = 75)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>50 FTW</td>
<td>0.45 (0.22 to 0.68)</td>
<td>1.08 (0.44 to 1.72)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 CST</td>
<td>0.84 (0.61 to 1.07)</td>
<td>0.98 (0.73 to 1.22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSFS</td>
<td>0.55 (0.32 to 0.78)</td>
<td>1.18 (0.75 to 1.62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF-36 PF</td>
<td>0.2 (−0.03 to 0.43)</td>
<td>0.31 (0.01 to 0.63)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SF-36 PCS</td>
<td>0.2 (−0.02 to 0.43)</td>
<td>0.3 (0.02 to 0.58)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WOMAC Function</td>
<td>0.7 (0.47 to 0.93)</td>
<td>0.84 (0.53 to 1.14)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0269215511434993">
<p>SRM, standardized response mean; GRI, Guyatt’s Responsiveness Index; 50 FTW, 50-foot timed walk; 30 CST, 30-second chair stand test; PSFS, Patient Specific Functional Scale; SF-36 PF, SF-36 Physical Function scale; SF-36 PCS, SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0269215511434993" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The current investigation assessed the validity of six measures of physical function for people awaiting hip or knee joint replacement surgery using four tests: convergent validity, discriminant validity, known groups validity and responsiveness. Convergent validity was demonstrated amongst the measures; however, lower correlations between the Patient Specific Functional Scale and the remaining measures suggest it measured a different aspect of function. Significant, though low correlations between the SF-36 Mental Health scale and both the 30- second chair stand test and WOMAC Function scale suggest they measured somewhat overlapping constructs and indicate a possible relationship between physical and psychological well-being. For known groups validity and responsiveness, the SF-36 Physical Function scale and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale underperformed compared to the other measures suggesting these measures were the least valid in our sample of people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee.</p>
<p>For convergent validity, moderate correlations between the WOMAC Function scale and SF-36 scales indicated that these tools were measuring similar constructs. In a similar preoperative population, Wright and Young<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0269215511434993">19</xref></sup> also found a moderate correlation between the WOMAC Function and SF-36 Function scale (ρ = 0.70). Considering the content of these measures, the convergence of these measures is not surprising as both measures ask 10 or more questions about physical function across a range of similar situations. The two performance-based measures also demonstrated a moderate to strong correlation with each other. Factors that influence both these tests would explain this result including a participant’s strength, flexibility, aerobic fitness, pain with weight-bearing activity and motivation. The moderate correlation between the WOMAC Function scale and 30-second chair stand test could reflect a mediating factor that influenced performance on both measures such as strength. Jones et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0269215511434993">14</xref></sup> found a moderately high correlation between chair-stand performance and maximum leg press performance (<italic>r</italic> = 0.77) that supported criterion-related validity that the chair stand test is a measure of lower body strength. Strength could be an important determinant of ability for many of the physical tasks measured in the WOMAC Function scale such as negotiating stairs, rising from sitting, performing heavy domestic tasks and getting in/out of a car, and this could explain the moderate association between scores on the 30- second chair stand test and WOMAC Function scale. The strong correlation between the SF-36 Physical Function and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale was expected as the SF-36 Physical Function is the largest contributor to the composite scale.</p>
<p>The comparatively low correlations between the Patient Specific Functional Scale and the other instruments suggest that the Patient Specific Functional Scale measured a different perspective of physical function. Chatman et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269215511434993">9</xref></sup> investigated the measurement properties of the Patient Specific Functional Scale on 38 subjects with knee dysfunction and found low to moderate correlation (<italic>r</italic> = 0.34) between the Patient Specific Functional Scale and the SF-36 Physical Function scale. Chatman et al. argued that only fair correlations (0.30−0.50) would be expected because of differences between the instruments. The SF-36 is designed to measure activities common to everyone, whereas the Patient Specific Functional Scale is designed to measure only a small number of activities that might be unique and important to each patient. In the current investigation, the most frequently selected activity for inclusion on the Patient Specific Functional Scale was walking (<italic>n =</italic> 51), followed by climbing stairs (<italic>n =</italic> 32) and getting up from a chair (<italic>n =</italic> 23), but other activities included line dancing, climbing a ladder and pulling up anchor. The high specificity of the Patient Specific Functional Scale might cause less overlap between the activities it measured compared to the other instruments and this might explain the low to moderate correlations found. The Patient Specific Functional Scale is not a comprehensive measure of disability and is intended to compare the results of an individual over time as opposed to the amount of disability among groups of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269215511434993">9</xref></sup> When comparing group results, generic and condition-specific measures are required.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269215511434993">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>Chronic illness in the general population is often associated with reduced mental health.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269215511434993">20</xref></sup> The low, yet significant associations between the SF-36 Mental Health scale and both the 30-second chair stand test and WOMAC Function scale could reflect a relationship between mental health and physical health. Elsewhere, there is conflicting evidence about the mental health status of people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee. For example, both Croft et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0269215511434993">20</xref></sup> and Jones et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0269215511434993">21</xref></sup> found that the mental health status of those awaiting joint replacement of the hip or knee was similar to population norms, whereas Ackerman et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0269215511434993">22</xref></sup> found high or very high psychological distress in a sample of 214 people awaiting hip or knee replacement. Considering the powerful effects that psychological factors can have on health,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0269215511434993">23</xref></sup> further clarification of the relationship between psychological and physical function in the current population appears warranted.</p>
<p>The 30-second chair stand test, 50-foot timed walk and WOMAC Function scales demonstrated evidence of known groups validity; the Patient Specific Functional Scale approached a significant result for known groups validity (<italic>P</italic> = 0.06). Effect size estimates were largest for the two performance-based measures suggesting they were most adept at distinguishing between patients who would be expected to differ in their physical performance. The SF-36 Physical Function and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scales failed to find a difference in performance between those who used a gait aid and those who did not; hence these scales were less able to discriminate between groups with different functional abilities.</p>
<p>Responsiveness is the ability of a questionnaire to detect clinically important change over time and is considered a measure of longitudinal validity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0269215511434993">24</xref></sup> All instruments except the SF-36 Physical Function and SF-36 Physical Component Summary scale demonstrated moderate or large responsiveness for both measures of responsiveness. Inferences regarding the responsiveness of the SF-36 in the current investigation should acknowledge that the upper limit of its 95% confidence interval did approximate moderate responsiveness. However, our results are consistent with other investigators that found the SF-36 had inferior responsiveness when compared to the WOMAC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511434993">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0269215511434993">25</xref></sup> and the Patient Specific Functional Scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0269215511434993">9</xref></sup> in populations similar to ours. These results support a broader perspective that condition-specific and patient-specific instruments better detect changes in health status than generic instruments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269215511434993">5</xref></sup> Our results did not support the notion that patient-specific measures are more responsive than condition-specific measures. However, given that the Patient Specific Functional Scale only assessed activities that were important to the patient, arguably it assessed clinically important change to a greater extent than the WOMAC Function scale.</p>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-0269215511434993">
<title>Clinical messages</title>
<list id="list1-0269215511434993" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The WOMAC Function scale, 30-second chair stand test and 50-foot timed walk had the strongest evidence of validity for measuring physical function in people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The Patient Specific Functional Scale captured a distinct perspective of physical function and should be used when assessing change at an individual level.</p></list-item>
</list>
</boxed-text>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The Department of Human Services Victoria supported this work as part of a state-wide initiative of ‘Improving Outcomes of Patients Waiting for Elective Surgery’. Dr Natalie de Morton was funded by an NHMRC Post Doctoral Fellowship (ID 519555).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0269215511434993">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bellamy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recommendations for a core set of outcome measures for future phase III clinical trials in knee, hip, and hand osteoarthritis. Consensus development at OMERACT III</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0269215511434993">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Veenhof</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bijlsma</surname><given-names>JWJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ende</surname><given-names>CHM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van den Dijk</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Pisters</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of osteoarthritis questionnaires: A systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0269215511434993">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kolopack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC): a review of its utility and measurement properties</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0269215511434993">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>JE</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <article-title>SF-36 health survey update</article-title>. <source>Spine</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3130</fpage>–<lpage>3139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0269215511434993">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Angst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stucki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Responsiveness of the WOMAC osteoarthritis index as compared with the SF36 in patients with osteoarthritis of the legs undergoing a comprehensive rehabilitation intervention</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>834</fpage>–<lpage>840</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0269215511434993">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westaway</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Binkley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessing disability and change on individual patients: a report of a patient specific measure</article-title>. <source>Physiother Can</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0269215511434993">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pietrobon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coeytaux</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vellis</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Standard scales for measurement of functional outcome for cervical pain or dysfunction: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Spine</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0269215511434993">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pengel</surname><given-names>LHM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Refshauge</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Responsiveness of pain, disability, and physical impairment outcomes in patients with low back pain</article-title>. <source>Spine</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>879</fpage>–<lpage>883</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0269215511434993">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chatman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hyams</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The patient- specific functional scale: measurement properties in patients with knee dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Phys Ther</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>820</fpage>–<lpage>829</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0269215511434993">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pagura</surname><given-names>SMC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wessel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gollish</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woodhouse</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the factorial validity and clinical interpretability of the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)</article-title>. <source>Physiother Can</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0269215511434993">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McBurney</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reliability of performance-based measures in people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee</article-title>. <source>Physiother Res Int</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0269215511434993">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McBurney</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Land-based versus pool-based exercise for people awaiting joint replacement surgery of the hip or knee: results of a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0269215511434993">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kosinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>SF36 Physical and Mental Health Summary Scales: A manual for the users of version 1</source>, <edition>second edition</edition>. <comment>QualityMetric Incorporated</comment>, <year>2001</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0269215511434993">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rikli</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beam</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A 30-s chair-stand test as a measure of lower body strength in community-residing older adults</article-title>. <source>Res Q Exerc Sport</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0269215511434993">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Middel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bouma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Sonderen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van den Heuvel</surname><given-names>WJA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How to validate clinically important change in health-related functional status. Is the magnitude of the effect size consistently related to magnitude of change as indicated by a global question rating?</article-title> <source>J Eval Clin Pract</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0269215511434993">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thalheimer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How to calculate effect sizes from published research articles: a simplified methodology</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://work-learning.com/effect_sizes.htm">http://work-learning.com/effect_sizes.htm</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 24 July 2004</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0269215511434993">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Husted</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farewell</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gladman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Methods for assessing responsiveness: a critical review and recommendations</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0269215511434993">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of five low back disability questionnaires: reliability and responsiveness</article-title>. <source>Phys Ther</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0269215511434993">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of different indices of responsiveness</article-title> .<source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0269215511434993">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wynn Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coggon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health status in patients awaiting hip replacement for osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1007</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0269215511434993">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voaklander</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suarez-Almazor</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health related quality of life outcomes after total hip and knee arthroplasties in a community based population</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1745</fpage>–<lpage>1752</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0269215511434993">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wicks</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bennell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Severely compromised quality of life in women and those of lower socioeconomic status waiting for joint replacement surgery</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>658</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0269215511434993">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Social determinants of health: The solid facts</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0269215511434993">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Terwee</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bot</surname><given-names>SDM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quality criteria were proposed for measurement properties of health status questionnaires</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0269215511434993">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellamy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of the responsiveness and relative effect size of the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index and the short-form medical outcomes study survey in a randomized, clinical trial of osteoarthritis patients</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>