<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Reprod Sci</journal-id>
<journal-title>Reproductive Sciences</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1933-7191</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1933-7205</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1933719112440051</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1933719112440051</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Immune Response Gene Profiles in the Term Placenta Depend Upon Maternal Muscle Mass</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Tierney</surname>
<given-names>P. F.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1933719112440051">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McWeeney</surname>
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1933719112440051">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1933719112440051">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1933719112440051">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-1933719112440051">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hanson</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>DPhil</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1933719112440051">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-1933719112440051">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Inskip</surname>
<given-names>H. M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-1933719112440051">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>T. K.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9-1933719112440051">9</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bagby</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10-1933719112440051">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>DM</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-1933719112440051">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-1933719112440051">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Godfrey</surname>
<given-names>K. M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-1933719112440051">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-1933719112440051">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Thornburg</surname>
<given-names>Kent L.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11-1933719112440051">11</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff12-1933719112440051">12</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1933719112440051"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1933719112440051">
<label>1</label>Heart Research Center, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1933719112440051">
<label>2</label>Institute of Developmental Sciences, University of Southampton Faculty of Medicine, Southampton General Hospital, Southampton, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1933719112440051">
<label>3</label>Division of Bioinformatics &amp; Computational Biology, Medical Informatics &amp; Clinical Epidemiology, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1933719112440051">
<label>4</label>Division of Biostatistics, Public Health &amp; Preventative Medicine, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff5-1933719112440051">
<label>5</label>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff6-1933719112440051">
<label>6</label>Oregon Clinical and Translational Research Institute, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff7-1933719112440051">
<label>7</label>Southampton NIHR Biomedical Research Unit in Nutrition, Diet &amp; Lifestyle, University of Southampton Faculty of Medicine, Southampton General Hospital, Southampton, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff8-1933719112440051">
<label>8</label>MRC Lifecourse Epidemiology Unit, University of Southampton Faculty of Medicine, Southampton General Hospital, Tremona Road, Southampton, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff9-1933719112440051">
<label>9</label>Department of Pathology, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff10-1933719112440051">
<label>10</label>Dept of Medicine (Hematology &amp; Medical Oncology), Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff11-1933719112440051">
<label>11</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff12-1933719112440051">
<label>12</label>Department of Medicine (Cardiovascular Medicine), Oregon Health and Science University, Portland, OR, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1933719112440051">Kent L. Thornburg, Heart Research Center, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, 3303 SW Bond Ave, CH15H Portland, Oregon, USA Email: <email>thornbur@ohsu.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>1041</fpage>
<lpage>1056</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Gynecologic Investigation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Maternal thinness leads to metabolic challenges in the offspring, but it is unclear whether reduced maternal fat mass or muscle mass drives these metabolic changes. Recently, it has been shown that low maternal muscle mass—as measured by arm muscle area (AMA)—is associated with depressed nutrient transport to the fetus. To determine the role of maternal muscle mass on placental function, we analyzed the gene expression profiles of 30 human placentas over the range of AMA (25.2-90.8 cm<sup>2</sup>) from uncomplicated term pregnancies from the Southampton Women’s Survey cohort. Eighteen percent of the ∼60 genes that were highly expressed in less muscular women were related to immune system processes and the interferon-γ (IFNG) signaling pathway in particular. Those transcripts related to the IFNG pathway included <italic>IRF1</italic>, <italic>IFI27</italic>, <italic>IFI30</italic>, and<italic> GBP6</italic>. Placentas from women with low muscularity are, perhaps, more sensitive to the effects of inflammatory cytokines than those from more muscular women.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>placenta</kwd>
<kwd>muscle mass</kwd>
<kwd>immune response</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1933719112440051">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Adult muscle mass derives from muscle growth during fetal and postnatal life. In men, adult fat-free mass increases 2.2 kg for every 1 kg increase in birth weight.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
</sup> Barker et al proposed that in low-birth-weight babies, muscle development in utero is sacrificed in preference to brain growth in the “brain-sparing” process.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
</sup> Accordingly, people undernourished in the womb will have a relatively low muscle mass for life.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112440051">2</xref>
</sup> This finding has been validated by Baker et al using data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1933719112440051">3</xref>
</sup> They showed that the rate of growth of muscle mass—as measured by arm muscle area (AMA)—remains stunted in people born small, while brain growth is conserved well into childhood. Low muscularity in a pregnant woman may have important implications for her amino acid turnover and glucose metabolism, two processes that are critically important for fetal growth.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112440051">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1933719112440051">4</xref>
</sup> There is evidence that maternal thinness leads to metabolic challenges in the offspring. For example, low maternal body mass index (BMI) is associated with higher fasting insulin levels in adult progeny independent of birth weight and placental weight.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1933719112440051">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1933719112440051">6</xref>
</sup> Maternal influences on placental structure and function could explain relationships between maternal body composition and disease in later life. Placental function is sensitive to maternal BMI as reflected in changes in placental gene expression of inflammatory markers, metabolic pathways, and nutrient transporters that relate to maternal BMI.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112440051">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1933719112440051"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1933719112440051"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1933719112440051">10</xref>
</sup> However, maternal muscle mass, a component of BMI that may also affect placental and fetal growth and function, has received little attention. While BMI is usually used as an indicator of relative fat mass in pregnant women, a high BMI can reflect a large muscle mass-to-height ratio as well. Our lack of understanding of the separate role of muscle mass in regulating placental growth and function leaves an important gap in our knowledge because muscle mass is a key regulator of maternal metabolic capacity<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
</sup> and is thus a potential regulator of placental function. To shed light on that issue, Lewis et al recently reported that placental system A amino acid transport activity is reduced in mothers with low AMA,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1933719112440051">11</xref>
</sup> suggesting that the placenta is sensitive to maternal muscle mass. </p>
<p>We hypothesized that the quantity of muscle in a mother’s body would lead to a unique molecular signature in her term placenta. We sought to determine whether specific groups of genes or functional pathways in the placenta would be differentially regulated according to the levels of maternal muscle mass. To test this hypothesis, we analyzed the gene expression profiles of 30 human placentas from women in three different quintiles of AMA from a cohort of uncomplicated term pregnancies collected during the Southampton Women’s Survey. </p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1933719112440051" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1933719112440051">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Fifty women enrolled in the Southampton Women’s Survey with healthy term pregnancies were ranked by AMA. For this study, 10 women were selected using random numbers from the highest, middle, and lowest quintiles across the AMA spectrum.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1933719112440051">12</xref>
</sup> Women from the fifth, third, and first quintiles were chosen for further study in order to maximize the ability to detect the expression differences between placentas by focusing on clusters of 10 within the middle of the AMA range and the extremes. Their AMA had been measured before pregnancy using the mid-upper arm circumference and triceps skinfold thicknesses according to the established formulae<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1933719112440051">13</xref>
</sup> [(arm circumference − Π × triceps skinfold thickness)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1933719112440051">2</xref>
</sup>/4Π] − 6.5. The trend in maternal characteristics across the AMA groups was assessed using linear regression in Stata version 11.0 (Statacorp, Texas).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1933719112440051">
<title>Tissue Collection and RNA Extraction</title>
<p>The placenta was collected within 30 minutes of delivery. The umbilical cord and blood clots were removed, membranes were trimmed and placentas weighed. Five villous tissue samples were collected from each placenta using a stratified random method. Villous tissue was snap frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C until further analysis. Prior to analysis, samples were pulverized in a frozen press and mixed to generate a representative sample. RNeasy fibrous tissue RNA isolation mini kit (Qiagen, UK) was used to extract total RNA per manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1933719112440051">
<title>Microarray Hybridization</title>
<p>Microarray assays were performed using Affymetrix HG-U133 Plus 2.0 oligonucleotide arrays designed for analysis of 47 000 transcripts. Hybridizations were done in the Affymetrix Microarray Core of the Oregon Health and Science University (OHSU) Gene Microarray Shared Resource and amplified and labeled target complementary RNA (cRNA) was generated following methods described in the Affymetrix GeneChip Expression Analysis Technical Manual (www.affymetrix.com/support/technical/manual/expression_manual.affx). Messenger RNA (mRNA) was amplified and labeled from 2 μg of total RNA using the Affymetrix IVT amplification/labeling protocol (Affymetrix, Inc, Santa Clara, CA) for gene expression profiling with GeneChip 3’IVT arrays. Target yield was measured by UV<sub>260</sub> absorbance. Before hybridization, quality assessment of cRNA was performed on the RNA 6000 LabChip using the 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent, Palo Alto, California).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1933719112440051">
<title>Microarray Analysis</title>
<p>Raw Affymetrix data files (.CEL files) were normalized together using Robust Multiarray Average. It was noted that anomalies in the expression distributions remained after normalization. One sample in the low AMA group had a noticeably distinct interquartile range and was excluded from further analysis. A linear model was fit to each transcript to test for putative differential expression. All <italic>P</italic> values were false discovery rate (FDR) adjusted per Benjamini and Hochberg.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1933719112440051">14</xref>
</sup> Based on FDR adjusted <italic>P</italic> &lt; .10, there were 61 significant transcripts used for high versus low AMA comparison, 123 for high versus mid-AMA comparison, and 15 for mid versus low AMA. </p>
<p>Differentially expressed transcript data (FDR 10%) was imported into GeneSifter software (GeoSpiza, Inc, Seattle, Washington) for annotation and further analysis. Unsupervised hierarchical clustering of data was performed using Euclidean distance. To identify genes whose expression differed between maternal AMA groups, samples were partitioned using K-medoid clustering. Gene ontology (GO) functional terms were used to aid in the interpretation of the biological significance of the gene clusters. <italic>GO </italic>stat software<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1933719112440051">15</xref>
</sup> was used to find statistically overrepresented GO terms within gene clusters. <italic>P</italic> values for GO enrichment were corrected for multiple testing and dependencies.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1933719112440051">16</xref>
</sup> Functional gene networks were identified by uploading the gene lists to the Ingenuity pathway analysis software version 8.8 (Ingenuity Systems; Redwood City, CA http://ingenuity.com). </p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1933719112440051">
<title>Real-Time PCR</title>
<p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed using the Stratagene Mx3005P Thermocycler (Stratagene, Santa Clara, CA). Gene-specific primers were designed using primer designer software (Clone Manager ProfessionalSuite ver.8). β-Actin, a housekeeping gene that is not altered by maternal AMA based on the microarray data and confirmed by real-time PCR analysis, was used as a control. The PCR amplicons were detected by fluorescent detection of SYBR Green (Power SYBR Green Master Mix; Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA). For each primer pair, standard curve samples, no template controls, and unknowns were run in triplicate. Following cycling, the melt curve of the resulting amplicon was analyzed to ensure that a single product was detected. Quantification of mRNA was achieved using the respective standard curves with manufacturer’s software (MxPro QPCR; Stratagene). Values were expressed as a ratio of the gene of interest:control in each sample. Significant differences between maternal AMA groups were assessed by 1-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with post hoc differences determined by Tukey multiple comparison tests. Significance was defined as <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. Data are expressed as mean ± standard error of the mean.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1933719112440051">
<title>Pathological Scoring</title>
<p>Fixed placental tissue was paraffin embedded and sectioned for histologic examination. The chorionic villi and chorionic plate were scored for histologic evidence of acute or chronic inflammation using routine hematoxylin and eosin-stained histologic sections by a board-certified placental pathologist (T.K.M.) blinded to all identifiers. </p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1933719112440051">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p>Samples of 6 randomly selected placentas from women in each of the 3 AMA groups were studied by immunohistochemistry: a human superoxide dismutase (SOD) 2 antibody (The Binding Site; SanDiego, California; Cat. # PC096), CD3 (Dako; Carpinteria, California; Cat.# A0452; Polyclonal Rabbit Anti-Human), CD20 (Dako; Cat.# M0755; Monoclonal Mouse Anti-Human), CD64 (AbD Serotec; Raleigh, North Carolina; Cat.# MCA756GT; Monoclonal Mouse Anti-Human), and CD68 (Dako; Cat.# M0814; Monoclonal Mouse Anti-Human). Staining intensity of SOD2 was scored blindly on a scale of 1 to 3 as <italic>weak focal</italic> (1) to <italic>diffuse strong</italic> (3) using at least 4 representative ×10 objective fields with the most staining per case. For CD3, CD20, CD64, and CD68, the number of positive cells counted per area of tissue analyzed in each objective field was averaged over ×10 objective fields per case. Scores were averaged for cases within each group and compared by 1-way ANOVA with post hoc differences determined by Tukey multiple comparison tests. Statistical significance was defined as <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. </p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1933719112440051">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section11-1933719112440051">
<title>Characteristics of Maternal Muscle Mass Groups</title>
<p>The physical characteristics of the mothers, babies, and placentas are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1933719112440051">Table 1</xref>. There was a trend across AMA groups by AMA and BMI which was not surprising, and a suggestion of a trend with height, but apart from these variables, there was no apparent difference between the groups in parameters relating to the pregnancy or birth.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Neonatal and Placental Characteristics Within Maternal Arm Muscle Area Quintiles</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Mean ± SD</th>
<th>High AMA (5th Q)</th>
<th>Mid AMA (3rd Q)</th>
<th>Low AMA (1st Q)</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic>
<sub>trend</sub> </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Maternal AMA, cm<sup>2</sup>
</td>
<td>55.4 ± 13.3</td>
<td>36.7 ± 0.94</td>
<td>27.8 ± 1.97</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maternal height, cm</td>
<td>167.1 ± 9.9</td>
<td>162.1 ± 7.7</td>
<td>160.1 ± 5.4</td>
<td>.054</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maternal BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td>
<td>33.4 ± 5.7</td>
<td>26.0 ± 3.8</td>
<td>21.9 ± 2.1</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maternal age, years</td>
<td>29.1 ± 4.4</td>
<td>32.0 ± 5.6</td>
<td>32.7 ± 4.3</td>
<td>.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gestational age, week</td>
<td>40.5 ± 1.1</td>
<td>39.2 ± 1.3</td>
<td>39.8 ± 1.3</td>
<td>.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Birth weight, g</td>
<td>3786 ± 534</td>
<td>3311 ± 316</td>
<td>3526 ± 415</td>
<td>.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Placental weight, g</td>
<td>522 ± 88</td>
<td>439 ± 67</td>
<td>504 ± 88</td>
<td>.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fetal sex, M/F</td>
<td>6/4</td>
<td>7/3</td>
<td>7/3</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1933719112440051">
<p>Abbreviations: SD, standard deviation; AMA, arm muscle area; BMI, body mass index.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1933719112440051">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> N = 10 per group.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1933719112440051">
<title>Effect of Maternal Muscle Mass on Global Placental Gene Expression Profiles</title>
<p>Of 47 000 genes queried on the HG-U133 Plus 2.0 oligonucleotide array, we observed a statistically significant change in expression (FDR 10%) of 188 probe sets, corresponding to 184 genes, between placentas of women with high, mid, and low AMA. To examine the relationship between groups (H, M, and L), hierarchical clustering of the groups was performed. Placentas from the mid- and low-AMA groups were most similar to each other. K-medoids (Euclidean) were used to supervise the clustering of probe sets into 2 groups. Cluster 1 and cluster 2 represent probe sets that show low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1933719112440051">Figure 1A</xref>) or high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1933719112440051">Figure 1B</xref>) levels of gene expression in the lower maternal AMA groups (M and L). The 2 clusters were further analyzed to determine GO terms associated with these different gene expression patterns. We found that the GO significantly overrepresented in cluster 2 (genes with high expression in the lower maternal AMA groups) are involved in immune response (<italic>P</italic> = 10<sup>−7</sup>) and immune system processes (<italic>P</italic> = 10<sup>−5</sup>). No GO terms were statistically significantly overrepresented in cluster 1 (transcripts with low expression in the lower maternal AMA placentas). </p>
<fig id="fig1-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>K-medoids clusters of differentially expressed genes that are coexpressed. K-medoids (Euclidean) were used to cluster probe sets into 2 groups. Clusters 1 and 2 represent probe sets that show a decrease (A) or increase (B), respectively, in gene expression with a decrease in maternal arm muscle area (AMA). H, high maternal AMA; M, mid maternal AMA; L, low maternal AMA.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig1-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Heat maps of differentially expressed placental transcripts (limited to those with &gt;0.5 log<sub>2</sub> fold change for display purposes) from clusters 1 and 2 are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1933719112440051">Figure 2</xref>. Placentas from women with high AMA are the most distinct from the other 2 groups, indicated by the highest branch point. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1933719112440051">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1933719112440051">3</xref> list placental transcripts with significantly lower and higher expression, respectively, in less muscular women (mid-AMA and low-AMA) as compared with the high muscle mass group.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Differentially expressed genes with ≥0.5 log<sub>2</sub> fold change between placentas from women with different arm muscle areas (AMAs). Transcripts were clustered into two groups using K-medoids (Euclidean). Clusters represent probe sets that show a decrease (A) or increase (B), respectively, in gene expression with a decrease in maternal AMA. These clusters are displayed as heat maps of normalized log intensity data. Groups (columns) are arranged from left to right ordered by decreasing maternal AMA. Each gene is annotated with Affymetrix probe set ID and gene symbol. H indicates high maternal AMA; M, mid maternal AMA; L, low maternal AMA. </p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig2-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of Gene Ontologies of Interest Among Differentially Expressed Transcripts (False Discovery Rate 10%) Which Are Higher (Cluster 1) or Lower (Cluster 2) in Placentas From Women With High Arm Muscle Area Compared With Less Muscular Women</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Biological process</th>
<th>Cluster 1, %</th>
<th>Cluster 2, %</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Metabolic process</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Signal transduction</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Multicellular organismal development</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cellular differentiation and proliferation</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inflammation and immune response<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transcription and translation</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transport</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unassigned</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>44</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1933719112440051">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Gene ontologies included in the inflammation and immune response category (immune response and immune system process) were overrepresented in cluster 2 as compared with cluster 1 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001, corrected for multiple comparisons).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Transcripts With Lower Expression in Placentas of Less Muscular Women as Compared With Those With High Arm Muscle Area</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table3.tif"/>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table3a.tif"/>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table3b.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">GO Term</th>
<th rowspan="2">Gene Symbol</th>
<th colspan="2">Fold Change</th>
<th rowspan="2">Gene Name</th>
<th rowspan="2">Location</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>H vs M</th>
<th>H vs L</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Cellular process</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3"> Cell cycle</td>
<td>UHMK1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>U2AF homology motif (UHM) kinase 1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TFDP1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Transcription factor Dp-1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PARD6G</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Par-6 partitioning defective 6 homolog gamma (<italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>)</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2"> Cell growth</td>
<td>PPP2CA</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Protein phosphatase 2, catalytic subunit, alpha isozyme</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FGFRL1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Fibroblast growth factor receptor-like 1</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3"> Cell motility</td>
<td>TSPAN3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Tetraspanin 3</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARHGDIA</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Rho GDP dissociation inhibitor (GDI) alpha</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARPC5</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Actin related protein 2/3 complex, subunit 5, 16kDa</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cell proliferation</td>
<td>CNOT8</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>CCR4-NOT transcription complex, subunit 8</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2"> Cytoskeleton organization</td>
<td>MID1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Midline 1 (Opitz/BBB syndrome)</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MAP7</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Microtubule-associated protein 7</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="11">Developmental process</td>
<td>NPAS2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Neuronal PAS domain protein 2</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RAB23</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>RAB23, member RAS oncogene family</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPAP2B</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Phosphatidic acid phosphatase type 2B</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TBX3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>T-box 3</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NGRN</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Neugrin, neurite outgrowth associated</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SNCA</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>-1.1</td>
<td>Synuclein, alpha (non A4 component of amyloid precursor)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TSHZ2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Teashirt zinc finger homeobox 2</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DCX</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Doublecortin</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ACRV1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Acrosomal vesicle protein 1</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CYTH1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Cytohesin 1</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MAB21L2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Mab-21-like 2 (<italic>C elegans</italic>)</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inflammatory response</td>
<td>RELA</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>v-rel reticuloendotheliosis viral oncogene homolog A (avian)</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="12">Metabolic process</td>
<td>UBFD1</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Ubiquitin family domain containing 1</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MTHFSD</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Methenyltetrahydrofolate synthetase domain containing</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPAP2B</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Phosphatidic acid phosphatase type 2B</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPP2CA</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Protein phosphatase 2, catalytic subunit, alpha isozyme</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UHMK1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>U2AF homology motif (UHM) kinase 1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FKBP1A</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>FK506-binding protein 1A, 12kDa</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ADSS</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Adenylosuccinate synthase</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SNCA</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>-1.1</td>
<td>Synuclein, alpha (non-A4 component of amyloid precursor)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UBQLN3</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>Ubiquilin 3</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MMP8</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Matrix metallopeptidase 8 (neutrophil collagenase)</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MIPEP</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Mitochondrial intermediate peptidase</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NSMAF</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>Neutral sphingomyelinase (N-SMase) activation associated factor</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Nucleic acid metabolic process</td>
<td>EXOSC3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Exosome component 3</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SERBP1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>SERPINE1 mRNA-binding protein 1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LSM11</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>LSM11, U7 small nuclear RNA associated</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="18">Signal transduction</td>
<td>GTF2I</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>General transcription factor IIi</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RAB1A</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>RAB1A, member RAS oncogene family</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NPAS2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Neuronal PAS domain protein 2</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SMAD6</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>SMAD family member 6</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RHEB</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Ras homolog enriched in brain</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RAB23</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>RAB23, member RAS oncogene family</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OR7E156P</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Olfactory receptor, family 7, subfamily E, member 156 pseudogene</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPAP2B</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Phosphatidic acid phosphatase type 2B</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GPR126</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>G protein-coupled receptor 126</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MLLT4</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Myeloid/lymphoid or mixed-lineage leukemia (trithorax homolog, Drosophila); translocated to, 4</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RASSF8</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family (N-terminal) member 8</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MED17</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Mediator complex subunit 17</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FKBP1A</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>FK506-binding protein 1A, 12kDa</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TFG</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>TRK-fused gene</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DCX</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Doublecortin</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NSMAF</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>Neutral sphingomyelinase (N-SMase) activation associated factor</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CNKSR2</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Connector enhancer of kinase suppressor of Ras 2</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CDC42SE2</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>CDC42 small effector 2</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="16">Transcription</td>
<td>GTF2I</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>General transcription factor IIi</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NPAS2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Neuronal PAS domain protein 2</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RBM15</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>RNA-binding motif protein 15</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SMAD6</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>SMAD family member 6</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ZNF200</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Zinc finger protein 200</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPP2CA</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Protein phosphatase 2, catalytic subunit, alpha isozyme</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RELA</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>V-rel reticuloendotheliosis viral oncogene homolog A (avian)</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MED17</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Mediator complex subunit 17</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GTF2F2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>General transcription factor IIF, polypeptide 2, 30kDa</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TMPO</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Thymopoietin</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CNOT8</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>CCR4-NOT transcription complex, subunit 8</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TFDP1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Transcription factor Dp-1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TSHZ2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Teashirt zinc finger homeobox 2</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TSC22D1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>TSC22 domain family, member 1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ZNF582</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Zinc finger protein 582</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IRF5</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Interferon regulatory factor 5</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="6">Transport</td>
<td>STX16</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>Syntaxin 16</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RAB1A</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>RAB1A, member RAS oncogene family</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RAB23</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>RAB23, member RAS oncogene family</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VPS26A</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Vacuolar protein sorting 26 homolog A (<italic>Schizosaccharomyces</italic>  <italic>pombe</italic>)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COL4A4</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>Collagen, type IV, alpha 4</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AP1G1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Adaptor-related protein complex 1, gamma 1 subunit</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="29">Unassigned</td>
<td>TM9SF3</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>Transmembrane 9 superfamily member 3</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LTBP3</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Latent transforming growth factor β-binding protein 3</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AKIRIN1</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>Akirin 1</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IMPAD1</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Inositol monophosphatase domain containing 1</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RLIM</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Ring finger protein, LIM domain interacting</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RCN2</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Reticulocalbin 2, EF-hand calcium binding domain</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LCA5</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Leber congenital amaurosis 5</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C6ORF57</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>Chromosome 6 open reading frame 57</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SRSF9</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>Serine/arginine-rich splicing factor 9</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SPPL3</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Signal peptide peptidase 3</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ZNF609</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>Zinc finger protein 609</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPPDE2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>PPPDE peptidase domain containing 2</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LOC404266</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Hypothetical LOC404266</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RNF32</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Ring finger protein 32</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UQCC</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Ubiquinol–cytochrome c reductase complex chaperone</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FAM135B</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Family with sequence similarity 135, member B</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C6ORF204</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Chromosome 6 open reading frame 204</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMD5</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) 26S subunit, non-ATPase, 5</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C2ORF83</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Chromosome 2 open reading frame 83</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C19ORF69</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Chromosome 19 open reading frame 69</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LOC100287147</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>Hypothetical protein LOC100287147</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RAB11FIP3</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>RAB11 family interacting protein 3 (class II)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C2ORF49</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>Chromosome 2 open reading frame 49</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RBM33</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>RNA-binding motif protein 33</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RNF38</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Ring finger protein 38</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PPPDE1</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>PPPDE peptidase domain containing 1</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ACAP2</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>ArfGAP with coiled-coil, ankyrin repeat and PH domains 2</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TMEM67</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>Transmembrane protein 67</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DPPA4</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>Developmental pluripotency associated 4</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1933719112440051">
<p>Abbreviation: GO: gene ontology</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1933719112440051">
<title>Confirmation of Gene Expression</title>
<p>Real-time PCR analysis was used to confirm the expression patterns of selected genes from clusters 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1933719112440051">Figure 3C</xref>) and 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1933719112440051">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1933719112440051">B</xref>). We were able to confirm the microarray expression patterns in 12 of 17 genes analyzed. Superoxide dismutase 2 mRNA (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 by ANOVA, Tukey post hoc test) and protein expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1933719112440051">Figure 4</xref>) were low in placentas of women with high AMA. Interferon-inducible 27 (IFI27) was higher in women with low AMA (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). Placental Ras homolog enriched in brain (RHEB) was lowest in women with mid or low AMA. </p>
<fig id="fig3-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Markers of T cells (CD3; A&amp;E), B cells (CD20; B&amp;F), macrophages (CD68; C&amp;G), and neutrophils (CD64; D&amp;H) immunostaining in term placental sections from women with high, average, or low arm muscle area (AMA). Immune cells staining positive for their respective markers (E-H: representative photomicrographs showing positive staining, arrows) within villous tissue were counted and averaged to villous area (A-D: histograms of positive cells/area). Photomicrograph using Leica microscope and ×40 objective. Stain is brown and sections are counterstained with hematoxylin. N = 6 per group; H, high maternal AMA; M, mid maternal AMA; L, low maternal AMA. </p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig3-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Gene expression confirmation using real-time PCR. Genes were chosen from cluster 1 (A-B) and 2 (C) for further analysis by PCR. Gene-of-interest expression was normalized to β-actin levels which were not significantly different between groups by microarray analysis or PCR. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 versus high muscle mass by ANOVA. N = 10 per group; H, high maternal AMA; M, mid maternal AMA; L, low maternal AMA; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; ANOVA, analysis of variance. </p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig4-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1933719112440051">
<title>Gene Ontology and Ingenuity Pathway Analysis</title>
<p>To further examine the biological significance of placental genes which are differentially expressed between maternal AMA groups, we grouped the transcripts by function using GO annotation. Cluster 1 contained 125 transcripts representing 121 unique genes, 78 of which were annotated. Cluster 2 contained 63 transcripts representing 63 unique genes, 33 of which were annotated. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1933719112440051">Table 4</xref> shows the distribution of gene ontologies of interest among placental transcripts which are lower or highly expressed in the less muscular women. The only GO categories that significantly differ between the 2 clusters were in the “inflammation and immune response” category. They include the GO categories “immune response” and “immune system process” (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1933719112440051">Table 5</xref>). These GO terms were overrepresented among transcripts that were more highly expressed in cluster 1 than in cluster 2. To investigate the potential relationships between differentially expressed immune response/inflammatory transcripts, we used Ingenuity pathway analysis software (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1933719112440051">Figure 5</xref>) and found that many of these genes are associated with the interferon-γ (IFNG) signaling pathway.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Transcripts High Expressed in Placentas of Women With Lower Arm Muscle Area as Compared With Those With High Arm Muscle Area</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table4.tif"/>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table4a.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>GO Term</th>
<th>Gene Symbol</th>
<th colspan="2">Fold Change</th>
<th>Gene Name</th>
<th>Location</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
<th>H vs M</th>
<th>H vs L</th>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="13">Immune response</td>
<td>CD40</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>CD40 molecule, TNF receptor superfamily member 5</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GBP6</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Guanylate-binding protein family, member 6</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HLA-DRB1</td>
<td>−2.5</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>Major histocompatibility complex, class II, DR beta 1</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICOS</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Inducible T-cell co-stimulator</td>
<td>Plasma Membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFI27</td>
<td>−1.9</td>
<td>−1.9</td>
<td>Interferon, alpha-inducible protein 27</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFI35</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>Interferon-induced protein 35</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LST1</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Leukocyte specific transcript 1</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LY86</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Lymphocyte antigen 86</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMB8</td>
<td>−1.8</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 8 (large multifunctional peptidase 7)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMB9</td>
<td>−2.0</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 9 (large multifunctional peptidase 2)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FYB</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>FYN-binding protein</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QA</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, A chain</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QB</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.5</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, B chain</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="5">Metabolic process</td>
<td>AKR1C1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Aldo-keto reductase family 1, member C1 (dihydrodiol dehydrogenase 1; 20-alpha (3-alpha)-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>APOL6</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Apolipoprotein L, 6</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FYB</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>FYN-binding protein</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MMAB</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Methylmalonic aciduria (cobalamin deficiency) cblB type</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PADI1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td>Peptidyl arginine deiminase, type I</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Response to stress</td>
<td>ANXA8L2</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Annexin A8-like 2</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SOD2</td>
<td>−1.7</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Superoxide dismutase 2, mitochondrial</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="6">Signal transduction</td>
<td>CD40</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>CD40 molecule, TNF receptor superfamily member 5</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LY86</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Lymphocyte antigen 86</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>APOL6</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Apolipoprotein L, 6</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GIT2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>G protein-coupled receptor kinase interacting ArfGAP 2</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFITM1</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Interferon induced transmembrane protein 1 (9-27)</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PLEK</td>
<td>−1.5</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Pleckstrin</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="5">Transcription</td>
<td>IRF1</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Interferon regulatory factor 1</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ISY1</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>ISY1 splicing factor homolog (<italic>Saccharomyces  cerevisiae</italic>)</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>POLR3C</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Polymerase (RNA) III (DNA directed) polypeptide C (62kD)</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SP100</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>SP100 nuclear antigen</td>
<td>Nucleus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SOD2</td>
<td>−1.7</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Superoxide dismutase 2, mitochondrial</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Transport</td>
<td>C1QA</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, A chain</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QB</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.5</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, B chain</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AKR1C1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Aldo-keto reductase family 1, member C1 (dihydrodiol dehydrogenase 1; 20-alpha (3-alpha)-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>APOL6</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Apolipoprotein L, 6</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="13">Unassigned</td>
<td>C10ORF12</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Chromosome 10 open reading frame 12</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CLEC12B</td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>C-type lectin domain family 12, member B</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CLMN</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.7</td>
<td>Calmin (calponin-like, transmembrane)</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FGFR1OP2</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>FGFR1 oncogene partner 2</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IDO1</td>
<td>−1.7</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1</td>
<td>Cytoplasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>INGX</td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Inhibitor of growth family, X-linked, pseudogene</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LOC286370</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>Hypothetical LOC286370</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MTPAP</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Mitochondrial poly(A) polymerase</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MUTED</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−0.8</td>
<td>Muted homolog (mouse)</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NKG7</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Natural killer cell group 7 sequence</td>
<td>Plasma membrane</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SLC43A3</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Solute carrier family 43, member 3</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TMPRSS15</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td>Transmembrane protease, serine 15</td>
<td>Extracellular space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WDR37</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>WD repeat domain 37</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1933719112440051">
<p>Abbreviation: GO: gene ontology</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table5-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Overrepresented GO Terms Among Placental Transcripts Highly Expressed in Less Muscular Women Versus Women With High Arm Muscle Area</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="2">Fold Change</th>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>GO Term</th>
<th>Gene Symbol</th>
<th>H vs M</th>
<th>H vs L</th>
<th>Gene Name</th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic> Value<sup>a</sup>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="13">Immune system process</td>
<td>HLA-DRB1</td>
<td>−2.5</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>Major histocompatibility complex, class II, DR beta 1</td>
<td rowspan="13">.00001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMB9</td>
<td>−2.0</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 9 (large multifunctional peptidase 2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMB8</td>
<td>−1.8</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 8 (large multifunctional peptidase 7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QA</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, A chain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFI35</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>Interferon-induced protein 35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD40</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>CD40 molecule, TNF receptor superfamily member 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QB</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.5</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, B chain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LY86</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Lymphocyte antigen 86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFITN1</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Interferon-induced transmembrane protein 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FYB</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td> FYN-binding protein</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LST1</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Leukocyte specific transcript 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICOS</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Inducible T-cell costimulator</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GBP6</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Guanylate-binding protein family, member 6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="13">Immune response</td>
<td>HLA-DRB1</td>
<td>−2.5</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>Major histocompatibility complex, class II, DR beta 1</td>
<td rowspan="13">&lt;.00001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMB9</td>
<td>−2.0</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 9 (large multifunctional peptidase 2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSMB8</td>
<td>−1.8</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 8 (large multifunctional peptidase 7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QA</td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, A chain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFI35</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>Interferon-induced protein 35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CD40</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>CD40 molecule, TNF receptor superfamily member 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C1QB</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.5</td>
<td>Complement component 1, q subcomponent, B chain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LY86</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Lymphocyte antigen 86</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IFITN1</td>
<td>−1.3</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>Interferon-induced transmembrane protein 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FYB</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>FYN-binding protein</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LST1</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Leukocyte specific transcript 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICOS</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Inducible T-cell costimulator</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GBP6</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td>Guanylate-binding protein family, member 6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn8-1933719112440051">
<p>Abbreviation: GO: gene ontology.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-1933719112440051">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> <italic>P</italic> value is corrected for multiple comparisons and dependencies among GO terms (Yekutieli correction).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig5-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Superoxide dismutase (SOD)-2 immunostaining of term placental sections from women with high, average, or low arm muscle area (AMA). SOD-2 localizes to villous trophoblasts (arrow). Photomicrograph using Leica microscope and ×10 objective. Stain is brown and sections are counterstained with hematoxylin. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 versus high muscle mass by Student <italic>t</italic> test. N = 5-7 per group; H, high maternal AMA; M, mid maternal AMA; L, low maternal AMA.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig5-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1933719112440051">
<title>Histologic Examination</title>
<p>To further explore the observed differences in immune response gene expression, a pathologist blinded to groupings reviewed histologic sections of placentas from each AMA group. Histological analysis did not reveal any significant difference in the frequency of chronic inflammation (chronic villitis) or acute inflammation (acute chorioamnionitis) between groups. To increase the sensitivity to detect differences in immune cells, placentas were also immunostained for lineage-specific markers of macrophages (CD68), neutrophils (CD64), T cells (CD3), and B cells (CD20). No differences were identified between groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1933719112440051">Figure 6</xref>). </p>
<fig id="fig6-1933719112440051" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Ingenuity pathway analysis (IPA) displaying regulatory relationships among highly expressed (green) and lower (red) placental transcripts in less muscular women as compared with women with high arm muscle area. Symbol shapes denote the type of protein encoded by the transcript. Uncolored symbols represent transcripts relevant to the pathway but not differentially expressed according to microarray analysis. </p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig6-1933719112440051" xlink:href="10.1177_1933719112440051-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1933719112440051">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This study compared placental transcriptomes across the range of muscularity in 3 quintile groups of mothers. We found that levels of placental immune response gene transcripts were higher in women in the middle and lowest quintiles of prepregnant AMA compared with the upper quintile. Of the ∼100 genes with lower expression within the lower AMA groups, no particular functional pathway or gene ontology was over- or underrepresented. In contrast, 18% of the ∼60 genes that were highly expressed in less muscular women were involved in immune system processes, and many were related to the IFNG-signaling pathway. While the biological meaning of this finding is uncertain, we speculate that placentas from the lower muscle mass women would be more sensitive to the actions of cytokines and especially to those that stimulate inflammatory processes.</p>
<sec id="section17-1933719112440051">
<title>Maternal Muscle Mass and Placental Immune Response</title>
<p>Muscle mass is a key regulator of metabolism,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112440051">1</xref>
</sup> and as maternal metabolic capacity has an important influence on placental function, fetal growth, and development,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1933719112440051">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1933719112440051"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112440051">19</xref>
</sup> we hypothesized that women with high and low muscle mass would have unique placental gene expression profiles. One key finding of this study was that placental immune response pathways were stimulated among women with lower muscle mass. Excessive activation of inflammatory molecules within the placenta has been associated with preeclampsia, fetal growth restriction, preterm labor, and fetal death.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112440051">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112440051">19</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1933719112440051"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1933719112440051"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1933719112440051"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1933719112440051">23</xref>
</sup> Additionally, maternal obesity and diabetes (conditions of altered metabolic capacity) are associated with placental inflammation.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112440051">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112440051">19</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>We found increased expression levels in a number of genes that are regulated by IFNG in placentas of less muscular women. The IFNG is a proinflammatory cytokine that plays an important role in activating cellular immunity and apoptosis. It is important for normal reproduction including  successful implantation and establishment of pregnancy in mice.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1933719112440051">24</xref>
</sup> We would not characterize the placentas from the lower muscle mass women as “inflamed” because we did not find histologic evidence of acute or chronic inflammation or immune cell infiltration in placentas from any group. We did not expect to find obvious signs of inflammation in these term placentas from uncomplicated pregnancies. Roberts et al found high inflammatory gene expression within placentas of nonpreeclamptic, nondiabetic obese women, without detecting an influx of leukocytes in the chorionic villi.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1933719112440051">25</xref>
</sup> We suggest that the high expression of IFNG-regulated genes in placentas of less muscular women indicates the activation of inflammatory pathways that may have significant downstream effects on other placental pathways. At first glance, our observations in placentas of lean, less muscular women seem to contradict previous findings that women with the highest BMI have the highest levels of placental inflammation.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112440051">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112440051">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1933719112440051">25</xref>
</sup> However, placental inflammatory signatures differ between obese women with and without gestational diabetes,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1933719112440051">19</xref>
</sup> between lean women with and without preeclampsia<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1933719112440051">20</xref>
</sup> and between lean and severely obese women,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1933719112440051">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1933719112440051">25</xref>
</sup> suggesting along with our data that different maternal phenotypes and pregnancy conditions are associated with unique placental gene expression patterns. Although recent studies have focused on the poor outcomes associated with maternal obesity, the negative effects associated with maternal thinness, which are supported by our current findings, have also been reported.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1933719112440051">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1933719112440051">26</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Several of the immune response genes that were highly expressed in low AMA placentas are known to be regulated by IFNG including <italic>IFI27</italic> (interferon-α inducible protein 27<italic>)</italic>, <italic>IFI35 </italic>(interferon-induced protein 35), <italic>GBP6</italic> (guanylate-binding protein family member 6), <italic>IFITM2</italic> (interferon-induced transmembrane protein 2), and<italic> IRF1 </italic>(interferon regulatory factor 1). The latter is a transcription factor, activated by IFNG signaling through the JAK/STAT1 pathway,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1933719112440051">27</xref>
</sup> that stimulates the transcription of major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class 1a and II molecules as well as <italic>GBP6</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1933719112440051">
<italic>
<sup>24</sup>
</italic>
</xref>
<sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1933719112440051">27</xref>
</sup> Furthermore, we found that expression of the MHC class II β chain gene (<italic>HLA-DRB1</italic>) and proteasome subunit beta type 8 and 9 (<italic>PSMB8</italic> and <italic>PSMB9</italic>), located in the class II region of MHC, were highest in placentas of women with lower muscle mass. Although MHC class II genes are not expressed by the trophoblast, they are constitutively expressed in leukocytes<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1933719112440051">28</xref>
</sup>; either maternal or fetal immune cells are likely sources of <italic>HLA-DRB1</italic> mRNA. The trophoblast mimics immune cell behavior by monitoring the surrounding environment and communicating with local leukocytes to protect the fetus from infection.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1933719112440051">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1933719112440051">29</xref>
</sup> Although not associated with an influx of immune cells, the high levels of IFNG-responsive genes detected in placentas of lower muscle mass women may signify an increased sensitivity of maternal or fetal leukocytes, trophoblast, or endothelial cells to inflammatory cytokines.</p>
<p>Three immune response genes were lower in placentas of lower AMA women  compared with those with high AMA: the NF-kappaB subunit <italic>RELA</italic> (transcription factor p65),<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1933719112440051">30</xref>
</sup> <italic>IRF5</italic> (interferon responsive factor 5)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1933719112440051">31</xref>
</sup> a protein known to influence inflammatory macrophage polarization,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1933719112440051">32</xref>
</sup> and CD40<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1933719112440051">33</xref>
</sup> required for activation of antigen-presenting cells. Expression of all 3 of these genes is responsive to IFNG. Despite seeing numerous changes in IFNG-responsive genes, we did not detect differences in the expression of the <italic>IFNG</italic> gene itself in the placentas of women with lower AMA groups compared with the high-AMA group. We speculate that many of the highly expressed IFNG-related genes in the lower muscle mass women have high expression in response to circulating IFNG or the stimuli from unknown maternal chemical cues related to low maternal muscularity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1933719112440051">11</xref>
</sup> Alternatively, the placenta, maternal, or fetal immune cells may be sensitive to altered metabolism (glucose homeostasis) in women with lower muscle mass leading to the stimulation of IFNG-related genes, as found in other tissues.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1933719112440051">34</xref>
</sup> Although altered glucose homeostasis is typically studied in the setting of obesity, several studies have found an association between altered glucose metabolism, thinness, and low muscle mass.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1933719112440051">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1933719112440051">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1933719112440051">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1933719112440051">35</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1933719112440051">
<title>Nutrient-Sensitive Signaling Pathways</title>
<p>Lewis et al found that maternal muscle mass was positively correlated with placental system A amino acid transport activity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1933719112440051">11</xref>
</sup> The authors proposed that placentas of muscular women “sense” a metabolic or endocrine factor released by maternal skeletal muscle that leads to enhanced amino acid transport. Amino acid transport activity is known to be regulated by mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1933719112440051">36</xref>
</sup> The mTOR signaling pathway is responsive to glucose, insulin, and amino acid levels and is important in regulating nutrient uptake and transport.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1933719112440051">36</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1933719112440051"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1933719112440051">38</xref>
</sup> mTOR is potently activated by the binding of the guanosine triphosphatase (GTPase) RHEB.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1933719112440051">39</xref>
</sup> High levels of RHEB stimulate the mTOR pathway.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1933719112440051">39</xref>
</sup> We found that placental RHEB mRNA expression was 20-fold higher in women with high muscle mass as compared with less muscular women. Thus, increases in RHEB may underlie the positive relationship between placental system A amino acid transport activity and high muscle mass in pregnant women and vice versa.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1933719112440051">11</xref>
</sup> </p>
<p>We did not detect differences in system A amino acid transporter (SNATs) expression between maternal AMA groups. This is consistent with the findings of Lewis et al that placental SNAT mRNA expression did not mirror activity levels.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1933719112440051">11</xref>
</sup> Their findings suggest that the placental transport activity for system A amino acids is sensitive to maternal muscularity; this may be driven by changes in the mTOR signaling pathway, independent of concomitant alterations in <italic>SNAT</italic> gene expression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1933719112440051">
<title>Placental Antioxidant Expression is Related to Maternal Muscle Mass</title>
<p>Lower levels of the antioxidant SOD-2 were found in placentas of women with high AMA as compared with less muscular women. This dismutase binds the superoxide anion, a natural product of oxidative phosphorylation, and catalyzes the conversion to hydrogen peroxide and diatomic oxygen which protects the cell from damage from reactive oxygen species.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1933719112440051">40</xref>
</sup> The interpretation of this finding is unclear. While decreased antioxidant levels may indicate a response to chronic oxidative stress reviewed by Myatt and Cui,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1933719112440051">41</xref>
</sup> others have shown that genes for antioxidants, such as SOD2, are upregulated in response to increases in pro-oxidant molecules and that low levels indicate a low demand for antioxidant action.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1933719112440051">42</xref>
</sup> Further experiments are needed to determine the relationship between maternal muscularity and placental oxidant/antioxidant status. </p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1933719112440051">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Arm muscle area is a validated measure of muscle mass,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1933719112440051">13</xref>
</sup> but we cannot exclude the possibility that other maternal factors which are also different among AMA groups could be contributory. Based on anthropometric measures, it is not possible to cleanly separate different aspects of maternal body composition, and future studies may confirm these findings through dual energy x-ray absorptiometry in women before or after pregnancy. Groups of 10 women with the highest, lowest, and mid quintiles of AMA were chosen for analysis. Information may have been lost by grouping the data in this manner rather than analyzing AMA as a continuous variable against gene expression. Although the differences in SOD2 expression were confirmed using immunohistochemical techniques, protein levels of the remaining differentially expressed genes were not investigated in this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1933719112440051">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>We have shown that placentas from women with high and average/low prepregnancy maternal muscle masses are distinguished by their unique gene expression signatures. High maternal muscularity is associated with placental gene expression profiles that promote amino acid transport. Our findings suggest that placentas of less muscular women have gene expression patterns that suggest cytokine stimulation and that these placentas would be more vulnerable to the effects of proinflammatory cytokines, such as IFNG, compared with mothers with high muscle mass.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors would like to thank Kristina Vartanian, Michelle Garred, and Chris Harrington of the OHSU Gene Microarray Shared Resource for valuable advice regarding microarrays. In addition, we thank Cara Poage and Carolyn Gendron of OHSU Histopathology Shared Resource for technical assistance in preparation of samples for histologic analysis.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1933719112440051">
<label>Author’s Note</label>
<p>KT, KG, RL, DB, GB, and MH designed and initiated the study. PFO, TKM, and SM were involved in data analysis. KG, CC, HMI, and the Southampton Women’s Survey study group designed and/or implemented aspects of the Southampton Women’s Survey from which the tissues were collected and prepregnancy measurements were made. RML collected the tissues and performed the RNA extraction. All authors were involved in the writing of the manuscript.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-1933719112440051">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1933719112440051">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: PFO is supported by the National Institute of Child Health &amp; Development (1K99HD062841-01). KG is supported by the National Institute for Health Research through the Southampton NIHR Nutrition, Diet &amp; Lifestyle Biomedical Research Unit. SKM is supported by the National Institutes of Health, National Center for Research Resources (5UL1RR024140) and National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute (5 P30 CA069533-13). TKM is supported in part by the Office of Research on Women’s Health and the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, Oregon (BIRCWH HD043488-08). This work was also supported by the National Heart Lung and Blood Institute (HL048546 [GB]), National Cancer Institute (CA138237 [GB]), Department of Veterans Affairs (GB), Edwards Endowment (KLT), British Heart Foundation (MH), Medical Research Council (CC, HI, KG) and Arthritis Research UK (CC).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1933719112440051">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eriksson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Forsen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuomilehto</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osmond</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Size at birth, fat-free mass and resting metabolic rate in adult life</article-title>. <source>Horm Metab Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1933719112440051">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hales</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fall</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Type 2 (non-insulin-dependent) diabetes mellitus, hypertension and hyperlipidaemia (syndrome X): relation to reduced fetal growth</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1933719112440051">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Workman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bedrick</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frey</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hurtado</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Brains versus brawn: an empirical test of Barker's brain sparing model</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1933719112440051">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jansson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pettersson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haafiz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Down-regulation of placental transport of amino acids precedes the development of intrauterine growth restriction in rats fed a low protein diet</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>576</volume>(<issue>Pt 3</issue>):<fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>946</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1933719112440051">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shiell</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diet in late pregnancy and glucose-insulin metabolism of the offspring 40 years later</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>890</fpage>–<lpage>895</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1933719112440051">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Law</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osmond</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of infant birthweight and maternal body mass index in pregnancy on components of the insulin resistance syndrome in China</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1933719112440051">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Challier</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bintein</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity in pregnancy stimulates macrophage accumulation and inflammation in the placenta</article-title>. <source>Placenta</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1933719112440051">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woollett</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barbour</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prasad</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Powell</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-fat diet before and during pregnancy causes marked up-regulation of placental nutrient transport and fetal overgrowth in C57/BL6 mice</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1933719112440051">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>VH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLea</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heizer</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Myatt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of increasing maternal body mass index on oxidative and nitrative stress in the human placenta</article-title>. <source>Placenta</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1933719112440051">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ramsay</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greer</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caslake</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferrell</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal assessment of maternal endothelial function and markers of inflammation and placental function throughout pregnancy in lean and obese mothers</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>969</fpage>–<lpage>975</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1933719112440051">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenwood</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cleal</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal muscle mass may influence system A activity in human placenta</article-title>. <source>Placenta</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1933719112440051">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Inskip</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Godfrey</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cohort profile: The Southampton Women's Survey</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1933719112440051">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heymsfield</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McManus</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nixon</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anthropometric measurement of muscle mass: revised equations for calculating bone-free arm muscle area</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1933719112440051">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Benjamini</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hochberg</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc B</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1933719112440051">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beissbarth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Speed</surname>
<given-names>TP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>GOstat: find statistically overrepresented gene ontologies within a group of genes</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1464</fpage>–<lpage>1465</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1933719112440051">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reiner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yekutieli</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benjamini</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Identifying differentially expressed genes using false discovery rate controlling procedures</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1933719112440051">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boney</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verma</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vohr</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome in childhood: association with birth weight, maternal obesity, and gestational diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e290</fpage>–<lpage>e296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1933719112440051">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Catalano</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Presley</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Minium</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hauguel-de Mouzon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fetuses of obese mothers develop insulin resistance in utero</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1076</fpage>–<lpage>1080</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1933719112440051">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Radaelli</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Varastehpour</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Catalano</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hauguel-de Mouzon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gestational diabetes induces placental genes for chronic stress and inflammatory pathways</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2951</fpage>–<lpage>2958</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1933719112440051">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sitras</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paulssen</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gronaas</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Differential placental gene expression in severe preeclampsia</article-title>. <source>Placenta</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1933719112440051">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mestan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Matoba</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Placental inflammatory response is associated with poor neonatal growth: preterm birth cohort study</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e891</fpage>–<lpage>e898</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1933719112440051">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Salafia</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ernst</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pezzullo</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wolf</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosenkrantz</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vintzileos</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The very low birthweight infant: maternal complications leading to preterm birth, placental lesions, and intrauterine growth</article-title>. <source>Am J Perinatol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1933719112440051">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tayade</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Croy</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A review of gene expression in porcine endometrial lymphocytes, endothelium and trophoblast during pregnancy success and failure</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Dev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1933719112440051">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tayade</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ashkar</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hatta</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Croy</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interferon gamma in successful pregnancies</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>848</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1933719112440051">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riley</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Placental structure and inflammation in pregnancies associated with obesity</article-title>. <source>Placenta</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1933719112440051">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ravelli</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van der Meulen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Michels</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Glucose tolerance in adults after prenatal exposure to famine</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>351</volume>(<issue>9097</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1933719112440051">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kroger</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koster</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schroeder</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Activities of IRF-1</article-title>. <source>J Interferon Cytokine Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1933719112440051">
<label>28</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holtz</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of major histocompatibility complex class II gene expression in trophoblast cells</article-title>. <source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>52</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1933719112440051">
<label>29</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mor</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation and pregnancy: the role of toll-like receptors in trophoblast-immune interaction</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>1127(1)</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1933719112440051">
<label>30</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YQ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ghosh</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Crystal structure of p50/p65 heterodimer of transcription factor NF-kappaB bound to DNA</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>391</volume>(<issue>6665</issue>):<fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1933719112440051">
<label>31</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Takaoka</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yanai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kondo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Integral role of IRF-5 in the gene induction programme activated by Toll-like receptors</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>434</volume>(<issue>7030</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1933719112440051">
<label>32</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krausgruber</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blazek</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smallie</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>IRF5 promotes inflammatory macrophage polarization and TH1-TH17 responses</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1933719112440051">
<label>33</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>VT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benveniste</surname>
<given-names>EN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of STAT-1 and ets family members in interferon-gamma induction of CD40 transcription in microglia/macrophages</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>275</volume>(<issue>31</issue>):<fpage>23674</fpage>–<lpage>23684</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1933719112440051">
<label>34</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nareika</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sundararaj</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Im</surname>
<given-names>YB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Game</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lopes-Virella</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High glucose and interferon gamma synergistically stimulate MMP-1 expression in U937 macrophages by increasing transcription factor STAT1 activity</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>202</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1933719112440051">
<label>35</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Srikanthan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karlamangla</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relative muscle mass is inversely associated with insulin resistance and prediabetes. Findings from the third national health and nutrition examination survey</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2898</fpage>–<lpage>2903</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1933719112440051">
<label>36</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roos</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Palmberg</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mammalian target of rapamycin in the human placenta regulates leucine transport and is down-regulated in restricted fetal growth</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>582</volume>(<issue>pt 1</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1933719112440051">
<label>37</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roos</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Powell</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Placental mTOR links maternal nutrient availability to fetal growth</article-title>. <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>pt 1</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1933719112440051">
<label>38</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roos</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kanai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prasad</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Powell</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of placental amino acid transporter activity by mammalian target of rapamycin</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>296</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>C142</fpage>–<lpage>C150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1933719112440051">
<label>39</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Inoki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rheb GTPase is a direct target of TSC2 GAP activity and regulates mTOR signaling</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1829</fpage>–<lpage>1834</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1933719112440051">
<label>40</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>St Clair</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of superoxide dismutase genes: implications in disease</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1933719112440051">
<label>41</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Myatt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress in the placenta</article-title>. <source>Histochem Cell Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>122</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1933719112440051">
<label>42</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lyall</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greer</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brockman</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eis</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Myatt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increased nitrotyrosine in the diabetic placenta: evidence for oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1753</fpage>–<lpage>1758</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>