<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sperg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Ergonomics in Design: The Quarterly of Human Factors Applications</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1064-8046</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1064804612449124</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1064804612449124</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Departments</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Books</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Designing for Older Adults: Principles and Creative Human Factors Approaches (2nd ed.)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>Carryl</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>29</fpage>
<lpage>29</lpage>
<product>
<source>Designing for Older Adults: Principles and Creative Human Factors Approaches (2nd ed.)</source> By <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>Arthur D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>Wendy A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charness</surname><given-names>Neil</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czaja</surname><given-names>Sara J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharit</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>, <page-count count="277"/> pages, <price>$69.95</price> <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name> ISBN <isbn>978-1420-0805-51</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Books is edited by Gerald P. Krueger. To suggest recently published books for review, or to volunteer as an <italic>EID</italic> book reviewer, please contact him at <email>jerrykrueg@aol.com</email>.</p>
<p><italic>Designing for Older Adults</italic> provides accessible coverage of a broad range of important usability topics. Core concepts in virtually all aspects of designing for older adults are covered. These topics range from sensory, cognitive, and motor challenges associated with increased age to methods of improving training and designing products, systems, and interfaces that match these capabilities to the extent possible. The book presents in-depth coverage of essential information, providing tutorials on key areas such as conducting research with older adults, usability testing, task analyses, and user-centered design. For these reasons it will be of interest to a wide audience.</p>
<p>The book begins with a rationale for why there is a need to design products and systems with older adults in mind. That explanation is followed by a solid review of the sensory and cognitive challenges faced by older adults and the ramifications of those challenges for usability, including a description of major concepts and principles in the design process, particularly, usability testing. Detailed design guidelines address age-related changes in sensory acuity and provide suggestions for how to enhance the perceptual capabilities of older adults. Perceptibility – the ability to see, hear, or feel the interface – is essential to its usability. The authors discuss important guidelines for the design of input and output devices that enhance the capabilities of older users. The theme of age-related changes in sensory, cognitive, and motor capabilities is carried throughout this discussion, and an ample number of examples facilitate the understanding of these concepts.</p>
<p>Interface design is a key concept throughout the book. Use of computers and advanced technologies is prevalent in the everyday lives of older adults (e.g., automated teller machines at banks, home appliances, and automated messaging systems). Older adults have become more reliant on these systems to maintain functional independence. The book provides guidelines for age-friendly interface design, including methods of reducing the memory load required by these devices, supporting older adults’ mental models of devices, and organizing information so as to minimize the required number of cognitive operations.</p>
<p>The relevance of the book’s design guidelines is illustrated in four main areas: work, health care, transportation, and home design. Each area presents a critical need for considering the capabilities of older adults in the design process, and the authors provide solid examples of how the material presented can be applied to everyday work, leisure, and home environments. They demonstrate design guidelines to facilitate things such as finding health care information on the Internet and wayfinding in airports. The book’s tutorials on key design aspects are particularly innovative.</p>
<p>The authors comprehensively cover these broad topics without sacrificing the level of detail that designers need. Students and researchers will benefit from both the range of issues covered as well as ample references and documented examples of guidelines based on empirical research. Each chapter contains a recommended reading list to guide readers who wish to gain a deeper understanding of particular topics.</p>
<p>The book makes a valuable addition to the library of anyone interested in the design process. As the authors point out, good design for older adults is generally good design for everyone.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Carryl Baldwin</bold> is an assistant professor in the Psychology Department at George Mason University in Fairfax, Virginia. Her research interests are in the area of applied auditory cognition. Together with her Auditory Research Group, she investigates the human performance implications of factors that affect the interaction of sensory and cognitive processes in young and older adults. She can be reached at <email>cbaldwi4@gmu.edu</email>.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>