<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsjp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1403-4948</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1651-1905</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494812455113</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1403494812455113</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Referral from primary to secondary care in Germany: Developing a taxonomy based on cluster analysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1403494812455113">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Träger</surname><given-names>Susanne</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1403494812455113">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bösner</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ilhan</surname><given-names>Muazzez</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Annette</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>Erika</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Donner-Banzhoff</surname><given-names>Norbert</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1403494812455113">Department of General Practice/Family Medicine, University of Marburg, Marburg, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1403494812455113">Oliver Hirsch, Department of General Practice/Family Medicine Philipps University Marburg, Karl-von-Frisch-Str.4, D-35043 Marburg/Germany. E-mail <email>oliver.hirsch@staff.uni-marburg.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1403494812455113">
<label>*</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this paper.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>571</fpage>
<lpage>578</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>26</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 the Nordic Societies of Public Health</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Associations of Public Health in the Nordic Countries Regions</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Aims</italic>: Referrals from primary to secondary care may differ regarding motivation and initiative. Previous research on the frequency and variation of referrals has mostly treated referrals as homogeneous. We intended to develop a taxonomy regarding referrals from primary to secondary care in Germany that could support decision making on a macro level. <italic>Methods</italic>: We analyzed 3,988 referrals by 29 German general practitioners (GPs). GPs were asked to document all referrals during one week; in subsequent audits they stated the reasons and initiative for any referral. We postulated the following five referral types: clinical problem, shared care, administrative, patient initiated and shared cost. The data were analyzed with k-means cluster analysis. <italic>Results</italic>: We identified three of our five postulated referral types with cluster analytic techniques: shared care, clinical problem, and patient initiated. This solution accounted for 11.7% of total variance. The majority of referrals in German primary care practices were initiated by the GP, or they were part of a shared decision with patients. <bold><italic>Conclusions</italic>: We suggest a taxonomy of referrals that might offer insights regarding the allocation of resources within the German health system. Referrals might be reduced by improved training of primary care physicians and by giving them more competencies in routine care of chronic patients.</bold></p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cluster analysis</kwd>
<kwd>primary care physicians</kwd>
<kwd>referral and consultation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1403494812455113" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The role of primary care physicians in the Western world is that of gate keepers and coordinators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812455113">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1403494812455113">2</xref>], and it is therefore not only in Germany that general practitioners (GPs) play an important role in the allocation of resources. Within Germany’s healthcare system there is a high number of physician-patient contacts per year. They add up to 7.1 consultations per year for GPs, and 17.9 for any physician in ambulatory care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812455113">3</xref>]. In Germany, physicians that operate their independent surgeries are either GPs or specialists. Basic characteristics of the German health system are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1403494812455113">Table I</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1403494812455113">4</xref>].</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1403494812455113" position="float">
<label>Table I.</label>
<caption>
<p>Basic characteristics of the German health system.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1403494812455113" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812455113-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>• Primary care physicians are not gatekeepers. Patients have direct access to primary and secondary care specialists.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>• About three quarters of primary and secondary care physicians have solo practices.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>• Half of office-based physicians are GPs.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>• Patients must pay a consultation fee of 10€ at the first physician contact in every quarter of a year.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>• Patients who are exempted from the practice fee are allowed to contact a secondary care specialist without referral.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Several studies have examined the referral decisions of primary care physicians. In the US, a referral was made in 5.1% of office visits, and 68% of referrals were made by physicians during office visits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812455113">5</xref>]. A European study on referral behaviour revealed that the number of practice visits and the number of referrals in Germany are higher than in other European countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812455113">6</xref>]. The referral rate was higher in physicians with fewer practice contacts. Most direct referrals (referrals within a consultation with the physician) went to orthopaedic, surgery, and internal medicine. Most indirect referrals (physician signed referrals without personal contact with the patient) were issued to gynaecology, ophthalmology, and otolaryngology specialists. More than half of direct referrals were influenced by patients. Women received more referrals, and about a quarter of direct referrals were issued to patients of 65 years and older. The authors concluded that not much is known about the determinants of referral behaviour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812455113">6</xref>].</p>
<p>In another German study in which only patients with direct physician contact were included, the main goals for referrals were diagnostic clarity, exclusion of serious illness, information on treatment options, and provision of treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812455113">7</xref>]. The vast majority of referrals were considered by external consultants to be justified. Patients preferred the physician to take the initiative for referral. The authors argue in favour of the gatekeeper role of the GP. Similar reasons for referrals are listed by Donohoe et al., but generalists mentioned that one third of referrals could have been avoided by doctors being trained in simple procedures and by communicating with colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812455113">8</xref>]. A Norwegian study found higher referral rates with increasing GP/population ratio, in municipalities with a hospital, and in patients with higher education [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812455113">9</xref>].</p>
<p>Previous research on the frequency and variation of referrals has insufficiently distinguished motives and agents and treated referrals as a more or less homogeneous entity. In the aforementioned studies, reasons for referral and possible causes of variation in referral rates were not examined on a multivariate background to detect underlying patterns. Identification of different referral patterns is, however, relevant for decision making on a macro level regarding the allocation of resources. We considered a typology of referrals useful for future in-depth analyses of research in this area. Therefore, on the basis of the cited literature and experience of the German health system, we postulated the following five referral types: clinical problem, shared care, administrative, patient initiated, and shared cost.</p>
<p>In the clinical problem type, the GP mainly initiates the referral when special investigations or special treatment options are needed; the number of previous referrals is low. Shared care is characterized by a patient being treated by a GP and specialist in parallel. This is especially common in complex and chronic diseases and related therapies. The administrative type consists of referrals to specialties that are accessed directly, such as gynaecology and ophthalmology, for which the GPs in Germany have no standardized training and therefore little expertise. If patients obtain a referral from their GP they can avoid a consultation fee. Specialists can also bill a higher fee when the patient has been formally referred. These referrals are often made without a direct consultation with the GP. In the patient initiated type, referrals are primarily made at the request of an anxious or dissatisfied patient. In the shared cost type, referrals are issued because specialists are expected to prescribe expensive medication or physiotherapy, for example.</p>
<p>These categories show very clearly that referrals can fulfil very heterogenous purposes. In our view, previous research has not differentiated enough between these categories. Therefore, the aim of our study was to examine a large dataset of referrals in primary care with the help of cluster analytic techniques in order to confirm or refute our postulated referral types and to draw conclusions for macro-level decision making in the German health system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1403494812455113" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We performed a cross-sectional study in which a random sample of 33 medical practices in urban and rural areas were asked to participate in our referral study, 29 of which agreed. Over a three month period these 29 practices collected all referrals during one specific week. Data collection was spread equally across the respective quarter because it is known that referral rates are highest at the beginning of a quarter. With the introduction of a consultation fee (10 euros), patients are encouraged to first contact their family physician. If the GP considers a referral is necessary, then the patient does not have to pay this fee again when seeing the respective specialist. Patients can also contact specialists directly without a referral, but they then have to pay the fee each time. Therefore, at the beginning of a quarter many patients ask for referrals from their GP for all kinds of specialist contacts that they may have on a regular basis, which leads to the observed high referral rate. Patients who are exempted from the practice fee are allowed to contact a secondary care specialist without referral. These were not included in our study.</p>
<p>Data collection was randomly distributed among practices at the beginning, in the middle or at the end of a quarter. It took place from the middle of February to the middle of April (middle and end of first quarter and beginning of second quarter).</p>
<p>Participating practices were categorized according to the features of single/group practice, doctor’s age, and rural/urban area. To assess reasons for referral in a physician questionnaire, we offered several possibilities such as diagnostic or therapeutic reasons, allaying the patient’s fear, organizational matters such as patients who are in a special disease management programme (standardized treatment for patients with chronic illnesses on the basis of evidence based medicine), and indirect referrals that were issued on behalf of the specialist (coded as 100% physician initiated) or the patient’s wish (coded as 100% patient initiated). Initiation of referral was measured by using a semantic differential, which is a scale with bipolar limits that represents different poles of an underlying construct. Patients were asked to rate on a 0–100 visual analogue scale taking the initiative of the GP as a reference point for “100” and their own initiative as a reference point for “0” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812455113">10</xref>]. Values larger than 50 therefore represent a higher initiative of the physician, values lower than 50 indicate a higher initiative of the patient. The referred specialty, the patient’s age and gender were also recorded by the physicians.</p>
<p>In an audit about 10 days after data collection, all recorded referrals were reviewed together with the physicians. For each referral the main reason for referral, the number of previous referrals for the same cause in the last two years, the content, quantity and quality of information flow, satisfaction with local healthcare provision, and service of the practice, such as contacting the respective specialist by telephone and attempting to make an appointment, were recorded. This audit was performed by ST, a primary care physician. The discussion about a referral lasted about five minutes on average.</p>
<sec id="section3-1403494812455113">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>We performed k-means cluster analysis generalized to all scales of measurement with squared Euclidean distances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812455113">11</xref>]. The k-means procedure identifies relatively homogenous subgroups while maximizing the variability between clusters. Variables with mixed scaling can be handled in cluster analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812455113">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1403494812455113">12</xref>]. Calculations were done with ALMO 12 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.almo-statistik.de">www.almo-statistik.de</ext-link>), which includes a k-means algorithm that is able to handle the different scaling of our variables and the large sample size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812455113">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812455113">13</xref>]. There are no methods for sample size calculation in cluster analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1403494812455113">14</xref>]. This programme provides statistical measures to evaluate the appropriateness of a cluster solution (F value, eta<sup>2</sup>). It is also possible to evaluate the contribution of single variables to cluster partitioning by eta<sup>2</sup>. The higher eta<sup>2</sup>, the higher the explanatory power. Jaccard and Becker define eta<sup>2</sup> values of .10 and higher as signalling a small to medium effect and eta<sup>2</sup> over .50 as showing a large effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812455113">15</xref>].</p>
<p>Only relevant variables should be included in a cluster analysis. Irrelevant variables can destroy the clustering and prevent an interpretable solution from appearing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1403494812455113">16</xref>]. Consequently, cluster analysis is an iterative process. We therefore ran several analyses and excluded variables with no statistically or theoretically meaningful contribution (eta<sup>2</sup> ≤.001). Variables chosen for the final analysis were location of the practice, gender and age group of patients, number of referrals to the same specialty in the last two years, initiation of referral, reason for referral, and referred speciality.</p>
<p>Although we postulated several distinct referral types, we were not able to perform a confirmatory cluster analysis because algorithms for this type of analysis have barely been established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1403494812455113">17</xref>]. Nevertheless, cluster analysis is the method of choice to search for groups on a patient level on the basis of data with different scaling properties, as in our study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1403494812455113">16</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1403494812455113" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The characteristics of participating physicians are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1403494812455113">Table II</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1403494812455113" position="float">
<label>Table II.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of participating physicians (<italic>n</italic>=43).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1403494812455113" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812455113-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">No. (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Male</td>
<td>28 (65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Female</td>
<td>15 (35)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Age (years)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 31–40</td>
<td>3 (7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 41–50</td>
<td>20 (47)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 51–60</td>
<td>18 (41)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • &gt;60</td>
<td>2 (5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Type of practice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Single handed</td>
<td>14 (33)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Group</td>
<td>28 (65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Partnership</td>
<td>1 (2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Locality</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Urban</td>
<td>20 (47)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Rural</td>
<td>23 (53)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>About two thirds of the physicians are male. Age and gender dispersions are representative for family physicians in Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1403494812455113">18</xref>]. About two thirds work in group practices; urban and rural practices are equally represented.</p>
<p>Descriptive statistics of the classification variables in our cluster analysis are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1403494812455113">Table III</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1403494812455113" position="float">
<label>Table III.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive statistics of classification variables to group the 3,988 referrals in cluster analysis.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1403494812455113" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812455113-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">No. (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Referrals</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Urban</td>
<td>2,057 (51.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Rural</td>
<td>1,931 (48.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Gender (patients)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Male</td>
<td>1,358 (34.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Female</td>
<td>2,630 (66.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Age (patients)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 0–15 years</td>
<td>87 (2.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 16–30 years</td>
<td>560 (14.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 31–45 years</td>
<td>765 (19.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 46–60 years</td>
<td>1,095 (27.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 61–75 years</td>
<td>992 (24.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • 76 years and older</td>
<td>489 (12.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Reason for referral</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Specialist request</td>
<td>237 (5.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Organizational (DMP<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1403494812455113">a</xref></sup>)</td>
<td>154 (3.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Diagnostic</td>
<td>2,138 (53.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Therapeutic</td>
<td>1,006 (25.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Balance budget</td>
<td>90 (2.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Allay patient</td>
<td>204 (5.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • No comment</td>
<td>159 (4.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Referred specialist</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Orthopaedics</td>
<td>446 (11.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Surgery</td>
<td>313 (7.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Radiology</td>
<td>202 (5.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Internal medicine</td>
<td>634 (15.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Otolaryngology</td>
<td>267 (6.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Gynaecology</td>
<td>562 (14.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Dermatology</td>
<td>377 (9.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Ophthalmology</td>
<td>472 (11.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Neurology/psychiatry/psychotherapy</td>
<td>460 (11.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Urology</td>
<td>177 (4.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Anaesthesia/pain therapy</td>
<td>21 (0.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Paediatrics</td>
<td>34 (0.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> • Others</td>
<td>23 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of referrals to same specialty last two years</td>
<td>Mean 2.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>SD 2.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Range 0–10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Initiation of referral</td>
<td>Mean 49.4<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1403494812455113">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>SD 34.3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1403494812455113">
<label>a</label>
<p>Disease-Management-Programm (DMP) is a standardized treatment for patients with chronic illnesses on the basis of evidence-based medicine. <sup>b</sup>Mean represents a balanced initiation of referrals between physicians and patients.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>A three cluster solution was the best way to classify the 3,988 individual referrals and resulted in an F value of 263.49 and an eta<sup>2</sup> of 0.117. This means that 11.7% of the variance can be explained by this partitioning. This cluster solution possesses acceptable quality criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812455113">11</xref>]. The descriptive characteristics of the three clusters are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1403494812455113">Table IV</xref>. The most important variables for cluster partitioning are initiation of referral (eta<sup>2</sup> = 0.594), number of referrals to the same specialist in the past two years (eta<sup>2</sup> = 0.396), and reason for referral (eta<sup>2</sup> = 0.126). Excluded variables (eta<sup>2</sup> ≤0.001) were quantity and quality of information flow, support of the practice regarding appointments with specialists, satisfaction with local healthcare provision, physician’s age, and physician’s gender. The excluded variables were not meaningful regarding their statistical characteristics and their importance with regards to content.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1403494812455113" position="float">
<label>Table IV.</label>
<caption>
<p>Description of the three cluster solution and contribution of the classification variables to cluster partitioning (eta<sup>2</sup>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1403494812455113" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812455113-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Cluster 1 (<italic>n</italic>=1,004)</th>
<th align="left">Cluster 2 (<italic>n</italic>=2,002)</th>
<th align="left">Cluster 3 (<italic>n</italic>=982)</th>
<th align="left">eta<sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Initiation of referral (mean)</td>
<td>49.1</td>
<td>70.9</td>
<td>5.9</td>
<td>0.594</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of referrals to same specialist (mean)</td>
<td>4.81</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.69</td>
<td>0.396</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type of referral</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.126</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Specialist request</td>
<td>3%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>20%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Organizational (DMP<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812455113">a</xref></sup>)</td>
<td>10%</td>
<td>2%</td>
<td>2%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Diagnostic</td>
<td>16%</td>
<td>85%</td>
<td>29%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Therapeutic</td>
<td>63%</td>
<td>12%</td>
<td>13%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Balance budget</td>
<td>8%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Allay patient</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td>19%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No comment</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>16%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patients’ age groups</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 0–15 years</td>
<td>0.1%</td>
<td>3.0%</td>
<td>2.6%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 16–30 years</td>
<td>6.7%</td>
<td>16.7%</td>
<td>16.1%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 31–45 years</td>
<td>14.6%</td>
<td>20.4%</td>
<td>21.4%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 46–60 years</td>
<td>26.0%</td>
<td>27.9%</td>
<td>28.1%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 61–75 years</td>
<td>31.1%</td>
<td>22.3%</td>
<td>23.7%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 76 years and older</td>
<td>21.5%</td>
<td>9.7%</td>
<td>8.0%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Area</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.012</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urban</td>
<td>57%</td>
<td>53%</td>
<td>42%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural</td>
<td>43%</td>
<td>47%</td>
<td>58%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Specialty</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Orthopaedics</td>
<td>8%</td>
<td>11%</td>
<td>14%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Surgery</td>
<td>3%</td>
<td>11%</td>
<td>5%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiology</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>5%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Internal medicine</td>
<td>16%</td>
<td>18%</td>
<td>11%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Otolaryngology</td>
<td>3%</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>9%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gynaecology</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>19%</td>
<td>11%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dermatology</td>
<td>6%</td>
<td>7%</td>
<td>18%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ophthalmology</td>
<td>13%</td>
<td>8%</td>
<td>18%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Neurology/psychiatry/psychotherapy</td>
<td>33%</td>
<td>5%</td>
<td>3%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urology</td>
<td>6%</td>
<td>4%</td>
<td>4%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anaesthesia/pain therapy</td>
<td>2%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Paediatrics</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Others</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>0%</td>
<td>1%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient’s gender</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>41%</td>
<td>32%</td>
<td>30%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>59%</td>
<td>68%</td>
<td>70%</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1403494812455113">
<label>a</label>
<p>A Disease-Management-Programm (DMP) is a standardized treatment for patients with chronic illnesses on the basis of evidence based medicine.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Cluster 1 (<italic>n</italic>=1,004) consists of more urban practices. Most referrals were issued for older people (46 years and over). The predominant reason for referral was therapeutic. The majority of referrals were made to specialists in psychotherapy/psychology/neurology (33%) and to internal medicine (16%). The number of referrals to the same specialists in the past two years was high, indicating a higher chronicity in patients. The initiative regarding referrals was shared between physicians and patients (mean 49.1).</p>
<p>Cluster 2 (<italic>n</italic>=2,002) equally consists of urban and rural practices. Most referrals were issued for patients between 31 and 75 years. The predominant reason for referral was diagnostic. Most referrals went to specialists in gynaecology (19%) and to internal medicine (18%). The number of referrals to the same specialists in the past two years was low, which emphasises the diagnostic nature of referrals. The initiative for referral was dominated by GPs (mean 70.9).</p>
<p>Cluster 3 (<italic>n</italic>=982) consists of more rural practices. Most referrals were issued for patients between 31 and 75 years. The reasons for referral were mixed (diagnostic 29%, specialist request 20%, allay patient 19%). Most referrals went to specialists in ophthalmology and dermatology (18% each) and to orthopaedics (14%). The number of referrals to the same specialists in the past two years was intermediate. The initiative for referral was clearly dominated by patients (mean 5.9).</p>
<p>The main cluster characteristics with regards to content are depicted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1403494812455113">Table V</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1403494812455113" position="float">
<label>Table V.</label>
<caption>
<p>Main characteristics of the three clusters in descending importance regarding their contribution to cluster partitioning.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1403494812455113" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812455113-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Cluster 1 (<italic>n</italic>=1,004)</th>
<th align="left">Cluster 2 (<italic>n</italic>=2,002)</th>
<th align="left">Cluster 3 (<italic>n</italic>=982)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Initiation of referral</td>
<td>Shared</td>
<td>GP</td>
<td>Patient</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of referrals to same specialist</td>
<td>High</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Intermediate</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type of referral</td>
<td>Therapeutic</td>
<td>Diagnostic</td>
<td>Diagnostic, Specialist request, allay the patient</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patients’ age group (years)</td>
<td>46 and older</td>
<td>31–75</td>
<td>31–75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Area</td>
<td>Urban</td>
<td>Equally distributed</td>
<td>Rural</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Specialty</td>
<td>Neurology/psychiatry/psychotherapy, internal medicine</td>
<td>Gynaecology, internal medicine</td>
<td>Dermatology, ophthalmology, orthopaedics</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1403494812455113" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The aim of our study was to search for referral types in a large dataset of referrals in primary care with the help of cluster analytic techniques.</p>
<p>A three cluster solution was best interpretable and possesses acceptable quality criteria with an explained variance of 11.7% (eta<sup>2</sup> =.117). Jaccard and Becker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812455113">15</xref>] consider this to be a small to medium effect, while others regard an eta<sup>2</sup> <underline>≥</underline>0.09 to denote a large effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1403494812455113">19</xref>]. The most important variables for cluster partitioning were initiation of referral, number of referrals to the same specialist in the past two years, and reason for referral. In Cluster 1, we found that the initiative for referrals was shared between physicians and patients. The predominant reason for referral was therapeutic. In Cluster 2, the initiative for referral was dominated by GPs who mainly refer for diagnostic reasons. In Cluster 3, the initiative for referral was clearly dominated by patients.</p>
<p>We were able to find three of our five postulated referral types. Cluster 1 corresponded to our shared care type in which we postulated a shared care between GP and specialist. Patients were mainly referred for therapeutic reasons to the fields of neurology/psychiatry/psychotherapy and internal medicine. The majority were elderly patients with chronic conditions where the evidence for therapeutic measures is often equivocal.</p>
<p>Cluster 2 matched our clinical problem type in which the GP mainly initiates the referral because of diagnostic purposes. The number of previous referrals was low. There may be an overlap with an administrative type because the referral rate for gynaecology was the highest with 19%, but immediately followed by internal medicine with 18%. This referral cluster fitted in with previous findings in the literature that emphasize diagnostic goals as the main purpose for referrals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812455113">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812455113">8</xref>]. The desire for reassurance might be an important factor here, especially in patients with chronic diseases or high comorbidities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1403494812455113">20</xref>].</p>
<p>Cluster 3 corresponded to our postulated patient initiated type in which referrals are primarily made to allay and/or satisfy patients with presumably unexplained symptoms. The main reason for referrals was of a diagnostic nature, requested by the specialist and advocated for by the patient. The main focus was on dermatology, ophthalmology, and orthopaedics. In about a quarter of referrals, this patient initiation was the dominating factor, which is less than in previous German studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812455113">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812455113">7</xref>], but more than in an American study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812455113">5</xref>]. Chenot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1403494812455113">21</xref>] provide non-medical reasons for referrals to orthopaedic surgeons which were mainly based on patient initiative and therefore support the characteristics of patients in our Cluster 3.</p>
<p>We did not find a definitive administrative type with unique features that consists of referrals to specialties for which the GP rarely has expertise (e.g., gynaecology and ophthalmology). The most likely explanation is that in the cluster analysis these specialties are fairly equally distributed among two other categories (clinical problem and patient initiated type) and therefore did not form a category on its own. In the clinical problem type, the GP might realize that there is a lack of expertise in a certain specialty, while in the patient oriented type this initiative might be the result of a discussion between the patient and the specialist. We were also unable to find our hypothesized shared cost type because this referral reason was rarely selected, presumably because of social desirability. Primary care physicians perhaps did not want to admit that they hand over costs to their colleagues in secondary care.</p>
<p>There is considerable variation in the referral rates of GPs. This variation is not satisfactorily explained [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1403494812455113">22</xref>]. It is concluded that patient characteristics explain less than 40%, and practice and GP characteristics less than 10% of the variation. This is further complicated by the fact that there is a lack of consensus about the appropriateness of referrals, and that the use of guidelines was not able to alter referral behaviour. A Dutch study came to the conclusion that patient morbidity explained 45% of the variance in GPs’ referral rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1403494812455113">23</xref>]. A UK study was able to explain just 30% of the variance of the variation in referrals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1403494812455113">24</xref>]. A further result of this study was the high variation in referrals within practices. Level of confidence was the decisive factor that differentiated best between high and low referrers. Inappropriate referrals were not able to explain the variation in referral rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1403494812455113">25</xref>]. It has even been proposed that doctors might have a unique referral threshold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1403494812455113">26</xref>], which would be difficult to trace empirically. It can still be argued that studies were not able to find patient and/or physician characteristics that are associated with variation in referral rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1403494812455113">27</xref>]. Another complicating issue is that the focus of specialists is on those patients who were not referred, although there was an indication to do so (false negatives) and not on those who were not referred and did not have an indication for referral (true negatives) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1403494812455113">28</xref>]. Therefore, the gatekeeper role of primary care is not acknowledged enough.</p>
<p>Our results might have important implications for macro level decisions in the German healthcare system. Inherent in all three types are factors that need not necessarily lead to a referral, e.g. equivocal evidence for therapies in chronic conditions, reassurance, and patient initiative. We therefore are in line with previous studies that come to the conclusion that the rate of referrals to secondary care can be reduced by further training of primary care physicians and by giving them more competencies in routine care of chronic patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812455113">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812455113">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1403494812455113">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1403494812455113">30</xref>]. Valderas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1403494812455113">29</xref>] found that the majority of specialist care was based on routine and preventive care that could also be done in the primary care sector. Consequently, referrals from primary to secondary care should be closely examined to optimize healthcare system-level decisions. A reassessment of the roles of primary and secondary care could therefore be beneficial for a more efficient use of resources within the German healthcare hystem. On the basis of our results referral pathways for different diseases could be established to optimize the referral process from primary to secondary care.</p>
<sec id="section6-1403494812455113">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>The strengths of our study are the large sample size and audits with participating physicians to discuss reasons for referral. Our study has several limitations. We could not differentiate between direct and indirect referrals. The shared cost option was rarely selected, presumably because primary care physicians did not want to admit that they hand over costs to their colleagues in secondary care. The GPs in this investigation had to comment on each referral, so perhaps there was a certain degree of post-hoc justification with regard to the reason for referral. Patients who are exempted from the practice fee are allowed to contact a secondary care specialist without referral. These were not included in our study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1403494812455113" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>We found three referral types with cluster analytic techniques which can be described as shared care, clinical problem, and patient initiated. To our knowledge, this is the first study that has analyzed referral data with such a multivariate and explorative approach. The statistical quality criteria of this solution are acceptable, but one has to consider that the majority of variation in referral behaviour still remains unexplained. We suggest a taxonomy of referrals that has the potential to stimulate future research about the reassessment of the roles of primary and secondary care. The results of our study have to be seen against the background of the German health system. Therefore, our results might apply more in some healthcare systems than in others. The availability of specialists in Germany is quite high, patients have to pay consultation fees, and there is a segmentation of primary care between specialists in that they are also providing certain aspects of primary care.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by the German Federal Ministry of Research and Education, [grant number 01 GK 0701].</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1403494812455113">
<label>[1]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loudon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The principle of referral: the gatekeeping role of the GP</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>; <comment>discussion 30</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1403494812455113">
<label>[2]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bodenheimer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casalino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Primary care physicians should be coordinators, not gatekeepers</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>2045</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1403494812455113">
<label>[3]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grobe</surname><given-names>TGD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Institut für Sozialmedizin, Epidemiologie Gesundheitssystemforschung. GEK-Report ambulant-ärztliche Versorgung 2008. Auswertung der GEK-Gesundheitsberichtserstattung, Schwerpunkt: Erkrankung und zukünftige Ausgaben</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Institute for social medicine, epidemiology, health system research. GEK report on ambulatory medical provision 2008. Analysis of the GEK health report, main focus: disease and future costs</trans-title>.] <publisher-loc>St. Augustin:</publisher-loc> <publisher-name>Asgard-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. p.<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1403494812455113">
<label>[4]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reisberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health care systems in transition: Germany</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Copenhagen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO Regional Office for Europe on behalf of the European Observatory on Health Systems and Policies</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1403494812455113">
<label>[5]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nutting</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Starfield</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Schrader</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Family physicians’ referral decisions: results from the ASPN referral study</article-title>. <source>J Fam Pract</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1403494812455113">
<label>[6]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thies-Zajonc</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Köhle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szecsenyi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Überweisungsverhalten von Hausärzten, Gebietsärzten und Klinikern</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Referral behaviour of primary care physicians, district physicians, and clinicians</trans-title>]. <source>Der Allgemeinarzt</source> <year>1990</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1403494812455113">
<label>[7]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wensing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rueter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szecsenyi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Referrals from general practice to consultants in Germany: if the GP is the initiator, patients’ experiences are more positive</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1403494812455113">
<label>[8]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donohoe</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kravitz</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reasons for outpatient referrals from generalists to specialists</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1403494812455113">
<label>[9]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fylkesnes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Determinants of health care utilization – visits and referrals</article-title>. <source>Scand J Soc Med</source> <year>1993</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1403494812455113">
<label>[10]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measurement of subjective phenomena in primary care research: the Visual Analogue Scale</article-title>. <source>Fam Pract Res J</source> <year>1993</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1403494812455113">
<label>[11]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pöge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wenzig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clusteranalyse. Anwendungsorientierte Einführung in Klassifikationsverfahren</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Cluster analysis. Practical introduction in classification measures</trans-title>]. <publisher-loc>Munich</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oldenbourg</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1403494812455113">
<label>[12]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schendera</surname><given-names>CFG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clusteranalyse mit SPSS: Mit Faktorenanalyse</article-title>. [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Cluster analysis with SPSS: including factor analysis</trans-title>]. <publisher-loc>Munich</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oldenbourg</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1403494812455113">
<label>[13]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laatz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Statistische Datenanalyse mit SPSS für Windows</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Statistical data analysis with SPSS for Windows</trans-title>.]. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1403494812455113">
<label>[14]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Romesburg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cluster analysis for researchers</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Morrisville</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lulu</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1403494812455113">
<label>[15]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Statistics for the behavioral sciences</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Belmont</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1403494812455113">
<label>[16]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rousseeuw</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Finding groups in data</article-title>. <source>An introduction to cluster analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1403494812455113">
<label>[17]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Making sense of statistical methods in social research</article-title>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1403494812455113">
<label>[18]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Bundesärztekammer</collab>. <article-title>Tätigkeitsbericht 2010 der Bundesärztekammer</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">2010 Proceedings of the German Medical Association</trans-title>]. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bundesärztekammer</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1403494812455113">
<label>[19]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1403494812455113">
<label>[20]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piterman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koritsas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Part II. General practitioner-specialist referral process</article-title>. <source>Intern Med J</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1403494812455113">
<label>[21]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chenot</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kochen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Himmel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. [<article-title>Communication and exchange of clinical findings for low back pain between general practitioners and orthopaedic surgeons: a retrospective observational study</article-title>]. <source>Schmerz</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1403494812455113">
<label>[22]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Donnell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Variation in GP referral rates: what can we learn from the literature?</article-title> <source>Fam Pract</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1403494812455113">
<label>[23]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Delnoij</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spreeuwenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Variation in GP’s referral rates to specialists in internal medicine</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1403494812455113">
<label>[24]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ambler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Case-mix and variation in specialist referrals in general practice</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1403494812455113">
<label>[25]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fertig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Understanding variation in rates of referral among general practitioners: are inappropriate referrals important and would guidelines help to reduce rates?</article-title> <source>BMJ</source> <year>1993</year>;<volume>307</volume>:<fpage>1467</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1403494812455113">
<label>[26]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Do general practitioners have different “referral thresholds”?</article-title> <source>Br Med J (Clin Res Ed)</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>1037</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1403494812455113">
<label>[27]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilkin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Explaining variation in general practitioner referrals to hospital</article-title>. <source>Fam Pract</source> <year>1987</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1403494812455113">
<label>[28]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knottnerus</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Between iatrotropic stimulus and interiatric referral: the domain of primary care research</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1403494812455113">
<label>[29]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Valderas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Starfield</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sibbald</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ambulatory care provided by office-based specialists in the United States</article-title>. <source>Ann Fam Med</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1403494812455113">
<label>[30]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donohoe</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparing generalist and specialty care: discrepancies, deficiencies, and excesses</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>158</volume>:<fpage>1596</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>