<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OPP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spopp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Oncol Pharm Pract</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Oncology Pharmacy Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-1552</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-092X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078155212451936</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078155212451936</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A controlled before and after study to evaluate a patient and health professional partnership model towards effective medication reconciliation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lingaratnam</surname><given-names>Senthil</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1078155212451936"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1078155212451936">Pharmacy Department, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>Sanchia</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1078155212451936">Department of Nursing and Supportive Care Research, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia; School of Nursing and Social Work, Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences, The University of Melbourne, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>Tracy</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1078155212451936">Nursing Administration, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kirsa</surname><given-names>Sue</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff4-1078155212451936">Pharmacy Department, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078155212451936">Senthil Lingaratnam, Pharmacy Department, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Smorgon Family Building, St Andrew's Place, Melbourne 3002, Australia. Email: <email>Senthil.Lingaratnam@petermac.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>48</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Preventable medication errors impact substantially on the Australian healthcare system. Where ‘poor communication of medical information at transition points is responsible for as many as 50% of all medication errors’, a leading contributor for this type of medication error is lack of consumer knowledge about medicines information. This study was aimed at designing and testing the effectiveness of a consumer–healthcare professional partnership model towards effective medication reconciliation. This model aims to empower consumers about their medicines information, so that they would contribute more effectively to medication reconciliation and thereby minimise medication errors occurring at transition points. Components of this model were informed by qualitative data gleaned from patient opinion surveys, focus group sessions involving nurses, doctors and pharmacists working at the hospital and results of a literature search of medication safety tools. Programme development was informed by health improvement approaches centred on a Plan-Do-Study-Act cycle. Evaluation for effectiveness was conducted within a framework of a controlled before and after study. Results revealed that there was a 1.4-fold increase in the reporting rate of pharmacists intervention. The study could not demonstrate that the designed intervention was effective in minimising near-misses. However, there is statistically insignificant reduction in errors for patients that were correctly exposed to the intervention. Anecdotal evidence suggests there is utility for a patient population keen to claim greater ownership of their medicines information. Further, we advocate that patient education about medicines and the establishment of a consumer–healthcare professional model occur prior to ward admission.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Medication reconciliation</kwd>
<kwd>consumer participation</kwd>
<kwd>controlled before and after study</kwd>
<kwd>medicines information</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1078155212451936" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Inappropriate medication use results in at least 80,000 hospital admissions each year at a cost in excess of $350 million. Approximately, half of these events are potentially preventable errors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078155212451936">1</xref></sup> According to the Institute for Healthcare Improvement, ‘poor communication of medical information at transition points is responsible for as many as 50% of all medication errors’ and that a leading contributor for this type of medication error is lack of patient knowledge of their medicines information.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078155212451936">2</xref></sup> The Australian National Health Reform Agenda of April 2004 endorsed implementation of a process of pharmaceutical review, including medication reconciliation (MR), to focus attention on reducing the risk of errors that occur at these transition points.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212451936">3</xref></sup> Similar endorsements and associated patient safety programs have resonated across advanced healthcare systems in other western countries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078155212451936">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078155212451936">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>At the Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, preventable medication errors arise from incomplete medicines information flow where patients’ usual medications may be omitted during hospitalisation and/or from discharge, and where medication changes may not be reported to primary care physicians or not well understood by patients who may recommence ceased medication on return home. <italic>Pharmacist interventions</italic> or <italic>near-misses</italic> arising from unreconciled medications at transition points are commonly documented in the surgical unit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078155212451936">6</xref></sup> Given that patients must manage their medications independently in the home (or with the aid of family members and carers), a healthcare professional–consumer partnership model was proposed to empower patients to better understand and manage their medications (and changes).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078155212451936">7</xref></sup> It was also envisaged that patient empowerment and ownership of medicines information would facilitate the MR process, which would in turn reduce medication errors at transition points.</p>
<p>In February 2006, the Department of Health (Victoria) launched the consumer, carer and community participation policy in the health service system: ‘Doing it with us not for us’. Subsequently in May 2007, the department sought expressions of interest for a series of demonstration projects titled <italic>Evaluating the Effectiveness of Participation (EEP)</italic> in a bid to increase the body of evidence on the effectiveness of consumer and carer participation in improving the quality and safety of healthcare. The Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre was successful in securing an EEP grant under the auspices of the Department of Health’s Quality and Safety branch to design and investigate the effectiveness of a partnership model in MR. Consequently, a project reference group was established to design and then oversee implementation of a set of strategies (or model) aimed at minimising medication errors and reducing <italic>near-misses</italic> in MR at admission and discharge from a hospital ward. The design of this model was informed by qualitative data obtained from patient opinion surveys, focus group sessions involving separate groups of nurses, doctors and pharmacists working at the hospital, and results of a literature search of published medication safety tools and patient education materials. Programme development was informed by health improvement approaches centred on a single participation evaluation and monitoring cycle (or Plan-Do-Study-Act) conducted in three phases; a design phase followed by an implementation phase and then an evaluation phase, in order to assess outcomes over time. Effectiveness of the model was determined by changes in rates of reported medication errors and near-misses. This was conducted within a framework of a before-and-after cohort study design and compared to control (for effects of other organisational changes that may affect study outcomes), as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1078155212451936">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="fig1-1078155212451936" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Control before and after study design.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451936-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1078155212451936" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
<p>This was a 10-month prospective study divided into three phases: (a) the design phase; (b) the implementation phase, in which the proposed model was piloted, then implemented; and (c) an evaluation phase to evaluate effectiveness of the model. Approval from the institutional ethics committee was granted prior to project initiation.</p>
<sec id="sec3-1078155212451936"><title/>
<sec id="sec4-1078155212451936"><title>(a) Design phase</title>
<p>Patient surveys and focus group sessions involving, nurses, pharmacists and doctors were conducted and qualitative data were collated and evaluated to inform design of the model. Patients on two wards (the test ward which is a surgical ward, and control ward which is a specialist medical oncology ward) were randomly selected (non-English speaking patients were excluded) and invited to participate in a telephone survey within 7 days of discharge from the ward. A total of 30 patient opinion surveys were conducted; 18 from the test ward and 12 from the control ward. Patients’ attitudes towards medicines and their experience with the hospital’s system of MR provided insights into designing an effective set of strategies. Patient feedback also helped to identify potential undocumented errors arising from unreconciled medication at transition points. Three focus group sessions involving healthcare professionals were conducted; one session with a group of three resident medical officers comprising surgical oncology and medical oncology doctors, another session with a group of five ward nurses of various disciplines nominated by nurse unit managers and a final session with a group of seven pharmacists. The goal was to identify barriers to discussion of MR matters with patients at transition points, and plausible solutions within the organisational framework of the hospital and ward. Although, focus groups were small so as not to minimise disruption to workflow during work hours, these findings were considered by the project reference committee and heads of nursing, pharmacy and medical departments to be a well-represented description of the major organisational barriers at our institution. Key priority areas were subsequently formulated and considered by a consumer centred project reference group established to design an effective set of strategies (or model). This group comprised of a consumer representative, hospital’s patient advocate, three pharmacists, three nurses and a senior hospital medical officer. Results of a literature search of published medication safety tools and patient education materials using Ovid®, Medline and leading organisations involved in MR such as the Institute for Healthcare Improvement, Australian Council for Safety and Quality in HealthCare, Society of Hospital Pharmacists of Australia (SHPA) and National Prescribing Service were also considered by the project reference committee. Strategies were guided by processes identified in the SHPA Guidelines for the Practice of MR.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1078155212451936">8</xref></sup> The design phase also comprised of baseline qualitative and quantitative data collation for monitoring of outcome measures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1078155212451936"><title>(b) Implementation phase</title>
<p>The project reference group oversaw implementation of the model, which comprised of a four-stage patient orientated empowerment strategy.</p>
<p>Stage 1 occurred prior to admission onto the ward. Patients who nominated English as their first or preferred language were planned to receive first education by their primary care nurse (nurse coordinator or pre-admission clinic nurse) during one of their outpatient clinic appointments. Targeted communication skills training was provided to nursing staff to ensure consistency in the quality of nursing education. This consisted of raising their awareness about medication errors and strategies to avoid such errors, i.e. correctly documenting regular medicines on a medicines list. Patients were given a plain-language brochure containing information relevant to helping the patient understand important aspects of their medicines that they should become familiar with. The language and structure of the brochure was developed in close consultation with the project group’s consumer representative and after feedback from patients in pre-admission clinic. Patients literacy levels were confirmed by the nurse before they were asked to fill in relevant sections of the brochure (medicines list, medicine allergies or sensitivities and regular pharmacy details) after they had read it carefully at home, and bring it with them when admitted onto the ward. The brochure is both a learning tool for patients to correctly document current medicines, and a document which aids ward staff undertaking MR on admission. Stage 2 of the intervention occurred at admission onto the ward. Ward nurses were asked to receive completed brochures from patients (where completed brochures were not available, patients were asked to review and complete a brochure with the aid of friends or carers that were present in the ward), and discuss with them medication safety themes highlighted in the brochure as well as encourage them to become more engaged with staff about their medications (i.e. asking questions or voicing concerns if uncertain). A guide for discussion was detailed within a nursing checklist that was inserted into each patient’s end-of-bed folder by the ward clerk. Nurses checked off each category after counselling their patients and lists were collated to monitor compliance. The information documented in the brochure was then cross-checked by the pharmacist as a means of further educating and highlighting any inconsistencies to the patient. Patients were deemed to be at risk of making medication errors if they were non-compliant with hospital MR processes owing to their personal attitudes, or their inability to cope or a feeling of being overwhelmed because they were receiving polypharmacy, palliative care management, or were elderly. These patients were referred to the pharmacist who facilitated patient understanding and put in place specific strategies such as a record of medicines information, provision of medication lists at discharge for patients to update whenever they receive medical advice to make changes to their medication regimen, follow-up calls after discharge and appointments with carers to discuss the same. Stage 3 of the intervention occurred at discharge. All patients received counselling and a medication list from the pharmacist, in keeping with standards of practice outlined in the SHPA Clinical Pharmacy Practice standards. The medicines list is encased in an A4 plastic pocket foldable into wallet size to ensure portability and durability. Stage 4 of the intervention occurred for high-risk patients within 7 days after patient discharge. The pharmacist organised a time to phone patients to ensure that the patient was managing their medicines and newly learnt strategies for recording medicines.</p>
<p>The project reference group assisted with refinement of the intervention strategies during the first 2-month period of introduction of the intervention. Feedback from patients and staff was crucial to ensuring feasibility of the intervention in practice, and its acceptability to clinicians and user-friendliness for both clinicians and patients. Final implementation of the programme of change occurred over a 3-month period of the new practice during which project group support was removed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1078155212451936"><title>(c) Evaluation phase</title>
<p>Outcome measures were collected for a 2-month period after the intervention had been operational for 3 months without project group support and data were compared to baseline. Quantitative outcome measures were pharmacists’ interventions or <italic>near-miss</italic> statistics for both the test and the control wards, as well as patient medical record audits conducted alongside patient surveys to report on potential undocumented errors (example delayed, missed or wrong medication orders). Near-miss statistics, represented as rates, were compared using Chi-squared test. Statistical significance was demonstrated if <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. The methodology for documentation and classification of pharmacist interventions (by low, moderate and high or extreme risk) is as described in the SHPA Standards of Practice for Clinical Pharmacy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212451936">3</xref></sup> The qualitative outcome measures were patient opinion surveys of satisfaction and accounts of empowerment or improved engagement with medicines information. This was undertaken for both intervention and control units to assess change and sustainability of the change after project support withdrawal. Observations of practice were also undertaken by tracking patients exposed to the intervention and monitoring staff compliance so as to understand process aspects of this programme.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1078155212451936" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>Outlined below are results of components of the study.</p>
<sec id="sec8-1078155212451936"><title>Focus group sessions and patient opinion surveys: Key priority areas</title>
<p>Eight key priority areas were identified from the patient opinion surveys and healthcare professional focus group sessions. Solutions for five of these priorities were designed by the project reference group and piloted during the project (as tabulated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1078155212451936">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table1-1078155212451936" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Key priority areas and plausible solutions identified from focus group sessions and patient opinion surveys.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1078155212451936" xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451936-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Key priority areas identified from focus group sessions and surveys</th>
<th colspan="2">Piloted solutions<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr><th>Patient-orientated solution to address relevant key priority area(s)</th>
<th>Health professional/healthsystem-orientated solution to address relevant key priority area(s)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1. Patients lack awareness about medication errors</td>
<td>Patients should receive education comprising of raising awareness and learning strategies to avoid errors</td>
<td rowspan="1">Primary care nurses to verbalise key information to patients. Support with literature and learning tools. Targeted communication skills training to ensure consistent quality of teaching</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Patients generally unaware of aspects of information to document and present at MR</td>
<td>Education should occur at key stages 1. Prior to admission 2. Reiteration on ward at admission, and correcting documentation with patient</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="1">3. Patients’ level of retention of new information is reduced by many external factors</td>
<td>3. Prompt counselling at initiation of new medication/dosage 4. Follow-up calls for higher-risk patients</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">4. Medicines information not always available at admission because medicines were not brought in by patients or not transferred from theatre, patient’s own list and/or Health Assessment Questionnaire are not comprehensive and where patient relies on recall, accuracy is felt to be poor</td>
<td>Patients receive a medicines list form to fill in and present at admission, also receive education on maintaining and updating medicines list.</td>
<td>Ward staff to promote use of brochure and medicines list, and encourage participation from carers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Provision for a portable and durable medicines list at discharge – wallet sized and plastic protected foldable list</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">5. Patient needs are varied. Distinct groups – polypharmacy, elderly and palliative care patients are higher risk and their coping mechanisms must be incorporated into devising strategies</td>
<td rowspan="4">Literature and verbal information to be reiterated. Referral to pharmacist for discussion of strategies to better and more easily manage medicines, and aids to make learning and documenting medicines easier</td>
<td>Population targeting</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Risk-stratify patients. Higher risk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>groups should be followed-up, have carers encouraged to participate. Ward pharmacist to take on responsibility</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Comprehensive medication history to be documented in pharmacy database</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1078155212451936"><p>MR: medication reconciliation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1078155212451936"><title>Qualitative data: Type of patient groups identified</title>
<p>Results of the patient opinion survey suggested that patients participating in the study could be categorised into three main groups according to their own perceptions on coping and managing their medication regimen at home (as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1078155212451936">Figure 2</xref>). These categories are:
<list id="list1-1078155212451936" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>patients who were confident with their management of medicines and perceived themselves to cope well;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>patients who desired greater involvement in coping strategies irrespective of level of confidence and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>patients who were reluctant to participate. This group cited fear of giving inaccurate information as reason for subsequent error, greater reliance on health professionals to get it right ‘you’re the experts – don’t want to mess you up’ and overwhelming and stressful condition (new diagnosis/complications/pain/‘too much on board’) as being a barrier to further involvement and learning.</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig2-1078155212451936" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Qualitative data from patient surveys; distribution of patient types: attitudes towards greater participation in a proposed partnership model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451936-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Although the majority of patients surveyed claimed that they were confident about their medicines, when relying on recall, approximately half of these patients could not specify with confidence one or more of: (a) all the medicines they were taking; (b) medicine name; (c) dose form; (d) strength; and (e) directions. Most of these patients relied on prescription labels and/or already kept a list of medicines. According to patient accounts, these lists were not always updated correctly or did not contain comprehensive information as detailed in (a) to (e) above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1078155212451936"><title>Near-miss statistics</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1078155212451936">Table 2</xref> lists <italic>near-miss</italic> statistics or pharmacist interventions. Rates of near-misses arising from unreconciled medications per admitted patient were monitored to reflect how well the model facilitated patient-initiated MR. Pharmacist intervention rates increased from 0.35 to 0.49 after implementation of the intervention.
<table-wrap id="table2-1078155212451936" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><italic>Near-miss</italic> or <italic>pharmacist intervention</italic> statistics before and after intervention.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1078155212451936" xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212451936-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th colspan="3">Pre-implementation<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Post-implementation<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr><th/>
<th colspan="3">Two months: September–October 2007<hr/></th>
<th colspan="3">Two months: May–June 2008<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr><th/>
<th>Interventions (type)</th>
<th>Patients admitted</th>
<th>Rates (pharmacist intervention at admission per patient)</th>
<th>Interventions (type)</th>
<th>Patients admitted</th>
<th>Rates (pharmacist intervention at admission per patient)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td align="justify">Test ward</td>
<td align="justify">51 (admissions) and 12 (discharge) = total 63</td>
<td align="justify">178</td>
<td align="justify">63/178 = 0.35</td>
<td align="justify">72 (admissions) and 12 (discharges) = total 84</td>
<td align="justify">170</td>
<td align="justify">72/170 = 0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify">Classification:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify">Classification:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 4 High risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 5 High risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 56 Moderate risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 46 Moderate risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 0 Low risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 32 Low risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 3 Unclassified</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 1 Unclassified</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Control ward</td>
<td align="justify">38 (admissions) and 43 (discharge) = total 81</td>
<td align="justify">103</td>
<td align="justify">81/103 = 0.79</td>
<td align="justify">3 (admissions) and 2 (discharge)</td>
<td align="justify">120</td>
<td align="justify">5/120 = 0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify">Classification:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify">Classification:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 3 High risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 1 High risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 55 Moderate risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 2 Moderate risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 23 Low risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="justify"> 2 Low risk</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Of the 31 patients that received Stage 1 education, 13 (42%) submitted completed medicines information brochures/forms. The pharmacist intervention rate for the group of patients that were compliant with submitting completed medicines information was 0.9. Nine near-misses (seven of moderate risk and two of high risk) occurred for four of these patients. Further analysis showed that the higher rate of near-misses documented for the patient group compliant with brochures arose from brochure information being relayed to the pharmacist, instead of the prescriber.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1078155212451936"><title>Patient opinion surveys correlated to patient medical record</title>
<p>Pre-implementation: Thirty patients were surveyed (18 from test ward and 12 from control ward) and had their medical records audited. Twentyfive patients (83%) took more than two regular medications prior to admission. The average number of medications per person prior to admission was five. Eight potential or undocumented errors (two of moderate risk and six of low risk) may have occurred in the test ward whilst five such errors (one of moderate risk and four of low risk) may have occurred in the control ward.</p>
<p>Post-implementation: Thirty patients were surveyed (17 from test ward and 13 from control ward) and had their medical records audited. Twentytwo patients (73%) took more than two regular medications prior to admission. The average number of medications per person prior to admission was also five. Two potential or undocumented errors (of low risk) may have occurred in the intervention ward whilst seven such errors may have occurred in the control ward (one of moderate risk and six of low risk). No undocumented errors were identified from chart audits for the patient group that returned completed brochures in the sample that was surveyed (<italic>n</italic> = 5). Survey findings revealed that three of five patients derived benefit from the brochure and education provided to them before admission. The remaining two patients filled in the brochure easily because they were very familiar with their medicines; they derived little or no incremental benefit from the patient information materials.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1078155212451936" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>The use of a patient brochure and form to facilitate self-reporting of medicines information facilitated MR efforts by the pharmacist and assisted with minimising errors. However, we could not demonstrate a statistically significant increase in pharmacist intervention rates due to poor uptake of the patient education process and limited distribution of the brochure to patients prior to their admission. Despite this, approximately 42% of patients that received the brochure from a pre-admission clinic, but without receiving the intended education, were compliant and presented completed medicines information to ward staff. This suggests first that the tool was user friendly and second, an eagerness for a relatively high proportion of patients to participate with limited encouragement if education and appropriate tools were provided prior to admission into hospital. More errors were detected by the pharmacist for this group of patients. The near-misses at admission were attributed to the brochure information not being relayed to the prescribing doctor but instead to the pharmacist who documented their intervention as a near-miss. Since these were near-misses that arose on admission, it is not unconceivable that errors may have occurred if not for patients self-reporting their medicines information to the pharmacist.</p>
<p>Whilst most of the recommendations of the project reference group were adopted, certain recommendations could not be accommodated. The most important of which was the inability to engage nurse coordinators with educating and providing patients with the brochure/form during Stage 1. It was anticipated that ward nurses would intercept the proportion of patients not exposed to Stage 1. However, compliance here was also poor. As suggested by study findings and supported by published evidence, we feel that patients should be cautiously and selectively educated well before their admission to hospital about the facts around medication errors in hospitals, and duly assisted with taking ownership of their medicines information in order to minimise such errors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1078155212451936">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1078155212451936">10</xref></sup> The brochure information should be accompanied by education from a suitable health professional in the pre-admission setting. Retrospective cohort studies have demonstrated improvements in patient safety and cost-effectiveness when clinical oncology pharmacist services are available in the outpatient setting and include consultative services such as patient education.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1078155212451936">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Survey findings from patients that returned completed brochures to ward staff showed that although these patients were generally familiar with their medicines, they did not realise the comprehensiveness of information required to be recorded or provided to healthcare staff. Greater clarity about important aspects of medicines documentation was provided by the brochure and this was perceived by them as a benefit. Some patients that received the brochure pre-admission stated a change in attitude from a prior notion that ‘doctors know best’. They stated they were more willing to contribute and engaged carers to help out with documenting medicines. Whilst open ended questions seeking description of attitudes and feelings were asked during the patient surveys, there may be some element of bias in the responses received from these patients stemming from an eagerness to please. Most respondents felt the need to compliment the quality of service received during their care at the hospital. Further, a project reference group member was involved in administering the patient’s surveys and evaluating this data.</p>
<p>The primary quantitative outcome measure routinely being monitored is the pharmacy near-miss statistic. Findings suggest that the model was ineffective in minimising near-misses. However near-miss recording is subject to the confounding effects of level of experience and documentation practices of the pharmacist on duty. Post-intervention near-miss data occurred shortly after the rotation of pharmacists and commencement of a newly registered pharmacist on the intervention ward. The marked reduction in intervention rates for the control ward is attributed to the change in documentation practices of the new pharmacist on duty. Additionally, we note that the test ward was a surgical ward which in comparison to the control (or medical oncology) ward is associated with greater patient turnover and is also more likely to yield a greater number of pharmacist interventions at patient admission and discharge. Whilst there is a relative increase in the count of near-misses for the intervention ward, closer scrutiny shows that there is a shift from moderate risk to low risk near-misses post-intervention. However, this shift is not statistically significant. Further, classification of near-miss data is subject to intra-rater variability between pharmacists – this has been described in previous literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1078155212451936">12</xref></sup> Given the scarcity of exposure of the brochure to the desired sample group and the quality of outcome measure being monitored, no conclusive findings can be drawn to demonstrate effectiveness in minimising medication errors. Although not statistically significant, where patients were correctly exposed to the test model, more errors were prevented on admission.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1078155212451936" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The study could not demonstrate that the designed model was effective in minimising errors and in reducing near-misses. However, despite limitations associated with project implementation, findings suggest that the brochure/form was patient-friendly and facilitated MR on admission. Whilst there is little evidence to suggest that patients who are reluctant to become more involved in the MR process may derive benefit from this brochure, anecdotal evidence suggests this strategy could be further developed in conjunction with pharmacist counselling to influence change in this patient group’s attitudes and their ownership of medicines information. Importantly, this study demonstrates the need to further research the role of patient knowledge and information about medications as a potential intervention point in reducing MR errors.</p>
<p>Together, pharmacists and nurses play significant roles in ensuring medication safety and both professions should be involved in a systems wide approach to reducing MR errors in hospitals. We recommend further investigation of factors that might improve nursing engagement with medication safety initiatives. We advocate that patient education about medicines and the establishment of a consumer–healthcare professional model should occur prior to ward admission.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec14-1078155212451936"><title>Funding</title>
<p>Grant funding by way of an “Evaluating the Effectiveness of Participation” (EEP) Grant was received from the Quality and Safety branch, Department of Health (Victoria).</p>
</sec>
<ack><title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The project reference group duly acknowledges the assistance received from the Cochrane Consumers and Communication Review Group, La Trobe University and wishes to thank patients, carers and consumer representatives who actively participated in the design and implementation of the intervention. Thanks also to the preadmission clinic nurse Kay Kenchington and pharmacists, Gail Rowan, Sally Brooks and Charini Jayasinghe. We would like to acknowledge the large contributions Angela Stefanou has made to the pharmacy department.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078155212451936"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Roughead EE. The nature and extent of drug-related hospitalisations in Australia. <italic>J Qual Clin Pract</italic> 1999; 19: 19–22, cited in Australian Council for Safety and Quality in HealthCare, Second National Report on Patient Safety: Improving Medication Safety, Canberra: Commonwealth Department of Health, 2002.</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078155212451936"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Safer systems – saving lives (based on the Institute for Healthcare Improvements’ 100K Lives Program), Australian Council for Safety and Quality in Healthcare, 2005.</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078155212451936"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>SHPA Committee of Specialty Practice in Clinical Pharmacy</collab>. <article-title>SHPA standards of practice for clinical pharmacy</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Prac Res</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078155212451936"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Institute for Healthcare Improvement. The 5 million lives campaign, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ihi.org/IHI/Programs/Campaign/">http://www.ihi.org/IHI/Programs/Campaign/</ext-link> (accessed 28 January 2008).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078155212451936"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Canadian Patient Safety Institute. Safer healthcare now! <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.saferhealthcarenow.ca">http://www.saferhealthcarenow.ca</ext-link> (accessed 28 January 2008).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078155212451936"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhanji</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacy involvement in a surgery pre-admission program</article-title>. <source>Am J Hosp Pharm</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078155212451936"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Myrhaug</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source><italic>Methods of consumer involvement in developing healthcare policy and research, clinical practice guidelines and patient information material (review). Cochrane Consumers and Communication Review Group</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>The Cochrane Collaboration</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1078155212451936"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>SHPA standards of practice for the provision of medication reconciliation</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Pract Res</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1078155212451936"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Justeson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Patient safety standardization as a mechanism to improve safety in health care</article-title>. <source>Jt Comm J Qual Saf</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1078155212451936"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marvanova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roumie</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Health literacy and medication understanding among hospitalized adults</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Med</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>488</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1078155212451936"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsden</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Is there a benefit to having a clinical oncology pharmacist on staff at a community oncology clinic?</article-title> <source>J Oncol Pharm Pract</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1078155212451936"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Yu K, Dooley M, Nation R, et al. Inter-rater and intra-rater validation of a pharmacist intervention risk assessment tool. In: <italic>National medicines symposium 2006</italic>, Canberra, Australia, 7–9 June 2006.</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>